<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01813617</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SweMyoNet 1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Centre of Care Science</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01813617</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Outcome in Patients With Recent Onset Polymyositis and Dermatomyositis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Outcome of Muscle Function and Disease Activity in Patients With Recent Onset Polymyositis and Dermatomyositis - a 1-year Follow-up Register Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karolinska University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karolinska University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Most patients respond to medical treatment with corticosteroids and immunosuppressive
      treatment, but a majority of patients develop sustained muscle impairment. The aim of this
      study was to evaluate the outcome of muscle endurance assessed with the Functional Index-2
      (FI-2), muscle strength assessed by the MMT-8 and disease activity assessed by the six item
      core set at 6 and 12 months following diagnosis in patients with polymyositis (PM) and
      dermatomyositis (DM).

      72 patients diagnosed with probable or definite PM or DM 2003-2010 who performed the FI-2 and
      the MMT at the time of diagnosis were included in this Swedish Myositis Register study. All
      patients had performed both the Functional Index-2 assessing muscle endurance and the Manual
      Muscle test (MMT) assessing isometric muscle strength. Physician Global assessment based on
      the evaluation of the consensus recommended six item core set for disease activity assessment
      was also included. Data were analysed on group levels as well as with criteria for individual
      responder criteria. A responder was identified as improving at least 20 % compared to
      baseline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study was to investigate the degree of impairment of isometric muscle
      weakness and dynamic muscle endurance in patients with recent onset PM and DM and to evaluate
      how muscle impairment and disease activity changes during the first year following diagnosis
      of PM or DM. A further aim was to investigate the association between muscle impairment,
      disease activity and autoantibodies in these patients.

      All patients diagnosed with definite or probable PM or DM according to Bohan and Peter
      criteria (Bohan and Peter 1975) 2003-2010, at the Rheumatology clinic at Karolinska
      University Hospital, also included in the Swedish Rheumatology Register (SweMyoNet) who had
      performed measures of dynamic muscle endurance by the FI-2 and isometric muscle strength by
      the MMT-8 were included in this register study (n=71).

      Functional Index-2 is a disease specific, valid and reliable instrument assessing muscular
      endurance in seven muscle groups including seven tasks; shoulder flexion, shoulder abduction,
      neck flexion, hip flexion, step test and toe lifts and heel lifts. Each muscle group are
      scored as the number of correctly executed repetitions.

      The six-item core set for measures of disease activity include; Physician's and patient's
      assessment of disease activity on a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), the Manual Muscle Test
      (MMT), the Stanford Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ), analyses of muscle enzymes and the
      extra-muscular disease activity scores Myositis Disease Activity Visual Analogue Scales
      (MYOACT) or the Myositis Intention to Treat Index (MITAX). The 8-muscle group MMT was
      performed on the dominant body side including muscle groups; neck flexors, deltoids, biceps
      brachia, dorsi flexors of the wrist, gluteus maximus and medius, quadriceps and dorsi flexors
      of the ankle. Total score varies between 0 and 80, where 80 indicate normal muscular
      strength.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Index 2 assessing change in muscle function over time.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The FI-2 is a disease-specific assessment of dynamic muscle endurance in 7 muscle groups and records the number of correct performed repetitions for each muscle group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Manual Muscle test, MMT-8, assessing change in muscle function over time.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measure isometric muscle strength in 8 muscle groups and is scored between 0-10 for each muscle group with a total score of 80 indicating godd muscle strength.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Physicians global assessment of disease activity assessing change over time.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Physician's global assessment is included in the consensus proposed six item core set of disease activity measures also including patient's global assessment, the MMT, Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ), analysis of muscle enzymes and the extra-muscular disease activity tools MITAX or MYOACT.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Polymyositis</condition>
  <condition>Dermatomyositis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Recent onset polymyositis and dermatomyositis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients in this cohort was diagnosed with polymyositis or dermatomyositis during 2003-2010 and was treated with corticosteroids and other immunosuppressive agents according to standard care. They were all diagnosed and treated at the Rheumatology Clinic, Karolinska University Hospital.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immunosuppressive Agents</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in the cohort received medical treatment according to standard care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Recent onset polymyositis and dermatomyositis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prednisone</other_name>
    <other_name>Methotrexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Azathioprine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients diagnosed with polymyositis or dermatomysitis at the Karolinska University
        Hospital 2003-2010.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Probable or definite polymyositis and dermatomyositis

          -  Performed both the FI-2 and the MMT at time of diagnosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with diagnosis inclusions body myositis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helene Alexanderson, PhD, RPT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska University Hospital / Karolinska Institutet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska University Hospital, Solna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>171 76</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 14, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 14, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 14, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Karolinska University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Helene Alexanderson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD, RPT</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Polymyositis</keyword>
  <keyword>Dermatomyositis</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle endurance</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle stength</keyword>
  <keyword>Outcome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatomyositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polymyositis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunosuppressive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azathioprine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

