<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03097900</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAFFEINE-HMO-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03097900</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Does Caffeine Enhance Bowel Recovery After Colorectal Surgery?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Caffeine Enhance Bowel Recovery After Colorectal Surgery?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative ileus is a frequently occurring surgical complication. It is defined as
      temporary inhibition of propulsive bowel activity and is manifested by abdominal distention,
      nausea, vomiting and diet intolerance. It may lead to a prolonged hospital stay,
      hospital-acquired infections or complications that may require additional treatments (e.g.
      analgesia, fluids, electrolyte replacement, nasogastric tube decompression), and as a result
      increase medical costs.

      Previous studies showed that postoperative coffee consumption shortens the time to first
      bowel movement after colorectal resections. However, none could explain the mechanism by
      which coffee stimulates intestinal motility and the determinant agent for this action is
      still up for discussion (either caffeine or another coffee component).

      Coffee has a negligible caloric content; It has a pH that varies from 5 to 6 (less acidity
      than other beverages that have no similar effect on bowel motility) and it is hypotonic.
      Therefore, it is highly unlikely that bowel motility is due to the physical properties of the
      coffee. Much more likely, that one (or more) of the numerous phytochemicals of the coffee
      bean are responsible for this effect, when the most obvious candidate seems to be caffeine.
      However, as mentioned above, very little evidence exists that caffeine was responsible for
      the observed effect on colonic function in previous studies.

      The purpose of this single-centered, prospective, single blinded, randomized clinical trial
      is to evaluate whether the use of caffeine in the post-operative period significantly reduces
      the duration of postoperative ileus, and therefore, improves recovery and shorten the
      hospital stay.

      The study hypothesis is that post-operative use of caffeine will reduce time to recovery of
      GI function (post-operative ileus) by at least 15 hours and thus reduce hospital length of
      stay by at least 15 hours in patients undergoing elective colorectal operations.

      50 patients due to undergo large bowel resection via laparotomy or laparoscopy will be
      enrolled and randomized (1:1) to those who will receive caffeine (100 mg 3 times per day) and
      those who will receive placebo (tap water) starting on the morning of postoperative day 1
      after surgery until flatus will occur for the first time or to a maximal period time of 7
      days, whichever comes earlier.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background Postoperative ileus is a frequently occurring surgical complication. It is defined
      as temporary inhibition of propulsive bowel activity and is manifested by abdominal
      distention, nausea and vomiting and diet intolerance. It may lead to a prolonged hospital
      stay, hospital-acquired infections or complications that may require additional treatments
      (analgesia, intravenous fluid administration, electrolyte replacement, nasogastric tube
      decompression etc.) and as a result increase medical costs.

      Surgeons are continually trying to find ways to shorten postoperative ileus. The means are
      diverse and include advancing diet as tolerated, avoiding the use of nasogastric tubes, early
      ambulation, occasional use of gastrograffin or alvimopan (a selective μ-receptor opioid
      antagonist) and the use of minimally invasive surgery (laparoscopic colectomy) rather than
      laparotomy. Asao et al showed that chewing gum after laparoscopic colectomy leads to an
      earlier return of bowel function and shorten the hospital stay, probably via the
      cephalic-vagal reflex which increase the production of gastrointestinal hormones associated
      with bowel motility. However, up until now, there has been no strategy or drug that has been
      consistently effective in accelerating bowel recovery from abdominal surgery.

      Coffee is a popular beverage with known influences on the central nervous system and the
      cardiovascular system. Although coffee can stimulate intestinal function in healthy
      volunteers, the mechanism by which coffee stimulates intestinal motility is still unknown.
      The cholinergic anti-inflammatory pathway (CAIP) has been proposed as a key mechanism by
      which the brain, through the vagus nerve, modulates the immune system in the spleen. Vagal
      stimulation by nicotine was shown to reduce intestinal inflammation and improve postoperative
      ileus. It is known that caffeine stimulates vagal activity. An average cup of caffeinated
      coffee contains 50-150 milligrams of caffeine, depending on the type, concentration and
      amount of coffee consumed.

      The gastrointestinal system can be stimulated by a substantial caloric intake, acidity,
      osmolality, or volume load. The caloric content of coffee is negligible (approximately 1
      kcal/ 100 mL). It has a pH which varies from 5 to 6 (less acidic than other beverages that
      have no similar effect on the bowel motility). Brewed and filtered coffee is hypotonic (as is
      water which serves as the control drink in previous studies). Therefore, it seems that the
      gastrointestinal effect of coffee is most probably not attributed to its physicochemical
      properties but to the biochemical activity of one or several of the many active compounds in
      coffee.

      In a study that was conducted in 1990, 29% of healthy volunteers claimed that coffee induced
      a desire to defecate. The effect of caffeinated coffee on recto-sigmoid motor activity was
      investigated with a manometry. The activity was accelerated four minutes after the intake of
      either regular or decaffeinated coffee. However, water had no comparable effect on the
      recto-sigmoid motility. Caffeine, when in the stomach, can act upon gastric myenteric and
      submucous nerves to induce gastric emptying. The influx of digestive metabolites into the
      small intestines may stimulate the gastrocolic reflex and be a possible mechanism behind
      caffeine causing the need to defecate shortly after consumption. The ultimate result of this
      reflex mediated by caffeine is an increased anal sphincter contraction power and less neural
      input required to induce contraction (decreased sensory threshold). Rao et al. performed an
      ambulatory manometry with inserting a catheter through the rectum up to the mid transverse
      colon. They investigated the effects of 240 mL regular coffee, 240 mL decaffeinated coffee,
      240 mL water and a 1000 kcal meal on colonic activity. Regular coffee, decaffeinated coffee
      and the calorie-rich meal induced more colonic contractions than water. Moreover, regular
      coffee induced colonic contractions at greater intensity compared to a caloric-rich meal, 60%
      stronger than water and 23% stronger than decaffeinated coffee. A randomized controlled trial
      performed in 2012 at the University of Heidelberg among patients after laparoscopic
      colectomy, studied the effect of coffee on the duration of postoperative ileus. The study
      showed that the time to first bowel movement was significantly shorter in the group (40
      patients) which received 3 caffeinated coffee cups per day compared to group (40 patients)
      receiving water only. No significant side effects were observed at the active treatment
      group. Dulskas.A et al. conducted a randomized controlled study in 2015 to evaluate whether
      consumption of 100 mL coffee is effective in reducing postoperative ileus. The study showed
      that coffee consumption after colectomy is safe and that decaffeinated coffee was associated
      with a shorter time to bowel movement and tolerance of solid food but not time to ﬁrst ﬂatus;
      caffeinated coffee did not impact the duration of postoperative ileus. In all the studies
      carried out so far, none could explain the mechanism by which coffee stimulates intestinal
      motility and the determinant agent for this action is still up for discussion: either
      caffeine or another component of the coffee, such as chlorogenic acids or melanoidins.

      Aim The purpose of this study is to evaluate whether the use of caffeine in the
      post-operative period significantly reduces the duration of postoperative ileus, and
      therefore, improves recovery and shorten the hospital stay. The study hypothesis is that
      post-operative use of caffeine will reduce time to recovery of GI function (i.e. reduce
      post-operative ileus) by at least 15 hours and thus reduce hospital length of stay by at
      least 15 hours in patients undergoing elective colorectal operations.

      Methods This will be a single-centered, prospective, randomized controlled, double blinded
      trial.

      50 patients due to undergo large bowel resection via laparotomy or laparoscopy will be
      enrolled. Patients will be randomized (1:1) to those who will receive caffeine (study group)
      and those who will receive placebo (control group). Randomization will occur via an online
      program (www.randomizer.org) which assigns participants to experimental conditions. Patients
      in the study group will be given 100 milligrams caffeine citrate orally diluted in 50
      milliliters of apple flavored water while patients in the control group will be given 50
      milliliters of apple flavored water only. Administration of caffeine or placebo will occur
      three times per day starting on the morning of postoperative day 1 after surgery until
      passage of flatus per rectum will occur for the first time or to a maximal period of time of
      7 days, whichever comes earlier.

      Sample size was calculated as 50 patients (25 pts in each group) which are required in order
      to have 1-sided α level of 0.05 and a power of 0.80 to detect a difference of 15 hours in the
      duration of postoperative ileus (standard deviation 21 hours), which is supported by prior
      studies. Any difference of 15 hours or more between the groups will be statistically
      significant.

      Caffeine or water will be supplied to the surgical floor per participating patient by the
      pharmacy in coordination with one of the co-investigators who will be un-blinded. At the
      floor the caffeine or water will be diluted with apple flavored water which will be supplied
      by the pharmacy, prior to each dose. The investigators (aside from the single un-blinded
      co-investigator) and primary team of doctors and nurses will be blinded to the patient's
      assignment.

      Postoperative care will be the same for all patients other than the administration of
      caffeine or placebo. Patients will be instructed to avoid consuming products that contain
      caffeine (e.g. coffee, tea, chocolate, cola etc.) until the first passage of flatus. No other
      restrictions on food or beverages consumption will be imposed other than usually are for
      patients undergoing the same kind of surgery. The patients will be hospitalized under
      surveillance and monitoring of the primary team during the study period. They will be
      instructed to keep in mind or to note the endpoints (time to first flatus, time to first
      bowel movement, time to tolerate solid diet) and to report them to the primary team and study
      investigators during the routine rounds.

      The criteria for hospital discharge include stable vital signs with no febrile morbidity for
      ≥24 hours, passage of stool, toleration of a regular diet and the absence of other
      complications.

      Safety Endpoints

        -  Any adverse events deemed possibly, probably or definitely related to treatment with
           caffeine: arrhythmia, muscle crumps/tremor, restlessness, irritability, headache,
           dizziness, tachycardia, allergic reactions (rare) or any other severe manifestation that
           can be attributed to caffeine side effects.

        -  Any major adverse event resulting from the surgery that might interfere with caffeine or
           might lead to meaningless endpoint data: organ failure, anastomotic leakage,
           intraabdominal abscess or invasive re-intervention (Clavien-Dindo classification of
           surgical complications &gt; 3).

      Patients Patients who are scheduled for laparoscopy or open elective colon resection (right
      or left hemicolectomy, sigmoid resection, anterior resection, segmental colectomy), for an
      oncologic or inflammatory indication, that are willing to participate in the study will be
      informed verbally by a member of the study team of the aims, the risks, alternative
      therapies, their rights and the course of the trial. The investigator will emphasize that
      study participation is voluntary and the patient can withdraw at any time during the study.

      Patients will be included if they fulfill all inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion
      criteria listed below within the protocol and after written informed consent was obtained.
      Enrolment period to the study will be 18 months

      Statistical analysis Pearson r correlation coefficient will be used to examine the
      relationship between two Quantitative variables.

      T test will be used to compare Quantitative variable between two categories of Qualitative
      variable.

      ANOVA test will be used to compare Quantitative variable between three or more categories of
      Qualitative variable.

      Chi- square test will be used to examine the relationship between two Qualitative variables.

      The variables which will be found significantly related to the dependent variable in the
      monothetic analysis (one-factor-at-a-time method) will be inserted to a multivariate analysis
      of ANCOVA.

      Risks and risk management Most of the population consumes high doses of caffeine (an average
      coffee consumption of 9-11 kg per person per year) without even noticing. The side effects
      listed above were previously described after consuming dosages much higher than 3 X 100
      mg/day. The safety of caffeine consumption after elective colorectal surgery has been
      demonstrated through numerous clinical studies as detailed above.

      In this study, any patient suffering from a medical condition or requiring treatment with a
      drug which might interfere with caffeine will be excluded. Therefore, consumption of caffeine
      in a cumulative dose of 300 mg/day should not cause any side effects.

      Despite this, patients will be hospitalized under supervision and monitored by the primary
      team and study investigators. Documentation of vital signs, physical examination, medical
      consultants support and assessment of serious adverse events will be conducted. Any
      unexpected adverse event will be treated efficiently and quickly without extra cost for the
      patient.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>First postoperative flatus</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout hospital stay for a maximum of 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The time in hours from end of surgery to first flatus.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>First bowel movement</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout hospital stay for a maximum of 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The time in hours from end of surgery to first bowel movement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerance of solid diet</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout hospital stay for a maximum of 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The time in hours from end of surgery to first solid meal tolerated (the first time the patient is able to eat any food requiring chewing, without vomiting or going back to liquid diet)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of postoperative hospital stay.</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout hospital stay for a maximum of 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The postoperative hospital stay is the number of hours from surgery until discharge. The criteria for hospital discharge include stable vital signs with no febrile morbidity for ≥24 hours, passage of stool, toleration of a solid diet and the absence of other complications.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Ileus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Caffeine Citrate) group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 patients after elective colorectal surgery will be given 100 mg caffeine citrate orally diluted in 50 ml apple flavored water three times per day starting on the morning of postoperative day 1 after surgery until flatus will occur for the first time or to a maximal period time of 7 days, whichever comes earlier.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (Water) group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 patients after elective colorectal surgery will be given 50 ml apple flavored water three times per day starting on the morning of postoperative day 1 after surgery until flatus will occur for the first time or to a maximal period time of 7 days, whichever comes earlier.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Caffeine Citrate</intervention_name>
    <description>25 patients after elective colorectal surgery will be given 100 mg caffeine citrate orally diluted in 50 ml apple flavored water three times per day starting on the morning of postoperative day 1 after surgery until flatus will occur for the first time or to a maximal period time of 7 days, whichever comes earlier.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (Caffeine Citrate) group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cafcit</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Water</intervention_name>
    <description>25 patients after elective colorectal surgery will be given 50 ml apple flavored water three times per day starting on the morning of postoperative day 1 after surgery until flatus will occur for the first time or to a maximal period time of 7 days, whichever comes earlier.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (Water) group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria

          1. Able to freely give written informed consent to participate in the study and have
             signed the Informed Consent Form;

          2. Males and females, 18 to 80 years of age inclusive at the time of study screening;

          3. Due to undergo large partial / total bowel resection via laparotomy or laparoscopy
             with primary anastomosis.

        Key Exclusion Criteria

          1. Scheduled for a colon resection with stoma creation or multi-visceral resection.

          2. Mentally incompetent or unable or unwilling to provide informed consent or comply with
             study procedures

          3. American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Class IV or V

          4. History of abdominal carcinomatosis

          5. History of radiation enteritis

          6. Children &lt;18 or adults &gt; 80 years of age

          7. Pregnant women

          8. Known allergy to caffeine

          9. Consumption of more than 800 milligrams of caffeine (8-10 cups of coffee) daily on a
             regular basis

         10. Complete abstention of caffeine consumption on a regular basis

         11. Consumption of drugs which are either substrates or inhibitors of CYP1A2 enzyme
             (Ciprofloxacin, Fluvoxamine or Clozapine( at the time of the study, due to expected
             change of caffeine metabolism it these patients

         12. Postoperative ventilation, pressor requirement or ICU stay

         13. Liver failure or/and liver cirrhosis (MELD&gt;15)

         14. Urgent surgery e.g. emergent laparotomy, sepsis, diverting stoma.

         15. Opioid treatment for at least a week before surgery.

         16. Prior extensive abdominal surgery (not including caesarean section, appendectomy,
             cholecystectomy or hernia repair).

         17. Known impaired mental status or language difficulties.

         18. Participation in another interventional trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Noam Shussman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Noam Shussman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+ 972 2 6779758</phone>
    <email>Noams@hadassah.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shani Parnasa, BsC</last_name>
    <phone>+ 972 54 7334024</phone>
    <email>shani.parnasa@mail.huji.ac.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah Medical Organization</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem Region</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hadas Lemberg, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>00 972 2 6777572</phone>
      <email>lhadas@hadassah.org.il</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/caffeine/art-20049372</url>
    <description>Ref 11. Mayo Clinic staff. Caffeine content for coffee, tea, soda and more. [Accessed March 14, 2017]</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kehlet H. Postoperative ileus--an update on preventive techniques. Nat Clin Pract Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2008 Oct;5(10):552-8. doi: 10.1038/ncpgasthep1230. Epub 2008 Aug 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18695704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basse L, Jakobsen DH, Bardram L, Billesbølle P, Lund C, Mogensen T, Rosenberg J, Kehlet H. Functional recovery after open versus laparoscopic colonic resection: a randomized, blinded study. Ann Surg. 2005 Mar;241(3):416-23.</citation>
    <PMID>15729063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jakobsen DH, Sonne E, Andreasen J, Kehlet H. Convalescence after colonic surgery with fast-track vs conventional care. Colorectal Dis. 2006 Oct;8(8):683-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16970579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mattei P, Rombeau JL. Review of the pathophysiology and management of postoperative ileus. World J Surg. 2006 Aug;30(8):1382-91. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16850151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wind J, Hofland J, Preckel B, Hollmann MW, Bossuyt PM, Gouma DJ, van Berge Henegouwen MI, Fuhring JW, Dejong CH, van Dam RM, Cuesta MA, Noordhuis A, de Jong D, van Zalingen E, Engel AF, Goei TH, de Stoppelaar IE, van Tets WF, van Wagensveld BA, Swart A, van den Elsen MJ, Gerhards MF, de Wit LT, Siepel MA, van Geloven AA, Juttmann JW, Clevers W, Bemelman WA. Perioperative strategy in colonic surgery; LAparoscopy and/or FAst track multimodal management versus standard care (LAFA trial). BMC Surg. 2006 Nov 29;6:16.</citation>
    <PMID>17134506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asao T, Kuwano H, Nakamura J, Morinaga N, Hirayama I, Ide M. Gum chewing enhances early recovery from postoperative ileus after laparoscopic colectomy. J Am Coll Surg. 2002 Jul;195(1):30-2.</citation>
    <PMID>12113542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>George SE, Ramalakshmi K, Mohan Rao LJ. A perception on health benefits of coffee. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. 2008 May;48(5):464-86. doi: 10.1080/10408390701522445.</citation>
    <PMID>18464035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu Z, Boersema GS, Jeekel J, Lange JF. Nicotine gum chewing: a novel strategy to shorten duration of postoperative ileus via vagus nerve activation. Med Hypotheses. 2014 Sep;83(3):352-4. doi: 10.1016/j.mehy.2014.06.011. Epub 2014 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>24998667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lubbers T, Buurman W, Luyer M. Controlling postoperative ileus by vagal activation. World J Gastroenterol. 2010 Apr 14;16(14):1683-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20379998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hibino G, Moritani T, Kawada T, Fushiki T. Caffeine enhances modulation of parasympathetic nerve activity in humans: quantification using power spectral analysis. J Nutr. 1997 Jul;127(7):1422-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9202101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown SR, Cann PA, Read NW. Effect of coffee on distal colon function. Gut. 1990 Apr;31(4):450-3.</citation>
    <PMID>2338272</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conway KJ, Orr R, Stannard SR. Effect of a divided caffeine dose on endurance cycling performance, postexercise urinary caffeine concentration, and plasma paraxanthine. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2003 Apr;94(4):1557-62. Epub 2002 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>12482764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tansy MF, Kendall FM. Experimental and clinical aspects of gastrocolic reflexes. Am J Dig Dis. 1973 Jun;18(6):521-31.</citation>
    <PMID>4705102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lohsiriwat S, Kongmuang P, Leelakusolvong S. Effects of caffeine on anorectal manometric findings. Dis Colon Rectum. 2008 Jun;51(6):928-31. doi: 10.1007/s10350-008-9271-y. Epub 2008 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18350336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stacewicz-Sapuntzakis M, Bowen PE, Hussain EA, Damayanti-Wood BI, Farnsworth NR. Chemical composition and potential health effects of prunes: a functional food? Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. 2001 May;41(4):251-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11401245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rao SS, Welcher K, Zimmerman B, Stumbo P. Is coffee a colonic stimulant? Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 1998 Feb;10(2):113-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9581985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Müller S. Author's reply: Randomized clinical trial on the effect of coffee on postoperative ileus following elective colectomy (Br J Surg 2012; 99: 1530-1538). Br J Surg. 2013 Mar;100(4):573. doi: 10.1002/bjs.9076.</citation>
    <PMID>23378207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dulskas A, Klimovskij M, Vitkauskiene M, Samalavicius NE. Effect of Coffee on the Length of Postoperative Ileus After Elective Laparoscopic Left-Sided Colectomy: A Randomized, Prospective Single-Center Study. Dis Colon Rectum. 2015 Nov;58(11):1064-9. doi: 10.1097/DCR.0000000000000449.</citation>
    <PMID>26445179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vitaglione P, Fogliano V, Pellegrini N. Coffee, colon function and colorectal cancer. Food Funct. 2012 Sep;3(9):916-22. doi: 10.1039/c2fo30037k. Epub 2012 May 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22627289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Noam Shussman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Postoperative Ileus</keyword>
  <keyword>Caffeine Citrate</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Citric Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Caffeine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Caffeine citrate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

