<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03097523</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JWCI-16-0501</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03097523</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mitigating Cephalad Fluid Shifts: A NSBRI Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>NSBRI</acronym>
  <official_title>Validation of a Cephalad Fluid Shift Countermeasure: Selection of Optimal Thigh Cuff Design Followed by Intracranial Pressure (ICP) Measurements During Extended Thigh Cuff Application</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>John Wayne Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Space Biomedical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>John Wayne Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a feasibility study to determine optimal thigh cuff design using a cephalad fluid
      shift protocol in patients who have an intraventricular catheter (such as Ommaya reservoir)
      placed for the delivery of central nervous system chemotherapy or for diagnosing potential
      elevation of ICP and monitoring its progression as part of standard medical care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in intracranial pressure using cerebral and cochlear fluid pressure (CCFP) analyser and a disposable pressure transducer</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Noninvasive and invasive ICP monitoring following standard of care procedures requiring access to ventricular catheter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Intracranial Pressure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with intraventricular catheter meeting eligibility criteria will undergo the following procedures:
Blood pressure, heart rate, electrocardiogram and Intracranial Pressure (ICP) monitoring after standard of care procedures are completed
Continuous ICP monitoring using a disposable pressure transducer (i.e., TruWaveTM)
Sequential placement in an upright, seated, supine 0°, and supine 15° head down tilt (HDT) positions for approximately 15 minutes for stabilization, followed by: Non-invasive ICP, intra-ocular pressure (IOP) assessment, femoral vascular ultrasound, jugular vascular ultrasound, and assessment of adverse events</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Custom Thigh Cuff</intervention_name>
    <description>The aim is to achieve positive and near normal forward arterial vascular blood flow to the lower extremities. Milder cuff pressures up to 65 mmHg will be used to limit venous return to the upper body.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, 18-89 years old

          -  Willing and able to provide informed consent

          -  Patients who have an intraventricular catheter placed for the delivery of central
             nervous system chemotherapy or for diagnosing potential elevation of ICP and
             monitoring its progression as part of standard medical care

          -  KPS ≥ 70

          -  For patients on active anti-cancer (intra-thecal or IV) therapy, must be at least 2
             weeks since last treatment; oral therapy is permitted

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 2 weeks since any prior surgery

          -  ICP &gt; 20 mmHg that cannot be clinically stabilized

          -  Pregnant (Note: women of child-bearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy
             test; women who are not of child-bearing potential are defined as: post-menopausal,
             age &gt; 55 years with cessation of menses for 12 or more months; or less than 55 years
             with postmenopausal status confirmed by follicle-stimulating hormone in the
             post-menopausal range; or who have had a hysterectomy, bilateral salpingectomy, or
             bilateral oophorectomy)

          -  Existing cardiovascular disease, diabetes, syncope, ocular disease that, in the
             opinion of the investigator, may confound the study results

          -  Uncontrolled neurological symptoms such as headache, nausea or vomiting that, in the
             opinion of the investigator, will limit the patient's ability to participate in the
             study

          -  Injury, trauma, venous thromboembolism, peripheral arterial disease or any condition
             that, in the opinion of the investigator, will prevent the subject from tolerating the
             application of a thigh cuff; history of treated DVT is permitted
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Santosh Kesari, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>John Wayne Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John Wayne Cancer Institute at Providence Saint John's Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Monica</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NSBRI</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data transfers or sharing is restricted to those JWCI study personnel identified on the site delegation log and/or per data use agreements. Data will be provided to the study sponsor.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

