<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03098524</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016/03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03098524</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low Tidal MEChanical Ventilation Against NO Ventilation During Cardiopulmonary Bypass Heart Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>MECANO</acronym>
  <official_title>Low Tidal MEChanical Ventilation Against NO Ventilation During Cardiopulmonary Bypass Heart Surgery : a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>CMC Ambroise Paré</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CMC Ambroise Paré</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND. Postoperative pulmonary complications are a leading cause of morbidity and
      mortality after cardiac surgery. To this date, there are no recommendations regarding
      mechanical ventilation associated with cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) during the surgery and
      anesthesiologists perform either no ventilation (noV) at all during CPB or maintain a
      low-tidal volume ventilation (LTV). Indirect evidence points towards better pulmonary
      outcomes when LTV is performed but no proper prospective trial with large inclusion of all
      types of cardiac surgery has been published.

      DESIGN. The MECANO trial is a single-center, double-blind, randomized controlled trial
      comparing two mechanical ventilation strategies, noV and LTV, during cardiac surgery with
      CPB. 1500 patients will be included for whom planned cardiac surgery with CPB is performed.
      They will be randomized between noV and LTV, on a 1:1 ratio. The noV group will receive no
      ventilation during CPB. The LTV group will receive 5 acts/minute with a tidal volume of 3
      mL/kg and positive end-expiratory pressure of 5 cmH2O. Primary endpoint will be composite of
      overall death, early respiratory failure defined as PaO2/FiO2 ratio &lt;200 mmHg at one-hour
      after arrival in the ICU, heavy oxygenation support (defined as a patient requiring either
      non-invasive ventilation, mechanical ventilation or high flow oxygen) at 2 days after arrival
      in the ICU or ventilator acquired pneumoniae defined by Center of Disease Control. Lung
      recruitment manoeuvers will be performed for noV and LTV groups, at the end of surgery and at
      the arrival in ICU with an insufflation at +30 cmH20 during 5 seconds. Secondary endpoints
      are those composing the primary endpoint with the addition of pneumothorax, CPB duration,
      quantity of postoperative bleeding, red blood cells transfusions, revision surgery
      requirements, length of stay in the ICU and in the hospital and total hospitalization costs.
      Patients will be followed until hospital discharge.

      SUMMARY. The MECANO trial compares a no-ventilation to a low-tidal volume strategy for
      mechanical ventilation during cardiac surgery with CPB, regarding a primary composite outcome
      including death, respiratory failure and pneumoniae.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND. Ventilator-acquired pneumonia (VAP) are a common postoperative complication and
      account for a large part of post-cardiac surgery morbidity and mortality. Incidence of VAP
      depends on numerous factors, some of which are pulmonary collapsus and atelectasis during
      cardiopulmonary bypass, a lowering of bronchial arterial blood flow and a systemic
      inflammation response syndrome during and after cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB).

      On the one hand, CPB allows blood oxygenation during cardiac surgery, regardless of heartbeat
      and oscillations, allowing surgeon to operate without disturbance.

      On the other hand, postoperative pulmonary complications appear to be more frequent when no
      mechanical ventilation is maintained while under CPB.

      Recent meta-analysis found oxygenation improvement after the weaning from CPB when
      low-tidal-volume (LTV) ventilation was maintained or after lung recruitment maneuvers (LRM),
      as compared to when there was no ventilation (noV). Furthermore, maintaining mechanical
      ventilation would reduce the inflammation response and tissue damage. The design of these
      studies did not provide with clinical hard endpoints such as respiratory complications, death
      or length of stay, hence, an unquestionable standardized strategy of lung protection during
      CPB has not been evidenced at this time and there are no scientific recommendations on
      whether mechanical ventilation has to be maintained during cardiac surgery or not, notably
      between low-tidal volume ventilation (LTV) and no-ventilation (noV).

      The investigators aim to prove superiority of LTV over noV strategy during CPB in cardiac
      surgery, in order to decrease postoperative respiratory complications.

      DESIGN. The MECANO trial is a single-center, double-blind, non-pharmacological, randomized
      controlled trial comparing two mechanical ventilation strategies, LTV and noV, during cardiac
      surgery with CPB.

      Population. All patients aged more than 18 years will be eligible planned for cardiac surgery
      with CPB will be eligible. All patients will provide written informed consent before their
      inclusion in the trial.

      Endpoints. Primary endpoint will be composite of overall death, early respiratory failure
      defined as PaO2/FiO2 ratio &lt;200 at one-hour after arrival in the ICU, heavy oxygenation
      support (defined as a patient requiring either non-invasive ventilation, mechanical
      ventilation or high flow oxygen) at 2 days after arrival in the ICU or ventilator acquired
      pneumoniae defined by Center of Disease Control. Secondary endpoints are those composing the
      primary endpoint with the addition of pneumothorax, CPB duration, volume of postoperative
      bleeding, red blood cells transfusions, requirements for revision surgery, length of stay in
      the ICU and in the hospital and total hospitalization costs. Patients will be followed until
      hospital discharge.

      Randomization. Patients will be randomized by the anesthesiologist when arriving in the
      operating room, between LTV and noV arm, on a 1:1 ratio, using a web software. Only the
      anesthesiologist will be aware of the allocation arm in order for him to perform the
      necessary ventilation strategy, however, physicians outside the operating room (hence, study
      investigators) will not be aware of the treatment arm. Any deviation from the protocol will
      be recorded, as will be the reason of deviation.

      Intervention. The noV group will receive no ventilation during CPB. The LTV group will
      receive 5 acts/minute with a tidal volume of 3 mL/kg and positive end-expiratory pressure of
      5 cmH2O.

      Lung recruitment maneuvers will be performed in both groups, at the end of surgery, and at
      the arrival in ICU with insufflation at +30 cmH20 during 5 seconds. In ICU, ventilation
      strategy will be lung-protective with: tidal volume=6 ml/kg of ideal body weight, PEEP=5
      cmH2O, FiO2 set to obtain PaO2 between 200 and 250 mmHg, inspiration/expiration time ratio =
      1:2. Other therapeutics will be left to the appreciation of the critical care medicine
      specialist.

      Data collection. All data will be recorded on a dedicated CRF. Preoperative data will be
      collected prior to the surgery (age, height, weight, Euroscore 2, smoking status, diabetes,
      peripheral arterial disease, pulmonary comorbidity, forced expiratory volume in one second,
      pulmonary infection in the past 30 days, creatininemia). Variables linked to the surgery will
      be: type of surgery, duration of CPB, number of red blood cells transfusions, number and
      reasons of manual insufflations. Daily visit will record temperature, PaO2, FiO2, ventilation
      mode, hemoglobinemia, leucocytemia, quantity of bleeding and any of the endpoints listed
      above. Time to events will be recorded as well. Follow up will be maintained until hospital
      discharge.

      Statistical considerations Sample-size calculation was based on a two-sided alpha error of
      0.05 and a 80% power. On the basis of respiratory insufficiency incidence after cardiac
      surgery, the investigators anticipate at least 25% of patients presenting postoperative
      respiratory complications. A relative improvement in the incidence of primary outcome of 20%
      between the 2 arms (odd-ratio 0.8 in favor of LTV arm as compared to noV arm) is expected.
      The required sample size is then 720 patients per group, 1440 patients in total. Accounting
      for attrition ratio, 1500 patients will be included. Intermediary analysis will be performed.

      Data analysis. Patients will be analyzed following intention to treat principle. Logistic
      regression will be performed for statistical analysis. Relative risks with 95% confidence
      intervals and differences between medians with 95% confidence intervals will be calculated
      when appropriate. Two-sided significance tests will be used throughout. The investigators
      will infer a subgroup effect if the interaction term of treatment and subgroup is
      statistically significant at P &lt;0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients are ventilated or not during the time they are sedated, so they are blind to their study arm.
Anesthesiologists perform mechanical ventilation or not during cardiopulmonary bypass and log per-operative data (such as number of insufflations) on a separate leaflet of the eCRF. Investigators (cardiologists and critical care specialists) are not aware of the treatment arm as it is performed during surgery.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause mortality or early respiratory failure or Late respiratory failure or Ventilator acquired pneumonia and early pneumonia</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented event or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Composite outcome with all-cause in-hospital mortality, early respiratory failure defined as PaO2/FiO2 ratio &lt;200 at the first hour after transfer in ICU after surgery, late respiratory failure defined as heavy oxygenation support (non-invasive ventilation, high flow oxygen or mechanical ventilation) two days after surgery and pneumonia (early or ventilator acquired) defined by Center of Disease Control (CDC) criteria (2016 guidelines).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause in-hospital mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until date of death from any cause, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>All-cause in-hospital mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early respiratory failure</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at one hour after transfer in postoperative ICU</time_frame>
    <description>PaO2/FiO2 ratio &lt;200 at the first hour after transfer in ICU after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>heavy oxygenation support</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed 2 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>requirement of non-invasive ventilation, high flow oxygen or mechanical ventilation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pneumonia (early or ventilator-acquired)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented event, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>pneumonia (early or ventilator acquired) defined by Center of Disease Control (CDC) criteria (2016 guidelines), diagnosed while in-hospital after the cardiac surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay in the ICU</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at the end of hospitalization, through study completion, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in the intensive care unit (ICU) (days) after the initial cardiac surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay in the hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at the end of hospitalization, through study completion, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in the hospital (days) after the initial cardiac surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost of hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at the end of hospitalization, through study completion, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Cost of hospitalization (euros)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Revision surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented event, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Requirement for any revision cardiac surgery after the initial surgery</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pneumothorax</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented event, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Pneumothorax diagnosed on chest x-ray or TDM occurring after the initial surgery</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at the end of hospitalization, through study completion, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative bleeding (mL)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiopulmonary bypass duration</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at the end of the initial cardiac surgery, up to 1000 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiopulmonary bypass duration (minutes)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Red blood cells transfusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at the end of hospitalization, through study completion, assessed up to 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Red blood cells transfusion (units)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Failure</condition>
  <condition>Atelectasis</condition>
  <condition>Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Pneumothorax</condition>
  <condition>Bleeding</condition>
  <condition>Surgery--Complications</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low tidal volume ventilation (LTV arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During cardiopulmonary bypass, mechanical ventilation is maintained with 5 acts/minute, tidal volume = 3 ml/kg (ideal body weight) with positive end-expiratory pressure = 5 cmH2O</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No ventilation (noV arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>No mechanical ventilation during cardiopulmonary bypass.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low tidal volume ventilation (LTV arm)</intervention_name>
    <description>During cardiopulmonary bypass, mechanical ventilation is maintained with settings described above.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low tidal volume ventilation (LTV arm)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No ventilation (noV arm)</intervention_name>
    <description>During cardiopulmonary bypass, no mechanical ventilation is performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No ventilation (noV arm)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lung recruitment manoeuver</intervention_name>
    <description>An insufflation with positive end-expiratory pressure +30 cmH20 during 5 seconds.
At the end of cardiopulmonary bypass, in the operative room. And after transfer to the ICU (intensive care unit).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low tidal volume ventilation (LTV arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No ventilation (noV arm)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion:

        more than 18 years old

        ability to provide an informed consent

        planned surgery

        surgical intervention with cardio-pulmonary bypass, aortic clamp and cardioplegia.

        Exclusion:

        impossibility to wean CPB at the end of cardiac surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lee S Nguyen, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CMC Ambroise Paré</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lee S Nguyen, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+33146418411</phone>
    <email>nguyen.lee@icloud.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Philippe Estagnasie, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+33146418411</phone>
    <email>philippe.estagnasie@wanadoo.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CMC Ambroise Paré</name>
      <address>
        <city>Neuilly-sur-Seine</city>
        <state>Ile-de-France</state>
        <zip>92200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie-Caroline Merand</last_name>
      <email>marie-caroline.merand@clinique-a-pare.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philippe Estagnasie, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lee S Nguyen, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alain Brusset, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.cdc.gov/nhsn/PDFs/pscManual/6pscVAPcurrent.pdf</url>
    <description>Center of Disease Control pneumonia criteria, 2016 update</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Canet J, Gallart L, Gomar C, Paluzie G, Vallès J, Castillo J, Sabaté S, Mazo V, Briones Z, Sanchis J; ARISCAT Group. Prediction of postoperative pulmonary complications in a population-based surgical cohort. Anesthesiology. 2010 Dec;113(6):1338-50. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181fc6e0a.</citation>
    <PMID>21045639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bignami E, Guarnieri M, Saglietti F, Belletti A, Trumello C, Giambuzzi I, Monaco F, Alfieri O. Mechanical Ventilation During Cardiopulmonary Bypass. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2016 Dec;30(6):1668-1675. doi: 10.1053/j.jvca.2016.03.015. Epub 2016 Mar 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27468893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schreiber JU, Lancé MD, de Korte M, Artmann T, Aleksic I, Kranke P. The effect of different lung-protective strategies in patients during cardiopulmonary bypass: a meta-analysis and semiquantitative review of randomized trials. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2012 Jun;26(3):448-54. doi: 10.1053/j.jvca.2012.01.034. Epub 2012 Mar 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22459933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cardiac surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Mechanical ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiopulmonary bypass</keyword>
  <keyword>Pneumonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Atelectasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumothorax</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Atelectasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

