<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03090334</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BDG-ETHIC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03090334</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A B-D-Glucan Driven Antifungal Stewardship Approach for Invasive Candidiasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A B-D-Glucan Driven Antifungal Stewardship Approach to Manage Empirical Therapy in Patients at Very High Risk for Invasive Candidiasis: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Bologna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Bologna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, prospective, open-label, randomized trial. Patients with severe
      abdominal condition developing severe sepsis or septic shock and receiving broad spectrum
      antibiotic and antifungal treatment will be randomized (1:1) to:

        1. discontinue antifungal treatment based on negative (&lt;80 pg/ml) result of 1,3
           beta-d-glucan performed on day 0,3,6 and 10

        2. continue antifungal treatment according with attending physician's decision.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary objective:

      Our objective is to establish whether a strategy based on beta-d-glucan (BG) assessment could
      achieve reduced antifungal consumption in patients with severe abdominal condition developing
      severe sepsis and septic shock without any impact on the outcome Secondary objectives i)
      Assess the accuracy of BG in the diagnosis of invasive candidiasis (IC) in in critically ill
      patients with a severe abdominal condition who develop severe sepsis or septic shock.

      ii) Describe the changes over the time of BG value according with colonization status,
      infection or none the aforementioned events.

      Material and Methods Study design: a multicenter, open label, randomized trial Population:
      all the patients with a severe abdominal condition who develop a severe sepsis or septic
      shock.

        1. Inclusion Criteria:

             1. adult (≥ 18 year) patients;

             2. signed informed consent before surgical procedure;

             3. severe sepsis or septic shock;

             4. at least one of the following conditions: i) post-operative peritonitis, ii)
                recurrent gastrointestinal perforation, iii) post-operative hepatobiliary and/or
                pancreatic disorders including necrotizing pancreatitis, iv) post-operative
                intra-abdominal abscess, and v) anastomotic leak.

        2. Exclusion criteria a. diagnosis of candidiasis before the enrollment b. exposure in the
           past 30 days to any antifungal treatment or diagnosis of invasive fungal infection; c.
           pregnancy or lactation; d. history of allergy to any of the antifungal drugs; e. major
           immunosuppression conditions including: i. neutropenia (&lt;0.5 × 109 neutrophils/L [&lt;500
           neutrophils/mm3] for &gt;10 days), ii. receipt of an allogeneic stem cell transplant or
           solid organ transplantation, iii. inherited severe immunodeficiency (such as chronic
           granulomatous disease or severe combined immunodeficiency), iv. HIV infection with
           lymphocyte T CD4+ cell count &lt; 200/mmc. f. patients with poor prognosis or unable to
           sign informed consent.

      Procedures Pre-randomization procedures

      At the time of patient enrollment (within 24 h from onset of severe sepsis/septic shock), a
      standardized diagnostic work-up must be performed including at least:

      i) two sets of blood cultures; ii) 5 surveillance cultures (rectal swab, urine culture,
      pharyngeal swab, axillary swab, groin swab).

      iii) in case of re-intervention or percutaneous drainage: Gram stain and culture of
      intra-abdominal samples; iv) serum BG determination. Antibiotic and antifungal empirical
      therapy should be started immediately after collection of microbiological samples according
      with a predefined standard of care (see appendix 1). Once completed this procedures patients
      will proceed to randomization.

      Randomization Patient eligible for the study after the beginning of antifungal therapy will
      be randomized 1:1 to receive (Group A) a BG driven de-escalation strategy or (Group B) a
      course of antifungal treatment based on the care provider's decision.

      In both groups, if cultures yield invasive candidiasis (see below) the patient will be
      managed in according with guidelines and excluded from the per-protocol analysis.

      In both groups, BG determination will be repeated at day +3, +6 and +10 after starting
      antifungal therapy.

      Randomization will be carried out providing closed envelopes to the participating centers
      immediately before the study onset.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>Care provider will be blinded to result of BG in patients enrolled in the standard of care arm</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antifungal consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Days of antifungal consumption will be compared between the two groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>28-day mortality will be compared between the two groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in ICU will be compared between the two groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy of BG</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value of BG in the diagnosis of invasive candidiasis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Invasive Candidiases</condition>
  <condition>Abdominal Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>De-escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this group, investigators will manage the antifungal therapy according to the BG levels as follows:
antifungal therapy will be stopped immediately after the BG response in case of serum BG &lt;80 pg/ml in presence of clinical stability (CS);
antifungal therapy will be continued until further BG determination, both for BG levels between 80-200 pg/ml and for BG &lt;80 pg/ml in patients without CS. In these cases, if the following BG value is &lt;80 pg/ml antifungal therapy will be stopped independently from the CS achievement.
antifungal therapy will be continued until day 10 for BG levels &gt;200 pg/ml</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this group antifungal treatment will be continued until clinician's decision.
Investigators will be blinded to the BG levels of patients enrolled in this arm, The BG results will be faxed directly to the coordinating center.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>De-escalation</intervention_name>
    <description>Antifungal therapy will be stopped according with BG results</description>
    <arm_group_label>De-escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  a. adult (≥ 18 year) patients; b. signed informed consent before surgical procedure;
             c. severe sepsis or septic shock; d. at least one of the following conditions: i)
             post-operative peritonitis, ii) recurrent gastrointestinal perforation, iii)
             post-operative hepatobiliary and/or pancreatic disorders including necrotizing
             pancreatitis, iv) post-operative intra-abdominal abscess, and v) anastomotic leak.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  a. diagnosis of candidiasis before the enrollment b. exposure in the past 30 days to
             any antifungal treatment or diagnosis of invasive fungal infection; c. pregnancy or
             lactation; d. history of allergy to any of the antifungal drugs; e. major
             immunosuppression conditions including: i. neutropenia (&lt;0.5 × 109 neutrophils/L [&lt;500
             neutrophils/mm3] for &gt;10 days), ii. receipt of an allogeneic stem cell transplant or
             solid organ transplantation, iii. inherited severe immunodeficiency (such as chronic
             granulomatous disease or severe combined immunodeficiency), iv. HIV infection with
             lymphocyte T CD4+ cell count &lt; 200/mmc. f. patients with poor prognosis or unable to
             sign informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maddalena Giannella, MD, phD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 0512143199</phone>
    <email>maddalena.giannella@unibo.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michele Bartoletti, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 0512143199</phone>
    <email>michele.bartoletti4@unibo.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospealiero Universitaria di Bologna Policlinico S.Orsola-Malpighi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <zip>40138</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maddalena Giannella, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 051 2143199</phone>
      <email>maddalena.giannella@unibo.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bassetti M, Marchetti M, Chakrabarti A, Colizza S, Garnacho-Montero J, Kett DH, Munoz P, Cristini F, Andoniadou A, Viale P, Rocca GD, Roilides E, Sganga G, Walsh TJ, Tascini C, Tumbarello M, Menichetti F, Righi E, Eckmann C, Viscoli C, Shorr AF, Leroy O, Petrikos G, De Rosa FG. A research agenda on the management of intra-abdominal candidiasis: results from a consensus of multinational experts. Intensive Care Med. 2013 Dec;39(12):2092-106. doi: 10.1007/s00134-013-3109-3. Epub 2013 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>24105327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kollef M, Micek S, Hampton N, Doherty JA, Kumar A. Septic shock attributed to Candida infection: importance of empiric therapy and source control. Clin Infect Dis. 2012 Jun;54(12):1739-46. doi: 10.1093/cid/cis305. Epub 2012 Mar 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22423135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maubon D, Garnaud C, Calandra T, Sanglard D, Cornet M. Resistance of Candida spp. to antifungal drugs in the ICU: where are we now? Intensive Care Med. 2014 Sep;40(9):1241-55. doi: 10.1007/s00134-014-3404-7. Epub 2014 Aug 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25091787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clancy CJ, Nguyen MH. Finding the &quot;missing 50%&quot; of invasive candidiasis: how nonculture diagnostics will improve understanding of disease spectrum and transform patient care. Clin Infect Dis. 2013 May;56(9):1284-92. doi: 10.1093/cid/cit006. Epub 2013 Jan 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23315320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Bologna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maddalena Giannella</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>beta-d-glucan</keyword>
  <keyword>abdominal candidiasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Candidiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intraabdominal Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Candidiasis, Invasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antifungal Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Miconazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

