<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03095625</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0089232</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03095625</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of Thromboelastography in Septic Shock</brief_title>
  <official_title>Role of Thromboelastography in Septic Shock: a Prospective Observational Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Turin, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Turin, Italy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Coagulation dysfunction is frequent in septic patients and it is associated with an increase
      risk of mortality. During sepsis platelets number usually decreases and their function is
      reduced and this mechanism is sustained by an inflammatory induced coagulopathy. Some recent
      studies evaluated the possibility to use viscoelastic whole blood tests of the haemostasis,
      such as thromboelastography (TEG), which analyze all blood components and their interactions
      during clot formation and dissolution and might be useful for assessing bleeding risk in
      septic patients. Maximun amplitude (MA) is one of the variables obtained from TEG analysis
      and it expresses the strength of the clot and the efficacy of platelet function. A low level
      of MA describes a lower strength of the clot determined by a lower number or a reduced
      function of platelet.

      The aim of the present study is to evaluate whether a lower level of MA and a pattern of
      hypocoagulability might be associated with an increased risk of bleeding and need of
      transfusion in patients with sepsis.

      We want to conduct a prospective multicenter observational study, enrolling 100 consecutive
      adults patients with sepsis. We will exclude patients under 18 years old of age, chronic use
      of oral anticoagulant and anti platelet treatment, hematologic malignancy, congenital
      bleeding disorders, oral contraceptives, lack of consent.

      Primary end point To evaluate whether a lower level of MA might be associated with an
      increased risk of bleeding.

      Secondary end points: to evaluate whether a different level of MA correlates with the
      biomarker of the severity of sepsis such as presepsin, with the biomarker of the severity of
      infection and whether a pattern of hypocoagulability might be associated with a risk of
      mortality.

      All enrolled patients will undergo a blood sample at admission (T0), after 72 hours (T1) and
      after 7 days (T2) and all the following parameters will be measured:

      Platelet count, APTT, PT, INR, fibrinogen, procalcitonin and presepsin .

      Additionally, all viscoelastic parameters (reaction time (R), clot formation speed (K), angle
      (alpha) and maximum amplitude (MA)) will be performed at bedside, at T0, T1, T2:

      Outcome measurements: Intensive Care Unit Length of Stay and mortality at 28 days and at 90
      days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction

      Coagulation dysfunction is frequent in patients with severe sepsis and it is associated with
      an increase risk of mortality. During sepsis platelets number usually decreases and their
      function is reduced and this mechanism is sustained by an inflammatory induced coagulopathy.
      Several studies have showed a correlation between altered function of platelets and sepsis
      severity.

      Conventional coagulation tests such as activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT),
      prothrombin time (PT) and international normalized ratio (INR) were developed mainly to
      monitor anticoagulation treatment and may not fully reflect the complex in vivo coagulation
      disturbances that usually characterizes sepsis. More recently some studies evaluated the
      possibility to use viscoelastic whole blood tests of the haemostasis, such as
      thromboelastography (TEG) and thromboelastometry (ROTEM), which analyze all blood components
      and their interactions during clot formation and dissolution and might be useful for
      assessing bleeding risk in septic patients.

      A more recent study identified a possible hypocoagulability pattern among septic patients at
      risk of bleeding using TEG variable and the authors found a strong correlation with increased
      risk of death. Maximun amplitude (MA) is one of the variables obtained from TEG analysis and
      it expresses the strength of the clot and the efficacy of platelet function. A low level of
      MA describes a lower strength of the clot determined by a lower number or a reduced function
      of platelet. In one recent study it has been described that a lower MA describing a
      hypocoagulability pattern might be associated with an increased risk of death.

      The aim of the present study is to evaluate whether a lower level of MA and a pattern of
      hypocoagulability might be associated with an increased risk of bleeding and need of
      transfusion in patients with sepsis.

      Methods A prospective multicenter observational study will be conducted in five intensive
      care units of five Italian university hospitals. We asked for Ethic Committee approval.

      Inclusion criteria: : all adult patients with diagnosis of sepsis admitted for more than 48
      hours will be enrolled.

      Exclusion criteria: patients younger than 18 years old of age; chronic use of oral
      anticoagulant and anti platelet treatment; hematologic malignancy; congenital bleeding
      disorders; oral contraceptives; lack of consent.

      Primary end point To evaluate whether a lower level of MA might be associated with an
      increased risk of bleeding.

      Secondary end points

        1. To evaluate whether a different level of MA correlates with the biomarker of the
           severity of sepsis such as presepsin (PSEP).

        2. To evaluate whether a different level of MA correlates with the biomarker of the
           severity of infection such as procalcitonin (PCT).

        3. To evaluate whether a pattern of hypocoagulability might be associated with a risk of
           mortality.

      Study Design Prospective, multicenter, observational

      All demographic and clinical data will be collected for each patient, as following:

      Age, gender, weight, simplify acute physiology score (SAPS) II, sequential organ failure
      assessment (SOFA) score (at admission and every 72 hours), clinical pulmonary infection score
      (CPIS), if the source of infection comes from lung, type of infection and microbiological
      isolation, haemodynamic parameters (heart rate, mean arterial pressure, pulmonary capillary
      wedge pressure, cardiac output, mixed venous oxygen saturation) and renal function
      (creatinine, urine output and fluid balance).

      All enrolled patients will undergo a blood sample at admission (T0), after 72 hours (T1) and
      after 7 days (T2) and all the following parameters will be measured:

      Platelet count, APTT, PT, INR, fibrinogen, procalcitonin and presepsin.

      Additionally, all viscoelastic parameters will be performed at bedside, using a TEG 5000
      Hemostasis Analyzer System (Haemoscope Corporation, Chicago, Illinois, USA), at T0, T1, T2:

        1. reaction time (R), normal range (3-8 sec)

        2. clot formation speed (K), normal range (1-3 sec)

        3. angle (alpha), which reflects the clot growth kinetics, normal range (55-75°)

        4. maximun amplitude (MA), normal range (51-69 mm)

        5. fibrinogen maximun amplitude (FFMA), normal range (14-24 mm)

      Bleeding definition We defined bleeding event as any intracranial bleeding identified at CT
      scan or any other bleeding at gastrointestinal tract (hematemesis or melena or frank blood in
      the stools), at tracheal aspirates or in the urine or bleeding during surgery and from wounds
      or any bleeding event requiring concomitant transfusion of three units of red blood cells.

      Outcome measurements

        1. Intensive Care Unit Length of Stay (ICU-LOS);

        2. Mortality at 28 days and at 90 days.

      Statistical analysis A power analysis was calculated considering primary endpoint:
      correlation between level of MA and risk of bleeding.

      We defined bleeding as intracranial, gastrointestinal, tracheal or surgical bleeding or any
      bleeding event requiring concomitant transfusion of three units of red blood cells. From
      previous study we observed an incidence of 26%.

      Power 86.4% B (size of the regression coefficient) 0.1 Standard deviation of MA 6 P (event
      rate) 26% Alpha 0.05

      The expected number of patients enrolled in 24 months is about 100 and with a Cox
      proportional hazard model we can estimate the Hazard Ratios (HR) and 95% CI with the
      parameters of the following table.

      A Cox regression of the log hazard ratio on MA as a covariate with a standard deviation of 6,
      based on a sample of 100 observations achieves 86.4% power at a 0.05 significance level to
      detect a regression coefficient equal to 0.1 (log of hazard ratio). The sample size was
      adjusted for a bleeding rate of 26%.

      The characteristics of the patients and clinical measures will be describe using the most
      appropriate statistics, as mean (SD), median (IQR) or percentages according to variable type
      and distribution.

      The cumulative incidence of bleeding during period of observation (7 days) will be estimated
      with the Gooley method, to take into account the competitive risk of death, and compared with
      the Gray test. The Fine and Grey model will be used to estimate adjusted HR and their 95% CI.

      Evaluation of associations between MA and severity of disease or infection will be assessed
      using Spearman's correlation test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>90 Days</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>risk of bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate whether a lower level of MA might be associated with an increased risk of bleeding</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensive Care Unit Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days and 90 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Sepsis</condition>
  <condition>Bleeding Disorder</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      whole blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        all adult patients with diagnosis of sepsis admitted to the ICU
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all adult patients with diagnosis of sepsis admitted for more than 48 hours will be
             enrolled

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients younger than 18 years old of age; chronic use of oral anticoagulant and anti
             platelet treatment; hematologic malignancy; congenital bleeding disorders; oral
             contraceptives; lack of consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luca Brazzi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 011 633</phone>
    <phone_ext>4001</phone_ext>
    <email>luca.brazzi@unito.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Daniela Pasero, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 011 633</phone>
    <phone_ext>6129</phone_ext>
    <email>daniela.pasero@unito.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Daniela Pasero</name>
      <address>
        <city>Turin</city>
        <state>Piedmont</state>
        <zip>10126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniela Pasero, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 011 633</phone>
      <phone_ext>6129</phone_ext>
      <email>daniela.pasero@unito.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Luana Bonaccurso</last_name>
      <phone>+39 011 633</phone>
      <phone_ext>6129</phone_ext>
      <email>223776@edu.unito.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Turin, Italy</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniela Pasero</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>Bleeding disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Viscoelastic tests</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sepsis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock, Septic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Blood Coagulation Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemostatic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

