<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00811603</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>474-07</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00811603</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial Comparing the Optimal Timing of Antibiotic Prophylaxis at the Time of Cesarean Delivery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimal Timing for Antibiotic Prophylaxis for Elective Cesarean Delivery in Term Gestations: A Randomized, Controlled Trial Comparing Cefazolin Administration Prior to Skin Incision Versus Following Cord Clamping</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MemorialCare</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Irvine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MemorialCare</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the rates of maternal and neonatal infectious
      morbidity in gravid patients undergoing cesarean delivery. Specifically, the investigators
      are examining whether the timing of antibiotic administration has any effect on rates of
      maternal and neonatal infections, neonatal sepsis work-up and length of hospital stay.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nearly fifty years have passed since Burke et al first demonstrated in animal model the
      reduction of infection rates in contaminated skin incisions with administration of antibiotic
      prophylaxis. Further research in the area confirmed the benefit of prophylactic antibiotics
      in human subjects. Patients who develop surgical infections are 60% more likely to spend time
      in intensive care unit, five times more likely to be readmitted to the hospital, and have
      twice the mortality rate compared to patients without infections. As a result the potential
      health care costs are staggering. Recently, the National Surgical Infection Prevention
      Project endorsed the recommendation that antibiotic prophylaxis should be administered within
      60 minutes before skin incision. This model has been universally accepted in all surgical
      fields with the exception of obstetrics.

      Cesarean delivery has been shown to be the most important risk factor for post-partum
      maternal infection. In fact, women undergoing cesarean delivery have a five to twenty-fold
      greater risk for developing infection compared to those undergoing vaginal delivery. Recent
      review by Cochrane Database found that there is an inconsistent and variable application of
      current recommendations in regard to appropriate timing, administration and choice of drug
      used for antibiotic prophylaxis at the time of cesarean delivery. Cesarean section holds a
      unique position amongst all the surgical procedures as being the only one where prophylactic
      antibiotics are administered after the incision is made. The concern for intrapartum fetal
      exposure of prophylactic antibiotics suppressing microbial growth and thereby masking
      neonatal sepsis led to a tradition of delaying antibiotic administration until umbilical cord
      clamping. While a recent study demonstrated that antibiotic levels do indeed reach
      therapeutic levels within cord blood very quickly after administration to the mother, no
      adverse outcomes to the newborns have ever been documented as a result. To date only four
      studies have looked at the timing of prophylactic administration at the time of cesarean
      section.

      In 1982, Cunningham et al randomized 642 women &quot;at high risk for infection following cesarean
      delivery&quot; to receiving antibiotics before or after cord clamping. The authors demonstrated
      that there was no difference between uterine infection rates between the two groups. While
      significantly more infants exposed to intrapartum maternal antibiotics were evaluated for
      sepsis, there were no cases of neonatal bacteremia in either group. However, it should be
      noted that the pediatricians in this study were fully aware of whether antibiotics had been
      given before or after cord clamping. Wax et al revisited the issue by randomizing 90
      consecutive term women in labor to receiving cefazolin preoperatively or after skin incision.
      While the authors failed to show any statistical significance between two groups, this study
      was clearly underpowered as only four cases achieved primary outcomes. Furthermore, the
      authors failed to demonstrate a significant increase is suspected sepsis in newborns whose
      mothers received cefazolin preoperatively. In 2005, Thigpen et al once again demonstrated
      that there was no disadvantage to the infant in regard to infectious morbidity. In addition,
      there was no difference in maternal infectious morbidity regardless of when antibiotics were
      administered. However, the results are questionable as nearly a quarter of all subjects
      received penicillin for GBS prophylaxis. Finally, Sullivan included 357 women in a well
      designed randomized, double-blinded study that demonstrated a statistically significant
      reduction in maternal infectious morbidity when the antibiotics where administered
      preoperatively. Not only was there no difference between two groups in regard to neonatal
      infection, but there was actually significantly fewer NICU admission days in preoperative
      antibiotic group.

      Despite the evidence that preoperative prophylactic antibiotics pose no harm to the fetus,
      obstetrics has been slow to adopt this practice. It is no wonder that cesarean infection
      rates have been shown to be considerably higher than comparable surgical procedures. While
      the evidence clearly demonstrates the absence of negative impact of preoperative antibiotics
      on neonatal outcomes, a contemporary scientific evaluation of the reduction in maternal
      infectious morbidity is warranted before adopting this practice on universal basis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the rates of maternal infectious morbidity with preoperative administration of antibiotics when compared to antibiotic prophylaxis given following umbilical cord clamping</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess incidence of neonatal infectious morbidity (i.e. rates of sepsis work-up, confirmed sepsis, and length of hospital stay) between two study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Cesarean Section</condition>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who receive antibiotic prophylaxis after clamping of the umbilical cord</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who receive antibiotic prophylaxis prior to skin incision</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cefazolin (Timing of Antibiotic Prophylaxis)</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients scheduled for a cesarean delivery will be randomly assigned to receive Cefazolin (antibiotic prophylaxis) either prior to skin incision or after the clamping of the umbilical cord</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients 18 years of age or older

          -  Any patient at term (&gt;37 weeks gestation) undergoing a scheduled cesarean delivery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women younger than 18 years

          -  Patients who are febrile during or prior to screening or with a diagnosis of clinical
             suspicion of endometritis (with or without maternal fever)

          -  Patients who present with ruptured membranes

          -  Known fetal malformations

          -  Contraindications to cefazolin administration (known anaphylactic reaction to
             penicillins or known cephalosporin allergy)

          -  Any exposure to antibiotics in one week prior to cesarean delivery

          -  Obstetrical indication for an emergent cesarean delivery

          -  Patients taking glucocorticoids or other immunosuppressant therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth Chan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Long Beach Memorial Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Long Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90806</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Irvine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 19, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 17, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 17, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 18, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Leo Pevzner</name_title>
    <organization>University of California, Irvine</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Antibiotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Prophylaxis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cesarean</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Antibiotic prophylaxis</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cefazolin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

