<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00816296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHW 08/159</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>GC 727</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00816296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Intestinal Microbiome in Obese Kids</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Intestinal Microbiome in Obese Children With and Without Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to investigate comparisons between the intestinal microbiome in
      patients with obesity and in patients with obesity and Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease
      (NAFLD). With this protocol we hope to better understand how the microbiome of each
      individual works with disease progression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to investigate and compare the composition of the intestinal
      microbiome in patients with obesity only to patients with obesity and Non-Alcoholic Fatty
      Liver Disease (NAFLD). In addition, we will investigate the relationship between alterations
      in the intestinal microbiome, immune activation, and the progression of NAFLD to
      Non-Alcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH). We hypothesize that alterations in the intestinal
      microbiome are associated with increased immune activation and progression of obesity
      associated NAFLD. Based on this hypothesis we propose the following aims:

      Aim 1. Identify and enroll pediatric cohort with obesity or obesity/NAFLD to study the role
      of the intestinal microbiome on the development of NAFLD.

        1. Enroll participants through the NEW Kids program for treatment of pediatric obesity at
           Children's Hospital of Wisconsin (CHW). Identify and classify participants through
           initial clinical evaluation, collect clinical metadata, and obtain and process blood and
           stool samples for analysis. Demonstrate feasibility by showing that participants can be
           recruited and participate in the specific study protocol.

        2. Follow study population through nutritional/exercise intervention, with follow up
           collection of clinical data, stool, and blood samples.

      Aim 2. Characterize the intestinal microbiome through quantitative PCR and high throughput
      sequencing analysis of stool specimens in participants with obesity and obesity/NAFLD.

        1. Demonstrate feasibility by showing that sampling aliquots from patient fecal samples can
           be successfully analyzed by proposed methods and yield consistent results for duplicate
           samples.

        2. Compare sequencing results and metagenomic analysis for study groups with particular
           attention to bacterial composition and metabolic capacity associated with energy
           harvest, lipid and carbohydrate transport, enhancement of epithelial barrier integrity,
           and choline metabolism.

        3. Investigate whether intervention (nutritional/exercise) results in longitudinal
           alterations in the intestinal microbiome.

      Aim 3. Characterize evidence of systemic inflammation by C-reactive protein (CRP), Tumor
      necrosis factor alpha (TNF-alpha)Transforming growth factor beta 1 (TGF-beta and LPS Binding
      Protein (LBP) levels, and analyze results in relationship to the intestinal microbiome and
      the presence of NAFLD.

        1. Compare levels of systemic inflammatory markers of participants with obesity vs.
           obesity/NAFLD

        2. Investigate whether intervention (nutritional/exercise) results in longitudinal
           alterations in systemic inflammation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    PI has left institution
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alterations in the intestinal microbiome are associated with increased immune activation and progression of obesity associated NAFLD.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize the intestinal microbiome through quantitative analysis of stool samples in participants with obesity and those with obesity and NAFLD.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize inflammatory markers of participants with obesity versus those obese participants that also have NAFLD.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Obese (BMI&gt;30) and normal AST and ALT. Between the ages of 5 and 18 years old.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Liver Disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Obese (BMI&gt;30) and elevated AST and/or ALT (evidence of NAFLD). Between the ages of 5 and 18 years old.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Draw</intervention_name>
    <description>2 tablespoons of blood will be drawn from participants at study entry, 3 months after study entry, and 6 months after study entry.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Liver Disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stool collection</intervention_name>
    <description>Stool will be collected from participants 3 times during the study -- at study entry, 3 months from study entry, and 6 months after study entry.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Liver Disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BodPod Measurement</intervention_name>
    <description>Body composition will be measured using a BodPod at study entry, 3 months after study entry, and 6 months after study entry.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Liver Disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liver Ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>A liver ultrasound will be performed at study entry and 6 months after study entry.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Liver Disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Participants will need to give a blood and stool samples on 3 separate occasions.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Gastroenterology Clinic at Children's Hospital of Wisconsin
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 5-18 Years old

          -  Willing to consent/undergo necessary procedures

          -  Obese (BMI&gt;30)

          -  Speak English or Spanish

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  any other causes of liver disease

          -  any chronic illnesses or life threatening conditions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vincent Biank, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital and Health System Foundation, Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Angulo P, Keach JC, Batts KP, Lindor KD. Independent predictors of liver fibrosis in patients with nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. Hepatology. 1999 Dec;30(6):1356-62.</citation>
    <PMID>10573511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iacobellis A, Marcellini M, Andriulli A, Perri F, Leandro G, Devito R, Nobili V. Non invasive evaluation of liver fibrosis in paediatric patients with nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. World J Gastroenterol. 2006 Dec 28;12(48):7821-5.</citation>
    <PMID>17203527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turnbaugh PJ, Ley RE, Mahowald MA, Magrini V, Mardis ER, Gordon JI. An obesity-associated gut microbiome with increased capacity for energy harvest. Nature. 2006 Dec 21;444(7122):1027-31.</citation>
    <PMID>17183312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li Z, Soloski MJ, Diehl AM. Dietary factors alter hepatic innate immune system in mice with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Hepatology. 2005 Oct;42(4):880-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16175608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brun P, Castagliuolo I, Di Leo V, Buda A, Pinzani M, Palù G, Martines D. Increased intestinal permeability in obese mice: new evidence in the pathogenesis of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol. 2007 Feb;292(2):G518-25. Epub 2006 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>17023554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fields DA, Goran MI, McCrory MA. Body-composition assessment via air-displacement plethysmography in adults and children: a review. Am J Clin Nutr. 2002 Mar;75(3):453-67. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11864850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nicholson JC, McDuffie JR, Bonat SH, Russell DL, Boyce KA, McCann S, Michael M, Sebring NG, Reynolds JC, Yanovski JA. Estimation of body fatness by air displacement plethysmography in African American and white children. Pediatr Res. 2001 Oct;50(4):467-73.</citation>
    <PMID>11568289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 30, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 30, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 1, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 21, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 21, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 24, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Vincent Biank</name_title>
    <organization>Medical College of Wisconsin</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NAFLD</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Microbiome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

