<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00818558</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>04-APN-08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00818558</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Method ISET (Insulation by Size of Epithelial Tumor Cells)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Value Forecasts of the Identification of the Circulating Tumoral Cells (CTC) in the Broncho-lung Carcinomas Not in Small Cells of Stages I and II by the Method ISET (Insulation by Size of Epithelial Tumor Cells)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is, i) to assess the presence and the frequency of CTC in NSCLC
      patients undergoing surgery by using cytopathological analysis after their isolation by size
      (ISET method), and, ii) to correlate the presence of CNHC with pTNM stage, histological
      subtype, and percentage of tumor cells present into the primary tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lung cancer is the most prevalent neoplasm and the major cause of tumor-related mortality
      worldwide. Despite recent advances in the management of resected lung cancers (i.e., the use
      of adjuvant therapy) and more effective treatments of metastatic tumors (i.e., molecular
      targeted agents), the cure rate of patients with lung cancer remains low (. Histological
      classification of lung tumors distinguishes small (SCLC) and non-small cell lung cancers
      (NSCLC). Most NSCLC display three histological subtypes: adenocarcinoma, squamous cell
      carcinoma and large cell carcinoma. The prognosis of these three NSCLC subtypes is quite
      similar. In this regard, development and validation of new prognostic/predictive biomarkers
      from tumor tissues and biological fluids is one of the more promising domain in translational
      cancer research. However, the clinical impact of new biomarkers has to be carefully
      validated, including for NSCLC. While pTNM staging is currently the only validated prognostic
      factor used in NSCLC patients follow up and treatment, 25% to 50% of patients with
      early-stage I NSCLC show tumor recurrence following extensive tumor resection, indicating the
      urgent need of more sensitive prognostic markers. Furthermore, it has been reported that the
      presence of occult metastatic disease correlates with disease recurrence in stage I NSCLC
      patients. There is now a sizable body of evidence that metastases could develop from
      circulating tumor cells (CTC) spread in blood before or during surgery . Thus, sensitive and
      specific detection of CTC in blood is considered as a potentially relevant predictive
      biomarker for patients with NSCLC. Indeed, the main goal for preoperative detection of CTC is
      to identify patients with high risk of recurrence after surgery, in order to perform more
      adapted therapeutic strategy. Despite several studies reported about CTC detection,
      methodological aspects concerning sensitivity, specificity and reproducibility have prevented
      a clear appraisal of their clinical impact. While RT-PCR and immune-mediated methods can be
      very sensitive, specificity remains a critical issue for these approaches as no transcript or
      antigen is known at present specifically recognizing tumor cells from solid tumors . In this
      setting, cytopathological analysis of circulating non hematological cells (CNHC), of
      epithelial (CEC) and endothelial (CEN-C) origin, isolated according to their size (ISET,
      Isolation by Size of Epithelial Tumor cells) is considered a promising approach, as CNHC
      enrichment is very sensitive and cell morphology is not damaged allowing to apply classical
      cytopathological criteria to identify tumor cells. In this regard, ISET technology has been
      previously reported to allow identification of CTC in patients with liver and breast tumors.
      However, ISET method has never been used to detect CTC in patients with NSCLC. The aim of
      this study is to determine the diagnostic potential of ISET method for preoperative detection
      of CTC in NSCLC patients. For this purpose cytomorphological criteria have been established
      by a group of 10 cytologists to classify CNHC in 3 groups : i) CNHC with malignant features
      (CNHC-MF) , ii) CNHC with uncertain features (CNHC-UMF), and, iii) CNHC with benign features
      (CNHC-BF). The presence and number of these circulating cells are then correlated with pTNM,
      histological subtype, and percentage of tumor cells into the primary tumors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence or absence of circulating tumoral Cells(Units) according to: 1) The pTNM stage 2) the histological type</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific survival and global survival, recurrence and metastasis</measure>
    <time_frame>in 2 years, 3 years and 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">520</enrollment>
  <condition>Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>stade IA [pT1 N0M0]</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>stade IB [pT2 N0M0]</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>stade IIA [pTI N1M0]</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>stade IIB [pT2 N1 et T3N0M0]</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>control groupe [tabagic subject]</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group B [intervention for a pulmonaire non tumoral pulmonary lesion]</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ISET Methode</intervention_name>
    <description>Sampling of blood - ISET Methode</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>6</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For the patients:

          -  patient having been operated for a strong suspicion or a suspicion of a malignant
             tumoral hurt corresponding to a primitive carcinoma not in small cell of the lung

        For the control subjects:

          -  Tabagical patients (between 10 and 30 packages years)

          -  unhurt of any malignant or mild tumoral pathology or patients that must benefit from a
             surgical operation for an extract of a hurt lung parenchymateuse for a not tumoral
             hurt

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with histories of cancer or the other synchronous cancer

          -  Patient with carcinomas with small cells, bronchiolo-alveolar carcinomas, the other
             types of tumors (lymphomes, sarcomas, etc.).

          -  Patient with neoadditives treatments

          -  Patient according to treatments additives others than protocols codified (in
             particular, platinum navelbine or gemcitabine platinum) for stages II
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Pr Hofman, PU-PH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU de Nice</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Pr HOFMAN, PU-PH</last_name>
    <phone>04 92 03 87 49</phone>
    <email>hofman.p@chu-nice.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pr Paul HOFMAN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Pr Hofman, PU-PH</last_name>
      <phone>04 92 03 87 49</phone>
      <email>hofman.p@chu-nice.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 7, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 7, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 7, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 8, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

