<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00810576</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2007-0658</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00810576</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination of Vorinostat and Bortezomib in Relapsed or Refractory T-Cell Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study To Determine The Safety and Efficacy Of The Combination of Vorinostat and Bortezomib In Patients With Relapsed Or Refractory T-Cell Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives:

        1. To evaluate the response rate for patients with T-cell Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma
           (NHL)receiving the combination of vorinostat and bortezomib

        2. To evaluate the safety and tolerability of the combination of vorinostat and bortezomib
           in patients with relapsed or refractory T-cell NHL.

      Secondary Objectives:

        1. To assess overall survival and time to treatment failure in patients with T-cell NHL
           treated with the combination of vorinostat and bortezomib.

        2. Correlative studies will be done to assess the role of vorinostat mediated apoptosis
           along with bortezomib synergy. Changes in marker expression from baseline to post
           treatment will be correlated with patient clinical response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Study Drugs:

      Vorinostat is designed to cause chemical changes in different groups of proteins that are
      attached to DNA (the genetic material of cells), which may slow the growth of cancer cells or
      cause the cancer cells to die.

      Bortezomib is designed to block a protein that plays a role in cell function and growth. This
      may cause cancer cells to die.

      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, on Days 1-14 of each 21-day study
      cycle, you will take vorinostat. Vorinostat capsules are taken by mouth, 2 times a day (1
      time in the morning and 1 time in the evening). The capsules must be taken with food (within
      30 minutes after a meal).

      On Days 1, 4, 8, and 11 of all cycles you will receive bortezomib through a needle in your
      vein. This will take less than 1 minute.

      If you begin to experience severe or intolerable side effects, the study drug schedule may be
      stopped for up to 2 weeks. If the side effects improve, you may be able to begin to receive
      the study drugs again, with a lower dose of bortezomib. The vorinostat dose will not be
      changed. If you continue to have severe or intolerable side effects with the lower dose of
      bortezomib, you will be taken off study.

      Study Visits:

      On Day 1 of all cycles, the following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will receive the vorinostat capsules (a 14-day supply for each study cycle) and
           instructions on how to take the drug. You will be instructed to return any unused
           vorinostat capsules back to the study staff at the end of each cycle.

        -  Your medical history will be recorded, including any drugs that you are taking.

        -  You will be asked about any side effects you may have.

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

      On Day 1, 4, 8, and 11 of all cycles, your vital signs will be measured.

      On Day 8 of all cycles, blood will be drawn (about 5 teaspoons) for routine tests.

      On Day 1 of every other cycle (Cycles 3, 5, 7, and so on), the following tests and procedures
      will be performed:

        -  You will have CT scans and/or Positron emission tomography (PET) scans to check the
           status of the disease.

        -  Blood (about 5 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests and to check the status of the
           disease.

        -  If the doctor thinks it is necessary, you may have a bone marrow aspirate and/or biopsy.

      You will have computed tomography (CT) scans and/or PET scans, as needed, every 2 cycles
      (Cycles 2, 4, 6 and so on), to check the status of the disease.

      Length of Study:

      You will receive the study drugs for up to 6 months (8 cycles). After 6 months (8 cycles) of
      receiving the study drugs, if the disease has not gotten worse or has become better, you may
      be able to stay on study and continue receiving the study drugs. The study drugs would
      continue to be given at the same dose and on the same schedule. The study visits, blood
      collections, and optional biopsies will also continue on the same schedule.

      If the disease gets worse or you develop severe or intolerable side effects at any time, you
      will be taken off the study drugs.

      End-of-Study Visit:

      If you go off study treatment for any reason, you will have an end-of-study visit within 4
      weeks of your last dose of study drug or before starting a new treatment. At this visit, the
      following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including a measurement of your vital signs.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  You will be asked how well you are able to perform the normal activities of daily living
           (performance status evaluation).

        -  Blood (about 5 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will have a CT scan and PET scans to check the status of the disease.

      Follow-Up Visits:

      After you are off study treatment, you will be contacted by phone call every 2 months to
      check on how you are doing for up to 5 years. These phone calls will last about 5 minutes.

      Up to 40 patients will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Terminated due to slow accrual.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients With Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Every two 21-day cycles</time_frame>
    <description>Computed tomography scans and/or Positron emission tomography (PET) scans obtained every two cycles to evaluate response using International Workshop Criteria of Complete Response, Partial Response, Progressive Disease, or Stable Disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vorinostat + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vorinostat 200 mg orally twice on Days 1-14 + Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m^2 intravenous (IV) on Days 1, 4, 8, 11.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vorinostat</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose of 200 mg by mouth twice daily on days 1-14 of each 21-day study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vorinostat + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SAHA</other_name>
    <other_name>Suberoylanilide Hydroxamic Acid</other_name>
    <other_name>MSK-390</other_name>
    <other_name>Zolinza</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Dose of 1.3 mg/m^2 by vein on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 of a 21 day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vorinostat + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
    <other_name>LDP-341</other_name>
    <other_name>MLN341</other_name>
    <other_name>PS-341</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have an established diagnosis of relapsed or refractory T-cell NHL
             Eligible histologies include; Peripheral T-cell lymphoma (unspecified), CD 30 +
             anaplastic large cell lymphoma ( ALK-1 positive and ALK-1 negative),
             angioimmunoblastic T-cell lymphoma, angiocentric/nasal type T/NK-cell lymphoma,
             intestinal T-cell lymphoma, hepatosplenic gamma delta T-cell lymphoma, subcutaneous
             panniculitic T-cell lymphoma, transformed Mycosis fungoides; All patients must have
             had at last one prior system regimen (radiation therapy does not qualify as systemic
             treatment).

          2. Patients who are eligible for blood and marrow transplant can receive this treatment
             to maximal reduction of tumor bulk: A minimum of two cycles of therapy will be given
             before crossing over to transplant.

          3. Patients must have at least one clear-cut bi-dimensionally measurable site by physical
             exam and/or computed tomography: Baseline measurements of measurable sites and
             evaluation of evaluable disease must be obtained within four weeks prior to
             registration of this study.

          4. Patient may have had prior radiation therapy for localized disease: Therapy must be
             completed at last four weeks before the enrollment in the study.

          5. Patient must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0
             to 2.

          6. Patients must be age 18 years old and above.

          7. Patients are required to have adequate bone marrow reserve as indicated: Absolute
             neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;/= 1000/mm^3; Platelets &gt;/= 80,000/mm^3; Hemoglobin &gt;/= 8g/dL;
             If there is bone marrow involvement by lymphoma then there is no minimum level of
             counts required; These values must be obtained within two weeks before protocol entry.

          8. Patients must have adequate liver function as indicated by:Bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5 times the
             upper limit of normal (ULN); Alanine transaminase (ALT) &lt;/= 2 times the (ULN) or
             aspartate transaminase (AST) &lt;/= 2 times the ULN; These values must be obtained within
             two weeks before protocol entry.

          9. Patients are required to have adequate renal function as indicated by a serum
             creatinine &lt;/= 2.5 mg/dL; This value must be obtained within two weeks before protocol
             entry.

         10. Male patients must agree to use an accepted and effective method of contraception for
             the duration of the study.

         11. Female patients must be willing to use two adequate barrier methods of contraception
             to prevent pregnancy or agree to abstain from heterosexual activity throughout the
             study or be post menopausal (free from menses &gt; two years or surgically sterilized).

         12. Female patients of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             (Beta hCG) within 72 hours of receiving the first dose of vorinostat.

         13. Patients must have the ability able to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with: T-cell lymphoma with skin involvement only are excluded if they have no
             evidence of systemic disease; T-cell prolymphocytic leukemia (T-PLL); T-cell large
             granular lymphocytic leukemia; Primary cutaneous CD30+ disorders: anaplastic large
             cell lymphoma and lymphomatoid papulosis

          2. Patients with active Hepatitis B and/or Hepatitis C infection.

          3. Patients with known HIV infection are excluded: These patients are excluded secondary
             to potential to target activated T-cells, in a population of patients already at risk
             for T-cell depletion, would be a contraindication to therapy.

          4. Patients with active infections requiring specific anti-infective therapy are not
             eligible until all signs of infections are resolved.

          5. Patients with left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 45%.

          6. Patients with pre-existing cardiovascular disease requiring ongoing treatment. This
             includes: Congestive heart failure; Severe CAD; Cardiomyopathy; Uncontrolled cardiac
             arrhythmia; Unstable angina pectoris; Recent MI.

          7. Patients with prior exposure to either vorinostat (including other HDAC inhibitors
             except valproic acid) or bortezomib: Patients who have received valproic acid (VPA)
             for the treatment of seizures may be enrolled on this study, but must not have
             received VPA within 30 days of study enrollment.

          8. Patients who are pregnant or breast-feeding: Effects of this treatment on the fetus
             and young children are unknown at this time.

          9. Patients who have had an invasive solid tumor malignancy in the past five years except
             non-melanoma skin cancers or cervical carcinoma in situ or ductal/lobular carcinoma in
             situ of the breast who is currently without evidence of disease.

         10. Patients undergoing anti-neoplastic chemotherapy, radiation, hormonal (excluding
             contraceptives) or immunotherapy, or investigational medications within the past four
             weeks. Receipt of systemic corticosteroids within 7 days of study treatment unless
             patient has been taking a continuous dose of no more than 10 mg/day of prednisone for
             at least 1 month.

         11. Patients with deep vein thrombosis within three months.

         12. Patients with lymphoma involvement of the CNS.

         13. Patients who have undergone prior allogenic transplantation: Prior autologous
             transplantation is accepted.

         14. Patient with concurrent use of complementary or alternative medicines that would
             confound the interpretation of toxicities and anti-tumor activity of vorinostat and/or
             bortezomib.

         15. Patient with a history of allergic reaction attributable to compounds containing boron
             or mannitol.

         16. Patients with psychiatric illness and/or social situations that would limit compliance
             with the study medication and requirements.

         17. Patients with grade 2 or more neuropathy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Barbara Pro, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 16, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>June 11, 2010</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2010</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2010</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Relapsed T-Cell Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory T-Cell Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>NHL</keyword>
  <keyword>T-cell NHL</keyword>
  <keyword>vorinostat</keyword>
  <keyword>SAHA</keyword>
  <keyword>Suberoylanilide Hydroxamic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>MSK-390</keyword>
  <keyword>Zolinza</keyword>
  <keyword>Bortezomib</keyword>
  <keyword>Velcade</keyword>
  <keyword>LDP-341</keyword>
  <keyword>MLN341</keyword>
  <keyword>PS-341</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral T-cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>CD 30 + anaplastic large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Angioimmunoblastic T-cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Angiocentric/nasal type T/NK-cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Intestinal T-cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatosplenic gamma delta T-cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Subcutaneous panniculitic T-cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Transformed Mycosis fungoides</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vorinostat</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Recruitment Period: 02/17/09 through 04/26/10. All participants recruited at UT MD Anderson Cancer Center.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Trial terminated due to slow accrual, only 1 patient registered.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Vorinostat + Bortezomib</title>
          <description>Vorinostat 200 mg orally twice on Days 1-14 + Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m^2 intravenously on Days 1, 4, 8, 11.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Vorinostat + Bortezomib</title>
          <description>Vorinostat 200 mg orally twice on Days 1-14 + Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m^2 intravenously on Days 1, 4, 8, 11.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="1"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="48" lower_limit="48" upper_limit="48"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Patients With Response</title>
        <description>Computed tomography scans and/or Positron emission tomography (PET) scans obtained every two cycles to evaluate response using International Workshop Criteria of Complete Response, Partial Response, Progressive Disease, or Stable Disease.</description>
        <time_frame>Every two 21-day cycles</time_frame>
        <population>No analysis done due to early termination resulting from low accrual.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Vorinostat + Bortezomib</title>
            <description>Vorinostat 200 mg orally twice on Days 1-14 + Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m^2 intravenously on Days 1, 4, 8, 11.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Patients With Response</title>
          <description>Computed tomography scans and/or Positron emission tomography (PET) scans obtained every two cycles to evaluate response using International Workshop Criteria of Complete Response, Partial Response, Progressive Disease, or Stable Disease.</description>
          <population>No analysis done due to early termination resulting from low accrual.</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="1"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Complete Response</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Partial Response</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Progressive Disease</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Stable Disease</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>13 Months</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Vorinostat + Bortezomib</title>
          <description>Vorinostat 200 mg orally twice on Days 1-14 + Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m^2 intravenously on Days 1, 4, 8, 11.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="1"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>1</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="1"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Barbara Pro, MD</name_or_title>
      <organization>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</organization>
      <phone>713-792-2933</phone>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

