<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00817102</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ATLANTA II</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00817102</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validation of Stenosis Assessment by Coronary Artery Computed Tomography Against Invasive Measurements of Fractional Flow Reserve in Patients With Significant Coronary Artery Stenoses</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Piedmont Healthcare</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Piedmont Healthcare</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the effectiveness of CorCTA by comparing the results of the test
      with another imaging method called Fractional Flow Reserve (FFR), which is done as a part of
      the cardiac catheterization.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Invasive X-ray coronary angiography remains the &quot;reference standard&quot; for the evaluation of
      coronary artery stenoses. Recently, coronary artery computed tomography angiography (CorCTA)
      has been introduced as a non-invasive method for the evaluation of coronary artery stenoses
      and has been shown to be highly accurate in stenosis detection when compared to invasive
      X-ray angiography. While invasive X-ray angiography and CorCTA evaluate morphological
      features of coronary arterial plaques, fractional flow reserve is an invasive measure of the
      hemodynamic significance of a stenosis obtained in the catheterization laboratory by
      measuring changes in intracoronary arterial pressure before and after maximal vasodilation
      induced by intracoronary adenosine. An FFR value less than 0.75 has been shown to predict
      ischemia in vascular beds distal to the stenosis by radionuclide perfusion modalities and has
      been shown to be associated with worse outcomes. Therefore, FFR is considered to be an
      invasive hemodynamic &quot;reference standard&quot; for the evaluation of the hemodynamic significance
      of coronary arterial stenoses. While intravascular ultrasound (IVUS) can provide additional
      morphological information in intermediate stenoses, it can not provide further functional
      information and cannot be used in more significant stenoses as the IVUS probe cannot be
      advanced through stenotic lesions.

      We are currently conducting investigation in the validation of CorCTA against FFR in
      intermediate coronary artery stenoses (40-70%) (see below under &quot;Preliminary Data&quot;). However,
      CorCTA has not been validated against invasive hemodynamic measurements of fractional flow
      reserve in patients with stenoses &gt;70% by invasive X-ray angiography. We hypothesize that
      CorCTA-derived measurements are accurate in the diagnosis of hemodynamically significant
      coronary artery stenoses, using FFR as the reference standard in patients with coronary
      artery stenoses&gt;70%.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The CT-derived endpoints: Study lesion %DS predicting FFR&lt;0.75; %AS predicting FFR&lt;0.75; MLD predicting FFR&lt;0.75; Study lesion MLA predicting FFR&lt;0.75; IVUS-derived endpoints: Study lesion MLD predicting FFR&lt;0.75; MLA predicting FFR&lt;0.75</measure>
    <time_frame>Upon completion of tests</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CorCTA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fractional Flow Reserve (FFR), Intravascular Ultrasound (IVUS), Virtual Histology (VH) or some combination of these three procedures</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FFR, IVUS, VH, or combination of the three</intervention_name>
    <description>Fractional Flow Reserve (FFR), Intravascular Ultrasound (IVUS), Virtual Histology (VH) or some combination of these three procedures will be completed during the cardiac catheterization procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CorCTA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 21-85

          -  Presence of at least one obstructive coronary artery stenosis as defined by:

               -  Previous catheterization or CT angiogram with any lesion 70% or greater

               -  Previous positive functional stress test (this does not include CTA alone)

          -  Ability and Willingness to provide informed consent

          -  Ability and Willingness to perform required follow up procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of coronary artery bypass graft surgery

          -  Previously revascularized lesion

          -  Creatinine&gt;1.6 mg/dL or GFR&lt;30 pre-procedure per institutional standards

          -  Known Pregnancy

          -  Inability to perform CTA

          -  Arrhythmia precluding diagnostic CT examination

          -  Contrast agent allergy that cannot be adequately premedicated

          -  Severe PVD precluding cardiac catheterization

          -  Patient not a candidate for IVUS and FFR

          -  Inability or unwillingness to provide informed consent

          -  Inability or unwillingness to perform required follow up procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Piedmont Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30309</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 2, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Charles Brown, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Piedmont Healthcare</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>coronary artery stenoses</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

