<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02219828</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>40/08/13</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001849-13</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02219828</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AnakInRa for Treatment of Recurrent Idiopathic Pericarditis (AIRTRIP)</brief_title>
  <acronym>AIR TRIP</acronym>
  <official_title>AnakInRa for Treatment of Recurrent Idiopathic Pericarditis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massimo Imazio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maria Vittoria Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent findings suggest that recurrent pericarditis (RP) may be a previously unrecognized
      autoinflammatory disease. The pivotal pathogenic role of interleukin (IL)-1 in RP has been
      shown by the achievement of complete responses after treatment with the recombinant
      IL-1-receptor antagonist, anakinra. Anakinra is the recombinant form of IL-1Ra. The proposed
      study is designed to demonstarate the efficacy of anakinra in RP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a 8-month, multicenter (3 Italian centers), randomized, double-blind,
      placebo-controlled, multicenter, medication-withdrawal study to evaluate the efficacy,
      tolerability, and safety of anakinra in adults and children with idiopathic recurrent
      pericarditis (RP).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence rate</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time to flare in the anakinra and placebo arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1. responder status in the open label phase</measure>
    <time_frame>60 days</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the responder status in the open label phase at Day 8 and 60 and at the end of the study with the following three criteria all to be met:
no or mild pericardial pain (a score ≤2.5 on a 21 circle VAS), AND
normal CRP levels (CRP ≤0.5 mg/dL), AND
absent or mild (≤10 mm) echocardiographic effusion. Assessments will be performed at Days 4, and 8 (study Period 1), and then at Day 30, and Months 2, 4, 6, and 8 if not otherwise specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2. change over time of the 3 outcome criteria, i.e. pericardial pain, CRP levels, and echocardiographic effusion;</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessments will be performed at Days 4, and 8 (study Period 1), and then at Day 30, and Months 2, 4, 6, and 8 if not otherwise specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3. time to response in the open label phase</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessments will be performed at Days 4, and 8 (study Period 1), and then at Day 30, and Months 2, 4, 6, and 8 if not otherwise specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>4. percentage of patients who relapse in the withdrawal part in the two arms;</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessments will be performed at Days 4, and 8 (study Period 1), and then at Day 30, and Months 2, 4, 6, and 8 if not otherwise specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5. change over time in patient's/parent's global assessment of overall well being on a 21 circle VAS;</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessments will be performed at Days 4, and 8 (study Period 1), and then at Day 30, and Months 2, 4, 6, and 8 if not otherwise specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6. change over time in the global evaluation of disease activity by physicians on a 21 circle VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessments will be performed at Days 4, and 8 (study Period 1), and then at Day 30, and Months 2, 4, 6, and 8 if not otherwise specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>8. percentage off CS and any other concurrent medication at 6weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessments will be performed at Days 4, and 8 (study Period 1), and then at Day 30, and Months 2, 4, 6, and 8 if not otherwise specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>9. tolerability and safety of the treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>8 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the tolerability and safety of the treatment, i.e. monitoring and recording all adverse events (AEs), with attention to local tolerability to s.c. injection, and serious adverse events (SAEs), and the regularly scheduled monitoring of hematology, blood chemistry, physical examinations, and vital signs including blood pressure over 8 months. Assessments will be performed at Days 4, and 8 (study Period 1), and then at Day 30, and Months 2, 4, 6, and 8 if not otherwise specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Idiopathic Recurrent Pericarditis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo sc</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anakinra</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Anakinra 2mg/Kg up to 100mg (maximum dose)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anakinra</intervention_name>
    <description>2mg/Kg daily sc up to 100mgday as maximum dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anakinra</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient's written informed consent for ≥ 18 years of age before any assessment is
             performed. Parents' or legal guardian's written informed consent and child's assent,
             if appropriate, are required before any assessment is performed for patients &lt; 18
             years of age.

          2. Age &gt; 2 years and &lt;70 years at screening visit;

          3. Recurrent pericarditis defined as a first episode of acute pericarditis followed by
             recurrences (Ann Intern Med. 2011;155:409-14) (at least two recurrences for this
             study). First episode of pericarditis is diagnosed when at least two of the following
             criteria were present: pericarditic typical chest pain (sharp and pleuritic, improved
             by sitting up and leaning forward), pericardial friction rubs, widespread ST segment
             elevation or PR depressions not previously reported, and new or worsening pericardial
             effusion. Recurrence is diagnosed when chest pain recurs and one or more of the
             following signs is present: fever, pericardial friction rub, ECG changes,
             echocardiographic evidence of new or worsening pericardial effusion, and elevations in
             the white blood cell count, erythrocyte sedimentation rate or C-reactive protein. To
             be enrolled in this study, elevation of C-reactive protein is mandatory both in the
             first attack and in the following recurrences. We differentiate recurrences from
             incessant pericarditis, term used to define patients with continued activity of
             pericarditis (with a symptom-free interval of &lt; 6 weeks) (Soler-Soler J,
             Sagristà-Sauleda J, Permanyer-Miralda G. Relapsing pericarditis. Heart.
             2004;90:1364-8).

          4. Specific etiologies excluded, including tuberculous, neoplastic or purulent
             etiologies, post-cardiac injury syndromes, and rheumatic autoimmune diseases.

          5. Records to document the number of prior pericardial recurrences, the time interval
             between them as well as prior treatments must be made available from the medical
             charts.

          6. Troponin values during at least one previous attack is recorded.

          7. QuantiFERON (QFT-TB G In-Tube) test or positive Purified Protein Derivative (PPD) test
             has been previously made and recorded.

          8. Patients will be enrolled at the time of a recurrent episode (at least the second
             recurrence, i.e. third episode) or &quot;relapse&quot; of pericarditis documented by the
             following criteria:

               -  recurrent pericardial pain (with a score of least 5 on the 21 circles VAS) AND

               -  increase in CRP≥1 mg/dL (being normal value = 0 - 0.5 mg/dL ), AND

               -  one or more of the following signs: fever (≥ 37°C), pericardial friction rub,
                  pertinent ECG changes, echocardiographic evidence of of new or worsening
                  pericardial effusion (see definition above)

          9. Continuous treatment with CS, the dose of which must not have been increased in the
             three days preceding enrolment

         10. Women of child bearing potentials (WCBP), defined as pre-menarche females aged 8 years
             and above or all women physiologically capable of becoming pregnant, sexually active,
             must use an effective form of contraception. Medically approved contraception (i.e.
             one that results in a less than 1% per year failure rate when used consistently and
             correctly, such as implants, injectables, combined oral contraceptives, and some
             intrauterine devices) could include total abstinence. Reliable contraception should be
             maintained throughout the study and for 3 months after anakinra discontinuation. Women
             are considered post-menopausal and not WCBP if they have had 12 months of natural
             (spontaneous) amenorrhea with an appropriate clinical profile (e.g. appropriate age,
             history of vasomotor symptoms) or six months of spontaneous amenorrhea with serum FSH
             levels &gt; 40 mIU/mL or have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or without
             hysterectomy) at least six weeks prior to study entry. In the case of oophorectomy
             alone, only when the reproductive status of the woman has been confirmed by follow up
             hormone level assessment she considered a WCBP.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients fulfilling any of the following criteria are not eligible for enrollment in
             this study:

               1. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of
                  a female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
                  positive hCG laboratory test (&gt; 5 mIU/mL).

               2. History of being immunocompromised, including a positive HIV at screening (ELISA
                  and Western blot) test result.

               3. Positive QuantiFERON (QFT-TB G In-Tube) test or positive Purified Protein
                  Derivative (PPD) test (≥ 5 mm induration) performed after the first attack of
                  pericarditis. Patients with a positive PPD test (≥ 5 mm induration) at screening
                  may be enrolled only if they have either a negative chest X-ray or a negative
                  QuantiFERON test.

               4. Live vaccinations within three months prior to the start of the trial, during the
                  trial, and up to three months following the last anakinra dose.

               5. History of malignancy of any organ system (other than localized basal cell
                  carcinoma of the skin), treated or untreated, within the past 5 years, regardless
                  of whether there is evidence of local recurrence or metastases

               6. History of significant other medical conditions, which in the Investigator's
                  opinion would exclude the patient from participating in this trial including
                  current pericarditis due to known diseases (e.g. tuberculosis, neoplastic or
                  purulent causes, connective tissue diseases, acute rheumatic fever, etc.)

               7. History of recurrent and/or evidence of active bacterial, fungal, or viral
                  infection(s).

               8. History of Type I hypersensitivity to anakinra.

               9. History of poor compliance.

              10. Use of any investigational drug (or biologic), or device within five half-lives
                  of the drug prior to study entry or during the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Internal Medicine Division, OSpedale Papa Giovanni XXIII</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergamo</city>
        <zip>24100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Dept. Ospedale Gaslini</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <zip>16100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiology Dpt, Maria Vittoria Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <zip>10141</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 14, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 17, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 17, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 17, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Maria Vittoria Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Massimo Imazio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Cardiology Dpt ASLTO2</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pericarditis</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent pericarditis</keyword>
  <keyword>corticosteroids</keyword>
  <keyword>anakinra</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pericarditis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interleukin 1 Receptor Antagonist Protein</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

