<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02215070</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00051736</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02215070</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pasireotide in Prevention of GI Toxicity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevention of Gastrointestinal Toxicity From Total Body Irradiation or High Dose Chemotherapy With Pasireotide</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Anthony Sung, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate if the drug, Pasireotide, is safe and effective in
      reducing the gastrointestinal side effects of the drugs received to prepare for allogeneic
      stem cell transplant. The study will also evaluate if Pasireotide is effective in reducing
      acute and chronic Graft-versus-Host-Disease (GvHD) after transplant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study design will be a non-randomized phase II. Forty patients receiving an ablative
      preparatory regimen will receive pasireotide subcutaneous (0.9 mg, b.i.d.) one day prior to
      initiation of the preparatory regimen and continuing for eight days following the completion
      of the preparatory regimen not to exceed 14 days total dosing. We select matched controls
      from existing patients who did not take the drug to minimize the time it takes to complete
      the trial.

      TBI is fractionated over four days to a total dose of 1200 Gy. Busulfan is used at an
      equivalent oral dose of 4 mg/kg daily over four days. These two agents are combined with
      cyclophosphamide to complete the preparatory regimen. GVHD prophylaxis with methotrexate will
      be on days +1, +3, +6 and +11. G-CSF is not used as part of the standard of care.

      The study will collect data prior to initiation of the drug, day 7, day 14 and weekly
      thereafter until day 100, a standard time to measure acute toxicity related to the stem cell
      transplantation. The total days on therapy will be recorded as well as any SAE that is
      outside the expected for stem cell transplantation. We will also follow the occurrence of
      GVHD and infectious complications.

      Video capsule endoscopy will be performed in a subset of ten study patients on the last day
      study drug is administered. Patients will be given detailed instructions to prepare for the
      procedure. An investigator who is blinded to the group allocation of the patients/volunteers
      separately will review the images obtained from each of the capsule examinations. Images will
      be examined for evidence of the four following types of abnormalities: reddened/edema/villous
      blunting, erosion, ulcer and stenosis. Each of these categories will be scored from 0-3 and
      summed to obtain an overall index that will range from 0 (normal study) to 12 (severely
      abnormal in all categories).

      Citrulline assay Measurement of citrulline concentration has been used as a marker for
      cytotoxic treatment-induced intestinal damage and it is highly reproducible. The citrulline
      concentration appears to be a quantitative parameter that is independent of the underlying
      cause for epithelial cell loss and functions well in the post-SCT setting. Five mls of blood
      will be collected in heparinized tubes on days 0, 7, and 14. Tubes will be centrifuged
      according to manufacturer's instructions and the plasma will be collected and stored at -80C
      until shipment to the laboratory performing the assay.

      Calprotectin assay Calprotectin has been described as another biomarker of GI injury. During
      radiation-induced inflammation, leucocytes infiltrate the mucosa and increase the level of
      fecal calprotectin. At least 50 g stool in a will be collected from patients on days 0, 7,
      and 14. Samples will be stored at -80C until shipment to the laboratory performing the assay.
      Calprotectin will be measured with an ELISA kit (CALPRO, Oslo, Norway) in accordance with the
      manufacturer's instructions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of GI toxicity from the preparatory regimen and the GVHD prophylaxis in Stem Cell Transplantation (SCT) patients who are treated with pasireotide</measure>
    <time_frame>100 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be conditioned with TBI or high dose busulfan prior to transplantation as both regimens can lead to severe GI toxicity. All patients will also receive systemic methotrexate as part of the GVHD prophylaxis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute or chronic GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
    <description>The control group will be selected based on concurrent patients who do not enroll on this study. This group will be matched based on age, preparatory regimen and number of prior therapies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Citrulline and fecal calprotectin levels will be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
    <description>These levels will be evaluated as biomarkers of GI tract health and function in SCT patients and the correlation between these biomarkers and GI toxicity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate GI toxicity assessment by video capsule endoscopy.</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Video capsule endoscopy will be performed in a subset of ten study patients on the last day study drug is administered. Images will be examined for evidence of the four following types of abnormalities: reddened/edema/villous blunting, erosion, ulcer and stenosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematological Malignancies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pasireotide + Chemo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pasireotide combined with Busulfan. Methotrexate will be given after the stem cell transplant.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pasireotide + Total Body Irradiation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pasireotide combined with Total Body Irradiation (TBI). Methotrexate will be given after the stem cell transplant.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pasireotide + Chemo</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible subjects will receive pasireotide daily for 5 days before stem cell transplant, the day of the stem cell transplant, and daily for 8 days following the stem cell transplant. Chemotherapy (Busulfan) will be given 4 days before stem cell transplant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pasireotide + Chemo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pasireotide + Total Body Irradiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible subjects will receive pasireotide daily for 5 days before stem cell transplant, the day of the stem cell transplant, and daily for 8 days following the stem cell transplant. Total Body Irradiation (TBI) will be given 4 days before stem cell transplant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pasireotide + Total Body Irradiation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Consenting 4-6/6 antigen matched stem cell donor or genetically matched unrelated bone
             marrow or adult stem cell donor.

          -  18 years of age or older at the time of study enrollment.

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis for which an allogeneic transplant is utilized.
             Eligible patients may include the following:

               -  High risk ALL in first complete remission, with high risk being defined by the
                  presence of t(4;11) or t(9;22), or those presenting with extreme
                  hyperleukocytosis or failure to achieve a complete remission after standard
                  induction therapy. Patients with Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) in first complete
                  remission.

               -  All patients with AML, Acute Lymphoid Leukemia (ALL) or Acute Non-Lymphocytic
                  Leukemia (ANLL) in second or subsequent remission.

               -  Patients with AML, ALL or ANLL in relapse.

               -  Patients with Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS).

               -  Patients with Chronic Myeloid Leukemia (CML).

               -  Patients with Lymphoma

          -  Meet standard criteria for allogeneic transplant

          -  Screening or baseline Fridericia Correction Formula (QTcF) &lt; 470 msec.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No active central nervous system (CNS) disease at the time of study enrollment.

          -  No uncontrolled (not being treated) infections at the time of cytoreduction or a
             history of immunodeficiency, including a positive HIV test result. An HIV test will
             not be required; however, previous medical history will be reviewed.

          -  No uncontrolled diabetes at the time of cytoreduction. All patients with diabetes must
             be optimized on their diabetes regimen prior to initiating pasireotide.

          -  If a patient is diabetic: uncontrolled diabetes as defined by HbA1c &gt; 8%* despite
             adequate therapy

          -  No concurrent involvement in any other clinical trial that affects mucositis or GI
             toxicity.

          -  Moderately impaired hepatic function (Child-Pugh B) or severe hepatic impairment
             (Child-Pugh C) are excluded.

          -  No co-morbid condition which, in the view of the Principal Investigator, renders the
             patient at high risk from treatment complications.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to somatostatin analogs or any component of the pasireotide LAR
             or s.c. formulations.

          -  Abnormal coagulation (PT or activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) elevated by
             30% above normal limits).

          -  On continuous anticoagulation therapy. Patients who were on anticoagulant therapy must
             complete a washout period of at least 10 days and have confirmed normal coagulation
             parameters before study inclusion.

          -  History of syncope or family history of idiopathic sudden death.

          -  Sustained or clinically significant cardiac arrhythmias.

          -  Risk factors for Torsades de Pointes such as hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, cardiac
             failure, clinically significant/symptomatic bradycardia, or high-grade
             atrioventricular (AV) block.

          -  Concomitant disease(s) that could prolong QT such as autonomic neuropathy (caused by
             diabetes, or Parkinson's disease), HIV, cirrhosis, uncontrolled hypothyroidism or
             cardiac failure.

          -  Family history of long QT syndrome.

          -  Concomitant medications known to prolong the QT interval.

          -  No major surgery/surgical therapy for any cause within 1 month. Patients should have
             recovered from the treatment and have a good clinical condition before entering the
             study.

          -  Known gallbladder or bile duct disease, symptomatic cholelithiasis, acute or chronic
             pancreatitis.

          -  Use of an investigational drug within 1 month prior to dosing

          -  History of non-compliance to medical regimens or who are considered potentially
             unreliable or will not be able to complete the entire study

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or lactating, or are of childbearing potential
             (defined as all women physiologically capable of becoming pregnant) and not practicing
             an effective method of contraception/birth control

          -  Known malabsorption syndrome, short bowel or chologenic diarrhea not controlled by
             specific therapeutic means.

          -  Not biochemically euthyroid. Patients with known history of hypothyroidism are
             eligible if they are on adequate and stable replacement thyroid hormone therapy for at
             least 3 months.

          -  Serum magnesium ≥ upper limit of normal

          -  Patients with hypocortisolism

          -  Patients with bradycardia

          -  Patients with QT prolongation

          -  Patients with pituitary hormone deficiency
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony Sung, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Krista Rowe, RN</last_name>
    <phone>919-684-7115</phone>
    <email>krista.rowe@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas R Spitzer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-1124</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jami Brown</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-9190</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anthony Sung, MD</last_name>
      <phone>919-668-5710</phone>
      <email>anthony.sung@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 11, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 12, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 13, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anthony Sung, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Lymphoid Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Non-Lymphocytic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Myeloid Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pasireotide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Somatostatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

