<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02214147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C14019</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1155-6072</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02214147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetics of Alisertib in Adults With Advanced Solid Tumors or Relapsed/Refractory Lymphoma With Varying Degrees of Hepatic Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetics of Oral Alisertib (MLN8237) in Adult Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors or Relapsed/Refractory Lymphoma With Varying Degrees of Hepatic Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effect of moderate or severe hepatic impairment
      on the single-dose pharmacokinetics of alisertib in adult participants with cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called alisertib. Alisertib is being tested to assess
      how it is processed by the body in participants with advanced solid tumors or
      relapsed/refractory lymphoma with varying degrees of liver function. This study will also
      assess laboratory results and safety.

      The study will enroll approximately 48 participants. Participants will be assigned to 1 of
      the 3 treatment groups based on the status of their liver function: Normal hepatic function
      (Total bilirubin ≤ upper limit of the normal range [ULN] and alanine aminotransferase [ALT]
      level ≤ ULN), moderate hepatic impairment (Total bilirubin &gt; 1.5-3 x ULN and ALT level =
      Any), or severe hepatic impairment (Total bilirubin &gt; 3 x ULN and ALT level = Any). All
      participants will be administered one 50 mg dose of alisertib on Day 1, Cycle 1. Alisertib
      will be administered again on Days 8 through 14 of Cycle 1, followed by a 14-day rest period.
      Doses administered on Days 8-14 will be 50, 30, or 20 mg of alisertib, depending on hepatic
      function. Alisertib may then be continued at the same dose as in Cycle 1, Days 8-14 in 21-day
      cycles (7 days of alisertib followed by a 14-day rest period) for up to 1 year (approximately
      16 cycles).

      This multicenter trial will be conducted in USA only. The overall time to participate in this
      study is up to 13 months unless it is determined by the investigator, with agreement by the
      sponsor, that a participant would derive clinical benefit from continued treatment beyond 12
      months. Participants will make up to 51 visits to the clinic including an end-of-study visit
      30 days after the last dose of study drug for a follow-up assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of alisertib</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 Day 1 Pre-dose and, and at multiple timepoints (up to 168 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) is the peak plasma concentration of a drug after administration, obtained directly from the plasma concentration-time curve.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to the time of the last quantifiable concentration (AUC0-last) of alisertib</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 Day 1 Pre-dose and, and at multiple timepoints (up to 168 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve from zero to the time of the last quantifiable concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to infinity (AUC0-∞) of alisertib</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 Day 1 Pre-dose and, and at multiple timepoints (up to 168 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to infinity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who experience at least 1 treatment-emergent adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 30 days after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any unfavorable and unintended sign (eg, a clinically significant abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a drug, whether or not it is considered related to the drug. A treatment-emergent adverse event is defined as an adverse event with an onset that occurs after receiving study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants who experience at least 1 serious adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 30 days after last dose</time_frame>
    <description>A serious adverse event is any untoward medical occurrence or effect that at any dose of a drug results in death, is life-threatening, requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in persistent or significant disability/incapacity, is a congenital anomaly/birth defect, or is medically important due to other reasons than the above mentioned criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with clinically significant laboratory values or vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to the end of the study (up to 12 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory assessments include serum chemistry and hematology. Vital signs include measurements of sitting diastolic and systolic blood pressure, heart rate, and temperature.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of the alisertib metabolites M1 and M2</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 Day 1 Pre-dose and, and at multiple timepoints (up to 168 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of the alisertib metabolites M1 and M2 will be determined from the concentration-time curve of each participant using non-compartmental methods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to reach the maximum plasma concentration (Tmax) of the alisertib metabolites M1 and M2</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 Day 1 Pre-dose and, and at multiple timepoints (up to 168 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The time to reach the maximum plasma concentration (Tmax) of the alisertib metabolites M1 and M2 will be determined from the concentration-time curve of each participant using non-compartmental methods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to the time of the last quantifiable concentration (AUC0-last) of the alisertib metabolites M1 and M2</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 Day 1 Pre-dose and, and at multiple timepoints (up to 168 hours) post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to the time of the last quantifiable concentration (AUC0-last) of the alisertib metabolites M1 and M2 will be determined from the concentration-time curve of each participant using non-compartmental methods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-normalized trough concentration of alisertib on Cycle 1 Day 14</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose on Day 14 of Cycle 1</time_frame>
    <description>A single blood sample will be collected pre-dose on Cycle 1 Day 14. The concentration of alisertib will be determined in the plasma sample and dose-normalized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Relapsed/Refractory Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alisertib: Normal hepatic function</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive alisertib 50 mg, orally, once, on Cycle 1 Day 1. Participants will then receive alisertib 50 mg twice daily (BID) for 7 days starting at Cycle 1 Day 8 through Cycle 1 Day 14 followed by a 14-day rest period. Starting at Cycle 2 Day 1, participants will receive alisertib 50 mg BID for 7 days followed by a 14-day rest period unless a dose reduction is indicated. Participants may continue to receive alisertib until they experience progressive disease or unacceptable alisertib-related toxicities for up to 12 months (approximately 16 cycles), unless it is determined by the investigator, with agreement by the sponsor, that a participant would derive clinical benefit from continued treatment beyond 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alisertib: Moderate hepatic impairment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive alisertib 50 mg, orally, once, on Cycle 1 Day 1. Participants will then receive alisertib 30 mg BID for 7 days starting at Cycle 1 Day 8 through Cycle 1 Day 14 followed by a 14-day rest period. Starting at Cycle 2 Day 1, participants will receive alisertib 30 mg BID for 7 days followed by a 14-day rest period unless a dose reduction is indicated. Patients may continue to receive alisertib until they experience progressive disease or unacceptable alisertib-related toxicities for up to 12 months (approximately 16 cycles), unless it is determined by the investigator, with agreement by the sponsor, that a participant would derive clinical benefit from continued treatment beyond 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alisertib: Severe hepatic impairment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive alisertib 50 mg, orally, once, on Cycle 1 Day 1. Participants will then receive alisertib 20 mg BID for 7 days starting at Cycle 1 Day 8 through Cycle 1 Day 14 followed by a 14-day rest period. Starting at Cycle 2 Day 1, participants will receive alisertib 20 mg BID for 7 days followed by a 14-day rest period unless a dose reduction is indicated. Participants may continue to receive alisertib until they experience progressive disease or unacceptable alisertib-related toxicities for up to 12 months (approximately 16 cycles), unless it is determined by the investigator, with agreement by the sponsor, that a participant would derive clinical benefit from continued treatment beyond 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alisertib</intervention_name>
    <description>Alisertib will be supplied as enteric coated tablets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alisertib: Normal hepatic function</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Alisertib: Moderate hepatic impairment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Alisertib: Severe hepatic impairment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MLN8237</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female participants 18 years of age or older.

          2. Histologically or cytologically confirmed metastatic and/or advanced solid tumors or
             lymphomas for which standard curative or life-prolonging treatment does not exist or
             is no longer effective or tolerable.

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 2.

          4. Female participants who:

               -  Are post-menopausal for at least 1 year before the screening visit, OR

               -  Are surgically sterile, OR

               -  If they are of childbearing potential, agree to practice 2 effective methods of
                  contraception, at the same time, from the time of signing the informed consent
                  through 30 days after the last dose of study drug, or agree to practice true
                  abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of the
                  participant (periodic abstinence [eg, calendar, ovulation, symptothermal,
                  postovulation methods] and withdrawal are not acceptable methods of
                  contraception).

          5. Male participants, even if surgically sterilized (ie, status postvasectomy), who:

               -  Agree to practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study
                  treatment period and through 4 months after the last dose of study drug, or

               -  Agree to practice true abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the participant (periodic abstinence [eg, calendar, ovulation,
                  symptothermal, postovulation methods for the female partner] and withdrawal are
                  not acceptable methods of contraception).

          6. Voluntary written consent must be given before performance of any study-related
             procedure not part of standard medical care, with the understanding that consent may
             be withdrawn by the participant at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

          7. Suitable venous access for the study-required blood sampling, including
             pharmacokinetics.

          8. Ability to swallow tablets.

          9. Participants with biliary obstruction for which a stent had been placed are eligible
             provided that the stent has been in place for more than 14 days before the first dose
             of alisertib and liver function has stabilized.

         10. Recovered from the reversible effects of prior antineoplastic therapy (ie, ≤ Grade 1
             toxicity or baseline).

         11. Clinical laboratory values as specified below:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1500/μL and platelet count ≥ 75,000/μL.

               -  Participants with normal hepatic function: Total bilirubin and alanine
                  aminotransferase (ALT) must be ≤ upper limit of the normal range (ULN).

               -  Participants with moderate hepatic impairment: total bilirubin must be &gt; 1.5 to 3
                  x ULN with any ALT level.

               -  Participants with severe hepatic impairment: total bilirubin must be &gt; 3 x ULN
                  with any ALT level.

               -  Measured creatinine clearance or calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 30 mL/minute.
                  Note: If a calculated creatinine clearance is used, it should be calculated
                  according to the Cockcroft-Gault formula.

               -  Hemoglobin must be ≥ 8 g/dL.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participants of North/East Asian ethnicity (ie, Japanese, Chinese, Korean) will be
             excluded.

          2. Recurrent nausea and/or vomiting within 14 days before the first dose of alisertib or
             known gastrointestinal (GI) abnormality or GI procedure that could interfere with or
             modify the oral absorption or tolerance of alisertib. Examples include, but are not
             limited to, disease-related bowel obstruction, pancreatic insufficiency, use of
             pancreatic enzymes, a gastric condition (such as severe reflux or active peptic ulcer
             disease) that requires chronic and uninterrupted use of proton pump inhibitors,
             partial gastrectomy, history of small intestine surgery, and celiac disease.

          3. Participants requiring treatment with clinically significant enzyme inducers, such as
             the enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic drugs phenytoin, carbamazepine, phenobarbital,
             oxcarbazepine, primidone, rifampin, rifabutin, rifapentine, or St. John's wort within
             14 days before the first dose of alisertib or requiring the use of these medications
             during the study.

          4. A medical condition requiring use of pancreatic enzymes; daily, chronic, or regular
             use of proton pump inhibitors (PPIs); or histamine 2 (H2) receptor antagonists.
             Participants who intermittently use these medications, must meet the following
             criteria:

               -  No use of PPIs within 5 days before the first dose of alisertib.

               -  No use of H2 antagonist or pancreatic enzymes within 24 hours before the first
                  dose of alisertib.

          5. Inadequate bone marrow or other organ function (excluding hepatic impairment per
             eligibility criteria).

          6. Female participants who are lactating and breastfeeding or have a positive serum
             pregnancy test during the Screening period or a positive urine pregnancy test on Day 1
             before first dose of alisertib.

          7. Any serious medical or psychiatric illness that could, in the investigator's opinion,
             potentially interfere with the completion of treatment according to this protocol.

          8. Treatment with any anticancer therapy or any investigational products within 3 weeks
             before the first dose of study drug.

          9. Exposure to nitrosoureas or mitomycin C within 42 days before the first dose of study
             drug.

         10. Radiotherapy within 14 days before the first dose of study drug.

         11. Prior treatment with radiation therapy involving ≥ 25% of the hematopoietically active
             bone marrow within 42 days before the first dose of study drug.

         12. Major surgery within 14 days before the first dose of study drug.

         13. Serious infection within 14 days before the first dose of study drug. Participant must
             have recovered from infection before first dose.

         14. Life-threatening illness unrelated to cancer.

         15. Symptomatic brain metastasis. Participants with brain metastases:

               -  Must have stable neurologic status following local therapy (surgery or radiation)
                  for at least 2 weeks after completion of the definitive therapy AND

               -  Must be without neurologic dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of
                  neurologic or other adverse events (AEs).

         16. Clinically significant coagulopathy or bleeding disorder.

         17. Severe central nervous system, pulmonary, or renal disease not related to the
             participant's cancer.

         18. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive.

         19. Known hepatitis B surface antigen positive or known or suspected active hepatitis C
             infection.

         20. Any of the following cardiovascular conditions:

               -  Evidence of current uncontrolled cardiovascular conditions, including cardiac
                  arrhythmias, congestive heart failure, angina, or electrocardiographic evidence
                  of acute ischemia or active conduction system abnormalities.

               -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 500 milliseconds in a 12-lead electrocardiogram
                  (ECG) during screening.

         21. History of uncontrolled sleep apnea syndrome or other condition that could result in
             excessive daytime sleepiness, such as severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.

         22. Use of moderate or strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A inhibitors or CYP3A inducers within
             2 weeks before the first dose of study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director Clinical Science</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>St Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 12, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alisertib</keyword>
  <keyword>MLN8237</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed/refractory lymphoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 9, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

