<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02215161</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14552</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-01936</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>14-13390</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>14552</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02215161</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Selinexor in Treating Patients With Abiraterone Acetate and/or Enzalutamide Refractory Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Single Agent Study of Selinexor (KPT-330) in Patients With Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer (mCRPC) and Prior Therapy With Abiraterone and/or Enzalutamide</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies selinexor in treating patients with prostate cancer that has
      spread to other parts of the body (metastatic), keeps growing even when the amount of
      testosterone in the body is reduced to very low levels (castration-resistant), and did not
      respond to treatment (refractory) with abiraterone acetate and/or enzalutamide. Selinexor may
      stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe radiographic progression free survival (rPFS) associated with selinexor in
      patients with abiraterone (abiraterone acetate) refractory metastatic castration-resistant
      prostate cancer (mCRPC).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To measure prostate-specific antigen (PSA) changes at 12 weeks post-selinexor initiation.

      II. To assess time to PSA progression. III. To measure time to development of &gt;= 2 new bone
      lesions. IV. To compare the relationship of abiraterone-resistance status (primary vs
      acquired) and treatment outcome.

      V. To determine the effect of selinexor on persistent pain associated with bone metastasis
      using the brief pain inventory (BPI) short form.

      VI. To describe the safety profile of selinexor in patients with metastatic
      castration-resistant prostate cancer.

      VII. To determine the effect of selinexor on circulating leukocyte exportin 1 (XPO-1)
      expression, leukocyte gene expression profile and macrophage inhibitory cytokine-1 (MIC-1)
      messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) expression.

      VIII. To assess serum selinexor trough levels as a function of dose and time since last dose.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe the relationship of XPO-1 expression to PSA decline. II. To describe the
      expression profile of metastatic tumor and outcome. III. To describe the type of progression
      (e.g. pain, bone etc). IV. To define XPO-1 expression in patients for whom pre- and
      post-treatment biopsy is obtained.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive selinexor orally (PO) on days 1 and 3 of weeks 1-3. Courses repeat every 28
      days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 30 days and then every 6
      months thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 15, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic progression free survival (rPFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined from study start until one of the following events occurs: &gt;= 2 new bone lesions on technetium bone scan; Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)-defined tumor progression; clinical deterioration requiring a change in prostate cancer therapy, or at clinician discretion; surgery or radiation to treat a prostate cancer related indication; or death from any cause. Estimated using Kaplan-Meier product limit method. The median times to event with two-sided 95% confidence intervals will be estimated, with the estimate of event rates at 6 and 12 months. Score statistic from Cox proportional hazards model will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abiraterone resistance status (primary versus acquired)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Radiographic progression free survival will be compared for patients with primary abiraterone resistance and acquired abiraterone resistance using a Cox proportional hazards model, and will be presented with a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of PSA response</measure>
    <time_frame>Time between the first evaluation at which the response criteria are met and the first documentation of PSA progression or death, assessed up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Early increase in PSA within 12 weeks, when followed by subsequent decline, is ignored in determining this endpoint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events, graded according to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Safety endpoints include incidence of worst grade adverse events; incidence of deaths and other serious and significant adverse events; and incidence of worst grade laboratory abnormalities. All recorded adverse events will be listed and tabulated by system organ class, preferred term, and by dose group and cohort and coded according to the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities. Vital signs, physical examinations, clinical laboratory test, medical history, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group, and electrocardiogram results will be listed and summarized by dose groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic analysis of selinexor impact on leukocyte gene expression profile</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1 and 15 of course 1 and on day 1 of courses 2 and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Summary statistics will be tabulated for the pharmacokinetic parameters of selinexor and study day. Geometric means and coefficients of variation will be presented for Cmin, Cmax, AUC(TAU), and AUC(INF). Medians, minima, maxima will be presented for Tmax. Means and standard deviations will be provided for the remaining pharmacokinetic parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic analysis of selinexor impact on MIC-1 messenger ribonucleic acid expression</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1 and 15 of course 1 and on day 1 of courses 2 and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Summary statistics will be tabulated for the pharmacokinetic parameters of selinexor and study day. Geometric means and coefficients of variation will be presented for Cmin, Cmax, AUC(TAU), and AUC(INF). Medians, minima, maxima will be presented for Tmax. Means and standard deviations will be provided for the remaining pharmacokinetic parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic analysis of selinexor impact on XPO-1 expression</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1 and 15 of course 1 and on day 1 of courses 2 and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Summary statistics will be tabulated for the pharmacokinetic parameters of selinexor and study day. Geometric means and coefficients of variation will be presented for concentration minimum (Cmin), concentration maximum (Cmax), area under the curve (AUC)(for a dosing interval [TAU]), and AUC(infinity [INF]). Medians, minima, maxima will be presented for Tmax. Means and standard deviations will be provided for the remaining pharmacokinetic parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prostate specific antigen (PSA ) decline of &gt;= 50%</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks post therapy initiation</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients experiencing a PSA decline from baseline of at least 50% in PSA at 12 weeks following the initiation of study therapy will be presented with a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in pain for symptomatic patients, measured using the brief pain inventory short form</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum selinexor levels as a function of dose and time</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of course 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to confirmed development of &gt;= 2 new bone lesions that cannot be attributable to bone scan flare</measure>
    <time_frame>Time interval between the date of treatment initiation and the date of documented new lesions, assessed up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Bone scans will be performed at week 8, 16, 24, and every 12 weeks thereafter; evaluation criteria is defined by the PSAWG2 criteria for bone scan evaluation. The time will be 'backdated' to when the &gt;= 2 new lesions were detected if a second scan is done to confirm progression. Kaplan-Meier methods will be used to estimate the median time to development of &gt;= 2 new bone scans with a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to PSA progression, defined as a rise in PSA of 50% above nadir value or 25% above baseline if there is no decline</measure>
    <time_frame>Time interval between the date of treatment initiation and the date of either first documented PSA progression, or death due to any cause, whichever comes first, assessed up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>PSA is measured monthly until PSA progression as defined by the Prostate-Specific Antigen Working Group 2 (PSAWG2) criteria. Kaplan-Meier methods will be used to estimate the median time to PSA progression with a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in XPO-1 expression in patients for whom pre-treatment biopsy is available through the Stand Up 2 Cancer ?Dream Team? program</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 30 days</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Expression profile of metastatic tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Expression profile of metastatic tumor and outcome will be assessed.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Type of progression (e.g. pain, bone etc)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>XPO-1 expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Relationship of XPO-1 expression to PSA decline will be assessed.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Castration Levels of Testosterone</condition>
  <condition>Hormone-Resistant Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Prostate Carcinoma in the Soft Tissue</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Carcinoma Metastatic in the Bone</condition>
  <condition>PSA Progression</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Prostate Adenocarcinoma AJCC v7</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (selinexor)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive selinexor PO on days 1 and 3 of weeks 1-3. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Selinexor</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (selinexor)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CRM1 Nuclear Export Inhibitor KPT-330</other_name>
    <other_name>KPT-330</other_name>
    <other_name>Selective Inhibitor of Nuclear Export KPT-330</other_name>
    <other_name>SINE KPT-330</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate

          -  Patients must have castrate levels of testosterone (&lt; 50 ng/dL) on
             gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogues or have had prior orchiectomy; GnRH
             analogues must be continued while on study

          -  Tumor tissue submitted for molecular and genetic analysis through the companion
             Stand-up 2 Cancer (SU2C) radiologically guided biopsy of abiraterone and/or
             enzalutamide refractory mCRPC protocol

               -  Patients who consent to participate in the companion biopsy protocol and are
                  subsequently determined to be ineligible for biopsy are eligible to participate
                  in the current protocol

          -  Progressive disease as demonstrated by a rising PSA (at least two determinations)
             prior to study entry, and/or radiographic evidence of tumor progression in soft tissue
             according to modified Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria
             or identification of new lesions by bone scan (i.e., &gt;= 2 new lesions)

          -  Primary resistance or acquired resistance (i.e., acquired resistance will be defined
             as disease progression following a period of response defined as &gt;= 50% decline in PSA
             within 12 weeks of starting therapy and not otherwise meeting criteria for primary
             resistance) to any of the following agents/combinations of therapy:

          -  Abiraterone acetate; primary resistance to abiraterone will be defined as:

               -  No PSA decline

               -  PSA decline less than 50% after 12 weeks of abiraterone therapy

               -  PSA progression within 12 weeks of abiraterone acetate (AA) treatment (by
                  Prostate Cancer Working Group-2 [PCWG2] criteria), after initial response to
                  therapy

               -  Objective progression, by RECIST criteria for soft tissue lesions and by modified
                  PCWG2 criteria for bone lesions within 12 weeks of starting abiraterone treatment

               -  Unequivocal clinical progression (per the treating provider's discretion) within
                  12 weeks of starting abiraterone treatment

          -  Enzalutamide; primary resistance to enzalutamide will be defined as:

               -  No PSA decline

               -  PSA decline less than 50% after 12 weeks of enzalutamide therapy

               -  PSA progression within 12 weeks of enzalutamide treatment (by PCWG2 criteria),
                  after initial response to therapy

               -  Objective progression, by RECIST criteria for soft tissue lesions and by modified
                  PCWG2 criteria for bone lesions within 12 weeks of starting enzalutamide
                  treatment

               -  Unequivocal clinical progression (per the treating provider's discretion) within
                  12 weeks of starting enzalutamide treatment

          -  Other second-generation investigational anti-androgen/androgen-receptor targeted
             therapies, including apalutamide (ARN-509); primary resistance will be defined as:

               -  No PSA decline

               -  PSA decline less than 50% after 12 weeks of enzalutamide therapy

               -  PSA progression within 12 weeks of enzalutamide treatment (by PCWG2 criteria),
                  after initial response to therapy

               -  Objective progression, by RECIST criteria for soft tissue lesions and by modified
                  PCWG2 criteria for bone lesions within 12 weeks of starting enzalutamide
                  treatment

               -  Unequivocal clinical progression (per the treating provider's discretion) within
                  12 weeks of starting enzalutamide treatment

          -  Combination therapy with abiraterone, enzalutamide and/or other second- generation
             investigational anti-androgen/androgen-receptor targeted therapies, including ARN-509;
             primary resistance to combination therapy will be defined as:

               -  No PSA decline

               -  PSA decline less than 50% after 12 weeks of abiraterone and enzalutamide therapy

               -  PSA progression within 12 weeks of abiraterone and enzalutamide treatment (by
                  PCWG2 criteria), after initial response to therapy

               -  Objective progression, by RECIST criteria for soft tissue lesions and by modified
                  PCWG2 criteria for bone lesions within 12 weeks of starting abiraterone and
                  enzalutamide treatment

               -  Unequivocal clinical progression (per the treating provider?s discretion) within
                  12 weeks of starting abiraterone and enzalutamide treatment

          -  Sequenced therapy, including any of the following:

               -  Abiraterone acetate followed by enzalutamide

                    -  Primary resistance will be defined per criteria for abiraterone monotherapy
                       primary resistance

               -  Enzalutamide followed by abiraterone acetate

                    -  Primary resistance will be defined per criteria for enzalutamide monotherapy
                       primary resistance

               -  Other second-generation investigational anti-androgen/androgen- receptor targeted
                  therapies, including ARN-509

                    -  Primary resistance will be defined per criteria for other investigational
                       anti-androgen monotherapy primary resistance

          -  Presence of 1 or more bone metastasis

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1

          -  Prior and ongoing zoledronic acid or denosumab therapy is allowed

          -  Prior therapy with radium-223 is allowed

          -  Discontinuation of prior therapy for mCRPC: a washout period of 28 days for the
             following therapies is required: abiraterone, enzalutamide, fluconazole, itraconazole,
             flutamide, bicalutamide, nilutamide, and other experimental hormonal agents (ARN509,
             orteronel [TAK-700], etc.), sipuleucel-T (Provenge), other experimental vaccines
             (PROSTVAC-V/F, etc.), strontium-89, samarium, and radium-223 chloride

          -  Leukocytes &gt; 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt; 125,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 5.59 mmol/L or 9 g/dL; up to 5% deviation is tolerated; transfusions and
             growth factors are allowed

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)(serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT]) &lt; 3 X
             institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT)(serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT]) &lt; 3 X
             institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits OR creatinine clearance &gt; 60 mL/min/1.73
             m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  Ability to understand a written informed consent document, and the willingness to sign
             it

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

          -  Able to swallow and retain oral medication

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Untreated brain metastases; brain metastases =&lt; 1 cm and not associated with any focal
             neurologic deficits are allowed

          -  Prior docetaxel or other chemotherapy for mCRPC; patients who have received docetaxel
             for metastatic hormone-sensitive prostate cancer are eligible

          -  Active or symptomatic viral hepatitis or chronic liver disease

          -  Clinically significant heart disease as evidenced by myocardial infarction, or
             arterial thrombotic events in the past 6 months, severe or unstable angina, or New
             York Heart Association (NYHA) class II-IV heart disease or known cardiac ejection
             fraction measurement of &lt; 50 % at baseline

          -  Patients with significantly diseased or obstructed gastrointestinal tract or
             uncontrolled vomiting or diarrhea or other gastrointestinal disorders (medical
             disorders or extensive surgery) that may interfere with the absorption of the study
             agents

          -  Pure small cell carcinoma of the prostate or any mixed histology cancer of the
             prostate (eg: neuroendocrine) that contains &lt; 50% adenocarcinoma, as observed on
             biopsy obtained at the time of diagnosis or on any subsequent biopsies

          -  Any ?currently active? second malignancy, other than non-melanoma skin cancer;
             patients are not considered to have a &quot;currently active? malignancy, if they have
             completed therapy and are considered by their physician to be at least less than 30%
             risk of relapse over next year

          -  Any condition, which in the opinion of the investigator, would preclude participation
             in this trial

          -  Active psychiatric illnesses/social situations that would limit compliance with
             protocol requirements

          -  Patients in whom urgent treatment with docetaxel is indicated, per clinician
             discretion; this includes, but is not limited to patients with symptomatic visceral
             metastatic disease

          -  Uncontrolled infection or concomitant medical illness that is not adequately
             controlled with current medical management, as determined per clinician discretion

          -  Active bleeding disorders or evidence of evidence of chronic or acute disseminated
             intravascular coagulation (DIC)

          -  Severely compromised immunological state, including known human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV)

          -  Any acute toxicities due to prior anti-cancer treatments and/or radiotherapy that have
             not resolved to a National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for
             Adverse Events (CTCAE) grade of =&lt; 1 (except alopecia)

          -  Prior radiation therapy completed &lt; 3 weeks or single fraction of palliative
             radiotherapy &lt; 14 days prior to first dose of KPT-330 (selinexor)

          -  Initiation of bisphosphonate therapy &lt; 4 weeks prior to first dose of KPT-330;
             patients receiving bisphosphonate or denosumab therapy must be on stable doses for at
             least 4 weeks prior to first dose of KPT-330

          -  Men unable or unwilling to employ 2 forms of highly effective contraception throughout
             the study and for 8 weeks after the end of study treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Ryan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 11, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 13, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abiraterone Acetate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 26, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>May 24, 2018</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

