<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02219737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2014-00571</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00571</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>14-145</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9588</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9588</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA008748</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02219737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ibrutinib and Combination Chemotherapy in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study Combining Ibrutinib With Rituximab, Ifosfamide, Carboplatin, and Etoposide (R-ICE) in Patients With Relapsed or Primary Refractory Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma (DLBCL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of ibrutinib when given together
      with rituximab, ifosfamide, carboplatin, and etoposide (combination chemotherapy) in treating
      patients with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) that has returned after a period of
      improvement (relapsed) or has not responded to treatment (refractory). Ibrutinib may stop the
      growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Drugs used in
      chemotherapy, such as, rituximab, ifosfamide, carboplatin, and etoposide, work in different
      ways to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from
      dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Giving ibrutinib together with combination
      chemotherapy may be a better treatment for patients with relapsed or refractory DLBCL.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Safety of ibrutinib in combination with rituximab-ifosfamide, carboplatin, and etoposide
      (R-ICE).

      II. Establishment of maximum tolerated dose of ibrutinib with R-ICE.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Pharmacokinetic (PK) studies of ibrutinib in combination with R-ICE. II. Clinical response
      rate of ibrutinib+R-ICE.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of ibrutinib.

      Patients receive ibrutinib orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-21, rituximab intravenously
      (IV) on day 1, ifosfamide IV on day 3, carboplatin intravenously piggy back (IVPB) on day 3,
      and etoposide IVPB on days 2-4. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 3 courses in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 52 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 12, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 11, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 11, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose of the combination of ibrutinib with standard dosing R-ICE, graded using the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 21</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity of the combination of ibrutinib with standard dosing R-ICE, graded using the CTCAE 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to week 52</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate, defined as the sum of partial and complete responses as determined by revised International Working Group Criteria for Malignant Lymphoma</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to week 52</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who achieve a clinical response (partial response or better) will be estimated in this patient population. This will be calculated among patients who receive any study drug, and additionally among patients who complete three cycles of therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of ibrutinib in the presence of R-ICE as a measure of potential drug-drug interaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose, 30 minutes, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10 (optional), and 24 hours on day 15 (course 1) and day 1 (course 2)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">26</enrollment>
  <condition>CD20 Positive</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib, R-ICE)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive ibrutinib PO QD on days 1-21, rituximab IV on day 1, ifosfamide IV on day 3, carboplatin IVPB on day 3, and etoposide IVPB on days 2-4. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IVPB</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib, R-ICE)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blastocarb</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatin Hexal</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosol</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbotec</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
    <other_name>Displata</other_name>
    <other_name>Ercar</other_name>
    <other_name>JM-8</other_name>
    <other_name>Nealorin</other_name>
    <other_name>Novoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinwas</other_name>
    <other_name>Ribocarbo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IVPB</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib, R-ICE)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Demethyl Epipodophyllotoxin Ethylidine Glucoside</other_name>
    <other_name>EPEG</other_name>
    <other_name>Lastet</other_name>
    <other_name>Toposar</other_name>
    <other_name>Vepesid</other_name>
    <other_name>VP 16-213</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16-213</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibrutinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib, R-ICE)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BTK Inhibitor PCI-32765</other_name>
    <other_name>CRA-032765</other_name>
    <other_name>Imbruvica</other_name>
    <other_name>PCI-32765</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ifosfamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib, R-ICE)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Asta Z 4942</other_name>
    <other_name>Asta Z-4942</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyfos</other_name>
    <other_name>Holoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Holoxane</other_name>
    <other_name>Ifex</other_name>
    <other_name>IFO</other_name>
    <other_name>IFO-Cell</other_name>
    <other_name>Ifolem</other_name>
    <other_name>Ifomida</other_name>
    <other_name>Ifomide</other_name>
    <other_name>Ifosfamidum</other_name>
    <other_name>Ifoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>IFX</other_name>
    <other_name>Iphosphamid</other_name>
    <other_name>Iphosphamide</other_name>
    <other_name>Iso-Endoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Isoendoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Isophosphamide</other_name>
    <other_name>Mitoxana</other_name>
    <other_name>MJF 9325</other_name>
    <other_name>MJF-9325</other_name>
    <other_name>Naxamide</other_name>
    <other_name>Seromida</other_name>
    <other_name>Tronoxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Z 4942</other_name>
    <other_name>Z-4942</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib, R-ICE)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib, R-ICE)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ibrutinib, R-ICE)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ABP 798</other_name>
    <other_name>BI 695500</other_name>
    <other_name>C2B8 Monoclonal Antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>Chimeric Anti-CD20 Antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>CT-P10</other_name>
    <other_name>IDEC-102</other_name>
    <other_name>IDEC-C2B8</other_name>
    <other_name>IDEC-C2B8 Monoclonal Antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>MabThera</other_name>
    <other_name>Monoclonal Antibody IDEC-C2B8</other_name>
    <other_name>PF-05280586</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituximab Biosimilar ABP 798</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituximab Biosimilar BI 695500</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituximab Biosimilar CT-P10</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituximab Biosimilar GB241</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituximab Biosimilar IBI301</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituximab Biosimilar PF-05280586</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituximab Biosimilar RTXM83</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituximab Biosimilar SAIT101</other_name>
    <other_name>RTXM83</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Autologous transplant eligible patients must have histologically or cytologically
             confirmed cluster of differentiation (CD)20 positive relapsed or refractory DLBCL by
             biopsy within 45 days prior to subject enrollment and must have been previously
             treated with an anthracycline and rituximab-containing regimen

          -  Baseline fludeoxyglucose F 18 (FDG)-positron emission tomography (PET) scans must
             demonstrate positive lesions compatible with computed tomography (CT) defined
             anatomical tumor sites

               -  CT scan showing at least:

                    -  2 or more clearly demarcated lesions/nodes with a long axis &gt; 1.5 cm and
                       short axis &gt;= 1.0 cm OR

                    -  1 clearly demarcated lesion/node with a long axis &gt; 2.0 cm and short axis &gt;=
                       1.0 cm

          -  Patient must have been previously treated for B cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma with any of
             the allowable below:

               -  First-line treatment with rituximab and an anthracycline-based chemotherapy

               -  Monotherapy rituximab, dosed prior to first-line rituximab combined with
                  anthracycline containing chemotherapy, or as maintenance therapy

               -  Radiotherapy as part of the first-line treatment plan including anthracycline and
                  rituximab

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 6 weeks

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,000/mcL (unless due to lymphoma involvement of the bone
             marrow)

          -  Platelets &gt;= 75,000/mcL (unless due to lymphoma involvement of the bone marrow)

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x within normal institutional limits (unless due to lymphoma
             involvement of liver or a known history of Gilbert's disease)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.5 × institutional upper limit of normal (unless due to lymphoma involvement of
             liver)

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits OR creatinine clearance &gt;= 40
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal (unless
             due to lymphoma)

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for
             90 days after the last dose of study drug; should a woman become pregnant or suspect
             she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she should
             inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Ibrutinib must be discontinued 7 days before (when possible) until 7 days after major
             surgery, and 3 days before (when possible) until 3 days after minor surgery; thus,
             patients to be enrolled on an ibrutinib trial must have completed major surgery within
             4 weeks before initiating treatment, and/or must have completed minor surgery &gt; 3 days
             before initiating treatment

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Must be able to swallow whole capsules

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy =&lt; 21 days (=&lt; 6 weeks for
             monoclonal antibodies) prior to first administration of study treatment or those who
             have not recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks
             earlier

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients with known brain metastases should be excluded from this clinical trial

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to ibrutinib or R-ICE

          -  Requires treatment with a strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A inhibitor; strong inhibitors
             or inducers of CYP3A4/5 should be avoided and moderate inhibitors or inducers should
             be used with caution; it is important to regularly consult a frequently-updated list;
             medical reference texts such as the Physicians' Desk Reference may also provide this
             information; as part of the enrollment/informed consent procedures, the patient will
             be counseled on the risk of interactions with other agents, and what to do if new
             medications need to be prescribed or if the patient is considering a new
             over-the-counter medicine or herbal product

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements; recent infections requiring systemic treatment need to have
             completed therapy &gt; 14 days before the first dose of study drug

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with ibrutinib R-ICE

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are eligible, unless the patient's CD4 count is below the institutional lower
             limit of normal, or the patient is taking prohibited CYP3A4/5 strong inhibitors or
             inducers

          -  Patients may not have received any anti-cancer therapy for their primary relapsed
             (rel)/refractory (ref) DLBCL with the exception of palliative radiation therapy (RT)

          -  Uncontrolled autoimmune hemolytic anemia or idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)
             resulting in (or as evidenced by) declining platelet or hemoglobin (Hgb) levels within
             the 4 weeks prior to first dose of study drug

          -  Presence of transfusion-dependent thrombocytopenia

          -  Prior exposure to bruton tyrosine kinase (BTK) inhibitor

          -  History of prior malignancy, with the exception of the following:

               -  Malignancy treated with curative intent and with no evidence of active disease
                  present for more than 3 years prior to screening and felt to be at low risk for
                  recurrence by treating physician

               -  Adequately treated non-melanomatous skin cancer or lentigo maligna melanoma
                  without current evidence of disease

               -  Adequately treated cervical carcinoma in situ without current evidence of disease

          -  Currently active clinically significant cardiovascular disease such as uncontrolled
             arrhythmia, congestive heart failure, or class 3 or 4 congestive heart failure as
             defined by the New York Heart Association Functional Classification, or history of
             myocardial infarction, unstable angina, or acute coronary syndrome within 6 months
             prior to first dose with study drug

          -  Unable to swallow capsules, or disease significantly affecting gastrointestinal
             function or resection of the stomach or small bowel, or symptomatic-inflammatory bowel
             disease or ulcerative colitis, or partial or complete bowel obstruction

          -  Serologic status reflecting active hepatitis B or C infection; patients that are
             positive for hepatitis B core antibody, hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), or
             hepatitis C antibody will need a negative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) prior to
             enrollment (PCR positive patients will be excluded); hepatitis C antibody positive
             patients are eligible if PCR is negative

          -  History of stroke or intracranial hemorrhage within 6 months prior to enrollment

          -  Current life-threatening illness, medical condition, or organ system dysfunction
             which, in the Investigator's opinion, could compromise the patient's safety, or put
             the study at risk

          -  Received anticoagulation therapy with Coumadin or equivalent vitamin K antagonists
             within the last 28 days

          -  Vaccinated with live, attenuated vaccines with 4 weeks of first does of study drug

          -  Unresolved toxicities from prior anti-cancer therapy, defined as having not resolved
             to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Event (CTCAE, version 4), grade =&lt; 1, or to
             the levels dictated in the inclusion/exclusion criteria with the exception of alopecia

          -  Known bleeding disorders (e.g., von Willebrand's disease) or hemophilia

          -  Unwilling or unable to participate in all required study evaluations and procedures

          -  Currently active, clinically significant hepatic impairment &gt;= moderate hepatic
             impairment according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI)/Child Pugh classification
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig Sauter</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 15, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isophosphamide mustard</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ifosfamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Podophyllotoxin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

