<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02317705</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OTL-2014-OTL38-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02317705</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Study of OTL38 for Intra-operative Imaging of Folate Receptor-alpha Positive Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Single Dose, Open-Label Study to Investigate the Safety and Efficacy of OTL38 Injection (OTL38) for Intra-operative Imaging of Folate Receptor-alpha Positive Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>On Target Laboratories, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>SynteractHCR</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>On Target Laboratories, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done to:

        -  test the safety of OTL38

        -  see if OTL38 helps light up the cancer when viewed with the special camera system

        -  test the safety of the special camera system for use along with OTL38 during surgery
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decision to increase dose and/or expand cohort will be based on the severity and confirmed by tumor-to-background ratio (TBR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OTL38</intervention_name>
    <other_name>OTL38 for Injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Female patients 18 years of age and older

          2. Have a primary diagnosis, or at high clinical suspicion, of primary ovarian cancer (of
             epithelial type), planned for primary debulking or interval debulking surgery, and:

               -  Who are scheduled to undergo laparotomy for the debulking surgery OR

               -  Who are scheduled to undergo laparoscopy and pre-authorized to undergo laparotomy
                  for the debulking surgery, if cancer is detected on the laparoscopy

          3. A negative serum pregnancy test at Screening followed by a negative urine pregnancy
             test on the day of surgery or day of admission for female patients of childbearing
             potential

          4. Female patients of childbearing potential or less than 2 years postmenopausal agree to
             use an acceptable form of contraception from the time of signing informed consent
             until 30 days after study completion

          5. Ability to understand the requirements of the study, provide written informed consent
             and authorization of use and disclosure of protected health information, and agree to
             abide by the study restrictions and to return for the required assessments

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous exposure to OTL38

          2. Known FR alpha-negative ovarian cancer

          3. Planned surgical approach via laparoscopy or robotic surgery

          4. Any medical condition that in the opinion of the investigators could potentially
             jeopardize the safety of the patient

          5. History of anaphylactic reactions or severe allergies

          6. History of allergy to any of the components of OTL38, including folic acid

          7. Pregnancy, or positive pregnancy test

          8. Clinically significant abnormalities on electrocardiogram (ECG)

          9. Presence of any psychological, familial, sociological or geographical condition
             potentially hampering compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule

         10. Impaired renal function defined as eGFR&lt; 50 mL/min/1.73m2

         11. Impaired liver function defined as values &gt; 3x the upper limit of normal (ULN) for
             alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline
             phosphatase (ALP), or total bilirubin.

         12. Known Stage IV ovarian cancer with Brain Metastases

         13. Received an investigational agent in another investigational drug or vaccine trial
             within 30 days prior to surgery

         14. Known sensitivity to fluorescent light
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of CA at Irvine Chao Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moffitt Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic-Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al Rawahi T, Lopes AD, Bristow RE, Bryant A, Elattar A, Chattopadhyay S, Galaal K. Surgical cytoreduction for recurrent epithelial ovarian cancer. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013 Feb 28;(2):CD008765. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD008765.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23450588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crane LM, Arts HJ, van Oosten M, Low PS, van der Zee AG, van Dam GM, Bart J. The effect of chemotherapy on expression of folate receptor-alpha in ovarian cancer. Cell Oncol (Dordr). 2012 Feb;35(1):9-18. doi: 10.1007/s13402-011-0052-6. Epub 2011 Jun 7. Erratum in: Cell Oncol (Dordr). 2012 Jun;35(3):229.</citation>
    <PMID>21647742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ibeanu OA, Bristow RE. Predicting the outcome of cytoreductive surgery for advanced ovarian cancer: a review. Int J Gynecol Cancer. 2010 Jan;20 Suppl 1:S1-11. doi: 10.1111/IGC.0b013e3181cff38b. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20065732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalli KR, Oberg AL, Keeney GL, Christianson TJ, Low PS, Knutson KL, Hartmann LC. Folate receptor alpha as a tumor target in epithelial ovarian cancer. Gynecol Oncol. 2008 Mar;108(3):619-26. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2007.11.020. Epub 2008 Jan 28.</citation>
    <PMID>18222534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leamon CP, Low PS. Membrane folate-binding proteins are responsible for folate-protein conjugate endocytosis into cultured cells. Biochem J. 1993 May 1;291 ( Pt 3):855-60.</citation>
    <PMID>8387781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markert S, Lassmann S, Gabriel B, Klar M, Werner M, Gitsch G, Kratz F, Hasenburg A. Alpha-folate receptor expression in epithelial ovarian carcinoma and non-neoplastic ovarian tissue. Anticancer Res. 2008 Nov-Dec;28(6A):3567-72.</citation>
    <PMID>19189636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker N, Turk MJ, Westrick E, Lewis JD, Low PS, Leamon CP. Folate receptor expression in carcinomas and normal tissues determined by a quantitative radioligand binding assay. Anal Biochem. 2005 Mar 15;338(2):284-93.</citation>
    <PMID>15745749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ross JF, Chaudhuri PK, Ratnam M. Differential regulation of folate receptor isoforms in normal and malignant tissues in vivo and in established cell lines. Physiologic and clinical implications. Cancer. 1994 May 1;73(9):2432-43.</citation>
    <PMID>7513252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shih KK, Chi DS. Maximal cytoreductive effort in epithelial ovarian cancer surgery. J Gynecol Oncol. 2010 Jun;21(2):75-80. doi: 10.3802/jgo.2010.21.2.75. Epub 2010 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>20613895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toffoli G, Russo A, Gallo A, Cernigoi C, Miotti S, Sorio R, Tumolo S, Boiocchi M. Expression of folate binding protein as a prognostic factor for response to platinum-containing chemotherapy and survival in human ovarian cancer. Int J Cancer. 1998 Apr 17;79(2):121-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9583724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Dam GM, Themelis G, Crane LM, Harlaar NJ, Pleijhuis RG, Kelder W, Sarantopoulos A, de Jong JS, Arts HJ, van der Zee AG, Bart J, Low PS, Ntziachristos V. Intraoperative tumor-specific fluorescence imaging in ovarian cancer by folate receptor-α targeting: first in-human results. Nat Med. 2011 Sep 18;17(10):1315-9. doi: 10.1038/nm.2472.</citation>
    <PMID>21926976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weitman SD, Lark RH, Coney LR, Fort DW, Frasca V, Zurawski VR Jr, Kamen BA. Distribution of the folate receptor GP38 in normal and malignant cell lines and tissues. Cancer Res. 1992 Jun 15;52(12):3396-401.</citation>
    <PMID>1596899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 15, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

