<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02316834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-0474</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-02608</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SP50CA083639</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02316834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>POSITION: A PilOt Study of InducTion PARP InhibitiON in Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>POSITION: A PilOt Study of InducTion PARP InhibitiON in Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BioMarin Pharmaceutical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn about the effects of BMN 673 on ovarian,
      Fallopian tube, and peritoneal cancer. Researchers want to find out if certain
      characteristics of the DNA (the genetic material in cells) affect how the disease responds to
      therapy with BMN 673 and if treatment with BMN 673 affects the genetic material in cancer
      cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      If participant is eligible to continue the study, they will begin taking BMN 673 tablets by
      mouth every day, starting on the day of their scheduled laparoscopy. Participant will take
      the study drug for at least 7 days before their scheduled tumor reduction surgery.
      Participant will stop taking the drug on the day of the surgery and during their recovery
      time. Once participant has recovered from surgery (about 3-6 weeks later), they will receive
      standard chemotherapy treatment. The chemotherapy is part of participant's standard of care
      treatment and is not part of this research study. The type of chemotherapy participant
      receives will be up to their doctor.

      The tablets should be taken either 2 hours before or 2 hours after meals. If participant
      vomits after taking their daily dose of BMN 673, they should not retake the dose. Participant
      should wait until their next scheduled dose, the next day.

      Participant will need to record when they take each dose in a study drug diary. The study
      drug diary will be provided by the study staff, and they will show participant how to fill it
      out.

      Study Visits:

      On the day of participant's screening visit, blood (about 1-2 teaspoons) will be drawn for
      routine tests as part of their standard clinical care. Part of this sample will also be used
      for the genetic research tests described above.

      On the day of participant's laparoscopy, the following procedures will be performed for this
      study:

        -  At least 4 fresh samples of tumor tissue (1 x 1 cm tissue section) will be collected for
           research purposes during the laparoscopic exam. Tissue may be collected from the ovary
           (2 samples), peritoneum, omentum, diaphragm, or other sites. All samples will be stored
           at the MD Anderson Gynecologic Oncology Tumor Bank. Participant's samples will be stored
           under a unique identifier known to only authorized members of the study team. The
           assigned unique identifier will ensure protection of participant's private health
           information. Samples will be stored at the MD Anderson Gynecologic Oncology Tumor Bank
           indefinitely.

      On the day of participant's pre-operative visit, they will only have routine tests. Blood
      (about 1-2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests as part of participant's standard
      clinical care. Part of this sample will also be used for the genetic research tests described
      above.

      On the day of participant's surgery, the following procedures will be performed for this
      study:

        -  At least 4 fresh samples of tumor tissue (1 x 1 cm tissue section) will be collected for
           research purposes during the laparoscopic exam. Tissue may be collected from the ovary
           (2 samples), peritoneum, omentum, diaphragm, or other sites. All samples will be stored
           at the MD Anderson Gynecologic Oncology Tumor Bank. Participant's samples will be stored
           under a unique identifier known to only authorized members of the study team. The
           assigned unique identifier will ensure protection of participant's private health
           information. Samples will be stored at the MD Anderson Gynecologic Oncology Tumor Bank
           indefinitely.

      On the day of participant's post-operative visit, they will only have routine tests performed
      as part of their standard clinical care.

      Length of Treatment:

      Participant may take the study drug for up to 28 days, as long as the doctor thinks it is in
      their best interest. Participant will no longer be able to take the study drug if intolerable
      side effects occur, they are not eligible for treatment/surgery, or they are unable to follow
      study directions.

      Patient's participation on the study will be over after the follow-up visits.

      Follow-Up:

      Participant may be asked to come to the clinic for a follow-up visit 30 days after the tumor
      reduction surgery. At this visit, blood (about 1-2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests
      as part of participant's standard clinical care. Part of this sample will also be used for
      the genetic research tests described above.

      Participant's health status will be followed with information collected during their routine
      clinic visits every 3 months after stopping the study drug. If participant had to stop taking
      BMN 673 because of side effects, the study staff will follow up with them until the side
      effects go away.

      This is an investigational study. BMN 673 is not FDA approved. At this time, it is being used
      for research purposes only. The study doctor can explain how the study drug is designed to
      work.

      Up to 30 participants will take part in this research study. All will be enrolled at MD
      Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in DNA Copy Number Before and After Treatment with BMN 673</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics and graphical methods used to summarize change in DNA copy number from pre-treatment to post-treatment with BMN 673. Paired t-test used to test that mean changes from pre-treatment to post-treatment are different from 0. Median changes from pre-treatment to post-treatment tested with a Wilcoxon signed-rank test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in RNA Protein Expression Before and After Treatment with BMN 673</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Exact binomial test used to test proportion of patients treated with BMN 673 that exhibit an increase (or decrease) in RNA protein expression greater than 50%. Fisher's exact test used to compare treated and untreated patients with respect to proportion of patients that exhibit an increase (or decrease) in RNA protein expression. Median changes compared between treated and untreated patients with a Wilcoxon rank sum test. RNA protein expression also determined as present/absent using the HRD Assay. McNemar's test used to compare pre-treatment to post-treatment changes based on HRD Assay results. Fisher's exact test used to compare HRD Assay results between treated and untreated patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of Treatment with BMN 673: 70% of patients complete all planned doses of BMN 673 and post-operative chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment with BMN 673 considered feasible if 70% of patients complete all planned doses of BMN 673 and post-operative chemotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Fallopian Tube Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Peritoneal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BMN 673</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Starting the day of laparoscopic surgery, participants treated with BMN 673 for at least 7 days prior to tumor reductive surgery. BMN 673 treatment discontinued at time of tumor reductive surgery. BMN 673 given at a dose of 1 mg by mouth once daily. Participants instructed to take the BMN 673 until the day before surgery. Maximum duration of therapy is 28 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BMN 673</intervention_name>
    <description>1 mg by mouth once daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BMN 673</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Talazoparib tosylate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with presumed advanced-stage high grade serous ovarian, fallopian tube, or
             primary peritoneal carcinoma, based on the presence of carcinomatosis, and/or elevated
             CA125, and/or ovarian mass(es), or at the discretion of the treating physician.

          2. Medically able to undergo primary cytoreductive surgery, at least 7 days and up to 28
             days after starting study drug, as determined by treating physician.

          3. No prior therapy for high-grade serous ovarian, fallopian tube, or primary peritoneal
             carcinoma.

          4. Patients must be able to swallow and tolerate oral medications and not have
             gastrointestinal illnesses that would preclude absorption of BMN 673 (e.g.
             uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea; malabsorption syndrome; ulcerative
             disease)

          5. Patients must have normal organ and marrow function (measured within 28 days prior to
             entry/ randomization) as defined below: a. Absolute neutrophil count &gt;/= 1,500/mcL b.
             Hemoglobin&gt;/= 9gm/dL c. Platelets &gt;/= 100,000/mcL d. Total Bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5X ULN e.
             AST/ALT &lt;/= 2.5x upper limit of normal unless the liver is involved with tumor, in
             that case, ALT/AST must be &lt;/= 5x upper limit of normal f. Creatinine clearance &gt;/= 50
             mL/min (assessed by Cockcroft Gault estimation)

          6. Patients must have an ECOG performance status of 0 or 1

          7. The effects of BMN 673 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason,
             women of child-bearing potential and their partners must agree to use contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) from the time of study entry
             until 30 days after the last dose of study medication. Women of child-bearing
             potential (intact uterus) should have a negative serum pregnancy test. Should a woman
             become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study, she
             should inform her treating physician immediately.

          8. Cont. form #7. Female patients must have evidence of non-child-bearing potential by
             fulfilling one of the following criteria at screening: － Post-menopausal defined as
             aged more than 50 years and amenorrheic for at least 12 consecutive months following
             cessation of all exogenous hormonal treatments － Documentation of irreversible
             surgical sterilization by hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy or bilateral
             salpingectomy, but not tubal ligation. Male partners should be instructed to use
             contraception during the study period.

          9. It is unknown if BMN 673 is expressed in human breast milk. For this reason, women
             must not breast-feed while taking the study medications.

         10. Patients must be able to understand and willing to sign an informed consent.

         11. Patients must be at least 18 years of age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior treatment for ovarian, fallopian tube, or primary peritoneal cancer.

          2. Receipt of any other investigational agents or any additional anti-cancer agents.

          3. Significant symptom burden from presumed diagnosis including large volume ascites,
             pain requiring narcotic medication, or shortness of breath on exertion.

          4. Myocardial infarction within 6 months before starting therapy, symptomatic congestive
             heart failure (New York Heart Association &gt; class II), unstable angina, or unstable
             cardiac arrhythmia requiring medication.

          5. As judged by the Investigator, any evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic
             diseases (e.g., severe hepatic impairment, interstitial lung disease [bilateral,
             diffuse, parenchymal lung disease], uncontrolled chronic renal diseases
             [glomerulonephritis, nephritic syndrome, Fanconi Syndrome or Renal tubular acidosis]),
             or current unstable or uncompensated respiratory or cardiac conditions, or
             uncontrolled hypertension (blood pressure &gt;/= 140/90), active bleeding diatheses or
             active infection including hepatitis B, hepatitis C, and human immunodeficiency virus.
             Screening for chronic conditions is not required.

          6. As judged by the Investigator, the patient is unsuitable to participate in the study
             and the patient is unlikely to comply with study procedures, restrictions, and
             requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shannon N. Westin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 5, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fallopian Tube Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Peritoneal Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>BMN 673</keyword>
  <keyword>Talazoparib tosylate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fallopian Tube Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Talazoparib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

