<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02319915</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHUB-PTGexacyl-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02319915</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Pharmacokinetic Profile of Tranexamic Acid, After Injection in a Knee Neo-articulation.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Pharmacokinetic Profile of Tranexamic Acid, After Injection in a Knee Neo-articulation.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brugmann University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brugmann University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluate the pharmacokinetic profile of tranexamic acid injected intra-articularly with or
      without adrenaline, in a population of patients undergoing knee replacement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Orthopedic population, especially during a knee surgery, is at risk of significant bleeding
      and blood transfusion in the perioperative period. Tissue damage is associated with the
      activation of a cascade of mechanisms, in which the activation of the fibrinolyse plays an
      important role. This is why anti-fibrinolytic agents are regularly used in this context to
      reduce the perioperative bleeding and the use of blood transfusions.

      In the majority of cases, tranexamic acid, an analogue agent of lysine, is administered by an
      intravenous injection and more recently, by an intra-articular injection.

      Several questions however remain unanswered.

        -  what is the clearance of this substance ?

        -  does an intra-articular resorbtion exist, resulting in a plasmatic rate of the substance
           ? If yes, what is the plasmatic rate ?

        -  Is the intra-articular effect of tranexamic acid predominant compared to its systemic
           effect ?

        -  Does the addition of adrenalin increase the effect of the tranexamic acid by acting on
           its absorption ?

      The efficacy, safety and better administration route of the tranexamic acid remain unknown
      when injected intra-articularly. The goal of this study is to realize the first
      pharmacokinetic study after an intra-articular injection of tranexamic acid, alone of along
      with adrenalin, in a knee neo-articulation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 18, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 14, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 14, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The pharmacokinetic profile of tranexamic acid</measure>
    <time_frame>24h</time_frame>
    <description>Blood sampling will be performed to establish the pharmacokinetic profile of tranexamic acid. T0 will be defined as the injection time of tranexamic acid. The first blood sampling (T1) will be made 5 minutes after, with the garrot still in place. The garrot will then be loosened and the following blood samplings will take place at 1 minute, 5 minute, 15 minutes, 30 minutes, 1h, 2h, 4h, 8h, 12h and 24h after garrot loosening. 1ml of blood will be taken at each blood sampling. The blood will be placed in a tube suited for chemistry analysis (green tube with gel) and sent directly to the laboratory for analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee diameter</measure>
    <time_frame>12h</time_frame>
    <description>This will be part of the semi-quantitative evaluation of the knee bleeding. The diameter of both knees (the one undergoing surgery and the untouched one) will be measured before and after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Net weight of the compresses</measure>
    <time_frame>12h</time_frame>
    <description>This will be part of the semi-quantitative evaluation of the knee bleeding. The net weight of the blood soaked compresses will be measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Size of the blood stain on the band aid</measure>
    <time_frame>12h</time_frame>
    <description>This will be part of the semi-quantitative evaluation of the knee bleeding. The size of the blood stain, defined as the percentage of the circumference of the band aid that is blood stained, will be measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>72h</time_frame>
    <description>The blood loss will be deduced from the estimated circulating volume and the patient hematocrit level before and 72h after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Prosthesis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study of the pharmacokinetic profile of the plasmatic resorption of tranexamic acid after an intra-articular injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid + adrenalin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study of the pharmacokinetic profile of the plasmatic resorption of tranexamic acid after an intra-articular injection of tranexamic acid with adrenalin 1/200 000.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic Acid</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid + adrenalin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adrenalin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid + adrenalin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  programmed PTG, right or left

          -  surgery planned within the CHU Brugmann Hospital (Dr Reynders)

          -  ASA I to ASA III

          -  Signed informed consent within the patient file

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  re-do surgery

          -  urgent or multiple surgery

          -  ASA IV or higher

          -  Patients with a BMI superior or equal to 40

          -  Patient is a Jehovah Witness

          -  Allergy or contra-indication to tranexamic acid

          -  Coagulation troubles, defined as: Platelet count &lt; 80 000/mm3 and/or PTT &lt;70% and/or
             aPTT &gt;45s and/or Fibrinogen &lt;100mg/dL

          -  Preoperatory renal insufficiency defined as Creatinin &gt; 3mg/dL and/or Dialysis
             patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Van der Linden, MD, Pr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU Brugmann</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Brugmann</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1020</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gandhi R, Evans HM, Mahomed SR, Mahomed NN. Tranexamic acid and the reduction of blood loss in total knee and hip arthroplasty: a meta-analysis. BMC Res Notes. 2013 May 7;6:184. doi: 10.1186/1756-0500-6-184.</citation>
    <PMID>23651507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chareancholvanich K, Siriwattanasakul P, Narkbunnam R, Pornrattanamaneewong C. Temporary clamping of drain combined with tranexamic acid reduce blood loss after total knee arthroplasty: a prospective randomized controlled trial. BMC Musculoskelet Disord. 2012 Jul 20;13:124. doi: 10.1186/1471-2474-13-124.</citation>
    <PMID>22817651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ortega-Andreu M, Pérez-Chrzanowska H, Figueredo R, Gómez-Barrena E. Blood loss control with two doses of tranexamic Acid in a multimodal protocol for total knee arthroplasty. Open Orthop J. 2011 Mar 16;5:44-8. doi: 10.2174/1874325001105010044.</citation>
    <PMID>21552468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Charoencholvanich K, Siriwattanasakul P. Tranexamic acid reduces blood loss and blood transfusion after TKA: a prospective randomized controlled trial. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2011 Oct;469(10):2874-80. doi: 10.1007/s11999-011-1874-2. Epub 2011 Apr 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21512813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mutsuzaki H, Ikeda K. Intra-articular injection of tranexamic acid via a drain plus drain-clamping to reduce blood loss in cementless total knee arthroplasty. J Orthop Surg Res. 2012 Sep 29;7:32. doi: 10.1186/1749-799X-7-32.</citation>
    <PMID>23020868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sa-Ngasoongsong P, Channoom T, Kawinwonggowit V, Woratanarat P, Chanplakorn P, Wibulpolprasert B, Wongsak S, Udomsubpayakul U, Wechmongkolgorn S, Lekpittaya N. Postoperative blood loss reduction in computer-assisted surgery total knee replacement by low dose intra-articular tranexamic acid injection together with 2-hour clamp drain: a prospective triple-blinded randomized controlled trial. Orthop Rev (Pavia). 2011;3(2):e12. doi: 10.4081/or.2011.e12. Epub 2011 Jun 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22053253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ishida K, Tsumura N, Kitagawa A, Hamamura S, Fukuda K, Dogaki Y, Kubo S, Matsumoto T, Matsushita T, Chin T, Iguchi T, Kurosaka M, Kuroda R. Intra-articular injection of tranexamic acid reduces not only blood loss but also knee joint swelling after total knee arthroplasty. Int Orthop. 2011 Nov;35(11):1639-45. doi: 10.1007/s00264-010-1205-3. Epub 2011 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21253725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samama CM, Langeron O, Rosencher N, Capdevila X, Rouche P, Pegoix M, Bernière J, Coriat P. Aprotinin versus placebo in major orthopedic surgery: a randomized, double-blinded, dose-ranging study. Anesth Analg. 2002 Aug;95(2):287-93, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>12145035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 15, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brugmann University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Philippe VAN DER LINDEN</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Pr, MD, Head of clinic</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tranexamic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>knee prosthesis</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetic profile</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Racepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

