<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02317458</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C3BS-C-12-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02317458</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Congestive Heart Failure Cardiopoietic Regenerative Therapy (CHART-2) Trial - THE CHART-2 TRIAL</brief_title>
  <acronym>CHART-2</acronym>
  <official_title>EFFICACY AND SAFETY OF BONE MARROW-DERIVED MESENCHYMAL CARDIOPOIETIC CELLS (C3BS-CQR-1) FOR THE TREATMENT OF CHRONIC ISCHEMIC HEART FAILURE</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celyad (formerly named Cardio3 BioSciences)</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celyad (formerly named Cardio3 BioSciences)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to evaluate the efficacy and safety of the C3BS-CQR-1 in the treatment
      of patients with chronic heart failure secondary to ischemic cardiomyopathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with chronic heart failure secondary to ischemic cardiomyopathy being on standard of
      care will be screened per the protocol inclusion and exclusion criteria. Enrolled patients
      will be randomized on a 1:1 ratio to either standard of care and C3BS-CQR-1 injection
      (treatment group) or standard of care undergoing a sham procedure (control group). Patients
      randomized to the treatment group, for which C3BS-CQR-1 production met release criteria, will
      undergo endoventricular injection of the C3BS-CQR-1 using injection catheter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2017</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of C3BS-CQR-1 injection based on a hierarchical composite score</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Died of CV cause
Hospitalized 2 or more times for HF
Hospitalized once for HF
Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire (MLHFQ) total score worsened by 10 or more points
MLHFQ total score neither worsened by 10 or more points nor improved by 10 or more points, or died of non-CV cause
MLHFQ total score improved by 10 or more points</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One arm with standard of care and C3BS-CQR-1 injection (treatment group) using intramyocardial catheter injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One arm with standard of care undergoing a sham procedure (control group)using intramyocardial catheter injection. .</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Experimental</intervention_name>
    <description>One active arm with standard of car and treatment with C3BR-CQR-1 using intramyocardial injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>C3BR-CQR-1</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham comparator</intervention_name>
    <description>One arm with standard of care undergoing a sham procedure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 and &lt; 80 years.

          2. Systolic dysfunction with LVEF ≤ 35% as assessed by echocardiography.

          3. Ischemic heart failure ineligible for further revascularization. Ischemic heart
             failure is defined as history of myocardial infarction or evidence of clinically
             significant coronary disease associated with LV systolic dysfunction leading to HF.
             The patient must not be a candidate for revascularization in the judgment of the
             investigator, based on the absence of unstable coronary-related symptoms and either
             non-invasive testing or coronary angiography within 24 months prior to screening.

          4. Total MLHFQ score &gt; 30.

          5. Ability to perform a Six-Minute Walk Test &gt; 100 m and ≤ 375 m.

          6. History of hospitalization for HF within 12 months prior to screening or treatment in
             an out-patient clinic with intravenous therapy (including vasodilators, positive
             inotropic agents, vasopressors or diuretics) for worsening HF within 12 months prior
             to screening. Be or must have been diagnosed within the previous 12 months in NYHA
             class III or IV or INTERMACS class 4, 5, 6 or 7, and at the time of inclusion, must be
             at least in NYHA class II or greater. If in NYHA class II, 2 or more HF worsening
             events or NT-ProBNP &gt; 1000 pg/mL requiring hospitalization or outpatient IV therapy
             during the prior 12 months are required.

          7. Use of ACE inhibitor and/or ARB or sacubitril/valsartan (Entresto™); and beta blocker,
             for at least 3 months prior to screening visit, unless intolerant or contraindicated.

          8. Stable dosing of ACE inhibitor or ARB or sacubitril/valsartan (Entresto™) and beta
             blocker, aldosterone blocker, and diuretics for at least one month prior to screening
             visit, defined as ≤50% change in total dose of each agent.

          9. Willing and able to give written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women who are pregnant, confirmed by a positive urine or serum hCG laboratory test at
             screening.

          2. Women of child-bearing potential without a negative serum or urine pregnancy test at
             screening or who are not practicing a reliable form of birth control. Women who are
             postmenopausal (12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea or 6 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea with serum FSH level &gt; 40 mIU/mL or 6 weeks post-surgical bilateral
             oophorectomy) or surgically sterile are not considered to be of child-bearing
             potential. Reliable contraception includes surgical sterilization, hormonal
             contraception, or double-barrier methods.

          3. Men refusing to exercise a reliable form of contraception unless partner is unable to
             conceive.

          4. Acute coronary syndrome leading to myocardial infarction or unstable angina within 90
             days of screening.

          5. Percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) within 90 days prior to screening, or CABG
             surgery within 180 days prior to screening.

          6. Patient on a cardiac transplant list or previously received any solid organ
             transplant.

          7. Previously underwent cardiac surgery with remodeling procedure, left ventricular
             assist device placement or cardiomyoplasty. This exclusion does not apply to patients
             who underwent ventricularplasty without placements device &gt;1 year ago.

          8. Patient has undergone cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT) within 6 months (180
             days) prior to screening.

          9. Severe uncontrolled HF requiring need for intravenous diuretics or inotropic support
             within 1 month prior to screening.

         10. Inability to perform a Six-Minute Walk Test due to physical limitations other than HF
             including:

               1. Severe peripheral vascular disease

               2. Severe pulmonary disease or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) with
                  FEV1 &lt;30% predicted

               3. Orthopedic limitations, severe muscular diseases, any other joint or muscular
                  disease or neurological disorder (such as an old stroke or neuropathy) limiting
                  the ability to walk for 6 minutes.

         11. Dependence on chronic oral steroid therapy.

         12. Stroke or transient ischemic attack leading to limitations in lower extremities or
             occurring within 180 days prior to screening.

         13. Active myocarditis, constrictive pericarditis, restrictive, hypertrophic or congenital
             cardiomyopathy.

         14. BMI &lt; 19 or &gt; 40 kg/m2.

         15. Left ventricular thrombus.

         16. Left ventricular wall thickness &lt; 8mm visualized in more than 50% of LV, and defined
             as a &quot;LV no-go zone

         17. LV aneurysm or candidate for surgical aneurysmectomy.

         18. Sustained VT or VF which led to AICD therapy (shock) within 3 months prior to
             screening.

         19. Primary valvular disease of ≥ moderate degree, including mitral or aortic stenosis
             (with aortic valve area &lt; 1.5 cm2) or regurgitation. Secondary mitral and tricuspid
             regurgitation due to LV dilatation will not be excluded

         20. Prosthetic valve in aortic or mitral position, or prior MitraClip placement.

         21. Chronic infection or active malignancy.

         22. Compromised renal function as reflected by a serum creatinine level &gt;2,0 mg/dL (&gt;0.177
             mmol/l) or is currently on dialysis.

         23. Hematocrit &lt; 28%.

         24. Atherosclerosis and/or tortuosity of the aorta, iliac or femoral arteries of a degree
             that could impede or preclude the safe retrograde passage of the delivery catheter,
             including untreated aneurysm of the aorta.

         25. Chronic immunosuppressive therapy due to inflammatory or systemic disease.

         26. Patient tested positive for HIV 1 or 2, Hepatitis B or C, HTLV 1 or syphilis (as
             detailed in Section 19.1).

         27. Exposure to any previous experimental cell or angiogenic therapy and/or myocardial
             laser therapy and/or therapy with another investigational drug within 60 days prior to
             screening or enrollment in any concurrent study that may confound the results of this
             study.

         28. Known drug or alcohol dependence or any other factors which will interfere with the
             study conduct or interpretation of the results or in the opinion of the investigator
             are not suitable to participate.

         29. Any illness other than CHF which might reduce life expectancy to less than 2 years
             from screening.

         30. Known and relevant allergies and/or hyper-sensitivities to Dextran or other plasma
             volume expanders (including Gentran, Hyskon and Macrodex), to Bovine Serum Albumin
             (BSA) or to any albumin from animal origin.

         31. Known severe allergy to the cardiac radiological contrast mixture.

         32. Required dosage of cardiopoietic cells not reached
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 15, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

