<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02318290</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-1112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02318290</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Opioids Withdrawal Syndrome in Critically Ill Patients: a Multicenter Prospective Cohort Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>WAAICUP</acronym>
  <official_title>Opioids Withdrawal Syndrome in Critically Ill Patients: a Multicenter Prospective Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montreal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montreal</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Critically ill patients who are mechanically ventilated may require prolonged administration
      of sedatives and analgesics. Their prolonged use has been associated with withdrawal symptoms
      upon rapid weaning in critically ill patients. These withdrawal symptoms may be associated
      with adverse clinical outcomes. Although well studied in the paediatric population, little is
      known about the epidemiology, risk factors and optimal screening methods in adults. Studying
      this problem is essential as we strive to develop proper weaning strategies.

      Methods: Prospective observational two-center study in critically ill adult patients
      Objectives: 1) Describe the incidence of iatrogenic withdrawal of sedatives and analgesics in
      critically ill adult patients and 2) Evaluate the performance of screening tools assessing
      withdrawal that were developed for the paediatric patient in the adult population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of the study are: 1) to describe the incidence of iatrogenic withdrawal of
      sedatives and analgesics in critically ill adult patients and; 2) Validate screening tools
      for withdrawal in the adult population.

      Hypothesis

        1. Symptoms of iatrogenic benzodiazepines and opioids withdrawal occur commonly in
           mechanically ventilated patients exposed to high doses and/or prolonged infusions and
           who are rapidly weaned from these therapies.

        2. The scales for benzodiazepine and narcotic withdrawal detection used in paediatrics
           population correlate well with the DSM V diagnosis of withdrawal in an adult ICU
           population

        3. Major risk factors for withdrawal symptoms include longer duration of therapy and higher
           doses and admission for a medical condition (MICU)

      Methods

      A prospective multicenter observational study will be carried out in two
      University-affiliated hospital intensive care units (Hôpital du Sacré-Coeur and Montreal
      General Hospital). All mechanically ventilated ICU patients receiving continuous infusions of
      benzodiazepines and/or opioids for more than 96 hours will be prospectively screened daily
      for withdrawal symptoms by an intensivist. Withdrawal symptoms for opioid and benzodiazepines
      will be identified using the DSM-V criteria. Patients with moderate to severe head trauma, a
      severe neurological disease, or prior to admission substance abuse (significant alcohol,
      illicit or prescription drugs) will be excluded. We will also exclude patients with a
      regularly prescribed chronic opioid or benzodiazepine use prior to ICU admission. Risk
      factors for withdrawal including type of agents exposed, dosing, duration of exposure,
      weaning of agents, organ dysfunction, age, gender, smoking, severity of disease and admission
      diagnosis will be prospectively collected. The Withdrawal Assessment Tool-1 (WAT-1), a
      screening tools validated in the paediatric population, will also be administered daily. The
      criterion validity of this screening tool will be compared to the DSM-V criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opiate withdrawal according to DSM V critieria</measure>
    <time_frame>From ICU admission to 48 hours post-extubation or a maximum of 14 days passed since the beginning of the initial weaning process</time_frame>
    <description>Opiate withdrawal as evaluated by an intensivist using DSM V criteria</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Substance Withdrawal Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Critically ill patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Mechanically ventilated critically ill patients receiveing opiates for more than 96 hours will be prospectively followed for the emergence of withdrawal symptoms upon weaning of opiates</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Opiates</intervention_name>
    <description>Mechanically ventilated patients receiving opiates for more than 96 hours will be evaluated for withdrawal symptoms upon weaning of the opiates</description>
    <arm_group_label>Critically ill patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Analgesics</other_name>
    <other_name>Narcotics</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients under mechanical ventilation and receiving regular intermittent use or continuous
        infusion opioids for at least 96 hours
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  intermittent use or continuous infusion opioids for at least 96 hours

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient and/or relatives unable to communicate in French or English

          -  Patients unable to communicate (consent form and evaluation)

          -  Patient deaf without appropriate hearing aid

          -  Patients unable to communicate (consent form and evaluation)

          -  Imminent and predictable death according to medical team

          -  Severe brain injury, defined as Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) score of 8 or less at ICU
             admission

          -  Moderate brain injury, defined as GCS between 9 and 12, with elevated intracranial
             pressure (ICP &gt; 20 mm Hg) who requires ICP monitoring and osmotherapy

          -  Major confounding factors for withdrawal syndrome by causing shivering, sympathetic
             drive and autonomic disorders

          -  Underlying active neurological condition (status epilepticus, encephalopathy, hypoxia)

          -  Neurological problems are covariates, which would make the assessment of sedation or
             IWS difficult Patient previously included in the study at any of the two hospitals
             (readmission to the ICU at a later date during the period of recruitment for the
             study, limiting to 1 weaning episode per patient)

          -  Thoracic and cervical spinal cord injury

          -  Adrenergic response to pain will be difficult to assess

          -  Unable to assess validated tool: DSM-V, RASS, CAM-ICU

          -  Narcotic

          -  If the underlying neurological condition resolves within the 96 hours, the patient may
             be included in the study

          -  Substance abuse prior to ICU admission (28)

          -  Chronic alcohol use defined as alcohol consumption of more than 2 drinks per day
             and/or more than 14 drinks per week for men and 9 drinks per week for woman as
             reported by family or as per patient's medical record
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Williamson, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Perreaut, Pharm.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Montreal General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne Julie Frenette, M.Sc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital du Sacré-Coeur</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4J1C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cammarano WB, Pittet JF, Weitz S, Schlobohm RM, Marks JD. Acute withdrawal syndrome related to the administration of analgesic and sedative medications in adult intensive care unit patients. Crit Care Med. 1998 Apr;26(4):676-84.</citation>
    <PMID>9559604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Franck LS, Harris SK, Soetenga DJ, Amling JK, Curley MA. The Withdrawal Assessment Tool-1 (WAT-1): an assessment instrument for monitoring opioid and benzodiazepine withdrawal symptoms in pediatric patients. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2008 Nov;9(6):573-80. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e31818c8328.</citation>
    <PMID>18838937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 19, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montreal</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Williamson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Full Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypnotics and Sedatives</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Substance Withdrawal Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Opiate Alkaloids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

