<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02317783</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HCI69515</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02317783</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Amyloid Plaque Deposition in Chemotherapy-Induced Cognitive Impairment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Amyloid Plaque Deposition in Chemotherapy-Induced Cognitive Impairment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The initial goal of the investigators interdisciplinary group of imagers, oncologists,
      neurologists, neuro-psychologists, and biostatisticians is to obtain proof of concept pilot
      data for eventual submission of a National Cancer Institute Quick-Trial for Imaging and
      Image-Guided Interventions: Exploratory Grant (R10) depending on the results of this pilot
      study.

      The overall objective is to use [18F]Flutemetamol, FDG-PET, and MRI to better understand
      CICI, which effects up to 16 -50% of individuals receiving long-term adjuvant
      chemotherapy.2,3 To date there have been few studies examining this problem using
      multi-modality imaging techniques to better understand this complex and significant problem.

      FDG-PET and MRI are routinely used in clinical practice for the evaluation of cognitive
      dysfunction in older populations complaining of memory dysfunction. It is well recognized
      that FDG-PET can assist with the differentiation and characterization of various cognitive
      disorders due to unique patterns of cerebral metabolism caused by various cognitive and
      dementia-causing disorders.4-6 FDG-PET has been studied extensively in dementia research and
      has a high reliability in detecting Alzheimers disease (AD) many years before it can be
      diagnosed reliably using clinical criteria.4

      To the investigators knowledge, there has been only a single small study using FDG-PET and
      bolus water activation paradigms in cancer patients complaining of memory problems.7 To date,
      there have been no studies using [18F]Flutemetamol as a PET imaging agent to assess the
      possibility of increased amyloid plaque burden as a potential contributing factor to the
      cognitive deficits and complaints seen in patients experiencing CICI. The novel feature of
      this project is in the combined use of [18F]Flutemetamol-PET, FDG-PET, and anatomic MRI to
      study a poorly understood but common problem: cognitive impairment in breast cancer patients
      treated with chemotherapy.

      If [18F]Flutemetamol, FDG-PET, and MRI can provide information on the pathophysiology of this
      disorder, it will be an important step in better understanding the etiology of this
      phenomenon and possibly other conditions resulting in cognitive dysfunction. These imaging
      assessments will make it possible to explore any altered changes in cerebral structure,
      metabolism, and amyloid deposition that may be responsible for CICI. This may help to predict
      which individuals may be affected by this problem and provide information for eventual
      therapeutic strategies to treat this common cancer-associated disorder.

      This study will use [18F]Flutemetamol and FDG-PET imaging to assess and quantify the amyloid
      plaque burden and cerebral glucose metabolism, respectively, in breast cancer patients
      suffering from CICI and correlate those findings with structural changes on MRI. The
      [18F]Flutemetamol and FDG-PET scans of these study patients will then be compared to two GE
      software databases (CortexID-FDG and CortexID-Flutemetamol) which contain scan data from
      healthy control individuals to evaluate for abnormalities in cerebral glucose metabolism and
      amyloid plaque burden differing from the values expected for individuals in their age range.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>[18F]Flutemetamol and [18F]fluoro-2-deoxy-D-glucose (FDG) PET imaging agents and MRI in breast cancer patients with Chemotherapy-Induced Cognitive Impairment (CICI) to check brain changes.</measure>
    <time_frame>patients with CICI will have 2 scans within approximately 3 days. Medical record review will continue for approximately 2 years following the last scan to review patient progress.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FDG-PET, [18F]Flutemetamol Scanning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FDG-PET, [18F]Flutemetamol</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>FDG-PET, [18F]Flutemetamol Scanning</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female patients must be 18 years or older for inclusion in this research study. There
             is inadequate experience with the safety of Flutemetamol in children and therefore
             this radiopharmaceutical should not be used in patients under the age of 18.
             Individuals over 70 years age will be excluded as the incidence of amyloid positivity
             increases significantly even with no cognitive problems and will not allow for testing
             of our primary hypothesis.

          -  The patient must have a histologically proven diagnosis of Stage I through IIIC Breast
             Cancer.

          -  The patient must have completed adjuvant chemotherapy within at least 6 months, but no
             more than 36 months prior to initial study scan.

          -  The patient must report persistent cognitive problems, defined as being one or more
             standard deviations above normative data on our two scales of subjective cognitive
             dysfunction. This is defined as a total score of 45 or higher on the Cognitive Failure
             Questionnaire, and a T-score of 60 or higher on the Frontal System Behavioral Scale
             Questionnaire.

          -  Patients must agree to have clinical and radiographic endpoints and the results of
             histopathologic tissue analysis and other laboratory information entered into a
             research database, as evidenced by signing the informed consent form.

          -  All patients, or their legal guardians, must sign a written informed consent and HIPAA
             authorization in accordance with institutional guidelines.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with known allergic or hypersensitivity reactions to previously administered
             radiopharmaceuticals. Patients with significant drug or other allergies or autoimmune
             diseases may be enrolled at the Investigator's discretion.

          -  Adult patients who require monitored anesthesia for PET scanning.

          -  Patients who are too claustrophobic to undergo MRI or PET imaging.

          -  History of neurological disease known to affect cognition (e.g., stroke, head injury
             with loss of consciousness of greater than 30 minutes, seizure disorder, demyelinating
             disorder, mental retardation, primary brain tumor, brain metastases, etc.)

          -  Current or past major psychiatric illness (e.g., schizophrenia, bipolar affective
             disorder)

          -  Evidence of stroke or mass lesion on CT or MRI scan

          -  History of alcoholism or other substance abuse

          -  Current use of cholinesterase inhibitors, other cognitive enhancers, antipsychotics,
             antidepressants, or anticonvulsant medications

          -  Current use of gabapentin or venlafaxine for hot flashes

          -  History of radiation therapy to the brain

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes or blood glucose greater than 175 mg/dl on the day of the
             FDG-PET scan

          -  Currently pregnant

          -  Color blindness (cannot complete D-KEFS Stroop test)

          -  Moderate or Severe Depression as measured on the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI)
             -Short Form. The cut-off score for the BDI will be 8/9.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paige Nielsen</last_name>
    <phone>801-585-5942</phone>
    <email>Paige.Nielsen@hci.utah.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huntsman Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paige Nielsen</last_name>
      <phone>801-585-5942</phone>
      <email>Paige.Nielsen@hci.utah.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Hoffman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 15, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plaque, Amyloid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

