<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01194674</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100186</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-EI-0186</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01194674</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Microplasmin Intravitreal Administration in Participants With Uveitic Macular Edema</brief_title>
  <acronym>MIME</acronym>
  <official_title>Microplasmin Intravitreal Administration in Participants With Uveitic Macular Edema</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to investigate the safety and efficacy of microplasmin as a
      treatment for uveitic macular edema.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: Uveitis, an inflammatory condition that affects the uvea (iris, ciliary body and
      choroid) and adjacent structures of the eyes, is an important cause of visual loss. Most
      cases of uveitis, not related to an infectious agent, are thought to be autoimmune in origin
      and are effectively treated with medications to suppress the function of the immune system.
      Efforts to decrease morbidity, reduce the dose of more toxic immunosuppressive drugs, reduce
      the frequency of recurrences of inflammation and its sequelae are important goals in the
      treatment of uveitis. A frequent sequela of uveitis is macular edema. Treatment of macular
      edema in patients with uveitis has been a particular challenge. Current evidence from
      diabetic macular edema (DME) and vitreomacular traction (VMT) trials suggests that
      pharmacologically-induced vitreoretinal separation could be a potential treatment for macular
      edema associated with uveitis. Microplasmin, a truncated form of human plasmin and naturally
      occurring enzyme that dissolves blood clots, may be a reasonable candidate for the treatment
      of uveitic macular edema. The objective of this study is to investigate the safety and
      efficacy of microplasmin as a treatment for uveitic macular edema.

      Study Population: Five participants with uveitic macular edema, with or without VMT, will be
      enrolled. In addition, participants must have no evidence of macular or complete posterior
      vitreous detachment (PVD) by Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) or ultrasound.

      Design: This Phase I-II, non-randomized, prospective, uncontrolled, single-center study will
      involve a one-time intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin. Eligible
      participants can receive the intravitreal injection on the same day of the baseline
      examination. Participants will be followed for 24 weeks post-injection.

      Outcome Measures: The primary outcome measure related to the safety and tolerability of
      microplasmin will be assessed by the number and severity of adverse events (AEs) and systemic
      and ocular toxicities during the study. The secondary outcome measures related to the
      potential efficacy of an intravitreal injection of microplasmin for macular edema secondary
      to uveitis will be assessed by a change in central macular thickness from baseline measured
      by OCT in response to microplasmin at 4 and 12 weeks post-injection, the number of
      participants achieving macular or complete PVD at 4 and 12 weeks post-injection, the change
      of ETDRS best-corrected visual acuity (BCVA) and the change of retino-vascular leakage from
      baseline seen on fluorescein angiography (FA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of enrollment.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Severe Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Ocular Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The number of eye-related adverse events was calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Non-ocular Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The number of adverse events that were not eye-related was calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Central Macular Thickness, as Measured by Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT), at 4 Weeks vs. Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Retinal thickness was assessed by spectral-domain optical coherence tomography (Cirrus HD-OCT; Carl Zeiss Meditec, Dublin, CA), a non-invasive imaging technique that uses long-wavelength light to capture micrometer-resolution cross-sectional images from biological tissue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Achieving Macular or Complete Posterior Vitreous Detachment (PVT) at 4 Weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ETDRS Best-corrected Visual Acuity (BCVA) at 4 Weeks vs. Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Visual acuity was measured using the Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) protocol. Acuity is measured as letters read on an ETDRS eye chart and the letters read equate to Snellen measurements. For example, if a participant reads between 84 and 88 letters, the equivalent Snellen measurement is 20/20.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ETDRS Best-corrected Visual Acuity (BCVA) at 12 Weeks vs. Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Visual acuity was measured using the Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) protocol. Acuity is measured as letters read on an ETDRS eye chart and the letters read equate to Snellen measurements. For example, if a participant reads between 84 and 88 letters, the equivalent Snellen measurement is 20/20.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Retino-vascular Leakage, as Seen on Fluorescein Angiography (FA), at 4 Weeks vs. Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Retino-vascular leakage was calculated after manually outlining the inner and outer borders of the subretinal fluid packet in the optical coherence tomography (OCT) images using the &quot;Edit Segmentation&quot; function of the Cirrus HD-OCT software. For cases in which a pigment epithelial detachment was present, the volume of the pigment epithelial detachment was included in the calculation of leakage volume.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Uveitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Microplasmin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microplasmin</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants received an intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin at baseline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Microplasmin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Participant must be 18 years of age or older.

          2. Participant must understand and sign the protocol's informed consent document.

          3. Participant has a diagnosis of uveitic macular edema that requires treatment in at
             least one eye (the study eye) and the uveitis in the study eye is deemed clinically
             quiet by the investigator.

          4. Participant has no evidence of macular or complete PVD in the study eye by B-scan
             ultrasound and OCT.

          5. Participant has visual acuity of 20/400 or better in the study eye.

          6. Participant has a central macular thickness ≥ 270 microns in the study eye and loss of
             the normal foveal contour.

          7. Participant does not have significant cataract or media opacity in the study eye that
             makes posterior segment visualization difficult as determined by investigator.

          8. Female participants of childbearing potential must not be pregnant or breast-feeding
             and must have a negative serum pregnancy test at screening and throughout the study.

          9. Both female participants of childbearing potential and male participants able to
             father a child must agree to practice two effective methods of birth control for six
             months following administration of study medication. Acceptable methods of birth
             control for this study include hormonal contraception (birth control pills, injected
             hormones, dermal patch or vaginal ring), intrauterine device, barrier methods
             (diaphragm, condom) with spermicide or surgical sterilization (hysterectomy, tubal
             ligation or vasectomy). Participants with a hysterectomy or vasectomy (or have a
             partner with a hysterectomy or vasectomy) are exempt from using two methods of birth
             control.

         10. Participant is willing to comply with the study procedures and return for all study
             visits.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Participant has uncontrolled glaucoma, defined as intraocular pressure &gt;30 mmHg
             despite treatment with anti-glaucoma medication, in the study eye.

          2. Participant has lattice degeneration of the retina in the study eye deemed to be high
             risk by the investigator.

          3. Participant has untreated retinal holes or tears, or a macular hole in the study eye.

          4. Participant has a significant active ocular infection in the study eye.

          5. Participant had intraocular surgery within the past 90 days or anticipates elective
             intraocular surgery in the study eye.

          6. Participant had an injection of bevacizumab or ranibizumab within the past four weeks
             in the study eye.

          7. Participant had an injection of triamcinolone within the past six weeks in the study
             eye.

          8. Participant has a condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would preclude
             participation in the study (e.g., unstable medical status that would pose a
             significant hazard if investigational therapy was started).

          9. Participant has known anaphylaxis to sodium fluoride, or has urticaria, angioedema or
             an anaphylactoid response to sodium fluorescein dye that cannot be safely
             pre-medicated with an antihistamine and/or prednisone.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hatice Nida Sen, MD, MHSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2010-EI-0186.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gritz DC, Wong IG. Incidence and prevalence of uveitis in Northern California; the Northern California Epidemiology of Uveitis Study. Ophthalmology. 2004 Mar;111(3):491-500; discussion 500.</citation>
    <PMID>15019324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Djalilian AR, Nussenblatt RB. Immunosuppression in uveitis. Ophthalmol Clin North Am. 2002 Sep;15(3):395-404, viii. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12434489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whitcup SM, Hikita N, Shirao M, Miyasaka M, Tamatani T, Mochizuki M, Nussenblatt RB, Chan CC. Monoclonal antibodies against CD54 (ICAM-1) and CD11a (LFA-1) prevent and inhibit endotoxin-induced uveitis. Exp Eye Res. 1995 Jun;60(6):597-601.</citation>
    <PMID>7641842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 2, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 2, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 3, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>July 10, 2012</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2012</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">August 14, 2012</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 14, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 14, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nida Sen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, NEI</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Microplasmin</keyword>
  <keyword>Macular Edema</keyword>
  <keyword>Uveitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Macular Edema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Plasminogen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrinolysin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Microplasmin</title>
          <description>Participants received an intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin at baseline.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Microplasmin</title>
          <description>Participants received an intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin at baseline.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="2"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="40.50" spread="17.68" lower_limit="28" upper_limit="53"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Adverse Events</title>
        <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Microplasmin</title>
            <description>Participants received an intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin at baseline.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Adverse Events</title>
          <units>Adverse Events</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="2"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Central Macular Thickness, as Measured by Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT), at 4 Weeks vs. Baseline</title>
        <description>Retinal thickness was assessed by spectral-domain optical coherence tomography (Cirrus HD-OCT; Carl Zeiss Meditec, Dublin, CA), a non-invasive imaging technique that uses long-wavelength light to capture micrometer-resolution cross-sectional images from biological tissue.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline and 4 weeks</time_frame>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants Achieving Macular or Complete Posterior Vitreous Detachment (PVT) at 4 Weeks</title>
        <time_frame>Baseline and 4 weeks</time_frame>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in ETDRS Best-corrected Visual Acuity (BCVA) at 4 Weeks vs. Baseline</title>
        <description>Visual acuity was measured using the Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) protocol. Acuity is measured as letters read on an ETDRS eye chart and the letters read equate to Snellen measurements. For example, if a participant reads between 84 and 88 letters, the equivalent Snellen measurement is 20/20.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline and 4 weeks</time_frame>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in ETDRS Best-corrected Visual Acuity (BCVA) at 12 Weeks vs. Baseline</title>
        <description>Visual acuity was measured using the Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) protocol. Acuity is measured as letters read on an ETDRS eye chart and the letters read equate to Snellen measurements. For example, if a participant reads between 84 and 88 letters, the equivalent Snellen measurement is 20/20.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline and 12 Weeks</time_frame>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Severe Adverse Events</title>
        <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Microplasmin</title>
            <description>Participants received an intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin at baseline.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Severe Adverse Events</title>
          <units>Adverse Events</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="2"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Ocular Adverse Events</title>
        <description>The number of eye-related adverse events was calculated.</description>
        <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Microplasmin</title>
            <description>Participants received an intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin at baseline.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Ocular Adverse Events</title>
          <description>The number of eye-related adverse events was calculated.</description>
          <units>Adverse Events</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="2"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Non-ocular Adverse Events</title>
        <description>The number of adverse events that were not eye-related was calculated.</description>
        <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Microplasmin</title>
            <description>Participants received an intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin at baseline.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Non-ocular Adverse Events</title>
          <description>The number of adverse events that were not eye-related was calculated.</description>
          <units>Adverse Events</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="2"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Retino-vascular Leakage, as Seen on Fluorescein Angiography (FA), at 4 Weeks vs. Baseline</title>
        <description>Retino-vascular leakage was calculated after manually outlining the inner and outer borders of the subretinal fluid packet in the optical coherence tomography (OCT) images using the &quot;Edit Segmentation&quot; function of the Cirrus HD-OCT software. For cases in which a pigment epithelial detachment was present, the volume of the pigment epithelial detachment was included in the calculation of leakage volume.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline and 4 weeks</time_frame>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Microplasmin</title>
          <description>Participants received an intravitreal injection of 125 µg in 100 µL of microplasmin at baseline.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA (15.0)</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Conjunctivitis infective</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Investigations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Blood glucose increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arthralgia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rash</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>The study was terminated early due to lack of enrollment.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>H. Nida Sen, Principal Investigator, National Eye Institute</name_or_title>
      <organization>National Institutes of Health</organization>
      <phone>301-402-3254</phone>
      <email>senh@nei.nih.gov</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

