<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01198197</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100204</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-M-0204</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01198197</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PET Brain and Whole Body Distribution Studies for Nociceptin/Orphanin FQ Peptide (NOP) Receptor Using [11C]NOP-1A</brief_title>
  <official_title>PET Brain and Whole Body Distribution Studies for Nociceptin/Orphanin FQ Peptide (NOP) Receptor Using [(11)C]NOP-1A</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - A small brain protein called nociceptin/orphanin FQ peptide (NOP) receptor may be involved
      in several brain diseases such as anxiety, depression, drug abuse, and seizures. Researchers
      are interested in testing a new radioactive chemical that will help locate NOP receptors in
      the brain during imaging studies such as positron emission tomography (PET) scans. Because
      this chemical has not yet been approved by the Food and Drug Administration, it is considered
      to be an experimental drug.

      Objectives:

      - To investigate the effectiveness of the experimental chemical [11C]NOP-1A in imaging
      studies of the nociceptin/orphanin FQ peptide (NOP) receptor.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy volunteers between 18 and 50 years of age who are able to have imaging studies.

      Design:

        -  This study will involve three or four outpatient visits to the National Institutes of
           Health Clinical Center. All participants will be screened with a full physical
           examination, medical history, blood and urine tests, and electrocardiogram.

        -  Participants will be involved in one or more parts of this three-part study as directed
           by study researchers. Part 1 consists of brain imaging to study how the brain responds
           to the chemical. Part 2 is a whole body imaging study to evaluate how the chemical is
           distributed throughout the body after being administered. Part 3 is a set of testing and
           retesting scans to determine how precise the drug is in locating the NOP receptors in
           the brain.

        -  Part 1: Participants will have a brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. Then the
           study drug will be administered and participants will have a brain PET scan. Blood
           samples will be taken during the PET scan, and urine samples will be taken after the
           scan. These tests will take up to 3 hours to perform.

        -  Part 2: Participants will have a whole body PET scan that will last a maximum of 3
           hours.

        -  Part 3: Participants will receive the study drug and have two additional PET scans.
           Blood samples will also be taken during this part.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nociceptin/orphanin FQ peptide (NOP) receptor is a new class of opioid receptor cloned in
      1994 before identifying the endogenous ligand. Within a year, endogenous ligand was
      identified and soon many ligands were developed and evaluated in vitro and in vivo for NOP
      receptor distribution and activity. NOP receptor is widely distributed in brain, spinal cord
      and in peripheral organs such as heart, lungs, kidney, intestine and liver. Being a G-protein
      coupled receptor, its activation leads to changes in intracellular signal transduction
      mediated by adenylyl cyclase, Ca(2+) and K(+) ion channels, mitogen-activated kinase and
      phospholipase C. Based on preclinical studies, NOP receptor is implicated in regulation of
      pain, anxiety and depression, drug abuse, feeding, learning/memory, and motor activity.

      Since the time of cloning the receptor and identification of endogenous ligand, numerous
      compounds have been designed targeting this receptor. However, there are no PET radioligands
      currently available to study NOP distribution and activity in humans. We wish to test a newly
      developed PET radioligand, [(11)C]NOP-1A to study the role of NOP receptors in humans.

      The purpose of this protocol is (1) to perform brain imaging using [(11)C]NOP-1A in healthy
      volunteers to characterize the brain uptake and distribution (2) to perform whole body PET
      studies in healthy volunteers in order to estimate radiation absorbed doses for
      [(11)C]NOP-1A, (3) to perform brain test-retest studies in healthy volunteers in order to
      further examine the precision of the measurement of receptor binding and to determine optimal
      parameters for future experiments using [(11)C]NOP-1A, and, (4) to compare [(11)C]NOP-1A
      concentrations in artery and vein of healthy volunteers to assess the feasibility of
      replacing the arterial line with a less invasive venous line for brain scans.

      Successful development of a PET radioligand to image NOP receptor will have a strong impact
      on further understanding and clinical management of neuropsychiatric disorders that are
      mediated by opioid receptor system. Future experiments will include studies on any relevant
      neuropsychiatric disorder.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 3, 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2014</completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For the PET scans, we will measure the regional densities of NOP receptors as distribution volume (VT). Distribution volume is the ratio at equilibrium of brain uptake to the concentration of parent radioligand in plasma.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NOP-1A</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Healthy Volunteers:

        Subjects must be adults between 18-50 years old.

        Subjects must be able and willing to give written informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Current psychiatric illness or severe systemic disease based on history and physical exam.

        If women, pregnancy or breast feeding (betaHCG will be measured in all female patients
        within 24 hours of scan and must be negative)

        Clinically significant laboratory abnormalities.

        Serious medical problems including but not limited to chronic neurological disease such as
        multiple sclerosis, autoimmune diseases or any cardiopulmonary disease.

        Head trauma resulting in a period of unconsciousness lasting longer than 10 minutes.

        Recent exposure to radiation (i.e., PET from other research) which when combined with this
        study would be above the allowable limits.

        Positive urine drug screen at screening.

        Inability to lie flat on camera bed for about 2.5 hours

        Subjects who have metallic foreign bodies that would be affected by the MRI magnet, or fear
        of enclosed spaces likely to make the subject unable to undergo an MRI scan.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Masahiro Fujita, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berthele A, Platzer S, Dworzak D, Schadrack J, Mahal B, Büttner A, Assmus HP, Wurster K, Zieglgänsberger W, Conrad B, Tölle TR. [3H]-nociceptin ligand-binding and nociceptin opioid receptor mrna expression in the human brain. Neuroscience. 2003;121(3):629-40.</citation>
    <PMID>14568023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bridge KE, Wainwright A, Reilly K, Oliver KR. Autoradiographic localization of (125)i[Tyr(14)] nociceptin/orphanin FQ binding sites in macaque primate CNS. Neuroscience. 2003;118(2):513-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12699786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown AK, Fujita M, Fujimura Y, Liow JS, Stabin M, Ryu YH, Imaizumi M, Hong J, Pike VW, Innis RB. Radiation dosimetry and biodistribution in monkey and man of 11C-PBR28: a PET radioligand to image inflammation. J Nucl Med. 2007 Dec;48(12):2072-9. Epub 2007 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>18006619</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 5, 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 8, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Nociceptin/Orphanin FQ Peptide (NOP)</keyword>
  <keyword>PET Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nociceptin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nocistatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

