<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01196117</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>481-04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01196117</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sleepiness and the Effects of CPAP on Salivary Cortisol and Alpha-Amylase Levels in Patients With Sleep Apnea</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sleepiness and the Effects of CPAP on Salivary Cortisol and Alpha-Amylase Levels in Patients With Sleep Apnea</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ResMed</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome (OSAS) will evidence higher levels of salivary
      cortisol and alpha-amylase levels prior to use of placebo and continuous positive airway
      pressure (CPAP) and will evidence a decrease in these levels after consistent use of
      continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy as compared to placebo. Their level of
      sleepiness will also decrease with the use of CPAP therapy and will correlate with the levels
      of salivary cortisol and alpha-amylase in relation to their subjective sleepiness scale,
      Psychomotor Vigilance Test (PVT), and pupillometry.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It has been shown that there is an inconsistent response in serum cortisol levels in patients
      with Obstructive Sleep Apnea Syndrome (OSAS), but it is undetermined whether a change in
      hormone level was not seen due to compliance issues in these long-term studies. These
      investigators will be employing compliance monitoring continuous positive airway pressure
      (CPAP) machines and also assessing &quot;sleepiness&quot; before and after therapy. Sleepiness is the
      dependent variable in our study and will be measured subjectively using sleepiness scales and
      objectively using Psychomotor Vigilance Test (PVT) and an autonomic measure using
      pupillometry prior, during and after treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary Cortisol Level</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout the patient's 28 day participation</time_frame>
    <description>Salivary Cortisol Level in relation to Placebo and continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) use</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epworth Sleepiness Score (ESS)</measure>
    <time_frame>throughout the patient's 28 day participation</time_frame>
    <description>Epworth Sleepiness Score in relation to Placebo and continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Disordered Breathing</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>14 days of CPAP therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>14 days of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy with salivary cortisol measurement and Epworth Sleepiness Score (ESS) documentation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>14 days of Placebo therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>14 days of placebo therapy - use of guaifenesin with salivary cortisol measurement and Epworth Sleepiness Score (ESS) documentation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>14 days of CPAP therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>14 days of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy with salivary cortisol measurement and Epworth Sleepiness Score (ESS) documentation</description>
    <arm_group_label>14 days of CPAP therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CPAP arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>14 days of placebo therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>14 days of placebo therapy - use of guaifenesin with salivary cortisol measurement and Epworth Sleepiness Score (ESS) documentation</description>
    <arm_group_label>14 days of Placebo therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo arm, non-CPAP arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults

          -  Male and female

          -  Between ages 18 and 90

          -  Undergo a Polysomnography (PSG) with evidence of any sleep disordered breathing
             including snoring, mild/moderate/severe sleep apnea, and/or restless legs

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages 17 and under

          -  Pregnant women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hersel Raff, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandra L Ettema, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura Brusky, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>B Tucker Woodson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Froedtert West Clinics - Otolaryngology Clinc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Block AJ, Boysen PG, Wynne JW, Hunt LA. Sleep apnea, hypopnea and oxygen desaturation in normal subjects. A strong male predominance. N Engl J Med. 1979 Mar 8;300(10):513-7.</citation>
    <PMID>216912</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradley TD, Phillipson EA. Pathogenesis and pathophysiology of the obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. Med Clin North Am. 1985 Nov;69(6):1169-85. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3934481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sullivan CE, Issa FG. Obstructive sleep apnea. Clin Chest Med. 1985 Dec;6(4):633-50.</citation>
    <PMID>3936665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pasquali R, Colella P, Cirignotta F, Mondini S, Gerardi R, Buratti P, Rinaldi Ceroni A, Tartari F, Schiavina M, Melchionda N, et al. Treatment of obese patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS): effect of weight loss and interference of otorhinolaryngoiatric pathology. Int J Obes. 1990 Mar;14(3):207-17.</citation>
    <PMID>2341227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Onusko E. Diagnosing secondary hypertension. Am Fam Physician. 2003 Jan 1;67(1):67-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12537168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weitzman ED, Czeisler CA, Zimmerman JC, Moore-Ede MC. Biological rhythms in man: relationship of sleep-wake, cortisol, growth hormone, and temperature during temporal isolation. Adv Biochem Psychopharmacol. 1981;28:475-99. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7010946</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wittels EH. Obesity and hormonal factors in sleep and sleep apnea. Med Clin North Am. 1985 Nov;69(6):1265-80. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3906303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Entzian P, Linnemann K, Schlaak M, Zabel P. Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome and circadian rhythms of hormones and cytokines. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1996 Mar;153(3):1080-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8630548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bratel T, Wennlund A, Carlström K. Pituitary reactivity, androgens and catecholamines in obstructive sleep apnoea. Effects of continuous positive airway pressure treatment (CPAP). Respir Med. 1999 Jan;93(1):1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10464840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vgontzas AN, Chrousos GP. Sleep, the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis, and cytokines: multiple interactions and disturbances in sleep disorders. Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am. 2002 Mar;31(1):15-36. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12055986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lanfranco F, Gianotti L, Maccario M. Endocrine and metabolic alterations in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome. J Endocrinol Invest. 2003 Jun;26(6):491-2.</citation>
    <PMID>12952359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grunstein RR, Handelsman DJ, Lawrence SJ, Blackwell C, Caterson ID, Sullivan CE. Neuroendocrine dysfunction in sleep apnea: reversal by continuous positive airways pressure therapy. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1989 Feb;68(2):352-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2493027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooper BG, White JE, Ashworth LA, Alberti KG, Gibson GJ. Hormonal and metabolic profiles in subjects with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome and the acute effects of nasal continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) treatment. Sleep. 1995 Apr;18(3):172-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7610313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grunstein RR, Stewart DA, Lloyd H, Akinci M, Cheng N, Sullivan CE. Acute withdrawal of nasal CPAP in obstructive sleep apnea does not cause a rise in stress hormones. Sleep. 1996 Dec;19(10):774-82.</citation>
    <PMID>9085485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meston N, Davies RJ, Mullins R, Jenkinson C, Wass JA, Stradling JR. Endocrine effects of nasal continuous positive airway pressure in male patients with obstructive sleep apnoea. J Intern Med. 2003 Nov;254(5):447-54.</citation>
    <PMID>14535966</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rapoport D, Rothenberg SA, Hollander CS, Goldring RM: Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) and the neuroendocrine &quot;stress&quot; axis. Am Rev Respir Dis 1991; 143: A382 (abstract)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Follenius M, Krieger J, Krauth MO, Sforza F, Brandenberger G. Obstructive sleep apnea treatment: peripheral and central effects on plasma renin activity and aldosterone. Sleep. 1991 Jun;14(3):211-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1896722</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raff H: Salivary cortisol: a useful measurement in the diagnosis of cushing's syndrome and the evaluation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis. The Endocrinologist 2000; 10: 9-17</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laudat MH, Cerdas S, Fournier C, Guiban D, Guilhaume B, Luton JP. Salivary cortisol measurement: a practical approach to assess pituitary-adrenal function. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1988 Feb;66(2):343-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2828410</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Papanicolaou DA, Mullen N, Kyrou I, Nieman LK. Nighttime salivary cortisol: a useful test for the diagnosis of Cushing's syndrome. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2002 Oct;87(10):4515-21.</citation>
    <PMID>12364428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raff H, Findling JW. A physiologic approach to diagnosis of the Cushing syndrome. Ann Intern Med. 2003 Jun 17;138(12):980-91. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12809455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Umeda T, Hiramatsu R, Iwaoka T, Shimada T, Miura F, Sato T. Use of saliva for monitoring unbound free cortisol levels in serum. Clin Chim Acta. 1981 Mar 5;110(2-3):245-53.</citation>
    <PMID>6261989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vining RF, McGinley RA, Maksvytis JJ, Ho KY. Salivary cortisol: a better measure of adrenal cortical function than serum cortisol. Ann Clin Biochem. 1983 Nov;20 (Pt 6):329-35.</citation>
    <PMID>6316831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raff H, Raff JL, Findling JW. Late-night salivary cortisol as a screening test for Cushing's syndrome. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1998 Aug;83(8):2681-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9709931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castro M, Elias PC, Martinelli CE Jr, Antonini SR, Santiago L, Moreira AC. Salivary cortisol as a tool for physiological studies and diagnostic strategies. Braz J Med Biol Res. 2000 Oct;33(10):1171-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11004717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broderick JE, Arnold D, Kudielka BM, Kirschbaum C. Salivary cortisol sampling compliance: comparison of patients and healthy volunteers. Psychoneuroendocrinology. 2004 Jun;29(5):636-50.</citation>
    <PMID>15041086</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chatterton RT Jr, Vogelsong KM, Lu YC, Ellman AB, Hudgens GA. Salivary alpha-amylase as a measure of endogenous adrenergic activity. Clin Physiol. 1996 Jul;16(4):433-48.</citation>
    <PMID>8842578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skosnik PD, Chatterton RT Jr, Swisher T, Park S. Modulation of attentional inhibition by norepinephrine and cortisol after psychological stress. Int J Psychophysiol. 2000 Apr;36(1):59-68.</citation>
    <PMID>10700623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nater UM, Rohleder N, Gaab J, Berger S, Jud A, Wolf JM, Ehlert U: Reactivity of human salivary alpha-amylase in a psychosocial stress paradigm. J Psychophysiol 2002; 16(4): 245 (abstract)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nater UM, La Marca R, Florin L, Koller MM, Ehlert U: The relationship between salivary alpha-amylase and plasma catecholamines. J Psychophysiol 2003; 17(3): 170 (abstract).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graeber RC: Aircrew fatigue and circadian rhythmicity. In: Wiener E, Nagel DC, eds. Human Factors in Aviation. New York: Academic Press; 1987: 1-48</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akerstedt T. Sleepiness as a consequence of shift work. Sleep. 1988 Feb;11(1):17-34. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3283910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price WJ, Holley DC. Shiftwork and safety in aviation. Occup Med. 1990 Apr-Jun;5(2):343-77. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2203162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kecklund G, Akerstedt T. Sleepiness in long distance truck driving: an ambulatory EEG study of night driving. Ergonomics. 1993 Sep;36(9):1007-17.</citation>
    <PMID>8404830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akerstedt T. Work hours and sleepiness. Neurophysiol Clin. 1995;25(6):367-75. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8904199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitler MM, Miller JC, Lipsitz JJ, Walsh JK, Wylie CD. The sleep of long-haul truck drivers. N Engl J Med. 1997 Sep 11;337(11):755-61.</citation>
    <PMID>9287232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohayon MM, Caulet M, Philip P, Guilleminault C, Priest RG. How sleep and mental disorders are related to complaints of daytime sleepiness. Arch Intern Med. 1997 Dec 8-22;157(22):2645-52.</citation>
    <PMID>9531234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoddes E, Zarcone V, Smythe H, Phillips R, Dement WC. Quantification of sleepiness: a new approach. Psychophysiology. 1973 Jul;10(4):431-6.</citation>
    <PMID>4719486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johns MW. A new method for measuring daytime sleepiness: the Epworth sleepiness scale. Sleep. 1991 Dec;14(6):540-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1798888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chervin RD, Aldrich MS, Pickett R, Guilleminault C. Comparison of the results of the Epworth Sleepiness Scale and the Multiple Sleep Latency Test. J Psychosom Res. 1997 Feb;42(2):145-55.</citation>
    <PMID>9076642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jokinen T, Salmi T, Ylikoski A, Partinen M. Use of computerized visual performance test in assessing day-time vigilance in patients with sleep apneas and restless sleep. Int J Clin Monit Comput. 1995;12(4):225-30.</citation>
    <PMID>8820329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loh S, Lamond N, Dorrian J, Roach G, Dawson D. The validity of psychomotor vigilance tasks of less than 10-minute duration. Behav Res Methods Instrum Comput. 2004 May;36(2):339-46.</citation>
    <PMID>15354700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lowenstein O, Feinberg R, Loewenfeld ID: Pupillary movements during acute and chronic fatigue. Investigative Ophthalmolog 1963; 2: 138-157</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoss RE, Moyer NJ, Ogle KN. The pupillogram and narcolepsy. A method to measure decreased levels of wakefulness. Neurology. 1969 Oct;19(10):921-8.</citation>
    <PMID>5387594</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lüdtke H, Wilhelm B, Adler M, Schaeffel F, Wilhelm H. Mathematical procedures in data recording and processing of pupillary fatigue waves. Vision Res. 1998 Oct;38(19):2889-96.</citation>
    <PMID>9797985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merrit SL, Schnyders HC, Mercer P: Circadian aspects of papillary unrest reflecting daytime sleepiness. Sleep Research Online 1999; 2(Sup 1): 773</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merrit SL, Schnyders HC, Mercer P, Zhou X: The sensitivity of pupillography to circadian aspects of sleepiness. J Sleep Research 1998; 7(Sup 2): 176</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 3, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 7, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 10, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>B Tucker Woodson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>automatic positive airway pressure (APAP)</keyword>
  <keyword>continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP)</keyword>
  <keyword>Salivary Cortisol</keyword>
  <keyword>Apnea</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep Apnea and/or any Sleep Disordered Breathing</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone 17-butyrate 21-propionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cortisol succinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>January 15, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>February 11, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>February 19, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>March 21, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>May 6, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>June 13, 2016</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

