<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03408639</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ERY.CIN.MA.94</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IRCT201601156135N6</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03408639</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing Efficacy and Safety of CinnaGen Beta Erythropoietin (CinnaPoietin®) Versus Eprex® on the Treatment of Anemia in ESRD Hemodialysis Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III, Randomized, Two Armed, Parallel, Double Blind (Patient and Assessor Blinded), Active Controlled Non Inferiority Clinical Trial to Determine the Non Inferior Therapeutic Efficacy and Safety Between CinnaPoietin® (Beta Erythropoietin) and Eprex® (Epoetin Alpha) on the Treatment of Anemia in ESRD Hemodialysis Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cinnagen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cinnagen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase III, randomized, two-armed, parallel, double-blind, active-controlled clinical
      trial is designed to compare efficacy and safety of CinnaPoietin® (Beta erythropoietin) and
      Eprex® (epoetin alpha) on the treatment of anemia in 156 End-Stage Renal Disease hemodialysis
      patients. 156 patients have been planned to randomize and assign to receive CinnaPoietin® or
      Eprex® for a 26-week period. Administration dose for patients who are treated with
      erythropoietin is the similar dose of the previously administered amount (IV or SC without
      any change). After then, dose adjustment will be made based on patients' response. The
      primary objective of this study is to compare the efficacy of CinnaPoietin® with Eprex®. The
      secondary objectives of this study are further comparison and evaluation of efficacy along
      with safety between CinnaPoietin® and Eprex®.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a phase III, randomized, two-armed, parallel, double-blind (patient and
      assessor blinded), active-controlled noninferiority clinical trial to determine the
      non-inferior therapeutic efficacy and safety between CinnaPoietin® (Beta erythropoietin) and
      Eprex® (epoetin alpha) on the treatment of anemia in ESRD patient under hemodialysis. After
      signing the written informed consents, 156 patients have been planned to randomize and assign
      to receive CinnaPoietin® or Eprex® for a 26-weeks period. Administration dose for patients
      who are treated with erythropoietin is the similar dose of the previously administered amount
      (IV or SC without any change). After then, dose adjustment will be made based on patients'
      response. In addition to main intervention, Nephrovit tablet/day and B12 100 mcg/month were
      prescribed for patients. The primary objective of this study is to compare the efficacy of
      CinnaPoietin® with Eprex®. The secondary objectives of this study are further comparison and
      evaluation of efficacy and safety.

      The clinical trial will be conducted according to the GCP considerations. A comprehensive
      validation check program is used to verify the data, and discrepancy reports are generated
      accordingly for resolution by the investigator.

      In order to ensure the use of standard and unified procedure of each test, monitoring of each
      site and laboratory site are going to be applied by sponsor monitoring team and CRO as
      external monitoring team.

      The same prefilled syringe is used for CinnaPoietin® to be sure that there is no difference
      between CinnaPoietin® and Eprex® as brand drug. The drugs will be relabeled, and the same
      label is used for both prefilled syringe. So neither investigators nor subjects are able to
      notice any differences between them and are blind to the assignment.

      Determination of sample size 156 patients will be equally (1:1) divided into intervention
      arms (78 in each group considering drop out) for achieving 80% power in order to determine
      non-inferiority using a one-sided, independent sample t-test. The margin of non-inferiority
      is -1.00.

      The true difference between the means is assumed to be -0.500. The significance level (alpha)
      of the test is 0.05. The data are drawn from populations with standard deviations of 1.200
      and 1.200.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 22, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 19, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 19, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Hb change level during the last four weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 22 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoints of this study is to assess mean Hb change level during the last four weeks of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean weekly epoetin dosage per kg body weight during the last four weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 22 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>The mean weekly epoetin dosage per kg body weight during the last four weeks of treatment necessary to maintain the Hb level within 10-12 g/dl during the last four weeks of treatment is considered as the second primary endpoint.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with any permanent or transient dose change</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with any Hb measurement outside the target range (10-12 g/dl)</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients needed blood transfusions</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with treatment success</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 to week 26</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is considered as Hb concentration equal to or more than 11.0 g/dl and two consecutive weeks without any blood transfusion within the preceding three months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with maintenance success</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Maintenance success is considered as maintenance success is considered as maintenance of mean Hb concentration of 11.0 ± 1.0 g/dl for at least four consecutive weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of patients with Hb measurements more than 10.0 g/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 22 to week 26</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of hematocrit measurements more than 30%</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 22 to week 26</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of Hb levels above 13 g/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The first safety endpoint is the proportion of patients with at least one Hb measurement above 13 g/dL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with an increase in Hb concentration of &gt; 1.0 g/dl for four consecutive weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence rate of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">156</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia in End-Stage Renal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CinnaPoietin®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The starting dose of Erythropoietin is 60 (50-100) IU/kg body weight/week for naïve patients. Administration dose for patients who are treated with erythropoietin is similar dose of previously administered amount (IV or SC without any change). After then, dose adjustment will be done based on patients' response.
In addition to main intervention, Nephrovit tablet/day and vitamine B12 100 mcg/month will be prescribed for patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eprex®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The starting dose of Erythropoietin is 60 (50-100) IU/kg body weight/week for naïve patients. Administration dose for patients who are treated with erythropoietin is similar dose of previously administered amount (IV or SC without any change). After then, dose adjustment will be done based on patients' response. In addition to main intervention, Nephrovit tablet/day and vitamine B12 100 mcg/month will be prescribed for patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CinnaPoietin®</intervention_name>
    <description>The starting dose of Erythropoietin is 60 (50-100) IU/kg body weight/week for naïve patients. Administration dose for patients who are treated with erythropoietin is similar dose of previously administered amount (IV or SC without any change). After then, dose adjustment will be done based on patients' response.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CinnaPoietin®</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Beta erythropoietin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eprex®</intervention_name>
    <description>The starting dose of Erythropoietin is 60 (50-100) IU/kg body weight/week for naïve patients. Administration dose for patients who are treated with erythropoietin is similar dose of previously administered amount (IV or SC without any change). After then, dose adjustment will be done based on patients' response.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eprex®</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Epoetin alpha</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nephrovit</intervention_name>
    <description>Nephrovit tablet is daily administered to all the patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CinnaPoietin®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Eprex®</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin B12 Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Vitamin B12 is monthly injected to all the patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CinnaPoietin®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Eprex®</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged between 18 and 70

          -  ESRD patients who are on hemodialysis for ≥3 months.

          -  Hb level 8- 11.5 g/dl

          -  Patients are on adequate hemodialysis: the minimally adequate dose of hemodialysis
             given 3 times per week should be a spKt/V (single-pool delivered Kt/V; clearance of
             urea x dialysis time/volume of distribution) of 1.2 per dialysis. For treatment
             periods of less than 5 hours, an alternative minimum dose is a urea reduction rate
             (URR) of 65%. All types of hemodialysis systems and hemodiafiltration, including
             high-flux membranes are allowed as long as there is no plan to change the patient's
             regimen during the study.

          -  Sufficient iron stores, defined as serum ferritin ≥ 200 ng/ml and transferrin
             saturation ≥20%. (Patients not meeting these criteria may receive iron supplementation
             therapy during the Screening and stabilization period to appropriately correct their
             iron store deficiency to meet the criterion required for randomization);

          -  Ability to comply with study medication use, study visits, and study procedures as
             judged by the investigator;

          -  Females of childbearing potential agree to use an acceptable method of birth control
             (e.g., abstinence, hormonal or barrier methods, partner sterilization, or IUD) for the
             duration of the study.

          -  Qualified and willing to sign the informed consent form with the commitment of
             complying with all the scheduled visits, and study procedures as judged by the
             investigator;

          -  In any circumstances that potential participants are not able to give consent, it may
             be given by responsible parents or guardian.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (defined as pre-dialysis diastolic blood pressure ≥ 100 mmHg
             or systolic blood pressure ≥180 mmHg);

          -  Anemia secondary to other causes different to the CKD (e.g. multiple myeloma, aplastic
             anemia, leukemia;….)

          -  Decompensated liver failure;

          -  Clinical evidence of concurrent uncontrolled hyperparathyroidism (defined as serum
             parathyroid hormone (iPTH) &gt; 800 pg/ml);

          -  Heart failure [New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III and IV];

          -  Unstable angina pectoris, active cardiac disease, stroke and/or cardiac infarction
             within the last 6 months;

          -  History of or active blood coagulation disorders including DVT, PTE, native access
             Thrombosis during last 6 months.

          -  Thrombocytosis (platelet count &gt; 500,000/µl);

          -  Thrombocytopenia (platelet count &lt; 100,000/µl);

          -  White blood cell count &lt; 3,000/µl);

          -  White blood cell count &gt;15,000)

          -  Recent Bleeding (acute or chronic bleeding within three months prior to screening);

          -  Suspicion of or confirmed occult bleeding (increased reticulocyte count);

          -  Clinical evidence of concurrent systemic infection, or inflammatory disease (e.g;
             diabetic foot, bed sore, access infection, CRP&gt; 30,…)

          -  Currently receiving treatment for epilepsy;

          -  Major surgery within 3 months prior to randomization and during the conduct of the
             trial (except vascular access surgery);

          -  Concomitant immunosuppressive therapy; patients on a short course of steroids (up to 7
             days), topical or intranasal steroids are allowed in the study;

          -  History of any malignant disease within the last 5 years (except excised non-melanoma
             skin cancer);

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding;

          -  Known history of severe drug-related allergies;

          -  Known history of drug related allergy to Erythropoietin or one of the ingredients of
             the test or the reference products or hypersensitivity to mammalian-derived products;

          -  Transplant received within one year prior to the start of the study;

          -  Simultaneous participation in another clinical study or having received an
             Investigational Medicinal Product within three months before randomization in this
             study.

          -  Psychiatric, addictive (drugs or alcohol) or any other disorder that compromises the
             ability to give an informed consent;

          -  Any red blood cell transfusion during the last 3 months (measured at the time of
             eligibility verification);

          -  Primary hematological disorder (e.g. myelodysplastic syndrome, myeloma, sickle cell
             anemia, hematological malignancy, multiple myeloma hemolytic anemia);

          -  known resistance to the rHuEPO defined by a requirement &gt; 450 IU/kg/week by IV or 300
             IU/kg/week by SC, equivalent to approximately 20.000 IU/week SC and in absence of iron
             deficiency;

          -  who have suffered an event of active bleeding in the 30 days prior to the beginning of
             the study;

          -  Morbid obesity, defined by a Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt; 37 kg/m2 in women and &gt; 40 kg/m2
             in men.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Astor BC, Muntner P, Levin A, Eustace JA, Coresh J. Association of kidney function with anemia: the Third National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (1988-1994). Arch Intern Med. 2002 Jun 24;162(12):1401-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12076240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McLean E, Cogswell M, Egli I, Wojdyla D, de Benoist B. Worldwide prevalence of anaemia, WHO Vitamin and Mineral Nutrition Information System, 1993-2005. Public Health Nutr. 2009 Apr;12(4):444-54. doi: 10.1017/S1368980008002401. Epub 2008 May 23.</citation>
    <PMID>18498676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brittin GM, Brecher G, Johnson CA, Elashoff RM. Stability of blood in commonly used anticoagulants. Use of refrigerated blood for quality control of the Coulter Counter Model S. Am J Clin Pathol. 1969 Dec;52(6):690-4.</citation>
    <PMID>4982112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Locatelli F, Aljama P, Bárány P, Canaud B, Carrera F, Eckardt KU, Hörl WH, Macdougal IC, Macleod A, Wiecek A, Cameron S; European Best Practice Guidelines Working Group. Revised European best practice guidelines for the management of anaemia in patients with chronic renal failure. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2004 May;19 Suppl 2:ii1-47.</citation>
    <PMID>15206425</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weiss G, Goodnough LT. Anemia of chronic disease. N Engl J Med. 2005 Mar 10;352(10):1011-23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15758012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fehr T, Ammann P, Garzoni D, Korte W, Fierz W, Rickli H, Wüthrich RP. Interpretation of erythropoietin levels in patients with various degrees of renal insufficiency and anemia. Kidney Int. 2004 Sep;66(3):1206-11.</citation>
    <PMID>15327419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ross RP, McCrea JB, Besarab A. Erythropoietin response to blood loss in hemodialysis patients in blunted but preserved. ASAIO J. 1994 Jul-Sep;40(3):M880-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8555638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lipschitz DA, Cook JD, Finch CA. A clinical evaluation of serum ferritin as an index of iron stores. N Engl J Med. 1974 May 30;290(22):1213-6.</citation>
    <PMID>4825851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rambod M, Kovesdy CP, Kalantar-Zadeh K. Combined high serum ferritin and low iron saturation in hemodialysis patients: the role of inflammation. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2008 Nov;3(6):1691-701. doi: 10.2215/CJN.01070308. Epub 2008 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>18922994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernández-Rodríguez AM, Guindeo-Casasús MC, Molero-Labarta T, Domínguez-Cabrera C, Hortal-Casc n L, Pérez-Borges P, Vega-Díaz N, Saavedra-Santana P, Palop-Cubillo L. Diagnosis of iron deficiency in chronic renal failure. Am J Kidney Dis. 1999 Sep;34(3):508-13.</citation>
    <PMID>10469862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalantar-Zadeh K, Höffken B, Wünsch H, Fink H, Kleiner M, Luft FC. Diagnosis of iron deficiency anemia in renal failure patients during the post-erythropoietin era. Am J Kidney Dis. 1995 Aug;26(2):292-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7645533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aljama P, Ward MK, Pierides AM, Eastham EJ, Ellis HA, Feest TG, Conceicao S, Kerr DN. Serum ferritin concentration: a reliable guide to iron overload in uremic and hemodialyzed patients. Clin Nephrol. 1978 Sep;10(3):101-4.</citation>
    <PMID>699405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bárány P, Eriksson LC, Hultcrantz R, Pettersson E, Bergström J. Serum ferritin and tissue iron in anemic dialysis patients. Miner Electrolyte Metab. 1997;23(3-6):273-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9387132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blumberg AB, Marti HR, Graber CG. Serum ferritin and bone marrow iron in patients undergoing continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis. JAMA. 1983 Dec 23-30;250(24):3317-9.</citation>
    <PMID>6645029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hussein S, Prieto J, O'Shea M, Hoffbrand AV, Baillod RA, Moorhead JF. Serum ferritin assay and iron status in chronic renal failure and haemodialysis. Br Med J. 1975 Mar 8;1(5957):546-8.</citation>
    <PMID>49205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirahmadi KS, Paul WL, Winer RL, Dabir-Vaziri N, Byer B, Gorman JT, Rosen SM. Serum ferritin level. Determinant of iron requirement in hemodialysis patients. JAMA. 1977 Aug 15;238(7):601-3.</citation>
    <PMID>577960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spinowitz BS, Kausz AT, Baptista J, Noble SD, Sothinathan R, Bernardo MV, Brenner L, Pereira BJ. Ferumoxytol for treating iron deficiency anemia in CKD. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2008 Aug;19(8):1599-605. doi: 10.1681/ASN.2007101156. Epub 2008 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18525001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silverberg DS, Blum M, Agbaria Z, Deutsch V, Irony M, Schwartz D, Baruch R, Yachnin T, Steinbruch S, Iaina A. The effect of i.v. iron alone or in combination with low-dose erythropoietin in the rapid correction of anemia of chronic renal failure in the predialysis period. Clin Nephrol. 2001 Mar;55(3):212-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11316241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stancu S, Bârsan L, Stanciu A, Mircescu G. Can the response to iron therapy be predicted in anemic nondialysis patients with chronic kidney disease? Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2010 Mar;5(3):409-16. doi: 10.2215/CJN.04280609. Epub 2009 Dec 17. Erratum in: Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2010 Nov;5(11):2137-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20019121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fishbane S, Frei GL, Maesaka J. Reduction in recombinant human erythropoietin doses by the use of chronic intravenous iron supplementation. Am J Kidney Dis. 1995 Jul;26(1):41-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7611266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sunder-Plassmann G, Hörl WH. Importance of iron supply for erythropoietin therapy. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 1995 Nov;10(11):2070-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8643170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Macdougall IC, Tucker B, Thompson J, Tomson CR, Baker LR, Raine AE. A randomized controlled study of iron supplementation in patients treated with erythropoietin. Kidney Int. 1996 Nov;50(5):1694-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8914038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang CH, Chang CC, Chiang SS. Reduction in erythropoietin doses by the use of chronic intravenous iron supplementation in iron-replete hemodialysis patients. Clin Nephrol. 2002 Feb;57(2):136-41.</citation>
    <PMID>11863124</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeVita MV, Frumkin D, Mittal S, Kamran A, Fishbane S, Michelis MF. Targeting higher ferritin concentrations with intravenous iron dextran lowers erythropoietin requirement in hemodialysis patients. Clin Nephrol. 2003 Nov;60(5):335-40.</citation>
    <PMID>14640239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rozen-Zvi B, Gafter-Gvili A, Paul M, Leibovici L, Shpilberg O, Gafter U. Intravenous versus oral iron supplementation for the treatment of anemia in CKD: systematic review and meta-analysis. Am J Kidney Dis. 2008 Nov;52(5):897-906. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2008.05.033. Epub 2008 Oct 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18845368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Senger JM, Weiss RJ. Hematologic and erythropoietin responses to iron dextran in the hemodialysis environment. ANNA J. 1996 Jun;23(3):319-23; discussion 324-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8716991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Navarro JF, Teruel JL, Liaño F, Marcén R, Ortuño J. Effectiveness of intravenous administration of Fe-gluconate-Na complex to maintain adequate body iron stores in hemodialysis patients. Am J Nephrol. 1996;16(4):268-72.</citation>
    <PMID>8739277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tessitore N, Solero GP, Lippi G, Bassi A, Faccini GB, Bedogna V, Gammaro L, Brocco G, Restivo G, Bernich P, Lupo A, Maschio G. The role of iron status markers in predicting response to intravenous iron in haemodialysis patients on maintenance erythropoietin. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2001 Jul;16(7):1416-23.</citation>
    <PMID>11427634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Wyck DB, Roppolo M, Martinez CO, Mazey RM, McMurray S; United States Iron Sucrose (Venofer) Clinical Trials Group. A randomized, controlled trial comparing IV iron sucrose to oral iron in anemic patients with nondialysis-dependent CKD. Kidney Int. 2005 Dec;68(6):2846-56.</citation>
    <PMID>16316362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allegra V, Mengozzi G, Vasile A. Iron deficiency in maintenance hemodialysis patients: assessment of diagnosis criteria and of three different iron treatments. Nephron. 1991;57(2):175-82.</citation>
    <PMID>1902285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li H, Wang SX. Intravenous iron sucrose in Chinese hemodialysis patients with renal anemia. Blood Purif. 2008;26(2):151-6. doi: 10.1159/000113529. Epub 2008 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>18212498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palmer SC, Navaneethan SD, Craig JC, Johnson DW, Tonelli M, Garg AX, Pellegrini F, Ravani P, Jardine M, Perkovic V, Graziano G, McGee R, Nicolucci A, Tognoni G, Strippoli GF. Meta-analysis: erythropoiesis-stimulating agents in patients with chronic kidney disease. Ann Intern Med. 2010 Jul 6;153(1):23-33. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-153-1-201007060-00252. Epub 2010 Jun 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20439566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parfrey PS, Wish T. Quality of life in CKD patients treated with erythropoiesis-stimulating agents. Am J Kidney Dis. 2010 Mar;55(3):423-5. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2009.12.014.</citation>
    <PMID>20189050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gandra SR, Finkelstein FO, Bennett AV, Lewis EF, Brazg T, Martin ML. Impact of erythropoiesis-stimulating agents on energy and physical function in nondialysis CKD patients with anemia: a systematic review. Am J Kidney Dis. 2010 Mar;55(3):519-34. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2009.09.019. Epub 2009 Dec 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20031287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johansen KL, Finkelstein FO, Revicki DA, Gitlin M, Evans C, Mayne TJ. Systematic review and meta-analysis of exercise tolerance and physical functioning in dialysis patients treated with erythropoiesis-stimulating agents. Am J Kidney Dis. 2010 Mar;55(3):535-48. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2009.12.018. Epub 2010 Feb 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20133033</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solomon SD, Uno H, Lewis EF, Eckardt KU, Lin J, Burdmann EA, de Zeeuw D, Ivanovich P, Levey AS, Parfrey P, Remuzzi G, Singh AK, Toto R, Huang F, Rossert J, McMurray JJ, Pfeffer MA; Trial to Reduce Cardiovascular Events with Aranesp Therapy (TREAT) Investigators. Erythropoietic response and outcomes in kidney disease and type 2 diabetes. N Engl J Med. 2010 Sep 16;363(12):1146-55. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1005109.</citation>
    <PMID>20843249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>End-Stage Renal Disease, Anemia, Erythropoietin, Hemoglobine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B 12</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxocobalamin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epoetin Alfa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B Complex</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

