<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03400891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>US14/15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03400891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PROFRUVE Program to Promote Fruit and Vegetables Intake Among Children.</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROFRUVE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomised Controlled Trial of a Program Based on the Theory of Planned Behaviour to Promote Fruit and Vegetables Intake Among Children. PROFRUVE Study Protocol.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Basque Country University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Basque Country University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Because fruit and vegetables (FV) intake of children of Vitoria city is low, a controlled
      intervention program was proposed at school level. The intervention was based on the Theory
      of Planned Behavior (TPB) as long as behavioral theories have been proved to be the most
      effective changing infant FV intake pattern. The main purpose of the study is to evaluate the
      effectiveness of an intervention program based on TPB and aimed to increase FV consumption in
      schoolchildren aged 8 to 10. For that aim, eligible classrooms from different schools were
      randomly assigned to the intervention (n=86) or control (n=86) group. The intervention group
      received 14 sessions of 60 minutes during 9 months of an academic year. Sessions, designed by
      a multidisciplinary team, are based on TPB and aimed to modify determinants of behavior
      (attitudes, subjective norms, perceived behavioral control, intention of consumption), and
      intake of FV itself. Change in fruit and vegetable intake and determinants of eating behavior
      were evaluated at 9 months of intervention using validated surveys, 7 day food records, 24
      hour reminders and questionnaires. This study will provide a valid and useful tool to achieve
      changes in the consumption of FV at school level. A negative result will be useful to help
      redefining new strategies in the framework of changing habits in the consumption of FV.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In Vitoria, only two out of ten children and adolescents (aged 6 to 17) consume the
      recommended three servings of fruit and only one out of ten the recommended two servings of
      vegetables per day. Average intake of fruit was 1.8 servings/day and 0.8 servings/day for
      vegetables. For that reason, promotion of the adequate intake of FV must be a priority
      objective in the promotion of healthy eating habits. One of the most used theories in this
      type of interventions is TPB (Theory of Planned Behavior). According to this theory, eating
      behavior and intention of consumption determinants are both personal and environmental.
      Specifically, the TPB states that attitude, subjective norms and perceived control are
      determinants that influence both the intention to consume food and the action of consuming
      it.

      The hypothesis of the study is that an intervention program based on theories of behavior and
      aimed to increase FV intake in schoolchildren aged 8 to 10, will produce changes in attitude,
      subjective norms, perceived behavioral control and intention of eating fruit and vegetable
      among children, which in turn will modify the behavior, increasing FV intake.

      The main objective of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of an intervention program
      based on behavioral theory and aimed to increase FV intake in schoolchildren aged 8 to 10
      (short and long effect).

      Secondary objectives of the study are (i) to evaluate the change on FV intake on the study
      population after intervention, (ii) to examine the impact of the intervention program on
      behavioral determinants, (iii) to analyze the association of the determinants of behavior on
      FV intake, and (iv) to study the influence between social demographic variables and the
      effectiveness of the program.

      The recruitment of participants begun in may 2015 and they were randomly assigned to
      intervention or control groups. The intervention group received 14 sessions (one every 15
      days) of one hour to work TPB constructs: attitude; subjective norms; perceived behavioural
      control and intention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 11, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 16, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 16, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FV intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline food and vegetable intake at 9 months of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Fruit and vegetable daily intake (servings/day)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating behaviour determinant: Attitude</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline attitude at 9 months of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of attitude related to eat more FV (1-5 point score, from totally disagree to totally agree)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating behaviour determinant: Subjective Norms</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline subjective norms at 9 months of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of subjective norms or social pressure related to eat more FV (1-5 point score, from totally disagree to totally agree)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating behaviour determinant: Perceived Behavioural Control</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline perceived behavioural control at 9 months of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of perceived behavioural control related to eat more FV (1-5 point score, from totally disagree to totally agree)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating behaviour determinant: Intention</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline intention at 9 months of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of intention of eating more FV (1-5 point score, from totally disagree to totally agree)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social demographic outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline social demographic outcomes at 9 months of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Participants families social and demographic data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parents FV intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from parent's baseline food and vegetable intake at 9 months of interventions</time_frame>
    <description>Parents fruits and vegetables daily intake (servings/day)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">230</enrollment>
  <condition>Eating Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Diet</condition>
  <condition>Fruit and Vegetable Intake</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group received 14 sessions (one every 15 days) of one hour in the classroom, to work TPB constructs: attitude; subjective norms; perceived behavioural control and intention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 session of 1 hour each to give general information about fruit and vegetables intake and health.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Program based on the theory of planned behaviour</intervention_name>
    <description>14 sessions of one hour to work TPB constructs: attitude, subjective norms, perceived behavioural control and intention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all schools with children aged 7-11 years old

          -  schools with orchard

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  special schools

          -  schools carrying out other healthy eating programs at the intervention period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Basque Country University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Victor Manuel Rodriguez Rivera</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pediatric Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD will not be shared</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

