<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03406923</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-0951</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03406923</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Self-efficacy, Beliefs and Adherence- Pilot and Feasibility Trial of a Pharmacist-led Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Self-efficacy, Beliefs and Adherence- Pilot and Feasibility Trial of a Pharmacist-led Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>William S. Middleton Memorial Veterans Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study uses an intervention mixed methods design. The overall purpose is to improve
      medication adherence and assess the clinical impact on diabetes outcomes among patients with
      uncontrolled diabetes. We will examine if usual care combined with a clinic-based health
      literacy/psychosocial support intervention improves medication adherence compared to usual
      care alone. A randomized controlled trial will be conducted at William S. Middleton Memorial
      Veterans Hospital in Madison, targeting individuals with uncontrolled diabetes. The
      patient-centered health literacy intervention will focus on enhancing patients' self-efficacy
      and addressing patients' negative beliefs in medicine and illness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will improve medication adherence for patients with diabetes using two strategies:
      1) addressing health literacy by reducing the complexity of diabetes content disseminated to
      patients during medication counseling and 2) addressing health literacy by enhancing
      patient-pharmacist communication. The second strategy aims to improve the psychosocial
      support offered to patients by building self-efficacy and addressing negative beliefs about
      medicines and diabetes. Together, the patient and the pharmacist can work together towards
      goal setting, problem solving, and negotiation of competing priorities.

      Currently, with usual care, the pharmacist confirms if patients understand how to take
      medications correctly, adjusts diabetes medications, and monitor patients' hemoglobin A1C
      levels periodically to make sure that patients are capable of managing their diabetes
      appropriately. With the proposed intervention, the pharmacist will identify patients'
      concerns and barriers to medication taking and self-care with diabetes with an emphasis on
      self-efficacy, negative beliefs in medicine and illness. Then the pharmacist will provide
      individualized plans and set specific goals with each patient by strengthening their
      confidence in medication use and health literacy skills in navigating health information for
      diabetes self-care. The methods described for the intervention are in line with the current
      clinic workflow and will not require a substantial change to the current system for
      counseling diabetes patients. Knowledge change often does not lead to behavior change. Hence,
      the intervention will innovatively focus on moving knowledge towards action as the clinical
      pharmacist works with patients in assessing health literacy, identifying their barriers to
      medication use, including lack of self-efficacy, addressing negative beliefs about diabetes
      and diabetes medications; towards problem solving, and developing goals and action plans that
      will improve medication adherence and glycemic control.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in diabetes medication adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months, and 6 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of days covered and the 5-item Medication Adherence Rating Scale (MARS-5) will be used to measure diabetes medication adherence. The minimum score for the MAR scale is 5 and the maximum score is 25. Total score ranges from 5-25; Higher scores represent higher self-reported adherence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in diabetes control</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Hemoglobin A1c will be abstracted from electronic medical records using the most recent value for each participant within the prior six months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-efficacy for medication use</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, and 3 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Self-efficacy for medication use will be measured using the 13-item Self-efficacy for Appropriate Medication Use Scale. The minimum score is 13 and the maximum score is 39. Higher scores represent higher confidence in adhering to medication use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Illness beliefs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, and 3 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Illness beliefs will be measured using the 9-item the Brief Illness Perception Questionnaire. A higher score indicates a more threatening view of the illness. Total score ranges from 0-80.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beliefs in medicines</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 weeks, and 3 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Beliefs in medicines will be measured using the 10-item Belief about Medicines Questionnaire. The 10-item Belief about Medicines Questionnaire (BMQ) has the necessity beliefs and concern beliefs sub-scale (five items each). The scale has five-point Likert-type responses ranging from strongly disagree to strongly agree. Each sub-scale has scores ranging from 5-25, with a higher score meaning stronger concern or necessity beliefs about the medicine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health literacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Health literacy will be measured using the 6-item Newest Vital Sign. Each question will be scored &quot;0&quot; for incorrect and &quot;1&quot; for correct yielding a total score ranging from 0 to 6, with higher scores indicating better health literacy. Scores less than 2 represented a high likelihood (50% or more) of limited (inadequate) health literacy, 2 to 3 indicated the possibility of limited (marginal) health literacy, and more than 3 suggested adequate health literacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experiences and perceptions of the intervention processes and outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>A phenomenological qualitative approach using semi-structured 60-minute in-depth interviews will be conducted with 15 intervention participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receive usual care only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health literacy-psychosocial support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receive 6-week sessions of individual health literacy-psychosocial support in addition to usual care. The health literacy-psychosocial support intervention includes 45-minute face-to-face counseling at week 1 and week 6 as well as weekly phone calls (week 2 to week 5.)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health literacy-psychosocial support</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is based upon enhancing patient health literacy-related attributes by (1) addressing the barriers to patients' self-efficacy by working with the patient to minimize the barriers (2) clarifying the patient beliefs about diabetes and diabetes medications, and (3) developing personalized action plans. We will tailor the intervention to each patient, so, the details of the content of each session will depend on the individual's self-efficacy, beliefs in illness and medicines, and health literacy level obtained at baseline. In addition to the 45-minute scheduled sessions, patients will be able to call the clinical pharmacist on the phone during the 6-week session at their discretion, for patient-driven support for self-management of goals and skills.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health literacy-psychosocial support</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  English-speaking men and women 18-80 years old with diabetes

          -  Taking oral diabetes medications and/or insulin

          -  One hemoglobin A1C measure of 8% or greater in the last 18 months

          -  A score less than 25 on the Medication Adherence Rating Scale (MARS-5)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide informed consent

          -  Younger than 18 years old or older than 80 years old

          -  Unable to understand English

          -  Do not take oral diabetes medications and/or insulin

          -  A score equal to 25 on the Medication Adherence Rating Scale (MARS-5)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Olayinka Shiyanbola, PhD, BPharm</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>School of Pharmacy, University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Olayinka O Shiyanbola, PhD, BPharm</last_name>
    <phone>6088902091</phone>
    <email>Olayinka.Shiyanbola@wisc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>William S. Middleton Memorial Veterans Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Denise W Pigarelli, PharmD</last_name>
      <phone>608-280-7077</phone>
      <email>Denise.walbrandt-pigarelli@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farmer KC. Methods for measuring and monitoring medication regimen adherence in clinical trials and clinical practice. Clin Ther. 1999 Jun;21(6):1074-90; discussion 1073. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10440628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keogh KM, Smith SM, White P, McGilloway S, Kelly A, Gibney J, O'Dowd T. Psychological family intervention for poorly controlled type 2 diabetes. Am J Manag Care. 2011 Feb;17(2):105-13.</citation>
    <PMID>21473660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee YJ, Shin SJ, Wang RH, Lin KD, Lee YL, Wang YH. Pathways of empowerment perceptions, health literacy, self-efficacy, and self-care behaviors to glycemic control in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Patient Educ Couns. 2016 Feb;99(2):287-94. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2015.08.021. Epub 2015 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>26341940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Unni E, Shiyanbola OO, Farris KB. Change in Medication Adherence and Beliefs in Medicines Over Time in Older Adults. Glob J Health Sci. 2015 Sep 1;8(5):39-47. doi: 10.5539/gjhs.v8n5p39.</citation>
    <PMID>26652095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shiyanbola OO, Farris KB, Chrischilles E. Concern beliefs in medications: changes over time and medication use factors related to a change in beliefs. Res Social Adm Pharm. 2013 Jul-Aug;9(4):446-57. doi: 10.1016/j.sapharm.2012.07.003. Epub 2012 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22999805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Olayinka Shiyanbola</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health literacy</keyword>
  <keyword>Self-efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>Beliefs about diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Beliefs in medicines</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

