<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03406650</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SAKK 06/17</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017‐003565‐10</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03406650</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neoadjuvant and Adjuvant Durvalumab in Combination With Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy in Patients With Operable Urothelial Cancer.</brief_title>
  <acronym>SAKK 06/17</acronym>
  <official_title>Neoadjuvant and Adjuvant Durvalumab in Combination With Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy in Patients With Operable Urothelial Cancer. A Multicenter, Single-arm Phase II Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Swiss Group for Clinical Cancer Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Swiss Group for Clinical Cancer Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main objective is to demonstrate that the addition of neoadjuvant and adjuvant
      immunotherapy with durvalumab, to standard neoadjuvant chemotherapy (with
      cisplatin/gemcitabine) and surgery in urothelial carcinoma could improve event-free survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite optimal surgical management the prognosis for localized muscle invasive urothelial
      cancer (MIUC) is unfavorable with 5-year overall survival of around 45%.

      According to international guidelines the use of cisplatin-based neoadjuvant chemotherapy is
      considered standard of care in all patients with localized MIUC with planned curative local
      treatment.

      However, the benefit of neoadjuvant chemotherapy is limited and there is a clear medical need
      for improvement for this patient population.

      Durvalumab has been tested in a phase I/II open-label study including patients with
      metastatic urothelial cancer (mUC).

      The results demonstrated an overall response rate (RR) of 31% in 42 response-evaluable
      patients. The side effect profile was favorable with most common grade 1/2 AE representing
      fatigue (13%), diarrhea (10%) and decreased appetite (8%). Three patients (4.9%) had
      treatment related grade 3 AE's, no grade 4/5 events were noted.

      The combination of cisplatin/gemcitabine chemotherapy with modern immune-checkpoint
      inhibition has been demonstrated to be feasible with demonstration of favorable
      immunomodulatory effects.

      In view of these data it appears a logical step to apply these novel agents in the curative
      setting of neoadjuvant treatment.

      The expected benefit of combining chemotherapy with durvalumab and to continue durvaluamb
      postoperatively might be twofold:

        -  to increase the response rate in the pre-operative setting and subsequently to increase
           the rate of pathologic complete remission (pT0) and to reduce risk of local recurrence

        -  to evoke durable systemic anti-cancer responses and subsequently to increase disease
           free- and overall survival and furthermore to induce antitumor immune response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>event-free survival (EFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years after treatment start</time_frame>
    <description>Event-free survival is defined as the time from treatment start until one of the following events, whichever comes first:
Progression during neoadjuvant treatment leading to inoperability
Recurrence of locoregional disease after surgery
Appearance of metastases at any localization
Death Patients not experiencing an event will be censored at the date of the last available assessment before initiation of a subsequent treatment, if any.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival (EFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at the occurrence of the event or latest 5 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Event-free survival is defined as the time from treatment start until one of the following events, whichever comes first:
Progression during neoadjuvant treatment leading to inoperability
Recurrence of locoregional disease after surgery
Appearance of metastases at any localization
Death Patients not experiencing an event will be censored at the date of the last available assessment before initiation of a subsequent treatment, if any.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence-free survival (RFS) after R0 resection</measure>
    <time_frame>at recurrence or latest 5 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>RFS after R0 resection is defined as the time from surgery until one of the following events, whichever comes first:
Recurrence of locoregional disease
Appearance of metastases at any localization
Death Patients not experiencing an event will be censored at the date of the last available assessment before initiation of a subsequent treatment, if any.
This endpoint will only be calculated for patients in the R0 resection set.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at death or latest 5 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from treatment start until death from any cause. Patients not experiencing an event will be censored at the last date they were known to be alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of resection</measure>
    <time_frame>after surgery or the latest 20 weeks after registration</time_frame>
    <description>The quality of resection will be assessed in the following way:
Complete resection (R0) defined as free resection margins proved microscopically
Completeness of the lymphadenectomy and surgery using the photo documentation and histopathology
Postoperative complications will be assessed using the Clavien-Dindo classification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological complete response rate (ypT0)</measure>
    <time_frame>after surgery or the latest 20 weeks after registration</time_frame>
    <description>Pathological complete response (ypT0) is defined as no residual tumor in the surgical specimen. The proportion of patients with ypT0 will be calculated for patients in the resected patients set.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological response rate (PaR) defined by pathological downstaging to ≤ypT1N0M0</measure>
    <time_frame>after surgery or the latest 20 weeks after registration</time_frame>
    <description>Pathological response (PaR) is defined as pathological downstaging to ≤ ypT1N0M0. The proportion of patients with PaR will be calculated for patients in the resected patients set.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>after recurrence or latest 5 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Pattern of recurrence is defined as location of first tumor recurrence. Patterns can be locoregional or distant or any combination of these patterns.
Patients with secondary malignancies or patients with no recurrence will not be taken into consideration for this endpoint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>after treatment end or the latest 73 weeks after registration</time_frame>
    <description>The following feasibility criteria will be assessed:
completion of 4 cycles of neoadjuvant chemotherapy
completion of 4 cycles of neoadjuvant durvalumab treatment
timely admission to and completion of planned surgery
timely initiation and completion of 10 cycles of adjuvant durvalumab treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>within treatment start and 90 days after last trial treatment and resolution of all related AEs thereafter (at the latest 5 years after surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>All AEs will be assessed according to NCI CTCAE v4.03</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">61</enrollment>
  <condition>Urothelial Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Durvalumab in combination with standard therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combination of standard therapy consisting (4 cycles cisplatin/ gemcitabin followed by surgery) with 4 cycles of neoadjuvant durvalumab and 10 cycles of adjuvant durvalumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neoadjuvant and adjuvant durvalumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Neoadjuvant durvalumab 1500 mg q3w for 4 cycles Adjuvant durvalumab 1500 mg q4w for 10 cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>Durvalumab in combination with standard therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MEDI4736</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent according to ICH/GCP regulations before registration and
             prior to any trial specific procedures

          -  Histologically proven urothelial cell carcinoma of the bladder, urethra or upper
             urinary tract (T2, T3, or T4a and ≤ N1 (defined as a solitary lymph node ≤ 2 cm in the
             greatest dimension), M0) and be considered suitable for curative multimodality
             treatment including surgery by a multidisciplinary tumor board. Cytological diagnosis
             is only allowed for upper tract urothelial carcinoma. In these cases tumor has to be
             documented by urography

          -  All histological subtypes eligible if urothelial carcinoma predominant (exception:
             small cell component)

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  WHO performance status 0-1

          -  Bone marrow function: hemoglobin ≥ 90 g/L, neutrophil count ≥ 1.5 x 109/L, platelet
             count ≥ 100 x 109/L

          -  Hepatic function: bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN (except for patients with Gilbert's disease ≤
             3.0 x ULN), AST ≤ 2.5 x ULN and ALT ≤ 2.5 x ULN, alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 x ULN

          -  Renal function: estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &gt; 50 mL/min/1.73m²,
             according to CKD-EPI formula

          -  Cardiac function: Left ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) ≥ 50% as determined by
             echocardiography (ECHO)

          -  Women with child-bearing potential are using effective contraception (for details of
             definition see 9.9), are not pregnant or lactating and agree not to become pregnant
             during trial treatment and during 90 days thereafter. A negative pregnancy test before
             inclusion into the trial is required for all women with child-bearing potential

          -  Men agree not to father a child during trial treatment and during 90 days thereafter

          -  Body weight &gt; 30kg.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any pathological evidence of small-cell carcinoma component

          -  Presence of any distant metastasis

          -  History of hematologic or primary solid tumor malignancy, unless in remission for at
             least 3 years after registration, with the exception of adequately treated cervical
             carcinoma in situ, localized non-melanoma skin cancer or low risk localized prostate
             cancer (T1-T2a, Gleason &lt;7, PSA &lt;10ng/ml)

          -  Any previous treatment with a PD-1 or PD-L1 inhibitor, including durvalumab

          -  Concurrent treatment with prednisone (or equivalent); except for the prophylactic
             medication before chemotherapy, treatment of acute hypersensitivity reactions or
             chronic treatment (initiated &gt; 6 months prior to registration) at low dose (≤ 10
             mg/day of prednisone or an equivalent corticosteroid)

          -  Concurrent treatment with other experimental drugs or other anticancer therapy,
             treatment in a clinical trial within 28 days prior to registration

          -  Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 28 days prior to
             registration, with the exception of intranasal and inhaled corticosteroids or systemic
             corticosteroids

          -  Major surgical procedure within 28 days prior to registration

          -  Preexisting peripheral neuropathy (&gt; grade 1)

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus

          -  Active or prior documented autoimmune or inflammatory disorders (including
             inflammatory bowel disease [e.g., colitis or Crohn's disease], diverticulitis [with
             the exception of diverticulosis], systemic lupus erythematosus, sarcoidosis syndrome,
             or Wegener syndrome [granulomatosis with polyangiitis, Graves' disease, rheumatoid
             arthritis, hypophysitis, uveitis, etc]). The following are exceptions to this
             criterion:

               -  Patients with vitiligo or alopecia

               -  Patients with hypothyroidism (e.g., following Hashimoto syndrome) stable on
                  hormone replacement

               -  Any chronic skin condition that does not require systemic therapy

               -  Patients without active disease in the last 5 years may be included but only
                  after consultation with the coordinating investigator

               -  Patients with celiac disease controlled by diet alone

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or active chronic Hepatitis C or
             Hepatitis B Virus infection or any uncontrolled active systemic infection requiring
             intravenous (iv) antimicrobial treatment

          -  History of allogeneic organ transplant

          -  Receipt of live attenuated vaccine within 30 days prior to registration. Note:
             Patients, if enrolled, should not receive live vaccine during trial treatment and up
             to 30 days after the last dose

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness, including but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, interstitial lung disease, serious chronic
             gastrointestinal conditions associated with diarrhea, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirement, substantially increase
             risk of incurring AEs or compromise the ability of the patient to give written
             informed consent

          -  Any concurrent drug contraindicated for blocking the effect of durvalumab; this
             includes systemic corticosteroids, methotrexate, azathioprine, and tumor necrosis
             factor (TNF)-α blockers. Any concurrent drug contraindicated for use with the other
             trial drugs according to the locally approved product information

          -  Known hypersensitivity to cisplatin, gemcitabine or durvalumab or to any excipient

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding or male or female patients of
             reproductive potential who are not willing to employ effective birth control from
             screening to 90 days after the last dose of durvalumab.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Cathomas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Kantonsspital Graubünden, Chur</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martina Schneider, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+41 31 389 91 91</phone>
    <email>trials@sakk.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>PD Dr. Richard Cathomas</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kantonspital Aarau</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarau</city>
        <zip>CH-5001</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tobias Wehrhahn, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 62 838 59 27</phone>
      <email>tobias.wehrhahn@ksa.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tobias Wehrhahn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kantonsspital Baden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baden</city>
        <zip>CH-5404</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andreas Erdmann, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 56 486 27 62</phone>
      <email>andreas.erdmann@ksb.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andreas Erdmann, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitaetsspital Basel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <zip>4031</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sacha Rothschild, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 61 265 25 25</phone>
      <email>sacha.rothschild@usb.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sacha Rothschild, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inselspital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roland Seiler, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 31 632 20 45</phone>
      <email>roland.seiler@insel.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roland Seiler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kantonsspital Graubünden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chur</city>
        <zip>7000</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Cathomas, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 81 256 61 11</phone>
      <email>Richard.Cathomas@ksgr.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Cathomas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois CHUV</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lausanne</city>
        <zip>CH-1011</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dominik Berthold, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 21 314 80 83</phone>
      <email>Dominik.Berthold@chuv.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dominik Berthold, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Luzerner Kantonsspital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Luzern</city>
        <zip>6000</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christian Riklin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 41 205 58 73</phone>
      <email>christian.riklin@luks.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian Riklin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kantonsspital St. Gallen</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Gallen</city>
        <zip>CH-9007</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sabine Schmid, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 71 494 11 11</phone>
      <email>sabine.schmid@kssg.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sabine Schmid, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kantonsspital Winterthur</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winterthur</city>
        <zip>8401</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Miklos Pless, Prof</last_name>
      <phone>+41 52 266 36 40</phone>
      <email>miklos.pless@ksw.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miklos Pless, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OnkoZentrum Zürich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zürich</city>
        <zip>8038</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ulf Petrausch, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 43 344 33 33</phone>
      <email>ulf.petrausch@ozh.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ulf Petrausch, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>muscle invasive urothelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>durvalumab</keyword>
  <keyword>MEDI4736</keyword>
  <keyword>adjuvant</keyword>
  <keyword>neoadjuvant</keyword>
  <keyword>radical cystectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>bladder</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

