<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00200941</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAPSS-178</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00200941</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Study of Topiramate to Treat Restless Legs Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel Group Study to Determine the Effacy and Safety of Topiramate in Subjects With Restless Legs Syndrome (RLS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Neurocare</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ortho-McNeil Pharmaceutical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Neurocare</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is intended to determine whether topiramate is an efficacious and safe treatment
      for restless legs syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Benzodiazepines, levo-dopa/carbidopa, dopamine agonists, anticonvulsants, and opioids have
      been used with variable success, to treat RLS. Often, RLS patients treated with a
      benzodiazepine, over the course of several months, develop tolerance to the medication. Also,
      benzodiazepines can cause confusion or daytime sleepiness and may be addictive. Patients may
      also develop tolerance to levo-dopa/carbidopa treatment. Because of the short half-life,
      symptoms may be suppressed for only the first part of the sleep period and then recur later
      during the night. Rebound has been reported. Worse yet, augmentation, the occurrence of RLS
      symptoms, often more severe than before treatment began, earlier in the day, may occur in up
      to 80% of RLS patients treated with levod-dopa/carbidopa. Dopamine agonists, including
      pergolide, pramipexole, and ropinirole, are effective for some patients but not for others.
      Common side effects of these drugs include coryza, hypotension, and rash. Of the
      anticonvulsants, preliminary reports suggest that gabapentin, carbamazepine, and divalproex
      can suppress RLS symptoms in some patients, especially those with mild RLS. Side effects
      include sleepiness, ataxia, and weight gain. Opioid treatment for RLS has been described as
      effective but, aside from the stigma of taking controlled substances regularly, side effects
      may include nausea, sedation, constipation, and dysequilibrium. Iron supplementation is
      therapeutic in some patients with iron deficiency and RLS.

      Preliminary anecdotal data suggest that topiramate reduces RLS symptoms. Topiramate has
      several potential mechanisms of action including enhancement of GABA-mediated inhibition,
      which may account for the observed benefit in patients with RLS.

      Topiramate may be a better alternative than the currently available treatments to suppress
      RLS symptoms. Like gabapentin, it offers the possibility of decreasing RLS symptoms while
      also diminishing pain, especially in those patients who have limb pain from neuropathy,
      radiculopathy, or other causes. Unlike gabapentin, topiramate may help overweight patients
      with RLS lose weight, if anedotal reports on weight reduction with the medication are
      correct.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Educational/Counseling/Training</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The average number of periodic leg movements during three consecutive nights of actigraphy beginning at the end of the double blind phase</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of time in bed without leg movements during the three consecutive nights of actigraphy beginning at the end of the double blind phase</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SF-36 at the last visit of the double blind phase</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on the RLS Rating Scale (modified) questionnaire at the last visit of the double blind phase</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Periodic leg movements during sleep and wakefulness during the PSG recorded at the end of the double blind phase</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSG measures including periodic leg movement arousal index, latency until sustained sleep, sleep efficacy, and wake after sleep onset</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep diaries at the last double-blind visit</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epworth sleepiness scale at the last double-blind visit</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>44</enrollment>
  <condition>Restless Legs Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Topiramate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The symptoms of each subject must meet the diagnostic criteria of the International
             RLS Study Group

          -  More than five periodic leg movements per hour recorded during baseline
             polysomnography (PSG)

          -  Each subject must discontinue all treatments for RLS and agreed not to take other RLS
             treatments during the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically unstable medical problems

          -  History of nephrolithiasis

          -  Progressive neurologic disease

          -  Inadequate therapeutic response from two previous treatment regimens for RLS

          -  Subjects unable to discontinue medications known to cause or suppress RLS

          -  Subjects with sleep apnea syndrome

          -  Subjects consuming daily more than three beverages containing caffeine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael P Biber, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Neurocare</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neurocare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newton</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02459</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 15, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 15, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Restless Legs Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Topiramate</keyword>
  <keyword>Actigraphy</keyword>
  <keyword>Polysomnography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychomotor Agitation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Restless Legs Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Topiramate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

