<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00206765</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>082-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00206765</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risperidone vs. Paroxetine for Panic Attacks</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-blind Trial of Risperidone vs. Paroxetine for Treatment of Panic Attacks</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beth Israel Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beth Israel Medical Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We are comparing the efficacy of Risperidone versus Paroxetine in the treatment of panic
      symptoms. The study hypothesis is that Risperidone will be a superior medicine for treating
      panic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale

      Risperidone is an atypical antipsychotic drug that acts as an antagonist at 5-HT2A/2C and D2
      receptors (Chouignard et al, 1993; Marder &amp; Meibach, 1994). In its serotonergic activity,
      risperidone resembles both the atypical antidepressant and 5HT2-antagonist nefazodone (Bakish
      et al, 1993) and a 5HT2-antagonist ritanserine (Lima &amp; Moncrieff, 2000; Preskorn 1995).
      Nefazodone treats anxiety symptoms and induces less agitation than other reuptake blockers
      (Fawcett et al, 1995) while ritanserin shows effectiveness in treatment of dysthymia in
      clinical trials. Moreover, risperidone increases release of dopamine and norepinephrine in
      the prefrontal cortex (Zhang et al, 2000), an activity that in other pharmacological agents
      is associated with their antidepressant, anxiolytic, and antipanic properties (Thase, 2002).

      Therefore, risperidone has a potential to be effective for treatment of either Generalized
      Anxiety Disorder, or Panic Disorder, or Major Depressive Disorder with Panic Attacks (DSM-IV,
      1994) as a single agent. Moreover, due to its D2 and 5-HT2A/2C antagonism and proven
      antipsychotic efficacy, the drug could be uniquely effective for severe panic attacks with
      psychotic features or para-psychotic features (Galynker et al, 1996). Consistent with this
      supposition, Marder et al (1997) reported that in patients with schizophrenia, risperidone
      produced significantly greater improvements than haloperidol in PANSS scores measuring
      anxiety and depression.

      Our clinical experience with over 50 patients with panic attacks showed that low dose
      risperidone, similar to lorazepam, reduced or eliminated anxiety and panic, often after the
      first dose. Risperidone was most effective for patients experiencing obsessive, intrusive,
      anxiety-inducing thoughts. In contrast to lorazepam, risperidone treatment did not result in
      building of tolerance to the drug or disinhibition. We did not observe extrapyramidal side
      effects in patients treated with risperidone for panic attacks. Thus, our preliminary
      clinical data indicate that due to its efficacy, quick onset of action, absence of addictive
      potential, and lack of side effects, risperidone could be superior to both benzodiazepines
      and SSRIs for treatment of panic attacks, particularly for severe panic attacks. Moreover,
      risperidone has a potential to be the first line drug for treatment of these symptoms.

      Consequently, at present, a clinical study of risperidone for treatment of panic attacks is
      indicated and is of great potential value. We are therefore proposing an exploratory open
      label single-blind trial of risperidone in vs. paroxetine for treatment of panic attacks.

      Hypothesis/Objectives

      Objective One. To compare the efficacy of risperidone to that of paroxetine in treatment of
      panic attacks in patients with Panic Disorder and with Major Depressive Disorder with Panic
      attacks.

      Hypothesis One: Risperidone and will be more efficacious in treatment of panic symptoms in
      both patient groups. Some patients will improve within 24 hrs.

      Objective Two. To compare the side effect profile of risperidone vs. paroxetine in treatment
      of panic attacks.

      Hypothesis Two: Risperidone, compared to paroxetine, will cause less sexual side effects,
      anxiety, and restlessness. There will be no difference in extrapyramidal side effects between
      the paroxetine and the risperidone groups.

      Objective Three. To compare response rates of risperidone vs. paroxetine in treatment of
      panic attacks.

      Hypothesis Three: Patients with panic attacks will respond significantly faster to
      risperidone that to paroxetine.

      Objective Four. To examine demographic and clinical predictors of robust response to
      risperidone treatment using appropriate statistical analysis of individual scales items and
      treatment response rates.

      Hypothesis Four: The subgroup patients with panic attacks who will have high scores on items
      reflecting somatic anxiety, and ruminative intrusive thinking, and those with nocturnal panic
      attacks will show better response to risperidone therapy than patients with low scores on
      those items.

      If study hypotheses are confirmed, future research could include a randomized, double blind
      fixed dose study of risperidone as the sole agent for treatment of panic disorder and Phase
      IV trials aimed to determine the effectiveness of 0.125 mg and 0.0675 mg dose of risperidone
      for treatment of anxiety and panic attacks.

      Study Population

      The patient population will consist of psychiatric outpatients who meet criteria for the
      DSM-IV diagnosis of Major Depressive Disorder with Panic Attacks or Panic Disorder. The
      subjects will be recruited from the Center for Treatment of Affective Disorders and from the
      Anxiety and Trauma Center in the Department of Psychiatry at the Beth Israel Medical center
      that provide care to 900 patients. At present, the patient ethnic and racial mix is 50%
      Hispanic, 15% African American, 32.5% Caucasian and 2.5% Asian. The gender distribution is
      approximately 33% male and 67 % female. The outpatient payer mix is 20 % Medicare, 74 %
      Medicaid and 6% combined. Of those patients, approximately 40% (360) manifest panic attacks.
      Based on our previous experience with recruitment for research studies, we expect that 10-12%
      of patients (36-42) meeting diagnostic criteria will also meet the inclusion and exclusion
      criteria, will sign the inform consent and will participate in the study. We expect to
      recruit 40 patients per year and to complete the study in 3 years.

      Inclusion Criteria

        1. Males and females, ages 21-55.

        2. Ability to sign an informed consent

        3. Diagnosis of Panic Disorder, or MDD with Panic attacks, single episode, recurrent, or
           chronic

        4. HAM-A score &gt;17

      Exclusion Criteria

        1. Alcohol or substance abuse within the last 6 months

        2. Current diagnosis of Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder

        3. Current diagnosis of Schizophrenia, Schizoaffective Disorder, or Bipolar Mood Disorder

        4. Use of antipsychotic medications over the two months preceding enrollment in the study

        5. Changes in antidepressant or mood stabilizer dosing over the two months preceding
           enrollment in the study

        6. Previous adverse reaction to risperidone or paroxetine.

      Study Design and Drug Regimens

      The study will be an 8-week parallel comparison (with a blinded rater) of risperidone and
      paroxetine for treatment of three groups of patients with panic attacks. Each group will
      consist of 30 subjects.

      After signing an informed consent, the subjects will be randomly assigned in the open manner
      to treatment with risperidone or paroxetine alone.

      Arm 1: Treatment with risperidone will be flexible-dose and will be initiated at 0.25 mg po
      qhs. For the subjects who did not achieve a remission of panic symptoms, the dose will be
      increased to 0.5 mg po qhs on day 3. For subjects who experienced morning sedation, the dose
      will be decreased to 0.125-mg po qhs on day 3.

      Arm 2: Treatment with Paroxetine will be flexible-dose and will be initiated at 10-mg po qhs.
      For subjects who experienced morning sedation, the dose will be decreased to 5-mg po qhs on
      day 3. For the subjects who did not achieve a remission of panic symptoms, the dose will be
      increased to 20-mg po qhs. For the subjects who did not achieve a remission of panic
      symptoms, the dose will be increased to 40-mg po qhs as needed.

      Arm 3: Treatment with Paroxetine on a fixed dose schedule will be initiated at 10 mg po qhs
      on day 1. On day 3 it will be increased to 20 mg po qhs. On day 7 it will be increased to 30
      mg po qhs. Most patients respond to an average therapeutic dose of 30 mg of paroxetine.. This
      will ensure that a subgroup of subjects will receive optimum therapeutic dose of Paroxetine
      and also aid to titrate Paroxetine equivalent dose of Risperidone.

      Patients randomized on any of the above arms, and not responding or having side effects will
      be taken off the study and referred for regular psychiatric treatment.

      The subjects receiving fixed dose antidepressants or mood stabilizers prior to their
      enrollment in the study will be continued on these medications throughout the study. No dose
      adjustment of antidepressants or mood stabilizers will be allowed. At the end of study,
      participants can choose to continue their study medications under the care of one of study
      physicians or one of the other psychiatrists at Psychiatric outpatients service for adults
      Beth Israel Medical Center 16 Street at First Avenue, 2 Bernstein. Those wishing to stop the
      study medications at the end of the study will be able to do so under the supervision of one
      of the study physicians. Paroxetine will be tapered over a two-week period to avoid SSRI
      withdrawal. Risperidone will be stopped abruptly since no withdrawal symptoms have been
      reported in the literature making risperidone taper unnecessary.

      Assessments to evaluate mood improvement will be performed by a rater blinded to medication
      status on a daily basis for the first three days and every other day for the first two weeks.
      The assessments (please see Appendix 1 for the assessment battery) will continue weekly for
      the rest of the study.

      All study participants' will provided with psychiatric treatment, free of charge, at our
      clinic, for one month following the end of the study. At the end of one-month period, we will
      assist you in finding further psychiatric care. Travel expenses will be reimbursed for the
      subjects participating in the study.

      Data Analysis

      We will calculate Pearson Product Moment correlation coefficients (r) for each of the
      treatment outcome variable groups. This will enable us to determine the degree of association
      between treatment and outcome. More importantly, we can interpret (r) with the Binomial
      Effect Size Display (BESD) (Rosenthal, 1991). The BESD will enable us to estimate a
      clinically meaningful improvement rate and to estimate the number of people that would
      improve as a result of treatment.

      Power Analysis and Precision Analysis

      As stated above, our measure of effect size will be the Pearson Product Moment correlation
      coefficient (r). For this study we chose an effect size of r = .50 as the smallest effect
      size that would be clinically meaningful, and then calculated that we would need a sample
      size of 26, to obtain power of 81%, and a 95.0% confidence interval (r = .13 to r = .75) that
      would not include zero. (Rosenthal, 1991).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder With Panic Attacks</condition>
  <condition>Panic Disorder</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Risperidone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paroxetine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females, ages 21-55.

          -  Ability to sign an informed consent

          -  Diagnosis of Panic Disorder, or MDD with Panic attacks, single episode, recurrent, or
             chronic

          -  HAM-A score &gt;17

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Alcohol or substance abuse within the last 6 months

          -  Current diagnosis of Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder

          -  Current diagnosis of Schizophrenia, Schizoaffective Disorder, or Bipolar Mood Disorder

          -  Use of antipsychotic medications over the two months preceding enrollment in the study

          -  Changes in antidepressant or mood stabilizer dosing over the two months preceding
             enrollment in the study

          -  Previous adverse reaction to risperidone or paroxetine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Igor Galynker, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beth Israel Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 19, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 19, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 22, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>panic</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Panic Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Risperidone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paroxetine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

