<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00206492</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H 13546</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00206492</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of ZD1839 (Iressa) and Tamoxifen in Breast Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Neoadjuvant Phase II Trial of ZD1839 (Iressa) and Tamoxifen in Inoperable Locally Advanced HER2-Overexpressing, ER-Positive Breast Cancer Patients: Biologic Correlative Study (AZ #1839US/0303)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor Breast Care Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor Breast Care Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The researchers want to learn whether ZD1839 can improve the activity of tamoxifen, a drug
      that participants will receive for the treatment of the type of breast cancer being studied.
      Tamoxifen medicine is part of the standard treatment for the type of breast cancer being
      studied. It is approved for the treatment of this problem. In order to help the researchers
      understand how the cancer responds to these medicines, the researchers will take a small
      tissue sample (biopsy) of the breast cancer before beginning treatment and after two weeks of
      treatment, at 6 weeks and when surgery is done as part of treatment for the cancer. If
      participants do not respond to treatment, another biopsy will be done to see why the
      participants did not respond. These samples will also be collected to look at different
      characteristics of the cancer. The researchers cannot and do not guarantee that participants
      will benefit if they take part in this study
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) is expressed or over-expressed in many human solid
      tumors and plays an important role in progression to invasion and metastases. The EGFR
      tyrosine kinase is activated by binding of a variety of ligands to the external domain.
      Autophosphorylation by the EGFR tyrosine kinase initiates a signaling cascade that feeds
      downstream cell cycle control machinery regulating cell proliferation, and these reactions
      are a major component in growth factor-induced proliferation of cancer cells.

      The Erb-B (HER) receptor family consists of four transmembrane tyrosine kinases:
      Erb-B1-epithermal growth factor receptor (EGFR, HER1), Erb-B2/neu (HER2), Erb-B3 (HER3), and
      Erb-B4 (HER4). The ectodomain of Erb-B1, Erb-B3, and Erb-B4 interacts with a specific set of
      ligand, whereas no ligand has been identified thus far for the Erb-B2 receptor. Nonetheless,
      Erb-B2 can be activated by any of the other ligand-activated Erb-B coreceptors. Upon ligand
      binding to the active domain of Erb-B1, Erb-B3, or Erb-B4, these receptors preferentially
      recruit Erb-B2 into a heterodimeric complex in which the Erb-B2 kinase can modulate receptor
      internalization and prolong signal transduction.

      Data are now emerging that Erb-B2 modulates cellular p27 and cyclin D1 protein levels through
      both Ras/MAP kinase and PI3K/Akt signaling. Reversible interruption of Erb-B2 function by
      trastuzumab (Herceptin) has been shown to inhibit MAPk and reduce MAPk-mediated transcription
      through cyclin D1. In addition, the signaling molecule Akt is important in the cell survival
      pathway. Akt inhibits apoptosis and is present in the PI3 kinase pathway, which is activated
      by the EGF family and the IGF family. Several biologic arguments support the use of EGR
      inhibitors to block HER2 signaling. In HER2-overexpressing cell lines, the HER2 receptor is
      constitutively phosphorylated. This suggests that HER2 may be transactivated through
      ligand-stimulated EGFR, also present in tumor cells. In addition, overexpression of HER2
      enhances the binding of EGFR ligands to the receptor and potentiates EGFR signaling. HER2
      inactivation has been shown to impair EGFR- mediated transformation, and conversely EGFR
      blocking antibodies can augment the growth inhibitory effect of antiHER2 antibodies in cells
      with high levels of HER2. Taken together, these data suggest that EGFR/HER2 crosstalk is
      present in a subset of human tumors and that interruption of EGFR may reduce HER2 signaling.
      Cell cycle progression is regulated predominantly by cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs), which
      in turn are controlled by a family of CDK inhibitory proteins that include P27KIP1 and
      P21CIP1-WAF1. Pathways involving CDK inhibitors are commonly destructive in cancer cells.
      ZD1839 is an orally active, selective EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor that blocks signal
      transduction pathways implicated in cancer cell proliferation, survival, and other
      host-dependent processes promoting cancer growth.

      In preclinical studies, ZD1839 causes tumor growth delay in a range of cancer cell lines and
      xenografts, and tumor regression has been observed at higher doses. ZD1839 was also shown to
      inhibit proliferation in DCIS together with significantly increased apoptosis in these
      tissues. Data from these different cell lines and xenografts suggest that ZD1839 may act via
      dose-dependent growth inhibition and by increasing apoptosis, and may even potentiate the
      activity of cytotoxic chemotherapy.

      In one phase II multicenter study, 63 women with metastatic breast cancer who could have had
      any number of previous chemotherapy or hormonal regimens were treated with an oral daily dose
      of 500 mg of ZD1839 until disease progression, intolerable toxicity, or withdrawal of
      consent. Dosage reduction to 250 mg daily was allowed for toxicity. The primary end point was
      clinical benefit rate (complete response + partial response [modified ICC/WHO criteria] +
      stable disease) at 6 months. There was 1 partial response and 2 patients with stable disease
      for more than 4 months (4 months in 1 patient and 7+ months in the other), for a total of
      4.8% clinical benefit. An additional 4 patients had stable disease lasting 1 to 2 months, and
      another 2 patients had stable disease lasting 1 month, resulting in an overall 14.3% partial
      response or stable disease in this heavily pre-treated population; 15% were on treatment for
      4 to 8+ months, and 2 patients stayed on treatment, despite progression, because of
      significant bone pain palliation.

      Preliminary efficacy and toxicity data from another phase II trial of 22 ER-positive or
      ER-negative patients were reported at the same conference. In that study, patients could have
      had 1 previous chemotherapy regimen or were experiencing disease progression while on
      tamoxifen and were given 500 mg of ZD1839 daily. Two patients had a partial response and 10
      had stable disease at 4 weeks. In both trials the toxicity profile was identical to that seen
      in patient with NSCLC.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    halted by the PI only 3 of 45 subjects were accrued.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cellular response</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>mechanisms of the cellular response, markers predicting response, by investigating whether ZD1839 with or without tamoxifen treatment is associated with altered biomarkers in cells isolated by core needle biopsy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iressa and Tamoxifen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Iressa and Tamoxifen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iressa</intervention_name>
    <description>Iressa</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iressa and Tamoxifen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ZD1839</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tamoxifen</intervention_name>
    <description>Tamoxifen</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iressa and Tamoxifen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients must be female and must have signed an informed consent form.

          2. Primary breast cancers must be human epidermal growth factor receptor (HER2)
             overexpressing (2+ or 3+, or both, as determined by immunohistochemistry [IHC]), and
             estrogen receptor (ER) positive. Primary breast cancers must be of clinical and/or
             radiologic size &gt;4 cm, with or without gross metastatic disease according to the
             International Union against Cancer (UICC) modified World Health Organization (WHO)
             criteria.

          3. Negative serum pregnancy test (bHCG) within 7 days of starting study, if of
             child-bearing potential.

          4. Adequate bone marrow function:

               -  Hematocrit &gt;30%,

               -  total neutrophil count must be &gt;1.5 x 10^9/L, and

               -  platelet count &gt;100 x 10^9/L.

          5. Renal function tests:

               -  creatinine within 1.5 times the institution's upper limit of normal (ULN).

          6. Liver function tests:

               -  Total serum bilirubin within ULN,

               -  liver transaminases within 2.5 x ULN,

               -  alkaline phosphatase within 5 x ULN.

          7. Performance status (WHO scale) &lt;2.

          8. Age &gt; 18 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy or unwillingness to use a reliable contraceptive method in women of
             child-bearing potential.

          2. Women who are lactating or breastfeeding.

          3. Severe underlying chronic illness or disease.

          4. Patients on other investigational drugs while on study will be excluded.

          5. Severe or uncontrolled hypertension, history of congestive heart failure, acute
             myocardial infarction, or severe coronary arterial disease.

          6. No previous or current malignancies at other sites within the preceding 5 years, with
             the exception of adequately treated, cone-biopsied in situ carcinoma of the cervix
             uteri and basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin.

          7. Any evidence of ongoing interstitial lung disease.

          8. Concomitant use of phenytoin, carbamazepine, rifampicin, barbiturates, or St John's
             Wort.

          9. Treatment with a non-approved or investigational drug within 30 days before Day 1 of
             study treatment.

         10. Known severe hypersensitivity to ZD1839 or any of the excipients of this product.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jenny Chang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor Breast Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor Breast Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.breastcenter.tmc.edu</url>
    <description>Web site</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Neoadjuvant</keyword>
  <keyword>HER2</keyword>
  <keyword>Overexpressing</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tamoxifen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gefitinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

