<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00207948</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1K12RR017613-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00207948</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimizing Antiretroviral Therapy in HIV-Infected Children and Adolescents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimizing Antiretroviral Therapy in HIV-Infected Children and Adolescents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This was a feasibility study aimed at elevating protease inhibitors (PI) dosage as a part of
      active antiretroviral therapy (HAART). After the pharmacokinetics for the currently
      prescribed PI were determined,patients with a vIQ&lt;1 were eligible for a 50% dose increase for
      an 8 week time frame after which their vIQ would be reassessed to determine if increasing
      their PI dosage thereby increasing the bioavaiability would reduce their viral load.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although, the use of protease inhibitors (PI) containing highly active antiretroviral therapy
      (HAART) has led to a remarkable improvement in the prognosis and outcome of HIV infection,
      only 45% to 70% of treatment-naïve patients who commence HAART achieve complete virological
      suppression. The emergence of HIV resistance to antiretroviral drugs is one of the main
      obstacles to the successful long-term suppression of HIV replication. Poor adherence and
      unfavorable pharmacokinetics (PK) caused by altered absorption, genetic variations in
      metabolism and drug-drug interactions frequently lead to antiretroviral drug concentrations
      below the inhibitory concentration for 50% of the viral quasispecies (IC50) and loss of viral
      suppression.

      Enzymes of the cytochrome (CYP) P450 (CYP2C19, CYP3A4, CYP3A5) family located in the liver
      and small intestine are responsible for the metabolism of PIs. The absence of expression of
      certain enzymes from this family was recently correlated with a genetic polymorphism, which
      may have a major role in variation of cytochrome P450-mediated drug metabolism. Results of
      these studies suggest significant differences in the distribution of the polymorphism
      associated alleles between ethnic groups, in particular between Caucasians and African
      Americans. Detection of cytochrome P450 variant alleles and more detailed data on their
      allelic frequency in various ethnic groups is critical to assess their impact on PK of
      antiretroviral agents, in particular PIs.

      This research proposal is aimed at the development of a novel multidisciplinary approach to
      optimize HAART in HIV infected children. It is increasingly clear that inter-individual
      variation in drug metabolism and responsiveness has a strong genetic component. The metabolic
      pathways leading to drug clearance, bio-availability, and cellular responses are complex, and
      only beginning to be understood. Key to our understanding of inter-individual responses is
      identification of the genetic polymorphisms that contribute to this variability, the relative
      contribution of different genes/SNPs, and the possible interactions between the corresponding
      protein products or pathways. We propose to develop a dosing regimen of PIs in HIV-infected
      children that takes into account genetic variability in drug metabolism and transport, and
      resistance of the dominant viral strain (as determined by virtual phenotype).

      In order to do so, the protocol address the following Specific Aims:

        -  Specific Aim 1 (completed previously): Determine the prevalence of genetic variations in
           CYP2C19, CYP3A4, CYP3A5, and MDR-1 genes in a cohort of children and adolescents with
           HIV infection.

        -  Specific Aim 2 (completed previously): Evaluate the relationship of this genetic
           variability to the pharmacokinetic parameters (Cmin, Cmax, AUC) and toxicity (graded by
           the Division of AIDS [DAIDS] classification) of protease inhibitors in pediatric
           patients with HIV infection.

        -  Specific Aim 3 (THIS STUDY): Evaluate the impact of dose adjustment of protease
           inhibitors based on pharmacogenetic profile and virtual inhibitory quotient (VIQ) on
           clinical outcome (measured by HIV-RNA viral load and CD4+ cell count changes) and
           toxicity (graded by the DAIDS classification) in pediatric patients with HIV infection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    no measurable response was detected at the 50% increase threshold.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluation of vIQ</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>vIQ would be reassessed to determine if increasing their PI dosage thereby increasing the bioavaiability would reduce their viral load.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Dose Adjustment</arm_group_label>
    <description>To adjust the doses of medications to meet target therapeutic concentrations</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dose adjustment of Kaletra</intervention_name>
    <description>Adjust the dose by up to +50% of reccomended dosa off the drug to meet target therapeutic concentrations</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic Dose Adjustment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lopinavir</other_name>
    <other_name>Ritonavir</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The total number of recruited subjects in a previous the study was 78 with 50 subjects on
        LPV/RTV based ART. Based on PK analysis 4 patients fit inclusion criteria for a dose
        adjustment feasibility pilot (this study)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Evidence of HIV infection confirmed by positive culture or PCR on at least two
             occasions, or a positive ELISA and a confirmatory Western Blot. At least one of these
             tests must be done in an ACTG certified laboratory which is approved to perform the
             assay for protocol testing

          -  Age 4-21 years

          -  Current use of HAART regimen (NRTI or/and NNRTI based) containing a PI

          -  HIV-RNA levels above 1,000 copies/mL (Stage II)

          -  vIQ&lt;1 for Kaletra

          -  Signed informed consent and, if indicated, signed informed assent or waiver of assent.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Grade 3-4 DAIDS defined toxicity

          -  Use of cimetidine (used as the internal standard for the HPLC-MS/MS assay)

          -  Any active opportunistic infection

          -  Any of the following laboratory findings at entry: absolute neutrophil count &lt;750
             cells/mm3; platelet count &lt;75,000 cells/mm3; AST &gt;3 times upper limit of age adjusted
             normal values; ALT &gt;3 times upper limit of age adjusted normal values; serum
             creatinine &gt;1.2mg/dL.

          -  Patients on dual PI regimen (except when second PI is given for boosting) at the time
             of enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Natella Y Rakhmanina, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's National Medical Center, Children's Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rakhmanina N, van den Anker J, Baghdassarian A, Soldin S, Williams K, Neely MN. Population pharmacokinetics of lopinavir predict suboptimal therapeutic concentrations in treatment-experienced human immunodeficiency virus-infected children. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2009 Jun;53(6):2532-8. doi: 10.1128/AAC.01374-08. Epub 2009 Mar 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19258274</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Neely MN, Rakhmanina NY. Comment on: Pharmacokinetics and 48 week efficacy of low-dose lopinavir/ritonavir in HIV-infected children. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2010 Apr;65(4):808-9; author reply 809-10. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkp489. Epub 2010 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>20086000</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rakhmanina NY, Neely MN, Van Schaik RH, Gordish-Dressman HA, Williams KD, Soldin SJ, van den Anker JN. CYP3A5, ABCB1, and SLCO1B1 polymorphisms and pharmacokinetics and virologic outcome of lopinavir/ritonavir in HIV-infected children. Ther Drug Monit. 2011 Aug;33(4):417-24. doi: 10.1097/FTD.0b013e318225384f.</citation>
    <PMID>21743379</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 3, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 3, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Natella Rakhmanina</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Human Immunodeficiency Virus</keyword>
  <keyword>Protease Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Genes, MDR1, Cytochrome P-450 enzymes</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatrics</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Experienced</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

