<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00203866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12403B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00203866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of G250 Peptide and IL-2 Following Surgical Resection of Locally Advanced/Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Pilot Phase II Trial of Adjuvant Immunization With G250 Peptide andThree Different Dose Levels of IL-2 Following Surgical Resection of Locally Advanced or Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the experimental vaccine G250 with or
      without IL-2 can produce an immune response in patients with renal cell carcinoma who have
      had all their cancer removed by surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Renal cell carcinoma is a chemotherapy and radiotherapy resistant neoplasm that has a poor
      prognosis. Immunotherapy with the biologic agent IL-2 consistently produces a response rate
      of 10-15 %. Currently, for patients with locally advanced disease or patients with solitary
      metastases, the only treatment modality with a curative potential is surgical resection.
      There is presently no approved agent for use as adjuvant therapy after surgical resection to
      decrease the risk of recurrence. Peptide-based vaccine approaches offer an attractive
      treatment option.

      The high prevalence of G250 in RCC, the definition of an HLA-A2-restricted epitope (the most
      common HLA type), and its immunogenicity makes it the most attractive candidate for
      peptide-based vaccine approaches in RCC therapy. The promising preclinical and clinical
      evidence provides the rationale for the use of IL-2 to potentiate the antitumor effects of
      cancer vaccines.

      There is presently no conclusive data on the best dose of IL-2 to use as an adjuvant to
      cancer vaccines. One paradoxical finding in preclinical and clinical trials is that despite
      the enhancement in the antitumor effects of cancer vaccines, the number of antigen-specific
      CTL is not increased when IL-2 is given with a cancer vaccine 35]. In contrast, patients
      treated with peptide vaccines (without IL-2) in some melanoma trials had evidence of high
      levels of antigen-specific CTL, with no tumor regression observed 36]. Some possible
      explanations include capillary leak from high dose IL-2 resulting in CTL leaving the
      circulation and the possibility that high dose IL-2 decreases efficient T-cell priming. A
      more recent explanation has been proposed through advances in the mechanism of 1-cell
      activation. As their level of activation increases, T-cells become more susceptible to
      apoptosis. This phenomenon is known as activation-induced cell death (AICD) IL-2 may then
      have a role in the amplification and downregulation of the immune response. High dose IL-2
      may help in augmenting the increase in the activation of CTL, but this may lead to increase
      their susceptibility to AJCD. The evidence in animal models that low doses of IL-2 were
      sufficient in increasing the potency of DC-based immunizations provides the rational for our
      study.

      In our current study, the lowest dose of IL-2 (1 x 106 IU) is similar to the doses used by
      Yee et al. in their adoptive I cell therapy. This dose has been shown to expand and maintain
      CTLs in both preclinical and clinical models. The highest dose (11 x 106 IU) was chosen based
      on the expected toxicities from higher doses of IL-2 and our experience with this dose as a
      single agent in RCC.

      Our hypothesis is that immunization with G250/Montanide/GM-CSF plus IL-2 can lead to an
      expansion of G250-specific CTL and result in killing of 0250 expressing micrometastatic RCC.
      We propose a dose finding study of escalating low doses of IL 2 (subcutaneous), since no
      prior study has specifically evaluated the use of low dose IL-2 as a cytokine adjuvant and
      attempted to establish a correlation between dose and immunolgic response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study completed
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether immunization with G250 peptide/Montanide/GM-CSF plus IL-2 elicits a specific CTL response as assessed by ELISPOT.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To explore differences in G250-specific CTL response as a function of IL-2 dose.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>G250 peptide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IL-2</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must express HLA-A2

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically proven renal cell carcinoma that
             expresses G250 by IHC

          -  Patients must have completely resected disease without any evidence of residual local
             or metastatic disease

          -  Patients with resected locally advanced disease

          -  Patients with metastatic disease(including synchronous metastatic site)

          -  Patients with solitary metachronous metastatic disease

          -  Age &gt;/=18 years

          -  ECOG performance status 0-1

          -  Patients must have normal organ and marrow function

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or an experimental (investigational)
             agent prior to starting treatment. Prior biologic therapy (IL-2 or interferon) is
             allowed only if it precedes a curative surgical therapy.

          -  Patients may not have received a previous G250 vaccine.

          -  Patients with residual metastatic disease following surgical resection are excluded
             from this clinical trial.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to G250, Montanide ISA-5 1, OM-CSF, or IL-2.

          -  Patients must not have autoimmune disorders (SLE, Rheumatoid Arthritis), conditions of
             immunosuppression (such as HIV), or treatment with immunosuppressive drugs (including
             oral steroids, continuous use of topical steroids, steroid inhalers). Replacement
             doses of steroids for patients with adrenal insufficiency are allowed.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, active GI bleeding, inflammatory bowel disease or psychiatric
             illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding women

          -  HIV-positive patients

          -  Patients with a currently active second malignancy other than non-melanoma skin cancer
             or carcinoma in situ of the cervix are not to be registered.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Walter Stadler, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 4, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 4, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

