<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00209066</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0422-1998</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98052113</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00209066</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Reduced Heart Rate Variability Associated With Major Depression With Electroconvulsive Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Means to Enhanced Cardiovascular Outcomes: Reduction of Exaggerated Platelet Activity Through Treatment of Depression.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Dana Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate alterations in sympathetic tone in patients with
      major depression with and without ischemic heart disease and then to reevaluate these
      patients after 8 treatments with electroconvulsive therapy(ECT). We expect to support the
      hypothesis that HRV are pathophysiologically associated with the state of major depression.
      We hypothesize the following:

        1. Heart rate variability (HRV) will be decreased prior to treatment of depression in
           comparison to post-treatment measures of HRV.

        2. After 8 treatments with ECT, HRV will be increased under basal conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is considerable evidence that patients with ischemic heart disease (IHD) and concurrent
      major depression have a less favorable prognosis than patients with IHD alone. Indeed, a
      number of recent studies implicate major depression in the pathophysiologic progression of
      cardiovascular disease as an independent risk factor, rather than a reaction to
      cardiovascular illness. This conclusion is supported by multiple recent studies (Anda et al;
      1993; Markowitz and Matthews, 1991; Musselman et al., 1994, 1995).

      Increased sympathetic tone and subsequent diminished heart rate variability secondary to
      elevated circulating levels of catecholamines provides a possible pathophysiologic link
      between IHD and depression. For example, Carney et al (1988) have established the correlation
      of increased heart rate and decreased heart rate variability (HRV) in patients with major
      depression and IHD. Thus it follows that enhancement of sympathetic tone may be important in
      the independent development of IHD and major depression. The interplay among these systems
      remains to be investigated. The present study seeks to determine the relationship between
      major depression and sympathetic tone.

      The primary objective of the Research Protocol is to determine the effects of major
      depressive disorder (MDD) (see Specific Aim 1), and its treatment, on autonomic function (see
      Specific Aim 2). Twenty-five depressed patients with and 25 depressed patients without a
      history of ischemic cardiovascular disease will be recruited to this study.

      To be determined is whether the exaggerated platelet reactivity and diminished HRV exhibited
      by depressed patients are affected by treatment with ECT. Autonomic function in depressed
      patients will be studied longitudinally before and after ECT. Heart rate variability (HRV) in
      depressed patients who exhibit a therapeutic response to ECT and who exhibited diminished HRV
      prior to treatment will support the hypothesis that HRV are pathophysiologically associated
      with the state of major depression. Successful ECT treatment of depressed mood that is not
      associated with normalization of HRV may indicate that: a) HRV is unrelated to Major
      Depressive Disorder, or b) HRV may reflect a pre-existing &quot;trait&quot; phenomena of major
      depressive disorder, or c) directly improve HRV.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 2005</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with major depressive disorder presenting for a course of electroconvulsive
        therapy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will not be accepted into the study if they abuse alcohol or drugs.

        Patients will be excluded from the study if they have had an MI within the past three
        months, unstable crescendo angina or ongoing warfarin treatment

        Patients also will not be accepted into the study if ECT will be harmful to them. These
        patients include:

          1. those who have had a recent MI (&lt;3 months)

          2. those who have an infection of the brain,

          3. those who have a condition in which there is increased intracranial pressure (e.g. a
             brain tumor)

          4. those who cannot tolerate general anesthesia.

        Any patient with a current DSM-IV Axis I diagnosis other than major depression will be
        excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dominique L Musselman, MD,MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Royster EB, Trimble LM, Cotsonis G, Schmotzer B, Manatunga A, Rushing NN, Pagnoni G, Auyeung SF, Brown AR, Schoenbeck J, Murthy S, McDonald WM, Musselman DL. Changes in heart rate variability of depressed patients after electroconvulsive therapy. Cardiovasc Psychiatry Neurol. 2012;2012:794043. doi: 10.1155/2012/794043. Epub 2012 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22966422</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 17, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 17, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dominique Musselman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Electroconvulsive Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet Activation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

