<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00203879</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11447A</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00203879</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00064168</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of MAGE-3/Melan-A/gp 100/NA17 and rhIL-12 With/Out Low Dose IL-2 in Metastatic Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase II Study of Immunization With MAGE-3/Melan-A/gp 100/NA17 Peptide-Pulsed Autologous PBMC and rhIL-12 With or Without Low Dose IL-2 Inpatients With Metastatic Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose of investigation: Primary hypotheses: Immunization of patients with 4 melanoma
      antigen peptides will induce augmented specific IFN-y-producing CD8+ T cells against all 4
      antigens simultaneously. Immunization with 4 melanoma antigen peptides will increase the
      response rate from 10% to 30%. Administration of low-dose IL-2 following each vaccine will
      result in a greater than 3-fold increase in specific T cells compared to no IL-2.

      Secondary hypotheses: Immunization will clear the blood of detectable circulating melanoma
      cells. Tumors that grow despite induction of melanoma antigen-specific T cells may lack
      expression of antigens, class I MHC, or the TAP peptide transporter, or may fail to show
      increased expression of mRNA for IFN-y or perforin. Tumors that resist vaccination may
      express a different array of genes than those that are susceptible to vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Based on the above preclinical and Phase I results, a logical strategy for a second
      generation melanoma vaccine has emerged. A randomized Phase II study in metastatic melanoma
      patients will be undertaken. Patients first will be HLA-typed; HLA-A2-positive patients will
      be eligible for screening. When feasible, each patient will undergo a tumor biopsy to screen
      for expression of MAGE-3, Melan-A, gplOO, and NAI 7 using RT-PCR and immunohistochemistry, to
      determine whether T cells are present in the lesion, to measure cytokine gene expression by
      RT-PCR, and to perform gene array analysis. In addition, blood cells will be analyzed for
      certain parameters of T cell function.

      Patients will be randomized to cohorts A (no IL-2) or B (with low-dose IL-2). For treatment,
      peripheral blood will be collected and fractionated by density centrifugation to isolate PBMC
      as a source of APC. The PBMC will be divided into four pools, each of which will be incubated
      with one of the following peptides: MAGE-3, Melan-A, gp 100, or Ni 7A. The peptide-loaded
      cells will then be washed and recombined into a single suspension in PBS, and lethally
      irradiated. Approximately 120 x 106 pulsed cells will be injected subcutaneously at a site
      near a lymph node not thought to be involved with tumor. The subcutaneous route has been
      selected for the reasons of safety, efficacy in the preclinical model, and the goal of
      targeting the vaccine to a draining lymph node. rhIL-12 (4 .tg straight dose) will then be
      given subcutaneously adjacent to the vaccine site days 1,3, and 5 of each cycle. This dose
      and schedule was found to be effective in our phase I study. In one-half of the patients
      (cohort B), IL-2 (I MU straight dose) will be administered subcutaneously daily, days 7-18.
      Re-immunization along with rhIL-12 followed by IL-2 (if assigned) will be performed at 3 week
      intervals as in cycle I.

      On day 1 of each cycle, peripheral blood will be collected to measure peptide-specific IFN-y
      production. Before treatment and after every 3 cycles, PBMC will be collected to quantify
      peptide specific CD8 T cells by flow cytometric analysis with peptide/HLA-A2 tetramers, and
      evidence for a molecular response will be assessed by performing RT-PCR. for melanoma
      antigens on peripheral blood samples. In addition, prior to treatment, after the first 3
      cycles, and at the time of going off- study, a tumor biopsy will be performed to assess the
      immune response in the tumor microenvironment, including gene array analysis. It is hoped
      that these studies will uncover the reason for lack of clinical response in patients with
      residual tumors. Clinical response will be assessed as a secondary outcome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary hypothesis is immunization of patients with 4 melanoma antigen peptides will induce augmented specific IFN-.-producing CD8+ T cells against all 4 antigens simultaneously, and to determine the clinical response rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>draft</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">19</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MAGE-3/Melan-A/gp100/NA17 Peptide-pulsed autologous PBMC, rhIL-12 with IL-2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MAGE-3/Melan-A/gp100/NA17 Peptide-pulsed autologous PBMC, rhIL-12 without IL-2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MAGE-3/Melan-A/gp100/NA PBMC, rhIL-12 (drug)</intervention_name>
    <description>draft</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>draft</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MAGE-3/Melan-A/gp100/NA17 Peptide-pulsed autologous PBMC, rhIL-12 with IL-2</intervention_name>
    <description>MAGE-3/Melan-A/gp100/NA17 Peptide-pulsed autologous PBMC, rhIL-12 with IL-2</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically-confirmed melanoma with evidence of metastatic disease, either by
             radiologic or physical examination. In transit metastases are allowed. Biopsy should
             be performed to reconfirm the diagnosis in cases of doubt.

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          -  Karnofsky performance status index &gt;/=70.

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Adequate hematopoietic, renal, and hepatic function

          -  LDH &lt;1.25 x ULN

          -  HLA typing: patient must express HLA-A2.

          -  Tumor biopsy: patient must agree to undergo biopsy of accessible tumor before and
             after therapy, when feasible, to study tumor cell properties and characteristics of
             immune cells.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Significant cardiovascular disease, or cardiac arrhythmia requiring medical
             intervention.

          -  Pregnant or nursing women.

          -  Biological therapy in the 4 weeks prior to the start of dosing.

          -  Prior therapy with a melanoma vaccine containing MAGE-3, Melan-A, gplOO, NA17
             peptides.

          -  Patients with intrinsic immunosuppression, including seropositivity for HIV antibody.
             Patient should be tested if risk factors are identified.

          -  Serious concurrent infection, including active tuberculosis, hepatitis B, or hepatitis
             C.

          -  Concurrent systemic corticosteroids (except physiologic replacement doses) or other
             immunosuppressive drugs (eg. cyclosporin A).

          -  Psychiatric illness that may make compliance to the clinical protocol unmanageable or
             may compromise the ability of the patient to give informed consent.

          -  Active or history of autoimmune disease including but not limited to: rheumatoid
             arthritis (RF-positive with current or recent flare), inflammatory bowel disease,
             systemic lupus erythematosis (clinical evidence with ANA 1:80 or greater), ankylosing
             spondylitis, scleroderma, multiple sclerosis, autoimmune hemolytic anemia, and immune
             thrombocytopenic purpura.

          -  Active gastrointestinal bleeding or uncontrolled peptic ulcer disease. Presence of
             untreated brain metastases. All patients must undergo brain imaging as part of the
             pre-study evaluation. Only patients with no brain metastases, or with brain lesions
             successfully treated by stereotactic radiation or surgical removal without recurrence
             at 28 day follow-up, will be eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Gajewski, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 4, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 4, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>metastatic melanoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

