<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01437293</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>#6141 P50 DA 009236-16</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P50DA009236</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P50DA009236-16</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01437293</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Behavioral and Physiological Effects of Cocaine in Cocaine-dependent Participants Treated With Levodopa in Combination With Carbidopa and Entacapone (LCE)</brief_title>
  <acronym>COST</acronym>
  <official_title>Behavioral and Physiological Effects of Cocaine in Cocaine-dependent Participants Treated With Levodopa in Combination With Carbidopa and Entacapone (LCE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An inpatient safety study to characterize the cardiovascular and behavioral effects of
      cocaine administration in the presence of LCE. The proposed study involves an inpatient stay
      of 12 days during which participants will have two cocaine-administration sessions, each
      including five doses of smoked cocaine with ascending doses.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cocaine dependence remains a serious public health problem; however no clearly effective
      pharmacological treatments have been identified to date. We hypothesize that identification
      of subgroups of cocaine-dependent patients will help to develop targeted and more effective
      treatments. We hypothesize that individuals who have difficulties in achieving abstinence
      have a deficit in dopaminergic functioning and correcting this deficit using dopaminergic
      medication levodopa in combination with carbidopa and entacapone (LCE) to increase
      availability and uptake of levodopa to synthesize dopamine in the brain will result in
      clinical improvement. We were unable to locate any clinical reports that might provide data
      on the interaction between cocaine and LCE. Therefore, we would like to conduct an inpatient
      safety study to characterize the cardiovascular and behavioral effects of cocaine
      administration in the presence of LCE. The proposed study involves an inpatient stay of 12
      days during which participants will have two cocaine-administration sessions, each including
      five doses of smoked cocaine with ascending doses. Participants will be maintained on placebo
      capsules prior to the first study session and on the LCE prior to the second session.
      Physiological (HR, BP, ECG) as well as behavioral (subjective effects) effects of cocaine
      will be monitored during cocaine-administration sessions. Serial blood samples will also
      follow cocaine administration to assess whether the pharmacokinetics of cocaine is altered
      during treatment with LCE. All participants will also undergo two cognitive testing sessions,
      one on placebo and one on LCE, employing a computerized battery (Quarters, Gambling task,
      Drug Stroop, Threat Responsivity task). There will be an optional functional MRI (fMRI)
      component that will investigate behavioral and neural indicators of reward responsivity,
      thought to reflect dopaminergic transmission. Participants choosing to undergo fMRI testing
      will complete two sessions, on the same days as the cognitive task sessions. Data obtained in
      the present study will be used to inform the large, controlled trial of LCE in treatment
      seeking cocaine-dependent individuals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>(baseline) prior to and after each of the 6 cocaine administrations at 4, 18, 32, 46, 60, 74, 104 and 134 minutes after the first dose</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum SBP, maximum DPB will be obtained at baseline, prior to the first session dose, and after each consecutive dose (0, 6, 12, 25, 50, 50 mg). Changes from baseline in blood pressure in the used by cocaine administration under placebo condition will be compared to those obtained during treatment with LCE using repeated measures ANOVA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>(baseline) prior to and after each of the 6 cocaine administrations at 4, 18, 32, 46, 60, 74, 104 and 134 minutes after the first dose</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate will be obtained at baseline, prior to the first session dose, and after each consecutive dose (0, 6, 12, 25, 50, 50mg). Changes from baseline in heart rate in the used by cocaine administration under placebo condition will be compared to those obtained during treatment with LCE using repeated measures ANOVA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite (or Profile) of Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>18, 32, 46, 60, 74, 104 minutes post dose</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax, Area Under Curve, Tmax</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>subjective cocaine experience</measure>
    <time_frame>Done at baseline and at 4, 18, 32, 46, 60, 74, 104 and 134 minutes after the first dose</time_frame>
    <description>1) An assessment of the subjective cocaine experience with and without study medication using a standard battery of 100 mm visual analog scales (VAS) that will be administered pre-dosing and after each dose. Each VAS item will be summarized using AUC, mean and peak scores collected for all time points and analyzed using ANOVA with corrections for multiple comparisons.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Cocaine Abuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>L-dopa / carbidopa / entacapone (LCE)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L-dopa / carbidopa / entacapone (LCE)</intervention_name>
    <description>For this trial we propose a target dosage of L-dopa / carbidopa / entacapone of 400 mg L-dopa / 100mg carbidopa / 200 mg entacapone, twice daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>L/C/E</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult, age 21-50.

          -  Smokes cocaine on average at least 1x/week; currently spends at least $30/week on
             cocaine. Has been using cocaine for at least 6 months Urine toxicology positive for
             cocaine metabolites

          -  Has patterns of smoked cocaine use in terms of frequency and amount that parallels or
             exceed those administered in the study

          -  Able to give informed consent and comply with study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current DSM-IV criteria of substance use disorders with the exception of cocaine or
             nicotine dependence, or a history of alcohol or cannabis dependence.

          -  Request for drug treatment

          -  Unstable medical disorders, or medical disorders that might interfere with study
             participation, including current seizure disorder, heart disease or a history of
             serious adverse effects due to cocaine.

          -  Judged to be noncompliant with study protocol

          -  Concurrent use of any psychotropic medications

          -  Concurrent use of MAO inhibitors or epinephrine (patients must be off MAOIs for a
             minimum of 2 weeks)

          -  Clinical laboratory tests outside normal limits that are clinically unacceptable to
             the study physician (systolic BP &gt; 140 and &lt; 90, diastolic BP &gt; 90 and &lt; 60, and heart
             rate &gt; 90; BUN, creatinine, LFTs &gt; ULN; hematocrit &lt; 34 for women, &lt; 36 for men;
             pseudocholinesterase deficiency)

          -  Positive serum pregnancy test, lactation, or unwillingness to use a satisfactory
             method of birth control

          -  History of myocardial infarction or ischemia, clinically significant left ventricular
             hypertrophy, angina, clinically significant arrhythmia, or mitral valve prolapse

          -  History of narrow angle glaucoma or prostate cancer

          -  History of melanoma or current suspicious undiagnosed skin lesions

          -  Currently meeting DSM-IV criteria for all major psychiatric/psychotic disorders other
             than transient psychosis due to drug abuse

          -  History of allergic reaction or adverse reaction to study medications
             (levodopa/carbidopa/entacapone).

          -  Current parole or probation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adam Bisaga, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://stars.columbia.edu</url>
    <description>stars website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adam Bisaga</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Psychiatrist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cocaine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cocaine-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levodopa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carbidopa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Entacapone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

