<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01430988</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Ahead™ M-100 B-AHEAD UK</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01430988</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Observational Study of the BrainScope® Ahead™ M-100 in UK Emergency Department Patients With Head Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Observational Clinical Study of the BrainScope® Ahead™ M-100 Hand Held Electroencephalogram in Emergency Department Patients With Head Injury (B-AHEAD UK Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>BrainScope Company, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>BrainScope Company, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the current study is proposed to prospectively assess how accurately the
      BrainScope® Ahead™ M-100 can distinguish risk categories for acute head injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      One million patients attend Emergency Departments (ED) with head injuries each year in the
      United Kingdom (UK) and Ireland. 150,000 of these patients will need hospital admission and
      one study estimates an incidence of 45-48% moderate or severe disability in those surviving
      admission. Although the incidence of head injury is high, the incidence of death from head
      injury is low. Therefore ED's are required to see a large number of patients with a
      minor/mild head injury, and identify the very small number of these that will go on to have
      serious complications. The challenge to the emergency medicine clinician is identifying which
      patients with a head injury have an important brain injury that requires further attention
      and which patients can be safely sent home. The standard for determining an important brain
      injury is the result on the Computerised Tomography (CT) scan of the head. CT scanning is
      nonportable and exposes individuals to high radiation levels.

      The study medical device is a portable, point of care, noninvasive and non radiation-emitting
      medical device designed to assist clinicians in early identification, staging, and
      optimisation of treatment for patients who are head injured.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The trial was terminated prematurely following a suspected data processing concern in the study
    device. The concern did not pose a patient safety issue.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Structural Injury Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of head injury</time_frame>
    <description>There are four co-primary endpoints in this study: two sets of sensitivity and specificity to divide the data into three classes.
Using a BrainScope classification algorithm, the Ahead M100 will identify subjects showing sensitivities among 3 classes: Green-normal, nonhead injured controls,Yellow-head injured subjects who do not exhibit brain electrical activity that is consistent with a structural brain injury observable on CT or for whom CT was not deemed necessary,Red-head injured subjects who exhibit brain electrical activity consistent with a structural brain injury observable by CT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Injury Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of head injury</time_frame>
    <description>There are two co-secondary endpoints for the secondary objective, the sensitivity and specificity to split Yellow from the primary endpoint into two sub groups depending on degree of brain functional impairment observable by an evaluation of the clinical findings on a clinical charter used as the assessment of truth.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">318</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Injuries</condition>
  <condition>Craniocerebral Trauma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Head Injured Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects who are suspected of a traumatically induced structural brain injury and/or clinical manifestations of functional brain injury, as a result of insult to the head from an external force, e.g., the head being struck by an object, the head striking an object, the head being exposed to forces generated from a blast or explosion, and/or the brain undergoing an acceleration/deceleration movement without direct external trauma to the head will be recruited from patients who enter the Emergency Department at hospitals that are participating as clinical sites for this study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>A normal control group will be recruited for comparison and will consist of Emergency Department patients who have sustained an injury but do not exhibit any trauma above the clavicle and no history of Road Traffic Accident requiring an ED visit or TBI within the past one (1) year, and no primary complaint of syncope.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Head Injured Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>A 'head injured' control group will be recruited and will consist of Emergency Department patients who are suspected or who have sustained a head injury but do not report or manifest symptoms, e.g. facial lacerations and/or whiplash.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who present to the Emergency Department or Accident &amp; Emergency within the
        selected hospitals participating in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females ages 18 to 80 (the entire age range), who are admitted to the
             Emergency Department (ED), who are suspected of a traumatically induced structural
             brain injury and/or clinical manifestations of functional brain injury, as a result of
             insult to the head from an external force, e.g., the head being struck by an object,
             the head striking an object, the head being exposed to forces generated from a blast
             or explosion, and/or the brain undergoing an acceleration/deceleration movement
             without direct external trauma to the head with a Glasgow Coma Scale of &gt;8. The acute,
             suspected traumatically induced structural brain injury and/or clinical manifestations
             of functional brain injury will have occurred within the past 24 hours upon admission
             to the ED.

          -  The 'head injured' control group will be males and females ages 18 to 80 (the entire
             age range), who are admitted to the ED and are suspected or who have sustained a head
             injury but do not report or manifest symptoms, e.g. facial lacerations and/or
             whiplash.

          -  The ED normal control group will be males and females ages 18 to 80 (the entire age
             range), who are admitted to the ED for presenting complaints that do not involve the
             head or neck (no trauma above the clavicles) and no history of Road Traffic Accident
             requiring an ED visit or TBI within the last one (1) year and no primary complaint of
             syncope.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will be excluded who have forehead, scalp, or skull abnormalities or other
             conditions that would prevent correct application of the electrode headset on the
             skin. In addition, subjects with dementia, Parkinson's Disease, multiple sclerosis,
             seizure disorder, brain tumours, history of brain surgery, psychiatric disorder for
             which there is a prescribed psychiatric medication taken on a daily basis, substance
             dependence, history of TIA or stroke within the last year, currently receiving
             dialysis or in end-stage renal disease, active fever defined as greater than 100
             degrees F or 37.7 degrees C, current condition is listed as &quot;critical&quot;, subject is
             suffering from an open head injury, subject requires advanced airway management (i.e.
             mechanical ventilation), currently receiving procedural sedation medications (e.g.
             benzodiazepine, anaesthetic, NMDA receptor antagonist, or opioid agonist), subjects
             below the age of 18 years, pregnant women, and prisoners will not be eligible for
             study. ED normal control subjects will be excluded if there is a suspected neck injury
             or trauma above the clavicles, a primary complaint of generalized weakness, or a
             primary complaint of headache or migraine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rupert Pearse, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal London Hospital, Barts and The London School of Medicine and Dentistry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal London Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Whitechapel</city>
        <state>London</state>
        <zip>E1 1BB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Salford Royal Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salford</city>
        <state>Manchester</state>
        <zip>M6 8HD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Addenbrooke's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <zip>CB2 0QQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naunheim RS, Treaster M, English J, Casner T. Automated electroencephalogram identifies abnormalities in the ED. Am J Emerg Med. 2011 Oct;29(8):845-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2010.03.010. Epub 2010 May 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20825903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naunheim RS, Treaster M, English J, Casner T, Chabot R. Use of brain electrical activity to quantify traumatic brain injury in the emergency department. Brain Inj. 2010;24(11):1324-9. doi: 10.3109/02699052.2010.506862.</citation>
    <PMID>20722504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naunheim RS, Casner T. Novel method for detecting brain abnormality in a patient with epidural hematoma: a case report. Am J Emerg Med. 2010 Mar;28(3):386.e1-2. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2009.05.008.</citation>
    <PMID>20223405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCrea M, Prichep L, Powell MR, Chabot R, Barr WB. Acute effects and recovery after sport-related concussion: a neurocognitive and quantitative brain electrical activity study. J Head Trauma Rehabil. 2010 Jul-Aug;25(4):283-92. doi: 10.1097/HTR.0b013e3181e67923.</citation>
    <PMID>20611046</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 7, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 7, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head Injuries</keyword>
  <keyword>Head Trauma</keyword>
  <keyword>TBI (Traumatic Brain Injury)</keyword>
  <keyword>Emergency Department</keyword>
  <keyword>Accident &amp; Emergency</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Craniocerebral Trauma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

