<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01432184</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ICM 08-1009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01432184</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility Trial to Maintain Normal Cerebral Oxygen Saturation in High-Risk Cardiac Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>Tête-à-coeur</acronym>
  <official_title>Perioperative Interventions to Optimize Cerebral Oxygen Saturation (rSO2) in High-risk Patients Undergoing Cardiac Surgery Should Have a Beneficial Systemic Effect for Enhancing Global Tissue Perfusion and Improve Outcomes.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Montreal Heart Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Université de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Montreal Heart Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Using the brain and the heart as index organs, perioperative interventions to optimize
      cerebral oxygen saturation and cardiac contractility in high-risk patients undergoing cardiac
      surgery should have a beneficial systemic effect for enhancing global tissue perfusion and
      improve outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proportion of high-risk patients requiring cardiac surgery and of high-risk cardiac
      surgeries is increasing. These populations of patients are at increased risk of perioperative
      morbidity and mortality. Transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) evaluation in cardiac surgery
      has been shown to impact on the perioperative management of patients and to improve outcomes.
      Near infrared-reflectance spectroscopy (NIRS) is a technique that has been employed since the
      mid-1970's and that can be used as a non-invasive and continuous monitor of the balance
      between cerebral oxygen delivery and consumption. Two recent randomized trials have shown an
      association between correction of cerebral desaturation and shorter recovery room and
      hospital stay in non-cardiac surgery, and with a decrease in major organ dysfunction and in
      intensive care length of stay after coronary artery bypass. By combining NIRS and TEE in
      high-risk patients, optimal tissue perfusion could be achieved and perioperative morbidity
      and mortality could be reduced.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Success rate of reversing decreases in cerebral oxygen saturation below 10% of baseline values to values within 10% of baseline in the INTERVENTION group.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Consensus on the appropriate strategies to prevent and reverse cerebral oxygen desaturations remains controversial. In a recent study by Slater and al.12, randomization into an intervention group failed because anesthesiologists were unable to follow the protocol aimed at strategies to reverse decreases in rSO2. A group from the Montreal Heart Institute has developed a physiologically oriented algorithm to help with the task of reversing decreases in rSO2. The goal of the present study is therefore to confirm that this approach can be used with success by most institutions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>First 30 days post-operative outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>readmission to hospital within 30 days
death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU data</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>ICU admission and discharge times
tracheal extubation time in hours</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>First 24 hours complications</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>clinical stroke manifested as focal neurological deficit persisting 24hr and confirmed by brain computed tomography imaging
prolonged ventilation defined as extubation at &gt; 24 h postoperatively
new, persistent Q-wave myocardial infarction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>renal failure as defined by the RIFLE criteria
reoperation for any cause
arrhythmia requiring treatment
Hospital length of stay
wound infection requiring specific antibiotic coverage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Hypoxia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>an alarm threshold at a value of 90% of the resting baseline cerebral saturation value (baseline - 10%) will be established. To minimize the probability of patients reaching significant decreases rSO2 values, interventions to improve cerebral oxygenation will be initiated according to the strategies described in the algorithm. The success and failure of these interventions will be noted. As in the Control group, the screen will remain blinded in the ICU and the intensivist will not see the values.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>the cerebral oxymetry screen will be blinded and changes in NIRS values will be unknown to the anesthesiologist. The management of the case will proceed as per normal local practice. The screen will remain blinded in the ICU and the intensivist will not see the values.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>strategies to reverse decrease in rSO2</intervention_name>
    <description>an alarm threshold at a value of 90% of the resting baseline cerebral saturation value (baseline - 10%) will be established. To minimize the probability of patients reaching significant decreases rSO2 values, interventions to improve cerebral oxygenation will be initiated according to the strategies described in the algorithm. The success and failure of these interventions will be noted. As in the Control group, the screen will remain blinded in the ICU and the intensivist will not see the values.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cerebral Oxymetry decrease</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with EUROSCORES ≥ 10.

          -  Planned complex surgery including more than one procedure, or redo procedures.

          -  Patient able to read and understand the consent form.

          -  Patients ≥ 18 years of age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  High risk patients undergoing of off pump coronary artery bypass.

          -  Emergency surgeries less than 6 hours from diagnosis.

          -  Patient unable to read and understand the consent form.

          -  Patients with and IABP or a ventricular assist device

          -  Planned circulatory arrest

          -  Planned surgery of the descending aorta.

          -  Patients with acute endocarditis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alain Deschamps, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Montreal Heart Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montreal Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H1T 1C8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taillefer MC, Denault AY. Cerebral near-infrared spectroscopy in adult heart surgery: systematic review of its clinical efficacy. Can J Anaesth. 2005 Jan;52(1):79-87. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15625262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kurth CD, Steven JL, Montenegro LM, Watzman HM, Gaynor JW, Spray TL, Nicolson SC. Cerebral oxygen saturation before congenital heart surgery. Ann Thorac Surg. 2001 Jul;72(1):187-92.</citation>
    <PMID>11465176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hadolt I, Litscher G. Noninvasive assessment of cerebral oxygenation during high altitude trekking in the Nepal Himalayas (2850-5600 m). Neurol Res. 2003 Mar;25(2):183-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12635520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Casati A, Fanelli G, Pietropaoli P, Proietti R, Tufano R, Danelli G, Fierro G, De Cosmo G, Servillo G. Continuous monitoring of cerebral oxygen saturation in elderly patients undergoing major abdominal surgery minimizes brain exposure to potential hypoxia. Anesth Analg. 2005 Sep;101(3):740-7, table of contents. Erratum in: Anesth Analg. 2006 Jun;102(6):1645. Fierro, Giovanni [corrected to Fierro, Giuseppe].</citation>
    <PMID>16115985</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murkin JM, Adams SJ, Novick RJ, Quantz M, Bainbridge D, Iglesias I, Cleland A, Schaefer B, Irwin B, Fox S. Monitoring brain oxygen saturation during coronary bypass surgery: a randomized, prospective study. Anesth Analg. 2007 Jan;104(1):51-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17179242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Denault A, Deschamps A, Murkin JM. A proposed algorithm for the intraoperative use of cerebral near-infrared spectroscopy. Semin Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2007 Dec;11(4):274-81. doi: 10.1177/1089253207311685.</citation>
    <PMID>18270192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jöbsis FF. Non-invasive, infra-red monitoring of cerebral O2 sufficiency, bloodvolume, HbO2-Hb shifts and bloodflow. Acta Neurol Scand Suppl. 1977;64:452-3.</citation>
    <PMID>268870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edmonds HL Jr, Ganzel BL, Austin EH 3rd. Cerebral oximetry for cardiac and vascular surgery. Semin Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2004 Jun;8(2):147-66. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15248000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sokol DK, Markand ON, Daly EC, Luerssen TG, Malkoff MD. Near infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) distinguishes seizure types. Seizure. 2000 Jul;9(5):323-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10933986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shojima M, Watanabe E, Mayanagi Y. Cerebral blood oxygenation after cerebrospinal fluid removal in hydrocephalus measured by near infrared spectroscopy. Surg Neurol. 2004 Oct;62(4):312-8; discussion 318.</citation>
    <PMID>15451273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gracias VH, Guillamondegui OD, Stiefel MF, Wilensky EM, Bloom S, Gupta R, Pryor JP, Reilly PM, Leroux PD, Schwab CW. Cerebral cortical oxygenation: a pilot study. J Trauma. 2004 Mar;56(3):469-72; discussion 472-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15128115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vernieri F, Tibuzzi F, Pasqualetti P, Rosato N, Passarelli F, Rossini PM, Silvestrini M. Transcranial Doppler and near-infrared spectroscopy can evaluate the hemodynamic effect of carotid artery occlusion. Stroke. 2004 Jan;35(1):64-70. Epub 2003 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>14684777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yao FS, Tseng CC, Ho CY, Levin SK, Illner P. Cerebral oxygen desaturation is associated with early postoperative neuropsychological dysfunction in patients undergoing cardiac surgery. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2004 Oct;18(5):552-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15578464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slater JP, Guarino T, Stack J, Vinod K, Bustami RT, Brown JM 3rd, Rodriguez AL, Magovern CJ, Zaubler T, Freundlich K, Parr GV. Cerebral oxygen desaturation predicts cognitive decline and longer hospital stay after cardiac surgery. Ann Thorac Surg. 2009 Jan;87(1):36-44; discussion 44-5. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2008.08.070.</citation>
    <PMID>19101265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Tournay-Jetté E, Denault A, Dupuis G, Cartier R, Deschamps A, Bherer L: Cerebral oxygen saturation (rSO2) changes and post cognitive decline in elderly patients undergoing coronary artery bypass surgery. en préparation</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deschamps A, Rochon A, Lebon J-S, Ayoub C, Qizilbash B, Couture P, Cogan J, Toledano K, Bélisle S, Hemmings G, Taillefer J, Blain R, Denault A: Decreases in Cerebal Oxygen Saturation: an algorithmic approach. Canadian Anaesthetists' Society Journal 2009; Abstract: #613224</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fergusson DA, Hébert PC, Mazer CD, Fremes S, MacAdams C, Murkin JM, Teoh K, Duke PC, Arellano R, Blajchman MA, Bussières JS, Côté D, Karski J, Martineau R, Robblee JA, Rodger M, Wells G, Clinch J, Pretorius R; BART Investigators. A comparison of aprotinin and lysine analogues in high-risk cardiac surgery. N Engl J Med. 2008 May 29;358(22):2319-31. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0802395. Epub 2008 May 14. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2010 Sep 23;363(13):1290.</citation>
    <PMID>18480196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 12, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 16, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 16, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 20, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Montreal Heart Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alain Deschamps</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD, MD, FRCPC,</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cerebral</keyword>
  <keyword>hypoxia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia, Brain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

