<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01437280</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-28686-GOAT</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>GOAT</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01437280</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GOAT; Phase I Open Label Study of CGTG-102, a GM-CSF Encoding Oncolytic Adenovirus, for Advanced Cancers</brief_title>
  <acronym>GOAT</acronym>
  <official_title>GOAT; Phase I Single-Center Open Label Dose Escalation Study of CGTG-102, a GM-CSF Encoding Oncolytic Adenovirus, for Therapy of Advanced Cancers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Methodist Hospital System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harris County Hospital District</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Oncolytic viruses are viruses that can be found in nature, but they have been modified so
      that they can no longer multiply in normal cells. These viruses &quot;infect&quot; cancer cells and
      kill them. Once the cancer cell dies thousands of the viruses are released and can
      potentially infect other cancer cells in the area. The effects of oncolytic viruses on the
      tumor are felt to be the result of a combination of the oncolytic viruses directly killing
      the tumor cells as well as the patient's immune system killing cancer cells that are infected
      with the oncolytic virus.

      Modern oncolytic viruses have been used for treatment of thousands of patients. The safety of
      such treatments has been good and there have been no deaths caused by treatment with
      oncolytic viruses. Many patients have benefited from the treatment in the sense that their
      tumors have stopped growing, become smaller or even completely disappeared. Some benefits are
      temporary, but about one third of patients seem to gain longer lasting benefit likely to
      impact survival. The effect of oncolytic viruses on improving survival has not been
      demonstrated yet.

      Oncolytic viruses can be created from many different types of viruses. In this study the
      investigators are using an oncolytic virus created from an adenovirus. Adenoviruses are the
      types of viruses that cause the common cold and the flu. Because replication in normal cells
      does not take place, these oncolytic viruses should not cause any diseases in normal cells.
      Further, to date there has been no incidence of passing the virus on to other humans from
      patients who were treated with oncolytic viruses.

      The purpose of this study is to see the highest dose of CGTG-102 (the oncolytic virus being
      used in this study) that can safely be given to subjects. The investigators will also
      evaluate whether or not the CGTG-102 is helpful in reducing the size of the cancer and
      improving patient survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pre-treatment visit - subject will undergo a physical examination with vital signs, a blood
      sample will be taken and a PET (Positron emission tomography)-CT (Computer tomography) scan
      will be performed.

      Thereafter, there will be 4 visits with injections performed on trial days 1, 4, 8 and 15.

      TREATMENT:

      The injections are given directly into the tumors with help from using an ultrasound. The
      total dose of oncolytic virus the subject will receive will be divided into 1-10 injections
      which will be injected into individual tumors in the body. The maximum number of tumors that
      can be injected for one treatment will be 10 tumors.

      STUDY VISIT 1:

      On the day 1 visit, blood samples will be taken as well as two biopsies from one of the
      tumors. In addition pleural fluids (fluids from the chest) or ascites (fluids from abdominal
      walls) may be collected if possible. Then the subject will receive the first set of
      injections with CGTG-102. Before the injections, the subject may be given a dose of Tylenol.

      STUDY VISIT 2:

      On the day 4 visit, in addition to blood samples being taken the subject will receive a
      second round of intratumoral injections into the same tumors selected for injections on day
      1. Urine will also be collected right before the subject goes home.

      STUDY VISIT 3:

      The day 8 visit is identical to the day 4 visit. The same blood samples and urine sample are
      taken.

      STUDY VISIT 4:

      On the day 15 visit blood samples and a urine sample will be taken as well as a biopsy from
      one of the tumors.

      Subjects will have to stay overnight at the hospital after each treatment.

      FOLLOW UP:

      A follow-up visit will be scheduled on days 29 where only blood samples and a urine sample
      will be taken.

      The end of trial visit is scheduled around day 43 where in addition to lab samples a PET-CT
      scan will be performed.

      Following day 43 the subject will be contacted by study staff at 6 week intervals for 3
      months, then at 3 month intervals for up to one year and yearly thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of CGTC-102 in patients with solid tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the safety of the maximum tolerated dose and/or maximum feasible dose of CGTG-102 administered by intratumoral injection in a patient population with unresectable, refractory solid tumors</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of CGTC-102 in patients with solid tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the maximum tolerated dose and/or maximum feasible dose of CGTG-102 administered by intratumoral injection in a patient population with unresectable, refractory solid tumors</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of tumor following the injection</measure>
    <time_frame>43 days</time_frame>
    <description>To measure the development of adenovirus and tumor specific humoral responses following virus injection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of cellular immune response following the injection</measure>
    <time_frame>43 days</time_frame>
    <description>To measure the development of cellular immune responses following virus injection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CGTG-102</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CGTG-102 is an oncolytic adenovirus</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CGTG-102</intervention_name>
    <description>VP=virus particle
Dose Level 1: 3x10^10 VP/injection
Dose Level 2: 1x10^11 VP/injection
Dose Level 3: 3x10^11 VP/injection
Patients will receive 4 administrations of CGTG-102 (on days 1, 4, 8, 15).
Escalation to the next dose level will occur when the safety of all 4 administrations has been evaluated at day 43 on all patients in the preceding dose level.
The total dose will be injected into up to 10 tumors injectable by either direct visualization/palpitation and/or ultrasound. Typically, the largest safely injectable tumors are chosen.
Injections will be performed by a radiologist or other trained physician. Injections will be planned based on the baseline PET-CT: only PET-positive tumors or tumor regions should be injected. Injection needles designed for percutaneous insertion into tissues will be used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CGTG-102</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Age 18 - 70 years

          2. Histologically-confirmed, advanced/metastatic solid tumor that is relapsed and/or
             refractory to standard therapy (progressive disease despite therapy).

          3. Cancer is not surgically resectable for cure.

          4. At least one measurable tumor mass by PETCT (i.e. PET-positive lesion that can
             reliable be assessed for SUV (standard update value) peak/SUV max, typically featuring
             longest diameter greater than or equal to 1 cm) and that can be injected by direct
             visualization/palpitation or by imaging-guidance (ultrasound)

          5. Tumor suitable for biopsy. Biopsy is to be performed twice during the study (day 1 and
             day 15). The aim is to biopsy the same tumor at these visits.

          6. Expected survival for approximately 12 weeks or longer

          7. Performance Status WHO (World Health Organization) 0-2

          8. Total bilirubin less than or equal to ULN (Upper Limit of Normal)

          9. AST (Aspartate transaminase), ALT (Alanine aminotransferase) less than or equal to 3.0
             × ULN

         10. Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN

         11. INR (International Normalized Ratio) less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN

         12. Hematologic parameters: Patients can be transfused to meet these entry criteria:

               1. Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 10 g/dL

               2. Leucocytes greater than or equal to 2300/mL

               3. platelet count greater than or equal to 75,000 plts/mm

         13. Willing to participate as demonstrated by signed informed consent form.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Known brain metastases or glioma. Central Nervous System malignancy, including
             carcinomatosis meningitis.

          2. Tumor in the immediate pericardial vicinity

          3. Use of high dose systemic corticosteroids or other immune suppressive medication
             within 3 weeks of first treatment.

             Note: patients taking low-dose corticosteroids for the treatment of nausea and/or
             taking maintenance corticosteroids for adrenal insufficiency are permitted to enroll.

          4. Known infection with HIV (Human immunodeficiency virus) as this would affect the
             immune response of treatment or known underlying genetic immunodeficiency disease

          5. Treatment of the injected tumor(s) with radiotherapy, chemotherapy, surgery, or an
             investigational drug within 4 weeks prior to first treatment.

          6. Use of anti-viral medication. [Patients who discontinue such medications within 7 days
             prior to first treatment may be eligible for this study.]

          7. Recent thromboembolic event

          8. Clinically significant active infection or uncontrolled medical condition considered
             high risk for investigational new drug treatment (e.g. pulmonary, neurological,
             cardiovascular, metabolic such as type 2 diabetes, clinically significant and/or
             rapidly accumulating ascites, peri-cardial and/or pleural effusions)

          9. Severe or unstable cardiac disease.

         10. Current, active, progressing CNS (Central nervous system) malignancy, including
             carcinomatosis meningitis (definitively surgically resected or irradiated metastases
             allowed)

         11. Pulse oximetry O2 (oxygen) criterion &lt;90% at rest on room air

         12. Vaccination with a live virus (i.e. measles, mumps, rubella, etc) &lt; 30 days prior to
             first treatment

         13. History of hepatic dysfunction, cirrhosis, hepatitis or malaria

         14. Evidence of coagulation disorder

         15. Women who are pregnant or nursing an infant

         16. Previous organ transplant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martha M Pritchett, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 15, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 12, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 12, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 14, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Martha Mims</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

