<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01430975</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CGEN-104</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01430975</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Evaluation of Strontium in Patients After CardioGen-82 PET MPI Scanning at Two Clinical Sites</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Study to Estimate Inadvertent Radiation Exposure From Strontium Isotopes in Patients Who Have Undergone CardioGen-82® PET MPI Scanning at Two Clinical Sites</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bracco Diagnostics, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bracco Diagnostics, Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to be performed at two clinical sites where patients received CardioGen-82
      during the time period January to June, 2011 and where patients were scanned chronologically
      near to the index patients (2 days before or after). Of these, it is planned that at least 30
      patients will be entered in this trial. Index patient is the term applied to individuals who
      had radiation spectra indicative of Sr-82 and Sr-85 detected by hand-held survey meters.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This clinical study protocol will use a three tier approach consisting of the following
      examinations:

        -  Patient examination with Survey Meter: The patient will first be tested at the clinical
           sites using a survey meter. In those patients whose radiation count is ≥ 2 times above
           background count using a standard survey meter, the presence of Sr-82 and/or Sr-85 will
           be assessed through a quantitative reading from a calibrated portable isotope
           identifier.

        -  Patient examination with Portable Isotope Identifier: This examination will be done by
           use of a portable isotope identifier, which will be supplied by the Sponsor to the study
           sites. An assessor, independent to the study site and will perform the examination. In
           those patients whose radiation count is ≥ 2 times above background count using a
           standard survey meter, the presence of Sr-82 and/or Sr-85 will be assessed through a
           quantitative reading from a calibrated portable isotope identifier. The reading will be
           forwarded along with the date of the reading, the date of the patient's CardioGen-82®
           scan, and the total dose of CardioGen-82® administered to the patient, to an independent
           medical expert, independent to the study site, who will back-calculate an estimated dose
           of Sr-82 and/or Sr-85 from these data.

        -  Patient examination at Oak Ridge National Laboratory: Any patient whose estimated dose
           of Sr-82 exceeds the specified limit of 0.02 microcuries per mCi Rb-82 administered,
           and/or whose estimated dose of Sr-85 exceeds the specified limit of 0.2 microcuries per
           mCi Rb-82 administered, will be asked to travel to Oak Ridge National Laboratory in
           Tennessee, for accurate whole body scanning. Scan data from Oak Ridge National
           Laboratories will be analyzed by one or more independent medical experts to accurately
           back-calculate exposure to Sr-82 and/or Sr-85, and to estimate health hazard for the
           patient.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of radiation exposure from Sr-82 and/or Sr-85</measure>
    <time_frame>on average within 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determine radiation exposure from Sr-82 and/or Sr-85 in patients administered CardioGen-82® for PET MPI at the two sites reporting Sr-82/Sr-85 breakthrough</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of extent of SR-82/Sr-85 exposure, if positive exposure is detected</measure>
    <time_frame>within 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the extent of the Sr-82/Sr-85 exposure, in the subset of patients with positive testing exceeding the specified threshold for the breakthrough of Sr-82/Sr-85, by performing whole body scanning at Oak Ridge National Laboratory for eventual health hazard assessment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Radiation Exposure</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CardioGen-82</intervention_name>
    <description>CardioGen-82 was not administered as part of this trial but the patients enrolled had to have received CardioGen-82 previously</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CardioGen-82</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients do not received CardioGen-82 as part of this study. To be in the study they would have had to receive CardioGen-82 previously.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population would come from the two sites who administered CardioGen-82® to the
        index patients. Each site that agrees to participate will enroll patients administered
        CardioGen-82 2 days before and 2 days after the use of that generator.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female;

          -  Gave informed consent to participate in the study;

          -  Received CardioGen-82 that has been eluted from the generator in close proximity (2
             days before or after) the index patients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -Any patient previously enrolled in and completed this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Sireci, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bracco Diagnostics, Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bracco Diagnostics, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Princeton</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08540</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 7, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 25, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Radiation Exposure</keyword>
  <keyword>Rubidium 82</keyword>
  <keyword>Strontium 82</keyword>
  <keyword>Strontium 85</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

