<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01433835</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01433835</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Single Oral Doses of MBX-400 in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Single Oral Doses of MBX-400 in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Microbiotix, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Microbiotix, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and pharmacokinetics following a single
      oral dose of MBX-400.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cytomegalovirus (CMV; herpesvirus 5), a member of the betaherpesvirus subgroup, occurs as a
      benign infection in the majority of humans, with a 90% prevalence in the adult population1.
      However, CMV infection continues to be a major cause of morbidity and mortality in
      immunosuppressed patients, particularly recipients of solid organ or bone marrow transplants.
      CMV is also known for its association with severe blinding retinitis, pneumonia and
      gastrointestinal inflammation in AIDS patients. However, with the successful introduction of
      HAART (highly active anti-retroviral therapy), the problem of CMV infection in AIDS patients
      has decreased substantially. CMV remains the most important cause of congenital viral
      infection in the United States, and CMV infection of neonates is associated with deafness,
      mental retardation and mortality. In addition, CMV is a suspected pathogenic agent in
      cardiovascular disease and can persist in large-vessel endothelial cells and infect all cell
      types involved in cardiovascular lesions. CMV has been implicated in the restenosis of
      diseased coronary arteries following angioplasty and has been associated with myocarditis. In
      severely immunocompromised patients with CMV infection, prolonged antiviral therapy is often
      necessary, which increases the risk of resistant viruses. Currently available therapy has
      limitations that preclude their long-term use including toxicity, poor oral bioavailability
      and the development of drug-resistant strains. MBX-400 is a nucleoside analog that is
      structurally related to ganciclovir and acyclovir and is being developed for the possible use
      in the prevention and/or treatment of CMV. MBX-400, has been shown to be a potent inhibitor
      of viral DNA synthesis and therefore may be useful in treating and/or preventing CMV
      infection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Safety is evaluated by assessing the incidence and severity for 14 days following a single dose of MBX-400 including:
Product-related serious and life-threatening adverse events
Adverse events
Laboratory data abnormalities and clinically significant changes
Electrocardiogram abnormalities and clinically significant changes
Physical exam abnormalities and clinically significant changes
Vital signs abnormalities and clinically significant changes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 18, 24, 36, 48, 60, 72, 84 and 96 hours following dosing</time_frame>
    <description>The following pharmacokinetic parameters will be evaluated:
Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax)
Time of maximum plasma concentration (Tmax)
Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC)
Terminal plasma half-life (t1/2)
Apparent plasma clearance (Cl/F)
Apparent volume of distribution (Vd/F)
Amount excreted in urine (Ae)
Urinary clearance (Clu)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Adult Subjects</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MBX-400</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MBX-400</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsule(s) for oral administration as a single dose. Planned doses include: 35, 100, 350, 700, 1000 and 1350 mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MBX-400</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ZSM-I-62</other_name>
    <other_name>NSC D745998</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclopropavir (CPV)</other_name>
    <other_name>(Z)-9-{[2,2-bis-(hydroxymethyl)cyclopropylidene] methyl}guanine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsule(s) for oral administration as a single dose. Planned doses include: 35, 100, 350, 700, 1000 and 1350 mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>microcrystalline cellulose</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female 18 to 65 years of age

          2. Females must be surgically-sterilized or post-menopausal (defined as at least 1 year
             since last menses with follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) level indicating subject is
             post-menopausal)

          3. Males must have undergone vasectomy

          4. Able to understand study requirements, agrees to participate in the study and willing
             and able to provide informed consent (using an informed consent form in a language in
             which the subject is fluent)

          5. Willing and able to stay in a clinical facility for up to 7 days

          6. BMI of 18 to 32 kg/m2

          7. Non-smoker or former smoker or user of nicotine-containing products (defined as
             someone who smoked or used nicotine-products one or more times a week for at least one
             month) who has not smoked for at least 3 months and has not used nicotine-containing
             products for at least 1 month and is willing to abstain from nicotine-containing
             products during the study

          8. Has adequate venous access

          9. Willing to abstain from alcohol and illicit drugs during the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participation in another clinical trial within 3 months of screening

          2. Unwilling to comply with study procedures or cooperate with study personnel.

          3. Donated blood or had significant blood loss (greater than 1 unit) within 3 months of
             screening

          4. History of any of the following

               -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), cytomegalovirus (CMV), hepatitis B or
                  hepatitis C infection

               -  Alcohol or drug abuse

               -  Anemia or bleeding disorders

               -  Gastrointestinal disorders

               -  Chronic illness

               -  Regular medication use (prescription, over-the-counter or herbal; defined as more
                  than once per week; except multivitamins) or use of medication (except
                  multivitamins) within 1 week of screening.

               -  Recent illness requiring treatment within 1 month of screening

               -  History of renal failure or renal insufficiency

          5. Clinically significant abnormal electrocardiogram (e.g., abnormal rhythm, abnormal
             intervals)

          6. Clinically significant results of hematology, chemistry, coagulation studies or
             urinalysis, including, but not limited to the following:

               -  White blood cell count, red blood cell count or platelet count less than the
                  lower limit of normal or greater than 1.5 times the upper limit of normal

               -  Hemoglobin or hematocrit less than the lower limit of normal or greater than the
                  upper limit of normal

               -  Alanine aminotransferase and aspartate aminotransferase greater than the upper
                  limit of normal

               -  Prothrombin, partial thromboplastin time or international normalized ratio
                  greater than 1.5 times the upper limit of normal

               -  Abnormal electrolyte values (i.e., sodium, potassium, carbon dioxide/bicarbonate,
                  chloride and/or calcium outside of the reference range)

               -  Urinalysis showing presence of red blood cells, protein or microalbumin

               -  Cotinine level indicative of nicotine use

               -  Positive test for any drug of abuse on urine drug screen

               -  Positive serum pregnancy test if female

               -  Positive ethanol test

          7. Clinically significant vital signs

               -  Temperature above 100.0 °F

               -  Heart rate &lt; 45 or &gt; 100 beats per minute

               -  Respiratory rate &lt; 12 or &gt; 20 breaths per minute

               -  Systolic blood pressure &lt; 100 or &gt; 140 mm Hg OR diastolic blood pressure &lt; 60 or
                  &gt; 90 mm Hg

          8. Known hypersensitivity to any ingredients in the MBX-400 capsules or Placebo capsules
             (e.g., MBX-400, microcrystalline cellulose, gelatin, titanium dioxide).

          9. Scheduled for surgical procedure during the study

         10. Investigator deems that subject has a condition that warrants exclusion from or is not
             suitable for the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gregory J Tracey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Frontage Clinical Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Frontage Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kern ER, Bidanset DJ, Hartline CB, Yan Z, Zemlicka J, Quenelle DC. Oral activity of a methylenecyclopropane analog, cyclopropavir, in animal models for cytomegalovirus infections. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2004 Dec;48(12):4745-53.</citation>
    <PMID>15561852</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou S, Zemlicka J, Kern ER, Drach JC. Fluoroanalogues of anti-cytomegalovirus agent cyclopropavir: synthesis and antiviral activity of (E)- and (Z)-9-{[2,2-bis(hydroxymethyl)-3-fluorocyclopropylidene]methyl}-adenines and guanines. Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids. 2007;26(3):231-43.</citation>
    <PMID>17454732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mhaske SB, Ksebati B, Prichard MN, Drach JC, Zemlicka J. Phosphonate analogues of cyclopropavir phosphates and their E-isomers. Synthesis and antiviral activity. Bioorg Med Chem. 2009 Jun 1;17(11):3892-9. doi: 10.1016/j.bmc.2009.04.020. Epub 2009 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19410465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li C, Gentry BG, Drach JC, Zemlicka J. Synthesis and enantioselectivity of cyclopropavir phosphates for cellular GMP kinase. Nucleosides Nucleotides Nucleic Acids. 2009 Sep;28(9):795-808. doi: 10.1080/15257770903172720.</citation>
    <PMID>20183619</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gentry BG, Gentry SN, Jackson TL, Zemlicka J, Drach JC. Phosphorylation of antiviral and endogenous nucleotides to di- and triphosphates by guanosine monophosphate kinase. Biochem Pharmacol. 2011 Jan 1;81(1):43-9. doi: 10.1016/j.bcp.2010.09.005. Epub 2010 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>20846508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chou S, Bowlin TL. Cytomegalovirus UL97 mutations affecting cyclopropavir and ganciclovir susceptibility. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2011 Jan;55(1):382-4. doi: 10.1128/AAC.01259-10. Epub 2010 Nov 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21041510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James SH, Hartline CB, Harden EA, Driebe EM, Schupp JM, Engelthaler DM, Keim PS, Bowlin TL, Kern ER, Prichard MN. Cyclopropavir inhibits the normal function of the human cytomegalovirus UL97 kinase. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2011 Oct;55(10):4682-91. doi: 10.1128/AAC.00571-11. Epub 2011 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21788463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 14, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cytomegalovirus</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiviral</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

