<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01540448</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DS-005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01540448</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of CT Angiography With Three-dimensional Reconstruction of Mesenteric Vessels in Planning and Performing of Laparoscopic Colorectal Resections</brief_title>
  <acronym>3DCT</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Roma La Sapienza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Roma La Sapienza</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate if the prior knowledge of the individual mesenteric
      vascular anatomy of patients represents an advantage in performing laparoscopic colorectal
      resections. The investigators want demonstrate that the three-dimensional reconstruction of
      colonic vascular anatomy, acquired with a CT angiography, may lead to a more effective and
      less extensive dissection and to a fewer intraoperative and postoperative complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical Performance (operative time)</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The consequences on the surgical performance of preoperative knowledge of the mesenteric vascular anatomy assessed by the evaluation of the operative time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>complex identification of mesenteric vessels performing laparoscopic colorectal resection</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 4 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Iatrogenic vascular or visceral injuries</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 10 postoperative days</time_frame>
    <description>Iatrogenic vascular or visceral injuries related to difficult identification of right anatomy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intraoperative bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>intraoperative bleeding related to dissection for mesenteric vessels quest. Blood loss of less than 20 mL was considered mild; between 20 and 100 mL, moderate; and more than 100 mL, severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 15 postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>lymph nodes harvesting</measure>
    <time_frame>within first 4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>number harvested of lymph nodes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anatomical variations of mesenteric vessels</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours before surgical procedure</time_frame>
    <description>anatomical variations of mesenteric vessels detected by peroperative CT scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Laparoscopic Resection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No-3DCT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients were subjected to a CT scan with 3D mesenteric angiography but the surgeon was able to view the 3D reconstruction only after surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3DCT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients were subjected to a CT scan with 3D mesenteric angiography and the surgeon was able to view 3D reconstruction before and during laparoscopic colorectal resection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laparoscopic Right Hemicolectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>We perform the Right Hemicolectomy (RH) with a 3 trocars technique. The procedure starts with the identification and sectioning of the ileocolic vessels at their origin. Next, is possible to divide the mesentery towards the terminal ileum, which was sectioned by laparoscopic linear stapler. The procedure continues with the incision of the Houston's ligament and the retroperitoneal dissection of the cecum and ascending colon up to the right flexure by pulling the terminal ileum upwards. During this maneuvers and eventually after the incision of the hepato-duodenocolic ligament, is possible to identify and cut the right colic vessels and, if necessary, the middle colic vessels and the Henle's venous branch.With the right colon and proximal transverse completely mobilized, it is possible to section the colon with a linear laparoscopic stapler and to create a 4-6 cm service incision to remove the specimen and perform an extracorporeal ileo-colic isoperistaltic mechanical anastomosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No-3DCT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3DCT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laparoscopic Left Hemicolectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>We routinely perform the Left Hemicolectomy (LH) with a 3 trocars technique eventually placing the 4th trocar in the left flank if needed. The procedure started with the division of the gastro-spleno-colic ligament and the subsequent mobilization of the left colic flexure. Then is possible to identify and section the inferior mesenteric vessels. Performing LH the Inferior Mesenteric Artery (IMA) is usually tied immediately below the origin of the Left Colic Artery (LCA) while in presence of benign disease, to preserve the IMA, the dissection is performed along the course of the vessel, sectioning progressively the sigmoid arterial branches close to the colonic wall. When left colon is completely mobilized from the retroperitoneum along the avascular plane between the mesocolon and perirenal fat is possible to section the distal colon and finally perform a termino-terminal mechanical anastomosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No-3DCT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3DCT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anterior Rectal Resection</intervention_name>
    <description>We routinely perform the Anterior Rectal Resection (ARR) with a 3 trocars technique eventually placing the 4th trocar in the left flank if needed. The procedure started with the division of the gastro-spleno-colic ligament and the subsequent mobilization of the left colic flexure. Then is possible to identify and section the inferior mesenteric vessels. Performing ARR the Inferior Mesenteric Artery (IMA) is usually tied at origin but in particular cases it can be tied immediately below the origin of the Left Colic Artery (LCA). When left colon and is completely mobilized from the retroperitoneum along the avascular plane between the mesocolon and perirenal fat is possible to perform a partial or total mesorectal excision. Usually a termino-terminal mechanical anastomosis is performed at the end of the procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No-3DCT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3DCT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  need of colorectal resection

          -  absence of preoperative CT scan

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  contraindications to laparoscopy

          -  ASA IV

          -  BMI &gt; 40 Kg/m2

          -  need of non standard colonic resection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Sant'Andrea</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00189</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 28, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 28, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Roma La Sapienza</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Francesco Saverio Mari</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prinicipal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

