<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01544790</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL35048.041.11</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11141</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01544790</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Robot-assisted Thoraco-laparoscopic Esophagectomy Versus Open Transthoracic Esophagectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>ROBOT</acronym>
  <official_title>Robot-assisted Minimally Invasive Thoraco-laparoscopic Esophagectomy Versus Open Transthoracic Esophagectomy for Resectable Esophageal Cancer. The ROBOT-trial: a Monocenter Randomized Controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UMC Utrecht</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is the first randomized controlled trial designed to compare robot-assisted minimally
      invasive thoraco-laparoscopic esophagectomy with open transthoracic esophagectomy as surgical
      treatment for resectable esophageal cancer.

      If our hypothesis is proved correct, robot-assisted minimally invasive thoraco-laparoscopic
      esophagectomy will result in a lower percentage of postoperative complications, lower blood
      loss, shorter hospital stay, but with at least similar oncologic outcomes and better
      postoperative quality of life compared with the open transthoracic esophagectomy (current
      standard).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: As stated in the 2010 revised Dutch esophageal carcinoma guidelines, the golden
      standard for surgical treatment of esophageal carcinoma is open transthoracic esophagectomy.
      Recent evidence suggests that robot-assisted thoraco-laparoscopic esophagectomy using the Da
      Vinci ® robot can provide an extensive resection, with possibly better or at least equal
      radical (R0) resection rates and an equal number of dissected lymph nodes. This is
      accompanied with markedly reduced blood loss and reduction of overall complications with
      shorter intensive care unit (ICU) and hospital stay. Therefore, the robot-assisted
      thoraco-laparoscopic esophagectomy is now at a stage that it should be compared to the
      current standard of care in a randomized controlled trial.

      Objective: Evaluate the benefits, risks and costs of robot-assisted thoraco-laparoscopic
      esophagectomy as an alternative to open transthoracic esophagectomy as treatment for
      esophageal cancer.

      Study design: Randomized controlled parallel-group superiority trial Study population:
      Patients (age ≥ 18 and ≤ 75 jaar) with histologically proven surgically resectable (cT1-4a,
      N0-3, M0) squamous cell carcinoma, adenocarcinoma or undifferentiated esophageal carcinoma of
      the intrathoracic esophagus with European Clinical Oncology Group (ECOG) status 0, 1 or 2.

      Intervention: 112 patients will be randomly allocated to either A) robot-assisted
      thoraco-laparoscopic esophagectomy (n=56) or B) open transthoracic esophagectomy (n=56).

      Patients will receive the following interventions:

      Group A. Robot-assisted thoraco-laparoscopic esophagectomy, with gastric conduit formation.

      Group B. Open transthoracic esophagectomy, with gastric conduit formation.

      Main study parameters/endpoints: Primary outcome is the percentage of overall complications
      (Grade 2 and higher) as stated by the modified Clavien-Dindo classification (MCDC).

      Secondary outcomes are individual components of the primary endpoint (major and minor
      complications), (in hospital) mortality within 30 and 60 days, R0 resections, operation
      related events, postoperative recovery, oncologic outcomes, cost-effectiveness and quality of
      life.

      Follow-up: 60 months after randomization
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative complications modified Clavien-Dindo classification (MCDC) grade 2 and higher</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of this study is the percentage of overall complications (Grade 2 and higher) as stated by the modified Clavien-Dindo classification of surgical complications (MCDC)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Individual components of the primary endpoint (major and minor complications)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Major complications (MCDC grade 2-4) Including: myocardial infarction, anastomotic leakage (clinical or radiologic diagnosis), anastomotic stenosis, chylothorax (chylous leakage, presence of chylous in chest tubes or indication start medium chain triglycerides containing tube feeding (Vivonex®), gastric tube necrosis (proven by gastroscopy), pulmonary embolus, deep vein thrombosis, vocal cord palsy or paralysis.
Minor complications (MCDC grade 1) Including: wound infections, pleural effusions, delayed gastric emptying</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>(In hospital) Mortality within 30 and 60 days</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks and within 30 days or 60 days</time_frame>
    <description>(In hospital) mortality and mortality within 30 and 60 days will be reported. The cause of death and the results of the autopsy report will be noted.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>R0 resections (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The pathological analysis will be finished within 2 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operation related events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery, up to 24 hours after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Operation time is defined as time from incision until closure (minutes) for both the thoracic and the abdominal phase of the procedure. For the robotic procedure, set up time will be recorded separately. Unexpected events and complications occurring during the operation will be recorded (e.g. massive hemorrhage, perforation of other organs).
Blood loss during operation (ml, per phase). In case of conversion to thoracotomy or laparotomy the reason for conversion has to be explained (absolute numbers/percentage).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pain: Type and dose of used analgesics will be noted during the hospital admission period.
Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for pain will be noted at following times: pre-operatively and the first 10 days after surgery and a fixed periods during follow up (6 weeks, 6 months and yearly post-operatively up to 5 years).
Length of intensive care unit (ICU) - medium care unit (MCU) stay (days). Length of hospital stay (days).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oncologic outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 60 months after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>2, 3 and 5 year disease free and overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 60 months after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaires will be required at following times:
SF-36, EORTC QLQ-C30 (Dutch), EORTC OES18 (Dutch) and EQ-5D (Appendix 1 &amp; 2) pre-operative &lt; 5 days and 6 weeks, 6 months and yearly up to 5 years post-operatively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Costs (euro)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Direct general costs, due to extra operating room time and extra instruments. Indirect costs, such as reduced ICU or hospital stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Robot-assisted esophagectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Robot-assisted thoraco-laparoscopic esophagectomy with gastric conduit formation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Open transthoracic esophagectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>traditional open transthoracic esophagectomy with gastric conduit formation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Esophagectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>In this monocenter prospective randomized controlled trial, we compare robot-assisted minimally invasive esophagectomy with conventional open transthoracic esophagectomy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Robot-assisted esophagectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Open transthoracic esophagectomy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>robot-assisted minimally invasive esophagectomy</other_name>
    <other_name>robot-assisted thoraco-laparoscopic esophagectomy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically proven squamous cell carcinoma, adenocarcinoma or undifferentiated
             carcinoma of the intrathoracic esophagus.

          -  Surgical resectable (T1-4a, N0-3, M0)

          -  Age ≥ 18 and ≤ 75 years

          -  European Clinical Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0,1 or 2

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Carcinoma of the cervical esophagus

          -  Carcinoma of the gastro-esophageal junction (GEJ) with major tumor in the gastric
             cardia (Siewert III)

          -  Prior thoracic surgery at the right hemithorax or thorax trauma (rationale: these
             patients will undergo open resection)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard R. van Hillegersberg, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMC Utrecht, dept. of Surgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMC Utrecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <zip>3584 CX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 6, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>UMC Utrecht</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard van Hillegersberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Esophageal carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Esophageal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Robotic surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Esophagectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Minimally invasive</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

