<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01540786</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>905-EC-010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01540786</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Exploratory Study to Investigate Bladder Contractions in the Storage Phase and Related Bladder Sensations in Healthy Females and Females With Overactive Bladder (OAB) Using High Resolution and Conventional Urodynamics</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Exploratory Study to Evaluate Bladder Contractions in the Storage Phase (Non Voiding Activities) and Related Bladder Sensation in Healthy Females and Untreated Females With Overactive Bladder (&quot;OAB&quot;) Using High Resolution and Conventional Urodynamics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma Europe Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Astellas Pharma Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to identify differences in bladder contractions during the storage phase (non
      voiding activities) between OAB subjects and healthy subjects, using high resolution
      urodynamics.

      The study is divided into two parts:

        -  PART 1: Consists of 5 females with overactive bladder

        -  PART 2: Consists of 25 females with overactive bladder and 15 healthy females

      Part 1 subjects will be enrolled followed by part 2 subjects. The data from part 1 subjects
      will be reviewed and analysed by a group of experts before starting the second part (part 2)
      of the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The subjects will complete a total of 2 visits and a follow up telephone call (or visit at
      the investigator's discretion).

      Upon meeting eligibility criteria subjects will be screened and complete visit at hospital
      (Visit 1). They will then be asked to complete procedures such micturition diary,
      questionnaires and if applicable discontinued their ongoing OAB medication. Upon confirmation
      of eligibility criteria subjects will then be enrolled and complete visit 2 within 6 to 31
      days post V1. At Visit 2 subjects will complete high resolution urodynamic assessment
      followed by the conventional urodynamic assessment. The visit will take approximately half a
      day. Safety follow up phone call (or visit at investigator's discretion) will take place 4 to
      6 days post visit 2.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    It was decided to discontinue the study due to insufficient recruitment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify objective parameters to characterize Non Voiding Activity (NVA) in healthy and OAB subjects using high resolution urodynamic assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>During the High resolution urodynamics (Day 1)</time_frame>
    <description>NVA is defined as changes of pressure in the bladder lumen. These changes are measured as detrusor pressure (Pdet) calculated from substraction of intra-abdominal pressure (Pabd) from intra-vesical pressure (Pves). All Pdet with an amplitude of at least 1cm of water, frequency below 0.2 Hz and pulse duration between 5 and 60 seconds qualify as NVA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify NVA in healthy and OAB subjects using conventional urodynamic assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>During High resolution and conventional urodynamic (Day 1) assessments</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the subjects bladder sensations measured by visual analogue scale (VAS) and 5-points categorical scale (Appendix 8 &amp; 7) during the high resolution urodynamic and conventional assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>During High resolution and conventional urodynamic assessments (Day 1)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the correlation between NVA and subjects bladder sensations</measure>
    <time_frame>During High resolution and conventional urodynamic assessments (Day 1)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Explore NVA in a subgroup of subjects defined by the severity of OAB symptoms collected as background information (3-days bladder diary)</measure>
    <time_frame>During High resolution and conventional urodynamic assessments (Day 1)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Illustrate the amount of NVA detected with high resolution urodynamic test methodology compared to NVA detected with conventional urodynamic assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>During High resolution and conventional urodynamic assessments (Day 1)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess symptoms severity, bother and its impact on quality of life using: OAB-Q short form and Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI-6) questionnaires and a 3-Day micturition bladder diary as background information to characterize the study population</measure>
    <time_frame>During High resolution and conventional urodynamic assessments (Day 1)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Subjects</condition>
  <condition>Overactive Bladder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: OAB subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Healthy subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: OAB subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High resolution urodynamic assessment</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: OAB subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Healthy subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: OAB subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional urodynamic assessment</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: OAB subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Healthy subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: OAB subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        OAB Subjects

          -  Has history of signs and symptoms of OAB including urinary frequency, urgency or urge
             incontinence for greater than or equal to 3 months

          -  At enrolment visit (V2) the subjects must have:

               -  At least 1 episode of urgency with or without incontinence in the last 3-day
                  micturition diary

               -  Frequency of micturition greater than or equal to 8 per 24 hours period during
                  the 3-day micturition diary period

          -  At the screening visit, the subject should be either naïve to OAB treatment (e.g no
             prior history of medications to treat lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS), including
             OAB) or currently on treatment for LUTS (including OAB) and is willing to undergo a
             washout period for 3 weeks

        Main Exclusion criteria:

        Healthy subjects

          -  History of lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS), including OAB

          -  History of stress urinary incontinence, urethral sphincter incompetence and neurogenic
             detrusor overactivity

          -  History of signs or symptoms suggestive of urinary tract infection (confirmed by
             positive urine analysis)

          -  History of bladder outlet obstruction (not including detrusor-overactivity) for
             example bladder/vesicouterine pro-lapse (&gt; grade II) or chronic obstruction

          -  History of urinary tract surgery less than or equal to 6 months prior to screening

          -  Has an indwelling catheter or permanent catheter fitted

          -  History of pelvic area radiotherapy treatment

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus

          -  History of fibromyalgia

          -  Pregnant or intends to become pregnant during the study or sexually active, of
             childbearing potential and is unwilling to utilize a reliable method of birth control
             (note: reliable methods are contraceptive pills of combination type, hormonal
             implants, injectable contraceptives, sexual abstinence or vasectomized partner)

          -  Pregnancy within 6 months before screening or breast feeding within 3 months before
             screening

          -  History of a positive hepatitis A, B surface antigen, hepatitis C antibody or HIV test
             result.

          -  Any use of drugs of abuse within 3 months prior to screening visit.

          -  History of smoking more than 10 cigarettes (or equivalent amount of tobacco) per day
             within 3 months prior to screening visit

          -  History of drinking more than 14 units of alcohol per week (1 unit = 10 g pure alcohol
             = 250 ml of beer (5%) or 35 ml of spirits (35%) or 100 ml of wine (12%) within 3
             months prior to screening visit

          -  Is currently receiving or has a history of treatment with alpha blockers, beta
             receptor blockers or agonists, botulinum toxin (less than 12 months), resiniferatoxin
             or pelvic floor muscle relaxants less than or equal to 9 months prior to screening

        Main exclusion criteria OAB subjects

          -  Refer to healthy subjects exclusion criteria number 2 to 16
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Study Manager</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Astellas Pharma Europe Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Principal Investigator</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maastricht University Medical Center, Maastricht</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <zip>6202</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.clinicaltrials.jp/user/ctrSearch_e.jsp</url>
    <description>Link to Results on JAPIC - enter 140629 in the JapicCTI-RNo. field</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 29, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 15, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>OAB</keyword>
  <keyword>High Resolution Urodynamics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

