<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01764191</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BCCA-Cardiac PET</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01764191</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>18F-FDG PET Imaging in Cardiac Sarcoidosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>[18 F]-Fluorodeoxyglucose (18F-FDG) Positron Emission Tomography (PET) in Cardiac Sarcoidosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>British Columbia Cancer Agency</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>British Columbia Cancer Agency</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study has been designed to provide patients suspected of having cardiac sarcoidosis (CS)
      with a potentially diagnostic 18F FDG PET/CT. CS is difficult to diagnose with currently
      available methods, therefore this project will allow access to 18F FDG PET/CT scanning, which
      may more accurately diagnose the presence of CS. This study will also provide additional data
      to further examine the effectiveness and safety profile of 18F FDG for this condition.
      Accurate and early detection is important to allow for better management of CS and improve
      patient care.

      The purpose of this study is to provide access to 18F-FDG PET/CT imaging in patients with
      clinical suspicion of cardiac sarcoidosis, and to collect additional data about the safety
      and effectiveness of 18F-FDG PET/CT in this patient population
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Purpose:The purpose of this study is to provide access to 18F-FDG PET/CT imaging in
           patients with clinical suspicion of cardiac sarcoidosis, and to collect additional data
           about the safety and effectiveness of 18F-FDG PET/CT in this patient population.

        2. Hypothesis:18F-FDG PET/CT has greater sensitivity, specificity, and accuracy compared to
           the current clinical gold standard of diagnosis for CS, the Japanese Ministry of Health,
           Labour, and Welfare (MHLW) guidelines

        3. Justification:Currently a clinical diagnosis CS is diagnosed using a combination of
           diagnostic techniques including imaging and biopsy. Biopsies are challenging as it can
           be difficult to locate the disease or access the desired biopsy location. MRI has been
           proven effective but it is limited as patients with pacemakers and
           cardioverter-defibrillators or patients with renal impairments are unable to have an
           MRI. Finally radionuclide scintigraphy with Gallium-67 or Thallium-201 (201Tl) has been
           useful, but can be non-specific for sarcoidosis. 18F-FDG PET/CT has significant
           advantages over other radionuclide imaging modalities due to superior resolution of PET
           coupled with the affinity of inflammatory cardiac tissue to metabolize FDG. 18F-FDG
           PET/CT has been found to have higher sensitivity and specificity over other
           conventionally used imaging modalities.

        4. Research Method:This will be an expanded access study in which adult subjects with a
           clinical suspicion of CS will be invited to participate, in order to identify potential
           sites for biopsy or provide confirmation of the presence of CS. Based on population
           extrapolation from all diagnosed or suspected cases of CS in British Columbia (BC), as
           well as expert clinical opinion, it is estimated that 10 to 15 patients per year will be
           enrolled in the study. Over a three year period, the expected sample size will be 30 -
           45 patients. All subjects will receive an 18F-FDG PET/CT at the BC Cancer Agency (BCCA)
           - Vancouver Centre.

        5. Statistical Analysis:The planned sample size is 150 patients. The primary endpoint is to
           provide PET/CT imaging to patients diagnosed with or suspected of CS. The secondary
           end-point will be to assess the sensitivity, specificity and accuracy of 18F-FDG PET in
           BC population. Confidence intervals of 95% will be used to assess this using exact
           binomial distribution. All analyses will be performed in direct consultation with a
           qualified statistician.

      Sensitivity (ratio of true positive lesions to total positive lesions), specificity (ratio of
      true negative lesions to total negative lesions) and accuracy (ratio of total correct studies
      to the total number of biopsied lesions) of 18F-FDG PET studies performed by the BCCA will be
      obtained by comparing results of the PET scan with a composite of the outcome of clinical
      examinations, histopathological diagnosis, if those results are available, and results of all
      other available imaging (cardiac MRI, 201Tl, 67Ga). Confidence intervals (95% CI) for
      sensitivity, specificity and accuracy will be calculated using exact binomial distribution.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>No longer available</overall_status>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiac Sarcoidosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>18F-Fluorodeoxyglucose (18F-FDG) PET/CT</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects suspected of cardiac sarcoidosis will receive an intravenous dose of 18F-FDG (determined by weight, but not to exceed 521 MBq). Following an uptake phase of about 60 minutes, each subject will receive a PET/CT scan to evaluate the presence of cardiac sarcoidosis.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 19 years or older.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group(ECOG) performance status 0 - 3.

          -  Able to provide written informed consent.

          -  Patients must be able to tolerate the physical/logistical requirements of completing a
             PET scan including lying flat for up to 45 minutes and tolerating intravenous
             cannulation for injection.

          -  Clinical suspicion of cardiac sarcoidosis, including a combination of:

               -  Patients with systemic sarcoidosis and symptoms suggestive of heart failure (eg.
                  fatigue, dyspnea, edema etc.)

               -  Idiopathic heart failure, particularly of preserved systolic function variety

               -  Presentation with arrhythmia (eg. heart block, ventricular tachycardia, etc.)

               -  Progressive heart failure symptoms not responding to conventional therapy

               -  Other clinical presentations where in the experience of treating cardiologist
                  cardiac sarcoid needs to be ruled out (ie. Heart transplant or ventricular assist
                  device candidacy)

          -  Routine tests for CS are inconclusive, such as:

               -  ECG

               -  Holter

               -  echocardiogram

               -  67Ga scintigraphy is inconclusive

               -  Cardiac MRI is inconclusive or not possible to conduct

          -  Patient has renal dysfunction which limits other radionuclide imaging.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients blood glucose &gt; 11.1 mmol/L (200 mg/dL) measured by glucometer immediately
             prior to scan.

          -  Patients with confirmed diabetes.

          -  Patients unable to comply with the dietary modifications or prolonged fasting as per
             trial protocol.

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Patients who are medically unstable eg. acute cardiac or respiratory distress, or
             hypotensive.

          -  Patients who exceed the safe weight limit of the PET/CT bed (204.5 kg) or who cannot
             fit through the PET/CT machine (diameter 70 cm).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BC Cancer Agency</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 4E6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 3, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 30, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluorodeoxyglucose F18</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

