<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01762852</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>114674</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01762852</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Study of Intravenous Belimumab Versus Placebo in Subjects With Idiopathic Membranous Nephropathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>BEL114674: A 2 Year Study of Efficacy and Safety of Intravenous Belimumab Versus Placebo in Subjects With Idiopathic Membranous Nephropathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main clinical study will be a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, long term
      study involving a 100 week treatment period. The purpose of this study is to test for
      superiority of treatment with belimumab 10 mg/kg plus supportive therapy compared to placebo
      plus supportive therapy in idiopathic membranous nephropathy (IMN). The purpose of this study
      is also to investigate the effect of initiating earlier treatment with belimumab compared to
      delayed treatment with current immunosuppressive treatment regimens. The study will also
      determine the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of belimumab and further explore the mechanism of
      action of Belimumab as well as effects on quality of life. All subjects (on either active
      treatment or placebo) will receive background supportive therapy throughout the main clinical
      study, which includes angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEi) and/or angiotensin
      receptor blockers (ARBs) unless contraindicated and may include statins, diuretics, dietary
      salt restriction but excludes immunosuppressants (except low dose corticosteroids). Screening
      will be done within 5 to 2 weeks before the first scheduled dose of study treatment. A total
      of 94 evaluable subjects will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio such that 47 subjects receive
      intravenous belimumab 10 mg/kg and 47 receive intravenous placebo. Subjects will be dosed on
      Days 0, 14, 28 and then every 4 weeks through to, and including, Week 100, resulting in a
      total of 27 doses (giving 104 weeks of drug exposure). The dosing frequency will be adjusted
      to every 2 weeks if the subject's proteinuria as assessed by urinary protein creatinine ratio
      (PCR) is greater than 1000mg/mmol (greater than 10 g/24 h), to compensate for loss of
      belimumab in the urine. Subjects who are withdrawn from study treatment at any time during
      the study, eg for rescue therapy, will participate in follow-up visits every 12 weeks up to
      week 104. A subject will be regarded as having completed the main clinical study if they
      complete all phases of the main clinical study (screening, treatment period, 4 week and 16
      week post last dose short term safety follow-up). Subjects who complete the main clinical
      study will therefore participate in the main clinical study for approximately 28 months.
      After the main clinical study, there will be a 5 year (long term) follow-up phase to assess
      long term outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Withdrawn due to difficulties in to recruiting due to competing studies, changing treatment
    practices, unavailability of eligible study population
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of remission (complete [CR] or partial [PR]) at Week (WK) 104</measure>
    <time_frame>104 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>CR: urine protein to creatinine ratio (uPCR) &lt;30 mg/mmol (proteinuria &lt;0.3 g/24 hr) with no worsening of renal function (&lt;15% estimated glomerular filtration rate [eGFR] reduction from baseline [BL]).PR: uPCR &lt;350 mg/mmol (proteinuria &lt;3.5g/24 hrs) but &gt;=30 mg/mmol (proteinuria &gt;=0.3g/24 hrs) AND a decrease of &gt;50% from BL based on uPCR, with no worsening of renal function. uPCR: Mean from 2 consecutive 24 hr urine collections (pre and post dose or pre and post visit). eGFR: BL will be defined as mean of screening and Day 0 values. For WK 104 assessment, will be analysed at both WK 100 and 104</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of progression of IMN or failure to respond</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by at least one of the following:1.Persistent symptomatic nephrotic syndrome potentially necessitating rescue therapy 2.End Stage Renal Disease (eGFR &lt;15 mL/min/1.73m^2,dialysis or transplantation).3.Clinical thromboembolic events. 4.Death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to complete remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Complete Remission (CR) is defined as uPCR &lt;30 mg/mmol (proteinuria &lt;0.3 g/24 hrs) with no worsening of renal function (less than 15% reduction in estimated eGFR from baseline)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to partial remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Partial Remission (PR) is defined as uPCR &lt;350 mg/mmol (proteinuria &lt;3.5 g/24 hrs) but &gt;=30 mg/mmol (proteinuria &gt;=0.3g/24 hrs) AND a decrease of &gt;50% from baseline (Day 0) based on uPCR, together with no worsening of renal function (less than 15% reduction in eGFR from baseline)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in proteinuria levels at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 and Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Mean uPCR from 2 consecutive 24 hr urine collections (pre and post dose or pre and post visit)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in serum albumin levels at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 and Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Albumin levels will be measured to determine hypoalbuminaemia. Baseline will be defined as mean of screening and Day 0 values. For the week 104 assessment, albumin will be analyzed at both weeks 100 and 104.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in eGFR at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 and Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline will be defined as mean of screening and Day 0 values. For the week 104 assessment, eGFR will be analyzed at both weeks 100 and 104.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first thromboembolic event</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Thromboembolism is a formation in a blood vessel of a clot (thrombus) that breaks loose and is carried by the blood stream to plug another vessel. Thromboembolic event is a complication of nephrotic syndrome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in KDQOL-36 score at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 and Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>The Kidney Disease Quality of Life (KDQOL- 36) consists of the SF-12 Physical Health and Mental Health Composite scores along with the Burden of Kidney Disease and Effects of Kidney Disease subscales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of partial remission at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Partial Remission (PR) is defined as uPCR &lt;350 mg/mmol (proteinuria &lt;3.5g/24 hrs) but &gt;=30 mg/mmol (proteinuria &gt;=0.3 g/24 hrs) AND a decrease of &gt;50% from baseline (Day 0) based on uPCR, together with no worsening of renal function (less than 15% reduction in eGFR from baseline)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of complete remission at Week 104</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>Complete Remission (CR) is defined as uPCR &lt;30 mg/mmol (proteinuria &lt;0.3 g/24 hrs) with no worsening of renal function (less than 15% reduction in estimated eGFR from baseline)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of remission (complete or partial)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of remission (complete or partial) will be assessed to evaluate length of effect of belimumab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk-benefit calculation based on key efficacy and safety endpoints using a clinical utility index</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>A clinical utility index will be developed to objectively measure benefit over standard practice in a quantitative manner.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>SAEs are medical occurrences not due to the disease (unless more severe than expected), but which result in death, disability, incapacity, are life threatening, require or prolong hospitalization, are associated with specified liver injury/impaired function and other defined criteria. SAEs beyond Week 104 will be assessed as 'Other endpoints' or 'Long Term Follow-up endpoints'</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events (AEs) of special interest</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Week 104</time_frame>
    <description>AEs of special interest will include: Serious infusion reactions/hypersensitivity/anaphylaxis, fatal events; serious malignancies; serious infections including herpes zoster; cardiovascular SAEs (fatal and non-fatal events) including arrhythmia, congestive heart failure, cerebrovascular accident, deep vein thrombosis, myocardial infarction/unstable angina, peripheral arterial thromboembolism, revascularization; SAEs suggestive of suicidal or self-harming behavior</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety assessed by evaluation of Adverse events, clinical laboratory assessments, vital signs and immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 116 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability assessed by evaluation of adverse events (AE), clinical laboratory assessments (clinical chemistry, haematology and urinalysis), vital signs and immunogenicity. Including infusion-related and hypersensitivity reactions, infections and malignancies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival without renal progression</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of treatment up to 7 years</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will be followed annually for 5 years after Week 104 in the main clinical study or until ESRD or death, whichever is earlier for analysis of survival without renal progression. Survival without renal progression will be defined as the time from start of treatment until decrease in eGFR from baseline at entry into the study by greater than 20% OR end stage renal disease (eGFR &lt;15 mL/min/1.73 m^2, start of dialysis or renal transplantation) OR death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Glomerulonephritis, Membranous</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Belimumab Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive belimumab 10 mg/kg intravenous infusion [will last for 1 hour (hr)] on Day 0, Week 2, Week 4, then every 4 weeks for up to 100 weeks with frequency adjusted for subjects with &gt;1000 mg/mmol uPCR (&gt;10 g/24 hrs). All subjects will receive background supportive therapy throughout the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intravenous infusion (will last for 1 hr) on Day 0, Week 2, Week 4, then every 4 weeks for up to 100 weeks with frequency adjusted for subjects with &gt;1000 mg/mmol uPCR (&gt;10 g/24 hrs). All subjects will receive background supportive therapy throughout the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Belimumab 10 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Belimumab is Lyophilised powder for reconstitution in 4.8 mL sterile water for injection (SWFI) and diluted in normal saline (250 mL). 400 mg per vial plus excipients (citric acid/sodium citrate/sucrose/polysorbate). Belimumab 10 mg/kg intravenous infusion (will last for 1 hr) on Day 0, Week 2, Week 4, then every 4 weeks for up to 100 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Belimumab Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Normal saline solution (sodium chloride 154 mmol/L). Intravenous infusion (will last for 1 hr) on Day 0, Week 2, Week 4, then every 4 weeks for up to 100 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &amp; Gender: Male or female between 18 and 75 years of age inclusive, at the time of
             signing the informed consent.

          -  Histological diagnosis: Have clinical diagnosis of IMN, as verified by biopsy (either
             by light microscope with immuno-fluorescence, or by electron microscope) in the last 3
             years (biopsy results [and slides where possible] should be available for independent
             evaluation). For patients with relapsed disease, a biopsy should be available within
             the preceding 7 years.

          -  Proteinuria: Have clinically active disease (nephrotic range proteinuria) for at least
             3 months prior to screening and no improvement (&lt;30% reduction), despite supportive
             therapy (which must include maximal tolerated doses of ACE inhibitor or ARB unless
             contraindicated, and may include statins, diuretics, dietary salt restriction). During
             screening proteinuria must be &gt;400 mg/mmol by uPCR (or &gt;4.0 g per 24 hrs) as measured
             from a 24 hrs urine collection and/or spot urine sample (early morning where possible)
             on 2 occasions at least 7 days apart.

          -  Proteinuria in patients with relapsed disease: Patients who previously achieved
             proteinuria &lt;2 g per 24h for at least 6 months and have subsequently relapsed with
             proteinuria levels as documented above, may be eligible providing recurrence has been
             within the previous 3 years and patient is known to be anti-PLA2R positive.

          -  Female Subject is eligible to participate if she is not pregnant or nursing; is
             non-childbearing potential. Females of child-bearing potential must agree to use one
             of the approved contraception methods for an appropriate period of time (as determined
             by the product label or investigator) prior to the start of dosing to sufficiently
             minimise the risk of pregnancy at that point. Female subjects must agree to use
             contraception until 16 weeks after the last dose.

          -  French subjects: In France, a subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study
             only if either affiliated to or a beneficiary of a social security category.

          -  Inclusion Criteria for Long Term Follow-up: Subjects who have signed informed consent
             for the Long Term Follow-up and have completed 2 years study treatment and the 16 week
             follow-up visit, or who have withdrawn early from study treatment but completed the
             Week 104 Withdrawn visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-Idiopathic MN or other condition affecting the kidney: If the diagnosis of MN is
             secondary to other conditions, or the subject has renal impairment from a condition
             that is not MN. Causes of secondary MN include (but are not limited to) Immune
             diseases (Systemic lupus erythematosus, diabetes mellitus; rheumatoid arthritis,
             Hashimoto's disease, Grave's disease, mixed connective tissue disease, Sjogren's
             syndrome, primary biliary cirrhosis, bullous pemphigoid, small bowel enteropathy
             syndrome, dermatitis herpetiformis, ankylosing spondylitis, graft-versus-host-disease,
             Guillain-Barre syndrome); or Infectious or parasitic diseases (Hepatitis B; Hepatitis
             C, syphilis, filariasis, hydatid disease, schistosomiasis, malaria, leprosy); or Drugs
             and toxins (Gold, penicillamine, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents, mercury,
             captopril, formaldehyde, hydrocarbons, bucillamine); or Miscellaneous(Tumors excluded
             with reasonable diligence, renal transplantation, sarcoidosis, sickle cell disease,
             Kimura disease, angiofollicular lymph node hyperplasia).

          -  Anti-PLA2R autoantibody: Patients known to be negative for anti-PLA2R autoantibody.

          -  Severely reduced or deteriorating kidney function: An eGFR at screening &lt;40
             mL/min/1.73m^2 (as determined by 4 variable version MDRD equation) or kidney function
             not stable (as defined by &gt;15% decrease in eGFR in 3 months before screening unless
             due to medication change).

          -  Blood Pressure: Uncontrolled hypertension defined as blood pressure (BP) &gt;150/90 mmHg
             (treatment target &lt;=140/80)

          -  Prior Therapy: Have received treatment with the following therapies at the times
             specified prior to Day 0: Therapy - B-cell targeted therapy except rituximab (e.g.,
             other anti- CD20 agents, anti-CD22 [epratuzumab], anti-CD52 [alemtuzumab],
             BLyS-receptor fusion protein [BR3], TACI Fc, or belimumab), Time period: anytime;
             Therapy: Rituximab (subjects with rituximab treatment between 1 and 2 years prior to
             Day 0 are eligible if there is documented evidence of B-cell repopulation to &gt;50% of
             pre-treatment levels), Period: 2 years; Therapy: Abatacept and any other biologic
             investigational agent other than B cell targeted therapy (i.e. not approved for sale
             in the country in which it is being used), Time Period: 364 days; Therapy:
             Cyclophosphamide or chlorambucil 3 or more courses of systemic corticosteroids for
             concomitant conditions (e.g., asthma, atopic dermatitis). (Topical or inhaled steroids
             are permitted.), Time Period: 180 days; Therapy: Anti-tumour necrosis factor (TNF) or
             anti-IL-6 therapy (e.g. adalimumab, etanercept, infliximab, tocilizumab).
             Interleukin-1 receptor antagonists (e.g. anakinra). Other
             immunosuppressive/immunomodulatory agents (e.g azathioprine, 6-mercaptopurine,
             mycophenolate mofetil (PO)/ mycophenolate mofetil hydrochloride (IV), mycophenolate
             sodium (PO), methotrexate, tacrolimus, sirolimus, thalidomide, leflunomide,
             mizoribine, ciclosporin). Intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG). Plasmapheresis,
             leukapheresis, Time Period: 90 days; Therapy: A non-biologic investigational agent
             (i.e. not approved for sale in the country in which it is being used). Intravenous
             corticosteroid, Adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH). Aliskiren. A change in dose of
             &gt;50% for angiotensin pathway antihypertensive (e.g., ACE inhibitor, angiotensin
             receptor blocker), Time Period: 60 days; Therapy: A live vaccine. Greater than
             30mg/day corticosteroid, Time Period: 30 days; Therapy: Greater than 10mg/day
             corticosteroid. A change in dose of a corticosteroid. Note: Changes to inhaled
             steroids and new topical immunosuppressive agents (e.g., eye drops, topical creams)
             are allowed, Time Period: 14 days.

          -  Transplantation: Have a history of a major organ transplant (e.g., heart, lung,
             kidney, liver) or hematopoietic stem cell/marrow transplant.

          -  Cancer: Have a history of malignant neoplasm within the last 5 years, except for
             adequately treated cancers of the skin (basal or squamous cell) or carcinoma in situ
             of the uterine cervix.

          -  Acute or chronic infection: Have required management of acute or chronic infections
             such as currently on any suppressive therapy for a chronic infection such as
             tuberculosis, pneumocystis, cytomegalovirus, herpes simplex virus, herpes zoster and
             atypical mycobacteria); or hospitalisation for treatment of infection within 60 days
             prior to Day 0; or use of parenteral (IV or IM) antibiotics (anti-bacterials,
             anti-virals, anti-fungals, or anti-parasitic agents) within 60 days prior to Day 0.

          -  Liver disease: Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or
             biliary abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic
             gallstones).

          -  Other diseases/conditions: Have clinical evidence of significant unstable or
             uncontrolled acute or chronic diseases not due to IMN (i.e., cardiovascular,
             pulmonary, haematologic, gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, neurological, malignancy or
             infectious diseases) which, in the opinion of the investigator, could confound the
             results of the study or put the subject at undue risk; or have a planned surgical
             procedure or a history of any other medical disease (e.g. cardiopulmonary), laboratory
             abnormality, or condition (e.g., poor venous access) that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, makes the subject unsuitable for the study.

          -  Positive serology: Have a historically positive HIV test or test positive at screening
             for HIV. Serologic evidence of Hepatitis B (HB) infection based on the results of
             testing for HBsAg, anti-HBc and anti-HBs. Positive test for Hepatitis C antibody
             confirmed on the same sample with a Hepatitis C RIBA immunoblot assay if available.

          -  Liver function tests: Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase
             (ALT) &gt;=2x upper limit of normal (ULN); alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN
             (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5ULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct
             bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Immunodeficiency: Have an IgA deficiency (IgA level &lt; 10 mg/dL) or have IgG level &lt;250
             mg/dL and have previously received any non-glucocorticoid immunosuppression during the
             previous 6 months.

          -  Laboratory test abnormalities: Have clinically significant abnormalities in screening
             laboratory assessments (not related to the disease), as judged by investigator.

          -  Drug sensitivity / Anaphylaxis: History of sensitivity or intolerance to any of the
             study medications, or components thereof or a history of drug or other allergy that,
             in the opinion of the investigator or GSK Medical Monitor, contraindicates their
             participation. History of an anaphylactic reaction to parenteral administration of
             contrast agents, human or murine proteins or monoclonal antibodies.

          -  Suicidality: Subjects who have evidence of serious suicide risk including any history
             of suicidal behaviour in the last 6 months and/or any suicide ideation of type 4 or 5
             on the Columbia Suicide-Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) in the last 2 months or who in
             the investigator's judgement, pose a significant suicide risk.

          -  Substance abuse: Evidence of current drug or alcohol abuse or dependence.

          -  Blood donation: Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or
             blood products in excess of 500 mL within a 56 day period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Lambton</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2305</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 5A5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha 2</city>
        <zip>128 08</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amiens cedex 1</city>
        <zip>80054</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Créteil Cedex</city>
        <zip>94010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris Cedex 15</city>
        <zip>75743</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse Cedex 9</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
        <zip>68167</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <state>Baden-Wuerttemberg</state>
        <zip>89081</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muenchen</city>
        <state>Bayern</state>
        <zip>80336</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuerzburg</city>
        <state>Bayern</state>
        <zip>97080</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aachen</city>
        <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
        <zip>52074</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Solingen</city>
        <state>Nordrhein-Westfalen</state>
        <zip>42653</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lecco</city>
        <state>Lombardia</state>
        <zip>23900</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lido di Camaiore (LU)</city>
        <state>Toscana</state>
        <zip>55041</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1081 HV</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6525 GA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>L'Hospitalet de Llobregat</city>
        <zip>08907</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46017</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cardiff</city>
        <zip>CF14 4XW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gloucester</city>
        <zip>GL1 3NN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leicester</city>
        <zip>LE5 4PW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW3 2QG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE5 9RS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reading</city>
        <zip>RG1 5AN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 4, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 8, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Benlysta</keyword>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>proteinuria</keyword>
  <keyword>Idiopathic membranous nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK1550188</keyword>
  <keyword>anti-phospholipase A2 receptor antibodies</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>BLyS</keyword>
  <keyword>belimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphostat-B</keyword>
  <keyword>membrane attack complex</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis, Membranous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Belimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

