<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01101399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FER-FID-CHEMO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01101399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ferric Carboxymaltose in Subjects With Functional Iron Deficiency Undergoing Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>FID-CHEMO</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomised Controlled Open-label Study to Evaluate Efficacy &amp; Safety of Intravenous Ferric Carboxymaltose Versus no Treatment in Anaemic Subjects With Lymphoid Malignancies &amp; Functional Iron Deficiency Receiving Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vifor Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vifor Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Anaemia and functional iron deficiency are common conditions in patients with lymphoid
      malignancies, conditions which reduce significantly the quality of life and increase
      morbidity and mortality. Traditionally, Erythropoiesis Stimulating Agents (ESAs) have been
      used, but recently their use has been shown to have a negative impact on overall survival in
      different oncology populations. Recently published data suggest that intravenous (IV) iron
      can be effective in anaemia treatment, even without ESAs. This exploratory study is the first
      clinical project with ferric carboxymaltose (FCM) in patients with lymphoid malignancies: the
      data generated may be used for further evaluations of the drug in larger populations. In this
      study, 1,000 mg of IV iron as FCM will be administered on the same day or within 24 hours
      before or after chemotherapy treatment. The primary objective is to evaluate the efficacy of
      FCM in the correction of haemoglobin levels in anaemic subjects with lymphoid malignancies,
      undergoing chemotherapy. Secondary objectives aim to describe the safety and tolerability of
      FCM, and the effect of FCM treatment on iron status variables in subjects suffering from
      lymphoid malignancies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multicentre, randomised, controlled, 2-arm open-label prospective pilot study to evaluate
      efficacy and safety of FCM in the treatment of anaemia in LPD subjects with functional iron
      deficiency (FID), undergoing chemotherapy. The subjects will be screened for eligibility
      within 4 weeks prior to inclusion to receive intravenous (IV) infusions of FCM or no FCM
      infusions (the subjects may be treated according to the local institutional practice if
      requiring symptomatic management of anaemia). After randomisation, the visits are scheduled
      weekly until Week 8.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in haemoglobin from baseline to Week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4 post baseline</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects with blood haemoglobin increase of at least 1 g/dL in the absence of any red cell transfusion or ESA treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in haemoglobin from baseline to Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in haemoglobin from baseline to Week 8</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">19</enrollment>
  <condition>Iron-Deficiency Anemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ferric carboxymaltose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a total dose of 1,000 mg iron as FCM on the day of the next scheduled chemotherapy cycle after randomisation or continuous chemotherapy. In subjects with weight ≤66 kg, the first dose iron will be 500 mg; the second dose (500 mg) will be administered on the visit 4 (week 2).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Local standard of care.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be treated according to the local institutional practice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ferric carboxymaltose</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single dose of 1,000 mg iron as FCM infusion at baseline.
Subjects of bw ≤66 kg will receive a single dose of 500 mg iron as FCM infusion at baseline (Week 0) and at Visit 4 (Week 2).
Ferric carboxymaltose will be administered on the same day with chemotherapy treatment or within 24 hours before or after the chemotherapy. For subjects with bw ≤66 kg, if no chemotherapy planned for the visit 4 (Week 2), the second FCM dose should be infused independent of chemotherapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ferric carboxymaltose</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ferinject</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects (male or female) aged ≥18, suffering from indolent non-Hodgkin's lymphoma,
             multiple myeloma or chronic lymphocytic leukaemia on any chemotherapy excluding
             anthracycline containing.

          -  Life expectancy at least 6 months.

          -  Received at least 12 weeks (or 3 cycles) of treatment in the current course of
             chemotherapy before start of iron therapy.

          -  8.5 g/dL Hb 10.5 g/dL at time of randomisation.

          -  Iron-restricted erythropoiesis as defined:

               -  Stainable iron in bone marrow combined with transferrin saturation (TSAT) ≤20% OR

               -  where the evaluation of stainable iron in bone marrow is not possible or
                  available:

                    -  ferritin &gt;30 ng/mL (women) or &gt;40 ng/mL (men) and

                    -  TSAT ≤20%

          -  Signed informed consent (before any study procedure).

          -  Females of child-bearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any anaemia treatment within 4 weeks before inclusion (including red blood cell
             transfusion, ESA treatment and any oral/parenteral iron supplementation).

          -  Subjects weighing &lt;35 kg.

          -  Subjects with increase in Hb during the chemotherapy (&gt;1 g/dL rise between initiation
             of CT and screening laboratory value).

          -  Folate deficiency (serum folate &lt;4.5 nmol/L) and/or vitamin B12 deficiency (serum
             cobalamin &lt;145 pmol/L).

          -  Ongoing haemolysis defined as serum haptoglobin &lt;0.2 g/L.

          -  Recent significant bleeding/surgery.

          -  Monotherapy with immunotherapy agents.

          -  Known chronic renal failure, creatinine &gt;125 μmol/L.

          -  Anthracycline containing chemotherapy regimens.

          -  Clinically relevant active inflammatory disease other than the malignant disease
             (according to the judgement of the Investigator).

          -  Clinically relevant ongoing infectious disease including known human immunodeficiency
             virus.

          -  Serum-ferritin &gt;800 ng/mL.

          -  Ongoing significant neurological or psychiatric disorders including psychotic
             disorders or dementia.

          -  Significant cardiovascular disease prior to study inclusion including myocardial
             infarction within 12 months prior to study inclusion, congestive heart failure New
             York Heart Association (NYHA) Grade III or IV, or poorly controlled hypertension
             according to the judgment of the Investigator.

          -  Elevation of liver enzymes (aspartate aminotransferase, alanine aminotransferase) over
             3 times above the normal range or known acute hepatic disorder.

          -  Subject currently is enrolled in or has not yet completed at least 30 days since
             ending other investigational device or drug study(ies), or subject is receiving other
             investigational agent(s).

          -  Females who are evidently pregnant (e.g., positive HCG test) or are breast feeding.

          -  Subject is not using adequate contraceptive precautions. Adequate contraceptive
             precautions are defined as those which result in a low failure rate (i.e., less than
             1% per year) when used consistently and correctly such as implants, injectables,
             combined oral contraceptives, some intra-uterine devices, sexual abstinence or
             vasectomised partner. Non-childbearing potential includes being surgically sterilised
             at least 6 months prior to the study or post menopausal, defined as amenorrhea for at
             least 12 months.

          -  Subject has known sensitivity to any of the products to be administered during dosing.

          -  Subject will not be available for follow-up assessment.

          -  Subject has any kind of disorder that compromises the ability of the subject to give
             written informed consent and/or to comply with study procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Torbjörn Karlsson, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Capio St Görans Sjukhus, Stockholm</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Morgan McNamara</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Vifor Pharma, CH-8152 Glattbrugg, Switzerland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Medicine, St Görans Hospital (Capio St Görans Sjukhus)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>SE-112 81</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 8, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 16, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 16, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoproliferative Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>ferric carboxymaltose</keyword>
  <keyword>iron</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Iron-Deficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Iron</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ferric Compounds</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

