<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01107327</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HCI18327</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA121003-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01107327</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG)-Positron Emission Tomography (PET) in Cancer Associated Venothromboembolism</brief_title>
  <official_title>FDG PET in Cancer Associated Venothromboembolism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Venothromboembolic disease (VTE), which includes deep venous thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary
      embolism (PE), is a severe health problem, effecting 1.5/1000 per year in the general
      population. In patients over 60 years of age, the incidence is 1/100 per year. Of the two
      million Americans per year who will develop VTE, one third will develop pulmonary embolism
      (PE). VTE is usually diagnosed by Doppler ultrasound or contrast venography when present in
      the extremities, VQ scan or pulmonary angiography when PE is present. However, there are many
      instances when the diagnosis of VTE by conventional modalities is limited. These include
      obesity, recent trauma or surgery, the presence of a mass, the presence of clot around
      central lines, and clot occurring in the abdomen and pelvis. Furthermore, the differentiation
      between new and old clot has evaded all diagnostic imaging modalities, and no existing
      modality allows for an accurate delineation of all sites of thrombus within the body. New
      approaches to the diagnostic imaging of VTE in complicated cases are needed. The first
      hypothesis of this project is that FDG PET/CT can be used to accurately diagnose the presence
      and extent of acute VTE, and that it will distinguish new clot from old.

      Approximately 20-25% of all new cases of venous thromboembolism occur in known cancer
      patients. The risk of VTE is 4-6 fold greater in patients with cancer as those without (8-12%
      vs. 2%, respectively, lifetime risk). In many cases, the development of VTE occurs as the
      first clinical sign of the cancer, even before it is diagnosed. Among patients presenting
      with acute VTE have no obvious cause (defined as &quot;idiopathic&quot; or &quot;unprovoked&quot;, as opposed to
      &quot;secondary&quot; VTE), the literature reports that up to 20% (range of reported incidence 7-20%)
      may ultimately prove to have cancer, depending on the series and whether the thrombosis is
      unifocal or multifocal. Despite the substantial prevalence of occult cancer in patients
      presenting with idiopathic VTE, there are no current recommendations that these patients be
      screened for the presence of cancer. The second hypothesis of the project is that FDG PET/CT
      can accurately be used to screen for the presence of cancer in patients with unprovoked
      (idiopathic) acute VTE.

      Objectives:

      There are two specific objectives to test the hypotheses associated with this project:

        1. To establish the sensitivity of FDG PET/CT in the diagnosis of acute VTE.

        2. To perform a pilot project to aid in the design of a larger trial to define the
           incidence of occult cancer in patients rigorously selected for idiopathic (unprovoked)
           VTE, and to investigate the value of FDG PET in the early detection of occult cancer in
           this population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study AIM #1 To establish the sensitivity of FDG PET/CT in the diagnosis of acute VTE.

      Rationale: We believe that FDG PET/CT can be used to accurately diagnose the presence,
      extent, and acuity of VTE. It is unrealistic to assume that FDG-PET could or should become
      the primary imaging modality for evaluating VTE. The cost, compared to Doppler ultrasound,
      would be prohibitive, and would involve unnecessary radiation of the patient. We intend to
      establish the value of FDG PET, instead, as an alternative modality for the diagnosis of VTE.
      Clinical situations where this might prove useful include: 1) the presence of old clot, when
      the distinction between new and old may be important; 2) evaluation of abdominal, pelvic and
      thoracic thrombus, where Doppler is difficult-to-impossible because of patient obesity; 3)
      Complicated anatomy due to the presence of tumor or post-therapeutic changes.

      The sensitivity of FDG PET/CT will be established in patients with acute VTE. The accuracy
      with which sites of abnormal FDG uptake can be related, spatially, to vascular structures
      will be critical to the success of this study. There is little doubt that this can better be
      accomplished with PET/CT than with PET alone. PET/CT will be used for all of these studies.
      Patients with documented acute VTE, will be enrolled. To determine the utility of FDG PET/CT
      in distinguishing acute from subacute or chronic clot, and to establish the extent of acute
      clot, the initial whole body PET/CT scan must be performed within 2 weeks of onset of
      symptoms of DVT, and subsequent limited region PET/CT scans will be performed at 2-3 weeks
      and at 6 weeks following the initial PET/CT scan. Whenever possible, subjects will be
      recruited who have unprovoked VTE because the potential benefit to the patient for
      participating in this study will be greatest for these patients are at a higher risk for
      harboring an underlying occult malignancy. However, patients with both provoked and
      unprovoked VTE will be eligible for enrollment under this specific aim.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy of FDG PET/CT scanning to diagnose presence, extent, and acuity of Ventothromboembolism diagnosis.</measure>
    <time_frame>April 2012</time_frame>
    <description>We believe that FDG PET/CT can be used to accurately diagnose the presence, extent, and acuity of VTE. We intend to establish the value of FDG PET, instead, as an alternative modality for the diagnosis of VTE. Clinical situations where this might prove useful include: 1) the presence of old clot, when the distinction between new and old may be important; 2) evaluation of abdominal, pelvic and thoracic thrombus, where Doppler is difficult-to-impossible because of patient obesity; 3) Complicated anatomy due to the presence of tumor or post-therapeutic changes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Venothromboembolism</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FDG-PET/CT</intervention_name>
    <description>The study is focused on two goals, both of which use a new imaging test called PET/CT. PET/CT combines a special radioactive scan with a CT scan. PET/CT is most commonly used in medical practice to evaluate cancer. Abnormal areas such as cancer &quot;light up&quot; on the PET/CT scan. However, many doctors, including us, have noticed that PET/CT also &quot;lights up&quot; in areas of blood clot formation as well. In this study, PET/CT will be used to evaluate the two goals of this project.</description>
    <other_name>PET scan,</other_name>
    <other_name>PET/CT scan</other_name>
    <other_name>FDG-PET/CT scan</other_name>
    <other_name>FDG-PET</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be eligible either with provoked or unprovoked DVT.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Inclusion criteria will include documented acute DVT (+/-PE) by Doppler ultrasound or
             contrast venography.

          2. Subjects will be eligible either with provoked or unprovoked DVT.

          3. To meet the inclusion criteria, patients must be enrolled and the initial PET/CT scan
             performed within 2 weeks of initial onset of symptoms of VTE.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects less than 18 years of age,

          2. Those who are unable to understand and provide signature informed consent

          3. Pregnant subjects. Any female of childbearing age who has a uterus and functional
             ovaries will undergo a serum pregnancy test prior to inclusion. 4. Subjects with
             calf-only blood clot will be excluded, due to the fact that these cases are often
             complicated by venous stasis disease, post-phlebitic syndrome, and the presence of
             both acute and chronic clot, which may compromise interpretation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathryn Morton, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah Huntsman Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 29, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 29, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

