<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01105572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Biomonitoring099</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01105572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Aetna_Intel Medicare Home Biomonitoring Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of Impact of Home Biomonitoring With Nurse Case Manager Support for a Congestive Heart Failure Cohort, Compared to Case Manager Support Without Biomonitoring</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aetna, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Intel Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Aetna, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The hypothesis is that use of Internet-connected home biomonitoring of weight, blood pressure
      and other indicators, in conjunction with nurse case management, will result in improved
      outcome for Medicare beneficiaries with with Congestive Heart Failure; compared to case
      management assistance without the biomonitoring device.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Goals of the Study:

        -  Demonstrate synergy between the Intel速 Health Guide home biomonitoring and nurse case
           management. Measure positive impact on member engagement and clinical outcomes for
           members with Heart Failure.

        -  Quantify the potential to avoid costly re-hospitalization based on the Intel速 Health
           Guide - enhanced case management interaction through early alerts and early
           intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to acute hospital admission</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>During the 6 month intervention period, it is expected that the time from entering the study until the first primary event (acute hospital admission, emergency room visit or death) will be, on average, longer for those using the Intel速 Health Guide with case management (HG-CM) than for those in the routine case management (Case Management-Only Group). The primary measure to be compared across the study groups will be the unadjusted hazard ratio.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute Hospital Admission, Emergency Room Visit or Death</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>It is expected that the proportion of members with an inpatient acute admission, emergency room visit, or death in the intervention period and follow-up periods will be lower in the HG-CM Group than the Case Management-Only Group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease the number of acute hospital admissions and emergency room visits</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of acute hospital admissions and emergency room visits will decrease during the 6 month intervention period and the number during the 3 months after the intervention period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Inpatient Hospital Days associated with Acute Admissions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Medicare members using the Intel速 Health Guide are expected to have fewer Inpatient Acute Days in the intervention 6 months and during the 3 month follow-up period than do those in the Case Management-Only Group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Admissions Decreased</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of members with a hospital admission or emergency room visit for a cardiovascular DRG diagnosis in the intervention 6 months or during the 3 months' follow-up period will decrease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">316</enrollment>
  <condition>Congestive Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intel Home Health Guide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will receive the use of the Intel Healthguide, an Internet-connected device with member-customized protocols and response algorithms. Participants interact with the Intel HealthGuide device, receiving immediate feedback when transmitting blood pressure, weights and responses to questions to a site monitored by their nurse case manager. Medicare Case Managers review and coordinate services for members with multiple and complex needs with identified gaps in their care. Medicare Case Management staff strives to enhance the member's quality of life, support continuity of care, facilitate provision of services in the appropriate setting and manage cost and resource allocation to promote quality, cost-effective outcomes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Case Management Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants in the comparison group, are identified for outreach and assistance by a nurse case manager. Specialized Medicare Case Managers review and coordinate services for members with multiple and complex needs with identified gaps in their care. Medicare Case Management staff strives to enhance the member's quality of life, support continuity of care, facilitate provision of services in the appropriate setting and manage cost and resource allocation to promote quality, cost-effective outcomes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intel Health Guide</intervention_name>
    <description>An Internet-connected device with member-customized protocols and response algorithms. Participants interact with the Intel HealthGuide device, receiving immediate feedback, and also transmitting blood pressure, weights and responses to questions to a site monitored by their nurse case manager.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intel Home Health Guide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Case Management</intervention_name>
    <description>Specialized Medicare Case Managers review and coordinate services for members with multiple and complex needs with identified gaps in their care Medicare Case Management staff strives to enhance the member's quality of life, support continuity of care, facilitate provision of services in the appropriate setting and manage cost and resource allocation to promote quality, cost-effective outcomes. Specially trained Medicare Case Managers collaborate with the member, family, caregiver, member authorized representative, treating practitioner, health care provider, community services and other Aetna programs to coordinate care, with a focus on member education and maximizing quality outcomes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Case Management Only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aetna Medicare (PFFS, HMO/PPO fully insured) Individual members, plus Medicare members
             from any plan sponsor that has agreed it would like its members to be included

          -  Member meets Aetna Health Profile Database criteria for Chronic Heart Failure (Disease
             Management Eligibility = Y) with a disease risk stratification score of 3 - 5
             (moderately severe to severe). These proprietary criteria yield a group of individuals
             for whom historical claims data estimates a substantial risk of hospital readmission
             within the coming 6 months.

          -  Acute inpatient admission or 2 or more emergency room visits within 6 months prior to
             identification

          -  Residence in the designated geographic areas selected for the study (The planned
             source population is all New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania and North Central Aetna
             Individual Medicare members and North Central. If members identified from these states
             have not filled the study within three months, the source population may be expanded
             to include Aetna's North Central region members in Illinois and Ohio. These North
             Central members would include all Aetna Medicare Individual members in these areas,
             plus any Group Medicare members from Groups whose Plan Sponsors agree that the study
             may be offered to the members.)

          -  Member may be currently open/ active in case management

          -  Responds telephonic outreach to offer study participation, or to Interactive Voice
             Response outreach call, and confirms each of:

               -  Their own identity {secure Health Insurance Portability Accountability Act
                  (HIPAA) compliant acknowledgement to caller}

               -  That they have been told of having a heart condition

               -  Interest in hearing more and possibly participating in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Member had case management and this was closed within the 30 days prior to
             identification for the study

          -  End-of life, terminal cancer, end stage renal disease, hospice, late stage Alzheimer's
             disease, dementia, ventricular assist device, heart transplant or active in heart
             transplant program. Excluded diagnoses or conditions will be identified where it is
             evident through Aetna's Health Profile Data diagnoses in claims, or upon case
             management assessment.

          -  Chronic or ongoing intravenous heart failure medication

          -  Any response to Interactive Voice Response outreach call other than &quot;Yes, I am
             interested&quot;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcia Wade, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Aetna, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aetna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Princeton</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08540</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 15, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 15, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 16, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 15, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 15, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 16, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Marcia Wade</name_title>
    <organization>Aetna, Inc</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Congestive Heart Failure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>February 3, 2012</submitted>
    <returned>February 14, 2012</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

