<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00320970</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HI831</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00320970</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Angiotensin II Antagonism of TGF-Beta 1</brief_title>
  <official_title>Angiotensin II Antagonism of TGF-Beta 1: A Candesartan Dose - TGF-Beta 1 Response Relationship Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Providence Health &amp; Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Providence Health &amp; Services</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diabetic nephropathy is a frequent microvascular complication that occurs in approximately
      40% of patients with either type 1 or type 2 diabetes. The most common cause of end-stage
      renal disease (ESRD) in the United States and in the developed world is diabetic nephropathy.
      Currently, more than half the United States ESRD population has diabetes. More effective
      therapies to prevent and treat diabetic nephropathy are urgently needed. One way to increase
      therapeutic effectiveness is to refine treatment targets based on improved understanding of
      how treatments modulate disease processes. The purpose of this study is to determine whether
      a treatment for diabetic nephropathy, the angiotensin receptor blocker candesartan, modifies
      mediators of kidney injury independent of blood pressure and the relationships to drug dose.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Transforming growth factor-beta 1 (TGF-beta 1) is a potent inducer of extracellular matrix
      production and of fibrogenesis and has been associated with the occurrence of diabetic micro-
      and macrovascular complications. Several in vitro and in vivo studies have implicated
      TGF-beta 1 in the pathogenesis of diabetic kidney disease. Recent animal and in vitro
      experiments have demonstrated that ACE inhibitors and Angiotensin II (AT-II) receptor
      antagonists, including candesartan, decrease the synthesis and secretion of renal TGF-beta 1
      and prevent the development of glomerulosclerosis, interstitial fibrosis, and progressive
      renal dysfunction. These protective effects appear to be unrelated to the antihypertensive
      effects of the agents.

      Limited data in humans have supported these findings in patients with diabetic nephropathy. A
      recent human study with the AT-II receptor antagonist losartan demonstrated that the ability
      to correct microalbuminuria was independent of blood pressure control and correlated with
      normalization of circulating levels of TGF-beta 1. The results were further supported by the
      observation that markers of collagen type 1 metabolism were normalized in hypertensives in
      whom TGF-beta 1 was normalized with treatment but remained unaltered in the remaining
      hypertensives despite blood pressure control. Such findings are consistent with the recent
      observation that the AT-II receptor antagonist irbesartan is renoprotective independently of
      its blood pressure-lowering effect in patients with type 2 diabetes and microalbuminuria.

      The use of ACE-inhibitors and AT-II receptor antagonists as a means to reduce progression of
      renal fibrosis is becoming increasingly widespread. Dosage recommendations to achieve this
      goal are unclear prompting some experts to ask whether TGF-beta 1 rather than blood pressure
      should be a therapeutic target. Although not verified under chronic conditions, previous
      short-term studies with the AT-II antagonist candesartan have demonstrated different
      dose-response relationships to exist for blood pressure, renal plasma flow, and plasma renin
      activity. It is likely that dose-response relationship differences also exist between the
      aforementioned parameters (particularly blood pressure) and TGF-beta 1. In type 1 diabetic
      patients treated with captopril a relationship was demonstrated between percent change in
      plasma TGF-beta 1 and percent decline in GFR. In another study of 21 patients with a baseline
      GFR of &lt;75 ml/min there was a striking correlation between the captopril-induced reduction in
      serum TGF-beta 1 and 2-year change in GFR (r = -0.73, p =0.0001). This latter observation is
      particularly important in demonstrating that the relationship between TGF-beta 1 and rate of
      decline in kidney function can be modified through pharmacologic intervention.

      The dosage range for candesartan according to the FDA approved package insert is 4 to 32 mg
      daily, adjusted based on blood pressure response. Whether the dose that effectively lowers
      blood pressure is sufficient to suppress urinary TGF-beta 1 concentrations is unknown. In the
      absence of data, many experts are already suggesting doses higher than needed to control
      hypertension. Including a maximum dose of candesartan 64 mg in a dose titration scheme will
      be important to help resolve this issue. Furthermore, it is unclear if the candesartan
      dose/concentration - effect relationship for TGF-beta 1 and blood pressure are dissimilar.
      Information regarding the relationship between candesartan dose and effect on urinary
      TGF-beta 1 concentrations in patients with diabetic nephropathy would be valuable in
      tailoring therapy and enhancing our understanding of the optimal use of agents that modulate
      the renin-angiotensin system.

      Recent data in experimental models of diabetes indicate that the renin angiotensin system
      interacts with advanced glycation end products (AGEs) to produce kidney damage in diabetes.
      ACE inhibition in diabetic rats reduced circulating and renal accumulation of AGEs, possibly
      by increasing expression of the soluble receptor for AGEs. In a rat model of normoglycemia
      with AGE infusion, increased kidney expression of renin angiotensin system components along
      with structural changes similar to those in diabetic models was observed. Renin angiotensin
      system activation and kidney structural changes were reversed by valsartan. Therefore,
      modulation of AGEs may also be an important mechanism of kidney protection by renin
      angiotensin system inhibition in diabetes. This hypothesis is unexplored in humans. An
      exploratory sub-study will assess whether candesartan reduces urinary excretion of
      carboxymethyllysine, a prominent AGE, in patients with diabetic nephropathy.

      Study Objectives and Hypotheses:

      The overall objective of this study is to provide information that will improve kidney health
      in patients with diabetes. In a population of patients with type 2 diabetes, nephropathy, and
      hypertension the following hypotheses will be tested:

        1. Changes in parameters of blood pressure, urinary TGF-beta 1, serum AT-II, and urinary
           albumin demonstrate correlation with changes in chronic candesartan dose and serum
           concentrations.

        2. The candesartan dose and concentration response curves for BP and urinary TGF-beta 1 are
           significantly different and not predictive of one another.

        3. Candesartan treatment will reduce urinary excretion of carboxymethyllysine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>September 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary TGF-Beta 1</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum angiotensin II</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary albumin</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary carboxymethyllysine</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>36</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Nephropathy</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Candesartan</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 2 diabetes

          -  Nephropathy (proteinuria &gt;500 mg/day)

          -  Chronic Hypertension (as determined by current antihypertensive therapy and/or an
             average of diastolic blood pressure greater than 90 mmHg or greater or systolic blood
             pressure of 140 mmHg confirmed on at least two subsequent visits over one week or
             more).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Conditions associated with elevated TGF-Beta (e.g. rheumatoid arthritis, cancer,
             etc.).

          -  Conditions associated with alterations in serum levels of PIP and/or CITP (liver
             cirrhosis, osteoporosis, hyperthyroidism, multiple myeloma, osteolytic metastases, and
             systemic glucocorticoid treatment

          -  History of Stage III hypertension (diastolic BP &gt; 110 mmHg or systolic BP &gt; 180 mmHg)
             or a history of hypertensive urgency or emergency.

          -  NYHA Class III or IV heart failure

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance of less than 30 ml/min or serum creatinine &gt; 3 mg/dL

          -  HbA1c &gt; 10%

          -  Patients unable to be withdrawn for 2 weeks from AT-II antagonist or ACE- inhibitor
             therapy

          -  Blood Pressure &lt;140/90 is unachievable in the absence of an AT-II antagonist or
             ACE-inhibitor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katherine R. Tuttle, MD,FASN,FACP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Providence Medical Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Providence Medical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>TGF-Beta 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Angiotensin II</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced glycation end products</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Nephropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Candesartan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Candesartan cilexetil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angiotensin II</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angiotensinogen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

