<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00321555</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060150</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-C-0150</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00321555</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00337311</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LMB-2 to Treat Hairy Cell Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Clinical Trial of Anti-Tac(Fv)-PE38 (LMB-2) Immunotoxin for CD25 Positive Hairy Cell Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  About 80% of patients with hairy cell leukemia (HCL) have tumor cells that have a
           protein on their surface called CD25.

        -  The experimental drug LMB-2 is a recombinant immunotoxin that has been shown to kill
           leukemia and lymphoma cells with the CD25 protein. (A recombinant immunotoxin is a
           genetically engineered drug that has two parts - a protein that binds or targets a
           cancer cell, and a toxin that kills the cancer cell to which it binds.)

      Objectives:

        -  To evaluate the safety and effectiveness of LMB-2 in patients with HCL whose cancer
           cells contain the CD25 protein.

        -  To evaluate the effects of LMB-2 on the immune system, determine how the drug is
           metabolized by the body and examine its side effects.

      Eligibility:

      -Adults with hairy cell leukemia whose tumor cells have CD25 on their surface

      Design:

        -  Up to 27 patients may be included in the study.

        -  Patients receive an infusion of LMB-2 through a vein every other day for three doses
           (days 1, 3, 5), constituting one treatment cycle.

        -  Patients may receive up to six treatment cycles every 4 weeks unless their cancer
           worsens or they develop unacceptable side effects.

        -  Blood is drawn weekly for various tests.

        -  Before each cycle and in follow-up visits, disease status is evaluated with a physical
           examination, blood tests, chest x-ray and electrocardiogram.

        -  Before the first cycle, patients may have a CT scan, echocardiogram (heart ultrasound
           test) and bone marrow biopsy. With the patient's permission, these tests may be repeated
           before other cycles also.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: About 80% of patients with hairy cell leukemia (HCL) have malignant cells that
      express CD25 (Tac or IL2Ra). Normal resting B- and T-cells do not express CD25. LMB-2 is an
      anti-CD25 recombinant immunotoxin containing variable domains of MAb anti-Tac and truncated
      Pseudomonas exotoxin. A phase I trial at NCI found that the MTD of LMB-2 was 40 microg/Kg IV
      given every other day for 3 doses (QOD x3). The most common adverse events were transient
      fever, hypoalbuminemia and transaminase elevations. In that trial, 4 of 4 patients with
      chemoresistant HCL had major responses, including one complete (CR) and 3 partial remissions.
      The patient with CR entered the trial transfusion dependent and now still has normal
      hemoglobin and platelet counts over 7 years later. Because HCL is more frequently CD22+ than
      CD25+ (100 vs 80%), HCL patients were subsequently treated with the anti-CD22 recombinant
      immunotoxin BL22 and no further HCL patients were treated with LMB-2. BL22 has induced 25 CRs
      out of 51 evaluable HCL patients. LMB-2 may be useful in patients incompletely responding to
      BL22, because it may distribute more evenly through extravascular sites of disease. Moreover,
      BL22 but not LMB-2 has caused hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) in 7 patients, 6 with HCL, and
      several of these patients could benefit by LMB-2. Thus, LMB-2 may be a useful and potentially
      lifesaving agent in patients who are unable to receive or who have not responded adequately
      to BL22.

      Objectives: The purpose of this study is to determine the activity of anti-Tac(Fv)-PE38
      (LMB-2) in patients with CD25-expressing hairy cell leukemia (HCL). The primary endpoint of
      this trial is response rate. We will also evaluate response duration, LMB-2 immunogenicity,
      pharmacokinetics, toxicity, and monitor soluble Tac levels in the serum.

      Eligibility: Patients must have CD25+ HCL cells by flow cytometry, cytopenia or high
      circulating HCL count, prior treatment with or inability to receive BL22, prior treatment
      with cladribine, ECOG PS 0-2, at least 18 years old, ALT and AST grade 0-2, albumin grade
      0-1, bilirubin less than or equal to 2.2, creatinine less than or equal to 1.4 or creatinine
      clearance greater than or equal to 50, lack of high levels of neutralizing antibodies, lack
      of anti-CD25 Mab therapy for 12 weeks and other systemic treatment for 4 weeks, no prior
      treatment with LMB-2, lack of other uncontrolled illness including 2nd malignancy, no HIV or
      hepatitis C positivity, no coumadin therapy, LVEF greater than or equal to 45%, DLCO greater
      than or equal to 55%, and FEV1 greater than or equal to 60%.

      Design: Patients will receive LMB-2 at 40 microg/Kg QOD x3 at intervals of at least 25 days
      for up to 6 cycles. Retreatment is permitted in the absence of neutralizing antibodies or
      progressive disease. Patients in CR may receive 2 consolidation cycles, or 4 consolidation
      cycles if CR is with minimal residual disease.

      Dose level: LMB-2 40 microg/Kg QOD x3

      Expected Accrual: 5-10 patients/year, total of 25 patients
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who obtain partial/complete response.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fraction of responding patients who achieve a six month response duration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Hairy Cell Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LMB-2 Infusion: 40 micro-g/Kg will be infused in 50 ml of 0.9% NaCl and 0.2% albumin via over 30 minutes every other day for 3 doses. Patients may receive up to six treatment cycles every 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-Tac(Fv)-PE38 (LMB-2) Immunotoxin</intervention_name>
    <description>LMB-2 Infusion: 40 micro-g/Kg will be infused in 50 ml of 0.9% NaCl and 0.2% albumin via over 30 minutes every other day for 3 doses. Patients may receive up to six treatment cycles every 4 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Histopathological evidence of CD25+ HCL confirmed by the NIH pathology
                  department. This will require a monoclonal population of peripheral malignant
                  lymphocytes that are CD25 positive by fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS)
                  with anti-CD25 antibody. Positive expression in a FACS assay is defined as more
                  than 2 times the mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) of the control antibody by
                  FACS. HCLv (HCL variant) is usually CD25 negative, and eligibility would require
                  CD25+ HCLv.

               2. At least one of the following indications for treatment: neutropenia (ANC less
                  than 1000 cells/ microL), anemia (Hgb less than 10g/dL), thrombocytopenia (Plt
                  less than 100,000/ microL), an absolute lymphocyte count of greater than 20,000
                  cells/microL or symptomatic splenomegaly.

               3. Previous treatment with or inability to receive BL22 or HA22 recombinant
                  immunotoxin. Patients must have had at least 2 prior systemic therapies,
                  including 2 courses of a purine nucleoside analog (PNA), or 1 course of either
                  rituximab or BRAF inhibitor following a single prior course of PNA.

               4. ECOG performance status of 0 - 2.

               5. At least 18 years old.

               6. Understand and give informed consent.

               7. A negative pregnancy test in female patients of childbearing potential. Women
                  must not be breast-feeding.

               8. ALT and AST less than or equal to 5-times the upper limits of normal. Albumin
                  greater than or equal to 3.0 gm/dL. Total bilirubin less than or equal to 2.2
                  mg/dL.

               9. Creatinine less than or equal to 1.4 mg/dL or creatinine clearance greater than
                  or equal to 50 ml/min.

              10. Serum that neutralizes less than or equal to 75% of the activity of 1 microg/mL
                  of LMB-2 using a bioassay.

              11. No systemic cytotoxic chemotherapy within 4 weeks of enrollment or systemic
                  steroids (except stable doses of Prednisone less than or equal to 20 mg/day, or
                  up to 4 doses of steroid given for non-therapy reasons) within 4 weeks of
                  enrollment.

              12. No anti-CD25 monoclonal antibody therapy within 12 weeks of enrollment.

              13. No prior treatment with LMB-2.

              14. Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents.

              15. Patients should not have uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not
                  limited to, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
                  cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
                  compliance with study requirements.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients who have HIV or hepatitis C. Patients would not be excluded for hepatitis B
             surface antigen positivity if on Lamivudine.

          -  Patients receiving coumadin.

          -  Patients with a left ventricular ejection fraction of less than 45%.

          -  Patients with a DLCO less than 55% of normal or an FEV1 less than 60% of normal based
             on either NIH or USA normal ranges.

          -  Patients who have an active 2nd malignancy requiring systemic treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert J Kreitman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2006-C-0150.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carson DA, Wasson DB, Beutler E. Antileukemic and immunosuppressive activity of 2-chloro-2'-deoxyadenosine. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1984 Apr;81(7):2232-6.</citation>
    <PMID>6585795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blasińska-Morawiec M, Robak T, Krykowski E, Hellmann A, Urbańska-Ryś H. Hairy cell leukemia-variant treated with 2-chlorodeoxyadenosine--a report of three cases. Leuk Lymphoma. 1997 Apr;25(3-4):381-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9168448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheson BD, Martin A. Clinical trials in hairy cell leukemia. Current status and future directions. Ann Intern Med. 1987 Jun;106(6):871-8. Review. Erratum in: Ann Intern Med 1987 Oct;107(4):604.</citation>
    <PMID>3555204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 4, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 4, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biologic Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Monoclonal Antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Pseudomonas Exotoxin</keyword>
  <keyword>Targeted Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Hairy Cell Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>HCL</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Hairy Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunotoxins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daclizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

