<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00321139</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1189-2005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00321139</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Translesional Markers and Metabolomics</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Assessment of Translesional Markers and Metabolomics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston Scientific Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Blockages in the blood vessels of the heart are the main cause of chest pain, heart attacks,
      and sudden death. A cardiac catheterization, or injecting x-ray dye into the blood vessels of
      the heart and taking pictures, is currently the best way of assessing these blockages. This
      procedure, however, does not allow us to know what is happening inside the blockages. Some
      blockages have a higher risk of &quot;rupturing&quot; and completely blocking of the blood vessel while
      others are at low risk for doing this.

      Blood levels of different substances produced by the body have been shown to be associated
      with a higher risk of having chest pain, a heart attack, or sudden death. There is also
      evidence from studies in animals and tissues taken from humans during surgery that some of
      these substances are made in the blockages themselves.

      We would like to investigate whether a number of these substances are made in the blockages
      and released into the bloodstream. We will do this by taking one tablespoon samples of blood
      upstream and downstream of the blockages in the blood vessels of the heart. The samples will
      be obtained by using a very thin catheter, or plastic tubing, that is about 1/3 the size of
      the blood vessels of the heart. We will take samples from the tightest blockage found as well
      as another, less tight, blockage and compare the two. We will also sample blood from the
      tightest blockage after it is opened by doing an angioplasty. Finally, we will also take
      pictures of the blockages studied using a very small ultrasound camera inserted into the
      blood vessel. We will compare the levels of the substances measured with the features we see
      on the pictures.

      We hope to learn if some or all of the substances measured can identify which blockages are
      more at risk for rupturing and causing heart attacks and sudden death.

      All patients who are entered into this study will already be having an angioplasty done. The
      procedures needed for the study (sampling of blood and taking pictures with an ultrasound)
      are already often, though not always, used in patients undergoing an angioplasty.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction

      Hypothesis

      Coronary heart disease is the leading cause of death in the United States, accounting for &gt;
      500,000 lives each year. Atherosclerosis is the underlying mechanism for unstable angina,
      myocardial infarction, and sudden cardiac death. Luminal narrowing of the arteries caused by
      atherosclerotic plaque encroachment causes the chronic ischemic manifestations of coronary
      heart disease, whereas superimposition of thrombi over the plaques leads to acute coronary
      syndromes. To date, angiography has been the method of choice of detecting arterial lesions.
      However, this diagnostic technique, which approximately compares the degree of luminal
      stenosis of arteries relative to its' segments, does not provide insight into the disease
      state within the artery, and often fails to detect those lesions prone to thrombosis, often
      referred to as 'vulnerable plaque'. Multiple invasive and non-invasive methods have been
      employed in order to identify vulnerable plaque, usually by trying to image the plaque and
      its morphology, however none has gained widespread use.

      Elevation of several biochemical markers in the bloodstream has been associated with adverse
      cardiovascular events. Inflammation has been identified as a significant component of the
      unstable atherosclerotic plaque. The inflammatory response seems to participate early in the
      development of atherosclerosis and involves multiple pathways3. Indeed, many markers of
      inflammation have now been shown to predict cardiovascular risk4-7 and recent studies have
      shown that key inflammatory markers are synthesized within atherosclerotic lesions8-10.
      Another process that appears to precede inflammation is oxidative stress. Increased cellular
      oxidative stress may be the process that initiates much of the subsequent inflammation and
      ultimately to development of the atherosclerotic process. Our preliminary data demonstrates
      that oxidative stress is increased in patients with acute coronary syndromes and after
      coronary stenting. The immune system is also activated in those with unstable atherosclerotic
      plaque with well documented changes in the T cells11-12.

      An exciting new field of medicine is the application of systems approaches. One of these
      systems approaches is metabolomics. Metabolomics is based on the use of NMR (and other
      spectroscopic methods) and multivariate statistics for data analysis and interpretation. NMR
      spectroscopy is based on the behavior of atoms placed in a static external magnetic field.
      1H-NMR spectroscopy allows the simultaneous detection and quantification of thousands of
      low-molecular-weight metabolites within a biologic fluid, resulting in the generation of an
      endogenous profile that may be altered in disease to provide a characteristic &quot;fingerprint&quot;
      of the disease process. It has been used clinically in the detection of ovarian cancer and
      coronary artery disease13, 14.

      With this in mind, the difference in levels of oxidation and inflammatory markers, activated
      leucocytes, and the metabolomic profile across an atherosclerotic lesion, that is the
      translesional gradient, may be of clinical utility. An elevated translesional gradient of
      inflammatory and oxidative markers, leucocyte activation, as well as a change in the
      metabolomic profile, could be used to identify plaques prone to rupture. By implication, the
      ability to simply and reliably identify such plaques would have profound clinical
      consequences by either allowing placement of intracoronary stents in high-risk, but not yet
      flow-limiting lesions that if left untreated would rupture and lead to an acute coronary
      syndrome.

      We hypothesize that:

        1. the translesional gradients of (a) markers of oxidative stress, and (b) inflammation,
           and (c) activated leucocytes will be elevated across culprit lesions as opposed to
           non-culprit lesions in the same individuals; and

        2. the translesional gradients of markers of oxidation, inflammation and leucocyte
           activation will differ in plaques with high-risk morphologic appearance compared to
           plaques with low-risk morphologic appearance, as assessed by intravascular ultrasound
           (IVUS); and

        3. The metabolomic profile assessed by 1H-NMR spectroscopy will differentiate culprit and
           non-culprit lesions as well as plaques that have high-risk and low-risk morphologies.

      Objectives

      Aim 1: To determine and compare the translesional gradients of established markers of
      oxidative stress, inflammation, and leucocyte activation across culprit lesions vs
      non-culprit lesions in the same individuals.

      Aim 2: To compare the translesion gradients of markers of oxidation, inflammation and
      leucocyte activation with plaque morphology as assessed by intravascular ultrasound (IVUS).

      Aim 3: To determine if a systems approach using 1H-NMR-based metabolomics can be used to
      distinguish ruptured culprit and non-culprit lesions as well as plaques that have high-risk
      and low-risk morphologies.

      Endpoints

        1. A comparison of the markers of oxidation, inflammation, and leucocyte activation in the
           following:

             1. A comparison will be made between the translesional marker gradients (distal level
                - proximal level) of samples from the culprit lesion and non-culprit lesion.

             2. A comparison will be made between levels (distal level - proximal level) to the
                culprit lesion before and after angioplasty/stenting.

        2. A comparison of the markers of oxidation, inflammation, and leucocyte activation with
           plaque morphologic indices as assessed by intravascular ultrasound.

        3. A comparison of 1H-NMR metabolomic spectra from culprit and non-culprit lesions as well
           as plaques that have high-risk and low-risk plaque morphologies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2006</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison of the markers of oxidation, inflammation, and leucocyte activation in the following:</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison will be made between the translesional marker gradients (distal level - proximal level) of samples from the culprit lesion and non-culprit lesion.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison will be made between levels (distal level - proximal level) to the culprit lesion before and after angioplasty/stenting.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>3. A</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A comparison of the markers of oxidation, inflammation, and leucocyte activation with plaque morphologic indices as assessed by intravascular ultrasound.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>comparison of 1H-NMR metabolomic spectra from culprit and non-culprit lesions as well as plaques that have high-risk and low-risk plaque morphologies.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women from the ages of 21 and older

          -  Able to give informed consent

          -  Already scheduled to undergo diagnostic catheterization or percutaneous coronary
             intervention

          -  A culprit lesion (&gt;60% diameter stenosis) in an artery that is at least 2.5 mm in
             diameter immediately proximal to the lesion.

          -  Presence of a second, non-culprit lesion, that is between 20 and 60% diameter stenosis
             in an artery that is at least 2.5 mm in diameter immediately proximal to the lesion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction

          -  Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction (TIMI) grade 0 flow in the vessel containing the
             culprit lesion

          -  Autoimmune diseases, malignancy, or with active infections

          -  Taking immune-modulating therapies, eg prednisone

          -  Culprit lesion is in-stent restenosis

          -  Culprit lesion cannot be crossed with a wire and/or balloon

          -  Those enrolled in another research study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ziyad B Ghazzal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Arshed A. Quyyumi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>oxidative stress</keyword>
  <keyword>intravascular ultrasound</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

