<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00328744</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01DK074721-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00328744</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reducing Snack Variety in Weight Loss Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Reducing Snack Food Variety During Obesity Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Miriam Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Miriam Hospital</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The rising prevalence of obesity in the United States is believed to be due to increased
      exposure to adverse environmental factors, such as food portion sizes and increased dietary
      variety. Although decreasing portion sizes is a strategy used in weight loss programs,
      research has not studied the effects of decreasing dietary variety. Cross-sectional studies
      show a positive association between variety and body weight and in our own studies the
      investigators have shown that greater reductions in the number of different snack foods
      (i.e., cookies, chips) consumed predicted greater decreases in overall caloric and fat intake
      and greater weight loss. Limiting variety may reduce intake through long-term
      sensory-specific satiety and/or monotony. Reducing dietary variety is a novel dietary
      approach with the potential to improve long-term weight loss, which has not been studied as a
      clinical strategy in obesity research. The objective of this application is to conduct a
      randomized controlled trial of a behavioral weight loss intervention limiting the number of
      different snack foods consumed. Two hundred overweight and obese participants will be
      randomized to a standard behavioral intervention (Standard) or to a standard behavioral
      intervention that also limits the number of different snack foods consumed (Limited Variety).
      Both conditions will receive an 18-month standard behavioral intervention, using behavioral
      techniques (i.e., self-monitoring) to change eating behaviors. Participants in the Limited
      Variety condition will also limit variety in snack foods to only two chosen snack foods
      throughout the intervention. Measures of weight, snack food consumption and hedonics, and
      diet satisfaction will be taken at 0, 6, 12, and 18 months. This investigation will
      determine:

        1. if the Limited Variety condition produces greater weight loss than the Standard
           condition at 18 months;

        2. if the Limited Variety condition consumes fewer servings and calories from snack foods
           than the Standard condition;

        3. if limiting snack food variety produces long-term sensory-specific satiety and/or
           monotony.

      Relevance: Experimental studies show that limiting dietary variety profoundly reduces intake.
      To date, there is no dietary prescription that has been tested that capitalizes on the effect
      of variety on intake that can be maintained. This will be the first investigation to examine
      methods of manipulating dietary variety that can be adhered to over time and that influence
      intake, weight loss, and weight loss maintenance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight loss</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hedonics of food</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">202</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Behavioral: Behavioral weight loss (Standard)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Behavioral: Behavioral weight loss (Limited Variety)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard</intervention_name>
    <description>18-month standard behavioral weight loss intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Limited Variety</intervention_name>
    <description>Two chosen snack foods</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age between 21 and 65 years. Older adults may have more medical co-morbidities,
             requiring greater medical supervision. Although pediatric obesity is a significant
             concern, this group has different nutritional needs and requires different levels of
             therapist and parental involvement than are proposed.

          2. Body mass index (BMI) between 27 and 45 kg/m2. Based upon the Evidence Report (72),
             weight loss is recommended for individuals with a BMI &gt; 25. A BMI of &gt; 27 was chosen
             as eligibility criteria for this investigation because this level of BMI will allow
             for a 10% weight loss to occur prior to reaching a BMI of &lt; 25. Individuals with a BMI
             of &gt; 45 have more medical co-morbidities and require greater medical supervision, and
             thus will be considered ineligible for this investigation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Report a heart condition, chest pain during periods of activity or rest, or loss of
             consciousness on the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire (PAR-Q) (73).
             Individuals endorsing joint problems, prescription medication usage, or other medical
             conditions that could limit exercise will be required to obtain written physician
             consent to participate.

          2. Have an allergy to a food commonly found in snack foods (i.e., nuts, milk and egg
             proteins).

          3. Report major psychiatric diseases or organic brain syndromes.

          4. Are currently participating in a weight loss program and/or taking weight loss
             medication or lost &gt; 5% of body weight during the past 6 months.

          5. Intend to move outside of the metropolitan area within the time frame of the
             investigation.

          6. Are pregnant, lactating, less than 6 months post-partum, or plan to become pregnant
             during the time frame of the investigation.

          7. Consume &lt; 5 different types of snack food per week. Pilot data indicated that upon
             screening 44 participants, mean weekly variety of snack foods was 8.7 (range 2 to 14,
             with only two participants consuming &lt; 5 snack foods per week).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hollie Raynor, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Tennessee</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Miriam Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 19, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Weight</keyword>
  <keyword>Dietary intake</keyword>
  <keyword>Energy</keyword>
  <keyword>Hedonics</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral</keyword>
  <keyword>Sensory-specific satiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Monotony</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

