<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00868582</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NOPR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00868582</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The National Oncologic PET Registry</brief_title>
  <acronym>NOPR</acronym>
  <official_title>The National Oncologic PET Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>American College of Radiology Imaging Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>World Molecular Imaging Society (formerly Academy of Molecular Imaging)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>American College of Radiology Imaging Network</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS), as the Federal agency that administers
      the Medicare program, only pays for positron emission tomography (PET) scans in patients with
      cancer for certain reasons and for certain types of cancer. This study was developed to help
      CMS determine if they should pay for PET scans for additional reasons and additional types of
      cancer. In order to collect the information needed to decide which other types of cancer
      should be covered by Medicare, CMS will provide payment for the otherwise non-covered PET
      scans of patients who are properly registered with the National Oncologic PET Registry
      (NOPR). This information will then be analyzed to determine the effect PET scans had on the
      way physicians planned to treat their patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The National Oncologic PET Registry (NOPR) was developed in response to the Centers for
      Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS) proposal to expand coverage for positron emission
      tomography with F-18 fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG-PET) to include cancers and indications not
      presently eligible for Medicare reimbursement. Under this coverage with evidence development
      (CED) program, Medicare reimbursement for these cancers can be obtained if the patient's
      referring physician and the provider submit data to a clinical registry to assess the impact
      of PET on cancer patient management. The NOPR implemented this registry for CMS. The NOPR is
      sponsored by the World Molecular Imaging Society (formerly the Academy of Molecular Imaging),
      and managed by the American College of Radiology through the American College of Radiology
      Imaging Network.

      The original goal of the National Oncologic PET Registry was to assess the effect of positron
      emission tomography with F-18 fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG-PET) on referring physicians' plans of
      intended patient management for those cancers and indications not currently eligible for
      reimbursement from CMS. Data were collected from the referring physician before and after the
      PET study. If complete and timely data are reported to the NOPR within 30 days of the PET
      scan, the PET facility and interpreting physician (nuclear physician/radiologist) are
      eligible for reimbursement by CMS. Based in part on data obtained from the NOPR, CMS expanded
      coverage for FDG-PET in patients with cancer on April 3, 2009 and further expanded coverage
      on June 11, 2013. Specifically, on June 11, 2013, CMS issued a final decision memorandum
      ending the prospective data collection requirements under CED for all oncologic indications
      for FDG-PET. Overall accrual to the FDG-PET registry was nearly 288,000 scans.

      On February 26, 2010, CMS announced its decision to cover the use NaF-18 PET to identify bone
      metastasis. Under this new policy, the use of NaF-18 PET would be covered only under an
      approved (CED) program. The NOPR obtained CMS approval to develop a registry for NaF-18 as an
      amendment to the then-existing NOPR for FDG-PET. The NaF-18 PET registry component of NOPR
      was activated for accrual on February 7, 2011. Estimated total accrual to the NaF-PET
      registry is 45,000 cases.

      As with the registry for FDG-PET, the goal of the NaF-18 PET registry component is to assess
      the impact of this imaging examination on referring physicians' plans of intended management
      of patients with known or suspected osseous metastatic disease. Data are collected from the
      referring physician before and after the PET study, as well as from the interpreting
      physician. If complete and timely data are reported to the NOPR within 30 days of the PET
      scan, the PET facility and interpreting physician (nuclear physician/radiologist) are
      eligible for reimbursement by CMS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the effect of PET on referring physicians' plans of intended patient management of patients with cancer types eligible for inclusion in the National Oncologic PET Registry.</measure>
    <time_frame>PET Scans as ordered by treating physician per CMS frequency guidelines</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">333000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FDG-PET</arm_group_label>
    <description>F-18 fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG-PET)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NaF-18 PET</arm_group_label>
    <description>F-18 sodum-fluoride (NaF-18 PET)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PET scanning in cancer</intervention_name>
    <description>Collection of institutional practice PET imaging data</description>
    <arm_group_label>FDG-PET</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>NaF-18 PET</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NOPR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Medicare beneficiaries who are referred for NaF-18 PET (the FDG-PET arm of NOPR has
        completed enrollment)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All Medicare beneficiaries who are referred for NaF-18 PET to identify bone metastasis
             are eligible to be included in the NOPR.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  NaF-18 PET for other (non-oncologic) indications.

          -  NaF-18 PET performed as part of a clinical trial approved by CMS.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruce Hillner, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Virginia Commonwealth University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bruce Hillner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>804-828-5129</phone>
    <email>Hillner@vcu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Barry Siegel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-2809</phone>
    <email>Siegelb@mir.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>American College of Radiology Imaging Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joy A Brown</last_name>
      <phone>215-717-0859</phone>
      <email>jbrown@acr.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Martha Heckel</last_name>
      <phone>215-574-3169</phone>
      <email>mheckel@acr.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Siegel BA, Liu D, Shields AF, Gareen IF, Hanna L, Stine SH, Coleman RE. Impact of positron emission tomography/computed tomography and positron emission tomography (PET) alone on expected management of patients with cancer: initial results from the National Oncologic PET Registry. J Clin Oncol. 2008 May 1;26(13):2155-61. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2007.14.5631. Epub 2008 Mar 24. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2008 Sep 1;26(25): 4229.</citation>
    <PMID>18362365</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Siegel BA, Shields AF, Liu D, Gareen IF, Hunt E, Coleman RE. Relationship between cancer type and impact of PET and PET/CT on intended management: findings of the national oncologic PET registry. J Nucl Med. 2008 Dec;49(12):1928-35. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.108.056713. Epub 2008 Nov 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18997054</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Siegel BA, Shields AF, Liu D, Gareen IF, Hanna L, Stine SH, Coleman RE. The impact of positron emission tomography (PET) on expected management during cancer treatment: findings of the National Oncologic PET Registry. Cancer. 2009 Jan 15;115(2):410-8. doi: 10.1002/cncr.24000. Erratum in: Cancer. 2009 Mar 1;115(5):1133.</citation>
    <PMID>19016303</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Siegel BA, Shields AF, Duan F, Gareen IF, Hanna L, Coleman RE. Impact of dedicated brain PET on intended patient management in participants of the national oncologic PET Registry. Mol Imaging Biol. 2011 Feb;13(1):161-5. doi: 10.1007/s11307-010-0427-5.</citation>
    <PMID>21080232</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Siegel BA, Hanna L, Shields AF, Duan F, Gareen IF, Quinn B, Coleman RE. Impact of 18F-FDG PET used after initial treatment of cancer: comparison of the National Oncologic PET Registry 2006 and 2009 cohorts. J Nucl Med. 2012 May;53(5):831-7. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.112.103911. Epub 2012 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>22448033</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Tosteson TD, Tosteson AN, Wang Q, Song Y, Onega T, Hanna LG, Siegel BA. Intended versus inferred management after PET for cancer restaging: analysis of Medicare claims linked to a coverage with evidence development registry. Med Care. 2013 Apr;51(4):361-7. doi: 10.1097/MLR.0b013e318287d860.</citation>
    <PMID>23481033</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Tosteson AN, Tosteson TD, Wang Q, Song Y, Hanna LG, Siegel BA. Intended versus inferred care after PET performed for initial staging in the National Oncologic PET Registry. J Nucl Med. 2013 Dec;54(12):2024-31. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.113.123430. Epub 2013 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24221994</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Siegel BA, Hanna L, Duan F, Shields AF, Coleman RE. Impact of 18F-fluoride PET in patients with known prostate cancer: initial results from the National Oncologic PET Registry. J Nucl Med. 2014 Apr;55(4):574-81. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.113.130005. Epub 2014 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24578240</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Siegel BA, Hanna L, Duan F, Shields AF, Quinn B, Coleman RE. Impact of (18)F-Fluoride PET on Intended Management of Patients with Cancers Other Than Prostate Cancer: Results from the National Oncologic PET Registry. J Nucl Med. 2014 Jul;55(7):1054-61. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.113.135475. Epub 2014 May 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24819422</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillner BE, Siegel BA, Hanna L, Duan F, Quinn B, Shields AF. 18F-fluoride PET used for treatment monitoring of systemic cancer therapy: results from the National Oncologic PET Registry. J Nucl Med. 2015 Feb;56(2):222-8. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.114.150391. Epub 2015 Jan 15.</citation>
    <PMID>25593113</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 24, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 24, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 25, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Patients with proven or suspected cancer referred for NaF-18 PET to identify bone metastasis</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

