<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00865423</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01-079</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00865423</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Relative Bioavailability Study of Gabapentin Tablets 800 mg Under Fasting Conditions</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Relative Bioavailability Study of 800 mg Gabapentin Tablets Under Fasting Conditions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Actavis Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Actavis Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the relative bioavailability of 800 mg Gabapentin
      Tablets by Purepac Pharmaceutical Co. with that of 800 mg NEURONTIN® Tablets by Parke-Davis
      following a single oral dose (1 x 800 mg) in healthy adult volunteers under fasting
      conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Type: Interventional Study Design: Randomized, single-dose, two-way crossover design
      under fasting conditions

      Official Title: A Relative Bioavailability Study of 800 mg Gabapentin Tablets Under Fasting
      Conditions

      Further study details as provided by Actavis Elizabeth LLC:

      Primary Outcome Measures:

      Rate and Extend of Absorption
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2001</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2001</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate and Extend of Absorption</measure>
    <time_frame>60 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gabapentin 800 mg Tablets, single dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>NEURONTIN® 800 mg Tablets, single dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gabapentin 800 mg Tablets, single dose</intervention_name>
    <description>A: Experimental Subjects received Purepac formulated products under fasting conditions</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gabapentin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NEURONTIN® 800 mg Tablets, single dose</intervention_name>
    <description>B: Active comparator Subjects received Parke-Davis formulated products under fasting conditions</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gabapentin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Screening Demographics: All volunteers selected for this study will be healthy men or
             women 18 years of age or older at the time of dosing. The weight range will not exceed
             ± 15% for height and body frame as per Desirable Weights for Men -1983 Metropolitan
             Height and Weight Table or as per Desirable Weights for Women -1983 Metropolitan
             Height and Weight Table

          -  Screening Procedures: Each volunteer will complete the screening process within 28
             days prior to Period I dosing. Consent documents for both the screening evaluation and
             HIV antibody determination will be reviewed, discussed, and signed by each potential
             participant before full implementation of screening procedures.

          -  Screening will include general observations, physical examination, demographics,
             medical and medication history, an electrocardiogram, sitting blood pressure and heart
             rate, respiratory rate and temperature. -The physical examination will include, but
             may not be limited to, an evaluation of the cardiovascular, gastrointestinal,
             respiratory and central nervous systems.

          -  The screening clinical laboratory procedures will include:

               -  HEMATOLOGY: hematocrit, hemoglobin, WBC count with differential; RBC count,
                  platelet count

               -  CLINICAL CHEMISTRY: serum creatinine, BUN, glucose, AST(GOT), ALT(GPT), albumin,
                  total bilirubin, total protein, and alkaline phosphatase;

               -  HIV antibody and hepatitis B surface antigen screens;

               -  URINALYSIS: by dipstick, microscopic examination if dipstick positive; and .

               -  URINE DRUG SCREEN: ethyl alcohol, amphetamines, barbiturates, benzodiazepines,
                  cannabinoids, cocaine metabolites, opiates and phencyclidine.

               -  SERUM PREGNANCY SCREEN (female volunteers only)

          -  If female and:

               -  of childbearing potential, is practicing an acceptable barrier method of birth
                  control for the duration of the study as judged by the investigator(s), such as
                  condoms, sponge, foams, jellies, diaphragm; intrauterine device (IUD), or
                  abstinence

               -  is postmenopausal for at least I year; or

               -  is surgically sterile (bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy, or
                  hysterectomy).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Volunteers with a recent history of drug or alcohol addiction or abuse.

          -  Volunteers with the presence of a clinically significant disorder involving the
             cardiovascular, respiratory, renal, gastrointestinal, immunologic, hematologic,
             endocrine, or neurologic system(s) or psychiatric disease (as determined by the
             medical investigator).

          -  Volunteers whose clinical laboratory test values are outside the accepted reference
             range and when confirmed on re-examination are deemed to be clinically significant.

          -  Volunteers demonstrating a positive hepatitis B surface antigen screen or a reactive
             HIV antibody screen.

          -  Volunteers demonstrating a positive drug abuse screen when screened for this study.

          -  Female volunteers demonstrating a positive pregnancy screen.

          -  Female volunteers who are currently breastfeeding.

          -  Volunteers with a history of allergic response(s) to gabapentin or related drugs.

          -  Volunteers with a history of clinically significant allergies including drug
             allergies.

          -  Volunteers with a clinically significant illness during the 4 weeks prior to Period I
             dosing (as determined by the medical investigator).

          -  Volunteers who currently use tobacco products.

          -  Volunteers who have taken any drug known to induce or inhibit hepatic• drug metabolism
             in the 30 days prior to Period I dosing.

          -  Volunteers who report donating greater than 150 mL of blood within 30 days prior to
             Period I dosing. All subjects will be advised not to donate blood for four weeks after
             completing the study.

          -  Volunteers who have donated plasma (e.g. plasmapheresis) within 14 days prior to
             Period I dosing. All subjects will be advised not to donate plasma for four weeks
             after completing the study.

          -  Volunteers who report receiving any investigational drug within 30 days prior to
             Period I dosing.

          -  Volunteers who report taking any systemic prescription medication in the 14 days prior
             to Period I dosing, with the exception of oral contraceptives for female volunteers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James D. Carlson,, Pharm.D,</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>PRACS Institute, Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PRACS Institute, Ltd.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fargo</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://chem.sis.nlm.nih.gov/chemidplus/ProxyServlet?objectHandle=DBMaint&amp;actionHandle=default&amp;nextPage=jsp/chemidlite/ResultScreen.jsp&amp;TXTSUPERLISTID=060142963</url>
    <description>Gabapentin</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 13, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 13, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 17, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Meena Venugopal, Director, Clinical R&amp;D</name_title>
    <organization>Actavis Inc</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bioequivalence</keyword>
  <keyword>Gabapentin</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy subjects</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gabapentin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>gamma-Aminobutyric Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

