<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00861627</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REO 016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00861627</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Study of REOLYSIN® in Combination With Paclitaxel and Carboplatin for Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer With KRAS or EGFR Activation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 2 Study of Intravenous Administration of Reovirus Serotype 3 - Dearing Strain (REOLYSIN®) in Combination With Paclitaxel and Carboplatin in Patients With Metastatic or Recurrent Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Who Have KRAS or EGFR Activated Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oncolytics Biotech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oncolytics Biotech</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this Phase 2 study is to investigate whether intravenous administration of a
      wild type reovirus (REOLYSIN®) in combination with paclitaxel and carboplatin is effective
      and safe in the treatment of Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer with KRAS or EGFR activation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Reovirus Serotype 3 - Dearing Strain (REOLYSIN®) is a naturally occurring, ubiquitous,
      non-enveloped human reovirus. Reovirus has been shown to replicate selectively in
      Ras-transformed cells causing cell lysis. Activating mutations in ras or mutation in
      oncogenes signaling through the ras pathway may occur in as many as 80% of human tumors. The
      specificity of the reovirus for Ras-transformed cells, coupled with its relatively
      nonpathogenic nature in humans, makes it an attractive anti-cancer therapy candidate.

      Given the ability of reovirus to replicate and cause oncolysis in Ras-activated cells, the
      high incidence of K-ras mutations in lung cancers, and the Ras-mediated activation often
      encountered in EGFR-addicted tumors, the administration of REOLYSIN® in combination with
      chemotherapy is expected to result in enhanced clinical benefit in non-small cell lung cancer
      (NSCLC) patients with K-ras mutations and/or EGFR aberrant activation in their tumors.
      Patients with de novo or acquired EGFR mutations in their tumors that confer resistance to
      EGFR TKIs (e.g. T790) are expected to benefit as well. This is a single arm, open-label,
      Phase 2 study of REOLYSIN® given intravenously with paclitaxel and carboplatin every 3 weeks
      (21 days is defined as a cycle) in NSCLC patients with tumors driven by these pathways.

      Paclitaxel at a dose of 175 mg/m2 will be given i.v. as a 3 hour infusion on Day 1 followed
      by carboplatin given i.v. AUC 5 mg/mL•minute. REOLYSIN® will be given over 60 min on Day 1
      (starting after completion of the carboplatin infusion), and on Days 2 - 5. The treatment
      cycle will be repeated every 21 days.

      Patients will receive 4 to 6 cycles of paclitaxel and carboplatin, at the treating
      physician's discretion according to standard of practice, in conjunction with REOLYSIN®.
      After completion of the 4 to 6 cycles of paclitaxel and carboplatin, REOLYSIN® may be
      continued as monotherapy Days 1-5 of each 21 day cycle until there is evidence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients may continue to receive therapy under this
      protocol, provided they have not experienced either progressive disease or unacceptable
      drug-related toxicity that does not respond to either supportive care or dose reduction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the objective response rate (complete response (CR) + partial response (PR)) of the treatment regimen in the study population</measure>
    <time_frame>For PR or CR, changes in tumor measurements must be confirmed 4 weeks after the criteria for response are first met.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the median duration of progression-free survival of patients receiving the study treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>during and following study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the median to 1-year survival of patients receiving the study treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the safety and tolerability of REOLYSIN® in combination with paclitaxel and carboplatin in this patient population.</measure>
    <time_frame>within 30 days of last dose of REOLYSIN®</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the proportion of patients receiving the above treatment who are alive and free of disease progression at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Non-small Cell Lung</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>REOLYSIN®</intervention_name>
    <description>3x10E10 TCID50, 1 hour intravenous infusion, administered on Days 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 of a 21 day cycle</description>
    <other_name>reovirus serotype 3 Dearing Strain</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>5 AUC mg/mL min, 30 min intravenous infusion, given on Day 1 of a 21 day cycle</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>175 mg/m2, 3 hour intravenous infusion, given on Day 1 of 21 day cycle</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  have histologically or cytologically confirmed stage IIIB (pleural effusion; IVA on
             revised IASLC staging) or stage IV, or recurrent, non-small cell lung cancer with
             evidence of RAS- or EGFR- activation in their tumors, as defined by EGFR activating
             mutations in exons 18 to 21, EGFR FISH amplification, or K-ras mutations in exon 2
             (codons 12,13,61).

          -  have evidence of measurable disease. For patients previously irradiated, the
             measurable lesion(s) must be outside of the treated field.

          -  be chemotherapy naïve for their metastatic or recurrent NSCLC. Prior adjuvant
             chemotherapy or chemo-XRT for treatment of localized disease is allowed, provided it
             has been ≥ 6 months since the last chemotherapy infusion. Previous radiation for
             palliative purposes is also allowed, as long as it has been ≥4 weeks from the last
             dose.

          -  Patients who have been previously treated with EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors as
             their only systemic treatment are eligible, provided this treatment has been
             discontinued for ≥4 weeks. Patients who have received erlotinib as first line
             treatment without chemotherapy and experience tumor progression will be eligible.

          -  have NO continuing acute toxic effects (except alopecia) of any prior radiotherapy,
             chemotherapy, or surgical procedures, i.e., all such effects must have resolved to
             Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE, version 3.0) Grade ≤ 1. Surgery
             (except biopsies) must have occurred at least 28 days prior to study enrollment.

          -  have an ECOG Performance Score of ≤ 2.

          -  have a life expectancy of at least 3 months.

          -  have baseline laboratory results as follows:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 10E9 [SI units 10^9/L]

               -  Platelets ≥ 100 x10E9 [SI units 10E9/L] (without platelet transfusion)

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL [SI units gm/L] (with or without RBC transfusion)

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               -  AST/ALT ≤ 2.5 x ULN

               -  Negative pregnancy test for females of childbearing potential.

          -  be willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, the treatment plan, and
             laboratory tests.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Receive concurrent therapy with any other anticancer agent while on study.

          -  Received chemotherapy within 6 months, or radiotherapy or EGFR therapy within 4 weeks,
             prior to entering the study or have not recovered from adverse events due to agents
             administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          -  Have brain metastases. Patients with resected oligometastasis are eligible if post
             resection MRI demonstrates resolution. Gamma knife treated patients are also eligible,
             if there are no more than two treated metastases confined to the same area of the
             brain and a post treatment MRI shows a decrease in the metastases.

          -  Have ≥ grade 2 peripheral neuropathy at baseline.

          -  Have uncontrolled cardiac dysfunction, including a myocardial infarction in the
             preceding 6 months, or known cardiac ejection fraction &lt; 40%.

          -  Be on immunosuppressive therapy or have known HIV infection or active hepatitis B or
             C.

          -  Be a pregnant or breast-feeding woman. Female patients of childbearing potential must
             agree to use effective contraception, must be surgically sterile, or must be
             postmenopausal. Male patients must agree to use effective contraception or be
             surgically sterile. Barrier methods are a recommended form of contraception.

          -  Have uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or
             active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
             cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/ social situations that would limit
             compliance with study requirements.

          -  Have dementia or altered mental status that would prohibit informed consent.

          -  Have any other severe, acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory
             abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or study
             drug administration or may interfere with the interpretation of study results and, in
             the judgment of the Principal Investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for
             this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miguel Villalona, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgetown University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University Medical Center, James Cancer Hospital and Solove Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 13, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>REOLYSIN</keyword>
  <keyword>reovirus</keyword>
  <keyword>non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>oncolytics virus</keyword>
  <keyword>chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>paclitaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>carboplatin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

