<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00865358</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AT002915</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00865358</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Yoga for Chronic Low Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Yoga for Chronic Low Back Pain in a Predominantly Minority Population: A Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic low back pain is the most common cause of pain in the United States. Common
      treatments such as medication, physical therapy, and surgery often do not provide adequate
      relief. Yoga has shown promise for improving low back pain in studies of predominantly middle
      class white individuals. We will assess the feasibility and collect preliminary data on yoga
      for chronic low back pain in predominantly minority individuals in a community health center
      setting in a low income neighborhood of Boston, Massachusetts. We hypothesize that offering
      yoga for this population is feasible and will show promising efficacy and safety data.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Promising therapies for chronic low back pain such as yoga need to be studied because
      conventional treatments such as medication, physical therapy, and surgery frequently do not
      provide lasting relief. We will use a standardized yoga protocol, developed specifically for
      this trial by a consensus panel of yoga experts, in a pilot randomized controlled trial for
      subjects with chronic low back pain. We will recruit 30 predominantly English-speaking
      minority adults from Boston Medical Center (BMC) and its affiliated clinics with low back
      pain lasting &gt;12 weeks and an average pain level in the previous week of 4 or more on a scale
      of 0 to 10 (0 = no pain, 10 = worst possible pain). Subjects will be randomized to a yoga
      class once per week for 12 weeks (Group 1) or a wait-list control group (Group 2). All
      subjects will receive their usual medical care and an educational booklet designed for low
      back pain patients. Primary outcomes are 12 week pain intensity and functional status
      measured by the Roland Morris Disability scale. Secondary outcomes include analgesic use,
      health-related quality of life (SF-36), global improvement, subject satisfaction, adverse
      events, compliance, work status, and health expenditures. Group 2 will be offered yoga
      classes at 26 weeks. To refine estimates of effect size and further confirm safety of the
      protocol, we will also collect data from Group 2 during their yoga classes. This pilot will
      provide preliminary feasibility and efficacy data to plan a future adequately powered
      randomized controlled trial of yoga for chronic low back pain in predominantly minority
      subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Previous 7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Back related function (Modified Roland Morris Disability Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>previous 7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain medication use</measure>
    <time_frame>previous 7 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>previous 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (SF-36)</measure>
    <time_frame>previous 7 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Yoga Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A standardized hatha yoga protocol delivered in 12 weekly classes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants continue to receive their usual medical care for their back pain</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Yoga Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Reproducible standardized 12 week series of hatha yoga classes specifically developed for patients with chronic low back pain and little or no experience with yoga</description>
    <arm_group_label>Yoga Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hatha yoga classes</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18-64 years old. The rationale for including adults only less than 65 years old is
             that the causes of low back pain in older persons are more likely to be multifactorial
             (e.g., degenerative disk disease, spinal canal stenosis, fractures) and less likely to
             be the non-specific muscular type that our yoga protocol was designed to address. A
             study of yoga for low back pain in individuals &gt; 65 years old is important. However,
             the ideal design would likely benefit from a yoga protocol specifically designed for
             this purpose.

          2. Current non-specific low back pain lasting at least 12 weeks. Non-specific refers to
             predominantly muscular and ligamentous causes for the low back pain, and the absence
             of clear symptoms and signs of other causes of low back pain (e.g., herniated disk).
             This will be ascertained during the eligibility screening process using the
             Eligibility Screening Instrument (see Sect. S). This instrument was adapted from
             eligibility screening tools used in multiple published trials of CAM therapies for
             chronic low back pain by Karen Sherman PhD and Daniel Cherkin PhD. The instrument uses
             subject self-report to exclude specific causes of chronic low back pain that are
             exclusion criteria for the study.

          3. Average pain intensity during the week prior to enrollment is 4 or greater on a 0 to
             10 numerical pain scale (0=no pain, 10=worst possible pain).

          4. Compliant with filling out a 2 week daily pain score dairy during the eligibility
             screening processes.

          5. Ability to comprehend, read, and write English at a level necessary to understand the
             yoga class instructions and complete data collection forms. Given that this is the
             first pilot for the yoga protocol and the first trial of yoga for low back pain for
             predominantly minority adults at BMC and affiliated clinics, we have decided to
             enhance feasibility by focusing on English speakers first. Our goal is ultimately to
             study and offer this intervention in other languages commonly spoken by BMC patients
             (e.g., Spanish). We fully anticipate that this trial will provide the necessary
             experience to return to the IRB in the near future with a proposal for a pilot trial
             of Spanish speakers with chronic low back pain.

          6. Individuals with sufficient English language ability from all ethnic groups can
             enroll. However, since this pilot study is specifically targeting minorities with
             chronic low back pain, we will purposefully allocate 80% (24 of 30) of the openings in
             the study to minority subjects (ascertained by self-report).

          7. Consent to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &gt; 64 years old.

          2. Yoga use in the previous 12 months.

          3. Inability to understand English at a level necessary to follow yoga class
             instructions.

          4. Pregnancy - although back pain in pregnancy is common and may be amenable to yoga, the
             causes of the pain are likely different than non specific chronic low back pain in
             nonpregnant adults.

          5. Change in pain medications four weeks or fewer prior to enrollment.

          6. Other back pain treatments (e.g., physical therapy, epidural steroid injection,
             chiropractic, acupuncture) anticipated to begin in the next 6 months or initiated less
             than four weeks prior to enrollment.

          7. Ongoing or planned litigation related to back pain. Ongoing or planned workers'
             compensation, disability, or personal injury claims related to back pain. Litigation
             or claims that have been resolved or settled are not exclusion criteria.

          8. Back pain by self-report due to specific non-muscular pathologies (e.g., infection,
             malignancy, fracture); severe or progressive neurological deficits; active substance
             or alcohol abuse; serious underlying systemic or co-morbid disease that precludes
             physical or cognitive ability to perform the yoga protocol (see Inclusion Criteria #2
             above).

          9. Suicidal thoughts detected through the eligibility interview. Those who report
             suicidal thoughts will immediately be referred to their PCP and/or the BMC Department
             of Psychiatry.

         10. Lack of consent to participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert B Saper, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dorchester Multi-Service Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dorchester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Codman Square Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dorchester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>yoga</keyword>
  <keyword>complementary alternative medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>minority health</keyword>
  <keyword>health care disparities</keyword>
  <keyword>community health centers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

