<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00867061</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Onconova 04-11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00867061</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of 5-day Dosing of ON 01910.Na in Intermediate-1,-2, or High Risk Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2, Single-Arm Study To Assess The Efficacy and Safety Of 5-day Continuous Intravenous Dosing Of ON 01910.Na Administered Every 2 Weeks in Patients With Intermediate-1, Intermediate-2, or High Risk Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Onconova Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Onconova Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For MDS patients who have not responded to or have progressed after an initial response to
      DNA methyltransferase inhibitors (DNMTI) and are not stem cell transplant candidates,
      therapeutic options are limited. Participation in clinical trials such as this one may be
      considered. The specific objectives of this trial are to find out which dose of ON 01910.Na
      can be safety given to MDS patients and then find out if this dose of drug has any beneficial
      effects on the patients' disease. ON 01910.Na is a new, experimental drug; the reason for
      doing this trial is based on the anti-cancer activity of ON 01910.Na that has been observed
      in laboratory experiments and in early clinical trials.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single center, open label, phase 1/2 study in which two to thirty three patients
      with Intermediate-1, Intermediate-2, or High risk MDS will receive ON 01910.Na as a
      intravenous continuous infusion (IVCI) over 24 hours for 5 consecutive days every 2 weeks.

      In the phase 1 component of this trial the maximum tolerated dose of ON1910.Na in patients
      with Intermediate-1, Intermediate-2 or High Risk myelodysplastic syndromes will be
      determined. A standard &quot;3+3&quot; dose escalation scheme will be followed with up to six patients
      treated at the 800 mg/m2/day dose level. Patients will be observed for 2 cycles before dose
      escalation occurs. If none of the initial three patients in the 800 mg/m2/day cohort
      experience dose-limiting toxicity (DLT), during the first two cycles, then a new cohort of
      three patients will be treated at the 1500 mg/m2/day dose level. If none of the initial three
      patients in the 1500 mg/m2/day cohort experience DLT during the first two cycles, three
      additional patients will be treated at the 1500 mg/m2/day level. If no more than one of the
      six patients at the 1500 mg/m2/day dose level experiences a DLT, then that dose level will be
      confirmed as the MTD and no further dose escalation will occur.

      If one of the three patients in the 800 mg/m2/day cohort experiences DLT during the first two
      cycles, then up to three additional patients will be treated at the same dose level.
      Escalation to 1500 mg/m2/day will proceed if only one of the six patients experiences DLT at
      the 800 mg/m2/day dose level. If two or more patients in the 800 mg/m2/day cohort experience
      DLT during the first two cycles, then the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) will have been
      exceeded, no further dose escalation will occur, and a full safety review will determine if
      further enrollment of patients will proceed.

      If the 800 mg/m2/day dose level is under consideration as the MTD (i.e. if ≥ 2 patients
      experience DLT at the 1500 mg/m2/day dose level), and only three patients were treated before
      escalation to 1500 mg/m2/day, then three additional patients will be accrued. If no more than
      one of the six patients at the 800 mg/m2/day dose level experiences a DLT, then that dose
      level will be confirmed as the MTD.

      Once the phase 1 portion of the study is completed, accrual to the phase 2 portion will
      begin. Patients treated at the MTD during the phase 1 portion will be included in the phase 2
      component and will be evaluated for response and secondary end points.

      The total study duration is 29 weeks, which includes a 2-week screening phase, a 23-week
      dosing phase, and a 4-week follow-up phase that begins after the last dose of ON 01910.Na.
      Patients will be assessed for response and will undergo follow up.

      Patients who drop out for any reason will not be replaced. Patients who achieve a complete or
      partial response or stabilization of their disease by week 25 are eligible to receive an
      additional 24 weeks of ON 01910.Na at the same dose they received during the first 24 weeks
      of treatment(800 or 1500 mg/m2/day IVCI for 5 days Q2W).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Mutual decision by site and sponsor because of difficulty recruiting Patients.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>March 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (in Phase 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response according to International Working Group criteria (in Phase 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 to 3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response time</measure>
    <time_frame>2 - 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IPSS score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neutrophil response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Platelet response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Erythroid response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ON 01910.Na Concentrate</intervention_name>
    <description>5-day continuous intravenous dosing of ON 01910.Na given every 2 weeks (1 cycle) at a dose of 800 mg/m2/day or 1500mg/m2/day for up to 24 cycles.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of MDS confirmed within 4 weeks prior to study entry according to the World
             Health Organization (WHO) Criteria or the French-American-British (FAB)
             Classification.

          -  IPSS score of at least 0.5 (Intermediate-1, Intermediate-2 or High Risk MDS)

          -  Failure of, or insufficient response to 5-azacitidine or decitabine administered for 4
             to 6 cycles.

          -  Failed to respond to, relapsed following, or opted not to participate in bone marrow
             transplantation.

          -  Off all other treatments for MDS, including filgrastim (G-CSF) and erythropoietin for
             at least 2 weeks, and off standard or investigational MDS therapies for four weeks.

          -  ECOG Performance Status 0, 1 or 2.

          -  Adequate contraceptive [including prescription oral contraceptives (birth control
             pills), contraceptive injections, intrauterine device (IUD), double-barrier method
             (spermicidal jelly or foam with condoms or diaphragm), contraceptive patch, or
             surgical sterilization] before entry and throughout the study for female patients of
             reproductive potential.

          -  Female patients with reproductive potential must have a negative serum beta-HCG
             pregnancy test at screening.

          -  Willing to adhere to the prohibitions and restrictions specified in this protocol.

          -  Patient (or his/her legally authorized representative) must have signed an informed
             consent document indicating that he/she understands the purpose of and procedures
             required for the study and is willing to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anemia due to factors other than MDS (including hemolysis or gastrointestinal
             bleeding).

          -  Hypoplastic MDS (cellularity &lt;10%).

          -  Any active malignancy within the past year except basal cell or squamous cell skin
             cancer or carcinoma in situ of the cervix or breast.

          -  History of HIV-1 seropositivity.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to symptomatic congestive
             heart failure, unstable angina pectoris or cardiac arrhythmia.

          -  Active infection not adequately responding to appropriate therapy.

          -  Total bilirubin ≥ 1.5 mg/dL not related to hemolysis or Gilbert's disease, ALT or AST
             ≥ 2 X ULN.

          -  Serum creatinine ≥ 1.5 mg/dL or calculated creatinine clearance ≤ 60 ml/min/1.73 m2

          -  Ascites requiring active medical management including paracentesis, or hyponatremia
             (defined as serum sodium value of &lt;134 Meq/L).

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or lactating.

          -  Male patients with female sexual partners who are unwilling to follow the strict
             contraception requirements described in this protocol.

          -  Major surgery without full recovery or major surgery within 3 weeks of ON 01910.Na
             treatment start.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (defined as a systolic pressure ≥ 160 and/or a diastolic
             pressure ≥ 110).

          -  New onset seizures (within 3 months prior to the first dose of ON 01910.Na) or poorly
             controlled seizures.

          -  Any concurrent investigational agent or chemotherapy, radiotherapy or immunotherapy.

          -  Treatment with myeloid growth factors or erythropoiesis stimulating agents (ESA)
             within 2 weeks of starting ON 01910.Na.

          -  Treatment with standard MDS therapies or investigational therapy within 4 weeks of
             starting ON 01910.Na.

          -  Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit the patient's ability to
             tolerate and/or comply with study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Virginia Klimek, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org</url>
    <description>Website of trial study center. Provides cancer care information to healthcare professionals, researchers, patients, family members, and the public.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.onconova.com</url>
    <description>Website of trial sponsor. Provides background information about ON 01910.Na.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jimeno A, Chan A, Cusatis G, Zhang X, Wheelhouse J, Solomon A, Chan F, Zhao M, Cosenza SC, Ramana Reddy MV, Rudek MA, Kulesza P, Donehower RC, Reddy EP, Hidalgo M. Evaluation of the novel mitotic modulator ON 01910.Na in pancreatic cancer and preclinical development of an ex vivo predictive assay. Oncogene. 2009 Jan 29;28(4):610-8. doi: 10.1038/onc.2008.424. Epub 2008 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19029951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheson BD, Bennett JM, Kantarjian H, Pinto A, Schiffer CA, Nimer SD, Löwenberg B, Beran M, de Witte TM, Stone RM, Mittelman M, Sanz GF, Wijermans PW, Gore S, Greenberg PL; World Health Organization(WHO) international working group. Report of an international working group to standardize response criteria for myelodysplastic syndromes. Blood. 2000 Dec 1;96(12):3671-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11090046</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenberg P, Cox C, LeBeau MM, Fenaux P, Morel P, Sanz G, Sanz M, Vallespi T, Hamblin T, Oscier D, Ohyashiki K, Toyama K, Aul C, Mufti G, Bennett J. International scoring system for evaluating prognosis in myelodysplastic syndromes. Blood. 1997 Mar 15;89(6):2079-88. Erratum in: Blood 1998 Feb 1;91(3):1100.</citation>
    <PMID>9058730</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aarthi Shenoy, Loretta Pfannes, Francois Wilhelm, Manoj Maniar, Neal Young, and Elaine M Sloand Suppression of Cyclin D 1 (CD1) by ON 01910.Na Is Associated with Decreased Survival or Trisomy 8 Myelodysplastic Bone Marrow: A Potential Targetted Therapy for Trisomy 8 MDS. Blood (ASH Annual Meeting Abstracts), Nov 2008; 112: 1651.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elaine M. Sloand, Loretta Pfannes, Ramana Reddy, Premkumar Reddy, Jerome S. Groopman, and Neal S. Young Suppression of Cyclin D1 by ON 01910.Na Is Associated with Decreased Survival of Trisomy 8 Myelodyplastic Bone Marrow Progenitors: A Potential Targetted Therapy. Blood (ASH Annual Meeting Abstracts), Nov 2007; 110: 822.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Garcia-Manero G, Fenaux P. Comprehensive Analysis of Safety: Rigosertib in 557 Patients with Myelodysplastic Syndromes (MDS) and Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML). Blood Dec 2016, 128 (22) 2011; ASH 2016.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 19, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myelodysplastic</keyword>
  <keyword>IPSS Intermediate 1</keyword>
  <keyword>IPSS Intermediate 2</keyword>
  <keyword>IPSS High risk</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

