<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01973400</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VENUS-7327</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NMRR-10-948-7327</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01973400</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neuroprotection by Tocotrienols in Type 1 and Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <acronym>VENUS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Clinical Study on the Neuroprotection by Tocotrienols in Type 1 and Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Science Malaysia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clinical Research Centre, Malaysia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Malaysia Palm Oil Board</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Science Malaysia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Given that the tocotrienols have been shown to possess neuroprotective effects and that both
      type 1 and type 2 diabetes can lead to peripheral neuropathy and cognitive impairment, the
      present study aims to determine the beneficial effects of tocotrienols in ameliorating such
      neurological related events in both type 1 and type 2 diabetic patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Neuropathy affects approximately 30-50% of all diabetic patients and is the commonest form of
      neuropathy in the developed world. Pain is the most distressing symptom of neuropathy and the
      main factor that prompts the patient to seek medical advice. About 16-26% of diabetes
      patients experience chronic neuropathic pain. An animal study revealed that treating rats
      with α-tocopherol and tocotrienol for 10 weeks significantly improved all the biochemical and
      behavioral outcomes of alcohol-induced neuropathy in a dose-dependent manner with more potent
      effects observed with tocotrienols. The study demonstrates the effectiveness of tocotrienols
      in attenuation of alcoholic neuropathy.

      Cognitive dysfunction is a less addressed and not as well recognized complication of
      diabetes. Patients with type 1 and type 2 diabetes mellitus have been found to have cognitive
      deficits that can be attributed to their disease. Both old age and diabetes are independently
      associated with an increased risk of cognitive dysfunction; the risk is even greater for
      older adults with diabetes. Cognitive Function is the term used to describe a person's state
      of consciousness (alertness and orientation), memory, and attention span. It has been
      suggested that Vitamin E, including tocopherols and tocotrienols, can help to improve
      cognitive function and stall cognitive decline through its antioxidant effects. A reason for
      this nutrient's success at preventing oxidative damage in brain cells is its fat-soluble
      criteria. During the World Alzheimer's Congress held in July 2001, it was reported that high
      intakes of vitamin E effectively lessened memory loss and cognitive dysfunction among more
      than 6,000 elderly subjects who were generally taking Vitamin E between 200 to 400 IU per
      day.

      Tocotrienols, in particular α-tocotrienol have been shown to possess neuroprotective effect
      independent of anti-oxidant activity. Using cell-based studies, α-tocotrienol but not
      α-tocopherol was shown to prevent glutamate-induced neuronal cell death at nanomolar
      concentrations. Later studies showed that α-tocotrienol conferred protection against
      glutamate and stroke-induced neurodegeneration in rats.

      In view of the above neuroprotective property of tocotrienols, researchers have proceeded to
      demonstrate that tocotrienols supplementation helped to reverse neuropathic pain in diabetic
      rats. It has been postulated the beneficial properties of tocotrienols are due to their
      suppressive effects on the oxidative-nitrosative stress, inflammatory cytokine release and
      caspase-3 which are implicated in the pathogenesis of diabetic neuropathy.

      In the same year, tocotrienols were shown to prevent cognitive deficits and attenuate
      alcoholic peripheral neuropathy associated with selective neuronal damage due to chronic
      alcohol consumption. Moreover, the beneficial effects were found to be more pronounced with
      tocotrienols compared to tocopherols. It has been postulated that the anti-oxidants property
      of tocotrienols, the suppression of nitrosative stress and elevated cytokines levels together
      with acetylcholinesterase activity in the brain regions contributes significantly in
      preventing the chronic alcohol-induced cognitive deficits in rats.

      Yuen and his group are currently conducting a clinical study in human subjects on
      neuroprotective effects of tocotrienols (NCT00753532). In the study, subjects were followed
      up for 2 years to determine the volume of white matter lesions on repeated MRI after
      treatment with tocotrienol as compared to placebo. White matter lesions are related to
      vascular events in the brain and represent subclinical infarcts, resulting in death/
      degeneration of neurons and are positively correlated to cognitive impairment. Preliminary
      results from an interim analysis are encouraging; patients on tocotrienols shown significant
      reduction in volume of white matter lesion (confidential communication).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Symptoms Score (TSS) (pain, paresthesia, burning, and numbness)of patients with diabetes type 1 and 2 neuropathy.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropathy Impairment Score (NIS) of patients with diabetes type 1 and 2 neuropathy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) score, Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) test.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measures the effects of tocotrienols on cognitive impairment in type 1 and type 2 diabetes mellitus</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Neuropathy</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tocotrienol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>200 mg, twice a day, 12 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>200 mg, twice a day, 12 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tocotrienol</intervention_name>
    <description>Palm-Oil derived Vitamin E, tocotrienol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tocotrienol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diabetic adults ( both type 1 or 2) ≥20 years old with diabetic peripheral neuropathy
             with Total Symptom Score(TSS) ≥ 3 points.

          -  Patients with type 1 diabetes (duration of ≥5 years).

          -  Patients with type 2 diabetes (at diagnosis).

          -  Patients with Neuropathy Impairment Score(NIS) &gt; 2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients HbA1c &gt;12%.

          -  Patients with hypoglycemia or conscious impairment at the time of test conduction.

          -  Patients exhibiting symptoms of peripheral vascular disease with absence of 2 foot
             pulses on the same foot (Posterior tibialis, Dorsalis pedis)

          -  Immuno-compromised patients.

          -  Patients with severe visual impairment, history of psychosis; schizophrenia; bipolar
             disorder; current depression or brain trauma and patients with alcohol dependence or
             drug abuse such as cocaine, heroin, etc.

          -  Those having lesions with a propensity to bleed (e.g., bleeding peptic ulcers), those
             having a history of hemorrhagic stroke and those with inherited bleeding disorders
             (e.g., hemophilia) or patients on warfarin.

          -  Pregnancy and lactation.

          -  Patients with renal function test of more than 150 umol/L (serum creatinine).

          -  Patients with liver function test of more than 5 times of the upper normal range

          -  Active infection or infectious diseases.

          -  Other significant uncontrolled medical illnesses that may interfere with drug
             administration or interpretation of results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kah Hay Yuen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Science Malaysia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seberang Jaya Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seberang Jaya</city>
        <state>Penang</state>
        <zip>13700</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 24, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Science Malaysia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yuen Kah Hay</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Neuropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tocotrienols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin E</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tocopherols</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

