<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01974479</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NKCARCD19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01974479</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of Redirected Haploidentical Natural Killer Cell Infusions for B-Lineage Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study of Redirected Haploidentical Natural Killer Cell Infusions for B-Lineage Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University Health System, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Singapore General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University Health System, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Modern therapy for patients with B-lineage acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) is based on
      intensive administration of multiple drugs. In patients with relapsed disease, treatment
      response is generally poor; for most patients, particularly those who relapse while still
      receiving frontline therapy, the only therapeutic option is hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation (HSCT). There is no proven curative therapy for patients who relapse after
      transplant.

      Natural killer (NK) cells have powerful anti-leukemia activity. In patients undergoing
      allogeneic HSCT, several studies have demonstrated NK-mediated anti-leukemic activity. NK
      cell infusions in patients with leukemia have been shown to be well tolerated and void of
      graft-versus-host disease (GVHD) effects.

      NK cell cytotoxicity is most powerful against acute myeloid leukemia (AML) cells, whereas
      their capacity to lyse ALL cells is generally low. We have developed a novel method to expand
      and redirect NK cells towards CD19, a molecule highly expressed on the surface of B-lineage
      ALL cells but not expressed on normal cells other than B-lymphocytes. In this method, donor
      NK cells are first expanded by co-culture with the cell line K562-mb15-41BBL and interleukin
      (IL)-2. Then, the expanded NK cells are transduced with a signaling receptor that binds to
      CD19 (anti-CD19-BB-zeta). NK cells expressing these receptors showed powerful anti-leukemic
      activity against CD19+ ALL cells in vitro and in an animal model of leukemia.

      This study will assess the feasibility, safety and efficacy of infusing expanded, activated
      redirected NK cells into research participants with B-lineage ALL who have persistent disease
      after intensive chemotherapy . In this same cohort, we will study the in vivo lifespan and
      phenotype of these redirected NK cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1.0. Rationale

      In contrast to the well-established cytotoxicity of NK cells against AML cells, their
      capacity to lyse ALL cells is generally low and difficult to predict. We sought to overcome
      this intrinsic resistance by transducing CD56+ CD3─ NK cells with chimeric receptors directed
      against CD19, a molecule widely expressed by malignant B cells. Expression of anti-CD19
      receptors linked to CD3zeta overcame NK resistance and markedly enhanced NK cell-mediated
      killing of leukemic cells. This result was significantly improved by adding the 4-1BB
      costimulatory molecule to the chimeric anti-CD19-CD3zeta receptor: the cytotoxicity produced
      by NK cells expressing this construct uniformly exceeded that of NK cells whose signaling
      receptors lacked 4-1BB, even when natural cytotoxicity was apparent (Imai et al., Blood
      2005). NK cells expressing anti-CD19 receptors also exerted vigorous anti-ALL activity in a
      murine model of leukemia (Shimasaki et al., Cytotherapy 2012). Our findings indicate that
      enforced expression of signaling receptors by NK cells might circumvent inhibitory signals,
      providing a novel means to enhance the effectiveness of anti-ALL NK cell therapy.

      The great anti-leukemic efficacy of genetically modified NK cells shown in our preclinical
      studies, together with the demonstrated feasibility of infusing durable haploidentical NK
      cells in a non-HSCT setting and the established expertise by the NUH team in cell therapy
      (the only center in Asia accredited by Foundation for the Accreditation of Cellular Therapy,
      FACT), form a compelling rationale for the clinical testing of these NK cells.

      The preparation of the key reagent (anti-CD19-BB-zeta mRNA) is finalized in the Tissue
      Engineering &amp; Cell Therapy (TECT) Laboratory at NUH, where the GMP-compliant MaxCyte
      electroporator is located. The feasibility of large-scale expansion of NK cells has been
      demonstrated (Shimasaki et al. Cytotherapy 2012), and the feasibility of large-scale
      electroporation validated in the TECT laboratory.

      We will use flow cytometric and MRD technologies, to determine the presence of persistent
      disease , and will include in this study only patients with a limited amount of residual
      disease (&lt;1% leukemic lymphoblasts among normal bone marrow cells). We will use the same MRD
      methods to monitor the effects of treatment infusions. We do not expect that the conditioning
      regimen will have much effect by itself on leukemic cell counts, as the patients eligible for
      the study will have disease that is resistant to many anti-leukemic drugs. Nevertheless,
      because the conditioning regimen itself may have some salutary effects, it will be important
      to screen the peripheral blood and/or bone marrow for the presence of leukemic blast cells
      through all stages of the procedure, i.e., before, during, and after conditioning and after
      the NK cell infusion. The presence of leukemic cells in will be closely monitored by flow
      cytometry or PCR amplification of antigen-receptor genes (sensitivity for either method: 1
      leukemic cell in 10,000) to shed some light on the relative effect of each intervention.

      2.0. Hypothesis and Objectives

      The main hypothesis to be tested in this study is that infusion of NK cells expressing
      anti-CD19-BB-zeta receptors by electroporation can produce measurable clinical responses in
      patients with resistant B-lineage ALL.

      3.0. Primary Objectives

        -  To determine the feasibility and safety of redirecting NK cells with an anti-CD19
           chimeric antigen receptor by mRNA electroporation in a clinical setting.

        -  To determine the efficacy of anti-CD19 redirected NK cells in research participants with
           B-lineage ALL who have persistent disease as determined by MRD methods after intensive
           chemotherapy.

      4.0. Secondary Objectives

        -  To study the persistence and phenotype of redirected NK cells in research participants
           with B-lineage ALL who have residual disease after intensive chemotherapy.

      5.0. Endpoints

      In this study, treatment response will be measured by comparing MRD levels before and at
      several intervals after NK cell infusion.Achievement of MRD negativity in bone marrow, i.e.,
      &lt; 0.01% blasts by flow cytometry or PCR, will be regarded as a complete response. Partial
      response will be defined as ≥ 1 log decrease in MRD levels, while &lt; 1 log decrease in MRD
      levels will be regarded as a no response.

      Based on previous studies, donor NK cells will be eliminated in most cases by the resurgent
      cellular immunity of the haploidentical recipient after the effects of the transient
      immunosuppression caused by the conditioning regimen have ceased (typically within 1 month of
      infusion). Conceivably, however, NK cell engraftment may persist for a longer period with the
      possible risk of prolonged pancytopenia owing to NK cell killing on normal hematopoietic
      cells. Because of this possibility, we will plan for HSCT rescue in patients receiving
      redirected NK cell infusions. Indeed, for most of the patients eligible for this study, HSCT
      would be the treatment intervention regardless of whether they receive NK cell infusions or
      not. Because of these considerations, the potential benefits of NK cell therapy should
      outweigh its risks for those patients eligible for this study, i.e., patients with persistent
      leukemia for whom no other proven effective treatment is available.

      Because CD19 is universally expressed on B cells including early B cell precursors, normal
      recipient B cell will also be a target for the donor NK cells transduced with the anti-CD19
      chimeric receptors. Therefore, transient B-cell lymphopenia and hypogammaglobinemia are
      expected. We will monitor the CD19+ blood cell count and measure the Ig levels once a month
      and will give the participants intravenous immunoglobulins (IVIG) if their IgG level is lower
      than age-specific ranges.

      6.0. Summary of Study Design

      Peripheral blood cell will be collected by apheresis from donors. After ex vivo expansion for
      10 days by coculture with irradiated K562-mb15-41BBL cells (Fujisaki et al, Cancer Res 2009;
      Lapteva et al. Cytotherapy 2012) and T-cell depletion, haploidentical NK cells will be
      electroporated with anti-CD19-BB-zeta mRNA. Before infusion, patients will receive
      immunosuppressive therapy to promote temporary engraftment of NK cells. After infusion, they
      will receive IL-2 to support NK cell viability and expansion in vivo. The effects of NK cell
      infusion will be determine by comparing MRD levels before and after treatment.

      Receptor expression after electroporation is transient and typically declines after 48 hours
      becoming undetectable after 96 hours. Because the aim of NK cell therapy is not to induce
      durable immunity but to rapidly reduce tumor cell burden, and the infused NK cells are
      rejected by the host immune system after approximately 2 weeks of infusion, the transient
      nature of the expression should not significantly affect anti-tumor potential. Moreover, by
      using this strategy, safety concerns regarding insertional mutagenesis and long-term
      persistence of transduced residual T cells do not apply. In any case, we will minimize the
      number of residual T cells in the final product as much as possible by depleting the expanded
      product of T cells by using the CliniMACS device, and by limiting the number of T cells in
      the graft to &lt;0.05 x 10^6/kg.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Suspended for 12 months - an interim review of (CAR) CD19 research strategy for the treatment
    of CD19 positive ALL.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>To determine the feasibility, safety and efficacy of anti-CD19 redirected NK cells infusion in research participants with B-Lineage Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (B-ALL) who have persistent disease as determined by MRD methods after intensive chemotherapy.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Response Criteria - Minimal Disease Residual (MRD) Monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Month Post NK Cell Infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment response will be measured by comparing MRD levels before and 1 month after NK cell infusion. Achievement of MRD negativity in bone marrow, i.e., &lt; 0.01% blasts by flow cytometry or PCR, will be regarded as a complete response. Partial response will be defined as ≥ 1 log decrease in MRD levels, while &lt; 1 log decrease in MRD levels will be regarded as no response.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>B-cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>anti-CD19 redirected NK cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a single arm study. Intravenous Infusion of activated NK cells bearing anti-CD19-BB-zeta receptors at cell dose of 0.5 - 5 x 10^7 CD56+ cells/kg, and up to 1 x 10^8 CD56+ cells/Kg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>anti-CD19 redirected NK cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Haploidentical donor NK cells will be expanded and electroporated over 10 days and infused. NK cells will be infused at single dose on day 0. The patient will receive cyclophosphamide 60mg/kg on day - 7 , and Fludarabine 25 mg/m2/day will be given on day -6 to day -2 prior to the NK cell infusion. IL- 2 will be given subcutaneously for 6 doses every alternate day starting on day -1, for NK cell survival.</description>
    <arm_group_label>anti-CD19 redirected NK cells</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NKCARCD19</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  NK cell RECIPIENT:

               1. Age: 0 months to 80 years old.

               2. Patients with B-lineage ALL who have persistent disease (0.01% to less than 1% as
                  determined by flow cytometric or molecular measurements of residual disease)
                  despite intensive standard chemotherapy .

               3. Shortening fraction greater than or equal to 25%.

               4. Glomerular filtration rate greater than or equal to 50 ml/min/1.73 m2.

               5. Pulse oximetry greater than or equal to 92% on room air.

               6. Direct bilirubin less than or equal to 3.0 mg/dL (50 mmol/L).

               7. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) is no more than 2 times the upper limit of normal.

               8. Aspartate transaminases (AST)is no more than 2 times the upper limit of normal.

               9. Karnofsky or Lansky performance score of greater than or equal to 50.

              10. No known allergy to murine products or HAMA testing results within normal limits.

              11. No prior receipt of a gene-transfer agent (e.g. retroviral,adenoviral, lentiviral
                  vector).

              12. Does not have a current pleural or pericardial effusion.

              13. Has a suitable adult family member donor available for NK cell donation.

              14. Has recovered from all acute NCI Common Toxicity Criteria grade II-IV
                  non-hematologic acute toxicities resulting from prior therapy per the judgment of
                  the PI.

              15. At least two weeks since receipt of any biological therapy, systemic
                  chemotherapy, and/or radiation therapy.

              16. Is not receiving more than the equivalent of prednisone 10 mg daily.

              17. Not pregnant (negative serum or urine pregnancy test to be conducted within 7
                  days prior to enrollment).

              18. Not lactating.

          -  NK cell DONOR:

               1. First and second relative acceptable.

               2. 18 years of age or above.

               3. Not lactating.

               4. Greater than or equal to 3 of 6 HLA match to recipient.

               5. Meets eligibility and suitability criteria for hematopoietic cells donation as
                  per institutional guidelines.

               6. Not pregnant (negative serum or urine pregnancy test to be conducted within 7
                  days prior to enrollment).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Failure to meet any of the inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Poh Lin Tan</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NUHS Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dario Campana</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NUHS Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Paediatrics, National University Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>119228</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Haematology, NCIS, National University Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Hematology, Singapore General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Imai C, Iwamoto S, Campana D. Genetic modification of primary natural killer cells overcomes inhibitory signals and induces specific killing of leukemic cells. Blood. 2005 Jul 1;106(1):376-83. Epub 2005 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>15755898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shimasaki N, Fujisaki H, Cho D, Masselli M, Lockey T, Eldridge P, Leung W, Campana D. A clinically adaptable method to enhance the cytotoxicity of natural killer cells against B-cell malignancies. Cytotherapy. 2012 Aug;14(7):830-40. doi: 10.3109/14653249.2012.671519. Epub 2012 Mar 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22458956</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fujisaki H, Kakuda H, Shimasaki N, Imai C, Ma J, Lockey T, Eldridge P, Leung WH, Campana D. Expansion of highly cytotoxic human natural killer cells for cancer cell therapy. Cancer Res. 2009 May 1;69(9):4010-7. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-3712. Epub 2009 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>19383914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lapteva N, Durett AG, Sun J, Rollins LA, Huye LL, Fang J, Dandekar V, Mei Z, Jackson K, Vera J, Ando J, Ngo MC, Coustan-Smith E, Campana D, Szmania S, Garg T, Moreno-Bost A, Vanrhee F, Gee AP, Rooney CM. Large-scale ex vivo expansion and characterization of natural killer cells for clinical applications. Cytotherapy. 2012 Oct;14(9):1131-43. doi: 10.3109/14653249.2012.700767. Epub 2012 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22900959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 1, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National University Health System, Singapore</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Tan Poh Lin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Director and Senior Consultant of Paediatric Blood and Marrow Transplantation</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Redirected Natural Killer Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Haploidentical Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

