<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01972035</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1307M37702</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01972035</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ValGanciclovir Versus ValAcyclovir for Viral Prophylaxis in Kidney Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>ValGanciclovir Versus ValAcyclovir for Viral Prophylaxis in Kidney Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Our study will compare all kidney transplant recipients receiving valganciclovir vs.
      valacyclovir for one year following kidney transplant and compare:

        1. the incidence, magnitude and duration of CMV and EBV viremia in the first year after
           transplant.

        2. the side effects of the anti-viral drugs requiring dose reduction or cessation

      In addition, we will test renal tissue obtained from any biopsies post-transplant
      (surveillance or clinically indicated biopsies) by both polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and
      fluorescence in situ hybridization to assess for latent CMV and/or EBV.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Herpes viruses such as Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) and cytomegalovirus (CMV) cause considerable
      morbidity and mortality post-kidney transplant. Even subclinical CMV and/or EBV viremia have
      been associated with deterioration in kidney transplant function. Currently, valganciclovir
      (valG) is the primary prophylactic agent against CMV in kidney transplant recipients but CMV
      viremia has been noted in 22% of pediatric post-kidney transplant recipients, and the
      incidence at the University of Minnesota (UMMC) in all kidney transplant recipients is as
      high as 17% despite valG prophylaxis. CMV disease post-kidney transplant can manifest as
      fever, leucopenia, or mild to severe organ involvement. While an effective anti-CMV drug,
      valG has a number of adverse effects including leucopenia, also a side effect of
      mycophenolate mofetil (MMF), one of the cornerstones of current anti-rejection regimens.
      Combined therapy with MMF and valG frequently results in leucopenia associated infection or
      leucopenia necessitating reduction in MMF doses, increasing the risk of rejection. In
      addition, valG is prohibitively expensive forcing many centers adopt a pre-emptive
      therapeutic approach whereby post-Ktx patients are screened for CMV, and at new onset
      viremia, valG is initiated. This approach has been associated with increased CMV infections
      and resistant viral strains. Therefore, there is need for an alternate, more cost-effective
      drug with a more benign side effect profile and equal effectiveness against CMV.

      To date, the anti-EBV effect of valG is poorly defined and prevention of EBV infection is by
      close monitoring and immunosuppression reduction at the discovery of EBV viremia. EBV can
      present post-kidney transplants as infectious mononucleosis syndrome, hepatitis and, most
      importantly, can initiate potentially fatal lymphoproliferative disorders (PTLD). Between
      October 2003 and December 2009, EBV viremia occurred in 20% of adults and 50% of pediatric
      kidney transplant recipients (60/120) at UMMC, and, PTLD occurred in 6% (7/120) of pediatric
      recipients. Effective anti-EBV prophylaxis could substantially improve kidney transplant
      outcomes.

      UMMC conducts surveillance biopsies at transplant and 3 and 12 months post-kidney transplant
      on all adult transplant recipients, providing an ideal opportunity to assess kidney tissue
      for EBV and CMV via molecular and immunological assays. Isolating the virus from infected
      recipient would be a pivotal step in our understanding of the mechanisms of CMV and EBV
      infection post-kidney transplant.

      In summary, if valacyclovir and valganciclovir have equivalent efficacy in CMV prophylaxis,
      and valacyclovir has the anticipated effect on EBV prevention, the use of valacyclovir will
      result in a reduced risk of leucopenia-associated infection, and a lower incidence of
      rejection by allowing the use of standard MMF doses. Since valacyclovir is cheaper, it is
      plausible that universal prophylaxis will be a plausible and affordable option for all
      transplant recipients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare incidence, duration and magnitude of CMV and EBV viremia in kidney transplant recipients receiving valA vs. valG.</measure>
    <time_frame>First year post-kidney transplant</time_frame>
    <description>In infectious mononucleosis intervention trials, two weeks of valA therapy resulted in a statistically significant reduction in oral EBV shedding, accompanied by a clinical benefit, and valA is currently used for the therapy of severe cases of infectious mononucleosis in the community. ValA has also been shown to reduce the incidence and delay the onset of CMV disease in both CMV seronegative patients (P&lt;0.001) and CMV seropositive patients (P=0.03). Therefore we hypothesize that the anti-EBV and anti-CMV effects of valA will be equal to or more effective than valG in reducing post-kidney transplant EBV and CMV viremia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare dose-limiting side effects in kidney transplant recipients receiving valA vs. valG.</measure>
    <time_frame>First year post-kidney transplant</time_frame>
    <description>ValG is associated with adverse events including diarrhea, fever, nausea, vomiting, tremor, leucopenia, neutropenia, anemia and thrombocytopenia in ≥20% of patients. ValG induced leucopenia often necessitates a reduction in immunosuppressive therapy, increasing the risk of allograft rejection. Fewer severe adverse events are related to valA, including rash (8%), abdominal pain (1% to 11%), nausea (5% to 15%), vomiting (less than 1% to 6%), headache (13% to 38%) and fatigue (8%). Very high doses of valA (8g/day) for post-kidney transplant CMV prophylaxis was shown to have no severe or treatment-limiting side effects compared to placebo. Therefore we anticipate that the proportion of patients requiring dose reduction or cessation of valA vs. valG due to adverse drug side effects will be less.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To identify the presence and quantity of EBV and CMV in renal tissue biopsies from kidney transplant recipients.</measure>
    <time_frame>For first year post-kidney transplant</time_frame>
    <description>It is postulated that latent virus in renal tissue is a major source of post-kidney transplant recipient infection, but this remains unproven. The ability in this research study to test renal tissue obtained from adult protocol biopsies at the time of kidney transplant and 3 and 12 months post-kidney transplant (corresponding with the timing of routine surveillance post-kidney transplant biopsies) by both polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and fluorescence in situ hybridization provides a unique opportunity to test this.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Transplantation Infection</condition>
  <condition>Epstein-Barr Virus Infections</condition>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ValAcyclovir</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Kidney recipients who give informed consent will be randomly assigned to receive ValA or ValG in a 1:1 ratio. Duration of therapy is 3-12 months depending on risk and age of recipient. Dosing is based on glomerular filtration rate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ValGanciclovir</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Kidney recipients who give informed consent will be randomly assigned to receive ValG or ValA in a 1:1 ratio. Duration of therapy is 3-12 months depending on risk and age of recipient. Dosing is based on glomerular filtration rate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Valacyclovir</intervention_name>
    <description>Experimental Arm</description>
    <arm_group_label>ValAcyclovir</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Valtrex</other_name>
    <other_name>Valacyclovir Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Valacyclovir HCL</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Valganciclovir</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care</description>
    <arm_group_label>ValGanciclovir</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Valcyte</other_name>
    <other_name>Valganciclovir hydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All consenting kidney transplant recipients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-consent.

          -  Recipients with allergies to valacyclovir or valganciclovir

          -  Recipients that are unable to independently understand the consent form and do not
             have a legally authorized representative.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Priya Verghese, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amy Hanson</last_name>
    <phone>612-626-4424</phone>
    <email>amhanson@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amanda Galster</last_name>
    <phone>612-625-4443</phone>
    <email>gals0004@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of MN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Hanson</last_name>
      <phone>612-626-4424</phone>
      <email>amhanson@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Priya Verghese, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kacer M, Kielberger L, Bouda M, Reischig T. Valganciclovir versus valacyclovir prophylaxis for prevention of cytomegalovirus: an economic perspective. Transpl Infect Dis. 2015 Jun;17(3):334-41. doi: 10.1111/tid.12383. Epub 2015 May 26.</citation>
    <PMID>25824586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reischig T, Kacer M, Jindra P, Hes O, Lysak D, Bouda M. Randomized trial of valganciclovir versus valacyclovir prophylaxis for prevention of cytomegalovirus in renal transplantation. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2015 Feb 6;10(2):294-304. doi: 10.2215/CJN.07020714. Epub 2014 Nov 25.</citation>
    <PMID>25424991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>EBV</keyword>
  <keyword>CMV</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>valganciclovir</keyword>
  <keyword>valacyclovir</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epstein-Barr Virus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Valacyclovir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acyclovir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Valganciclovir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ganciclovir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

