<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01975753</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013/004/HP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01975753</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>First Evaluation of Morphine Hydrochloride by Nebulisation in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <acronym>AEROMORPH1</acronym>
  <official_title>First Evaluation of Morphine Hydrochloride by Nebulisation Compared to Intravenous Route in Healthy Volunteers: Preliminary Study Dose</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Rouen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Rouen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute pain relief in emergency setting is still a public health priority. Pain is the primary
      reason for emergency room use, but the situation of &quot;oligo-analgesia&quot; persists in all
      countries. Intravenous morphine titration has become the standard method for severe acute
      pain management in the emergency department, but it is still insufficiently implemented.
      Deviations from the recommended protocol are common: initial additional loading doses,
      unusually extended intervals between bolus, premature discontinuation. Several factors
      contribute to these difficulties: heaviness of its setting up, especially in overcrowding
      case, procedure rigidity, high consumption of nursing time. This method requires a systematic
      intravenously route, which has several inconvenients: algogenic procedures, coupled initial
      diagnostic venous sampling (delay for analgesia), excessive &quot;medicalization&quot; of ambulatory
      patients (risk of infection and less mobility in the emergency department). An alternative to
      reduce the analgesic latency in emergency department, without losing the benefits of
      tolerance and safety should be welcome. The inhaled route looks promising, but has yet not
      been enough evaluated in adults, and even less in the emergency room. Aerosol techniques
      change from one study to another (molecules, materials, doses, painful intensities included,
      judgment criteria and assessment times). A morphine titration by aerosol therapy could be an
      interesting alternative to the standard method disadvantages, using faster, painless and
      easier procedures, leading to &quot;demedicalization&quot;.

      To the need for stronger fundamentals, an additional study was designed in healthy
      volunteers. The objective is to compare the titration of intravenous morphine titration
      aerosol in moderate acute pain caused by electrostimulation.

      To purchase this aim, we first need to determine accurately the smallest dose of effective
      and well tolerated inhaled morphine, to provide the &quot;bolus&quot; dose we have to repeat by
      titration, which is still currently unknown. This dose is called ED50, it's the effective
      dose for at least 50% of healthy volunteers relieved. ED50 for intravenous morphine is also
      needed to be established, unknown in this indication. The determination of these two parallel
      ED50 would allow a reliable conversion factor between the two routes of administration for
      morphine &quot;bolus&quot;, which can then be tested in comparative titrations. To validate our induced
      pain model in healthy volunteers, we also have chosen to fix in these conditions the ED50 of
      fentanyl that the effective dose by nebulization is better known. This study would also
      describe the pharmacokinetics of inhaled morphine and its derivatives after a single spray.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effective doses of intravenous morphine hydrochloride &quot;bolus&quot; and nebulized &quot;bolus&quot; in 50% of healthy painful volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>7 min</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is efficacy: relief from healthy volunteers thanks to VAS decreasing, defined as ≤ 20 (100mm). At the end of the study the dose chosen is the effective dose for 50% of the volunteers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety</measure>
    <time_frame>7 min</time_frame>
    <description>Check tolerance of aerosols on respiratory and systemically 2. Describe the pharmacokinetics of a &quot;bolus&quot; and a titration of morphine hydrochloride aerosol standardized, and of all its metabolites 3. Establish the concentration-effect relationship of a spray &quot;bolus&quot; and of a titration of morphine hydrochloride standardized (for the analgesic effect) using a pharmacokinetic / pharmacodynamic model (PK / PD) and mathematical modeling 4. Methodological validation by determining the ED50 of a inhaled fentanyl &quot;bolus&quot; 5. Establish pharmacokinetic bases that can provide a secure further study in the emergency room, targeting patients with severe spontaneous acute pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intravenous morphine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>one bolus of intravenous morphine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>nebulized morphine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>one &quot;nebulized&quot; bolus of morphine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>fentanyl</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>one &quot;nebulized&quot; bolus of fentanyl</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morphine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intravenous morphine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>nebulized morphine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fentanyl</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>fentanyl</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Sex: We choose to include 50% of men and 50% women (this covariate will be included in
             the parameters to balance the randomization list).

          -  Age: Healthy volunteers will be between 18 to 60 years

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 19 and 29 kg / m²

          -  effective contraception methods in women of childbearing age

          -  Signature of informed consent

          -  Affiliation to a social security scheme

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Taking painkillers long-term

          -  Taking psychotropic drugs long-term

          -  Healthy volunteers with chronic pain

          -  Drug addiction

          -  Chronic neuropsychiatric pathology which may alter the pain threshold

          -  Active Smoking

          -  Chronic obstructive or restrictive respiratory pathology

          -  Progressive known pathology (hypertension, kidney failure, heart, liver ...)

          -  Chronic treatments are prohibited except oral contraception

          -  Delirium or dementia, people who did not understand the pain scales

          -  Lack of understanding of the French language

          -  pregnancy and lactation

          -  Poor venous capital

          -  History of abnormal reaction at a local / regional anesthesia

          -  Heart rate : HR &lt;50 bpm

          -  Hypotension TAsyst with systolic blood pressure &lt;100 mm Hg

          -  Atrioventricular block (PR interval&gt; 200 ms)

          -  Period exclusion of another biomedical research

          -  Nobody placed under judicial protection, guardianship
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>VIRGINIE LVOVSCHI, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0232888990</phone>
    <phone_ext>8050533</phone_ext>
    <email>virginie.lvovschi@chu-rouen.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <state>Haute Normandie</state>
        <zip>76000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>LVOVSCHI Virginie, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lvovschi V, Aubrun F, Bonnet P, Bouchara A, Bendahou M, Humbert B, Hausfater P, Riou B. Intravenous morphine titration to treat severe pain in the ED. Am J Emerg Med. 2008 Jul;26(6):676-82. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2007.10.025.</citation>
    <PMID>18606320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 5, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

