<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01971489</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 240413</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01941</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>I 240413</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016056</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01971489</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Buparlisib, Gemcitabine Hydrochloride, and Cisplatin in Treating Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of the PI3-Kinase Inhibitor BKM120 in Combination With Gemcitabine and Cisplatin in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and the best doses of buparlisib, gemcitabine
      hydrochloride, and cisplatin in treating patients with solid tumors that have spread to other
      places in the body. Buparlisib may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the
      enzymes needed for cell growth. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as gemcitabine hydrochloride
      and cisplatin, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing
      the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Giving buparlisib, gemcitabine hydrochloride,
      and cisplatin may be a better treatment for solid tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe the dose-limiting toxicities, maximally tolerated dose, and identify the
      recommended Phase II dose (RP2D) of the combination of BKM120 (buparlisib), gemcitabine
      (gemcitabine hydrochloride), and cisplatin in patients with advanced solid tumors.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe safety and tolerability of the combination of BKM120, gemcitabine, and
      cisplatin in patients with advanced solid tumors.

      II. To describe preliminary evidence of efficacy with this combination. III. To describe any
      pharmacokinetic (PK) effect of gemcitabine and cisplatin on the plasma concentrations of
      BKM120.

      IV. To evaluate phosphatidylinositol-4, 5-bisphosphate 3-kinase, catalytic subunit alpha
      (PIK3CA) mutations as predictive biomarkers of efficacy for the combination.

      V. To evaluate PIK3CA polymorphisms and polymorphisms in BKM120 transport and metabolism as
      predictors of toxicity and/or efficacy.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study.

      Patients receive buparlisib orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-21, gemcitabine
      hydrochloride intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on days 1 and 8, and cisplatin IV over 2
      hours on day 1. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 30 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be coded and evaluated for severity using NCI-CTCAE, version 4.0 and will be summarized by system organ class and preferred term.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum-tolerated dose (MTD) defined as the maximum dose level at which less than or equal to 1 out of 6 patients have DLTs using NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 21 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate using RECIST (CR, PR, and SD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR) calculated as the number of patients with a confirmed complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) divided by the total number of patients using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor response will be summarized for the evaluable patient population, and the 95% confidence interval for ORR (CR+PR) will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PIK3CA mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed as potential predictive biomarkers of efficacy for the combination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PIK3CA polymorphisms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK effect of gemcitabine hydrochloride and cisplatin on buparlisib</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and at 0.5, 1, 2, and 4 hours post-dose on day 21 of course 1, and pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 2, and 4 hours post-dose on day 1 of course 2 (or day 3 of course 2 for the 2 days off, 5 days on dosing schedule)</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters include time to reach maximum concentration (Tmax), maximum concentration (Cmax), clearance (CL), half-life (T1/2), area under the curve (AUC)0-infinity, and AUC0-t for the dosing interval following multiple dose administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Polymorphisms in buparlisib transport and metabolism</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed as potential predictors of toxicity and/or efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RECIST response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The number and percent of patients qualifying for each RECIST response category (CR, PR, stable disease [SD], and progressive disease [PD]).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Solid Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Non-Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (buparlisib, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive buparlisib PO QD on days 1-21, gemcitabine hydrochloride IV over 30 minutes on days 1 and 8, and cisplatin IV over 2 hours on day 1. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Buparlisib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (buparlisib, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BKM120</other_name>
    <other_name>PI3K Inhibitor BKM120</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (buparlisib, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abiplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Blastolem</other_name>
    <other_name>Briplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diammine-dichloroplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloridoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloro Platinum (II)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloroplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-dichloroammine Platinum (II)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinous Diamine Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum II</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum II Diamine Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cismaplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatina</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Citoplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Citosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cysplatyna</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Lederplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Metaplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Neoplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Peyrone's Chloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Peyrone's Salt</other_name>
    <other_name>Placis</other_name>
    <other_name>Plastistil</other_name>
    <other_name>Platamine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiblastin-S</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinex</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol- AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ VHA Plus</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum Diamminodichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiran</other_name>
    <other_name>Platistin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platosin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (buparlisib, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>dFdCyd</other_name>
    <other_name>Difluorodeoxycytidine Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
    <other_name>LY-188011</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (buparlisib, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (buparlisib, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (buparlisib, gemcitabine hydrochloride, cisplatin)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of solid malignancy

          -  Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 1

          -  Life expectancy of &gt;= 12 weeks

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 150 x 10^9/L

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.5 x 10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 1.5 upper limit
             normal (ULN), or &lt; 3 x ULN if liver metastases are present

          -  Serum total bilirubin =&lt; ULN or 1.5 x ULN if liver metastases are present or total 3 x
             ULN with direct bilirubin =&lt; ULN in patients with well documented Gilbert syndrome

          -  Calculated or measured creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min

          -  Fasting plasma glucose &lt; 120 mg/dL

          -  Magnesium &gt;= the lower limit of normal

          -  Lipase =&lt; 1.5 ULN

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test performed within 7
             days prior to the start of study drug

          -  Male and female subjects of child-bearing potential must agree to use double-barrier
             contraceptive measures, oral contraception, or avoidance of intercourse during the
             study and for 90 days after last investigational drug dose received

          -  Subject or legal representative must understand the investigational nature of this
             study and sign an Independent Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board approved
             written informed consent form prior to receiving any study related procedure

          -  For dose expansion cohort, patients must have histologic or cytologic confirmed
             non-small cell lung cancer that are not curable

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous anti-cancer chemotherapy, immunotherapy or investigational agents &lt; 4 weeks,
             or palliative radiation &lt; 2 weeks prior to the first day of study treatment, or who
             have not recovered to grade 1 or better from related side effects of such therapy
             (except alopecia); patients who receive gamma knife radiosurgery for brain metastases
             are eligible if procedure was performed &gt; 2 weeks before treatment is started, is
             clinically stable and has been on stable low dose corticosteroid treatment (e.g.,
             dexamethasone 2 mg/day, prednisolone 12 mg/day for at least 14 days before start of
             study treatment are eligible); ongoing hormonal therapies (luteinizing
             hormone-releasing hormone [LHRH] antagonists, megestrol) are allowed

          -  Previous treatment with a phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (P1-3K) inhibitor

          -  Patients who have taken herbal medications and certain fruits within 7 days prior to
             starting study drug; herbal medications include, but are not limited to St. John's
             wort, Kava, ephedra (ma huang), gingko biloba, dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA), yohimbe,
             saw palmetto, and ginseng; fruits include the cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A
             (CYP3A) inhibitors Seville oranges, grapefruit, pummelos, or exotic citrus fruits

          -  Patient has a known hypersensitivity to any of the excipients of BKM120

          -  Patient has had major surgery within 14 days prior to starting study drug or has not
             recovered from major side effects

          -  Patient is currently receiving increasing or chronic treatment (&gt; 5 days) with
             corticosteroids or another immunosuppressive agent, as chronic administration of
             corticosteroids (&gt; 5 days) can induce cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A,
             polypeptide 4 (CYP3A4)

               -  The following uses of corticosteroids are permitted: single doses; e.g. with
                  standard premedication for taxanes; topical applications (e.g., rash), inhaled
                  sprays (e.g., obstructive airways diseases), eye drops or local injections (e.g.,
                  intra-articular)

          -  Patient is being treated at start of study treatment with any of the following drugs:

               -  Drugs known to be moderate and strong inhibitors or inducers of isoenzyme CYP3A4
                  including herbal medications

               -  Drugs with a known risk to induce Torsades de Pointes

               -  Note: The patient must have discontinued strong inducers for at least one week
                  and must have discontinued strong inhibitors before the treatment is initiated;
                  switching to a different medication prior to starting study treatment is allowed

          -  Patient is currently receiving warfarin or other Coumarin derived anti-coagulant, for
             treatment, prophylaxis or otherwise; therapy with heparin, low molecular weight
             heparin (LMWH), or fondaparinux is allowed

          -  Patients who have other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions that
             would, in the investigator's judgment, contraindicate patient participation in the
             clinical study (eg. active or uncontrolled severe infection, chronic active hepatitis,
             immunocompromised, acute or chronic pancreatitis, uncontrolled high blood pressure,
             interstitial lung disease, etc.)

          -  Patient has a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection (testing
             not mandatory) infection

          -  Patient has any of the following cardiac abnormalities:

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure

                    -  History of documented congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association
                       functional classification III-IV), documented cardiomyopathy

                    -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 50% as determined by multiple
                       gated acquisition (MUGA) scan or echocardiogram (ECHO)

               -  Myocardial infarction =&lt; 6 months prior to enrollment

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

               -  Serious uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia

               -  Symptomatic pericarditis

               -  Corrected QT interval using Fridericia's formula (QTcF) &gt; 480 msec on the
                  screening electrocardiogram (ECG) (using the QTcF formula)

               -  Currently receiving treatment with medication that has a known risk to prolong
                  the QT interval or inducing Torsades de Pointes, and the treatment cannot be
                  discontinued or switched to a different medication prior to starting study drug

          -  Patient has impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of study drug (e.g., ulcerative diseases,
             uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, or small bowel
             resection)

          -  Patient has a score &gt;= 12 on the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ)-9 questionnaire

          -  Patient selects a response of &quot;1, 2 or 3&quot; to question number 9 on the PHQ-9
             questionnaire regarding potential for suicidal thoughts or ideation (independent of
             the total score of the PHQ-9)

          -  Patient has a General Anxiety Disorder (GAD)-7 mood scale score &gt;= 15

          -  Patient has a medically documented history of or active major depressive episode,
             bipolar disorder (I or II), obsessive-compulsive disorder, schizophrenia, a history of
             suicidal attempt or ideation, or homicidal ideation (e.g. risk of doing harm to self
             or others), or patients with active severe personality disorders (defined according to
             Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition [DSM-IV]) are
             not eligible; Note: for patients with psychotropic treatments ongoing at baseline, the
             dose and the schedule should not be modified within the previous 6 weeks prior to
             start of study drug

          -  Patient has &gt;= Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) grade 3 anxiety

          -  Patient has other prior or concurrent malignancy (except for the following: adequately
             treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, or other adequately treated in situ
             cancer, early gastric or GI cancer resected completely by endoscopy procedures or any
             other cancer from which the patient has been disease free for &gt;= 3 years)

          -  Patient has a history of non-compliance to medical regimen or inability to grant
             consent

          -  Patient is concurrently using other approved or investigational antineoplastic agent

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) laboratory test (&gt; 5 mIU/mL); patients
             with elevated hCG at baseline that is judged to be related to the tumor are eligible
             if hCG levels do not show the expected doubling when repeated 5-7 days later, or
             pregnancy has been ruled out by vaginal ultrasound

          -  Patient who does not apply highly effective contraception during the study and through
             the duration as defined below after the final dose of study treatment:

               -  Sexually active males should use a condom during intercourse while taking drug
                  and for 8 weeks after the final dose of study treatment and should not father a
                  child in this period, but may be recommended to seek advice on conservation of
                  sperm; a condom is required to be used also by vasectomized men in order to
                  prevent delivery of the drug via seminal fluid

               -  Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
                  becoming pregnant, must use highly effective contraception during the study and
                  through at least 4 weeks after the final dose of study treatment

               -  Highly effective contraception is defined as either:

                    -  Total abstinence: when this is in line with the preferred and usual
                       lifestyle of the subject; (periodic abstinence [e.g., calendar, ovulation,
                       symptothermal, post-ovulation methods] and withdrawal are not acceptable
                       methods of contraception)

                    -  Female sterilization: have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or
                       without hysterectomy) or tubal ligation at least six weeks before taking
                       study treatment; in case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive
                       status of the woman has been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment

                    -  Male partner sterilization (with the appropriate post-vasectomy
                       documentation of the absence of sperm in the ejaculate); (for female study
                       subjects, the vasectomized male partner should be the sole partner for that
                       patient)

                    -  Use a combination of the following:

                         -  Placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS)

                         -  Barrier methods of contraception: condom or occlusive cap (diaphragm or
                            cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/vaginal
                            suppository

                         -  Note: hormonal contraception methods (e.g. oral, injected, and
                            implanted) are not allowed

          -  Women are considered post-menopausal and not of child-bearing potential if they have
             had 12 months of natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea with an appropriate clinical profile
             (e.g. age appropriate, history of vasomotor symptoms) or have had surgical bilateral
             oophorectomy (with or without hysterectomy) at least six weeks ago; for women with
             therapy-induced amenorrhea, oophorectomy or serial measurements of
             follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and/or estradiol are needed to ensure
             postmenopausal status; NOTE: ovarian radiation or treatment with a luteinizing
             hormone-releasing hormone (LH-RH) agonist (goserelin acetate or leuprolide acetate) is
             not permitted for induction of ovarian suppression
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alex Adjei</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 23, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 29, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 11, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 11, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 13, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

