<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02231814</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0105-14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02231814</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of Partial Enteral Nutrition With a Unique Diet for the Treatment of Adult Patients With Crohn's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>CDED-ADULTS</acronym>
  <official_title>Dietary Therapy Using Partial Enteral Nutrition and the Crohn's Disease Exclusion Diet (CDED) for Induction and Maintenance of Remission in Mild to Moderate Crohn's Disease in Adults- A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Prof. Arie Levine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wolfson Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate a novel diet for adult crohn's disease patients (The Crohn's Disease
      Exclusion Diet - CDED). Half of the patients in this study will receive the CDED alone while
      the other half will receive the CDED and a liquid diet formula, for 24 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Environmental factors, the microbiome (bacteria in our gut) and innate immunity all play a
      role in the pathogenesis of Crohn's disease .Exclusive enteral nutrition (EEN) was found to
      be effective for inducing remission in active pediatric Crohn's disease, while Partial
      Enteral Nutrition (PEN) with free diet was not; suggesting that the mechanism of EEN depends
      on exclusion of dietary components. Dietary factors may play a role in the pathogenesis of
      the disease, and maybe an important under-investigated therapeutic target.

      &quot;The Crohn's Disease Exclusion Diet&quot; (CDED) is a palatable diet excluding components
      suspected to interfere with the bacteria in our gut or impair immune mechanisms. Our group
      previously evaluated 47 patients using the Crohn's disease Exclusion Diet + 50% Polymeric
      formula for 6 weeks, and demonstrated a 78% response rate and 70% disease remission rate
      using stringent criteria. This was accompanied by a highly significant reduction in markers
      for inflammation (C-reactive protein (CRP) and Erythrocyte Sedimentation Rate (ESR)), and
      normalization of CRP in 70% of those entering remission. Among these patients were 13 adults
      aged 19-32, the remission rate in these 13 patients was 69%, similar to the pediatric data.
      Importantly, 6/7 patients in this study who refused to drink formula and just used the diet
      achieved remission, suggesting that the exclusion and not partial enteral nutrition are
      responsible for the high remission rate. Our former study did not evaluate mucosal healing as
      an end point, since performing colonoscopies after 6- 12 weeks of therapy is neither ethical
      nor feasible in children.

      At present, data about nutritional therapy and this new dietary approach have been generated
      primarily in children, and this new diet has not been evaluated for early mucosal healing.
      The objectives of this pilot study are to generate data in adults, evaluate the diet over a
      longer period of time (24 weeks) and evaluate mucosal healing. The study is a prospective
      open label randomized controlled pilot trial in adults, with mild to moderate Crohn's disease
      who will receive the Crohn's Disease Exclusion Diet (CDED) for 24 weeks.

      If effective, this could enable use of a feasible, safe intervention for induction and
      maintenance of remission as a new therapy or as an adjunctive therapy with medical therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical remission defined as Harvey Bradshaw Index (HBI)&lt;5</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Steroid free remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6, 12 and 24.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mucosal healing- Normal colonoscopy or normal MRE with normal calprotectin</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24-26</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in mean C-Reactive Protein (CRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 6, 12 and 24.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mean fecal calprotectin</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6, 12 and 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Crohn's Disease Exclusion Diet+Partial Enteral Nutrition (PEN): Crohns Disease Exclusion Diet + PEN</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Crohn's Disease Exclusion Diet alone with a calcium supplement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Crohns Disease Exclusion Diet + PEN</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will use the CDED for a 24 week period, coupled with 1000 m&quot;l of polymeric formula (1 Kcal/m&quot;L) for the first 6 weeks. For weeks 7 to 24 patients will use the CDED coupled with 600 ml formula and a calcium supplement. The CDED is divided into 3 stages: 0-6 weeks induction phase, weeks 7-12 step down phase, weeks 13-24 maintenance phase.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CDED + Liquid dietary formula</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Crohns Disease Exclusion Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Crohn's Disease Exclusion Diet alone with a calcium supplement during the study (0-24). The CDED is divided into 3 stages: 0-6 weeks induction phase, weeks 7-12 step down phase, weeks 13-24 maintenance phase.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CDED</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Informed consent

          2. Established Crohn's disease

          3. Aged 18-55

          4. Duration of disease up to 5 years

          5. Harvey Bradshaw Index 5 ≤( HBI) ≤15

          6. Patients with uncomplicated disease involving the terminal ileum and or cecum

          7. Patients who performed colonoscopy (or MR/CTEnterography with elevated
             calprotectin&gt;200) demonstrating active disease in the previous 8 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Patients with severe Disease (HBI &gt; 15) or HBI&lt;5

          2. Pregnancy,

          3. Patients with active extraintestinal disease, current B2 (Fixed non inflammatory
             stricture1 or small bowel obstruction) or B3 disease,

          4. Patients who used immunomodulator &lt;8 weeks, or had dose changed in past 8 weeks,

          5. Patients with current or past use of biologics, or use of systemic steroids2,

          6. Patients with deep ulcers involving the colon distal to the splenic flexure on most
             recent colonoscopy

          7. Any proven current infection such as positive stool cultures or positive tests for
             parasites or C. difficile. Stool tests are mandatory only if diarrhea is present.

          8. Active Perianal disease ( clarification-fistula with discharge or abscess)

          9. Patients who have undergone an intestinal resection

         10. Patients with systemic disease including: type 2 diabetes, kidney failure, liver
             failure, neurological disease, active heart disease and patients with active
             autoimmune condition requiring medication3

         11. Patients unwilling to consume any animal source protein (eggs, chicken or fish).

        Comments:

          1. Patients with ileo-cecal valve narrowing maybe included

          2. Patients active despite budesonide may enter the trial if they are on 3 mg, and stop
             budesonide within 14 days of commencement of the trial.

          3. Patients with Celiac disease or Hashimoto Thyroiditis can be enrolled
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arie Levine, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wolfson Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Iris Dotan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tel Aviv Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Irit Hermesh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rambam Medical Center,Haifa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wolfson Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Holon</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arie Levine, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+972-35028878</phone>
      <email>alevine@wolfson.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arie Levine, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sigall-Boneh R, Pfeffer-Gik T, Segal I, Zangen T, Boaz M, Levine A. Partial enteral nutrition with a Crohn's disease exclusion diet is effective for induction of remission in children and young adults with Crohn's disease. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2014 Aug;20(8):1353-60. doi: 10.1097/MIB.0000000000000110.</citation>
    <PMID>24983973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 27, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wolfson Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Arie Levine</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Pediatric Gastroenterology and Nutrition unit.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Crohn's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Mild to moderate Crohn's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Diet</keyword>
  <keyword>Enteral Nutrition</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

