<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02236663</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00054334</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HD076881-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02236663</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of a Safety App to Respond to Dating Violence for College Women and Their Friends</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of a Safety App to Respond to Dating Violence for College Women and Their Friends</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Arizona State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intimate partner violence (IPV), including violence in dating relationships (dating violence,
      DV) is a widespread and serious public health problem. Among U.S. female IPV survivors, 47.1%
      report their first abusive relationship occurred at college age (age 18-24). Similarly, in
      national surveys, adults respondents 18-24 years of age report the highest rate of stalking
      victimization, most commonly by a former intimate partner. Safety planning is the most widely
      used intervention to prevent and respond to IPV, yet the vast majority of abused women never
      access safety planning services. Our challenge is to increase college women's access to
      safety planning, with the opportunity to consider their unique safety priorities and level of
      danger during and when ending an abusive relationship. In addition, while &quot;bystander&quot;
      interventions that train peers to safely intervene have been shown to be effective in sexual
      assault prevention on campus, and college women in abusive relationships most frequently
      disclose IPV to a friend, no similar interventions have been tested with friends for IPV
      response on campuses. Therefore, the objective of the study is to evaluate the:

        1. effectiveness of an interactive, personalized smart phone and web based safety
           application (&quot;App&quot;) intervention in Maryland and Oregon with: 1) college women (age
           18-24) who experience IPV and 2) friends (age 18-24) of women experiencing IPV. The
           safety decision App allows the user to enter information on: a) relationship health; b)
           safety priorities; and c) severity of violence/danger in relationship. The App then uses
           the information to provide the user with a personalized safety planning information and
           resources; and

        2. dissemination of the App in an expanded four states (Arizona, Maryland, Missouri, and
           Oregon) to determine the reach, adoption, implementation and maintenance of App use
           among university/college students.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in survivors' use of safety strategies on Safety Behavior Checklist at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Adapted from Intimate Partner Violence Strategies Index to assess for survivors the range of strategies used to halt, escape, or resist violence, and the helpfulness of each strategy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in survivors' and friends' decisional conflict on Decisional Conflict Scale (DCS) immediately post intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The DCS consists of twelve items, with each question having three response options (yes, no, and unsure). The DCS provides a total score, which is a measure of the decision process, as well as scores for four subscales (feeling informed, certainty about decision, values clarity, and support), with higher scores on the DCS indicating a greater degree of decisional conflict (indicative of a poorer decision process). Will be used to assess decisional conflict with survivors and friends.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in friends' efficacy to intervene on adapted Self-efficacy to Deal with Violence Scale at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>19 times scale adapted to assess friends of survivors' confidence to intervene.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline in friends' supportive behaviors on Supportive Behaviors Checklist at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses supportive behaviors used to assist a friend experiencing intimate partner violence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in survivors' drug and alcohol use on adapted Monitoring the Future Drug and Alcohol Questionnaire at 12 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in survivors' abuse exposure on the Composite Abuse Scale (CAS) at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The CAS is a 30 item validated comprehensive intimate partner violence screening measure with</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in survivors' and friends' Decisional Conflict on Decisional Conflict Scale at 12 mo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in survivor' depression on Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale, Revised at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item self report measure, designed to screen for depressive symptoms in community samples and assess the probability that an individual meets the criteria for major depressive disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline in friends' attitudes on the Intimate Partner Violence on the Acceptance of Dating Violence Scale at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>5 item scale used to measures norms that support violence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">649</enrollment>
  <condition>Intimate Partner Violence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>App Based Safety Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Personalized App-Based Safety Decision Aid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual Care Safety Plan</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care Safety Planing App</intervention_name>
    <description>The control group App will provide women and friends with basic safety planning information and a brief resource list of IPV resources. The resources will be targeted to college students age 18-24 years. The control group App safety plan is not personalized to woman/friend's safety priorities and danger in the relationship.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control App</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Personalized App-Based Safety Decision Aid</intervention_name>
    <description>Setting of priorities for safety: participants will establish priorities by making pairwise comparisons of importance between 5 factors.
Danger Assessment: asks participants to report on well-established risk factors for repeat violence and lethal IPV. A weighted scoring algorithm provides participants with their validated level of danger and safety planning information and resources based on their level of danger.
Personalized action plan: Based on a participant's answers to the previous sections, a list of safety strategies with links to resources will be presented tailored to their level of danger and priority settings. The participant is given the option to print results and the personalized plan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>App Based Safety Decision Aid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Females who report current physical violence, sexual violence, psychological abuse or
             stalking by a dating/intimate/ex-intimate partner, or who have a female friend
             currently experiencing abuse from dating/intimate/ex-intimate partner.

          -  Males who have a female friend currently experiencing physical violence, sexual
             violence, psychological abuse or stalking by a dating/intimate/ex-intimate partner

          -  English speaking

          -  Between the ages of 18-24 years old

          -  Attend a college in Maryland or Oregon

          -  Enrolled in college or university (at least part time)

          -  Have access to a safe smart-phone or computer with internet and are comfortable
             downloading an app or using the internet

          -  Have a safe email address

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Younger than 18 years of age

          -  Older than 24 years of age

          -  Cannot read/speak English

          -  Live outside targeted states

          -  No access to safe smart phone or computer with internet

          -  Uncomfortable with downloading an app

          -  No access to a safe email address

          -  Does not report current violence from an intimate partner or having a female friend
             that has experienced intimate partner violence
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nancy Glass, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University School of Nursing</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arizona State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85004</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University School of Nursing</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Foundation Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 8, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 10, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intimate Partner Violence</keyword>
  <keyword>Dating Violence</keyword>
  <keyword>Relationships</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety Planning</keyword>
  <keyword>College</keyword>
  <keyword>Student</keyword>
  <keyword>App</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

