<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02231242</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HE13-004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02231242</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intrathecal Stem Cells for Cerebral Palsy Phase II</brief_title>
  <acronym>ISCII</acronym>
  <official_title>Intrathecal Autologous Stem Cells for Children With Cerebral Palsy Phase II</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the infusion of intrathecal autologous bone
      marrow total nucleated cells would improve the neurologic evolution of pediatric patients
      with quadriparetic cerebral palsy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is accumulated evidence that shows that the administration of bone marrow total
      nucleated cells (TNC) into the brain may produce some benefits by different mechanisms like
      cytokine production, in several neurological areas such as motor, social, adaptative and
      cognitive.

      It has been found that after introducing TNC in the subarachnoid space of the spinal cord,
      these cells may be transported through the cerebrospinal fluid and can be delivered more
      efficiently to the injured area, compared with intravenous route in patients with neurologic
      injury.

      Patients will be stimulated for 3 consecutive days with subcutaneous granulocyte colony
      stimulating factor (G-CSF) and then their bone marrow will be harvested according to their
      weight. Bone marrow will be processed in order to obtain the buffy coat and minimize the
      amount of red blood cells. An inoculum of 10mL of this TNC will be infused intrathecally.
      Patients will be evaluated with the &quot;Gross Motor Functional Classification System&quot; before the
      procedure and one, three and six months after that.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who show progress in GMFCS scale after autologous bonemarrow TNC intrathecal infusion.</measure>
    <time_frame>six months</time_frame>
    <description>Patients, in an outpatient basis, will be stimulated with Granulocyte Colony Stimulating Factor (G-CSF) for 3 consecutive days. Their bone marrow will be harvested under sedation and, after being processed in the laboratory, the buffy coat of 10 mL will be infused intrathecally.
Patient will be monitored during acute phase to register any adverse effect (malaise, headache, fever, and nausea or vomit, etc).Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) scale is going to be monitored at baseline, one, three and six months to measured differences between the scales.
GMFCS is based on patient's self-initiated movement with particular emphasis on sitting, walking, and wheeled mobility. Distinctions between levels are based on functional abilities, the need for assistive technology, including hand-held mobility devices (walkers, crutches, or canes) or wheeled mobility, and to a much lesser extent, quality of movement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal Autologous Bone Marrow TNC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Procedure/Surgery: Intrathecal Autologous Bone Marrow TNC. Other Names: Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation Patients will be stimulated with Granulocyte Colony Stimulating Factor (G-CSF) (10mcgr/kg of body weight) for 3 consecutive days. Bone marrow will be harvested under sedation and, after being processed in the laboratory, the autologous TNC concentrate of 10 mL will be infused intrathecally.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be evaluated with the &quot;Gross Motor Functional Classification System&quot; initially, at one, three and six months, and then cross to the intervention arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be stimulated with Granulocyte Colony Stimulating Factor (G-CSF) 3 consecutive days. Bone marrow will be harvested under sedation and, after being processed in the laboratory, the buffy coat (TNC) of 10 mL will be infused intrathecally.
Intrathecal Autologous Bone Marrow TNC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal Autologous Bone Marrow TNC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with quadriplegic cerebral palsy, with an age from 7 to 9 years of age,
             regardless the age at the time of injury, time post-injury, or previously received
             therapies, different from ours

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with neurodegenerative or autoimmune diseases

          -  Patients with active infection in any organ or tissue at the time of entering the
             study, the onset of stimulation with G-CSF or at the procedure

          -  Patients who do not sign the informed consent form
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>9 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Consuelo Mancias-Guerra, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Consuelo Mancias-Guerra, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+52 81 83 48 61 36</phone>
    <phone_ext>413</phone_ext>
    <email>consuelomanciasg@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Oscar Gonzalez-Llano, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+52 86 75 67 18</phone>
    <email>ogzzll25@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hematology Service, Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monterrey</city>
        <state>Nuevo Leon</state>
        <zip>64460</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Consuelo Mancias-Guerra, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+52 81 83 48 61 36</phone>
      <phone_ext>413</phone_ext>
      <email>consuelomanciasg@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>David Gomez-Almaguer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+52 81 83 48 61 36</phone>
      <email>dgomezalmaguer@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Consuelo Mancias-Guerra, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hematologia-uanl.com/</url>
    <description>web page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mancías-Guerra C, Marroquín-Escamilla AR, González-Llano O, Villarreal-Martínez L, Jaime-Pérez JC, García-Rodríguez F, Valdés-Burnes SL, Rodríguez-Romo LN, Barrera-Morales DC, Sánchez-Hernández JJ, Cantú-Rodríguez OG, Gutiérrez-Aguirre CH, Gómez-De León A, Elizondo-Riojas G, Salazar-Riojas R, Gómez-Almaguer D. Safety and tolerability of intrathecal delivery of autologous bone marrow nucleated cells in children with cerebral palsy: an open-label phase I trial. Cytotherapy. 2014 Jun;16(6):810-20. doi: 10.1016/j.jcyt.2014.01.008. Epub 2014 Mar 15.</citation>
    <PMID>24642016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehta T, Feroz A, Thakkar U, Vanikar A, Shah V, Trivedi H. Subarachnoid placement of stem cells in neurological disorders. Transplant Proc. 2008 May;40(4):1145-7. doi: 10.1016/j.transproceed.2008.03.026.</citation>
    <PMID>18555135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pakula AT, Van Naarden Braun K, Yeargin-Allsopp M. Cerebral palsy: classification and epidemiology. Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am. 2009 Aug;20(3):425-52. doi: 10.1016/j.pmr.2009.06.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19643346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Felling RJ, Snyder MJ, Romanko MJ, Rothstein RP, Ziegler AN, Yang Z, Givogri MI, Bongarzone ER, Levison SW. Neural stem/progenitor cells participate in the regenerative response to perinatal hypoxia/ischemia. J Neurosci. 2006 Apr 19;26(16):4359-69.</citation>
    <PMID>16624956</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eglitis MA, Mezey E. Hematopoietic cells differentiate into both microglia and macroglia in the brains of adult mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1997 Apr 15;94(8):4080-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9108108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woodbury D, Schwarz EJ, Prockop DJ, Black IB. Adult rat and human bone marrow stromal cells differentiate into neurons. J Neurosci Res. 2000 Aug 15;61(4):364-70.</citation>
    <PMID>10931522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mezey E, Key S, Vogelsang G, Szalayova I, Lange GD, Crain B. Transplanted bone marrow generates new neurons in human brains. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2003 Feb 4;100(3):1364-9. Epub 2003 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>12538864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hayashi T, Iwai M, Ikeda T, Jin G, Deguchi K, Nagotani S, Zhang H, Sehara Y, Nagano I, Shoji M, Ikenoue T, Abe K. Neural precursor cells division and migration in neonatal rat brain after ischemic/hypoxic injury. Brain Res. 2005 Mar 15;1038(1):41-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15748871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nakatomi H, Kuriu T, Okabe S, Yamamoto S, Hatano O, Kawahara N, Tamura A, Kirino T, Nakafuku M. Regeneration of hippocampal pyramidal neurons after ischemic brain injury by recruitment of endogenous neural progenitors. Cell. 2002 Aug 23;110(4):429-41.</citation>
    <PMID>12202033</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rempe DA, Kent TA. Using bone marrow stromal cells for treatment of stroke. Neurology. 2002 Aug 27;59(4):486-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12196638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li Y, Chen J, Chen XG, Wang L, Gautam SC, Xu YX, Katakowski M, Zhang LJ, Lu M, Janakiraman N, Chopp M. Human marrow stromal cell therapy for stroke in rat: neurotrophins and functional recovery. Neurology. 2002 Aug 27;59(4):514-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12196642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gordon PH, Yu Q, Qualls C, Winfield H, Dillon S, Greene PE, Fahn S, Breeze RE, Freed CR, Pullman SL. Reaction time and movement time after embryonic cell implantation in Parkinson disease. Arch Neurol. 2004 Jun;61(6):858-61.</citation>
    <PMID>15210522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kulbatski I, Mothe AJ, Nomura H, Tator CH. Endogenous and exogenous CNS derived stem/progenitor cell approaches for neurotrauma. Curr Drug Targets. 2005 Feb;6(1):111-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15720218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Back SA, Rivkees SA. Emerging concepts in periventricular white matter injury. Semin Perinatol. 2004 Dec;28(6):405-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15693397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Follett PL, Deng W, Dai W, Talos DM, Massillon LJ, Rosenberg PA, Volpe JJ, Jensen FE. Glutamate receptor-mediated oligodendrocyte toxicity in periventricular leukomalacia: a protective role for topiramate. J Neurosci. 2004 May 5;24(18):4412-20.</citation>
    <PMID>15128855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levison SW, Rothstein RP, Romanko MJ, Snyder MJ, Meyers RL, Vannucci SJ. Hypoxia/ischemia depletes the rat perinatal subventricular zone of oligodendrocyte progenitors and neural stem cells. Dev Neurosci. 2001;23(3):234-47.</citation>
    <PMID>11598326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robinson S, Petelenz K, Li Q, Cohen ML, Dechant A, Tabrizi N, Bucek M, Lust D, Miller RH. Developmental changes induced by graded prenatal systemic hypoxic-ischemic insults in rats. Neurobiol Dis. 2005 Apr;18(3):568-81.</citation>
    <PMID>15755683</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldman SA, Schanz S, Windrem MS. Stem cell-based strategies for treating pediatric disorders of myelin. Hum Mol Genet. 2008 Apr 15;17(R1):R76-83. doi: 10.1093/hmg/ddn052. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18632701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herzog EL, Chai L, Krause DS. Plasticity of marrow-derived stem cells. Blood. 2003 Nov 15;102(10):3483-93. Epub 2003 Jul 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12893756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goodell MA. Stem-cell &quot;plasticity&quot;: befuddled by the muddle. Curr Opin Hematol. 2003 May;10(3):208-13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12690288</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Appel SH, Engelhardt JI, Henkel JS, Siklos L, Beers DR, Yen AA, Simpson EP, Luo Y, Carrum G, Heslop HE, Brenner MK, Popat U. Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in patients with sporadic amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Neurology. 2008 Oct 21;71(17):1326-34. doi: 10.1212/01.wnl.0000327668.43541.22.</citation>
    <PMID>18936424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 14, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 3, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 3, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 4, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Consuelo Mancias Guerra</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dra. Consuelo Mancias Guerra</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>brain</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>cerebral palsy</keyword>
  <keyword>bone marrow stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>intrathecal autologous total nucleated cells</keyword>
  <keyword>quadriparesis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

