<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02233868</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140192</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-AA-0192</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02233868</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain Inflammation and Function in Alcoholism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brain Inflammation and Function in Alcoholism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Brain inflammation due to high alcohol intake may affect thinking, memory, and
      concentration. Researchers want to measure this using positron emission tomography (PET).

      Objective:

      - To study how excessive alcohol consumption affects brain function.

      Eligibility:

        -  Adults 30-75 years old who are moderate or severe alcohol drinkers.

        -  Healthy volunteers.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with medical history, physical exam, interview, and blood
           and urine tests. Their breath will be tested for alcohol and recent smoking.

        -  Phase 1:

        -  Participants will stay in the hospital 3 days. They will have blood and heart tests and
           daily urine tests.

        -  A small plastic tube will be inserted by needle in each arm. One will go in a vein, the
           other in an artery.

        -  Participants will have 2 PET scans with 2 different radioactive compounds. Participants
           will lie on a bed that slides in and out of the scanner with a cap on their head.

        -  Participants will have magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans. Participants will lie in
           the scanner either resting with their eyes open or while performing an attention task.

        -  Participants will have tests of memory, attention, concentration, and thinking. They may
           answer questions, take tests, and perform simple actions.

        -  Phase 2 of the study will only be done if Phase 1 results show brain inflammation.

        -  Phase 2 will repeat Phase 1.

        -  For healthy volunteers, Phase 2 will begin 3 weeks after Phase 1.

        -  Other volunteers must not have alcohol for at least 3 weeks and stay in a hospital up to
           4-6 weeks between Phase 1 and Phase 2. After Phase 2, they will have 5 follow-up calls
           over 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The abuse of high doses of alcohol is associated with cognitive impairment that in extreme
      cases can result in dementia. However, the mechanisms underlying the neurotoxic effects of
      alcohol to the human brain are poorly understood. Here we test the hypothesis that
      alcohol-induced neuroinflammation contributes to its neurotoxic effects in humans

      Objectives: The primary objectives are to assess if there is inflammation in the brain of
      alcoholics and if present to determine if it recovers after 3 weeks of abstinence as compared
      between groups (alcoholic vs. healthy volunteers) in Phase I. Secondary outcomes are to
      evaluate the functional consequences of inflammation as assessed by: regional brain glucose
      metabolism, functional brain activation to cognitive tasks, structural brain imaging, resting
      functional connectivity and neuropsychological tests.

      Study population: Participants diagnosed with alcohol use disorder (AD) as per DSM IV or DSM
      5 AD and healthy controls. Males and females ages 30-75 will be included

      Design: This study has two phases (phase I and II). The two phases can be done as inpatient
      (AD subjects) or as outpatient (AD and healthy controls) over a 2-3 day period. In phase I
      participants will undergo two positron emission tomography (PET) scans, one with [11C]PBR28
      (marker of neuroinflammation) and one with 18FDG (marker of brain glucose metabolism) and
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans to assess brain structure, functional reactivity and
      functional connectivity. In parallel we will perform neuropsychological tests (NP). Phase II
      will include the same procedures as Phase I but it will be done about 3 weeks later over a
      2-3 day period only in the participants (alcoholics or controls) who in Phase I show evidence
      of inflammatory changes. In AD participants Phase II will be done after alcohol abstinence
      and in healthy controls it will be repeated with no intervention. We will complete studies on
      at least ten alcoholic users (n=10) before we can feel confident that there is no
      neuroinflammation. In parallel we need to collect data on at least ten (n=10) controls so we
      have a comparison group scanned under the same characteristics as the alcoholics to do this
      preliminary investigation.

      Outcome parameters: Main outcome measure is to assess if there is neuroinflammation with
      alcoholism and if it recovers with detoxification. Secondary outcome measures are: to assess
      if neuroinflammation is associated with markers of brain function, which include (1) regional
      brain glucose metabolism; (2) MRI based voxel-based morphometry (VBM) to assess cortical
      atrophy; (3) blood-oxygenation level-dependent (BOLD) activation to a cognitive task, (4)
      brain functional connectivity, (5) myo-inositol (mI) concentration, and (6) NP testing to
      assess cognitive performance, and to evaluate if neuroinflammation predicts relapse in AD
      over a 3 month follow-up period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 6, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 29, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess if there is inflammation in the brain of alcoholics as measured with [11C]PBR28 and to determine if it recovers with 3 weeks of detoxification.</measure>
    <time_frame>2020</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the impact of neuroinflammation on brain function (assessed with PET and 18FDG and with MRI for fMRI with task activation and for functional connectivity).</measure>
    <time_frame>2020</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine if the NP variables correlate with neuroinflammation.</measure>
    <time_frame>2020</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine if the measure of neuroinflammation predicts relapse in AD participants in the 3 month follow-up period.</measure>
    <time_frame>2020</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">144</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Functional Connectivity Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fcMRI) of connectivity in brain</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>C-11PBR28</intervention_name>
    <description>PET brain imaging of neuroinflammation using the radiotracer [11C]PBR28</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>F-18FDG</intervention_name>
    <description>PET brain imaging of neurofunction using the radiotracer F-18FDG</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        -All Participants

          1. Between 30 and 75 years of age.

          2. Ability to provide written informed consent as determined by physical examination and
             verbal communication. Capacity to consent will be determined by those giving the
             informed consent.

          3. Females: Negative urine pregnancy test and not currently breastfeeding.
             Post-menopausal or surgically sterile (tubal ligation or hysterectomy); or not
             sexually active with a male partner and able to get pregnant; or documented agreement
             to use an effective form of birth control. Acceptable forms of contraception include:
             hormonal contraceptives (birth-control pills, injectable hormones, vaginal-ring
             hormones); IUD; diaphragm with spermicide; condom with spermicide.

             -Specific For AD Participants

          4. DSM-IV diagnosis of alcohol dependence or alcohol abuse or DSM-5 diagnosis of moderate
             or severe alcohol use disorder (established through history and clinical exam). We
             include subjects that drink high doses of alcohol since alcohol's detrimental effects
             are greater with larger doses and particularly with binge drinking.

          5. Participants seeking treatment for their AD as well as those not seeking treatment for
             their AD will be included.

          6. Minimum 5 year history of heavy drinking (self-report).

          7. Must consume at least 20 alcoholic drinks per week (male) or 15 per week (female)
             (self-report).

          8. Must have had the last drinking episode (females 3 or more drinks; and males 4 or more
             drinks) within 1 week of baseline PET scan (self-report).

          9. Alcohol specified as the preferred drug (self-report).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  All Participants

               1. Unwilling or unable to refrain from use within 24 hours of scheduled study
                  procedures: psychoactive medications or medication that may affect study results
                  (e.g., analgesics [non narcotic], antibiotics (must finish course at least 24
                  hours prior to a scheduled procedure), antidiarrheal preparations,
                  anti-inflammatory drugs (systemic corticosteroids are exclusionary),
                  antinauseants, cough/cold preparations) (self-report, medical history). The
                  following medications are allowable for entry on this study: analgesics
                  (non-narcotic); antacids; antiasthma agents that are not systemic
                  corticosteroids; antifungal agents for topical use; antihistamines
                  (non-sedating); H2-Blockers/PPI (proton pump inhibitors); laxatives. The use of
                  antihyperlipidemics and/or diuretics are permitted as long as they have been
                  taken for at least 1 month before procedure visits and dose has been stabilized.
                  The use of benzodiazepines such as alprazolam (( )Xanax), diazepam (( )Valium)
                  and lorazepam (( )Ativan), will not exclude participants from this study.

               2. Current or past DSM-IV or DSM-5 diagnosis of a psychiatric disorder (other than
                  alcohol in AD participants and nicotine/caffeine use disorders) that required
                  hospitalization (any length), or chronic medication management (more than 4
                  weeks) and that could impact brain function at the time of the study as
                  determined by history and clinical exam. The following chronically used
                  medications are exclusionary from the study: analgesics containing narcotics;
                  anorexics (sibuteramine); antianginal agents; antiarrhythmics; antiasthma agents
                  that are systemic corticosteroids; antibiotics; anticholinergics; anticoagulants;
                  anticonvulsants; antidepressants; antidiarrheal preparations; antifungal agents
                  (systemic); antihistamines (sedating); antihypertensives; anti-inflammatory drugs
                  (systemic); antineoplastics; antiobesity; antipsychotics; antivirals (except for
                  treatment of HSV with agents without CNS activity, e.g. acyclovir, ganciclovir,
                  famciclovir, valacyclovir); anxiolytics; cough/cold preparations
                  (dextromethorphan preparations, pseudoephedrine); hormones (exceptions: thyroid
                  hormone replacement, oral contraceptives, and estrogen replacement therapy);
                  insulin; lithium; muscle relaxants; psychotropic drugs not otherwise specified
                  (nos) including herbal products (no drugs with psychomotor effects or with
                  anxiolytics, stimulant, antipsychotic, or sedative properties);
                  sedatives/hypnotics. Note that nicotine and/or caffeine use will not exclude
                  participants.

               3. Major medical problems that can permanently impact brain function (e.g., CNS,
                  cardiovascular, metabolic, autoimmune, endocrine) as determined by history and
                  clinical exam.

               4. Any clinically significant laboratory finding as determined during the screening
                  procedures that could impact brain function or study procedures (evidenced from
                  clinical laboratory results).

               5. Have had previous radiation exposure (from X-rays, PET scans, or other exposure)
                  that with the exposure from this study, would exceed NIH annual research limits
                  (self-report, medical history)

               6. Head trauma with loss of consciousness for more than 30 minutes (self-report,
                  medical history);

               7. Positive test for alcohol on the day of the PET, the MRI or the NP tests
                  (clinical laboratory results).

               8. Urine positive for psychoactive drugs (clinical laboratory results) on study days
                  involving imaging (PET and MRI) and neuropsychological testing.

               9. Pregnant or breast feeding (self-report)

              10. History of coagulation disorder (clinical laboratory results, medical history)

              11. Have a history of allergic reaction to lidocaine (self-report, medical history)

              12. Presence of ferromagnetic objects in the body that are contraindicated for MRI of
                  the head, fear of enclosed spaces, or other standard contraindication to MRI
                  (self-report checklist).

              13. Cannot lie comfortably flat on your back for up to 2 hours in the PET and MRI
                  scanners (self-report).

              14. Body weight &gt; 250 kg. The MR scanner bed is tested to a weight limit of 250 kg
                  (~550 lbs).

              15. Have a positive HIV test (clinical laboratory results, medical history).

              16. Homozygosity for the rs6971 polymorphism on TSPO that results in LB (Owen et al
                  2011) (genotyping results).

              17. NIH employees who meet criteria as AD subjects. Although we will include NIH
                  employees as healthy volunteers, study investigators and their superiors,
                  subordinates and immediate family members (adults children, spouses, parents,
                  siblings) will be excluded.

                  EXCLUSION CRITERIA SPECIFIC FOR CONTROL PARTICIPANTS:

          -  Consumption of moderate to high levels of alcohol. That includes if female, currently
             (within past 6 months) consuming more than 2 drinks on a given episode and if male,
             consuming more than 3 drinks on a given episode; and/or consuming if female, more than
             a total of 7 drinks a week or if male, more than 10 drinks a week (self-report).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gene-Jack Wang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gene-Jack Wang, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5012</phone>
    <email>gene-jack.wang@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-AA-0192.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ward RJ, Lallemand F, de Witte P. Biochemical and neurotransmitter changes implicated in alcohol-induced brain damage in chronic or 'binge drinking' alcohol abuse. Alcohol Alcohol. 2009 Mar-Apr;44(2):128-35. doi: 10.1093/alcalc/agn100. Epub 2009 Jan 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19155229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lehnardt S. Innate immunity and neuroinflammation in the CNS: the role of microglia in Toll-like receptor-mediated neuronal injury. Glia. 2010 Feb;58(3):253-63. doi: 10.1002/glia.20928. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19705460</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreutzberg GW. Microglia: a sensor for pathological events in the CNS. Trends Neurosci. 1996 Aug;19(8):312-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8843599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 25, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Imaging Studies</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcoholism</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Encephalitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

