<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01220999</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LUD2010-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01220999</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Imaging and Pharmacodynamic Trial of CS-1008 in Patients With Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Imaging and Pharmacodynamic Trial of CS-1008 in Patients With Metastatic Colorectal Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a clinical trial of CS-1008 which is a humanized monoclonal antibody.

      This trial explores where CS-1008 distributes in the body, and the activity of CS-1008 in
      patients with metastatic colorectal cancer. The purpose of this study is to give patients
      with metastatic colorectal cancer a series of different CS-1008 antibody doses in order to:

        -  Study how the dose of CS-1008 effects where the CS-1008 distributes in the body
           (biodistribution), how long it circulates in blood (pharmacokinetics) and how much
           attaches to tumour (tumour uptake). These issues are studied after the initial infusion
           of 111In-CS-1008 (CS-1008 tagged with a small amount of radioactive Indium - also called
           Indium-111 or 111In), and also during and after a cycle of weekly infusions of CS-1008
           antibody.

        -  Study changes in the function (metabolism) of tumour cells following CS-1008
           administration.

        -  Assess whether repeat doses of CS-1008 cause shrinkage of the tumour.

        -  Study whether experimental treatment with CS-1008 changes chemicals in the blood that
           may indicate tumour cell death (serum apoptosis biomarkers) and/or tumour response to
           treatment (serum tumour biomarkers (CEA - carcinoembryonic antigen)).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a clinical trial of a laboratory produced humanised monoclonal antibody called
      CS-1008. CS-1008 binds to a receptor found on cancer cells called death receptor 5 (DR5
      receptor) which, when stimulated, can cause the cancer cell to be destroyed by a process
      called apoptosis. CS-1008 could be an important potential therapeutic in patients with
      colorectal cancer and other cancers.

      The purpose of this study is to:

        -  Primarily

           - Determine the influence of CS-1008 dose on initial biodistribution, pharmacokinetics
           and tumour uptake of 111-In-CS-1008 (CS-1008 tagged with a small amount of radioactive
           Indium - also called Indium-111) following single infusion of CS-1008, and determine
           changes in these parameters following continuous sequential doses of CS-1008.

        -  Secondarily

             -  Determine changes in tumour metabolism following CS-1008 administration

             -  Describe anti-tumour response to CS-1008 in metastatic colorectal cancer.

             -  Determine changes in serum apoptosis biomarkers and serum tumour response markers
                following treatment with CS‐1008.

      Research design and methods:

      This is a non-randomised, open label, single site (Austin Hospital), dose cohort study of
      CS-1008 in patients with advanced colorectal carcinoma who have received at least one
      previous regimen of chemotherapy treatment for metastatic disease. Consenting, eligible
      patients will each receive a course of seven doses of CS-1008, given weekly as an intravenous
      (IV) infusion over 30 minutes. The initial infusion of CS-1008 is trace labeled with
      Indium-111 (111In-CS-1008). Ten to 25 patients will be treated in cohorts in which the
      allocated initial and sequential weekly doses of CS-1008 are assessed. Each of the five dose
      level cohorts will be made up of two patients and are expandable to five patients if
      additional information about biodistribution and/or pharmacokinetics of the cohort dose is
      required. The initial 111In-CS-1008 dose is followed by gamma camera imaging for
      biodistribution and tumour uptake studies and with blood sampling over a 10 day period to
      evaluate pharmacokinetics and serum biomarkers. Weekly infusions of CS-1008 will subsequently
      occur. The day 36 infusion of CS-1008 will also be trace labeled with 111In, with subsequent
      gamma camera imaging for biodistribution and tumour uptake and blood sampling for
      pharmacokinetics and serum apoptosis biomarkers. Patients are reassessed for disease status
      (by RECIST v1.1), serum tumour biomarkers (CEA - carcinoembryonic antigen) and for
      development of human-anti-CS-1008-antibody development (HAHA) between day 44-50 (end of
      cycle/study visit). Patients are assessed for changes in the tumour metabolism following
      CS-1008 administration with 18F-FDG PET/CT scans at baseline, day 15 and end of cycle one.

      Patients with stable disease or better at the day 44-50 reassessment may continue weekly
      CS-1008 until disease progression in the absence of unacceptable toxicity or until the
      patient or treating physician requests cessation of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biodistribution and tumour uptake of CS1008 based on gamma camera imaging following initial single infusion 111In-CS-1008 and changes following continuous sequential doses of CS-1008.</measure>
    <time_frame>43 days</time_frame>
    <description>Biodistribution and tumour localization following initial dose of 111In‐CS‐1008 assessed by gamma camera images post initial single 111In‐CS‐1008 infusion. Changes in biodistribution and tumour localisation following continuous sequential doses of CS-1008 are assessed by gamma camera images following Day 36 111In-CS-1008 infusion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of 111In-CS-1008 and CS-1008 protein by gamma counting and ELISA of serum samples following initial single infusion 111In-CS-1008 and changes following continuous sequential doses of CS-1008.</measure>
    <time_frame>43 days</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics (PK) by gamma counting and ELISA to assess serum radioactivity (111In‐CS‐1008) and CS‐1008 protein concentration, respectively in sera following initial dose single 111In-CS-1008 infusion. Changes in pharmacokinetics (PK) following Day 36 111In-CS-1008 infusion are assessed by gamma counting and ELISA to assess serum radioactivity (111In‐CS‐1008) and CS‐1008 protein concentration, respectively in sera following continuous sequential doses of CS-1008.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumour metabolism response to CS‐1008 will be assessed by 18F‐FDG PET</measure>
    <time_frame>50 days</time_frame>
    <description>Tumour metabolic response to CS‐1008 will be assessed by 18F‐FDG PET/CT scan performed pre‐study and then during and following a treatment cycle of CS‐1008.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumour response to CS-1008 measured by RECIST (v1.1).</measure>
    <time_frame>50 days</time_frame>
    <description>Tumour response assesses according to the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (revised RECIST v1.1).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in serum apoptotic biomarkers following treatment with CS-1008.</measure>
    <time_frame>50 days.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in serum apoptosis biomarkers (e.g. caspase 3/7, 8 and M30) following treatment with CS‐1008.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in serum tumour response markers following treatment with CS-1008.</measure>
    <time_frame>50 days</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in serum tumour response markers (e.g. CEA - carcinoembryonic antigen) following treatment with CS‐1008.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">19</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>111In-CS-1008, CS-1008</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>111In-CS-1008, CS-1008</intervention_name>
    <description>CS-1008 will be given in 5 dose cohorts.
Weekly doses of CS-1008 are administered for 7 consecutive weeks in Cycle 1. On each dosing day, CS-1008 will be infused intravenously over approximately 30 minutes.
Cohort No.: Pts - Dose Day 1 - Day 8 - Day15,22,29 - Day 36 - Day 43
Cohort #1: 2-5 pts - 0.2 mg/kg - 6 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg
Cohort #2: 2-5 pts - 1 mg/kg - 6 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg
Cohort #3: 2-5 pts - 2 mg/kg - 6 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg
Cohort #4: 2-5 pts - 4 mg/kg - 4 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg
Cohort #5: 2-5 pts - 6 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg - 2 mg/kg
Day 1 and Day 36 doses will be trace labelled with Indium-111 (111In-CS-1008)
Additional treatment cycles in suitable patients with stable disease or better at the day 44-50 reassessment may continue be given as weekly infusions of CS-1008 at 2 mg/kg per week. Disease reassessment is planned after every second 4-week cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>111In-CS-1008, CS-1008</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically proven metastatic colorectal cancer with one target lesion ≥2cm and
             evaluable by gamma camera imaging. If this lesion has been previously irradiated,
             there must be documented progression following radiotherapy.

          -  Received at least one prior course of chemotherapy for metastatic disease.

          -  Expected survival of at least 3 months.

          -  ECOG Performance Status ≤2

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old.

          -  Able and willing to give written informed consent.

          -  Within the last 1 week prior to first study drug administration, laboratory parameters
             for vital functions should be in the normal range. Non clinically significant
             laboratory abnormalities are generally permitted, except for the following which must
             be within the ranges specified:

               -  Neutrophils - ≥ 1.5 x 10^9/L

               -  Platelets - ≥ 90 x 10^9/L

               -  INR - ≤ 1.5

               -  Serum bilirubin - ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               -  AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT) - ≤ 2 x normal upper limit (≤ 5 x ULN if liver metastases)

               -  Calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 55mL/min (Cockcroft-Gault formula)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active central nervous system metastases. Definitively treated metastases are allowed
             if stable for 6 weeks off therapy.

          -  Known immunodeficiency or HIV positivity.

          -  Serious illnesses e.g. serious infections requiring antibiotics, bleeding disorders,
             or any condition that in the opinion of the Investigator would interfere with ability
             of the patient to fulfill the study requirements.

          -  Other malignancy, except non-melanoma skin cancer, within 3 years prior to first study
             drug administration, that in the opinion of the investigator has &gt;10% risk of relapse
             within 12 months.

          -  Chemotherapy, radiotherapy or investigational agent within 4 weeks prior to first
             study drug administration.

          -  Regular corticosteroid, NSAID (other than paracetamol or low-dose aspirin) or other
             immunosuppressive treatment within 3 weeks prior to first drug administration.
             Intermittent dosing of corticosteroid or NSAID permitted if less than 4 doses within a
             3 day period.

          -  Mental impairment that may compromise ability to give informed consent and comply with
             the requirements of the study.

          -  Lack of availability for clinical follow-up assessments.

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding.

          -  Women of childbearing potential: refusal or inability to use effective means of
             contraception.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prof. Andrew M Scott MBBS, MD, FRACP, DDU</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research &amp; Austin Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ludwig Institute Tumor Targeting Program, Austin Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg (Melbourne)</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 13, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 28, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Linda Pan, Pharm.D. Assistant Director, Clinical Trials Management</name_title>
    <organization>Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Clinical trial</keyword>
  <keyword>CS-1008 mAb</keyword>
  <keyword>monoclonal antibody CS-1008</keyword>
  <keyword>Positron-Emission Tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacodynamics</keyword>
  <keyword>apoptosis</keyword>
  <keyword>caspases</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

