<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01225848</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCC 14809</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01225848</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Maintenance SU011248 Versus Placebo Post Chemotherapy Patients With Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Blinded Phase II Trial of Maintenance SU011248 Versus Placebo Post Chemotherapy Patients With Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized Blinded Phase II trial of Maintenance SU011248 Versus Placebo Post
      Chemotherapy for Patients With Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to compare the progression rate associated with
      SU011248 versus Placebo in patients with advanced urothelial carcinoma who have achieved at
      least stable disease following combination chemotherapy. Secondary objectives of the trial:
      We will explore the safety of SU011248, assess the objective response rate associated with
      SU011248 therapy in patients with stable disease after chemotherapy, and assess the median
      survival in patients with advanced urothelial carcinoma treated with SU011248 or placebo
      following chemotherapy. Correlative objectives of trial: To correlate changes in VEGF and
      sVEGFR-2 levels with clinical response in patients with advanced urothelial carcinoma.
      Tertiary objective of trial: Determine response and progression rates to SU011248 in patients
      crossed over to treatment after placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the progression rate associated with SU011248 versus Placebo in patients with advanced urothelial carinoma who have achieved at least stable disease following combination chemotherapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Patients With Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma.</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SU011248</intervention_name>
    <description>blinded-SU011248 or Placebo given at 50 mg/day as single agent for 4 consecutive weeks followed by a 2-week rest period to form a complete cycle of 6 weeks. Suty drug will be orally self administered once daily without regard to meals beginning on Day 1 of the study.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologic/cytologic diagnosis of urothelial carcinoma (tranisitional cell carcinoma
             either pure or mixed histology).

          -  All patients must have received four - six cylces of standard first line chemotherapy
             (see appendix A for suggested combinations) for treatment of locally recurrent or
             metastatic disease and must have achieved stable disease (SD), partial response (PR),
             or complete response (CR) to this chemotherapy.

          -  Patient must be registered within on month (or the next business day if falls on a
             weekend or holiday) of scans demonstrating stable disease or better and no more than
             42 days after receiving the last standard chemotherapy dose.

          -  patients may have received previous adjuvant or neoadjuvant therapy.

          -  No prior antiangiogenic therapy for this stage of the disease.

          -  An ECOG performance status of 0-2 and a life expectancy of greater than 6 months.

          -  If patients received radiation therapy, they must have recovered from side effects
             before registration to study.

          -  No prior malignancy is allowed, except for adequately treated basal cell (or
             squamouscell) skin cancer or in situ carcinoma of any site or other adequately treated
             malignancy for which the patient is currently disease free for at least one year.
             Patients with prostate cancer diagnosed at the time of cystectomy who have an
             undetectable PSA without hormonal therapy will be eligible.

          -  Timing guidelines for pre-study labs and measurements:

          -  All pre-study labs required for determination of eligibility are to be completed
             within 14 days prior to registration.

          -  X-rays and/or scans used for tumor measurement to determine disease status EKG, and
             MUGA are to be completed within one month prior to registration.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ and marrow function as defined below obtained within
             14 days from registration.

          -  All patients must be informed of the investigational nature of this study and must
             sign an informed consent in accordance with institutional and federal guidelines.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Major surgery within 4 weeks of starting the study treatment.

          -  NCI CTCAE grade 3 hemorrhage or higher within 4 weeks of starting the study treatment.

          -  History of or known spinal cord compression, or carcinomatous meningitis, or evidence
             of symptomatic brain or leptomeningeal disease on screening CT or MRI scan. However
             treated, stable and asymptomatic brain metastases are allowed.

          -  Known HIV - positive patients may not participate. This is to avoid additional
             complications that immune supression and HIV infection may cause due tothe intense
             nature of the chemotherapy in this trial.

          -  Any of the following within the 6 months prior to the study drug
             administration:myocardial infraction, severe/unstable angina, coronary/peripheral
             artery bypass graft, symptomatic congestive heart failure (CHF), cerebrovascular
             accident or transient ischemic attack, pulmonary embolism.

          -  Ongoing cardiac dysrhythmias of NCI CTCAE grade &gt;2.

          -  Patients with history of who are suspected to have CHF can be included as long as they
             are asymptomatic and have an ejection fraction that is equal to or above the
             institutional lower limit of normal by baseline MUGA.

          -  QTc interval&gt; 500 msec on baseline EKG.

          -  Hypertension that cannot be controlled by medications (&gt;150/11 mm Hg despite optimal
             medical therapy).

          -  Patients with pre-existing thyroid function abnormalities that can not be controlled
             medically.

          -  Patients may not have unresolved bacterial infection.

          -  Concurrent treatment on another clinical trial. Supportive care trials or
             non-treatment trials, e.g. QOL, are allowed.

          -  Pregnancy or brestfeeding. Female subjects must be surgically sterile or be
             postmenopausal, or must agree to use effective contraception during the period of
             therapy. All female subjects with reproductive potential must have a negative
             pregnancy test (serum or urine) prior to enrollment. Male subjects must be surgically
             sterile or must agree to use effective contraception during the period of therapy. The
             definition of effective contraception will be based on the judgement of the principal
             investigator or a designated associate.

          -  Other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory
             abnormally that may increase the risk associated with study participation or study
             drug administration, or may interfere with the interpretation of study results, and in
             the judgement of the investigator would make the subject inappropriate for entry into
             thid study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Vaughn, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 20, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Transitional Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sunitinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

