<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01229748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20090623</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01229748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Family Intervention for Teen Drinking in the ER</brief_title>
  <official_title>Family Intervention for Teen Drinking and Alcohol-Related Crises in the ER</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose a randomized controlled trial with five aims: 1. To investigate the
      engagement potential and effectiveness of a family-centered intervention (MDFT) and Family
      Motivational Interviewing Intervention (FMII)/group for teens with alcohol-related crises; 2.
      To explore differential treatment effects with comorbid adolescents; 3. To examine the role
      of motivation and family factors as treatment mediators; 4. To examine long-term abstinence,
      patterns and predictors of relapse up to 18 months follow-up; and 5. To compare the total and
      net monetary benefits to society of MDFT, FMII/group, and standard care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim 1: To investigate in a randomized controlled trial the engagement potential and
      effectiveness of family-centered intervention (MDFT) and family-involved MI (FMII) for teens
      with alcohol problems

        -  Hypothesis 1a: Treatment engagement will be higher in MDFT and FMII than in standard
           care as evidenced by higher numbers of MDFT and FMII youth enrolled in substance abuse
           treatment.

        -  Hypothesis 1b: Treatment completion will be higher for MDFT than FMII/group and standard
           care as evidenced by more teens/families in MDFT completing a full course of treatment.

        -  Hypothesis 1c: Youth assigned to MDFT and FMII/group will show greater decreases in
           alcohol use and binge drinking than youth in standard care at the 3 month follow-up (end
           of treatment). MDFT participants will show greater decreases in alcohol use and binge
           drinking than FMII/group and standard care during the post-treatment period and up to 18
           month follow-up, and they will be less likely to meet diagnostic criteria for an AUD at
           18 months.

        -  Hypothesis 1d: Youth assigned to MDFT and FMII/group will show greater reductions than
           youth in standard care in problems related to alcohol use, including drug use, drinking
           and driving, alcohol-related injury, health and mental health problems, school problems,
           delinquency, and association with substance abusing peers at the 3 month follow-up (end
           of treatment). Youth in MDFT will show greater reductions in these problems than
           FMII/group and standard care in the post-treatment period and up to 18 month follow-up.

      Aim 2: To explore differential treatment effects with comorbid adolescents

        -  Hypothesis 2: For youth with low baseline levels of alcohol, drug, and psychiatric
           problems, MDFT and FMII/group will both be more effective than standard care. MDFT will
           reduce alcohol use more significantly than FMII/group for teens with more severe
           baseline alcohol, drug, and psychiatric problems.

      Aim 3: To examine the contribution of motivation and family factors as mediators of treatment
      effects

        -  Hypothesis 3a: In both MDFT and FMII/group, motivation to change at the end of the
           initial engagement sessions in both teen and parent will predict treatment participation
           and 3 month outcomes (end of treatment) to a greater extent than motivation in the teen
           or parent alone.

        -  Hypothesis 3b: In both MDFT and FMII/group, effective parenting practices and strong
           family relationships will predict better alcohol and related outcomes at 3 month
           follow-up.

      Aim 4: To examine long-term abstinence, patterns and predictors of relapse up to 18 months
      follow-up

        -  Hypothesis 4a: Four distinct patterns of relapse will emerge between 3 month and 18
           month follow-up: high abstinence, low abstinence, decreasing abstinence, and increasing
           abstinence.

        -  Hypothesis 4b: MDFT youth will be more likely to be in the high abstinence and
           increasing abstinence groups; youth in FMII/group will be more likely to be in the
           decreasing abstinence group; and youth in standard care will be more likely to be in the
           low abstinence group.

        -  Hypothesis 4c: Youth in MDFT will show more significant reductions in risk factors for
           alcohol relapse (family dysfunction, lack of abstinence motivation, positive alcohol
           expectancies, poor abstinence coping, lack of support for abstinence) than youth in
           FMII/group or standard care.

      Aim 5: To compare the total/net monetary benefits to society of MDFT, FMII/group, and
      standard care

        -  Hypothesis 5: MDFT and FMII/group will generate significantly higher total and net
           monetary benefits to society than youth in standard care at 18 months post-ER visit.

        -  Research Question 5: Will MDFT or FMII/group generate higher total/net benefits to
           society?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment engagement/retention</measure>
    <time_frame>Proportion of adolescents enrolled in substance abuse treatment at 3 months post -intake.</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the engagement potential and effectiveness of a family-centered intervention (MDFT) and family-involved MI (FMII) for teens with alcohol-related crises.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol use/abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>Youth assigned to MDFT and FMII/group will show greater decreases in alcohol use and binge drinking than youth in standard care at 3 months post intake.</time_frame>
    <description>MDFT participants will show greater decreases in alcohol use and binge drinking than FMII/group and standard care during the post-treatment period and up to 18 month follow-up, and they will be less likely to meet diagnostic criteria for an AUD at 18 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">104</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Abuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multidimensional Family Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multidimensional Family Therapy is an outpatient family-based treatment for troubled youth.(Liddle, 2002) considered in the U.S. and abroad as an empirically supported Best Practice treatment for teen substance abuse and delinquency (USDHHS 2002; Drug Strategies 2003; NIDA 1999; Rigter et al 2004).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Family Motivational Interviewing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Motivational Interviewing (MI; Miller 1983; Miller &amp; Rollnick 1991), is a client-centered treatment designed to strengthen clients' commitment and empower them to change their substance use behavior (Miller &amp; Rollnick 2002).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The standard care condition will represent typical services for teens with alcohol problems in the community: assessment and referral for treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Clients attend two 90-minute group sessions per week.Treatment lasts for three months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multidimensional Family Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Multidimensional Family Therapy is an outpatient family-based treatment for troubled youth (Liddle, 2002). Treatment duration is 3 months, sessions last 60-90 minutes, with an average of 2 sessions per week and additional extrafamilial work and phone contacts as needed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Multidimensional Family Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Family Motivational Interviewing Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Youth and parents receive 2 FMII sessions in their homes within 72 hours of the ER incident, and youth will be linked with group treatment lasting 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Family Motivational Interviewing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Between ages 12 to 18 years old

          2. Present in ER/trauma unit

          3. Meet minimum cut-off of 4 on the AUDIT; OR BAC of 0.01% or more on QED; OR report
             alcohol use within 6 hours of ER visit

          4. Not receiving any other behavioral treatment

          5. At least one parent/guardian is willing to participate in assessments and intervention

          6. Parent consent/youth assent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Meet DSM-IV dependence criteria for any substance other than alcohol, marijuana, or
             tobacco

          2. Mental retardation or pervasive developmental disorders

          3. Psychotic symptoms

          4. Current suicidality
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cynthia L Rowe, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jackson Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami Miller School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33155</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowe CL, Liddle HA. Family-based treatment development for adolescent alcohol abuse. Int J Adolesc Med Health. 2006 Jan-Mar;18(1):43-51.</citation>
    <PMID>16639858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 26, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 1, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cynthia Rowe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Underage Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

