<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01220362</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>093/10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01220362</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Thoracic Epidural Analgesia and Surgery on Lower Urinary Tract Function: A Randomized, Controlled Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Thoracic Epidural Analgesia and Surgery on Lower Urinary Tract Function: A Randomized, Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative urinary retention (POUR) is one of the most common complications after surgery
      and neuraxial anesthesia of which the treatment of choice is bladder catheterization 1. It
      has been a common practice to place an indwelling catheter in the bladder in patients
      receiving epidural analgesia and to leave the catheter as long as the epidural analgesia is
      maintained despite a lack of evidence supporting this approach.

      Transurethral catheterization is associated with significant morbidity such as patient
      discomfort, urethral trauma and urinary tract infections (UTI). Prolonged catheterization is
      the primary risk factor for catheter associated UTI (CAUTI), which is one of the most common
      nosocomial infections and can prolong hospitalisation 2. For this reason there is a growing
      focus on limiting the duration of catheterization and finding methods to avoid unnecessary
      catheterization in perioperative medicine 3,4.

      Lower urinary tract function depends on coordinated actions between the detrusor muscle and
      the external urethral sphincter. Motorneurons of both muscles are located in the sacral
      spinal cord between L1 and S4. Most afferent fibers from the bladder enter the sacral cord
      through the pelvic nerve at segments L4-S2.

      Because epidural analgesia can be performed at various levels of the spinal cord, it is
      possible to block only a portion of the spinal cord (segmental blockade). Based on the
      innervation of the bladder and sphincter between L1 and S4 it can be assumed that epidural
      analgesia within segments T4-6 to T10-12 has no or minimal influence on lower urinary tract
      function.

      In a previous study, we found, against our expectations that thoracic epidural analgesia
      (TEA) significantly inhibits the detrusor muscle during voiding, resulting in clinically
      relevant post-void residuals which required monitoring or catheterisation 5. Because the
      study adopted a before-after design, we could not definitively identify the mechanisms
      responsible for this change in bladder function. In particular, we could not determine
      whether TEA per se or surgery was the main cause. Concerning TEA, it remains unclear which
      compounds of the solution, the local anesthetic, the opioid or both are responsible for the
      observed changes in lower urinary tract function.

      The aim of this study is to compare lower urinary tract function before and during TEA with
      two different epidural solutions (group 1: bupivacaine 1.25 mg/ml vs group 2: bupivacaine
      1.25 mg/ml combined with fentanyl 2 µg/ml) within segments T4-6 to T10-12 for postoperative
      pain treatment in patients undergoing lumbotomy for open renal surgery.

      We expect that a better understanding of lower urinary tract function during TEA could lead
      to a more restrictive use of indwelling transurethral catheters perioperatively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      Acute urinary retention is one of the most common complications after surgery and anesthesia.
      It can occur in patients of both sexes and all age groups and after all types of surgical
      procedures. It is linked to several factors including increased intravenous fluids,
      postoperative pain and type of anaesthesia 1.

      Micturition depends on coordinated actions between the detrusor muscle and the external
      urethral sphincter. Motorneurons of both muscles are located in the sacral spinal cord and
      coordination between them occurs in the pontine tegmentum of the caudal brain stem.
      Motorneurons innervating the external urethral sphincter are located in the nucleus of Onuf,
      extending from segment S1 to S3. The detrusor smooth muscle is innervated by parasympathetic
      fibers, which reside in the sacral intermediolateral cell group and are located in S2-4.
      Sympathetic fibers innervating the bladder and urethra play an important role in promoting
      continence and are located in the intermediolateral cell group of the lumbar cord (L1-L4).
      Most afferent fibers from the bladder enter the sacral cord through the pelvic nerve at
      segments L4-S2 and the majority are thin myelinated or unmyelinated.

      There are few studies on the urodynamic effects of various anaesthetic agents 2-8, which
      mainly focused on lumbar epidural anaesthesia. Under the influence of epidural analgesia,
      patients may not feel the sensation of bladder filling, which can result in urinary retention
      and bladder overdistension. Overfilling of the bladder can stretch and in some cases
      permanently damage the detrusor muscle.

      Because epidural anesthesia can be performed at various levels of the spinal cord, it is
      possible to block only a portion of the spinal cord (segmental blockade). Based on knowledge
      of the bladder innervations, it can be assumed that epidural analgesia within segments T4-6
      to T10-12 has no or minimal influences on lower urinary tract function.

      In a previous study, we found, against our expectations that thoracic epidural analgesia
      significantly inhibits the detrusor muscle during voiding, resulting in clinically relevant
      post void residuals which required monitoring or transurethral catheterisation 9. Because the
      study adopted a before-after design, we could not definitively identify the mechanisms
      responsible for bladder dysfunction. In particular, we could not say whether thoracic
      epidural analgesia per se or surgery was the cause of bladder dysfunction. Furthermore, it
      remains which ingredients, whether the local anesthetic, the opioid or both are behind
      changes in voiding function.

      Objective

      In our previous studies, we found that TEA significantly inhibits the detrusor muscle during
      voiding, resulting in clinically relevant post-void residuals which required monitoring or
      catheterization with similar findings 5,30.

      Because these studies adopted a before-after design, we could not definitively identify the
      mechanisms responsible for lower urinary tract dysfunction. In particular, we could not say
      whether TEA per se or surgery was the cause of lower urinary tract dysfunction. Furthermore,
      it remains unclear which compounds in the epidural solution, the local anesthetic, the opioid
      or both are behind the observed changes in lower urinary tract function.

      The objectives of this study are to determine if TEA per se or surgery are the cause of
      bladder dysfunction and which drugs in the epidural solution are responsible for this effect.

      Methods

      Randomised controlled double-blind study. Patients will be randomly allocated to one of the
      two groups by a computer-generated randomization list. Randomization will be stratified by
      gender, in order to reach an equal number of male and females in the two groups. Patients and
      investigators will be blinded to the epidural solution administrated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in post-void residual between bupivacaine (group 1) and bupivacaine-fentanyl (group 2) after surgery on day 2 or 3, depending on patient mobilisation.</measure>
    <time_frame>day 2 or 3 after surgery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in post-void residual before and after surgery under segmental blockade.</measure>
    <time_frame>day 2 or 3 after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in secondary outcomes (see 2.1.2.) between group 1 and group 2 before surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>day 2 or 3 after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in secondary outcomes (see 2.1.2.) before and after surgery under segmental blockade.</measure>
    <time_frame>day 2 or 3 after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Analgesia, Epidural</condition>
  <condition>Urodynamics</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Retention</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bupivacaine 0.125%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bupivacaine 0.125%/Fentanyl 2mcg/ml</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivacain 0.125%</intervention_name>
    <description>Bupivacain 0.125%</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivacain 0.125%/Fentanyl 2mcg/ml</intervention_name>
    <description>Bupivacain 0.125%/Fentanyl 2mcg/ml</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Open kidney surgery with lumbotomy

          -  Thoracic epidural analgesia

          -  International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) &lt; 7

          -  Preoperative residual urine volume &lt; 100ml

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Contraindications to epidural analgesia or refusal

          -  Preoperative residual urine volume &gt; 100ml

          -  International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) &gt; 7

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fiona C Burkhard, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Dep. of urology, University Hospital Bern, 3010 Bern, Switzerland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dep. of Anesthesiology and Pain Therapy, University Hospital Bern, 3010 Bern,Switzerland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <state>BE</state>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baldini G, Bagry H, Aprikian A, Carli F. Postoperative urinary retention: anesthetic and perioperative considerations. Anesthesiology. 2009 May;110(5):1139-57. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31819f7aea. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19352147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wuethrich PY, Kessler TM, Panicker JN, Curatolo M, Burkhard FC. Detrusor activity is impaired during thoracic epidural analgesia after open renal surgery. Anesthesiology. 2010 Jun;112(6):1345-9. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181d4f4fe.</citation>
    <PMID>20461004</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 13, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr. med. Patrick Wüthrich</name_title>
    <organization>Department of Anesthesiology and Pain Therapy,University Hospital Bern Inselspital Bern</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Analgesia, Epidural</keyword>
  <keyword>Urodynamics</keyword>
  <keyword>Urinary Retention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Agnosia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Retention</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

