<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01227473</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-0563</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21AT004276-01A</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21AT004276-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01227473</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>We Can Prevent Diabetes: A Behavioral Intervention to Reduce Diabetes Risk in African Americans</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Mindfulness-based Intervention to Reduce Diabetes Risk in Pre-diabetic African Americans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pre-diabetes, characterized by glucose levels that are above normal but below the diagnostic
      criteria for diabetes, is an increasingly common condition, particularly among African
      Americans. Changes in physical activity, changes in diet, and levels of stress influence the
      course of the disease. Helping individuals to reduce stress and to increase healthy coping
      strategies may enhance conventional diabetes prevention efforts, especially among African
      Americans. Mindfulness training is a cost-effective intervention which may be effective in
      reducing stress and enhancing the ability to make behavioral changes. This exploratory pilot
      study will examine the potential efficacy of a diabetes prevention education program that
      includes training in mindfulness-based stress reduction (intervention group) for pre-diabetic
      African Americans, comparing it to a conventional diabetes prevention program (control group)
      in the ability to improve glucose metabolism as well as other relevant physiological and
      psychological secondary outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pre-diabetes, characterized by glucose levels that are above normal but below the diagnostic
      criteria for diabetes, is an increasingly common condition affecting approximately 54 million
      U.S. adults. African Americans are disproportionately affected by pre-diabetes and experience
      high rates of diabetes-associated morbidity and mortality including damage to the circulatory
      system, kidneys, and nervous system. Patients with pre-diabetes who increase their physical
      activity and improve their diets have reduced risk of developing diabetes. Psychological
      distress negatively influences the course of the disease by increasing deleterious health
      behaviors; preventing scheduling and maintenance of positive behavior change; and stimulating
      HPA-axis activation and dysregulation, which may have a direct impact on insulin resistance
      and glucose metabolism. African Americans may have increased exposure to stress and increased
      vulnerability to adverse stress-related health outcomes like diabetes, because of their
      unique history, sociocultural experiences, and societal position in the U.S. Helping
      individuals to reduce stress and to increase healthy coping strategies may enhance
      conventional diabetes prevention efforts, especially among African Americans.

      Mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR), a mind-body practice with a wide range of health
      benefits, has been shown to result in statistically significant reductions in psychological
      stress and anxiety in randomized, controlled studies. Mindfulness training is cost-effective
      in comparison with other small-group or individualized programs, and can be taught safely and
      effectively by well-trained instructors. There is little research, and no randomized,
      controlled trials of MBSR as a treatment for individuals with pre-diabetes. There is also
      little research on the acceptability of MBSR program to a prediabetic subgroup of African
      Americans, or on the acceptability of an MBSR program for a general population of African
      Americans.

      Overall goals of this exploratory pilot study are to study the potential efficacy of a
      diabetes prevention education program that includes training in mindfulness-based stress
      reduction for pre-diabetic African Americans. Specific Aims are 1) to determine the
      feasibility of developing a clinical trial to compare the effectiveness of a
      mindfulness-based diabetes prevention program (treatment group) with a conventional diabetes
      prevention program (control group) in improving glucose metabolism in pre-diabetic African
      American adults; 2) to identify relevant physiological and psychological secondary outcomes
      associated with a mindfulness-based, educational self-care program in African-Americans with
      pre-diabetes; 3) to assess the acceptability and cultural relevance of MBSR for pre-diabetic
      African Americans via a post-intervention qualitative study, to include interviews of
      participants, dropouts, and instructors; and 4) to identify, and find solutions for, problems
      in conducting a well-powered clinical trial to assess the efficacy of a mindfulness-based
      diabetes prevention program in improving glucose metabolism in pre-diabetic
      African-Americans.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>insulin resistance, as measured by the homeostatic model assessment-insulin resistance (HOMA-IR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Fasting samples will be collected 3 weeks, on average, before the intervention and at 3 months post intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>The homeostatic model assessment-insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) is a calculated measure based on the FPG and fasting insulin levels.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>Salivary cortisol will be measured before the intervention and at 2 weeks, 3 months, and 6 months post intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin resistance as measured by the HOMA-IR</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks and 6 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The HOMA-IR is calculated from the fasting insulin and fasting glucose.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Prediabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mindfulness prediabetes education group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The mindfulness-based diabetes prevention education group meets for 2 ½ hours per week for eight weeks, with one 4-hour retreat between the 6th and 7th weeks, and monthly booster sessions for 6 months. During the 8-week interventions, the group receives a 30-minute health behavior presentation (based on the landmark Diabetes Prevention Program). In the mindfulness-based diabetes prevention group, the instruction will be enhanced with instruction in mindfulness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>conventional prediabetes education group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The conventional diabetes prevention education group meets for 2 ½ hours per week for eight weeks, with one 4-hour retreat between the 6th and 7th weeks, and monthly booster sessions for 6 months. During the 8-week interventions, the group receives a 30-minute health behavior presentation (based on the landmark Diabetes Prevention Program). In the conventional diabetes prevention group, the instruction will be enhanced with group exercises and discussions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness-based diabetes prevention education group</intervention_name>
    <description>The mindfulness-based diabetes prevention group meets for 2 ½ hours per week for eight weeks, with one 4-hour retreat between the 6th and 7th weeks, and monthly booster sessions for 6 months. During the 8-week interventions, this group receives a 30-minute health behavior presentation (based on the landmark Diabetes Prevention Program). In the mindfulness-based diabetes prevention group, the instruction will be enhanced with a modified mindfulness meditation training designed to support the behavioral-change programming.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mindfulness prediabetes education group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MBSR</other_name>
    <other_name>DPP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional diabetes prevention education group</intervention_name>
    <description>The conventional diabetes prevention education group meets for 2 ½ hours per week for eight weeks, with one 4-hour retreat between the 6th and 7th weeks, and monthly booster sessions for 6 months. During the 8-week interventions, the group receives a 30-minute health behavior presentation (based on the landmark Diabetes Prevention Program). In the conventional diabetes prevention group, the instruction will be enhanced with group exercises and discussions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>conventional prediabetes education group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DPP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  African-American

          -  25-65 years of age

          -  meeting the ADA criteria for pre-diabetes (either by fasting plasma glucose (FPG) of
             100-125 mg/dl or glucose of 140-199 mg/dl at 2 hours in an oral glucose tolerance test
             (OGTT))or a HbA1c of 5.7-6.4%

          -  experiencing some degree of stress

          -  willing to attend 1 1/2 hour group meetings once weekly for 8 weeks, followed by
             monthly booster sessions for six months, and to complete assessment instruments.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  diabetes diagnosed by a physician

          -  past or current use of hypoglycemic medication (except gestational diabetes)

          -  disease associated with disordered glucose metabolism

          -  use of medications associated with impaired glucose metabolism

          -  active treatment for or history of a major medical illness

          -  previous training in meditation or mindful yoga, tai chi, qigong

          -  pregnant or planning a pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Gaylord, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 15, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 21, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 25, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Susan Gaylord</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prediabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>African Americans</keyword>
  <keyword>mindfulness</keyword>
  <keyword>behavioral</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prediabetic State</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Intolerance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

