<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01585454</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999912108</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-DK-N108</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01585454</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Lifestyle in Pregnancy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Healthy Lifestyle in Pregnancy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Women can gain too much weight or develop diabetes during pregnancy. If the mother is
      overweight or has diabetes during pregnancy, her baby may also be at risk of being overweight
      or developing diabetes. A woman s chance of getting diabetes increases if her parents or
      family members are overweight or have diabetes. Poor diet and exercise habits can also lead
      to weight gain and diabetes. Researchers want to study how best to improve the health of
      pregnant women and their children. They will do so by providing healthy lifestyle counseling
      for women receiving prenatal care at the Phoenix Indian Medical Center.

      Objectives:

      - To study the effectiveness of healthy lifestyle counseling for overweight and/or diabetic
      pregnant women.

      Eligibility:

        -  Women at least 18 years of age who will receive pregnancy care at the Phoenix Indian
           Medical Center.

        -  Participants must be overweight or obese. They may or may not have diabetes.

      Design:

        -  Participants will receive standard prenatal care from the midwives, doctors, and
           dietitians at the Phoenix Indian Medical Center.

        -  Participants will work with National Institutes of Health staff for about 2 hours every
           week. These sessions may include phone calls, home visits, or group meetings.

        -  Participants will have a total of nine measurement visits. The first visit will be at or
           before 16 weeks of pregnancy. The next three visits will be within a week of the first
           visit. Another four visits will take place between 23 and 28 weeks of pregnancy.

        -  Participants will have different tests through their pregnancy. They will wear heart
           monitors and wrist monitors to measure heart rate and movement. They will provide
           information on their eating habits, physical activity, and mood and feelings during
           pregnancy. Blood samples will be collected to measure blood glucose (sugar) levels.

        -  Participants will receive counseling on healthy eating and physical activity habits.
           They will be encouraged to invite friends or family members to learn more about healthy
           lifestyle choices.

        -  The study will end with the final visit about 6 to 8 weeks after giving birth. A final
           blood sample will be collected. Participants will be asked questions about mood and
           feelings.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      American Indians are at high risk for developing type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and its
      complications. Major factors responsible for this finding include obesity and intrauterine
      exposure to diabetes; the latter increases the risk of diabetes in the offspring particularly
      during childhood and adolescence. This study is designed to evaluate the feasibility of
      conducting an intensive lifestyle intervention (ILI) in adult (age greater than or equal to
      18 years) pregnant women of any race or ethnicity who are eligible for prenatal care at
      Phoenix Indian Medical Center (PIMC). Most of these women or their fetuses will be of
      American Indian heritage. Interventions will be provided to overweight and obese pregnant
      women who may have diabetes, develop gestational diabetes (GDM), or be at high risk of
      developing diabetes. We will evaluate our ability to maintain engagement and motivate
      adoption of a healthy diet and increased physical activity. The lifestyle intervention will
      be patterned after the Diabetes Prevention Program (DPP) that prevented or delayed the onset
      of diabetes in non pregnant adults; the interventions will be modified to be appropriate in
      pregnancy. A major modification will be to encourage managed weight gain instead of weight
      loss. For women who have or develop diabetes, interventions will include coaching to optimize
      glycemic control. In this protocol, we will seek to identify strategies that can successfully
      accomplish these goals. Results from this study will permit us to formulate appropriate
      intervention strategies for a large randomized clinical study to evaluate the impact of an
      intensive lifestyle intervention on pregnant women and their offspring.

      The project will be conducted in collaboration between the nurse midwifery and obstetrics
      services at Phoenix Indian Medical Center (PIMC) and the National Institute of Diabetes and
      Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK). Important feasibility measures include evaluating our
      ability to enroll and retain pregnant women in a lifestyle intervention program and collect
      serial measures of gestational weight and glucose, objective measures of physical activity,
      and nutritional questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 27, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 20, 2016</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gestational Weight Gain</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gestational Diabetes</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications of Pregnancy and Delivery</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Hperglycemia</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Weight Gain</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. At least 18 years of age.

               2. Receive prenatal care at the nurse midwifery/obstetrics service of PIMC and plan
                  to continue receiving such care throughout the pregnancy.

               3. Are able to have an OGTT prior to 16 weeks gestation (if diabetes was not
                  previously diagnosed). Hyperemesis can preclude some pregnant women from
                  successfully completing the OGTT; these women will not be excluded if the fasting
                  blood samples can be obtained. Pregnant women with previously diagnosed diabetes
                  are eligible if measures of glycemia (FPG, HbA1c, glycated albumin) are completed
                  prior to 16 weeks gestation.

               4. Estimated prenatal BMI &gt;25 kg/m2.

               5. Able to commit the time required for the interventions and follow-up.

               6. Able and willing to provide informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Contraindication to aerobic or resistance exercise (ACOG, 2002).

          2. Twin or multiple gestation.

          3. Severe anemia, uncontrolled asthma, uncontrolled hypertension, cardiac disease, or any
             condition that requires follow-up at specialty care clinics outside of PIMC (e.g.,
             pregnancies at high risk for maternal or fetal demise).

          4. Any condition that in the opinion of the investigators would interfere with consent,
             treatment, or follow-up.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William C Knowler, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cedergren MI. Optimal gestational weight gain for body mass index categories. Obstet Gynecol. 2007 Oct;110(4):759-64.</citation>
    <PMID>17906006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dabelea D, Hanson RL, Lindsay RS, Pettitt DJ, Imperatore G, Gabir MM, Roumain J, Bennett PH, Knowler WC. Intrauterine exposure to diabetes conveys risks for type 2 diabetes and obesity: a study of discordant sibships. Diabetes. 2000 Dec;49(12):2208-11.</citation>
    <PMID>11118027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>International Association of Diabetes and Pregnancy Study Groups Consensus Panel, Metzger BE, Gabbe SG, Persson B, Buchanan TA, Catalano PA, Damm P, Dyer AR, Leiva Ad, Hod M, Kitzmiler JL, Lowe LP, McIntyre HD, Oats JJ, Omori Y, Schmidt MI. International association of diabetes and pregnancy study groups recommendations on the diagnosis and classification of hyperglycemia in pregnancy. Diabetes Care. 2010 Mar;33(3):676-82. doi: 10.2337/dc09-1848. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20190296</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 20, 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 24, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 24, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 25, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes Mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Weight Gain</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Gain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

