<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01584661</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ABB-1-2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01584661</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Continuity of Nutritional Care Among Elderly Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Continuity of Nutritional Care From the Hospital to the Community and Its Impact on Health and Functional Indicators Among Elderly Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bait Balev Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ben-Gurion University of the Negev</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bait Balev Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives:

        1. To determine the level of compliance with nutritional recommendations (dietary and
           nutritional supplements) following discharge from hospitalization;

        2. To identify barriers for post-discharge adherence to professional nutritional
           recommendations;

        3. To determine the impact of adherence (high vs. low) to the nutritional treatment
           guidelines on functional and health indicators.

      Working hypothesis:

      High adherence to nutritional care after hospitalization will be associated with better
      functional and health outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study will follow patients who were hospitalized in the rehabilitation
      departments at &quot;Bait Balev&quot;. Patients who were treated with nutritional supplements by a
      dietitian during hospitalization and received dietary recommendations upon discharge will be
      followed for their adherence with the treatment recommendations. The impact of the level of
      adherence to the nutritional recommendations on health will be assessed.

      C2. Experimental design:

      This shall be a retrospective and prospective cohort study. Patients from the orthopedic and
      neurologic rehabilitation departments, who received nutritional intervention by nutritional
      supplements during hospitalization and were advised to receive nutritional enrichment at
      discharge, will be enrolled to the study. The main criteria for nutritional intervention
      during hospitalization and recommendation for supplements upon discharge include, among
      others, withdrawal of alternative nourishment, underweight, undernutrition, non-voluntary
      weight loss, low protein status and other criteria typical among this population during
      hospitalization. In order to assess the level of compliance with dietitian's recommendations
      upon discharge, only patients who were discharged to their homes will be followed. In order
      to increase the sample size, a retrospective cohort study will be conducted, in which
      patients from the same departments who were discharged in the last 3 months will be followed
      both retrospectively and prospectively.

      Home visits will take place 3 and 6 months after discharge, during which the dietitian shall
      complete a questionnaire measuring the level of patient compliance to the nutritional
      recommendations, and in addition the patient or their legal guardian shall provide anamnesis
      in order to review the effect of compliance on health, functional, nutritional and social
      status (it should be noted that approx. 90% of the patients in the hospital belong to the
      Maccabi Health Care Services group, so the follow up of discharged patients in the community
      will be conducted with Maccabi Health Care Services).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary: Compliance with nutritional recommendations</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health status</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <condition>Continuity of Nutritional Care</condition>
  <condition>Health Care Use</condition>
  <condition>Nutritional Status</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Compliance with nutritional care</arm_group_label>
    <description>The Inclusion criteria comprise patients who were treated nutritionally with food enrichment supplements during their hospitalization in &quot;Bait Balev&quot; and were discharged to their homes with dietary recommendations. Participants who are willing to participate will sign an informed consent form. For patients with cognitive impairment or dementia, as reported in their medical records, their formal primary caregiver or proxy will sign the informed consent form.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dietary recommendations</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Compliance with nutritional care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population Patients over the age of 65 who are members of Maccabi Health Care
        Services will be recruited for the current study. The Inclusion criteria comprise patients
        who were treated nutritionally with food enrichment supplements during their
        hospitalization in &quot;Bait Balev&quot; and were discharged to their homes with dietary
        recommendations. Participants who are willing to participate will sign an informed consent
        form. For patients with cognitive impairment or dementia, as reported in their medical
        records, their formal primary caregiver or proxy will sign the informed consent form.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:comprise patients who were treated nutritionally with food enrichment
        supplements during their hospitalization in &quot;Bait Balev&quot; and were discharged to their homes
        with dietary recommendations. Participants who are willing to participate will sign an
        informed consent form. For patients with cognitive impairment or dementia, as reported in
        their medical records, their formal primary caregiver or proxy will sign the informed
        consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Patients who were discharged to a Retirement home; 2. Palliative patients; 3.
             Patients who are not members of Maccabi Health Care Services. 4. Patients with enteral
             nutrition (PZ / PEG / PEJ)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>95 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bait Balev</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bat-Yam</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yulia Ginzburgh, RD</last_name>
      <phone>972526885631</phone>
      <email>yulia_ginzburg@walla.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bait Balev</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bat-Yam</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yulia Ginzburgh, RD</last_name>
      <phone>972526885631</phone>
      <email>yulia_ginzburg@walla.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Danit R Shahar, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 24, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 24, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 25, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 25, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ben-Gurion University of the Negev</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Danit R Shahar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

