<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01583972</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N3-TSA-003</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PR-10012</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01583972</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Newborn Vitamin A Supplementation in Improving Immune Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Newborn Vitamin A Supplementation in Improving Immune Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>USDA, Western Human Nutrition Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>World Health Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>USDA, Western Human Nutrition Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vitamin A supplementation at birth may increase survival of infants through one year of age
      by reducing mortality from infectious diseases, though current studies are not conclusive on
      this point. The goal of our study is to determine if supplementation of newborn infants with
      50,000 IU of vitamin A improves aspects of immune function that may be impaired by vitamin A
      deficiency. Our underlying assumption is that supplementation may thus decrease risk of death
      by improving immune function and the ability to survive infections. This project will be
      limited to the examination of the impact of vitamin A on immune function and will not aim to
      determine the impact on morbidity or mortality, which would require larger sample sizes. The
      hypotheses addressed by this study are as follows: Provision of vitamin A supplements to
      newborns at risk of vitamin A deficiency will (1) improve functioning of the thymus (the
      source of T lymphocytes, cells of the immune system that are important in response to
      infection and immunization); (2) enhance T lymphocyte-mediated responses to standard vaccines
      given at birth and early in infancy; and (3) improve gut barrier function (i.e., ability to
      prevent bacterial infection across the epithelial barrier), relative to provision of a
      placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project will examine the effect of vitamin A supplementation (50,000 IU) or placebo
      given with BCG and oral polio virus (OPV) immunization within 48 h of birth on immune
      function in 300 Bangladeshi infants (150 in each group) at risk of vitamin A deficiency
      recruited in a poor community of Dhaka, Bangladesh. Infants will be followed from birth
      through 15 wk of age. Current evidence from community-based mortality trials is not
      conclusive but suggests that such supplementation will decrease infant mortality from
      infectious disease through 6 m of age. The biological mechanism underlying this potential
      benefit is unclear but is presumed to include improving immune function. The investigators
      hypothesize that vitamin A supplementation at birth prevents vitamin A deficiency during a
      critical window of a few days to weeks when the immune system is first exposed to both
      normal, non-pathogenic organisms (e.g., commensal gut flora) and to potential pathogens.
      During this period the investigators propose that vitamin A supplementation will improve
      three aspects of immune function that will have sustained benefits throughout infancy: (1)
      normal thymus maturation and function; (2) development and mucosal targeting of adaptive
      immune responses, including regulatory T-cells (Treg), T-helper type 2 (Th2) cells, and
      IgA-secreting plasma cells and memory B-cells; and (3) mucosal barrier function. The three
      specific objectives of our project are: (1) Determine if vitamin A supplementation improves
      thymus maturation and function as indicated by ultrasonic analysis of thymus size and by
      analysis of thymic output of naïve T-cells using flow cytometric analysis of peripheral blood
      T-cells and by quantification of T-cell-receptor excision circles (TRECs) in peripheral
      blood. (2) Determine if vitamin A supplementation at birth alters (2.1) the T-cell response
      to BCG and OPV immunization assessed at 6 and 15 wk of age; (2.2) the T- and B-cell response
      to OPV immunization, assessed at 15 wk of age, and the secretory IgA response to OPV assessed
      at 6, 11 and 15 wk of age; and (2.3) the B-cell response to tetanus toxoid (TT) immunization,
      assessed at 15 wk of age. (3) Determine if vitamin A supplementation at birth will decrease
      bacterial lipopolysaccharide (LPS) concentrations in capillary blood, a marker of bacterial
      translocation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Thymus size measured by ultrasound</measure>
    <time_frame>through 15 wk of age</time_frame>
    <description>Thymus size will be assessed sonographically using a validated method in which the transverse diameter of the thymus and the sagittal area of its largest lobe are multiplied to give a volume-related thymic index (TI). This index has been shown to correlate with thymus weight and has been used to show that the human thymus is sensitive to environmental influences during infancy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>peripheral blood naive T-helper lymphocyte concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>through 15 wk of age</time_frame>
    <description>Naive and memory CD4 T lymphocytes will be measured by flow cytometric analysis using the CD45RA and CD45RO markers to identify naive and memory CD4+ T-cells, respectively. Naive T cells develop in the thymus and their level in peripheral blood is an index of thymic function.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>T-cell receptor excision circle (TREC) level in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC)</measure>
    <time_frame>through 15 wk of age</time_frame>
    <description>Thymic T-cell production can be assessed by measuring signal-joint T cell receptor excision circles (TRECs) as a traceable molecular marker in newly produced naive T-cells. Thus, the content of TRECs in peripheral blood is an indicator of thymopoiesis or newly synthesized and exported naive T-cells. TREC assessment will be conducted in the stored peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) isolated from infant's blood by standard Ficoll density gradient methods.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>T-cell response to BCG (Bacillus Calmette-Guérin; to protect against tuberculosis) and oral polio virus (OPV) immunization</measure>
    <time_frame>through 15 wk of age</time_frame>
    <description>The Flow-cytometric Assay of Specific Cell-mediated Immune response in Activated whole blood (FASCIA) will be used on peripheral blood mononuclear cells to determine the percentage of CD4+ T cells that that are responsive to the BCG and OPV vaccines given at birth (OPV is given again at 6, 10 and 14 wk of age). The BCG response will be elicited using purified protein derivative of M. tuberculosis and the OPV response using formalin-inactivated polio virus antigen (types 1, 2 and 3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody response to oral polio virus (OPV) immunization</measure>
    <time_frame>through 15 wk of age</time_frame>
    <description>The antibody in lymphocyte supernatant (ALS) assay will be used to assess the production of polio-specific antibody by peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) at 15 wk of age and the secretory IgA response to OPV will be assessed at 6, 11 and 15 wk of age by measuring antibody in stool</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>T-cell and antibody response to tetanus toxoid (TT) and hepatitis B virus (HBV) vaccinations given at 6, 10 and 14 wk of age</measure>
    <time_frame>through 15 wk of age</time_frame>
    <description>The Flow-cytometric Assay of Specific Cell-mediated Immune response in Activated whole blood (FASCIA) will be used to measure the T-cell response to TT and HBV immunization using these vaccine antigens to stimulate a response at 6 and 15 wk of age. The antibody in lymphocyte supernatant assay (ALS) will be used to measure the antibody responses to these vaccines at 15 wk of age.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>bacterial translocation to blood</measure>
    <time_frame>through 15 wk of age</time_frame>
    <description>Bacterial lipopolysaccharide (LPS) concentrations will be measured in plasma as a marker of bacterial translocation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>vitamin A status by modified, relative dose-response (MRDR) test</measure>
    <time_frame>through 15 wk of age</time_frame>
    <description>vitamin A status will be measured using the MRDR in a subset of 30 subjects in each study arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>bulging fontanelle</measure>
    <time_frame>48 h after vitamin A dosing</time_frame>
    <description>The crainial fontanelle will be examined by study personnel to identify &quot;bulging&quot; as in indication of increased intracranial volume.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Vitamin A Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>50,000 IU vitamin A in edible oil</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>edible oil used as diluent for vitamin A</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>retinyl palmitate</intervention_name>
    <description>50,000 IU vitamin A in oil given within 48 h of birth from single-dose capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vitamin A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>edible oil used as diluent for vitamin A given within 48 h of birth from single-dose capsule identical in appearance to vitamin A capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infant receiving OPV and BCG within 48 hr of birth

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Mother is less than 18 years of age

          -  Infant is part of a multiple birth

          -  Infant will likely not remain in the study area for the next 4 months

          -  Infant has a condition precluding vaccination

          -  Infant is unable to breastfeed or drink other fluids

          -  Birth weight is less than 1.5 kg
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>48 Hours</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles B. Stephensen, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>USDA, Western Human Nutrition Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh (icddr,b)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dhaka</city>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bangladesh</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 14, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 24, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 22, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 22, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 26, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vitamin A deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin A</keyword>
  <keyword>retinyl palmitate</keyword>
  <keyword>malnutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>vaccination</keyword>
  <keyword>BCG</keyword>
  <keyword>tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>polio virus</keyword>
  <keyword>tetanus toxoid</keyword>
  <keyword>hepatitis B virus</keyword>
  <keyword>thymus</keyword>
  <keyword>T lymphocyte</keyword>
  <keyword>B lymphocyte</keyword>
  <keyword>antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>bacterial translocation</keyword>
  <keyword>T-cell receptor excision circle</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamin A Deficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Night Blindness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinol palmitate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

