<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01581762</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ChineseUHK</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01581762</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EUS-FNA With 22G Procore Needles vs 22G Conventional Needles</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Comparative Study on Endoscopic Ultrasonography (EUS) - Guided Fine-Needle Aspiration (FNA) Using the 22G Conventional Needles or Procore Needles Without Immediate On-site Cytopathologic Examination</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) is an important investigation
      tool to obtain tissue for diagnosis. Nowadays, the performance of EUS-FNA varies with
      accuracy rates ranging from 60% - 100%. Needles with different diameters have been explored
      to retrieve tissue specimens. The diagnostic yields, successful rates and safety profiles are
      similar. It has been suggested that although thinner needles provide less cellular material
      than do larger needles, the specimens from the former are less contaminated by blood, and
      thus easier to interpret. In addition, thinner needles may be easier to use because of
      greater flexibility, particularly for locations requiring important scope bending. As a
      result, a new 22G FNA needle has been designed in order to improve the tissue-sampling rate
      (ECHO-HD-22-C, Cook Endoscopy, USA). There is a reverse bevel at the tip of the new needle
      with promotes collection of core sample by shearing material from target lesion during
      retrograde movement of the needle in the lesion. The feasibility and safety of this newly
      design EUS-FNA needle have been demonstrated in a recent multicenter, pooled, cohort study
      using the 19G version. Successful puncture was technically feasible in 98.2% of cases and the
      overall accuracy of 92.9%. There were no complications related to the technique.

      The aim of this study is to compare the tissue-sampling rate and the diagnostic accuracy rate
      of EUS-FNA between the uses of the convention and newly designed 22-gauge needles.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) - guided fine needle aspiration (FNA) is a well-established
      technique for tissue sampling of intestinal and extra-intestinal mass lesions. The accuracy
      of EUS-guided FNA varies from 60% - 100% with a complication rate of 0% - 3%. The diagnostic
      accuracy of the procedure can be improved by the use immunohistochemical studies and genetic
      analyses.It may also be improved by obtaining a larger biopsy specimen with a core biopsy
      needle. However, puncturing with a core-biopsy needle may not be always feasible due to the
      technical difficulty of inserting the larger needle through the bended endoscope. As a
      result, the advantage of a core-biopsy needle on providing a larger amount of cellular
      material is offset by a higher rate of technical failures, especially in the setting of a
      transduodenal puncture. Recently, a new 22G FNA needle with a reverse bevel at the tip has
      become available (ECHO-HD-22-C, Cook Endoscopy, USA.). The design of the device promotes the
      collection of core samples by shearing material from target lesion during retrograde movement
      of the needle in the lesion. Hence, the aim of this study is to compare the tissue-sampling
      rate and the diagnostic accuracy rate of EUS-FNA using 22G conventional and Procore needles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with cyto-histopathology confirmed neoplasms diagnosed by EUS-guided FNA</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>A positive diagnosis of malignancy by an EUS biopsy specimen is accepted as a true positive. A benign diagnosis is confirmed by surgical tissue samples when available or clinical follow-up after 1 year.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>A positive diagnosis of malignancy by an EUS biopsy specimen is accepted as a true positive. A benign diagnosis is confirmed by surgical tissue samples when available or clinical follow-up after 1 year</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Self Efficacy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional 22G Needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Device: EUS-FNA with conventional 22G Needle</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>22G Procore Needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Device: EUS-FNA with 22G Procore Needle which has a reverse bevel at the tip of the needle to enhance tissue collection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EUS-guided FNA</intervention_name>
    <description>EUS-guided FNA with two types of needles - conventional 22G needle (Sham control) and Procore needle (active comparator)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional 22G Needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>22G Procore Needle</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ECHO-HD-22-C, Cook Endoscopy, USA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages of 18-80 undergoing EUS-guided tissue acquisition

          -  Informed consent available

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Coagulopathy

          -  Previous history of upper gastrointestinal surgery

          -  Contraindications for conscious sedation

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>CHARING C CHONG, MBChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Surgery, CUHK</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iglesias-Garcia J, Poley JW, Larghi A, Giovannini M, Petrone MC, Abdulkader I, Monges G, Costamagna G, Arcidiacono P, Biermann K, Rindi G, Bories E, Dogloni C, Bruno M, Dominguez-Muñoz JE. Feasibility and yield of a new EUS histology needle: results from a multicenter, pooled, cohort study. Gastrointest Endosc. 2011 Jun;73(6):1189-96. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2011.01.053. Epub 2011 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21420083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kida M. Pancreatic masses. Gastrointest Endosc. 2009 Feb;69(2 Suppl):S102-9. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.12.010. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19179132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gress F, Gottlieb K, Sherman S, Lehman G. Endoscopic ultrasonography-guided fine-needle aspiration biopsy of suspected pancreatic cancer. Ann Intern Med. 2001 Mar 20;134(6):459-64.</citation>
    <PMID>11255521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Toole D, Palazzo L, Arotçarena R, Dancour A, Aubert A, Hammel P, Amaris J, Ruszniewski P. Assessment of complications of EUS-guided fine-needle aspiration. Gastrointest Endosc. 2001 Apr;53(4):470-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11275888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yusuf TE, Ho S, Pavey DA, Michael H, Gress FG. Retrospective analysis of the utility of endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) in pancreatic masses, using a 22-gauge or 25-gauge needle system: a multicenter experience. Endoscopy. 2009 May;41(5):445-8. doi: 10.1055/s-0029-1214643. Epub 2009 May 5. Erratum in: Endoscopy. 2009 Jun;41(6):509.</citation>
    <PMID>19418399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Itoi T, Itokawa F, Kurihara T, Sofuni A, Tsuchiya T, Ishii K, Tsuji S, Ikeuchi N, Kawai T, Moriyasu F. Experimental endoscopy: objective evaluation of EUS needles. Gastrointest Endosc. 2009 Mar;69(3 Pt 1):509-16. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.07.017.</citation>
    <PMID>19231491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yun SS, Remotti H, Vazquez MF, Crapanzano JP, Saqi A. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided biopsies of pancreatic masses: comparison between fine needle aspirations and needle core biopsies. Diagn Cytopathol. 2007 May;35(5):276-82.</citation>
    <PMID>17427217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fritscher-Ravens A, Topalidis T, Bobrowski C, Krause C, Thonke E, Jäckle S, Soehendra N. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration in focal pancreatic lesions: a prospective intraindividual comparison of two needle assemblies. Endoscopy. 2001 Jun;33(6):484-90.</citation>
    <PMID>11437040</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Savides TJ, Donohue M, Hunt G, Al-Haddad M, Aslanian H, Ben-Menachem T, Chen VK, Coyle W, Deutsch J, DeWitt J, Dhawan M, Eckardt A, Eloubeidi M, Esker A, Gordon SR, Gress F, Ikenberry S, Joyce AM, Klapman J, Lo S, Maluf-Filho F, Nickl N, Singh V, Wills J, Behling C. EUS-guided FNA diagnostic yield of malignancy in solid pancreatic masses: a benchmark for quality performance measurement. Gastrointest Endosc. 2007 Aug;66(2):277-82.</citation>
    <PMID>17643700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harewood GC, Wiersema MJ. Endosonography-guided fine needle aspiration biopsy in the evaluation of pancreatic masses. Am J Gastroenterol. 2002 Jun;97(6):1386-91.</citation>
    <PMID>12094855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eloubeidi MA, Chen VK, Eltoum IA, Jhala D, Chhieng DC, Jhala N, Vickers SM, Wilcox CM. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine needle aspiration biopsy of patients with suspected pancreatic cancer: diagnostic accuracy and acute and 30-day complications. Am J Gastroenterol. 2003 Dec;98(12):2663-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14687813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 16, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Charing Chong, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>EUS, FNA</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

