<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01710423</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-009579</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01710423</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Peer-mentored Cooking Classes for Parents of Toddlers: Do Families Cook More and Eat Healthier After the Intervention?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Home Food Preparation Practices Among Families With Young Children: A Peer Mentoring Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to test the effectiveness of a community-located, peer mentored intervention
      to improve home food preparation practices in families with young children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Barriers to healthy eating and active living are at the heart of the obesity epidemic. This
      study focuses on a key factor underlying healthy eating: home food preparation. Preparing
      food at home entails a sequence of steps from obtaining food, to planning and cooking or
      preparing meals, to finally serving and eating the meal. Many strategies to curb obesity in
      children focus on eliminating processed and fast food from the diet, as well as improving
      access to fresh produce and other healthy ingredients. A collective ability to regularly and
      reliably prepare healthy food at home is implicit in these and other prevention strategies.
      Little research, however, has grappled with the phenomenon that there has been a generational
      loss of home food preparation ability over the past few decades. What is urgently needed is
      to design effective, enticing, and scalable interventions to improve home food preparation
      practices across diverse groups.

      This study aims to test the effectiveness of a community-located, peer mentored intervention
      to improve home food preparation practices in families with young children. The investigators
      will partner with Children's Hospital of Philadelphia Early Head Start, a community-based
      organization serving families with children ages 0 to 3 years in West Philadelphia, aiming
      specifically to:

        1. Use the principles of Community Based Participatory Research (CBPR) to design, evaluate
           and disseminate a peer mentored intervention aimed at improving home food preparation
           practices among families with young children.

        2. Conduct a randomized controlled trial with a delayed entry control group to test the
           effect of the intervention on three outcomes: home food preparation practices,
           healthfulness of the diet, and cooking-related self-efficacy.

      The investigators hypothesize that families participating in this intervention will
      demonstrate improvement in parental self-efficacy related to cooking, home food preparation
      practices, and the healthfulness of parents' and toddlers' diets post-intervention, compared
      to families who do not participate in the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Frequency Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>23 weeks from Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be the change in healthfulness of the diet as measured by food frequency questionnaires for participants through the course of the study. Study staff will meet with each participant and ask them to answer questions about the frequency of their food and beverage consumption over the course of a 12 month period. The results will be analyzed for consumption of specific food-groups (fruits, vegetables, whole grains, dairy, etc.). The primary endpoint is the difference in the healthfulness of the diet between the immediate intervention group and the control group at week 23.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cooking-related self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>23 weeks from Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Self-efficacy related to cooking will be measured using a 25-item instrument. We will assess to assess the difference between the immediate intervention group and the control group at week 23.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Home food preparation practices</measure>
    <time_frame>23 weeks from Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Home food preparation practices will be measured using questions from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey. We will measure the difference in home food preparation practices between the immediate intervention group and the control group at week 23.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>41 weeks from Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure the change in parent and child body mass index before and after the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Peer mentoring intervention ('Cooking with Friends')</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Entry Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peer mentoring intervention ('Cooking with Friends')</intervention_name>
    <description>'Cooking with Friends' is a community-located, peer mentoring intervention aimed at improving home food preparation practices in families with young children.
The intervention was developed in an iterative, community-based research approach, and will be conducted in partnership with Early Head Start (EHS) at The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia. Cooking with Friends builds on existing monthly cooking classes at EHS that have proven popular with EHS families. Through 5 weekly classes, this intervention will explore topics of how to prepare healthy foods at home.
The peer mentoring component is a novel innovation to this intervention. The intervention pairs peer mentors to individual mentees in a community setting, to effect behavioral change among caregivers of young children.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Mentee Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Eligible mentees will be caregivers of 0-3 year old children who are enrolled in Early
             Head Start at The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP EHS) at the time of
             recruitment.

          2. Caregiver enrollment in CHOP EHS requires the following:

               1. Children are 0-3 years old (Expectant mothers are also eligible to enroll)

               2. The family has an income at or below federal poverty level

               3. The family lives in West Philadelphia, within the geographic area served by CHOP
                  EHS.

          3. Caregiver is able to give informed consent.

        Mentor Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Eligible peer mentors should meet the inclusion criteria set for above for mentees.

          2. The study team, in conjunction with EHS staff, will decide which participants will be
             invited to be peer mentors, based on attributes including interest, leadership
             ability, and home food preparation skills.

        Children Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 0-3 year old children of mentee caregivers enrolled in the study

          2. If a mentee caregiver has more than one child currently enrolled in CHOP EHS, then all
             their eligible children will be enrolled in the study.

          3. If there are expectant mothers who are enrolled as mentees, their children will be
             enrolled in the study upon delivery.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Caregivers and children not meeting the inclusion criteria above.

          2. Subjects who, in the opinion of the Investigator, may be unable to participate in the
             study schedules or procedures.

          3. Children of peer mentors will not be eligible for this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Senbagam Virudachalam, MD, MSHP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 19, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Home Food Preparation</keyword>
  <keyword>Peer Mentoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Early Head Start</keyword>
  <keyword>Cooking</keyword>
  <keyword>Diet</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

