<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01710891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSR 11-3338</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01710891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Laryngoscope Versus CMAC for Endotracheal Intubation in Patients Undergoing Emergent Airway Management</brief_title>
  <official_title>Laryngoscope Versus CMAC for Endotracheal Intubation in Patients Undergoing Emergent Airway Management</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Minneapolis Medical Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Minneapolis Medical Research Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomized controlled trial of intubation using the C-MAC video laryngoscope versus standard
      laryngoscopy. Patients who are going to be intubated using standard laryngoscopy will be
      randomized to have their first intubation attempt done using either standard laryngoscopy or
      the C-MAC video laryngoscope. Subsequent attempts will be at the discretion of the treating
      physician.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Experimental Design and Methods:

      This will be a prospective randomized controlled trial of intubation using the C-MAC video
      laryngoscope versus standard laryngoscopy for patients requiring emergent intubation in the
      Emergency Department.

      Study Setting and Population:

      This study will be performed at an urban county medical center with approximately 97,000
      patient visits per year. Adult patients (age &gt;17) requiring intubation will be enrolled.

      Study Protocol:

      All ED patients who are unable to adequately breathe on their own requiring emergent
      intubation for airway management will be screened for inclusion in the study. Identified
      patients will be deemed eligible when the need for intubation has been determined by the
      treating physician. Eligible patients will be placed on capnograph, cardiac, blood pressure
      and pulse oximetry monitors. Patients will be randomly assigned to be intubated using
      standard laryngoscopy with the C-MAC blade or C-MAC videolaryngoscope. Sealed envelopes
      containing the randomization assignment for the treatment groups will be kept at the
      patient's bedside in the stabilization room. Patients will be monitored by oxygen saturation,
      blood pressure, heart rate, and respiratory rate, which are typical for patients requiring
      intubation in our ED. Data will be recorded every minute by a trained research assistant at
      the patient's bedside. The lowest oxygen saturation during the procedure will be recorded for
      determination of hypoxia. Hypoxia will be defined as an oxygen saturation &lt;93%. The number of
      attempts made to intubate and the total time to successful intubation will be recorded. An
      attempt starts when the intubating device enters the patients mouth and ends when the
      endotracheal tube placement is confirmed or when a new intubating device is put in the
      patients mouth after the previous device had been removed. Data collection includes the
      timing and number of breaths given via Bag-Valve-Mask and patient repositioning between the
      attempts. All treatments will be recorded. Data collection will continue until the patient is
      discharged from the Emergency Department. The patient's diagnosis at the time of discharge
      from the ED will be recorded. Patients' charts will be reviewed to determine the diagnosis,
      occurrence of aspiration pneumonia, ICU length of stay, and inpatient length of stay. Two
      attempts will be made to contact patients 28 days after study enrollment to determine their
      condition at that time.

      Data Analysis:

      Data will be collected by a designated research assistant during the procedure and will then
      be entered into an EXCEL (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, WA) database for storage. Data will be
      exported into STATA 10.0 (STATA Corp., College Station, TX) for further analysis. The number
      of attempts to successful intubation and total time to intubation will be compared using
      descriptive statistics. Occurrence of hypoxia and aspiration pneumonia will be compared in
      patients who were intubated with the C-MAC to patients intubated with standard laryngoscopy
      using Chi-Square tests. Oxygen saturation, ETCO2, and heart rate will be compared in both
      groups using multiple linear regression.

      The length of stay and 28 day follow up between the two groups will be compared using
      Wilcoxon rank sum tests. In order to detect a 15% difference in the length of stay between
      the two groups, with a power of 80% and an alpha of 0.05, 100 patients will be required in
      each group for a total of 200 patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Attempts Until Successful Intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>During intubation procedure up to 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>An attempt is counted as the intubating device entering the patients mouth until it is removed. Intubation success is defined as the endotracheal tube being placed in the patients lungs as confirmed by auscultation and end tidal carbon dioxide</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time the first device entered the patients mouth until succsessful intubation up to 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>The time in seconds from the time at which the intubating device is first placed in the patient's mouth until the time of successful intubation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of hospital admission until discharge up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The time in days from hospital admission until discharge, divided into time in the intensive care unit and total time in the hospital</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aspiration Pneumonia</measure>
    <time_frame>from the time of hospital admission up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The occurrence of aspiration pneumonia as defined by the clinical diagnosis in the patients chart and or radiographic determination of aspiration during the 28 days after the intubation procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Hypoxia</measure>
    <time_frame>From the start of the procedure until successful intubation up to 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Oxygen saturations will be recorded during the procedure, oxygen saturation less than 93% will be considered an occurrence of hypoxia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Failed Intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>from the start of the procedure until sucessful intubation up to one hour</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the operator switching to an alternate device or intubation technique after at least one unsuccessful intubation attempt.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Respiratory Distress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Direct Laryngoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo their first intubation attempt with direct laryngoscopy using the CMAC device without video assistance. The video monitor with be covered with a hood.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CMAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo their first intubation attempt using the CMAC videolaryngoscope using video assistance</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CMAC videolaryngoscope</intervention_name>
    <description>patients are intubated using the CMAC video laryngoscope</description>
    <arm_group_label>CMAC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Direct Laryngoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients undergo their first intubation attempt using direct laryngoscopy with a C-MAC device with the video display covered with a hood.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Direct Laryngoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients (age &gt;17) requiring emergent endotracheal intubation in the Emergency
             Department using direct laryngoscopy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Physician intends to intubate with a device other than a direct laryngoscope
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James R Miner, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Minneapolis Medical Research Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hennepin County Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55415</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 17, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 19, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 25, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>endotracheal intubation</keyword>
  <keyword>direct laryngoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>video laryngoscopy</keyword>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>February 18, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>March 15, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>August 24, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>October 17, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>June 26, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>January 31, 2018</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

