<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01711528</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2012-01737</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01737</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC1113</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI 9157</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000741989</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC1113</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9157</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015083</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA167511</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA069912</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1CA186686</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1CA186716</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01711528</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT02668731</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dinaciclib, Bortezomib, and Dexamethasone in Treating Patients With Relapsed Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Clinical Trial of a Novel CDK Inhibitor Dinaciclib (SCH 727965) in Combination With Bortezomib and Dexamethasone in Relapsed Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of dinaciclib and bortezomib when
      given together with dexamethasone in treating patients with multiple myeloma that has
      returned after a period of improvement. Dinaciclib and bortezomib may stop the growth of
      cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Drugs used in
      chemotherapy, such as dexamethasone, work in different ways to stop the growth of cancer
      cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by stopping them from
      spreading. Giving dinaciclib and bortezomib together with dexamethasone may kill more cancer
      cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the maximally tolerated doses of dinaciclib and bortezomib, when used in
      combination, in two different schedules, for treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the toxicities associated with dinaciclib and bortezomib, when used in
      combination, for treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma.

      II. To determine the overall response rate associated with dinaciclib and bortezomib, when
      used in combination, for treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma.

      III. To explore the differences in toxicity associated with two different schedules of
      dinaciclib and bortezomib used in combination.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To examine if expression levels of target cyclin dependent kinase (CDK): CDK 2,5,7 and 9
      levels in cluster of differentiation (CD)138-purified tumor cells, will be correlated with
      response (clinical and molecular) to determine if high or low level target CDK expression, if
      present, influences dinaciclib efficacy.

      II. To examine if immunoglobulin (Ig)H translocation status, P53 status and presence of v-myc
      myelocytomatosis viral oncogene homolog (avian) (Myc) amplification or rearrangement,
      determined on patient bone marrow before treatment, using a pre validated fluorescence in
      situ hybridization (FISH) panel to identify common myeloma translocations, will be correlated
      with molecular and/or clinical markers of drug activity, and to assess if specific genetic
      subgroups of myeloma tumors are responsive or resistant.

      III. To determine the gene expression profiles of myeloma cells before and after treatment to
      understand the role of tumor gene dysregulation and/or dinaciclib induced effects on
      transcription.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of dinaciclib and bortezomib. Patients are assigned
      to 1 of 2 treatment schedules.

      SCHEDULE I: Patients receive dinaciclib intravenously (IV) over 2 hours and bortezomib
      subcutaneously (SC) or IV (if patients do not tolerate SC injection) on days 1, 8, and 15 and
      dexamethasone orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1, 2, 8, 9, 15, and 16. Courses repeat
      every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      SCHEDULE II: Patients receive dinaciclib IV over 2 hours on day 1; bortezomib SC on days 1
      and 8; and dexamethasone PO QD on days 1, 2, 8, and 9. Courses repeat every 21 days in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days and 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 19, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 22, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 22, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of dinaciclib and bortezomib when given together with dexamethasone, based on the incidence of dose-limiting toxicity (DLT), graded according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>MTD is defined as the dose level below the lowest dose that induces DLT in at least one-third of patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events, graded according to NCT CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number and severity of all adverse events (overall, by dose-level, and by tumor group) will be tabulated and summarized in this patient population. Toxicity is defined as adverse events that are classified as possibly, probably, or definitely related to study treatment. Overall toxicity incidence as well as toxicity profiles by dose level, patient and tumor site will be explored and summarized. Frequency distributions, graphical techniques and other descriptive measures will form the basis of these analyses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Responses will be summarized by simple descriptive summary statistics delineating complete and partial responses as well as stable and progressive disease in this patient population (overall and by tumor group).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Summarized descriptively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to treatment failure</measure>
    <time_frame>From registration to documentation of progression, unacceptable toxicity, or refusal to continue participation by the patients, assessed up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Summarized descriptively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time until hematologic nadirs (absolute neutrophil count, platelets, hemoglobin)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Summarized descriptively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Plasma Cell Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule I (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive dinaciclib IV over 2 hours and bortezomib SC or IV (if patients do not tolerate SC injection) on days 1, 8, and 15 and dexamethasone PO QD on days 1, 2, 8, 9, 15, and 16. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule II (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive dinaciclib IV over 2 hours on day 1; bortezomib SC on days 1 and 8; and dexamethasone PO QD on days 1, 2, 8, and 9. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule I (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule II (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>[(1R)-3-Methyl-1-[[(2S)-1-oxo-3-phenyl-2-[(pyrazinylcarbonyl)amino]propyl]amino]butyl]boronic Acid</other_name>
    <other_name>LDP 341</other_name>
    <other_name>MLN341</other_name>
    <other_name>PS-341</other_name>
    <other_name>PS341</other_name>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule I (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule II (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aacidexam</other_name>
    <other_name>Adexone</other_name>
    <other_name>Aknichthol Dexa</other_name>
    <other_name>Alba-Dex</other_name>
    <other_name>Alin</other_name>
    <other_name>Alin Depot</other_name>
    <other_name>Alin Oftalmico</other_name>
    <other_name>Amplidermis</other_name>
    <other_name>Anemul mono</other_name>
    <other_name>Auricularum</other_name>
    <other_name>Auxiloson</other_name>
    <other_name>Baycuten</other_name>
    <other_name>Baycuten N</other_name>
    <other_name>Cortidexason</other_name>
    <other_name>Cortisumman</other_name>
    <other_name>Decacort</other_name>
    <other_name>Decadrol</other_name>
    <other_name>Decadron</other_name>
    <other_name>Decalix</other_name>
    <other_name>Decameth</other_name>
    <other_name>Decasone R.p.</other_name>
    <other_name>Dectancyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Dekacort</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltafluorene</other_name>
    <other_name>Deronil</other_name>
    <other_name>Desamethasone</other_name>
    <other_name>Desameton</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexa-Mamallet</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexa-Rhinosan</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexa-Scheroson</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexa-sine</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexacortal</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexacortin</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexafarma</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexafluorene</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexalocal</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexamecortin</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexameth</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexamethasonum</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexamonozon</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexapos</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexinoral</other_name>
    <other_name>Dexone</other_name>
    <other_name>Dinormon</other_name>
    <other_name>Fluorodelta</other_name>
    <other_name>Fortecortin</other_name>
    <other_name>Gammacorten</other_name>
    <other_name>Hexadecadrol</other_name>
    <other_name>Hexadrol</other_name>
    <other_name>Lokalison-F</other_name>
    <other_name>Loverine</other_name>
    <other_name>Methylfluorprednisolone</other_name>
    <other_name>Millicorten</other_name>
    <other_name>Mymethasone</other_name>
    <other_name>Orgadrone</other_name>
    <other_name>Spersadex</other_name>
    <other_name>Visumetazone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dinaciclib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule I (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule II (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CDK Inhibitor SCH 727965</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-7965</other_name>
    <other_name>SCH 727965</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule I (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Schedule II (dinaciclib, bortezomib, dexamethasone)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 2.5 mg/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1000/uL

          -  Untransfused platelet count &gt;= 75000/uL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 times institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Patients with relapsed multiple myeloma who have already received one or more standard
             treatment regimens

          -  Measurable disease of multiple myeloma as defined by at least ONE of the following:

               -  Serum monoclonal protein &gt;= 1 g/dL

               -  &gt;= 200 mg of monoclonal protein in the urine on 24 hour electrophoresis

               -  Serum immunoglobulin free light chain &gt;= 10 mg/dL and abnormal serum
                  immunoglobulin kappa to lambda free light chain ratio

               -  Monoclonal bone marrow plasmacytosis &gt;= 30% (evaluable disease)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0, 1 or 2

          -  Adequate residual organ function per treating physician discretion; Note: there is no
             limit with regard to the number of prior therapies

          -  Provide informed written consent

          -  Negative pregnancy test done =&lt; 7 days prior to registration, for women of
             childbearing potential only

          -  Willing to provide samples for correlative research purposes

          -  Willing to return to consenting institution for follow-up during the study

          -  Recovered (i.e., =&lt; grade 1 toxicity) from the reversible effects of prior
             antineoplastic therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any of the following recent therapies:

               -  Alkylators (e.g. melphalan, cyclophosphamide) =&lt; 14 days prior to registration

               -  Anthracyclines =&lt; 14 days prior to registration

               -  High dose corticosteroids, immune modulatory drugs (thalidomide or lenalidomide),
                  or proteosome inhibitors (bortezomib) =&lt; 7 days prior to registration

          -  Concomitant high dose corticosteroids (concurrent use of corticosteroids); EXCEPTION:
             patients may be on chronic steroids (maximum dose 20 mg/day prednisone equivalent) if
             they are being given for disorders other than amyloid, i.e., adrenal insufficiency,
             rheumatoid arthritis, etc.

          -  Other active malignancy =&lt; 2 years prior to registration; EXCEPTIONS: non-melanotic
             skin cancer or carcinoma in-situ of the cervix; NOTE: if there is a history of prior
             malignancy, they must not be receiving other specific treatment for their cancer

          -  Any of the following:

               -  Pregnant women or women of reproductive ability who are unwilling to use 2
                  effective methods of contraception from the time of signing the informed consent
                  form through 30 days after the last dose of study drug

               -  Nursing women

               -  Men who are unwilling to use a condom (even if they have undergone a prior
                  vasectomy) while having intercourse with any woman, while taking the drug and for
                  30 days after stopping treatment

          -  Other co-morbidity which would interfere with patient's ability to participate in
             trial, e.g. uncontrolled infection, uncompensated heart or lung disease

          -  Other concurrent chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or any ancillary therapy considered
             investigational; NOTE: bisphosphonates are considered to be supportive care rather
             than therapy, and are thus allowed while on protocol treatment

          -  Peripheral neuropathy &gt;= grade 2 on clinical examination during the screening period

          -  Major surgery =&lt; 14 days prior to registration

          -  Currently taking strong or moderate inhibitors/inducers of cytochrome P450, family 3,
             subfamily A, polypeptide 4 (CYP3A4); Note: dinaciclib is a CYP3A4 substrate; patients
             should not take grapefruit/grapefruit juice or St. John's wort; use of strong or
             moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors is prohibited from &lt; 7 days prior to registration; use of
             CYP3A4 inducers is prohibited from =&lt; 7 days prior to registration

          -  Any of the following conditions:

               -  Myocardial infarction =&lt; 6 months prior to registration or has New York Heart
                  Association (NYHA) class III or IV heart failure

               -  Uncontrolled angina

               -  Severe uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias

               -  Electrocardiographic evidence of acute ischemia

               -  Active conduction system abnormalities; NOTE: prior to study entry, any
                  electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormality at screening must be documented by the
                  investigator as not medically relevant

          -  Known hypersensitivity to bortezomib, boron, or mannitol

          -  Serious medical or psychiatric illness likely to interfere with participation in this
             clinical study per the judgment of the treating physician
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shaji Kumar</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University/Massey Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Hospital and Clinics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aspirus UW Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wisconsin Rapids</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>54494</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 18, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 22, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

