<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02707991</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00081068</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02707991</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nurse Case Management to Improve Hepatitis C Care in HIV Co-infection</brief_title>
  <acronym>Care2Cure</acronym>
  <official_title>Nurse Case Management to Improve Linkage to Hepatitis C Care and Treatment Initiation in HIV Co-infection: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Effective all-oral medications are finally available to cure hepatitis C virus, which affects
      more than 4 million Americans and one-in-four people living with HIV. However, many barriers
      exist that prevent people with HIV/HCV co-infection from getting this curative treatment,
      including low knowledge, competing demands, and drug interactions with HIV medications.

      This study evaluates if a hepatitis C nurse case management intervention in an HIV primary
      care clinic will improve patient attendance to hepatitis C care and help people start
      hepatitis C treatment earlier. Half of the participants will receive brief case management
      with a nurse, while the other half will receive usual clinic care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatitis C virus (HCV) is a leading cause of liver cancer and HCV-related liver disease is
      among the most common causes of non-AIDS related death among people living with HIV (PLWH).
      One quarter of PLWH in the U.S. are co-infected with HCV, which leads to a 3-fold increase in
      progression to end stage liver disease and liver cancer. HCV can be cured, but less than half
      of PLWH with chronic HCV in the U.S. have linked to HCV care, and about 7% initiated
      treatment. Poor treatment initiation rates historically have been due to low efficacy among
      PLWH, but HCV care now is at a turning point. The investigators have the ability to
      substantially decrease HCV-related morbidity and mortality in PLWH with the availability of
      effective all-oral treatment. As patients are funneled into HCV care, improving the process
      of linkage to care and treatment preparation related to HIV medication modifications
      necessary for current HCV regimens is essential to maximize the lifesaving potential of
      available therapies among PLWH.

      There are several barriers to linkage to HCV care and treatment. HCV is a &quot;silent epidemic&quot;
      often presenting no symptoms for 20 years. Knowledge about HCV and its available therapies is
      also low and lags behind new advancements in HCV treatment. Competing work, school and
      caregiving demands has also historically led to low motivation to engage in HCV care. For
      PLWH who are linked to HCV care, drug interactions between new HCV therapies and HIV
      treatment regimens introduce a new barrier to HCV treatment initiation. Up to 88% of PLWH
      will need to switch their HIV treatment regimen to avoid contraindicated drug interactions.
      The April 8, 2015 Guidelines for the Use of Antiretroviral Agents in HIV-1-infected Adults
      and Adolescents emphasize the need to modify HIV regimens to treat HCV in many PLWH. But
      modifying HIV treatment regimens can have severe negative consequences, including decreased
      quality of life, increased symptom burden, and loss of viral suppression.

      Interventions that both increase HCV knowledge and support HIV treatment modifications in the
      setting of drug interactions are needed to improve linkage to HCV care and decrease time to
      treatment initiation. In similar settings and populations, nurse case management
      interventions have been shown to improve these outcomes. However, few of these interventions
      have been rigorously tested in the context of HCV.

      This study is a randomized, single-blinded controlled trial to test whether a nurse case
      management intervention will improve the HCV treatment cascade among PLWH in an HIV primary
      care setting compared to usual care.

      Specifically, this study aims to:

        1. Test whether a nurse case management intervention will increase linkage to the Viral
           Hepatitis Clinic among persons with HIV/HCV co-infection compared to usual care;
           Hypothesis: A higher proportion of those who are randomized to the intervention arm will
           attend the Viral Hepatitis Clinic within 60 days of randomization compared to those who
           receive usual care.

        2. Determine if a nurse case management intervention will decrease time to HCV treatment
           initiation among persons with HIV/HCV co-infection compared to usual care; Hypothesis:
           Those who are randomized to the intervention arm will have a decreased time to HCV
           treatment initiation from the point of randomization compared to those who receive usual
           care.

        3. Describe the characteristics associated with uptake of HCV care among people living with
           HIV, controlling for covariates; Research question 2.1: What patient-level
           characteristics are associated with increased uptake of HCV care?; Research question
           2.2: Compared to the known historical barriers to engaging in HCV care, what factors
           continue to be associated with uptake of HCV care in the new paradigm of HCV treatment
           for people living with HIV?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Linkage to care</measure>
    <time_frame>60 days</time_frame>
    <description>Attendance at a Viral Hepatitis Clinic appointment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to hepatitis C treatment initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days from study enrollment to receipt of the first dose of HCV treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis C, Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual clinic appointment process plus receipt of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Hepatitis C Fact Sheet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nurse Case Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nurse-initiated hepatitis C clinic referral, strengths-based education, patient navigation, appointment reminders, and care coordination of HIV/hepatitis C drug-drug interaction prevention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nurse Case Management</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive one baseline nurse case management study visit in addition to appointment reminders one week and one day before the scheduled hepatitis clinic appointment. Those who link to the Viral Hepatitis Clinic and are identified as eligible to start hepatitis C therapy by their health care provider will have one additional study visit with the nurse case manager to coordinate drug-drug interaction prevention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nurse Case Management</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Care Coordination</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV infection

          -  Chronic hepatitis C infection

          -  Did not attend a hepatitis C specialty appointment in the past year

          -  Able to speak English

          -  Current patient at the John G. Bartlett Specialty Practice at Johns Hopkins Hospital
             (at least 1 visit in the past year)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Emergency medical care needed

          -  Unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jason E Farley, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.cdc.gov/hiv/pdf/library/factsheets/hiv-viral-hepatitis.pdf</url>
    <description>CDC HIV and Viral Hepatitis Fact Sheet</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.aidsinfo.nih.gov/ContentFiles/AdultandAdolescentGL.pdf</url>
    <description>Guidelines for the Use of Antiretroviral Agents in HIV-1-infected Adults and Adolescents, 2015</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://hcvguidelines.org</url>
    <description>AASLD/IDSA Recommendations for Testing, Managing, and Treating Hepatitis C</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://mmcp.health.maryland.gov/pap/docs/Clinical%20Criteria%20for%20Hepatitis%20C%208_8_17.pdf</url>
    <description>Maryland Department of Health Clinical Criteria for Hepatitis C (HCV) Therapy</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yehia BR, Schranz AJ, Umscheid CA, Lo Re V 3rd. The treatment cascade for chronic hepatitis C virus infection in the United States: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One. 2014 Jul 2;9(7):e101554. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0101554. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24988388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel N, Nasiri M, Koroglu A, Amin R, McGuey L, McNutt LA, Roman M, Miller C. Prevalence of drug-drug interactions upon addition of simeprevir- or sofosbuvir-containing treatment to medication profiles of patients with HIV and hepatitis C coinfection. AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses. 2015 Feb;31(2):189-97. doi: 10.1089/AID.2014.0215. Epub 2015 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25432275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cachay ER, Hill L, Ballard C, Colwell B, Torriani F, Wyles D, Mathews WC. Increasing Hepatitis C treatment uptake among HIV-infected patients using an HIV primary care model. AIDS Res Ther. 2013 Mar 28;10(1):9. doi: 10.1186/1742-6405-10-9.</citation>
    <PMID>23537147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ly KN, Xing J, Klevens RM, Jiles RB, Ward JW, Holmberg SD. The increasing burden of mortality from viral hepatitis in the United States between 1999 and 2007. Ann Intern Med. 2012 Feb 21;156(4):271-8. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-156-4-201202210-00004. Erratum in: Ann Intern Med. 2012 Jun 5;156(11):840.</citation>
    <PMID>22351712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lo Re V 3rd, Kallan MJ, Tate JP, Localio AR, Lim JK, Goetz MB, Klein MB, Rimland D, Rodriguez-Barradas MC, Butt AA, Gibert CL, Brown ST, Park L, Dubrow R, Reddy KR, Kostman JR, Strom BL, Justice AC. Hepatic decompensation in antiretroviral-treated patients co-infected with HIV and hepatitis C virus compared with hepatitis C virus-monoinfected patients: a cohort study. Ann Intern Med. 2014 Mar 18;160(6):369-79. doi: 10.7326/M13-1829.</citation>
    <PMID>24723077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas DL. Cure of hepatitis C virus infection without interferon alfa: scientific basis and current clinical evidence. Top Antivir Med. 2014 Jan;21(5):152-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24531555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehta SH, Genberg BL, Astemborski J, Kavasery R, Kirk GD, Vlahov D, Strathdee SA, Thomas DL. Limited uptake of hepatitis C treatment among injection drug users. J Community Health. 2008 Jun;33(3):126-33. doi: 10.1007/s10900-007-9083-3.</citation>
    <PMID>18165889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Afdhal NH, Zeuzem S, Schooley RT, Thomas DL, Ward JW, Litwin AH, Razavi H, Castera L, Poynard T, Muir A, Mehta SH, Dee L, Graham C, Church DR, Talal AH, Sulkowski MS, Jacobson IM; New Paradigm of HCV Therapy Meeting Participants. The new paradigm of hepatitis C therapy: integration of oral therapies into best practices. J Viral Hepat. 2013 Nov;20(11):745-60. doi: 10.1111/jvh.12173. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24168254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris M, Rhodes T. Hepatitis C treatment access and uptake for people who inject drugs: a review mapping the role of social factors. Harm Reduct J. 2013 May 7;10:7. doi: 10.1186/1477-7517-10-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23651646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swan D, Long J, Carr O, Flanagan J, Irish H, Keating S, Keaveney M, Lambert J, McCormick PA, McKiernan S, Moloney J, Perry N, Cullen W. Barriers to and facilitators of hepatitis C testing, management, and treatment among current and former injecting drug users: a qualitative exploration. AIDS Patient Care STDS. 2010 Dec;24(12):753-62. doi: 10.1089/apc.2010.0142.</citation>
    <PMID>21138381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Munoz-Plaza CE, Strauss S, Astone-Twerell J, Jarlais DD, Gwadz M, Hagan H, Osborne A, Rosenblum A. Exploring drug users' attitudes and decisions regarding hepatitis C (HCV) treatment in the U.S. Int J Drug Policy. 2008 Feb;19(1):71-8. doi: 10.1016/j.drugpo.2007.02.003. Epub 2007 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>18312822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fusfeld L, Aggarwal J, Dougher C, Vera-Llonch M, Bubb S, Donepudi M, Goss TF. Assessment of motivating factors associated with the initiation and completion of treatment for chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection. BMC Infect Dis. 2013 May 23;13:234. doi: 10.1186/1471-2334-13-234.</citation>
    <PMID>23701894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wagner G, Osilla KC, Garnett J, Ghosh-Dastidar B, Bhatti L, Witt M, Goetz MB. Provider and patient correlates of provider decisions to recommend HCV treatment to HIV co-infected patients. J Int Assoc Physicians AIDS Care (Chic). 2012 Jul-Aug;11(4):245-51. doi: 10.1177/1545109712444163. Epub 2012 May 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22564797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rockstroh JK. Optimal therapy of HIV/HCV co-infected patients with direct acting antivirals. Liver Int. 2015 Jan;35 Suppl 1:51-5. doi: 10.1111/liv.12721. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25529087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen EY, North CS, Fatunde O, Bernstein I, Salari S, Day B, Jain MK. Knowledge and attitudes about hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection and its treatment in HCV mono-infected and HCV/HIV co-infected adults. J Viral Hepat. 2013 Oct;20(10):708-14. doi: 10.1111/jvh.12095. Epub 2013 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24010645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Craw JA, Gardner LI, Marks G, Rapp RC, Bosshart J, Duffus WA, Rossman A, Coughlin SL, Gruber D, Safford LA, Overton J, Schmitt K. Brief strengths-based case management promotes entry into HIV medical care: results of the antiretroviral treatment access study-II. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2008 Apr 15;47(5):597-606. doi: 10.1097/QAI.0b013e3181684c51.</citation>
    <PMID>18285714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gardner LI, Metsch LR, Anderson-Mahoney P, Loughlin AM, del Rio C, Strathdee S, Sansom SL, Siegal HA, Greenberg AE, Holmberg SD; Antiretroviral Treatment and Access Study Study Group. Efficacy of a brief case management intervention to link recently diagnosed HIV-infected persons to care. AIDS. 2005 Mar 4;19(4):423-31.</citation>
    <PMID>15750396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tyler D, Nyamathi A, Stein JA, Koniak-Griffin D, Hodge F, Gelberg L. Increasing hepatitis C knowledge among homeless adults: results of a community-based, interdisciplinary intervention. J Behav Health Serv Res. 2014 Jan;41(1):37-49. doi: 10.1007/s11414-013-9333-3.</citation>
    <PMID>23616250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gupta K, Romney D, Briggs M, Benker K. Effects of a brief educational program on knowledge and willingness to accept treatment among patients with hepatitis C at inner-city hospitals. J Community Health. 2007 Aug;32(4):221-30.</citation>
    <PMID>17696047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holtzman CW, Shea JA, Glanz K, Jacobs LM, Gross R, Hines J, Mounzer K, Samuel R, Metlay JP, Yehia BR. Mapping patient-identified barriers and facilitators to retention in HIV care and antiretroviral therapy adherence to Andersen's Behavioral Model. AIDS Care. 2015;27(7):817-28. doi: 10.1080/09540121.2015.1009362. Epub 2015 Feb 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25671515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finitsis DJ, Pellowski JA, Johnson BT. Text message intervention designs to promote adherence to antiretroviral therapy (ART): a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. PLoS One. 2014 Feb 5;9(2):e88166. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0088166. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24505411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andersen RM. Revisiting the behavioral model and access to medical care: does it matter? J Health Soc Behav. 1995 Mar;36(1):1-10.</citation>
    <PMID>7738325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masson CL, Delucchi KL, McKnight C, Hettema J, Khalili M, Min A, Jordan AE, Pepper N, Hall J, Hengl NS, Young C, Shopshire MS, Manuel JK, Coffin L, Hammer H, Shapiro B, Seewald RM, Bodenheimer HC Jr, Sorensen JL, Des Jarlais DC, Perlman DC. A randomized trial of a hepatitis care coordination model in methadone maintenance treatment. Am J Public Health. 2013 Oct;103(10):e81-8. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2013.301458. Epub 2013 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>23947319</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottlieb LN. Strengths-based nursing. Am J Nurs. 2014 Aug;114(8):24-32; quiz 33,46. doi: 10.1097/01.NAJ.0000453039.70629.e2.</citation>
    <PMID>25036663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farley JE, Kelly AM, Reiser K, Brown M, Kub J, Davis JG, Walshe L, Van der Walt M. Development and evaluation of a pilot nurse case management model to address multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) and HIV in South Africa. PLoS One. 2014 Nov 18;9(11):e111702. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0111702. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25405988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 14, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Continuity of Patient Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Cascade</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coinfection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

