<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02704624</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAAE41674814500005147</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02704624</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Supplementation of Vitamin D in Patients With Crohn`s Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Serum Vitamin D and Calcium Levels on the Body Composition, Bone Mineral Density, Muscle Strength, Exercise Tolerance, Fatigue and Inflammatory Activity in Patients With Crohn's Disease: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of Juiz de Fora</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do estado de Minas Gerais</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of Juiz de Fora</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Thus, the aim of the current study is to assess the influence of vitamin D deficiency and,
      consequently, of serum calcium deficiency in the body composition, muscular activity, bone
      mineral density, fatigue, and exercise tolerance of CD patients. Secondly, it also aims to
      determine the impact of vitamin D supplementation on this population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a clinical, randomized, controlled, and double-blind trial comprising a
      consecutive sample of 110 CD patients in remission treated by the Gastroenterology team of
      the Inflammatory Intestinal Disease Clinic at the University Hospital (HU/CAS), Federal
      University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF). The patients will be divided into two groups: 55 patients
      with low serum vitamin D levels and 55 patients with normal vitamin D levels. Upon the
      approval by the Ethics Committee of the UFJF, the study aims and procedures will be
      previously explained to the individuals, who will sign an informed consent form.

      The sample size was based on the handgrip strength test REF, assuming an alpha risk of 5 %
      and beta risk of 80 %, standard deviation of 2.5, and a difference in magnitude of 30% of
      response between intervention and placebo control group, the sample size needed was 45
      patients in each group. Therefore, considering potential losses, 55 patients will be
      recruited for each group, requiring a total of 110 volunteers.

      Study procedure

      Phase 1. Assessment All patients in the study will be subjected to the following tests: a.
      clinical assessment; B. biochemical assessment; c. body composition assessment/anthropometry;
      d. bone mineral density assessment; e. peripheral muscle strength assessment; f. fatigue
      assessment; g.Exercise Tolerance Testing

      Clinical Assessment of the Disease The following data will be collected in the initial
      assessment: age, gender, CD duration, data related to the Montreal Classification (age at the
      time of diagnosis, disease behavior and location), glucocorticoid use and number of
      exacerbations in the previous year. The inflammatory activity assessment will be held
      according to the Harvey-Bradshaw Index, When the score is less than 5, the disease is
      considered to be inactive.

      Biochemical Assessment The participants will be instructed to fast 12 hours prior to the
      blood sampling for analysis. A stool sample as well as a 5 ml venous blood sample will be
      collected from the patients in order to determine biochemical parameters. The University
      Hospital routine laboratory will analyze the venous blood, the levels of C-reactive protein
      (CRP), calcium, 25-hydroxyvitamin D, parathyroid hormone (PTH) and inflammatory cytokines
      such as Interleukins (IL) 17, IL 6 and Tumor necrosis factor alfa (TNF-α) . Fecal
      calprotectin dosage will be performed in the stool samples. CRP and serum calcium are
      routinely evaluated in all CD patients under follow-up in the inflammatory bowel disease
      clinic at HU/CAS.

      The following reference values will be taken into consideration regarding 25-hydroxyvitamin
      D: &lt; 20ng/mL = deficiency, between 21 and 29 ng/mL = insufficiency, and &gt; 30 ng/mL =
      satisfactory.

      Bone Mineral Density Assessment A bone densitometer, Lunar Prodigy Primo (pr + 351035), will
      be used to measure the patients' bone mineral density (BMD), expressed in g/cm2, by
      dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA). The double-energy X-ray densitometry of the skeleton
      or specific sites such as the spine and the hip is based on the X-rays absorption by the
      calcium crystals in the bone. The lumbar spine regions between L1 and L4 and those of the
      total proximal femur will be assessed. The examination will be held under appropriate
      conditions, according to the technical quality controls. The coefficient of variation for the
      lumbar spine and total proximal femur will be obtained based on these results. The low BMD
      will be defined by the reduction greater than -2.0 standard deviations from the reference
      value mean of healthy individuals, adjusted according to height, age and gender (Z score), in
      compliance with the official positions of the International Society for Clinical Densitometry
      (ISCD).

      Body Composition Assessment/Anthropometry The assessment will be held through the Quantum BIA
      (bioelectrical impedance analysis) bioimpedance device. The device is four-pole, has digital
      display, and provides resistance and reactance values. Total and segmental body composition
      parameters will be also assessed by DXA expressed in kg.

      Muscle Strength Assessment The peripheral muscle strength will be assessed through the
      maximum voluntary handgrip strength using hand-held dynamometry (HHD), which consists of a
      simple and objective test that estimates the skeletal muscle function. The Jamar's hydraulic
      dynamometer will be used, since it is recommended by the American Society of Hand Therapists
      (ASHT) and is considered the most accurate and precise instrument used to assess HHD .

      Fatigue Assessment The questionnaire by Chalder et al. (Annex), which was validated in Brazil
      will be applied to assess fatigue.

      Exercise Tolerance Testing The exercise capacity is assessed by the walking test with
      progressive loading or Shuttle Walk Test.

      Phase 2. Intervention A double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study will be performed.
      After the evaluation of serum vitamin D levels, the intervention-group-selected patients
      presenting deficient or insufficient levels will receive vitamin D supplementation for at
      least six months as well as nutritional instructions from an experienced nutritionist
      regarding the consumption of vitamin-D-and-calcium-rich foods.

      The supplementation will be performed in patients with serum vitamin D levels below 29 ng/Ml.
      The replacement with cholecalciferol (vitamin D3) tablets will be provided at no cost to the
      patients. The dosage of 1.500-2.000 IU (International Units) vitamin D/day is recommended in
      order to meet the need of vitamin D above 30ng/ml in adults. However, a dose at least 2 to 3
      times higher is recommended for CD patients due to malabsorption, significant loss of adipose
      tissue and use of glucocorticoids. Thus, the dose of 50000IU/week will be administered.

      The contraindications and precautions on the use of vitamin D will be respected, namely:
      hypersensitivity to the D-group vitamins, hypercalcemia, hypercalciuria and metastatic
      calcification; and interactions with digitalis, thiazides, and anticonvulsant and antacid
      medications.

      Despite the possible interference of the skin melanin concentration in vitamin D absorption,
      no evidence was found to support the differentiated supplementation between Afro descendant
      and Caucasian individuals.

      The patients selected to the placebo group will receive inert content tablets without
      therapeutic effect. After the study completion, these control patients will receive complete
      treatment for hypovitaminosis D.

      Throughout the intervention phase, both the treated group and the control group patients will
      be monitored by phone every 15 days in order to optimize their adhesion.

      Phase 3. Reassessment At the end of 6 months of supplementation with cholecalciferol (vitamin
      D3), this subgroup of patients will be subjected to the same assessments performed in phase
      1.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in the grip strength in patients with Crohn under vitamin D supplementation</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>Grip strength will be expressed in kg</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in mineral bone density (MBD)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>MBD assessed by DXA, expressed in gr/cm²</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in fecal Calprotectin levels</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of calprotectin under 200µg/g</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global reduction in laboratorial inflammatory biomarkers (TNF-α)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>TNF-α expressed in pg/ml</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in exercise capacity assessed by Shuttle Walk Test (SWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement in the distance achieved in the SWT expressed in meters (m)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in lean body mass in patients with Crohn under vitamin D supplementation</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>Body mass will be assessed by DXA and will be expressed in kg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in fatigue perception in patients with Crohn under vitamin D supplementation</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue will be measured by the Chalder Fatigue Questionnaire (CFQ). The CFQ is analyzed by 2 domains physical and mental (cutoff: patient's total score higher than 2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global reduction in laboratorial inflammatory biomarkers (IL 6)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>IL 6 expressed in pg/ml</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global reduction in laboratorial inflammatory biomarkers (IL 17)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>IL 17 expressed in pg/ml</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global reduction in laboratorial inflammatory biomarkers (CRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months of supplementation with vitamin D</time_frame>
    <description>CRP expressed in mg/dl</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn Disease</condition>
  <condition>Vitamin D Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Fatigue</condition>
  <condition>Sarcopenia</condition>
  <condition>Muscle Weakness</condition>
  <condition>Disorder of Bone Density and Structure, Unspecified</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tablets with 50000UI cholecalciferol (vitamin D3) will be administered, weekly, for six months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients selected to the placebo group will receive inert content tablets without therapeutic effect, weekly, for six months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin D</intervention_name>
    <description>investigate the relationship between musculoskeletal manifestations, in Crohn population, and the hypovitaminosis D</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>compare the musculoskeletal manifestations of the Placebo group with the group receiving Vitamin D</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of Crohn's Disease (moderate to severe)

          -  Remission of Crohn's activity

          -  Reduced blood levels of vitamin D

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of other chronic concomitant disease

          -  Presence of other autoimmune disease

          -  Presence of sleep disturbance

          -  Abuse of alcohol and other drugs

          -  Pregnancy or lactation, climacteric and/or menopausal women

          -  Adherence to extreme diet (e.g. macrobiotic or vegetarian diet)

          -  Celiac disease

          -  Presence of extensive resection of the small intestine (more than 100cm²)

          -  Patients undergoing vitamin D replacement for the last 6 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Júlio MF Chebli, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Juiz de Fora</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Federal de Juiz de Fora</name>
      <address>
        <city>Juiz de Fora</city>
        <state>Minas Gerais</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernstein CN, Seeger LL, Sayre JW, Anton PA, Artinian L, Shanahan F. Decreased bone density in inflammatory bowel disease is related to corticosteroid use and not disease diagnosis. J Bone Miner Res. 1995 Feb;10(2):250-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7754804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beck A, Bager P, Jensen PE, Dahlerup JF. How fatigue is experienced and handled by female outpatients with inflammatory bowel disease. Gastroenterol Res Pract. 2013;2013:153818. doi: 10.1155/2013/153818. Epub 2013 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24072994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cho HJ, Costa E, Menezes PR, Chalder T, Bhugra D, Wessely S. Cross-cultural validation of the Chalder Fatigue Questionnaire in Brazilian primary care. J Psychosom Res. 2007 Mar;62(3):301-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17324680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dusso AS, Brown AJ, Slatopolsky E. Vitamin D. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol. 2005 Jul;289(1):F8-28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15951480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farraye FA, Nimitphong H, Stucchi A, Dendrinos K, Boulanger AB, Vijjeswarapu A, Tanennbaum A, Biancuzzo R, Chen TC, Holick MF. Use of a novel vitamin D bioavailability test demonstrates that vitamin D absorption is decreased in patients with quiescent Crohn's disease. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2011 Oct;17(10):2116-21. doi: 10.1002/ibd.21595. Epub 2011 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>21910173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaburri PD, Chebli JM, de Castro LE, Ferreira JO, Lopes MH, Ribeiro AM, Alves RA, Froede EC, de Oliveira KS, Gaburri AK, Gaburri D, Meirelles GS, de Souza AF. [Epidemiology, clinical features and clinical course of Crohn's disease: a study of 60 cases]. Arq Gastroenterol. 1998 Oct-Dec;35(4):240-6. Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>10347705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hwang C, Ross V, Mahadevan U. Micronutrient deficiencies in inflammatory bowel disease: from A to zinc. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2012 Oct;18(10):1961-81. doi: 10.1002/ibd.22906. Epub 2012 Apr 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22488830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iijima H, Shinzaki S, Takehara T. The importance of vitamins D and K for the bone health and immune function in inflammatory bowel disease. Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care. 2012 Nov;15(6):635-40. doi: 10.1097/MCO.0b013e328357f623. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22914505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim YG, Jang BI. The role of colonoscopy in inflammatory bowel disease. Clin Endosc. 2013 Jul;46(4):317-20. doi: 10.5946/ce.2013.46.4.317. Epub 2013 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>23964327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Langenberg DR, Gibson PR. Factors associated with physical and cognitive fatigue in patients with Crohn's disease: a cross-sectional and longitudinal study. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2014 Jan;20(1):115-25. doi: 10.1097/01.MIB.0000437614.91258.70.</citation>
    <PMID>24297056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peyrin-Biroulet L, Fiorino G, Buisson A, Danese S. First-line therapy in adult Crohn's disease: who should receive anti-TNF agents? Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2013 Jun;10(6):345-51. doi: 10.1038/nrgastro.2013.31. Epub 2013 Mar 5. Review. Erratum in: Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2013 Jun;10(6):ii.</citation>
    <PMID>23458890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Płudowski P, Karczmarewicz E, Bayer M, Carter G, Chlebna-Sokół D, Czech-Kowalska J, Dębski R, Decsi T, Dobrzańska A, Franek E, Głuszko P, Grant WB, Holick MF, Yankovskaya L, Konstantynowicz J, Książyk JB, Księżopolska-Orłowska K, Lewiński A, Litwin M, Lohner S, Lorenc RS, Lukaszkiewicz J, Marcinowska-Suchowierska E, Milewicz A, Misiorowski W, Nowicki M, Povoroznyuk V, Rozentryt P, Rudenka E, Shoenfeld Y, Socha P, Solnica B, Szalecki M, Tałałaj M, Varbiro S, Żmijewski MA. Practical guidelines for the supplementation of vitamin D and the treatment of deficits in Central Europe - recommended vitamin D intakes in the general population and groups at risk of vitamin D deficiency. Endokrynol Pol. 2013;64(4):319-27.</citation>
    <PMID>24002961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reich KM, Fedorak RN, Madsen K, Kroeker KI. Vitamin D improves inflammatory bowel disease outcomes: basic science and clinical review. World J Gastroenterol. 2014 May 7;20(17):4934-47. doi: 10.3748/wjg.v20.i17.4934. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24803805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Römkens TE, van Vugt-van Pinxteren MW, Nagengast FM, van Oijen MG, de Jong DJ. High prevalence of fatigue in inflammatory bowel disease: A case control study. J Crohns Colitis. 2011 Aug;5(4):332-7. doi: 10.1016/j.crohns.2011.02.008. Epub 2011 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21683303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sipponen T, Nuutinen H, Turunen U, Färkkilä M. Endoscopic evaluation of Crohn's disease activity: comparison of the CDEIS and the SES-CD. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2010 Dec;16(12):2131-6. doi: 10.1002/ibd.21300.</citation>
    <PMID>20848462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vázquez MA, Lopez E, Montoya MJ, Giner M, Pérez-Temprano R, Pérez-Cano R. Vertebral fractures in patients with inflammatory bowel disease compared with a healthy population: a prospective case-control study. BMC Gastroenterol. 2012 May 14;12:47. doi: 10.1186/1471-230X-12-47.</citation>
    <PMID>22584049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 9, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 10, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of Juiz de Fora</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lorena Nagme de Oliveira Pinto</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Crohn Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteopenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise Tolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin d</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D Deficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscle Weakness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paresis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

