<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02707874</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB#13-6466</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02707874</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PIB Versus CI Through a Popliteal Sciatic Nerve Catheter for Analgesia Following Major Ankle Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparing the Delivery of Local Anesthetic by Programmed Intermittent Bolus Versus Continuous Infusion Through a Popliteal Sciatic Nerve Catheter for Analgesia Following Major Ankle Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a clinical study to investigate and compare a new programmed intermittent bolus (PIB)
      delivery method for continuous popliteal sciatic nerve block for pain relief in patients
      undergoing major ankle surgery compared with the current practice of continuous local
      anesthetic infusion (CI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peripheral nerve blocks are commonly used for upper and lower limb surgery. Continuous
      popliteal sciatic nerve block achieved by delivery of local anesthetic through a perineural
      catheter plays an important role in post-operative pain control after major orthopedic
      surgeries of the ankle and foot. Factors affecting the success and clinical outcome of
      continuous sciatic nerve blocks include the accuracy of catheter placement, the local
      anesthetic dose (volume and concentration), and the infusion method.

      Methods of local anesthetic infusion commonly used for peripheral nerve blockade include
      continuous infusion (CI) and CI combined with patient-controlled analgesic (PCA) boluses. A
      third option, regular intermittent boluses of local anesthetic, is not commonly used as it
      usually requires manual administration by a healthcare provider and is thus time and
      labor-intensive. Recently, however, infusion pumps capable of providing automated programmed
      intermittent bolus (PIB) dosing have become available.

      The premise of PIB dosing is that it results in more extensive spread of local anesthetic
      around nerves, and thus more effective sensory block and analgesia. PIB dosing regimens have
      been extensively studied in labor epidural analgesia, where they have been shown to decrease
      local anesthetic consumption and improve maternal satisfaction when compared with continuous
      infusion regimens.

      In contrast, there has been little investigation into PIB dosing regimens in the context of
      continuous peripheral nerve blockade. In 2005, Taboada et al 2 published a study that
      compared automated PIB dosing with CI dosing of local anesthetic for continuous popliteal
      sciatic nerve blockade. In both regimens, patients were also allowed to administer PCA
      boluses of local anesthetic as needed to improve the quality of the nerve block. The authors
      found that the automated PIB dosing regimen resulted in patients using less local anesthetic
      and fewer PCA boluses, while providing equivalent analgesia. There was a non-significant
      trend to lower pain scores in the PIB group of patients. These effects are attributed to
      better perineural spread of local anesthetic with the PIB regimen. No other studies have been
      conducted to confirm these benefits.

      The reduced local anesthetic requirement is of particular advantage in patients who are
      discharged home with a nerve block catheter in situ as the supplied reservoir of local
      anesthetic will last longer. Ambulatory infusion pumps with both PIB and PCA features are now
      commercially available. The investigators hypothesize that a PIB+PCA dosing regimen using one
      of these new ambulatory infusion pumps will provide more effective postoperative analgesia
      with less local anesthetic consumption than the CI+PCA dosing regimen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average numerical rating score (NRS) for pain</measure>
    <time_frame>post-operative 48 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NRS for pain at rest and with movement at specified time points</measure>
    <time_frame>post-operative 48 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of local anesthetic PCA boluses administered</measure>
    <time_frame>post-operative 48 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total dose of local anesthetic</measure>
    <time_frame>post-operative 48 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction, on a 0-10 NRS</measure>
    <time_frame>post-operative 48 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CI 0.2% ropivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in Group Continuous Infusion (CI) will receive continuous infusion of 0.2% ropivacaine at 5 mL/hour; total 4-hourly consumption = 20 mL = 40 mg ropivacaine.
• All patients will be able to self-administer PCA boluses of 5 mL of ropivacaine 0.2% at intervals of 30 minutes as required.
2) Oral patient controlled analgesia (PCA) using oxycodone or hydromorphone. Patients under 70 years of age will receive either 10 mg of oxycodone or 2 mg of hydromorphone 2 hourly as needed, and patients 70 years of age or older will receive 5 mg of oxycodone or 1 mg of hydromorphone 2 hourly as needed.
3) Oral acetaminophen 1,000 mg 6 hourly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PIB 0.2% ropivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in Group programmed intermittent boluses (PIB) will receive automated programmed intermittent boluses of 10 mL of ropivacaine 0.2% every 2 hours; total 4-hourly consumption = 20 mL = 40 mg ropivacaine.
• All patients will be able to self-administer PCA boluses of 5 mL of ropivacaine 0.2% at intervals of 30 minutes as required.
2) Oral patient controlled analgesia (PCA) using oxycodone or hydromorphone. Patients under 70 years of age will receive either 10 mg of oxycodone or 2 mg of hydromorphone 2 hourly as needed, and patients 70 years of age or older will receive 5 mg of oxycodone or 1 mg of hydromorphone 2 hourly as needed.
3) Oral acetaminophen 1,000 mg 6 hourly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CI 0.2% ropivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in Group CI will receive continuous infusion of 0.2% ropivacaine at 5 mL/hour; total 4-hourly consumption = 20 mL = 40 mg ropivacaine. All patients will be able to self-administer PCA boluses of 5 mL of ropivacaine 0.2% at intervals of 30 minutes as required</description>
    <arm_group_label>CI 0.2% ropivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ropivacaine 0.2% Continuous infusion</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PIB 0.2% ropivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in Group Programmed intermittent bolus (PIB) will receive automated programmed intermittent boluses of 10 mL of ropivacaine 0.2% every 2 hours; total 4-hourly consumption = 20 mL = 40 mg ropivacaine. All patients will be able to self-administer PCA boluses of 5 mL of ropivacaine 0.2% at intervals of 30 minutes as required</description>
    <arm_group_label>PIB 0.2% ropivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ropivacaine 0.2% Programmed intermittent bolus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inpatients having major foot and ankle surgery that will benefit from continuous
             popliteal sciatic nerve block with an indwelling catheter

          -  American Society Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status I-III

          -  18-85 years of age, inclusive

          -  40-120 kg, inclusive

          -  150 cm of height or greater

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who undergo iliac crest bone graft harvesting as part of their surgery

          -  Preexisting neurological deficits or peripheral neuropathy in the distribution of the
             sciatic nerve

          -  Local infection

          -  Contraindication to regional anesthesia e.g. bleeding diathesis, coagulopathy

          -  Chronic pain disorders

          -  History of use of over 30mg oxycodone or equivalent per day

          -  Allergy to local anesthetics

          -  History of significant psychiatric conditions that may affect patient assessment

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Inability to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ki Jinn Chin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rongyu Jin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>416-603-5800</phone>
    <phone_ext>2016</phone_ext>
    <email>rongyu.jin@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>George RB, Allen TK, Habib AS. Intermittent epidural bolus compared with continuous epidural infusions for labor analgesia: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Anesth Analg. 2013 Jan;116(1):133-44. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3182713b26. Epub 2012 Dec 7. Review. Erratum in: Anesth Analg. 2013 Jun;116(6):1385.</citation>
    <PMID>23223119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taboada M, Rodríguez J, Bermudez M, Amor M, Ulloa B, Aneiros F, Sebate S, Cortés J, Alvarez J, Atanassoff PG. Comparison of continuous infusion versus automated bolus for postoperative patient-controlled analgesia with popliteal sciatic nerve catheters. Anesthesiology. 2009 Jan;110(1):150-4. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318191693a.</citation>
    <PMID>19104182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chludzinski A, Irani C, Mascha EJ, Kurz A, Devereaux PJ, Sessler DI. Protocol understanding and anxiety in perioperative clinical trial patients approached for consent on the day of surgery. Mayo Clin Proc. 2013 May;88(5):446-54. doi: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2012.12.014.</citation>
    <PMID>23639498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 27, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 27, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ropivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>by publication</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

