<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02704442</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6014969</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02704442</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Does Anxiety in Children on the Day of Surgery Impact Compliance in the Ophthalmology Clinic?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Anxiety in Children on the Day of Surgery Impact Compliance in the Ophthalmology Clinic?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Queen's University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Regina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Queen's University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The hypothesis is that pediatric patients with increased levels of anxiety on the day of
      surgery, in particular at point of anesthetic induction, will demonstrate decreased
      compliance with assessment in ophthalmology clinic postoperatively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are many studies demonstrating pediatric anxiety from a surgical experience leading to
      postoperative maladaptive behaviors such as nightmares, separation anxiety, eating problems,
      and increased fear of doctors. There is a significant amount of research looking at day of
      surgery anxiety and pain in children and possible modifiers. Very little work has explored
      the effect of maladaptive behaviors with follow up physician visits. Strabismus surgery is
      particularly important as children require early and regular follow up assessments after
      surgery for optimal outcome. These assessments are meticulous and require good patient
      cooperation in order to obtain useful information for the pediatric ophthalmologist.

      The study hypothesis is that pediatric patients with increased levels of anxiety on the day
      of surgery, in particular at point of anesthetic induction, will demonstrate decreased
      compliance with assessment in ophthalmology clinic postoperatively. The investigators expect
      this decrease in compliance will be evident based on changes seen on the ophthalmology clinic
      compliance scores generated pre and postoperatively.

      The proposed study will be a prospective cross sectional study. Investigators will be
      measuring compliance in the ophthalmology clinic pre and postoperative and relating any
      changes in compliance with anxiety levels on the day of surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Compliance with Ophthalmology examination</measure>
    <time_frame>4 days and 6 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A five point observer-rated Ophthalmology Clinic Compliance Checklist (OCCC) will be completed at the clinic visit one week prior to surgery and then at the 4 day and 6 week postoperative visits. The checklist includes sitting the ophthalmic chair, cover test, vision testing, stereo acuity and cycloplegic refraction. Compliance will be rated on a scale of 0 (non compliant ) 1 (compliant with minor coaxing) 2 (compliant with heavy coaxing) 3 (easily compliant)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>child observer rated anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Observations on day of surgery at time points 1. admission to hospital 2. day surgery waiting area 3. just prior to entering the operating room 4. anesthetic induction 5. recovery room and at 4 days and 6 weeks post operatively</time_frame>
    <description>Child observer-rated anxiety on day of surgery will be measured using the modified Yale Preoperative Anxiety Scale at 5 time-points throughout day-surgery process as described above and at Ophthalmology Clinic after surgery (i.e., day 4 post-surgery and 6 weeks post-surgery)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>parent anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>measured at 4 time points: 1. at the last clinic visit prior to surgery (approximately 7 days), on day of surgery 2. at admission to hospital and 3. in the recovery room after surgery and 4. 4 days after surgery at the post op clinic visit</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of parental anxiety will be measured by completion of the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory-state version at 3 time-points stated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>child temperament</measure>
    <time_frame>pre operative assessment</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will also be asked to complete a measure of child temperament [i.e., Emotionality, Activity, Sociability, Impulsivity temperament scale prior to the day of surgery (i.e., at clinic one week prior to surgery) 11.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">82</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Strabismus</condition>
  <condition>Compliance</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study personnel with approach all pediatric patients who are American Society of Anesthesia
        (ASA) classification I to III, between the ages of 3 and 10 attending the ophthalmology
        clinic for primary strabismus repair
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 3 - 10 years old

          -  ASA I - III

          -  Primary strabismus surgery one or both eyes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Preexisting anxiety disorder

          -  Preexisting chronic pain or chronic analgesia use

          -  Neurobehavioural pathology limiting our ability to assess the patient eg: Cerebral
             Palsy, Autism or Developmental Delay.

          -  Inability to adhere to study protocol

          -  Consult in Anesthesiology clinic prior to surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rachel Rooney, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Queen's University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rachel Rooney, MD</last_name>
    <phone>613 549-6666</phone>
    <phone_ext>7827</phone_ext>
    <email>rooneyr@kgh.kari.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yi Ning Strube, MD</last_name>
    <phone>613 544-3310</phone>
    <phone_ext>3100</phone_ext>
    <email>strubey@hdh.kari.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hotel Dieu Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 5G2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel Phelan, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>613 549-6666</phone>
      <email>phelanr@KGH.KARI.NET</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kain ZN, Caldwell-Andrews AA. Preoperative psychological preparation of the child for surgery: an update. Anesthesiol Clin North America. 2005 Dec;23(4):597-614, vii. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16310653</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kain ZN, Mayes LC, Caldwell-Andrews AA, Karas DE, McClain BC. Preoperative anxiety, postoperative pain, and behavioral recovery in young children undergoing surgery. Pediatrics. 2006 Aug;118(2):651-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16882820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kain ZN, Wang SM, Mayes LC, Caramico LA, Hofstadter MB. Distress during the induction of anesthesia and postoperative behavioral outcomes. Anesth Analg. 1999 May;88(5):1042-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10320165</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Varughese AM, Nick TG, Gunter J, Wang Y, Kurth CD. Factors predictive of poor behavioral compliance during inhaled induction in children. Anesth Analg. 2008 Aug;107(2):413-21. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e31817e616b.</citation>
    <PMID>18633018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kain ZN, Mayes LC, Wang SM, Caramico LA, Hofstadter MB. Parental presence during induction of anesthesia versus sedative premedication: which intervention is more effective? Anesthesiology. 1998 Nov;89(5):1147-56; discussion 9A-10A.</citation>
    <PMID>9822003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wollin SR, Plummer JL, Owen H, Hawkins RM, Materazzo F. Predictors of preoperative anxiety in children. Anaesth Intensive Care. 2003 Feb;31(1):69-74.</citation>
    <PMID>12635399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright KD, Stewart SH, Finley GA. When are parents helpful? A randomized clinical trial of the efficacy of parental presence for pediatric anesthesia. Can J Anaesth. 2010 Aug;57(8):751-8. doi: 10.1007/s12630-010-9333-1. Epub 2010 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>20499223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim JE, Jo BY, Oh HM, Choi HS, Lee Y. High anxiety, young age and long waits increase the need for preoperative sedatives in children. J Int Med Res. 2012;40(4):1381-9.</citation>
    <PMID>22971489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kain ZN, Mayes LC, Cicchetti DV, Bagnall AL, Finley JD, Hofstadter MB. The Yale Preoperative Anxiety Scale: how does it compare with a &quot;gold standard&quot;? Anesth Analg. 1997 Oct;85(4):783-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9322455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 10, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Queen's University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Rachel Rooney</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Rachel Rooney MD FRCPC, Assistant Professor Department of Anesthesiology, Queen's University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>anesthesiology</keyword>
  <keyword>ophthalmology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Strabismus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

