<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02701010</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>-1491-160-12/1648.4-5263</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02701010</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Behavioural Therapy Program for Female Overactive Bladder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparative Effectiveness of Three Different Teaching Methods in Behavioural Therapy Program for Female Overactive Bladder: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi Gulhane Tip Fakultesi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi Gulhane Tip Fakultesi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Researchers aimed to identify the effectiveness of three methods of patient education for
      behavioral therapy (BT), including verbal instructions combined with a leaflet on a
      structured training program of BT, only verbal instructions on a structured training and only
      a leaflet on a structured BT training. Therefore, a randomized controlled trial was designed
      to compare effectiveness of those methods of patient education in BT based on the two
      validated patient- reported outcome measures (PROMs) for women with overactive bladder.

      Idiopathic overactive bladder (iOAB) symptoms in female patients are perceived as normal,
      which does not threaten life and not require to be treated immediately. It is necessary to
      raise the awareness of iOAB on women. The education and consultancy role of continence nurses
      is important in the treatment and care of urinary incontinence (UI) associated with iOAB. In
      the study, it was seen that the training to be provided to patients is helpful regardless of
      the teaching method used. Also it was found that the method of verbal instructions in the
      form of a structured training plus giving a leaflet to patient is the most effective method
      of BT for female iOAB.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Behavioural therapy (BT) is the first-line treatment for urinary incontinence including
      idiopathic overactive bladder (iOAB) syndrome. It requires education of the actively
      participated patient as well as time and effort from the clinician. However, the most
      effective method for patient education in BT remains unclear. Researchers designed a
      randomized controlled trial to compare effectiveness of 3 different methods of patient
      education in BT for women with overactive bladder.

      The sample of the study consisted of 60 iOAB female patients who applied to urogynecology
      clinic between November 2012 and April 2013. These patients were equally randomized into 4
      groups of teaching models for BT. Group I included the patients educated by a continence
      nurse's verbal instructions in the form of a structured training including bladder training,
      bladder control strategies, pelvic floor muscle training and lifestyle changes and a leaflet
      containing information stated in structured training, group II included the patients taught
      by a continence nurse as the only verbal structured training, group III included the patients
      who were given only the leaflet and group IV was the control group consisted of female iOAB
      patients who were given an unstructured training by a healthcare worker with no specific
      experience in continence care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI-6)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 6 or 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>improvement in bladder functions at 6-8 weeks of the intervention compared to baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incontinence Impact Questionnaire (IIQ-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 6 or 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>improvement in bladder functions at 6-8 weeks of the intervention compared to baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary Incontinence-Specific Quality of Life Instrument (I-QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 6 or 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>positive changes in quality of life at 6-8 weeks of the intervention compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Structured training and leaflet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Structured training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Leaflet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Structured training and leaflet</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients who were given both &quot;explanatory verbal instructions of the educational leaflet on the structured behavioural therapy for iOAB&quot; by continence nurse and the educational leaflet were included in this group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Structured training</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients who were given only &quot;explanatory verbal instructions of the educational leaflet on the structured behavioural therapy&quot; by continence nurse were included in this group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leaflet</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients who were given &quot;only educational leaflet&quot; were included in this group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who were given unstructured explanations about continence care by a healthcare worker were included in control group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Eligible participants were all ambulatory adults aged 18 or over with predominant iOAB
        syndrome with or without stress urinary incontinence (the number of urgency and urgency
        incontinence episodes exceeded the number of stress incontinence episodes and other
        accidents in bladder diary), who were candidates for behavioural therapy as a first-line
        treatment after initial clinical assessment, including history, physical examination,
        symptom questionnaires, 3-day bladder diary, repeated uroflowmetry and postvoid residual
        measurements for all patients and urodynamics for some patients with a suspicion of
        presence of the exclusion criteria.

        Exclusion criteria were pregnancy, suspected neurogenic disease, stress predominant mixed
        urinary incontinence, continuous urinary leakage, previous anti-incontinence surgery,
        voiding dysfunction (PVR&gt; 100 ml), genitourinary malignancies, current or previous
        behavioural therapy programs, previous or current use of antimuscarinic agents, symptomatic
        pelvic organ prolapse, severe co-morbidities such as congestive heart failure, chronic
        renal failure, impaired cognitive functions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gulhane Military Medical Academy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ankara</city>
        <state>Kecioren</state>
        <zip>06010</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haylen BT, de Ridder D, Freeman RM, Swift SE, Berghmans B, Lee J, Monga A, Petri E, Rizk DE, Sand PK, Schaer GN; International Urogynecological Association; International Continence Society. An International Urogynecological Association (IUGA)/International Continence Society (ICS) joint report on the terminology for female pelvic floor dysfunction. Neurourol Urodyn. 2010;29(1):4-20. doi: 10.1002/nau.20798. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19941278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gormley EA, Lightner DJ, Faraday M, Vasavada SP; American Urological Association; Society of Urodynamics, Female Pelvic Medicine. Diagnosis and treatment of overactive bladder (non-neurogenic) in adults: AUA/SUFU guideline amendment. J Urol. 2015 May;193(5):1572-80. doi: 10.1016/j.juro.2015.01.087. Epub 2015 Jan 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25623739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sacco E, Tienforti D, D'Addessi A, Pinto F, Racioppi M, Totaro A, D'Agostino D, Marangi F, Bassi P. Social, economic, and health utility considerations in the treatment of overactive bladder. Open Access J Urol. 2010 Feb 11;2:11-24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24198609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abrams P. CL, Khoury S, Wein A, ed Incontinence 4th Edition. 21 ed. Paris: Health Publication; 2009. 4th International Consultation on Incontinence.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cam C, Sakalli M, Ay P, Cam M, Karateke A. Validation of the short forms of the incontinence impact questionnaire (IIQ-7) and the urogenital distress inventory (UDI-6) in a Turkish population. Neurourol Urodyn. 2007;26(1):129-33.</citation>
    <PMID>17083117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uebersax JS, Wyman JF, Shumaker SA, McClish DK, Fantl JA. Short forms to assess life quality and symptom distress for urinary incontinence in women: the Incontinence Impact Questionnaire and the Urogenital Distress Inventory. Continence Program for Women Research Group. Neurourol Urodyn. 1995;14(2):131-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7780440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patrick DL, Martin ML, Bushnell DM, Yalcin I, Wagner TH, Buesching DP. Quality of life of women with urinary incontinence: further development of the incontinence quality of life instrument (I-QOL). Urology. 1999 Jan;53(1):71-6. Erratum in: Urology 1999 May;53(5):1072.</citation>
    <PMID>9886591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ozerdoğan N, Beji NK, Yalçin O. Urinary incontinence: its prevalence, risk factors and effects on the quality of life of women living in a region of Turkey. Gynecol Obstet Invest. 2004;58(3):145-50. Epub 2004 Jun 29.</citation>
    <PMID>15237249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Available from: https://www.sealedenvelope.com/simple-randomiser/v1/lists, available date: 01.11.2012</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Subak LL, Goode PS, Brubaker L, Kusek JW, Schembri M, Lukacz ES, Kraus SR, Chai TC, Norton P, Tennstedt SL; Urinary Incontinence Treatment Network. Urinary incontinence management costs are reduced following Burch or sling surgery for stress incontinence. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2014 Aug;211(2):171.e1-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2014.03.012. Epub 2014 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24631433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lucas MG, Bosch RJ, Burkhard FC, Cruz F, Madden TB, Nambiar AK, Neisius A, de Ridder DJ, Tubaro A, Turner WH, Pickard RS; European Association of Urology. EAU guidelines on assessment and nonsurgical management of urinary incontinence. Eur Urol. 2012 Dec;62(6):1130-42. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2012.08.047. Epub 2012 Aug 31. Erratum in: Eur Urol. 2013 Jul;64(1):e20.</citation>
    <PMID>22985745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Botlero R, Urquhart DM, Davis SR, Bell RJ. Prevalence and incidence of urinary incontinence in women: review of the literature and investigation of methodological issues. Int J Urol. 2008 Mar;15(3):230-4. doi: 10.1111/j.1442-2042.2007.01976.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18304218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elbiss HM, Osman N, Hammad FT. Social impact and healthcare-seeking behavior among women with urinary incontinence in the United Arab Emirates. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2013 Aug;122(2):136-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ijgo.2013.03.023. Epub 2013 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23764126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsai YC, Liu CH. Urinary incontinence among Taiwanese women: an outpatient study of prevalence, comorbidity, risk factors, and quality of life. Int Urol Nephrol. 2009 Dec;41(4):795-803. doi: 10.1007/s11255-009-9523-3. Epub 2009 Feb 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19199071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsieh CH, Su TH, Chang ST, Lin SH, Lee MC, Lee MY. Prevalence of and attitude toward urinary incontinence in postmenopausal women. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2008 Feb;100(2):171-4. Epub 2007 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>17977542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hunskaar S. A systematic review of overweight and obesity as risk factors and targets for clinical intervention for urinary incontinence in women. Neurourol Urodyn. 2008;27(8):749-57. doi: 10.1002/nau.20635. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18951445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hägglund D, Walker-Engström ML, Larsson G, Leppert J. Reasons why women with long-term urinary incontinence do not seek professional help: a cross-sectional population-based cohort study. Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct. 2003 Nov;14(5):296-304; discussion 304. Epub 2003 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>14618304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Donnell M, Lose G, Sykes D, Voss S, Hunskaar S. Help-seeking behaviour and associated factors among women with urinary incontinence in France, Germany, Spain and the United Kingdom. Eur Urol. 2005 Mar;47(3):385-92; discussion 392. Epub 2004 Nov 21.</citation>
    <PMID>15716205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Subak LL, Quesenberry CP, Posner SF, Cattolica E, Soghikian K. The effect of behavioral therapy on urinary incontinence: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol. 2002 Jul;100(1):72-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12100806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kök G, Şenel N, Akyüz A. Nurses' roles in identifying urinary incontinence and its effects on social life. Int J Urol Nurs 2008;2:119-124.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altaweel W, Alharbi M. Urinary incontinence: prevalence, risk factors, and impact on health related quality of life in Saudi women. Neurourol Urodyn. 2012 Jun;31(5):642-5. doi: 10.1002/nau.22201. Epub 2012 Mar 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22415626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi Gulhane Tip Fakultesi</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sercan YILMAZ</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>behavioral therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>overactive bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>urinary incontinence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

