<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02704156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ChanghaiHosp</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02704156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy Study of Five-fraction Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy to Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Safety and Efficacy of Five-fraction Stereotactic Body Radiation Therapy Treating Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer With cyberKnife—a Phase II Clinical Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Changhai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Changhai Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The safety and efficacy of five-fraction stereotactic body radiation therapy treating locally
      advanced pancreatic cancer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although the incidence rate of pancreatic cancer is not as high as that of other
      gastrointestinal carcinoma in China, the cancer mortalities of males and females ranked the
      sixth and seventh respectively in 2013, with a surprising low 5-year survival rate (&lt;5%).
      Only 15%-20% patients are suitable for surgeries among those first diagnosed with pancreatic
      cancer and the 5-year survival rate of patients with R0 resection is still less than 20%.

      Therefore, better efficacy cannot be achieved via surgery alone, which results in promotion
      of adjuvant chemoradiotherapy. In America, it has been accepted as a standard treatment
      contributing to the improved overall survival rates compared with surgery alone. Benefits of
      the treatment have also been proved in European studies. However, adjuvant chemoradiotherapy
      is not indicated for 21%-35% patients due to its high postoperative complication rates and
      worse recovery. Additionally, postoperative chemoradiotherapy would delay the initial time of
      intensified chemotherapy, along with the difficulty in target volume delineation and low
      tolerance doses of organs at risk.

      As a result, great emphasis has been placed on neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy, with
      predominant features in accurate target volume delineation, low complication rates of organs
      at risk, low tumor load before surgeries and prevention of the delay of postoperative
      treatment. Therefore, the inappropriate locally advanced pancreatic cancer patients (30%-80%)
      for surgeries can be operated via neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy. Nevertheless, long durations
      of conventional radiotherapy results in delay of the thereafter treatment.

      Compared with conventional radiation, a single-fraction dose and total dose of target volume
      can be increased in stereotactic body radiation therapy (SBRT). In addition, doses of organs
      at risk would be reduced, thus effectively improving local control rates and reducing
      radiation related toxicity. Shorter course of SBRT also enhance patients' compliance and
      render the initial of other treatment on schedule possible. Pollom et al. demonstrated that
      no significant differences were found in six-month and one-year overall survival rates
      between single-fraction SBRT and multi-fraction SBRT. However, potential trends indicated
      prolonged overall survivals in patients receiving multifractions. Moreover, the incidence of
      gastrointestinal toxicity is higher in single-fraction SBRT due to higher doses. Therefore,
      multi-fraction SBRT is more common in pancreatic cancer treatment. To the best of our
      knowledge, there are few studies on pancreatic cancer SBRT treatment, and these studies are
      retrospective with small patient population. Therefore, the investigators propose to conduct
      a phase II study: five-fraction SBRT as the initial treatment for locally advanced pancreatic
      cancer. Whether patients would receive thereafter treatment, including chemotherapy of
      surgeries, depends on their medical conditions.

      Study Procedure:

        1. CyberKnife SBRT body fixation (vacuum-bag) will be used in immobilizing the body, the
           arms and the legs. Patients will undergo a plain CT as well as an enhanced pancreatic
           parenchymal CT for radiation treatment planning and target delineation.

        2. SBRT will be delivered on CyberKnife with Synchrony Respiratory Tracking system. The
           tumor will be tracked with implanted fiducial markers by Fiducial Tracking System.
           Treatment will be delivered in 5 fractions within 1 to 2 weeks at the discretion of the
           investigator.

        3. A body fixation (vacuum-bag) will be used in immobilizing the body, the arms (both arms
           are along the body) and the legs.

        4. The total doses depend on patients' medical conditions, ranging from 32.5Gy-45Gy/5Fx.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The median survival time will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>One-, two- and three-year overall survival rates will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>1year, 2 years and 3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The acute toxicities following SBRT will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The acute toxicities are determined by RTOG Acute Radiation Morbidity Scoring Criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The late toxicities following SBRT will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The late toxicities are determined by RTOG/EORTC Late Radiation Morbidity Scoring Criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The median progression free survival time will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time to progression will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The clinical benefit rates will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The objective response rates will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The quality of life will be analyzed.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The analysis of quality of life is based on QLQ-C30 and QLQ-PAN26.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Five-fraction SBRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with locally advanced pancreatic cancer meeting all inclusion criteria will receive five-fraction SBRT/cyberknife as the initial treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyberknife</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Five-fraction SBRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Locally advanced pancreatic cancer proved by CT or MRI and biopsy

          2. Without any other treatment before SBRT

          3. A life expectancy of &gt;3months

          4. KPS≥70

          5. Age of 18-75 years old

          6. Blood routine examination: Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 ×109 cells/L,
             leukocyte count≥ 3.5 ×109 cells/L, platelets ≥ 70×109 cells/L, hemoglobin ≥ 8.0 g/dl

          7. Liver and kidney function tests: Albumin &gt; 2.5 g/dL, total bilirubin &lt; 3 mg/dL,
             creatinine &lt; 2.0 mg/dL, AST&lt;2.5 × ULN(Upper Limit of Normal)(0-64U/L), ALT&lt;2.5 ×
             ULN(0-64U/L)

          8. INR &lt; 2 (0.9-1.1)

          9. Ability of the research subject or authorized legal representative to understand and
             the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior surgery, chemotherapy or radiation for the pancreatic cancer

          2. Evidences of metastatic disease such as nodal or distant metastases by abdomen CT and
             chest CT or FDG PET-CT

          3. Contraindication to receiving radiotherapy

          4. KPS&lt;70

          5. Age&lt;18 or &gt;75

          6. Abnormal results of blood routine examinations and liver and kidney tests

          7. Patients with active inflammatory bowel diseases or peptic ulcer

          8. Gastrointestinal bleeding or perforation within 6 months

          9. Heart failure: NYHA III-IV

         10. Women who are pregnant

         11. Participation in another clinical treatment trial while on study

         12. Patients in whom fiducial implantation was not possible

         13. Inability of the research subject or authorized legal representative to understand and
             the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Huo Jun Zhang, MD., PH.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Changhai Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xiao Fei Zhu, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+8613120637884</phone>
    <email>zhuxiaofei_zxf@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Changhai hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200433</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Huojun Zhang, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+8613311732399</phone>
      <email>chyyzhj@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Huojun Zhang, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siegel R, Naishadham D, Jemal A. Cancer statistics, 2012. CA Cancer J Clin. 2012 Jan-Feb;62(1):10-29. doi: 10.3322/caac.20138. Epub 2012 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22237781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sener SF, Fremgen A, Menck HR, Winchester DP. Pancreatic cancer: a report of treatment and survival trends for 100,313 patients diagnosed from 1985-1995, using the National Cancer Database. J Am Coll Surg. 1999 Jul;189(1):1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10401733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richter A, Niedergethmann M, Sturm JW, Lorenz D, Post S, Trede M. Long-term results of partial pancreaticoduodenectomy for ductal adenocarcinoma of the pancreatic head: 25-year experience. World J Surg. 2003 Mar;27(3):324-9. Epub 2003 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>12607060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tseng JF, Raut CP, Lee JE, Pisters PW, Vauthey JN, Abdalla EK, Gomez HF, Sun CC, Crane CH, Wolff RA, Evans DB. Pancreaticoduodenectomy with vascular resection: margin status and survival duration. J Gastrointest Surg. 2004 Dec;8(8):935-49; discussion 949-50.</citation>
    <PMID>15585381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoyer M, Roed H, Sengelov L, Traberg A, Ohlhuis L, Pedersen J, Nellemann H, Kiil Berthelsen A, Eberholst F, Engelholm SA, von der Maase H. Phase-II study on stereotactic radiotherapy of locally advanced pancreatic carcinoma. Radiother Oncol. 2005 Jul;76(1):48-53.</citation>
    <PMID>15990186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalser MH, Ellenberg SS. Pancreatic cancer. Adjuvant combined radiation and chemotherapy following curative resection. Arch Surg. 1985 Aug;120(8):899-903. Erratum in: Arch Surg 1986 Sep;121(9):1045.</citation>
    <PMID>4015380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oettle H, Post S, Neuhaus P, Gellert K, Langrehr J, Ridwelski K, Schramm H, Fahlke J, Zuelke C, Burkart C, Gutberlet K, Kettner E, Schmalenberg H, Weigang-Koehler K, Bechstein WO, Niedergethmann M, Schmidt-Wolf I, Roll L, Doerken B, Riess H. Adjuvant chemotherapy with gemcitabine vs observation in patients undergoing curative-intent resection of pancreatic cancer: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2007 Jan 17;297(3):267-77.</citation>
    <PMID>17227978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neoptolemos JP, Stocken DD, Tudur Smith C, Bassi C, Ghaneh P, Owen E, Moore M, Padbury R, Doi R, Smith D, Büchler MW. Adjuvant 5-fluorouracil and folinic acid vs observation for pancreatic cancer: composite data from the ESPAC-1 and -3(v1) trials. Br J Cancer. 2009 Jan 27;100(2):246-50. doi: 10.1038/sj.bjc.6604838. Epub 2009 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19127260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abbott DE, Baker MS, Talamonti MS. Neoadjuvant therapy for pancreatic cancer: a current review. J Surg Oncol. 2010 Mar 15;101(4):315-20. doi: 10.1002/jso.21469. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20187063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corsini MM, Miller RC, Haddock MG, Donohue JH, Farnell MB, Nagorney DM, Jatoi A, McWilliams RR, Kim GP, Bhatia S, Iott MJ, Gunderson LL. Adjuvant radiotherapy and chemotherapy for pancreatic carcinoma: the Mayo Clinic experience (1975-2005). J Clin Oncol. 2008 Jul 20;26(21):3511-6. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2007.15.8782.</citation>
    <PMID>18640932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herman JM, Swartz MJ, Hsu CC, Winter J, Pawlik TM, Sugar E, Robinson R, Laheru DA, Jaffee E, Hruban RH, Campbell KA, Wolfgang CL, Asrari F, Donehower R, Hidalgo M, Diaz LA Jr, Yeo C, Cameron JL, Schulick RD, Abrams R. Analysis of fluorouracil-based adjuvant chemotherapy and radiation after pancreaticoduodenectomy for ductal adenocarcinoma of the pancreas: results of a large, prospectively collected database at the Johns Hopkins Hospital. J Clin Oncol. 2008 Jul 20;26(21):3503-10. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2007.15.8469.</citation>
    <PMID>18640931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Timke C, Debus JP. [The role of radiation therapy in treatment of pancreatic cancer from the viewpoint of radio-oncologists]. Radiologe. 2009 Feb;49(2):149-53. doi: 10.1007/s00117-008-1758-y. Review. German.</citation>
    <PMID>19156394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>White RR, Tyler DS. Neoadjuvant therapy for pancreatic cancer: the Duke experience. Surg Oncol Clin N Am. 2004 Oct;13(4):675-84, ix-x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15350941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valentini V, Beets-Tan R, Borras JM, Krivokapić Z, Leer JW, Påhlman L, Rödel C, Schmoll HJ, Scott N, Velde CV, Verfaillie C. Evidence and research in rectal cancer. Radiother Oncol. 2008 Jun;87(3):449-74. doi: 10.1016/j.radonc.2008.05.022. Epub 2008 Jun 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18534701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spitz FR, Abbruzzese JL, Lee JE, Pisters PW, Lowy AM, Fenoglio CJ, Cleary KR, Janjan NA, Goswitz MS, Rich TA, Evans DB. Preoperative and postoperative chemoradiation strategies in patients treated with pancreaticoduodenectomy for adenocarcinoma of the pancreas. J Clin Oncol. 1997 Mar;15(3):928-37. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9060530</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krempien R, Muenter MW, Harms W, Debus J. Neoadjuvant chemoradiation in patients with pancreatic adenocarcinoma. HPB (Oxford). 2006;8(1):22-8. doi: 10.1080/13651820500468034.</citation>
    <PMID>18333234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moningi S, Marciscano AE, Rosati LM, Ng SK, Teboh Forbang R, Jackson J, Chang DT, Koong AC, Herman JM. Stereotactic body radiation therapy in pancreatic cancer: the new frontier. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther. 2014 Dec;14(12):1461-75. doi: 10.1586/14737140.2014.952286. Epub 2014 Sep 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25183386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berber B, Sanabria JR, Braun K, Yao M, Ellis RJ, Kunos CA, Sohn J, Machtay M, Teh BS, Huang Z, Mayr NA, Lo SS. Emerging role of stereotactic body radiotherapy in the treatment of pancreatic cancer. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther. 2013 Apr;13(4):481-7. doi: 10.1586/era.13.19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23560842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pollom EL, Alagappan M, von Eyben R, Kunz PL, Fisher GA, Ford JA, Poultsides GA, Visser BC, Norton JA, Kamaya A, Cox VL, Columbo LA, Koong AC, Chang DT. Single- versus multifraction stereotactic body radiation therapy for pancreatic adenocarcinoma: outcomes and toxicity. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2014 Nov 15;90(4):918-25. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2014.06.066. Epub 2014 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25585785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koong AC, Le QT, Ho A, Fong B, Fisher G, Cho C, Ford J, Poen J, Gibbs IC, Mehta VK, Kee S, Trueblood W, Yang G, Bastidas JA. Phase I study of stereotactic radiosurgery in patients with locally advanced pancreatic cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2004 Mar 15;58(4):1017-21.</citation>
    <PMID>15001240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 9, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Changhai Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhang Huo Jun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Radiation Oncology Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stereotactic body radiation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>CyberKnife</keyword>
  <keyword>Initial treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

