<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02707302</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>gztcm_001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02707302</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Surgical Adhesive Drapes for Prevention and Healing of Wound Infections After Total Hip Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>Iodophor-impregnated Versus Iodophor-free Adhesive Drapes for Prevention and Healing of Wound Infections After Total Hip Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Third Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Third Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to support the rational use of iodophor-impregnated surgical
      adhesive drapes for preventing wound infections after total hip arthroplasty.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Surgical-site infections, including deep-layer and superficial-layer wound infections, are
      common complications after total hip arthroplasty. Surgical infections lead to poor wound
      healing, increased hospital days, increased patient suffering and distress, higher costs, and
      even life-threatening events. Wound infections after total hip arthroplasty result in local
      pain, joint displacement, and reduced joint function. Compared with common bacterial
      infections, bacteria in the deep layer of the epidermis after total hip arthroplasty adhere
      to the metal prosthesis and bone cement, and may thus escape the immune system because of a
      lack of blood supply. Furthermore, the immune response contributes to the formation of a
      protective mucus layer on the prosthesis surface, and bacteria in this mucus layer may be
      protected from antibiotic intervention. Preventing surgical-site infection is thus an
      important factor determining the success of total hip arthroplasty. Measures to prevent
      surgical-site infection currently include instrument sterilization, protection of an aseptic
      area, and use of prophylactic antibacterial drugs, while reduced surgical-wound size and use
      of iodophor-impregnated antibacterial adhesive drapes have also been proposed to reduce
      infection.

      Surgical adhesive drapes can create an aseptic area around the wound, thus reducing the
      bacterial content and infection incidence. Compared with conventional iodophor-free
      polyethylene adhesive drapes, iodophor-impregnated polyester surgical adhesive drapes are
      more breathable and scalable, show better compliance, and provide better skin adhesion.
      Iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes attached to the sterilized surgical site can effectively
      inhibit intraoperative movement of bacteria, providing a persistent and effective protection
      against wound infection after total hip arthroplasty.

      Total hip arthroplasty involves a long operation and has a high risk of wound infection.
      Iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes are recommended because the iodophor-impregnated viscose
      persistently releases iodine ions to help maintain aseptic skin throughout surgery.
      Iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes have been shown to decrease the incidence of wound
      infection and show broad-spectrum antibacterial activity for several hours, unaffected by
      body fluids and blood, compared with iodophor-free adhesive drapes. Iodophor-impregnated
      adhesive drapes have been reported to reduce surgical-site infection in orthopedic surgery.
      However, few studies have reported on the use of antibacterial surgical adhesive drapes in
      China, though Ling et al. reported that they decreased the incidence of surgical-site
      infection. However, despite evidence suggesting that 3M iodophor-impregnated antibacterial
      adhesive drapes can reduce bacteria at the surgical site, prevent wound infection, and
      promote wound healing.

      Although the effects of surgical adhesive drapes on wound infection have been extensively
      studied, to the best of our knowledge, no clinical study has compared the effects of
      iodophor-impregnated and iodophor-free antibacterial adhesive drapes on wound infection
      caused by bacteria in the deep layer of the epidermis. We hypothesized that 3M
      iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes would inhibit bacteria around the surgical wound and in
      the deep layer of the epidermis after total hip arthroplasty, and promote wound healing more
      effectively than 3M iodophor-free adhesive drapes. We aim to validate this hypothesis in a
      single-center, randomized, double-blinded, and controlled clinical trial.

      Data collection, preservation, and monitoring Data will be collected on paper case-report
      forms and summarized in a table. The written records will be transferred to an electronic
      format using a double-data entry strategy. The trial process will be monitored by
      professional clinical research associates will full access to all essential documents to
      ensure patient safety and complete clinical data, including compliance with the
      informed-consent procedure, and evaluation of primary endpoints and compliance. In addition
      to regular site visits, the clinical research associates will also communicate with the trial
      center via e-mail and phone. If any patient(s) withdraws from the trial, an
      intention-to-treat analysis of related records should be performed, otherwise the patient's
      records will be deleted. The reasons for patient withdrawal should be recorded in the medical
      records.

      Statistical analysis All data will be analyzed statistically using Statistical Product and
      Service Solutions 10.0 software. Quantitative baseline data will be compared using two-sample
      t-tests and Mann-Whitney U tests, and qualitative data using χ2 or Fisher's exact probability
      tests. Differences in VAS and Harris scores between the iodophor-impregnated and
      iodophor-free adhesive drapes groups will be evaluated by two-sample t-tests. Non-normally
      distributed data will be converted or comparisons of primary and secondary outcomes prior to
      and after interventions will be compared between the groups using two-sample t-tests.
      Bacterial detection rates in peri-wound tissue and grade I wound-healing rates between the
      two groups will be compared by χ2 tests. A level of P &lt; 0.05 will be considered statistically
      significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>bacterial detection rate in the peri-wound tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time to bacterial culture</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>wound-healing time</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>wound-healing grade</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Wound-healing grade I = excellent wound healing without adverse reactions; grade II = inflammation including red swelling, sclerosis, hematoma and hydrops of the skin, but no suppuration; and grade III = wound suppuration and need for wound incision and drainage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pain evaluated by the Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hip-joint function, evaluated by Harris hip score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Hip Replacement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes group, routine disinfection will be carried out and bacteria samples will be harvested 1 cm from the wound site using sterilized swabs prior to use of the surgical adhesive drapes, and again at the end of surgery before skin suturing, for preoperative bacterial culture. The packaging of the 3M™ iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes will be opened and the aseptic adhesive drapes unfolded until the &quot;stop&quot; instruction. The adhesive drapes will then be pasted to the surgical wound and smoothed using an aseptic cloth, taking care to avoid air bubbles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iodophor-free adhesive drapes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the iodophor-free adhesive drapes group will undergo the same procedures, but with iodophor-free drapes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes group</intervention_name>
    <description>Odd-numbered patients are randomized to the iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes group.3M™ loban™2 iodophor-impregnated adhesive drape(3M Company, St. Paul, Minnesota, USA) will be used at the surgical site in the iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iodophor-impregnated adhesive drapes</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iodophor-free adhesive drapes group</intervention_name>
    <description>Even-numbered patients are randomized to the iodophor-free adhesive drapes group. Iodophor-free aseptic adhesive drapes(3M Company, St. Paul, Minnesota, USA) will be used at the surgical site in the iodophor-free adhesive drapes group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iodophor-free adhesive drapes</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age ≥18 years;

          -  either sex;

          -  able to tolerate anesthesia and surgery;

          -  hip-joint disease causing chronic discomfort and obvious joint-function disorders
             (including primary or secondary coxarthrosis, avascular necrosis of the femoral head,
             rheumatoid arthritis involving the hip joint, ankylosing spondylitis involving the hip
             joint, hip fracture (in older), tumor in the bone joint, and hemophilic arthritis);

          -  informed consent signed by patients, relatives or guardians and approved by the
             Hospital Ethics Committee.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  allergy to antiseptics, such as iodophor;

          -  scheduled surgical area with red swelling and ulceration; positive bacterial cultures
             in the first detection;

          -  participation in other clinical trials within 30 days prior to recruitment; pregnancy;

          -  human immunodeficiency virus type I and/or hepatitis virus infection; neurogenic
             disease, any disease presenting with rapid bone destruction, poor muscular strength
             around the hip joint, or complicated by other organ diseases; systemic or local severe
             bacterial infection; poor surgical tolerance;

          -  emotional disturbance;

          -  inability to complete the clinical trial because of poor compliance;

          -  unsuitability for the clinical trial according to the researchers.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhuo Wu, Master</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital of Bone Injury, Guangzhou University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Third Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhuo Wu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wound Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

