<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02707133</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Nevus Protocol v1.0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02707133</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validation of a Virtual Model of Service Delivery for Choroidal Nevi</brief_title>
  <official_title>Validation of a Virtual Clinic for Choroidal Nevomelanocytic Lesions: Safety, Patient Acceptability and Health Economics Analysis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Health Research, United Kingdom</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Choroidal nevomelanocytic lesions have a high prevalence affecting up to 7% of the entire
      population and are increasingly incidentally identified during routine eye check- ups in
      community optometry services. Given the tendency to err on the side of caution, there is
      evidence of excessive referrals challenging service delivery in both tertiary eye units and
      specialist ocular oncology services. Although previous studies have examined the natural
      history and risk factors for growth of choroidal nevomelanocytic lesions, optimal delivery of
      management remains uncertain. Management approaches display diversity with respect to the
      number and type of baseline investigations, the duration and frequency of monitoring of
      relevant patients. Utilisation of the skills of allied health professionals in appropriate
      cases would allow streamlining service delivery in a socialised healthcare system, maximise
      capacity, and allow community services to play an enhanced role. However, the evidence for
      this model of delivery is lacking. Within existing models of care for these lesions, patients
      are faced with delays, need for more than one attendances to the hospital and increased
      anxiety around prognosis.

      This project aims to answer the question of whether these low-risk, bland incidental findings
      might possibly be managed by allied health professionals with the use of clinical imaging and
      specific algorithms to make appropriate management decisions. We aim to validate a model of
      service delivery on a virtual basis that will accommodate for capacity pressures to accept
      all relevant referrals, while offering a safe service and optimising patient experience of
      care. We will thus validate the setting up of a virtual choroidal nevomelanocytic clinic in
      terms of safety and patient acceptability. More specifically, the degree of agreement between
      management decisions made by non-medical graders on the basis of imaging data alone as
      opposed to gold standard decisions (clinical and imaging tests combined) is examined. Health
      economics analysis of the proposed service delivery model will be undertaken to demonstrate
      cost-effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of agreement (kappa co-efficient) between management decisions reached clinically as opposed to those reached on the basis of imaging tests alone (virtual model)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Validation of the virtual model of service delivery will be sought by calculating the degree of agreement (kappa co-efficient) between management decisions (Discharge, Review or Refer patients) reached by direct clinical examination as opposed to decisions reached through assessing imaging tests only.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Choroidal Nevus</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients under the care of MREH and MEH for ocular nevomelanocytic lesions (CNL) will be
        recruited prospectively into the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        All patients attending the CNL clinics of MREH/MEH who have offered informed consent will
        be included in the study. Patients who are then diagnosed with alternate pathologies other
        than CNL (erroneous referrals) will be excluded from agreement analysis. Recognition of
        alternate pathologies by non-medical graders will, however, be an additional outcome
        measure for this project. Cases of Congenital Hypertrophy of the Retinal Pigment Epithelium
        (CHRPE) will be classified as 'alternate pathology' for the purposes of this study.
        Exclusion criteria will be media opacities (cornea, lens, vitreous body) precluding
        adequate visualisation of fundus and incomplete set of imaging data.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Konstantinos Balaskas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Consultant and Honorary Clinical Lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

