<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00613470</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>170-05</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01GM061388</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UL1RR024150</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00613470</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacodynamics and Pharmacokinetics of Citalopram and Escitalopram</brief_title>
  <acronym>PGRN-SSRI</acronym>
  <official_title>Pharmacodynamics and Pharmacokinetics of Citalopram and Escitalopram</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of General Medical Sciences (NIGMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Research Resources (NCRR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is one component of a larger U01 grant that was submitted in August, 2004 to the
      NIGMS as part of the Pharmacogenomic Research Network. This study will enroll 1200 patients
      over 4 years.

      It is known that functionally significant genetic polymorphisms for the cytochrome P450
      (CYPs) can contribute to individual differences in response to specific selective serotonin
      reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs). However, a better understanding of the pharmacogenomics of both
      PK and PD for SSRI antidepressants will inform clinical practice. Therefore, we propose to
      evaluate the contribution of pharmacogenomics to variation in response to the highly specific
      SSRIs citalopram (a racemic mixture) and escitalopram (a chiral compound containing the
      active S-isomer of citalopram ) by correlating both PK and PD variation for these agents with
      intragene haplotypes in genes encoding proteins involved in citalopram metabolism, as well as
      central nervous system (CNS) pathways for monoamine neurotransmitter biosynthesis,
      metabolism, storage, release, reuptake, and receptors. In the future this &quot;candidate pathway&quot;
      intragene haplotype genotyping strategy will also be complemented by the application of
      genome-wide screens performed with DNA from subjects with extreme phenotypes for response to
      citalopram.

      Phenotypes to be measured before and after the initiation of citalopram or escitalopram
      therapy will include determinations of serum citalopram and metabolite concentrations,
      treatment response as measured by Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression indices, and number
      and severity of side effects as determined by structured questionnaires. The hypothesis to be
      tested is that inherited variation in citalopram metabolism and transport (PK) and/or PD
      variation as a result of inherited variation in monoamine neurotransmitter biosynthesis,
      metabolism, reuptake, storage, receptors or signaling contribute to individual variation in
      citalopram antidepressant efficacy and/or side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in HRS-D17 will constitute the major research outcome measure used to assess drug response phenotype because it is widely used in psychiatric research, making it possible to perform comparisons with other studies.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 week and 8 week visits</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QIDS-C16 (obtained by the CRC), and the QIDS-SR16</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 4, and 8</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">927</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Citalopram and escitalopram</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Citalopram tablet or solution starting at 20 mg, increase to 40 mg at 4 weeks if QIDS-C16 &gt; 5, keep at same dose if QIDS-C16 &lt; 5.
Escitalopram tablets starting at 10 mg, increase to 20 mg at 4 weeks if QIDS-C16 &gt; 5, keep at same dose if QIDS-C16 &lt; 5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>citalopram and escitalopram</intervention_name>
    <description>escitalopram tablets starting at 10 mg, increase to 20 mg at 4 weeks if QIDS-C16 &gt; 5, keep at same dose if QIDS-C16 &lt; 5.
citalopram tablet or solution starting at 2o mg, increase to 40 mg at 4 weeks if QIDS-C16 &gt; 5, keep at same dose if QIDS-C16 &lt; 5.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Citalopram and escitalopram</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Outpatients or inpatients with nonpsychotic MDD.

          2. A score of &gt;14 on the HRS-D17 (equivalent to 10 or greater on PHQ-9 which is used in
             primary care to assess depression) given that when medication exceeds the effect of
             placebo in primary care participants have a HRS-D17 &gt;12. We added 2 HRS-D17 points to
             take into account the possibility of measurement error.

          3. Outpatients or inpatients for whom antidepressant treatment is deemed appropriate by
             the treating clinician.

          4. Subjects who are between 18-85 years of age.

          5. Participants who have general medical conditions (GMCs) which could conceivably be
             physiologically causing their depressive symptoms will receive treatment as usual for
             their GMCs as well as for their MDD.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with medical contraindications that preclude citalopram or escitalopram
             treatment and those who have previously failed to respond to citalopram or
             escitalopram will be excluded. In addition, patients with schizophrenia,
             schizoaffective disorder, or who have Bipolar I disorder will be excluded because they
             have a primary psychiatric condition that requires a different initial treatment.
             Subjects currently on antidepressant medication with subtherapeutic results in terms
             of depression management will undergo a medication taper and discontinuation prior to
             initiation of citalopram or escitalopram treatment. The subject will be closely
             monitored by the primary physician or psychiatrist during the medication taper and
             discontinuation phase. The medication taper is left upto the treating physician's or
             psychiatrist's discretion. Study subjects who cannot be safely tapered from their
             medication or experience adverse effects during the taper will be excluded from the
             study. Study subjects using their antidepressant medication for management of nicotine
             dependence, chronic pain, migraine prophylaxis or other diagnoses will not be eligible
             for the study. Trazodone, Melatonin, and Diphenhydramine may be used as rescue
             medications for insomnia. Benzodiazepines may be used for treatment of anxiety and
             atomoxetine may be used for the treatment of attention deficit disorder. Study
             subjects currently on antipsychotic medications (e.g., typical and atypical
             antipsychotic drugs) and mood stabilizing agents (e.g., lithium, carbamazepine,
             valproate, lamotrigine, gabapentin, or other anticonvulsants) are not eligible for the
             study with the exception of those starting quetiapine after baseline. Subjects unable
             to give informed consent are excluded. Pregnant subjects will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel K Hall-Flavin, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 30, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 13, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 16, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 16, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel K. Hall-Flavin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, Assistant Professor of Psychiatry, College of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Antidepressants</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Citalopram</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexetimide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

