<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03109093</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GMALL-MOLACT1-BLINA</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-000733-76</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03109093</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blinatumomab in Adult Patients With Minimal Residual Disease (MRD) of B-precursor Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Single-arm Study to Assess the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of the BiTE® Antibody Blinatumomab in Adult Patients With Minimal Residual Disease (MRD) of B-precursor Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (Blast Successor Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Goethe University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Goethe University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to confirm the efficacy, safety, and tolerability of blinatumomab in
      patients with MRD of B- precursor ALL in complete hematological remission including patients
      with relapse after SCT. The study aims to expand experience generated in previous trials in
      patients with MRD positive ALL with a focus on additional specific questions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Transfer of patients to alloHSCT after one cycle or after subsequent cycles is considered as
      per protocol discontinuation and as premature treatment discontinuation In case of
      hematological or extramedullary relapse, the study treatment will be permanently
      discontinued.

      There will be a safety follow-up visit at 30 days after end of the last infusion. There will
      be efficacy follow-up until 18 months after treatment start. In patients scheduled for SCT
      the 30-day safety-visit may be performed at the latest time point possible before initiation
      of subsequent treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MRD response after one cycle</measure>
    <time_frame>after one cycle of treatment (up to 43 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who achieve complete MRD response after one cycle of treatment with blinatumomab in patients with and without prior SCT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continuous complete remission</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months following initiation of blinatumomab</time_frame>
    <description>Probability of continuous complete remission (remission duration) at 18 months following initiation of blinatumomab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematological relapse-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months following initiation of blinatumomab</time_frame>
    <description>Probability of hematological relapse-free survival rate at 18 months following initiation of blinatumomab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months following initiation of blinatumomab</time_frame>
    <description>Probability of overall survival at 18 months following initiation of blinatumomab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse localisations</measure>
    <time_frame>In Case of Relapse, continuously until End of Follow-Up (up to 18 Months)</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of different relapse localisations in proportion to total hematological relapses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biological evaluation of hematological and extramedullary relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>In Case of Relapse, continuously until End of Follow-Up (up to 18 Months)</time_frame>
    <description>Biological evaluation of hematological and extramedullary relapses including CD19 expression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious Adverse Event (SAE) incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>continuously until End of Safety-Follow-Up (up to 26 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Overall incidence and severity of adverse events in patients with and without prior SCT (CTCAE 4.0)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MRD response after two cycles</measure>
    <time_frame>after two cycles of treatment (up to 85 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who achieve complete MRD response after two cycles of treatment with blinatumomab in patients with and without prior SCT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>duration of MRD response</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months following initiation of blinatumomab</time_frame>
    <description>Probability of continuous MRD response and complete MRD response and duration of MRD response at 18 months following initiation of blinatumomab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to MRD response</measure>
    <time_frame>MRD determination after each cycle of treatment (up to 24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Time to MRD response measured by time-point of first achievement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GvHD</measure>
    <time_frame>until End of Safety-Follow-Up (up to 26 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of GvHD as part of AE documentation and according to Glucksberg Criteria, grade and localisation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>treatment related mortality after subsequent SCT</measure>
    <time_frame>after subsequent SCT (at day 100 and later)</time_frame>
    <description>• Evaluation of overall survival, remission duration, relapse-free survival and treatment related mortality (at day 100 and later) in patients with SCT in complete remission after blinatumomab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>treatment related mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>continuously until End of Follow-Up (up to 18 Months)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of overall survival, remission duration, relapse-free survival and treatment related mortality in patients without SCT in complete remission after blinatumomab</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>until End of Follow-Up (up to 18 Months)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of Quality of Life with EORTC instruments (EORTC QLQ C30 and EQ-5D) at different time-points during treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment deviation1</measure>
    <time_frame>until end of treatment (up to 22 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of dose reductions</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment deviation2</measure>
    <time_frame>until end of treatment (up to 22 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>incidence of treatment interruptions</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment deviation3</measure>
    <time_frame>until end of treatment (up to 22 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>days of interruption</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment deviation4</measure>
    <time_frame>until end of treatment (up to 22 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>withdrawals</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment deviation5</measure>
    <time_frame>until end of treatment (up to 22 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>total delivered dose</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment deviation6</measure>
    <time_frame>until end of treatment (up to 22 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>total days of treatment</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment deviation7</measure>
    <time_frame>until end of treatment (up to 22 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>realisation rate calculated as scheduled total dose/delivered total dose</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalisation days</measure>
    <time_frame>until end of treatment (up to 22 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of hospitalisation days</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>ALL, Recurrent, Adult</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Blinatumomab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive four cycles of treatment, unless criteria for treatment discontinuation apply. The duration of one cycle is 6 weeks, including a four week continuous intravenous infusion and a two week infusion free interval, which may be extended by a maximum of 7 days.
Transfer of patients to alloHSCT after one cycle or after subsequent cycles is considered as per protocol discontinuation and as premature treatment discontinuation In case of hematological or extramedullary relapse, the study treatment will be permanently discontinued.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blinatumomab</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive blinatumomab at a dose of 28 µg/day as continuous intravenous infusion at constant flow rate for four weeks, followed by a two-week infusion free interval, defined as one treatment cycle. Up to of four cycles will be performed.
In case of defined toxicities, the dose of blinatumomab may be reduced to 9µg/day.
Patients with an MRD relapse may qualify to receive additional treatment with blinatumomab.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Blinatumomab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>blincyto</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with CD19 positive B-precursor ALL in complete hematological remission
             defined as less than 5% blasts in bone marrow after at least three intense
             chemotherapy blocks (e.g., GMALL induction I-II/consolidation I).

          2. Presence of minimal residual disease (MRD) at a level of ≥10-4 (molecular failure or
             molecular relapse) in an assay with a minimum sensitivity of 10-4 documented after an
             interval of at least 2 weeks from last systemic chemotherapy

          3. For evaluation of MRD patients must have at least one molecular marker based on
             individual rearrangements of immunoglobulin, TCR-genes or other suitable genes
             evaluated by the reference laboratory of the trial

          4. Bone marrow function as defined below:

               -  ANC (Neutrophils) &gt;= 1,000/µL

               -  Platelets &gt;= 50,000/µL (transfusion permitted)

               -  HB level &gt;= 9g/dl (transfusion permitted)

          5. Renal and hepatic function as defined below:

               -  AST (GOT), ALT (GPT), and AP &lt; 5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x ULN (unless related to Gilbert's Meulengracht disease)

               -  Creatinine &lt; 1.5x ULN

               -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min (e.g. calculated according Cockroft&amp;Gault)

          6. Negative HIV test, negative hepatitis B (HbsAg) and hepatitis C virus (anti-HCV) test

          7. Negative pregnancy test in women of childbearing potential

          8. ECOG Performance Status 0 or 1

          9. Age &gt;=18 years

         10. Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent

         11. Signed and dated written informed consent is available

         12. Participation in the registry of the German Multicenter Study Group for Adult ALL
             (GMALL)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Ph/BCR-ABL positive ALL

          2. Presence of circulating blasts or current extramedullary involvement by ALL

          3. History or presence of clinically relevant CNS pathology (e.g. seizure, paresis,
             aphasia, cerebrovascular ischemia/hemorrhage, severe brain injuries, dementia,
             Parkinson's disease, cerebellar disease, organic brain syndrome or psychosis)

          4. Current detection of ALL blast cells in cerebro-spinal fluid

          5. History of or active relevant autoimmune disease

          6. Systemic cancer chemotherapy within 2 weeks prior to study treatment (except for
             intrathecal prophylaxis)

          7. Radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to study treatment

          8. Live vaccination within 2 weeks before the start of study treatment

          9. Autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (SCT) within six weeks prior to
             study treatment

         10. Allogeneic SCT within 12 weeks before the start of study treatment

         11. Any active acute Graft-versus-Host Disease (GvHD), grade 2-4 according to the
             Glucksberg criteria or active chronic GvHD requiring systemic treatment

         12. Any systemic therapy against GvHD within 2 weeks before start of study treatment

         13. Therapy with monoclonal antibodies (rituximab, alemtuzumab) within 4 weeks prior to
             study treatment

         14. Treatment with any investigational product within four weeks prior to study treatment

         15. Previous treatment with blinatumomab or other anti-CD19-therapy

         16. Known hypersensitivity to immunoglobulins or to any other component of the study drug
             formulation

         17. History of malignancy other than ALL diagnosed within 5 years prior to start of
             protocol-specified therapy with the exception of:

               -  Adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer or lentigo maligna without evidence
                  of disease

               -  Adequately treated cervical carcinoma in situ without evidence of disease

               -  Adequately treated breast ductal carcinoma in situ without evidence of disease

               -  Prostatic intraepithelial neoplasia without evidence of prostate cancer

         18. Active infection, any other concurrent disease or medical condition that are deemed to
             interfere with the conduct of the study as judged by the investigator

         19. Nursing women

         20. Woman of childbearing potential and is not willing to use 2 highly effective methods
             of contraception while receiving study treatment and for an additional 3 months after
             the last dose of study treatment.

         21. Male who has a female partner of childbearing potential, and is not willing to use 2
             highly effective forms of contraception while receiving study treatment and for at
             least an additional 3 months after the last dose of study treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicola Goekbuget, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>GMALL-Study-Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>GMALL Study Center</last_name>
    <phone>+49 (0)69 - 6301</phone>
    <phone_ext>6366</phone_ext>
    <email>gmall@em.uni-frankfurt.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Frankfurt (Main)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt (Main)</city>
        <state>Hessen</state>
        <zip>60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>GMALL Study Center</last_name>
      <phone>+496963016366</phone>
      <email>gmall@em.uni-frankfurt.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicola Gökbuget, Dr. med.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité - Campus Benjamin Franklin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefan Schwarz, PD Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uniklinik Dresden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nael Alakel, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univeristätsklinikum Essen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andreas Hüttmann, PD Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Freiburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freiburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ralph Wäsch, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uniklinik Hamburg Eppendorf</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Walter Fiedler, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinik Leipzig</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dietger Niederwieser, Prof. Dr. Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum Mannheim</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniela Heidenreich, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinkum Gießen und Marburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jörg Hoffmann, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum Großhadern</name>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marion Subklewe, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Robert - Bosch - Krankenhaus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stuttgart</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sonja Martin, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinik Tübingen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tübingen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christoph Faul, Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinkum Ulm</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andreas Viardot, PD Dr.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.kompetenznetz-leukaemie.de/content/home/index_ger.html</url>
    <description>Trial Register of the Kompetenznetz Leukämien, additional trial information</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.uct-frankfurt.de/content/studien/studien/studienregister/index_ger.html</url>
    <description>Trial register of University Cancer Center Frankfurt, additional trial information</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Goethe University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nicola Goekbuget</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ALL</keyword>
  <keyword>acute lymphoblastic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>MRD positive</keyword>
  <keyword>minimal residual disease</keyword>
  <keyword>blinatumomab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm, Residual</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Blinatumomab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Bispecific</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

