<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03106584</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LS-17-10-Delahunt-DeVito</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03106584</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Marigot Osteoarthritis Nutritional Intervention (MOANi) Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>MOANi</acronym>
  <official_title>Investigating the Potential for Marigot's Nutrition Supplement to Improve Symptoms and Physical Function in Those With Mild to Moderate Knee Osteoarthritis (KOA) Versus the Current Market Leader (Glucosamine Sulphate)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College Dublin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Marigot Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College Dublin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to test 30 individuals with mild-moderate knee joint
      osteoarthritis to investigate whether the combination of Aquamin (a calcium-rich marine
      multi-mineral) and a polyphenol-rich pine bark extract (Enzogenol), when taken as a food
      supplement for 3 months has comparable or superior benefits to glucosamine sulphate in
      patients with painful knee osteoarthritis (KOA). From here on in we refer to Aquamin's
      combination product as Aquamin-plus. The main outcome measure is a reduction in pain.

      Provision of data that demonstrate preliminary equivalency or superiority to current,
      non-pharmaceutical options such as glucosamine will broaden consumer choice, and provide them
      with an option that is supported by science, rather than marketing alone.

      The hypothesis of the study is that the consumption of Aquamin-plus will have comparable
      effects on reducing pain in individuals with Knee Joint OA to glucosamine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project will be a double blinded randomized cross-over control (pilot) trial that will
      investigate whether the combination of Aquamin (a calcium-rich marine multi-mineral) and a
      polyphenol-rich pine bark extract (Enzogenol), when taken as a food supplement for 3 months
      (12 weeks) has comparable or superior benefits to glucosamine sulphate in patients with
      painful knee osteoarthritis (KOA). From here on in we refer to Aquamin's combination product
      as Aquamin-plus. The main outcome measure is a reduction in pain (WOMAC index) and improve
      physical function (6MWD and TUG).

      The hypothesis of the study is that the consumption of Aquamin-plus for a period of 3 months
      will have comparable or superior effects on to glucosamine sulphate in reducing pain and
      improving physical function in individuals with KOA.

      According to the Food and Drug Administration et al. osteoarthritis (OA) can be defined as a
      serious disease or condition because, among other aspects, it is &quot;…associated with morbidity
      that has substantial impact on day-to-day functioning…&quot; . Furthermore, the current
      Osteoarthritis Research Society International (OARSI) definition of OA has been proposed as,
      &quot;OA is a disorder involving movable joints characterized by cell stress and extracellular
      matrix degradation initiated by micro- and macro-injury that activates maladaptive repair
      responses including pro-inflammatory pathways of innate immunity. The disease manifests first
      as a molecular derangement (abnormal joint tissue metabolism) followed by anatomic, and/or
      physiologic derangements (characterized by cartilage degradation, bone remodeling, osteophyte
      formation, joint inflammation and loss of normal joint function), that can culminate in
      illness&quot;

      The condition can be characterized as a branch of rheumatic disease that is a progressive
      condition of synovial joints and is caused by the failure of a joint to repair following
      damage. This damage may have been caused by stresses due to an abnormality in the articular
      cartilage, subchondral bone, ligaments, menisci, periarticular muscles, peripheral nerves or
      synovium. Failure of these normal biological processes leads to breakdown of cartilage and
      bone and is characterized by symptoms of pain, stiffness, functional disability and can and
      lead to negative effects on fatigue, mood, sleep and overall quality of life. OA has the
      highest frequency of all rheumatic diseases and is one of the most prevalent chronic diseases
      in the modern day. According to the Global Burden of Disease (GBD) study, progressive ageing
      of the population could make OA the ninth cause of disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) in
      developed countries by the year 2020, with KOA accounting for 83% of the total OA burden.

      Investigations into the heritability of OA have identified some interesting results. In a
      British twin cohort, the genetic contribution to radiographically defined hip and KOA was
      estimated to 39-65% in women with a Danish twin studies finding similar variance in hip
      arthroplasty due to OA (47%) but only 18% for knee arthroplasty due to OA. However, more
      recent data from a larger cohort (n = 9058) showed a heritability of 73% and 45% in hip and
      knee arthroplasty, respectively. Interestingly, identified that while hip OA associated
      arthroplasty remains highly heritable regardless of environmental factors, while the genetic
      component of KOA (for arthroplasty) was significantly modifiable with increasing BMI. These
      data show the requirement for clinical interventions to focus on symptomatic KOA,
      particularly considering the exponentially increasing BMI and obesity in the western world.

      Data from The Irish Longitudinal Study on Ageing (TILDA) show that approximately 13%
      (women-17.3%, men-9.4%; self-reported) of Irish residence over the age of 50 suffer from
      symptomatic OA, with 19.2% of those reporting symptomatic KOA. These are similar to data from
      Arthritis Research UK showing an 18% prevalence of patients visiting a general practitioner
      presenting with symptoms of KOA. Moreover, these reported incidence rates are estimated to
      raise in tandem with population age (Arthritis Research UK, 2013). In fact, the prevalence of
      KOA in the US is 25% and increases by 2% each year, likely due to the aging population (as in
      the UK) and raising obesity rate, with a lifetime risk of symptomatic KOA as high as 60.5 %
      in obese individuals.

      Joint pain is the most common complaint among those who seek medical care for OA and as a
      result of OA pain 80% of individuals with have some degree of movement limitation, 25% cannot
      perform major activities of daily living and 11% of adults with KOA need help with personal
      care. Consequentially, OA can lead to negative effects on quality of life, mood, fatigue and
      sleep. Interestingly, poor sleep occurs in ~70% of older individuals with OA and is linked
      with fatigue, which in turn is associated with a greater fall risk in the elderly and
      identifies fatigue as a further concern, in addition to joint instability, of fall-related
      complications.

      OA is a progressive condition with no cure, however treatments do exist aimed at reducing
      symptoms and slowing progression of the disease. This in turn will improve mobility, quality
      of life and leads to a reduction in the need joint replacement surgery in the long-term and
      consequently reduces the demand on healthcare resource. Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs
      (NSAID) are the traditional approach for clinical management of mild-to-moderate OA symptoms,
      however NSAIDs have been associated with potentially harmful side effects such as
      gastrointestinal complications, renal disturbances and cardiovascular events. Therefore,
      non-pharmaceutical alternatives have been developed such as glucosamine compounds, however
      the reported efficacy for reducing OA symptoms varies. Nonetheless, while glucosamine
      compounds have a lower risk of adverse effects compared to NSAIDs and other symptomatic
      slow-acting drugs for OA (SYSADOA), glucosamine compounds show higher risk of adverse side
      effects than placebo and as such alternatives should be sought. Further to possible adverse
      health effects, NSAIDs and SYASDOAs are costly and greatly affect the socioeconomic health of
      patients with OA. A recent meta-analysis of global generalized OA has shown that the
      individual annual incremental healthcare costs ranged from €705 to €19,715 and concluded that
      the social cost of OA could be between 0.25% and 0.50% of a country's GDP. More specifically,
      the individual cost of KOA (both social healthcare and private) can range from €528 to €11293
      depending of severity. In fact, Hunter et al. recently called for urgent action to focus
      attention on opportunities to reduce the individual and socioeconomic burden of OA.

      Glucosamine supplementation for the treatment of OA and OA related phenotypes spans many
      decades, with the first (to the authors' knowledge) patent filled in 1969 and research on
      human derived glucosamine published long before. The earliest identifiable mention (to the
      authors' knowledge) of Aqumin is from the late 90's with a patent, containing Aqumin, filled
      for human consumption in 2003, &quot;Algae-based food supplement&quot;. Therefore, there is a
      significant advantage for glucosamine in the accumulation of large high quality studies into
      its therapeutic effects. Nonetheless, the few small pilot studies concerned with the
      therapeutic effects of Aquamin supplementation show promising results in comparison to both
      placebo and Glucosamine formulas. In fact, for some important OA phenotypes, Aquamin performs
      better, particularly in the reduction of NSAID use. While the proposed mechanisms of action
      differ considerable between the two supplements, inflammatory reduction occurs because of
      both. Currently, there have been no long-term trials concerned with the efficacy of Aquamin
      in the reduction of KOA related joint structural decline however, because Aquamin reduces
      inflammatory markers of KOA, albeit in only one small human study, it is possible that
      Aquamin might improve joint structural decline and KOA prognosis through possibly reducing
      joint tissue damage.

      This project will be a double blinded randomized cross-over control trial with a sample size
      of 30 participants (based off a sample size calculation detailed below). The project will
      investigate two supplements on their effects on self-reported pain, quality of life, knee
      extensor/flexor strength, knee extensor/flexor myoelectric activity, functional mobility and
      biomarkers associated with inflammation. The participants will first be assessed for baseline
      measurements of the outcome measures mentioned above. They will then be randomly allocated to
      either group A or B and will take either supplement A or B for a period of 12 weeks.
      Following this there will be follow up assessments of the same outcome measures. This will be
      followed by a 4-week washout period prior to each subjects' baseline measures being
      reassessed and each participant allocated the 'other' supplement. After 12 weeks'
      supplementation, the subjects will then be retested for a final time.

      An a priori sample size calculation indicated a total of 29 patients was required to enter
      this two-treatment crossover study to assess the primary outcomes. The probability is 80
      percent that the study will detect a treatment difference at a two-sided 0.05 significance
      level, if the true difference between treatments is 12.000 units. This is based on the
      assumption that the within-patient standard deviation of the response variable is 15.62.&quot;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The project is a double blind randomized controlled clinical trial (pilot), with a cross-over design. Participants, will be randomized to begin taking either Aquamin-plus or Glucosamine sulphate following medical diagnosis and baseline assessment.
Following 12 weeks of supplementation of Glucosamine sulphate or Aquamin-plus there will be a 4-week washout period before participants consume the other supplement.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The supplements provided by Marigot Ltd. will be marked either A or B. No member of the research team will be aware of the ingredients in either of the supplements, the only distinguishing feature will be the labels - A and B. It is for this reason that we can say that the study will be double blind as neither investigators nor participants will have any knowledge of the supplement that they will be consuming.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self reported KOA pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, mid intervention (4 and 8 weeks) post intervention (12 weeks), post washout period (16 weeks), mid intervention (20 and 24 weeks) post intervention (28 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure will be an assessment of the participants' knee pain. This will be measured using the validated Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index (WOMAC) pain and function sub-scale. This will allow for the determination of the comparability, superiority or otherwise of Aquamin-plus compared to glucosamine sulphate in improving participant's self-reported knee pain and function. Change from baseline assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed on 4 separate occasions: Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), post washout period (16 weeks), post intervention (28 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>This will be quantified by the EuroQoL-5D. The EuroQoL-5D will assess participants on their levels of function surrounding mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain / discomfort, anxiety / depression. Change from baseline assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee flexor and extensor muscle strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed on 4 separate occasions: Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), post washout period (16 weeks), post intervention (28 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants knee joint strength will be assessed using an isokinetic dynamometer (Cybex). Specifically isometric strength of the quadricep and hamstring muscles. Change from baseline assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee flexor and extensor muscle electrical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed on 4 separate occasions: Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), post washout period (16 weeks), post intervention (28 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Muscles activation (via electromyography) during the performance of the isometric testing will be assessed for the quadricep and hamstring muscles. Both the agonist and antagonist muscle activity will be assessed and a co-contraction value will be calculated. Change from baseline assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed on 4 separate occasions: Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), post washout period (16 weeks), post intervention (28 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Biomarkers known to be involved in the biological response to KOA will be assessed to investigate possible mechanistic effects and differences of both interventions. As such, in order to investigate these possible mechanistic parameters include venous blood sampling (10 mL). Change from baseline assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed on 4 separate occasions: Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), post washout period (16 weeks), post intervention (28 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed using the Six-minute Walk Test (6MWT) and the Timed Up and Go Test (TUG). These tests indicate levels of functional. Change from baseline assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed on 4 separate occasions: Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), post washout period (16 weeks), post intervention (28 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>A Dule-Energy X ray Absorptimetry (DEXA) will be used to assess participants body composition. Change from baseline assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glucosamine sulphate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Glucosamine sulphate will be consumed as either supplement A or B (i.e. blinded) for a period of 12-weeks. Glucosamine will be taken 2 times daily with food.
After 12 weeks of supplementation, participants will begin taking the alternative supplement (Aquamin-plus), after a washout period of not less than 1 month between the intervention arms of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aquamin-plus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aquamin-plus will be consumed as either supplement A or B (i.e. blinded) for a period of 12-weeks. Aquamin-plus will be taken 2 times daily with food.
After 12 weeks of supplementation, participants will begin taking the alternative supplement (Glucosamine sulphate), after a washout period of not less than 1 month between the intervention arms of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aquamin-Plus</intervention_name>
    <description>Aquamin (a calcium-rich marine multi-mineral) - 666.7mg magnesium hydroxide - 66.66mg pine bark - 30mg vitamin d3 - 2.5μg
Dosage:
4 Capsules is equal to effective dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Glucosamine sulphate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Aquamin-plus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucosamine sulphate</intervention_name>
    <description>The Glucosamine sulphate supplement contains 500mg of the active ingredient Glucosamine sulphate per serving (one capsule).
Dosage:
4 Capsules is equal to effective dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Glucosamine sulphate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Aquamin-plus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The project will focus on patients with a diagnosis of a mild-moderate KOA (level 1-3
        Kellgren and Lawrence and WOMAC in the lower two quartiles), in the target knee, (Frestedt
        et al., 2008) and a BMI between 20 and 30 kg/m2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        [1] rheumatoid arthritis [2] gout [3] pseudo gout [4] Paget's disease [5] seizure disorder
        [6] insulin dependent diabetes mellitus [7] uncontrolled hypertension [8] unstable
        cardiovascular disease [9] active hepatic or renal disease [10] active cancer and/or HIV
        infection, involved in other clinical trial or experimental treatments in the past 3
        months; pregnant, lactating, or at risk of becoming pregnant; intramuscular/systemic
        corticosteroid injection within 4 weeks; intra-articular corticosteroid injection within 2
        months; or inter-articular hyaluronic acid injection within 4 months prior to enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giuseppe De Vito, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>UCD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eamonn Delahunt, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Conor McCarthy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mater Misericordiae University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shane M Heffernan, Phd</last_name>
    <phone>00353 1 716 3433</phone>
    <email>shane.heffernan@ucd.ie</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mark McGroarty, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>00353 86 083 0034</phone>
    <email>mark.mcgroarty@ucd.ie</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institue for Sport and Health UCD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dublin</city>
        <state>Leinster</state>
        <zip>D04 V1W8</zip>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shane Heffernan, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>00353 1 716 3433</phone>
      <phone_ext>3433</phone_ext>
      <email>shane.heffernan@ucd.ie</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mark McGroarty, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>00353 86 0830034</phone>
      <email>mark.mcgroarty@ucd.ie</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ireland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.google.com/patents/EP1433388A1?cl=en</url>
    <description>Algae-based food supplement PATENT</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.google.com/patents/US3857938?dq=Rovati,+L.+(1972).&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiRusGNtOfSAhVEDMAKHRhzDcYQ6AEIIDAB</url>
    <description>Method of preparing a novel antacid pharmaceutical product PATENT</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frestedt JL, Walsh M, Kuskowski MA, Zenk JL. A natural mineral supplement provides relief from knee osteoarthritis symptoms: a randomized controlled pilot trial. Nutr J. 2008 Feb 17;7:9. doi: 10.1186/1475-2891-7-9.</citation>
    <PMID>18279523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frestedt JL, Kuskowski MA, Zenk JL. A natural seaweed derived mineral supplement (Aquamin F) for knee osteoarthritis: a randomised, placebo controlled pilot study. Nutr J. 2009 Feb 2;8:7. doi: 10.1186/1475-2891-8-7.</citation>
    <PMID>19187557</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy, C. T., et al.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kraus VB, Blanco FJ, Englund M, Karsdal MA, Lohmander LS. Call for standardized definitions of osteoarthritis and risk stratification for clinical trials and clinical use. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2015 Aug;23(8):1233-41. doi: 10.1016/j.joca.2015.03.036. Epub 2015 Apr 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25865392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lane NE, Brandt K, Hawker G, Peeva E, Schreyer E, Tsuji W, Hochberg MC. OARSI-FDA initiative: defining the disease state of osteoarthritis. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2011 May;19(5):478-82. doi: 10.1016/j.joca.2010.09.013. Epub 2011 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21396464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peña Ayala AH, Fernández-López JC. [Prevalence and risk factors in osteoarthritis]. Reumatol Clin. 2007 Oct;3 Suppl 3:S6-S12. doi: 10.1016/S1699-258X(07)73648-3. Epub 2008 Nov 13. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>21794484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy L, Schwartz TA, Helmick CG, Renner JB, Tudor G, Koch G, Dragomir A, Kalsbeek WD, Luta G, Jordan JM. Lifetime risk of symptomatic knee osteoarthritis. Arthritis Rheum. 2008 Sep 15;59(9):1207-13. doi: 10.1002/art.24021.</citation>
    <PMID>18759314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haq SA, Davatchi F. Osteoarthritis of the knees in the COPCORD world. Int J Rheum Dis. 2011 May;14(2):122-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1756-185X.2011.01615.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21518310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawrence RC, Felson DT, Helmick CG, Arnold LM, Choi H, Deyo RA, Gabriel S, Hirsch R, Hochberg MC, Hunder GG, Jordan JM, Katz JN, Kremers HM, Wolfe F; National Arthritis Data Workgroup. Estimates of the prevalence of arthritis and other rheumatic conditions in the United States. Part II. Arthritis Rheum. 2008 Jan;58(1):26-35. doi: 10.1002/art.23176.</citation>
    <PMID>18163497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carmona L, Ballina J, Gabriel R, Laffon A; EPISER Study Group. The burden of musculoskeletal diseases in the general population of Spain: results from a national survey. Ann Rheum Dis. 2001 Nov;60(11):1040-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11602475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haugen IK, Englund M, Aliabadi P, Niu J, Clancy M, Kvien TK, Felson DT. Prevalence, incidence and progression of hand osteoarthritis in the general population: the Framingham Osteoarthritis Study. Ann Rheum Dis. 2011 Sep;70(9):1581-6. doi: 10.1136/ard.2011.150078. Epub 2011 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21622766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hunter DJ, Schofield D, Callander E. The individual and socioeconomic impact of osteoarthritis. Nat Rev Rheumatol. 2014 Jul;10(7):437-41. doi: 10.1038/nrrheum.2014.44. Epub 2014 Mar 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24662640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kopec JA, Richardson CG, Llewellyn-Thomas H, Klinkhoff A, Carswell A, Chalmers A. Probabilistic threshold technique showed that patients' preferences for specific trade-offs between pain relief and each side effect of treatment in osteoarthritis varied. J Clin Epidemiol. 2007 Sep;60(9):929-38. Epub 2007 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>17689809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Magnusson K, Scurrah K, Ystrom E, Ørstavik RE, Nilsen T, Steingrímsdóttir ÓA, Ferreira P, Fenstad AM, Furnes O, Hagen KB. Genetic factors contribute more to hip than knee surgery due to osteoarthritis - a population-based twin registry study of joint arthroplasty. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2017 Jun;25(6):878-884. doi: 10.1016/j.joca.2016.12.015. Epub 2016 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27986619</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng M, Fleming T, Robinson M, Thomson B, Graetz N, Margono C, Mullany EC, Biryukov S, Abbafati C, Abera SF, Abraham JP, Abu-Rmeileh NM, Achoki T, AlBuhairan FS, Alemu ZA, Alfonso R, Ali MK, Ali R, Guzman NA, Ammar W, Anwari P, Banerjee A, Barquera S, Basu S, Bennett DA, Bhutta Z, Blore J, Cabral N, Nonato IC, Chang JC, Chowdhury R, Courville KJ, Criqui MH, Cundiff DK, Dabhadkar KC, Dandona L, Davis A, Dayama A, Dharmaratne SD, Ding EL, Durrani AM, Esteghamati A, Farzadfar F, Fay DF, Feigin VL, Flaxman A, Forouzanfar MH, Goto A, Green MA, Gupta R, Hafezi-Nejad N, Hankey GJ, Harewood HC, Havmoeller R, Hay S, Hernandez L, Husseini A, Idrisov BT, Ikeda N, Islami F, Jahangir E, Jassal SK, Jee SH, Jeffreys M, Jonas JB, Kabagambe EK, Khalifa SE, Kengne AP, Khader YS, Khang YH, Kim D, Kimokoti RW, Kinge JM, Kokubo Y, Kosen S, Kwan G, Lai T, Leinsalu M, Li Y, Liang X, Liu S, Logroscino G, Lotufo PA, Lu Y, Ma J, Mainoo NK, Mensah GA, Merriman TR, Mokdad AH, Moschandreas J, Naghavi M, Naheed A, Nand D, Narayan KM, Nelson EL, Neuhouser ML, Nisar MI, Ohkubo T, Oti SO, Pedroza A, Prabhakaran D, Roy N, Sampson U, Seo H, Sepanlou SG, Shibuya K, Shiri R, Shiue I, Singh GM, Singh JA, Skirbekk V, Stapelberg NJ, Sturua L, Sykes BL, Tobias M, Tran BX, Trasande L, Toyoshima H, van de Vijver S, Vasankari TJ, Veerman JL, Velasquez-Melendez G, Vlassov VV, Vollset SE, Vos T, Wang C, Wang X, Weiderpass E, Werdecker A, Wright JL, Yang YC, Yatsuya H, Yoon J, Yoon SJ, Zhao Y, Zhou M, Zhu S, Lopez AD, Murray CJ, Gakidou E. Global, regional, and national prevalence of overweight and obesity in children and adults during 1980-2013: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2013. Lancet. 2014 Aug 30;384(9945):766-81. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60460-8. Epub 2014 May 29. Erratum in: Lancet. 2014 Aug 30;384(9945):746.</citation>
    <PMID>24880830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>French HP, Galvin R, Horgan NF, Kenny RA. Prevalence and burden of osteoarthritis amongst older people in Ireland: findings from The Irish LongituDinal Study on Ageing (TILDA). Eur J Public Health. 2016 Feb;26(1):192-8. doi: 10.1093/eurpub/ckv109. Epub 2015 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26105959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy LB, Helmick CG, Schwartz TA, Renner JB, Tudor G, Koch GG, Dragomir AD, Kalsbeek WD, Luta G, Jordan JM. One in four people may develop symptomatic hip osteoarthritis in his or her lifetime. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2010 Nov;18(11):1372-9. doi: 10.1016/j.joca.2010.08.005. Epub 2010 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20713163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blalock D, Miller A, Tilley M, Wang J. Joint instability and osteoarthritis. Clin Med Insights Arthritis Musculoskelet Disord. 2015 Feb 19;8:15-23. doi: 10.4137/CMAMD.S22147. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25741184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reginster JY, Cooper C, Bruyère O. Re: Kucharz EJ, Kovalenko V, Szántó S, et al. A review of glucosamine for knee osteoarthritis: why patented crystalline glucosamine sulfate should be differentiated from other glucosamines to maximize clinical outcomes. Curr Med Res Opin 2016;32:997-1004. Curr Med Res Opin. 2016 Nov;32(11):1771-1772. Epub 2016 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27649741</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harirforoosh S, Asghar W, Jamali F. Adverse effects of nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs: an update of gastrointestinal, cardiovascular and renal complications. J Pharm Pharm Sci. 2013;16(5):821-47. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24393558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richy F, Bruyere O, Ethgen O, Cucherat M, Henrotin Y, Reginster JY. Structural and symptomatic efficacy of glucosamine and chondroitin in knee osteoarthritis: a comprehensive meta-analysis. Arch Intern Med. 2003 Jul 14;163(13):1514-22.</citation>
    <PMID>12860572</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAlindon TE, LaValley MP, Gulin JP, Felson DT. Glucosamine and chondroitin for treatment of osteoarthritis: a systematic quality assessment and meta-analysis. JAMA. 2000 Mar 15;283(11):1469-75. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10732937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee YH, Woo JH, Choi SJ, Ji JD, Song GG. Effect of glucosamine or chondroitin sulfate on the osteoarthritis progression: a meta-analysis. Rheumatol Int. 2010 Jan;30(3):357-63. doi: 10.1007/s00296-009-0969-5. Epub 2009 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>19544061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wandel S, Jüni P, Tendal B, Nüesch E, Villiger PM, Welton NJ, Reichenbach S, Trelle S. Effects of glucosamine, chondroitin, or placebo in patients with osteoarthritis of hip or knee: network meta-analysis. BMJ. 2010 Sep 16;341:c4675. doi: 10.1136/bmj.c4675. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20847017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy LB, Moss S, Do BT, Helmick CG, Schwartz TA, Barbour KE, Renner J, Kalsbeek W, Jordan JM. Annual Incidence of Knee Symptoms and Four Knee Osteoarthritis Outcomes in the Johnston County Osteoarthritis Project. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2016 Jan;68(1):55-65. doi: 10.1002/acr.22641.</citation>
    <PMID>26097226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kongtharvonskul J, Anothaisintawee T, McEvoy M, Attia J, Woratanarat P, Thakkinstian A. Efficacy and safety of glucosamine, diacerein, and NSAIDs in osteoarthritis knee: a systematic review and network meta-analysis. Eur J Med Res. 2015 Mar 13;20:24. doi: 10.1186/s40001-015-0115-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25889669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prieto-Alhambra D, Judge A, Javaid MK, Cooper C, Diez-Perez A, Arden NK. Incidence and risk factors for clinically diagnosed knee, hip and hand osteoarthritis: influences of age, gender and osteoarthritis affecting other joints. Ann Rheum Dis. 2014 Sep;73(9):1659-64. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2013-203355. Epub 2013 Jun 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23744977</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oliveria SA, Felson DT, Reed JI, Cirillo PA, Walker AM. Incidence of symptomatic hand, hip, and knee osteoarthritis among patients in a health maintenance organization. Arthritis Rheum. 1995 Aug;38(8):1134-41.</citation>
    <PMID>7639811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neogi T, Zhang Y. Epidemiology of osteoarthritis. Rheum Dis Clin North Am. 2013 Feb;39(1):1-19. doi: 10.1016/j.rdc.2012.10.004. Epub 2012 Nov 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23312408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gabriel SE, Michaud K. Epidemiological studies in incidence, prevalence, mortality, and comorbidity of the rheumatic diseases. Arthritis Res Ther. 2009;11(3):229. doi: 10.1186/ar2669. Epub 2009 May 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19519924</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irvine, James Colquhoun, David McNicoll, and Alexander Hynd.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacGregor AJ, Antoniades L, Matson M, Andrew T, Spector TD. The genetic contribution to radiographic hip osteoarthritis in women: results of a classic twin study. Arthritis Rheum. 2000 Nov;43(11):2410-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11083262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spector TD, Cicuttini F, Baker J, Loughlin J, Hart D. Genetic influences on osteoarthritis in women: a twin study. BMJ. 1996 Apr 13;312(7036):940-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8616305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacGregor AJ, Li Q, Spector TD, Williams FM. The genetic influence on radiographic osteoarthritis is site specific at the hand, hip and knee. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2009 Mar;48(3):277-80. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/ken475. Epub 2009 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19153142</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skousgaard SG, Skytthe A, Möller S, Overgaard S, Brandt LP. Sex differences in risk and heritability estimates on primary knee osteoarthritis leading to total knee arthroplasty: a nationwide population based follow up study in Danish twins. Arthritis Res Ther. 2016 Feb 11;18:46. doi: 10.1186/s13075-016-0939-8.</citation>
    <PMID>26864139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skousgaard SG, Hjelmborg J, Skytthe A, Brandt LP, Möller S, Overgaard S. Probability and heritability estimates on primary osteoarthritis of the hip leading to total hip arthroplasty: a nationwide population based follow-up study in Danish twins. Arthritis Res Ther. 2015 Nov 20;17:336. doi: 10.1186/s13075-015-0854-4.</citation>
    <PMID>26589897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Knee pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucosamine</keyword>
  <keyword>WOMAC</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

