<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03107208</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-1965</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03107208</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Glargine (Lantus) in DKA Management in Children With Type 1 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Management of Diabetic Ketoacidosis in Children: Does Early Glargine Prevent Rebound Hyperglycemia?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A frequent complication in the management of diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) in children with
      type 1 diabetes is rebound hyperglycemia (blood glucose over 180 mg/dL) which increases the
      risk of re-developing DKA and can lengthen the hospital stay. The investigators want to study
      whether giving the long-acting insulin glargine (Lantus®) early in DKA management (versus
      after complete resolution of the DKA) helps prevent rebound hyperglycemia and makes the
      transition to insulin injections easier. Participants will also have the option to wear a
      continuous glucose monitor (CGM) during the study to help us understand blood glucose control
      during and after DKA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) remains the leading cause of morbidity and mortality in children
      with type 1 diabetes (T1D) and the incidence of T1D is increasing. A frequent complication in
      DKA management that is associated with in-hospital mortality and longer hospital stay is
      hyperglycemia; specifically rebound hyperglycemia (defined as a serum glucose greater than
      180 mg/dL) within 12-24 hours after correction of the DKA. Rebound hyperglycemia increases
      the patient's risk of re-developing DKA. Few adult studies suggest that giving the
      long-acting insulin analog (glargine or Lantus®) early in the management of DKA (i.e. while
      still receiving intravenous insulin) can reduce rebound hyperglycemia without an increased
      risk of hypoglycemia and result in a smoother transition from intravenous insulin to
      subcutaneous insulin. This has not been well-studied in children to date. In this study the
      investigators want to determine whether giving glargine early in DKA management in children
      results in reduced rebound hyperglycemia without an increased risk in hypoglycemia. The
      investigators will do this by randomizing participants in DKA to either receive glargine
      early in the management of DKA (study group) or after resolution of DKA (control group); the
      latter is currently standard-of-care. Additionally, continuous glucose monitoring (CGM)
      systems have not been studied in a pediatric population with DKA. These devices measure blood
      sugar levels every 5 minutes and provide a great deal of information about blood sugar
      control patterns over many days. Not only will the use of CGM in this study provide
      meaningful information regarding blood sugar patterns during DKA treatment, it will also
      broaden the investigators knowledge of whether CGM is a feasible and accurate tool to use in
      this setting.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 21, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Rebound Hyperglycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 12 hours after resolution of diabetic ketoacidosis</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the rate of rebound hyperglycemia with a glucometer, defined as a serum glucose level of greater than 180 mg/dL (&gt;10 mmol/L) within 12 hours after discontinuation of IV insulin, in children treated for diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) with early glargine versus standard-of-care management.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Recurrent Ketogenesis</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 12 hours after discontinuation of IV insulin</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the rate of recurrent ketogenesis (beta-hydroxybutyrate ≥ 1.5 mmol/L within 12 hours after discontinuation of IV insulin) in children treated for diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) with early glargine versus standard-of-care management.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk of Hypoglycemia between those given early administration of glargine versus those given standard-of-care management.</measure>
    <time_frame>During treatment and within 12 hours after d/c IV insulin; while receiving IV insulin in children with DKA given early glargine versus standard-of-care management.</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the frequency of hypoglycemic events during treatment of DKA, and within 12 hours after discontinuation of IV insulin, in children given early glargine versus standard-of-care management vs. the rate of blood glucose decrease while receiving IV insulin in children with DKA given early glargine versus standard-of-care management.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of CGM and POC glucose monitoring during DKA treatment in children.</measure>
    <time_frame>During treatment of DKA and within 12 hours after discontinuation of IV insulin.</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the feasibility and utility of CGM as a tool to monitor blood glucose levels during DKA treatment in children.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Ketoacidosis</condition>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early glargine (Lantus)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A dose of glargine (Lantus®) is given subcutaneously early in the management of DKA (i.e. while the participant is still receiving intravenous insulin). Participants will also be asked to wear a continuous glucose monitor (CGM) during the DKA and for a week following the DKA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>A dose of glargine (Lantus®) is given subcutaneously after resolution of the DKA (i.e. when the intravenous insulin is stopped). This is currently the standard-of-care practice for children in DKA. Participants will also be asked to wear a continuous glucose monitor (CGM) during the DKA and for a week following the DKA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glargine</intervention_name>
    <description>A dose of glargine (Lantus) will be given subcutaneously either early in the management of DKA (study group) or upon resolution of DKA (control group).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early glargine (Lantus)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lantus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous Glucose Monitor (Abbott FreeStyle Libre Pro)</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will be asked to wear a continuous glucose monitor (CGM) during the DKA and for a week following the DKA in order to better understand blood glucose control during DKA. This is an optional part of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early glargine (Lantus)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CGM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 6-17.9 years at time of enrollment.

          2. Known history of type 1 diabetes or presumed new-onset type 1 diabetes.

          3. Diagnosis of DKA (serum glucose or fingerstick glucose concentration ≥ 200 mg/dL.

          4. Venous pH ≤7.3 and/or serum bicarbonate concentration ≤15 mmol/L.

          5. Evidence of ketonemia or ketonuria).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participants who present in DKA with conditions that affect neurological function such
             as:

               1. suspected alcohol or drug use,

               2. severe head trauma,

               3. meningitis, etc., who would not be able to consent/assent for the study.

          2. Participants who present in DKA who are showing signs of altered mental status at time
             of enrollment.

          3. Other known complicating illness or poorly-controlled chronic illness that is known to
             affect blood glucose levels and/or electrolyte balance such as:

               1. chronic renal disease (requiring hemodialysis),

               2. chronic liver disease (with evidence of current hepatic dysfunction,

               3. coagulopathy, and/or chronic hepatitis), or

               4. severe chronic lung disease (requiring the use of oral steroids).

          4. Use of medications that are known to affect blood glucose levels such as:

               1. oral glucocorticoids,

               2. Metformin,

               3. SGLT2 inhibitors,

               4. GLP-1 receptor agonists,

               5. DPP-4 inhibitors,

               6. thiazolidinediones

               7. sulfonylureas, and

               8. vasopressors, etc.

          5. Participants who have begun DKA treatment prior to being approached for enrollment and
             have received more than 6 hours of IV insulin therapy.

          6. Participants who are known to be pregnant.

          7. Participants who have a known diagnosis of type 2 diabetes.

          8. Participants for whom the treating physicians feel a specific insulin regimen is
             necessary such that patient safety or well-being could be compromised by enrollment
             into the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Ohman-Hanson</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rebecca A Ohman-Hanson, MD</last_name>
    <phone>720-777-2560</phone>
    <email>rebecca.ohman@childrenscolorado.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Guy T Alonso, MD</last_name>
    <phone>303-724-2323</phone>
    <email>guy.alonso@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Colorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathleen Grice</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-3285</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Regan Miller</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-2592</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rebecca A Ohman-Hanson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>DKA</keyword>
  <keyword>type 1 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>continuous glucose monitoring</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Ketoacidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Glargine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

