<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03101501</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P17-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03101501</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Study To Evaluate The Raindrop Near Vision Inlay In Presybopic or Pseudophakic Patients Treated With Mitomycin C Following Femtosecond Flap Creation.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Study To Evaluate The Raindrop Near Vision Inlay In Presybopic or Pseudophakic Patients Treated With Mitomycin C Following Femtosecond Flap Creation.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Key-Whitman Eye Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Key-Whitman Eye Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The clinical objective of this study is to evaluate the Raindrop® Near Vision Inlay for the
      improvement of near vision in presbyopic or pseudophakic patients treated with low dose
      Mitomycin C immediately following femtosecond flap creation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The scientific objective of this study is to evaluate the postoperative incidence of corneal
      reaction in patients treated with low dose Mitomycin C, immediately following femtosecond
      flap creation (LASIK correction if needed), and before implantation with the Raindrop corneal
      inlay in the non-dominant eye. The postoperative incidence of haze, visible by broad
      tangential illumination of the slit lamp, is known to adversely impact the safety and
      efficacy of the Raindrop corneal inlay. Three main strategies have been employed to minimize
      haze incidence after surgery: (i) perfection of the surgical technique, (ii) deeper
      implantation in the cornea, and (iii) extension of the steroid regimen after surgery. Haze
      has also been observed after another type of corneal refractive procedure, Photorefractive
      Keratectomy (PRK). Several prospective studies have shown that Mitomycin C, applied
      immediately following the PRK laser procedure, is effective in reducing the postoperative
      incidence of haze.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The manufacturing company of the Raindrop Corneal Inlay has stopped distribution or sales of
    the product.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 14, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Uncorrected Visual Acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>After the inlay procedure, patients will attain functional near visual acuity in the inlay eye and functional distance acuity binocularly.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Corneal Reaction</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patients treated with low dose mitomycin C will have minimal levels of corneal reaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endothelial Cell Count (measured by Konan Specular Microscope)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patients treated with low dose mitomycin C will not lose more than 10% of their endothelial cell count from the preoperative measurement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Presbyopia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mitomycin c</intervention_name>
    <description>Low dose mitomycin C at a concentration of 0.02% will be applied a duration of 10 to 30 seconds at the time of the surgical procedure.</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Raindrop Near Vision Inlay</intervention_name>
    <description>Implanted to improve near vision in Presbyopic or Pseudophakic subjects.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        4.2.1 Presbyopic patients 41-65 years of age.

        4.2.2 Pseudophakic patients at least 50 years of age.

        4.2.3 Patients require a near reading add from +1.50 to +2.50 D in the non-dominant eye.

        4.2.4 Patients have a photopic pupil size of at least 3.0 mm in the non-dominant eye.

        4.2.5 Patients have a corneal thickness greater than or equal to 500 microns in the
        non-dominant eye.

        4.2.6 Patients have corrected distance and near visual acuity of 20/25 or better in each
        eye.

        4.2.7 Patients have distance corrected near visual acuity of 20/40 or worse in each eye.

        4.2.8 Patients have no more than a 0.75 D difference at preop between MRSE and cycloplegic
        refraction spherical equivalent determined at the spectacle plane of each eye.

        4.2.9 Patients have targeted MRSE from -0.5 to +1.0 D in the non-dominant eye, with no more
        than 0.75 D of manifest cylinder with or without LASIK.

        4.2.10 Patients are willing and able to sign a written Informed Consent Form prior to any
        study-specific procedures.

        4.2.11 Pseudophakic patients must be at least 3 months after cataract surgery.

        4.2.12 Pseudophakic patients must have clear posterior capsule, open posterior capsule
        (post YAG Capsulotomy), or posterior capsule opacification that is not clinically
        significant at the opinion of the investigator.

        4.2.13 Patients are willing and able to return for scheduled follow-up examinations for 24
        months after the corneal inlay surgery.

        Exclusion Criteria

        4.3.1 Patients with prior corneal surgery including LASIK surgery in the non-dominant eye.
        (Not including Astigmatic Keratotomy or Limbal Relaxing Incisions)

        4.3.2 Patients with clinically significant dry eye (i.e., significant diffuse punctate
        staining with fluorescein and a tear breakup time less than 8 s) in either eye.

        4.3.3 Patients with a planned corneal residual bed thickness that is less than 300 microns
        (corneal thickness - (intended ablation depth + intended flap thickness)).

        4.3.4 Patients with clinically significant macular pathology based on dilated fundus exam
        and/or optical coherence tomography (OCT) image.

        4.3.5 Patients who would be co-managed by an ophthalmologist or optometrist who is not an
        approved sub-investigator.

        4.3.6 Patients with ocular pathology or disease (including pupil pathology such as fixated
        pupils) that might confound the outcome or increase the risk of adverse event in the
        investigator's opinion.

        4.3.7 Patients taking systemic or topical medications that might confound the outcome or
        increase the risk of adverse event. Patients taking isotretinoin or amiodarone
        hydrochloride and any other medication that affects the tear film or accommodation,
        including but not limited to, mydriatic, cycloplegic and mitotic agents, or any other
        medications in the investigator's opinion.

        4.3.8 Patients with known sensitivity to any planned study medications.

        4.3.9 Patients with residual, recurrent, active or uncontrolled eyelid disease.

        4.3.10 Patients with significant corneal asymmetry or irregular topography.

        4.3.11 Patients with clinically significant anterior segment pathology.

        4.3.12 Patients with any corneal abnormality, including but not limited to, slit lamp
        findings for corneal staining Grade 3 or higher, recurrent corneal erosion or severe
        basement membrane disease, and pterygium extending onto the cornea.

        4.3.13 Patients with ophthalmoscopic/topographic signs of keratoconus or those who are
        keratoconus suspect.

        4.3.14 Patients with history of Herpes zoster or Herpes simplex keratitis.

        4.3.15 Pseudophakic patients that have anterior chamber IOLs, multifocal IOLs, or extended
        range of vision IOLs in either eye.

        4.3.16 Patients with any progressive retinal disease or subjects with a history or evidence
        of retinal vascular occlusion and/or hypercoagulability, because of the risks associated
        with high pressures during suction application.

        4.3.17 Patients with known history of steroid-responsive intraocular pressure increases,
        glaucoma, preoperative IOP &gt; 21 mm Hg, or are otherwise suspected of having glaucoma.

        4.3.18 Patients with amblyopia or strabismus or those who are at risk for developing
        strabismus postoperatively as determined by corneal light reflex and cover-uncover testing.

        4.3.19 Patients with diabetic retinopathy, collagen, vascular, diagnosed autoimmune disease
        (e.g., lupus, rheumatoid arthritis, fibromylagia), immunodeficiency (e.g., HIV), connective
        tissue disease, or clinically significant atopic syndrome.

        4.3.20 Patients on chronic systemic corticosteroid or other immunosuppressive therapy that
        may affect wound healing at the opinion of the investigator.

        4.3.21 Patients with any type of active cancer (ophthalmic or non-ophthalmic).

        4.3.22 Patients with uncontrolled infections of any kind.

        4.3.23 Patients who are pregnant, lactating, of child-bearing potential and not practicing
        a medically approved method of birth control, or planning to become pregnant during the
        course of the trial, and patients with other conditions associated with fluctuation of
        hormones that could lead to refractive changes.

        4.3.24 Patients who actively participate in contact sports (i.e., boxing, martial arts)
        where impacts to the face and eye are a normal occurrence.

        4.3.25 Patients participating in any other ophthalmic or non-ophthalmic drug/device
        clinical trials during the time of this clinical investigation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>41 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Whitman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Key-Whitman Eye Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chu Vision Institue</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bloomington</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55420</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Key-Whitman Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75243</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parkhurst NuVision</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Key-Whitman Eye Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeffrey Whitman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>President and Chief Surgeon</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Presbyopia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mitomycins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitomycin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

