<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03107754</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-00083</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03107754</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Buffered Lidocaine in Paracervical Blocks</brief_title>
  <official_title>Buffered Lidocaine for Paracervical Block to Decrease Injection Pain During First Trimester Uterine Aspirations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Hawaii</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Hawaii</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For pain relief during a first trimester surgical aspiration, most providers use the
      paracervical block, either alone or in combination with other pain control techniques. Some
      providers use buffered lidocaine due to a belief that it decreases pain. Others use plain
      lidocaine. At our clinics, the standard pain management protocol is using 20 cc of 1% plain
      lidocaine in a two site injection. Few studies have compared buffered versus unbuffered
      lidocaine for paracervical blocks during first trimester uterine aspirations. This study
      seeks to determine if buffered lidocaine decreases injection pain versus plain lidocaine for
      paracervical blocks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Potential participants will be identified at their office visits to the University Women's
      Health Specialists. If a patient desires uterine aspiration of a first trimester pregnancy or
      management of a failed pregnancy in the first trimester, they will first receive standard
      counseling. Only after providing written informed consent for the procedure will the
      patient's be screened for eligibility for our study. If the patient is eligible, she will be
      asked by a member of the research team if she is interested in participating. If she is, the
      study will be explained to her and written consent will be obtained after she is given the
      opportunity to have all of her questions answered. The patient will then complete a written
      questionnaire to collect demographic data.

      This prospective randomized control trial will consist of two study arms. Participants will
      be randomly assigned to Arm 1, where a paracervical block will be administered with 20 cc of
      1% lidocaine, which is our standard office protocol, or to Arm 2, where a paracervical block
      will be administered with 20 cc of 1% lidocaine buffered with 8.4% sodium bicarbonate. Prior
      to the start of the study, study assignments will be generated in a 1:1 ratio.

      All patients who consent to the study will receive standard counseling prior to their
      procedure. The procedure will start with a bimanual exam by the provider. Next, the provider
      will place a speculum, cleanse the cervix with betadine solution, and place a single-tooth
      tenaculum on the anterior lip of the cervix. At this point, participants assigned to Arm 1
      will receive a paracervical block loaded with 20 cc of 1% lidocaine and injected at 2, 4, 8
      and 10 o'clock positions of the cervicovaginal junction. Participants assigned to Arm 2 will
      receive a paracervical block loaded with 18 cc of 1% lidocaine and 2 cc of 8.4% sodium
      bicarbonate and inject the block in the same fashion. The research assistant will ask the
      patient to verbally report their level of pain based on the 100 mm visual analog scale (VAS)
      at the following points of the procedure:

        1. Prior to the start of the procedure (baseline anxiety)

        2. After speculum placement

        3. After paracervical block

        4. After cervical dilation

        5. After suction curettage

        6. At end of procedure
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A statistician not involved with the conduct of the study will use a computer random number generator to generate random permuted blocks. This statistician will place allocation assignment cards in sequentially numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes. A different randomization scheme will be used for each location, one at the Kapi'olani office and one at the Queen's office.
A clinic staff member not involved with the conduct of the study will be trained specifically in the opening of the allocation envelopes. The staff member will be trained to open the envelope and remove the study card to read the allocation group: buffered lidocaine or plain lidocaine. The clinic staff member will then prepare the buffered lidocaine or plain lidocaine in an unlabeled syringe, and place it on the surgical tray.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Injection pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after injection of the paracervical block</time_frame>
    <description>Compare pain scores on a 100 mm VAS (anchors 0=no pain; 100=worst pain ever)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain after speculum placement, cervical dilation, aspiration, and immediately post-operatively</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after speculum placement, cervical dilation, uterine aspiration, and immediately after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Compare pain scores on a 100 mm VAS (anchors 0=no pain; 100=worst pain ever)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">98</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard paracervical block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A paracervical block will be administered with 20 cc of 1% lidocaine, which is our standard office protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Buffered lidocaine paracervical block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A paracervical block will be administered with 20 cc of 1% lidocaine buffered with 8.4% sodium bicarbonate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lidocaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Paracervical block will be injected at 4 points at the cervicovaginal junction to decrease pain</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard paracervical block</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paracervical anesthesia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lidocaine-Sodium Bicarbonate</intervention_name>
    <description>Paracervical block will be injected at 4 points at the cervicovaginal junction to decrease pain</description>
    <arm_group_label>Buffered lidocaine paracervical block</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women 14 years and older

          -  Desiring uterine aspiration for pregnancy or surgical management of a miscarriage

          -  Gestational age up to 13 weeks and 6 days to be established by best dating (i.e. last
             menstrual period [LMP] or earliest ultrasound)

          -  Treatment plan involves outpatient uterine aspiration

          -  Participant able to provide informed consent in English and willing to participate in
             the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to read, speak, or understand English

          -  Unable to provide informed consent

          -  Currently incarcerated

          -  Under the age of 14 years

          -  Contraindications to receiving lidocaine or buffered lidocaine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Principal Investigator</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Hawaii</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Principal Investigator</last_name>
    <phone>(808) 203-6500</phone>
    <email>WHRC@hawaii.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Womens Options Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Honolulu</city>
        <state>Hawaii</state>
        <zip>96814</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Principal Investigator</last_name>
      <email>whrc@hawaii.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiebe ER, Rawling M. Pain control in abortion. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 1995 Jul;50(1):41-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7556858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Renner RM, Jensen JT, Nichols MD, Edelman AB. Pain control in first-trimester surgical abortion: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Contraception. 2010 May;81(5):372-88. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2009.12.008. Epub 2010 Jan 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20399943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Renner RM, Nichols MD, Jensen JT, Li H, Edelman AB. Paracervical block for pain control in first-trimester surgical abortion: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol. 2012 May;119(5):1030-7. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e318250b13e.</citation>
    <PMID>22525915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Renner RM, Edelman AB, Nichols MD, Jensen JT, Lim JY, Bednarek PH. Refining paracervical block techniques for pain control in first trimester surgical abortion: a randomized controlled noninferiority trial. Contraception. 2016 Nov;94(5):461-466. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2016.05.005. Epub 2016 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27235677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Todd KH, Funk KG, Funk JP, Bonacci R. Clinical significance of reported changes in pain severity. Ann Emerg Med. 1996 Apr;27(4):485-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8604867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiebe ER. Comparison of the efficacy of different local anesthetics and techniques of local anesthesia in therapeutic abortions. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1992 Jul;167(1):131-4.</citation>
    <PMID>1442914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Welch MN, Czyz CN, Kalwerisky K, Holck DE, Mihora LD. Double-blind, bilateral pain comparison with simultaneous injection of 2% lidocaine versus buffered 2% lidocaine for periocular anesthesia. Ophthalmology. 2012 Oct;119(10):2048-52. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2012.05.029. Epub 2012 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22771049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kizer NT, Zhao Q, Peipert JF, Ioffe Y, Massad LS. A randomized trial of buffered versus nonbuffered lidocaine with epinephrine for cervical loop excision. J Low Genit Tract Dis. 2014 Jan;18(1):8-12. doi: 10.1097/LGT.0b013e31828deffd.</citation>
    <PMID>23774079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Narváez J, Wessels I, Bacon G, Chin VR, Baqai WK, Zimmerman GJ. Prospective randomized evaluation of short-term complications when using buffered or unbuffered lidocaine 1% with epinephrine for blepharoplasty surgery. Ophthalmic Plast Reconstr Surg. 2010 Jan-Feb;26(1):33-5. doi: 10.1097/IOP.0b013e3181b80c13.</citation>
    <PMID>20090482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hobeich P, Simon S, Schneiderman E, He J. A prospective, randomized, double-blind comparison of the injection pain and anesthetic onset of 2% lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine buffered with 5% and 10% sodium bicarbonate in maxillary infiltrations. J Endod. 2013 May;39(5):597-9. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2013.01.008. Epub 2013 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23611375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harreld TK, Fowler S, Drum M, Reader A, Nusstein J, Beck M. Efficacy of a Buffered 4% Lidocaine Formulation for Incision and Drainage: A Prospective, Randomized, Double-blind Study. J Endod. 2015 Oct;41(10):1583-8. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2015.06.017. Epub 2015 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>26253800</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 5, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

