<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00118170</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2012-03083</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CALGB-60301</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA031946</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000433342</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00118170</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sorafenib in Treating Patients With Metastatic or Unresectable Solid Tumors, Multiple Myeloma, or Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma With or Without Impaired Liver or Kidney Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetic and Phase I Study of Sorafenib (BAY 43-9006, NSC 724772, IND 69896) for Solid Tumors and Hematologic Malignancies in Patients With Hepatic or Renal Dysfunction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial is studying the side effects and best dose of sorafenib in treating
      patients with metastatic or unresectable solid tumors, multiple myeloma, or non-Hodgkin's
      lymphoma with or without impaired liver or kidney function. Sorafenib may stop the growth of
      cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth and by blocking blood
      flow to the cancer. Sorafenib may have different effects in patients who have changes in
      their liver or kidney function
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To characterize the pharmacokinetics of BAY 43-9006 in patients with hepatic or renal
      dysfunction (part 1 of the study).

      II. To determine a tolerable starting dose of BAY 43-9006 in patients with varying degrees of
      hepatic or renal dysfunction (part 2 of the study).

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation, multicenter study. Patients are assigned to 1 of 9
      treatment cohorts according to hepatic or renal function.

      Patients receive oral sorafenib once on day 1 and then once daily, twice daily, or every
      other day beginning on day 8 and continuing for 3 months. Patients are re-evaluated at 3
      months. Patients with responding disease may continue study treatment in the absence of
      disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Cohorts of 3-6 patients (per treatment cohort) receive escalating doses of sorafenib until
      the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that
      at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity. At least 6 patients are
      treated at the MTD.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 120 patients will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2004</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between the pharmacokinetics and measures of renal dysfunction categorized by creatinine clearance as estimated by the Cockcroft and Gault formula (Part 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to and at 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, and 24 hours post-dose on day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Explored using standard parametric and non-parametric methods for one- and two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) layouts (the dysfunction factor (hepatic/renal) and the severity factor (mild, moderate, severe, very severe).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of hepatic disease as assessed by the Child-Pugh criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Non-parametric measures of association for ordinal data will be employed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Distribution of and association patterns between the Child-Pugh score and that of patient's risk of toxicity beyond each dose or cohort, assessed using the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v3.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean levels of area under the curve (AUC) using the ANOVA model</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>90% confidence intervals for the relative change (from mild to moderate and from moderate to severe) of the mean AUC levels will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of sorafenib tosylate, assessed using the NCI CTCAE v3.0 (Part 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limiting toxicities (DLT), defined as any grade 3 or greater non-hematologic toxicity, assessed using the NCI CTCAE v3.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Extranodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma of Mucosa-associated Lymphoid Tissue</condition>
  <condition>Nodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Small Cleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Grade III Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Splenic Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Adult Diffuse Small Cleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Small Cleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <condition>Waldenström Macroglobulinemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive oral sorafenib once on day 1 and then once daily, twice daily, or every other day beginning on day 8 and continuing for 3 months. Patients are re-evaluated at 3 months. Patients with responding disease may continue study treatment in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
Cohorts of 3-6 patients (per treatment cohort) receive escalating doses of sorafenib until the MTD is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity. At least 6 patients are treated at the MTD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sorafenib tosylate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BAY 43-9006</other_name>
    <other_name>BAY 43-9006 Tosylate Salt</other_name>
    <other_name>BAY 54-9085</other_name>
    <other_name>Nexavar</other_name>
    <other_name>SFN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have cytologically or histologically confirmed tumors that are
             metastatic or unresectable and for which standard curative or palliative measures do
             not exist or are no longer effective; Patients with solid tumors, multiple myeloma, or
             non-Hodgkin's lymphoma are eligible

          -  Lesions that can be accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to
             be recorded) as ≥ 20 mm with conventional techniques or as ≥ 10 mm with spiral CT scan

          -  All other lesions, including small lesions (longest diameter &lt; 20 mm with conventional
             techniques or &lt; 10 mm with spiral CT scan) and truly nonmeasurable lesions; Lesions
             that are considered non-measurable include the following:

               -  Bone lesions

               -  Ascites

               -  Pleural/pericardial effusion

               -  Lymphangitis cutis/pulmonis

               -  Abdominal masses that are not confirmed and followed by imaging techniques

               -  Cystic lesions

          -  ≥ 4 weeks since major surgery

          -  ≥ 4 weeks since completion of radiation or chemotherapy except for ≥ 6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas, L-PAM or mitomycin-C

          -  ECOG Performance Status of 0-2

          -  Non-pregnant and non-nursing because the effects of BAY 43-9006 on the fetus/infant
             are unknown; in addition, women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use
             an appropriate method of birth control throughout their participation in this study;
             appropriate methods of birth control include abstinence, oral contraceptives,
             implantable hormonal contraceptives (Norplant), or double barrier methods (diaphragm
             plus condom)

          -  No patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to,
             ongoing or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina
             pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, uncontrolled hypertension, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirements

          -  No concomitant medications known to cause hepatic or renal toxicity, including
             anti-seizure medications, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents, and steroids

          -  No gastrointestinal tract disease resulting in an inability to take oral medication or
             a requirement for IV alimentation, prior surgical procedures affecting absorption, or
             active peptic ulcer disease

          -  No HIV-positive patients receiving combination anti-retroviral therapy because of
             possible pharmacokinetic interactions with BAY 43-9006; however, patients who are HIV+
             but without AIDS defining diagnosis and not on combination anti-retroviral therapy are
             eligible

          -  No patients with evidence of biliary or renal obstruction; patients should be observed
             for at least one week after treatment (i.e. stents or drains) for biliary or renal
             obstruction to ensure their organ dysfunction has stabilized before registration to
             this protocol

          -  No current treatment with other investigational agents

          -  No evidence of bleeding diathesis

          -  No patients on therapeutic anticoagulation; prophylactic anticoagulation (i.e., low
             dose warfarin) of venous or arterial access devices is allowed provided that the
             requirements for PT, INR or PTT is met

          -  No treatment with cytochrome P450 enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs (phenytoin,
             carbamazepine or Phenobarbital), rifampin or St. John's wort

          -  Patients with brain metastases are eligible if they meet all of the following
             criteria:

               -  Asymptomatic

               -  Radiographically stable disease for at least 2 months

               -  Previously received treatment for the brain metastases

               -  Not currently receiving steroid therapy or enzyme-inducing anticonvulsants (e.g.
                  phenytoin, phenobarbital, or carbamazepine)

          -  Granulocytes ≥ 1,500/μl

          -  Platelet count ≥ 75,000/μl

          -  Normal or abnormal organ function
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonius Miller</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer and Leukemia Group B</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer and Leukemia Group B (CALGB) Research Base</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60604-1104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 8, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 4, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 4, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 7, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell, Marginal Zone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Immunoblastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plasmablastic Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Extranodal NK-T-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

