<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00115453</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BNCT-P01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00115453</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Boron Neutron Capture Therapy (BNCT) as Treatment of Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Boron Neutron Capture Therapy in the Treatment of Glioblastoma Multiforme</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boneca Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boneca Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Boron Neutron Capture Therapy (BNCT) is an experimental radiation therapy technique that is
      based on the principle of irradiating boron atoms with neutrons. When neutrons have
      relatively low energy, boron atoms that have been targeted to cancerous tissue using a
      suitable boron carrier (an amino acid derivative called BPA, boronophenylalanine) will
      capture the neutrons. As a result from the neutron capture the boron atoms will split into
      two, producing helium and lithium ions. The helium and lithium ions, in turn, have only a
      short pathlength in tissue (about 5 micrometers) and will deposit their cell damaging effect
      mainly within the tumor provided that the boron carrier (BPA) has accumulated in the tumor.
      In practice, the study participants will receive BPA as an approximately 2-hour intravenous
      infusion, following which the tumor is irradiated with low energy (epithermal) neutrons
      obtained from a nuclear reactor at the BNCT facility. BNCT requires careful radiation dose
      planning, but neutron irradiation will last approximately only for one hour. In this study
      BNCT is given only once. The study hypothesis is that glioblastoma tissue may accumulate the
      boron carrier compound, and glioblastoma might respond to BNCT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single BNCT-facility, non-randomized, non-comparative, prospective, open-label,
      phase I/II trial to determine the value of BNCT in the treatment of subjects who have
      undergone surgery for glioblastoma, but glioblastoma has not been treated with radiation
      therapy or chemotherapy. The neutron irradiation site is the FiR 1 reactor site, located at
      Otaniemi, Espoo, Finland, about 6 kilometers from the Helsinki University Central Hospital,
      Helsinki, where patient evaluation and post-irradiation care will take place.

      BPA is infused as a fructose complex (BPA-F) into a peripheral vein over 2 hours prior to
      neutron irradiation. Blood samples will be taken before starting the BPA infusion, and
      thereafter at 20 to 40 minute intervals during the infusion, following infusion, and after
      delivering neutron irradiation to monitor the blood boron concentration. The blood samples
      will be analyzed for boron to estimate the average blood boron level during neutron
      irradiation. The first 12 patients are treated using a BPA dose of 290 mg/kg, following which
      the dose of BPA is increased stepwise to 500 mg/kg, provided that unacceptable toxicity will
      not occur.

      All patients will be evaluated for response using CT or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow accrual
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>safety</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>tumor response</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>effect on brain tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active treatment arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>irradiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Boronophenylalanine is infused into a peripheral vein prior to neutron irradiation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed glioblastoma multiforme

          -  Supratentorial location

          -  At least 30% of the tumor volume has been removed at craniotomy as judged from a
             pre/perioperative MRI

          -  Ability to understand the concept of investigational therapy

          -  Tolerates dexamethasone treatment

          -  Adequate anti-epileptic medication

          -  BNCT can be delivered within 6 weeks from the date of brain surgery

          -  A written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age less than 18 or greater than 75

          -  The tumor infiltrates into the optic chiasm or into the deep parts of the brain
             prohibiting delivery of an adequate radiation dose with BNCT

          -  Prior radiation therapy to the brain

          -  Prior chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or gene therapy

          -  Karnofsky performance score &lt;70

          -  Severe cardiac, liver, or kidney failure

          -  Severe infection

          -  A cardiac pace-maker, or a metal implant in the head and neck region that will
             prohibit MRI examination

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Phenylketonuria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heikki Joensuu, M.D., prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Helsinki University Central Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Oncology, Helsinki University Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>FIN-00029</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.boneca.fi</url>
    <description>Boneca Corporation is a Finnish company that provides BNCT.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kouri M, Kankaanranta L, Seppälä T, Tervo L, Rasilainen M, Minn H, Eskola O, Vähätalo J, Paetau A, Savolainen S, Auterinen I, Jääskeläinen J, Joensuu H. Undifferentiated sinonasal carcinoma may respond to single-fraction boron neutron capture therapy. Radiother Oncol. 2004 Jul;72(1):83-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15236879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Joensuu H, Kankaanranta L, Seppälä T, Auterinen I, Kallio M, Kulvik M, Laakso J, Vähätalo J, Kortesniemi M, Kotiluoto P, Serén T, Karila J, Brander A, Järviluoma E, Ryynänen P, Paetau A, Ruokonen I, Minn H, Tenhunen M, Jääskeläinen J, Färkkilä M, Savolainen S. Boron neutron capture therapy of brain tumors: clinical trials at the finnish facility using boronophenylalanine. J Neurooncol. 2003 Mar-Apr;62(1-2):123-34.</citation>
    <PMID>12749708</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 22, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 14, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 14, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>CEO Markku Pohjola</name_title>
    <organization>BONECA Ltd, Tukholmankatu 8</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>boron neutron capture therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>boronophenylalanine</keyword>
  <keyword>brain tumor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Boron</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

