<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00115856</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2001P-000114</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00115856</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imaging of Plaque With Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Imaging of Plaque in Atherosclerosis With Intravascular MRI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Peter Ganz MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to develop and refine the use of an intravascular wire to image plaque in the
      aorta, iliac and femoral artery using MRI. This project aims to use this increased resolution
      to identify the features within the plaque that is known to be associated with increased risk
      of plaque and vessel occlusion.

      The hypothesis is Intravascular MRI can detect and measure changes in response to therapy
      over time in the critical features in plaques in peripheral arteries of patients with
      atherosclerosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For those patients undergoing cardiac catheterization, an 8French sheath will be introduced
      via a femoral artery approach. This size sheath allows us to visualize the distal aorta while
      performing the intra vascular ultrasound ( IVUS). For these patients, if a femoral venous
      sheath is also positioned for clinical purposes, then this access will also be utilized to
      introduce the MRI coil. This imaging approach will allow us to compare the feasibility of
      intravascular MRI imaging from: a) the artery; b) the vein; c) a combination of both.

      For those patients not scheduled to undergo a clinically indicated cardiac catheterization,
      only a 6French sheath will be introduced via a femoral artery approach. In these patients, no
      femoral venous sheath will be introduced and the arterial access will not be upsized to a
      8French sheath.

      Two tablespoons of blood will be drawn from each patient to assess inflammatory markers such
      as C-Reactive Protein (CRP) as well as to confirm a negative pregnancy test for female
      patients of childbearing age.

      Using 20cc of non-ionic contrast, an angiogram of the distal aorta and the ilio-femoral
      region will be performed and recorded on disc (5mins). Thereafter, an approved guidewire and
      intravascular ultrasound catheter will be positioned in the same arteries via the same access
      route, and ultrasound images of the arterial segment will be recorded (10mins.). The
      guidewire and the ultrasound coil will then be removed. Finally, an intravascular MRI wire
      will be advanced through the same arterial access and/or the previously indicated venous
      access under X-ray control and positioned in the desired atherosclerotic segment in the
      region of the distal aorta or at the ilio-femoral area. The MRI wire(s) will be secured in
      place by Tegaderm and the femoral sheath(s) will be sutured in stable position. The patient
      will then be transported to the MRI scanner, positioned in the scanner and images recorded
      over a period not exceeding 60 minutes. During the transport and throughout the MRI scanning,
      the patient will be monitored via an MRI-compatible cardiac monitor. During the time that the
      intravascular MRI coil is within the femoral sheath, it will be continuously perfused with
      heparinized saline and the patient will receive weight- adjusted (12 U/kg) intravenous
      heparin for systemic anticoagulation to prevent thrombosis. To obtain the MRI images, the
      patients will receive gadolinium contrast as per routine radiology protocols (0.1-0.2
      mmol/kg). After recording the MRI images, the MRI coil(s) and the femoral sheath(s) will be
      removed from the artery and/or the vein as per usual care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Arterial Occlusive Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects studied</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm exploratory feasibility safety and efficacy study of MRI to image atherosclerosis in arteries</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intravascular MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Arterial imaging of atherosclerosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects studied</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female adults (aged 25-80) seen at the Brigham and Women's Hospital (BWH)
             clinic who have known arterial disease who consent to cannulation of the femoral
             artery for this research.

          -  Patients in the prespecified age group who are scheduled to undergo a clinically
             indicated heart or peripheral catheterization at the BWH catheterization (cath) lab
             who will have a tube (sheath) already positioned in their femoral artery

          -  Patient must be in stable condition with regard to symptoms, vital signs and the
             monitored electrocardiogram

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unstable symptoms, vital signs or electrocardiogram after the heart cath

          -  Any complications during the heart cath (eg., bleeding, angina, arrhythmias, technical
             difficulties cannulating the femoral artery)

          -  Creatinine &gt;2.0mg/dl

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Contraindications to anticoagulation

          -  Patients with a metal implant, pacemaker, cardiac defibrillator, metal fragments in
             the eye, bullets/metal objects in the body
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Selwyn, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Womens Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Womens Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrew Peter Selwyn, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arterial Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

