<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00112255</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HTA_97/32/31</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00112255</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Partner Notification for Chlamydia in Primary Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Partner Notification for Chlamydia in Primary Care: Randomised Controlled Trial and Economic Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Bristol</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Bristol</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study was to compare the effectiveness of partner notification by general
      practice nurses with referral to a specialist clinic for people with genital chlamydia
      diagnosed in a community setting. We hypothesised that referral to a specialist would be more
      effective in ensuring treatment of the sexual partners of infected people than the simpler
      nurse-led strategy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Partner notification (contact tracing) is essential to the control of sexually transmitted
      infections. Reports of new chlamydia infections have increased by 66% in the past five years.
      A National Chlamydia Screening Programme in England, and increasing primary care provision of
      sexual health care are part of the United Kingdom Government's strategy for tackling
      increasing rates of sexually transmitted infections. New strategies for managing chlamydia in
      non-specialist settings are urgently required: genitourinary medicine clinics are failing to
      cope with their increasing workload; and 45% of cases detected in the chlamydia screening
      pilot studies were diagnosed in general practice.

      Partner notification involves informing the sexual partners of someone with a sexually
      transmitted infection of the possibility of exposure, offering them diagnosis and treatment,
      and providing advice about preventing future infection. In the United Kingdom, this is
      usually done by specialist sexual health advisers in departments of genitourinary medicine.
      The effectiveness of partner notification in non-specialist settings in developed countries
      is not known. We conducted a randomised controlled trial to compare the effectiveness of
      practice nurse-led partner notification with referral to a genitourinary clinic for partner
      notification conducted by a specialist health adviser, and to compare the resources used by
      each strategy.

      Comparisons: Partner notification at the time of receiving diagnosis and treatment by general
      practice nurses who received a one-day training course and ongoing support by telephone calls
      or visits from a specialist adviser in sexual health, compared with referral to a
      genitourinary medicine clinic for partner notification by a specialist adviser in sexual
      health.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of index cases with at least one sexual partner treated</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of sexual partners per index case treated</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of sexual partners per index case elicited during sexual history taking</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive chlamydia test result six weeks after treatment</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to advice to abstain from sexual intercourse until both partners completed treatment</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>214</enrollment>
  <condition>Chlamydia Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Practice nurse-led partner notification</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Referral to specialist genitourinary clinic</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chlamydia trachomatis diagnosed through a population-based screening study

          -  Chlamydia test result received at patient's general practice

          -  Chlamydia cases diagnosed in general practice

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicola Low, MFPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Chlamydia Screening Studies (ClaSS) Project General Practices</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chlamydia Screening Studies (ClaSS) project general practices</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bristol</city>
        <state>Avon</state>
        <zip>BS8 2PR</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chlamydia Screening Studies (ClaSS) project general practices</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>West Midlands</state>
        <zip>B15 2TT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Low N, McCarthy A, Macleod J, Salisbury C, Horner PJ, Roberts TE, Campbell R, Herring A, Skidmore S, Sanford E, Sterne JA, Davey Smith G, Graham A, Huengsberg M, Ross J, Egger M. The chlamydia screening studies: rationale and design. Sex Transm Infect. 2004 Oct;80(5):342-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15459400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Low N, McCarthy A, Roberts TE, Huengsberg M, Sanford E, Sterne JA, Macleod J, Salisbury C, Pye K, Holloway A, Morcom A, Patel R, Robinson SM, Horner P, Barton PM, Egger M. Partner notification of chlamydia infection in primary care: randomised controlled trial and analysis of resource use. BMJ. 2006 Jan 7;332(7532):14-9. Epub 2005 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>16356945</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 31, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 31, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Chlamydia trachomatis</keyword>
  <keyword>Chlamydia infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized controlled trials</keyword>
  <keyword>Contact tracing</keyword>
  <keyword>Family practice</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chlamydia Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

