<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00114088</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5U01HS009506</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00114088</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Surgical Treatments Outcomes Project for Dysfunctional Uterine Bleeding (STOP-DUB)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Surgical Treatments Outcomes Project for Dysfunctional Uterine Bleeding (STOP-DUB)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      STOP-DUB is a multicenter randomized clinical trial that is assessing the efficacy and
      effectiveness of hysterectomy versus endometrial ablation (EA) for dysfunctional uterine
      bleeding (DUB) in women for whom medical management has not provided relief.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Surgical Treatments Outcomes Project for Dysfunctional Uterine Bleeding (STOP-DUB) is a
      multicenter, randomized clinical trial that assessed the efficacy and effectiveness of
      hysterectomy versus endometrial ablation (EA) for dysfunctional uterine bleeding (DUB) in
      women for whom medical management has not provided relief. Institutional review
      board-approved study sites included the coordinating center, chair's office, the American
      College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, and 33 clinical centers in the United States and
      Canada. STOP-DUB enrolled (1) 237 eligible patients for whom medical treatment had not been
      successful and who were randomized to either hysterectomy or EA; and (2) an observational
      cohort of 139 patients who were “provisionally ineligible” or who were eligible but did not
      wish to be randomized. Enrollment began November 25, 1997 and ended June 30, 2001. Randomized
      women were followed using telephone interviews at least 2 years and observational women were
      followed a maximum of 6 months. We also collected information on return clinical center
      visits and hospital bills from the sites directly. The primary outcome addressed by the
      randomized trial is the impact of surgery on bleeding, pain, fatigue, and the major problem
      (symptom) that led the woman to seek treatment for her condition, measured 1 year following
      surgery. Additional outcomes included the impact of surgery at time points after 1 year;
      changes in quality of life, activity limitation, sexual functioning, and urinary
      incontinence; surgical complications; additional surgery; and resource utilization. The costs
      and the relative cost-effectiveness of the two surgeries will be calculated. The main
      scientific objective for the observational study was to examine changes over time in terms of
      treatment selected, DUB-related symptoms, and quality of life. Enrolled women signed an
      informed consent to participate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Randomized trial: Impact of surgery on bleeding, pain,</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fatigue, and major problem (symptom) leading the woman to seek treatment for her condition.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Observational study: changes over time in treatment selected, DUB-related symptoms, and quality of life.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Randomized trial: Impact of surgery on primary outcomes at time points after 1 year, quality of life, activity limitation, sexual functioning, urinary incontinence, surgical complications, additional surgery, resource utilization.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>242</enrollment>
  <condition>Menorrhagia</condition>
  <condition>Uterine Bleeding</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hysterectomy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>endometrial ablation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Abnormal uterine bleeding in the absence of structural pathology, pharmacologic
             agents, IUD use, or systemic disorders of hemostasis that could explain the condition.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Prescreen

          -  Age &lt; 18 years

          -  Postmenopausal status (or bilateral oophorectomy)

          -  Bleeding not considered excessive by woman

          -  Desire to retain fertility

          -  Refusal to consider surgery

          -  Known myoma (from prior examination)

        Eligibility Screen

          -  Lack of willingness to have a gynecologic or ultrasound examination

          -  Lack of willingness to be interviewed about bleeding or consider study

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Prior endometrial resection or ablation

          -  Prior myomectomy, myolysis, or hysterectomy

        Medical History

          -  No tentative diagnosis of DUB

          -  History of malignancy of vagina, cervix, endometrium, or ovary

          -  History of complex endometrial hyperplasia or simple hyperplasia with atypia

          -  Current use of tamoxifen

          -  &lt; 6 months since onset of excessive uterine bleeding

          -  &lt; 9 months since stopping the use of IUD

          -  &lt; 9 months since stopping the use of implantable hormone agent

          -  &lt; 18 months since stopping use of Depo-Provera

          -  &lt; 6 months of anovulatory DUB after reaching euthyroid status for woman with diagnosis
             of hypothyroidism

          -  &lt; 3 months since pathology results indicate presence of endometrial polyp

        Baseline Gynecologic Examination

          -  Enlarged (&gt;= 14 weeks gestational age) uterus

          -  Focal bleeding of genital, urinary, or gastrointestinal tract

        Ultrasound Examination

          -  Presence of any submucosal myoma

          -  Presence of any myoma &gt;= 3 cm, any location

          -  Presence of &gt; 3 myomas, any size or location

          -  Presence of endometrial polyp(s)

          -  Malignancy of the vagina, cervix, endometrium, or ovary

        Laboratory and Ancillary Tests

          -  FSH level in women ages &gt; 45 years confirming postmenopausal status

          -  Abnormal urinary tract or gastrointestinal tract imaging related to uterine bleeding

          -  Evidence of cervical cancer (screened by Pap smear in last 12 months and confirmed by
             colposcopy)

          -  Evidence of complex endometrial hyperplasia or simple hyperplasia with atypia or
             endometrial cancer (endometrial biopsy in last 12 months)

          -  Any test value inconsistent with a diagnosis of DUB

          -  Any test values, unlikely to change, compromising patient safety for surgery

        Other

          -  Any existing medical condition, unlikely to change, putting patient at excessive risk
             for surgery

          -  Request for prophylactic bilateral oophorectomy by woman aged &lt;45 years

          -  Lack of willingness to comply with study requirements

          -  Uncooperative behavior

          -  Any coexisting condition that may influence a patient's ability to comply with
             participation

          -  Refusal to allow evaluation or follow-up

          -  In process of scheduling surgery at time of baseline visit

        Provisional Eligibility Criteria

          -  Refusal of randomization

          -  &lt; 3 months of medical management (excluding GnRH agonist therapy) within the past 2
             years

          -  Ongoing evaluation or treatment for abnormal cervical cytology (including endocervical
             polyps)

          -  Gastrointestinal or urinary tract condition unrelated to uterine bleeding currently
             being treated

          -  Any temporary test value compromising patient safety

          -  Any temporary existing medical condition putting patient at excessive risk from
             surgery

          -  Any coexisting condition requiring surgery (except tubal occlusion for any woman or
             oophorectomy for women &gt;= 45 years of age)

          -  Lack of willingness to proceed with surgery at this time

          -  Lack of willingness to proceed with surgery likely to result in infertility
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kay Dickersin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brown University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dickersin K, Munro M, Langenberg P, Scherer R, Frick KD, Weber AM, Johns A, Peipert JF, Clark M; Surgical Treatments Outcomes Project for Dysfunctional Uterine Bleeding Research Group. Surgical Treatments Outcomes Project for Dysfunctional Uterine Bleeding (STOP-DUB): design and methods. Control Clin Trials. 2003 Oct;24(5):591-609.</citation>
    <PMID>14500057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weber AM, Munro MG. Endometrial ablation versus hysterectomy: STOP-DUB. Medscape Womens Health. 1998 May;3(3):3.</citation>
    <PMID>9732095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 14, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Hysterectomy,</keyword>
  <keyword>Endometrial ablation,</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovulatory dysfunctional uterine bleeding,</keyword>
  <keyword>Anovulatory dysfucntional uterine bleeding,</keyword>
  <keyword>DUB</keyword>
  <keyword>Dysfunctional uterine bleeding</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Menorrhagia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metrorrhagia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

