<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00116129</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MK-0677/FM</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IND 71,596</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00116129</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of an Oral Growth Hormone Drug in the Treatment of Fibromyalgia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of MK-0677 25 mg in the Treatment of Primary Fibromyalgia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bennett, Robert, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bennett, Robert, M.D.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 24-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, trial to evaluate the
      safety, tolerability and efficacy of an orally administered growth hormone stimulating drug,
      (code named MK-0677) in the treatment of female subjects with primary fibromyalgia. The basis
      for this study is the observation that many fibromyalgia patients are growth hormone
      deficient; an earlier study of injectable growth hormone had shown benefit in this population
      of fibromyalgia patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study examines whether MK-0677 treatment will improve symptoms of fibromyalgia (FM).

      The rationale for this study is the observation that many fibromyalgia patients are growth
      hormone deficient in terms of low levels of IGF-1, and that improving IGF-1 levels with
      growth hormone injections has been shown to improve fibromyalgia symptoms.

      MK-0677 is an orally administered growth hormone secretagogue manufactured by Merck &amp; Co.,
      Inc. that acts on the growth hormone secretagogue receptor in the anterior pituitary to
      stimulate the release of growth hormone. This pathway represents an additional regulation of
      growth hormone release from pituitary somatotrophs to that mediated by growth hormone
      releasing hormone (stimulating) and somatostatin (inhibitory). Both stimulatory pathways lead
      to a pulsatile release of growth hormone, with approximately 4 hour intervals between peak
      levels. This growth hormone secretion leads to a rapid and robust up regulation of IGF-1
      levels by about 50 to 100% that can be maintained with chronic therapy at a dose of 25
      mg/day.

      The primary aims of this study are:

        1. To evaluate the efficacy of MK-0677 25 mg in primary fibromyalgia subjects over a
           24-week treatment period, as assessed by the FIQ.

        2. To evaluate the safety and tolerability of MK-0677 25 mg in subjects with fibromyalgia.

      The secondary aims of this study are to determine whether:

        1. MK-0677 25 mg is superior to placebo in reducing muscle tenderness, as assessed by the
           Fibromyalgia Myalgic Score (FMyS).

        2. MK-0677 25 mg is superior to placebo in improving the subjects' global perception of
           change in fibromyalgia symptoms, as assessed by the Subjects' Global Impression of
           Change Questionnaire (PGIC).

        3. MK-0677 25 mg is superior to placebo in improving the subjects' quality of life, as
           assessed by the Quality of Life Questionnaire (QOL).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MK-0677 25 mg is superior to placebo in reducing symptoms of fibromyalgia, as assessed by the Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire (FIQ) over a 24-week treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MK-0677 25 mg is generally safe and well tolerated in subjects with fibromyalgia</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MK-0677 25 mg is superior to placebo in improving the subjects' global perception of change in fibromyalgia symptoms, as assessed by the Subjects' Global Impression of Change Questionnaire (PGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MK-0677 25 mg is superior to placebo in improving the subjects' quality of life, as assessed by the Quality of Life Questionnaire (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibutamoren Mesylate (MK-0677)</intervention_name>
    <description>Ibutamoren Mesylate 25 mg/day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will all be female primary fibromyalgia subjects who are 30 to 65 years of
             age, inclusive, and have a low age adjusted serum IGF-1 level.

          -  All subjects will fulfill a diagnosis of fibromyalgia according to the classification
             criteria of the American College of Rheumatology (ACR).

          -  All subjects will have an initial Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire (FIQ) score ≥ 40.

          -  If subject is of childbearing potential and sexually active, she agrees to use
             effective barrier or appropriate oral contraception during the study. Subjects who are
             taking oral contraceptives must have done so for at least 2 months prior to entering
             the study.

          -  Subject is not pregnant and is not nursing.

          -  Patient has a normal screening breast exam. If screening breast exam is abnormal, but
             not suggestive of breast cancer, the patient must have had a normal mammogram within
             the last 6 months.

          -  Subject has a normal screening stool hemoccult. If the screening stool hemoccult is
             abnormal, but likely due to hemorrhoids, the subject must have had a normal
             sigmoidoscopy within the last 2 years.

          -  Subject is willing to discontinue using grapefruit juice for duration of study.

          -  Subject is willing to be followed by telephone contact for 3 months after she has
             discontinued study and completed and returned the Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire,
             Patient Global Change score, Quality of Life score, Brief Pain Inventory and Beck
             Depression Questionnaire.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has an-ongoing, unresolved disability litigation.

          -  Subject has diabetes or a significantly elevated random glucose at the Screening
             visit.

          -  Subject has a current or past history of cardiovascular, pulmonary, neurological,
             endocrine or renal disease that would preclude involvement in an exercise program
             (specifically hypertension, a myocardial infarction within the last 6 months, chronic
             obstructive pulmonary disease [COPD], asthma, untreated hypothyroidism, severe
             depression with suicide risk, previous pituitary disease or surgery).

          -  Subject has a history of angina or congestive heart failure with symptoms that occur
             at rest.

          -  Subject has a history or current evidence of a psychotic disorder (e.g.
             schizophrenia), bipolar disorder or major depression, or substance abuse by DSM-IV
             criteria; severe depression, as evidenced by a Beck Depression score of ≥ 30.

          -  Subject has history of neurological disorder other than fibromyalgia (e.g. epilepsy,
             stroke, neuropathy, neuropathic pain).

          -  Subject has ongoing symptoms of carpal tunnel syndrome.

          -  Subject has any other significant pain state, i.e. subject must have primary
             fibromyalgia.

          -  Subject has a history of hepatitis or liver disease that has been active within the
             past 12 weeks.

          -  Subject has cancer or a history of cancer within the past 2 years, or a history of
             cancer of more than 2 years ago and deemed to not be cured, or subject has ANY history
             of breast cancer. (NOTE: Subjects with a history of basal cell or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin treated more than 1 year ago and with no evidence of recurrence
             may participate.)

          -  Subject has abnormal thyroid stimulating-hormone, or T4 concentrations.

          -  Subject has a planned elective surgery during the study period.

          -  Subject has a history of hypersensitivity or idiosyncratic reaction to more than 2
             drug classes (by chemical classification).

          -  Subject has abnormal Screening visit laboratory values.

          -  Subject is using any of the following medications : heparin, ticlopidine, ginko (in
             subjects taking warfarin), oral steroids (&gt;/= 7 days per month), chronic use of strong
             CYP3A4 inhibitors (HIV protease inhibitors, macrolide antibiotics and nefazodone),
             chronic use of CYP3A4 inducers (carbamazepine, phenytoin, rifampin, and St. John's
             Wort).

             p. Subject has received an investigational drug or device within 30 days of study
             entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Bennett, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennett RM, Cook DM, Clark SR, Burckhardt CS, Campbell SM. Hypothalamic-pituitary-insulin-like growth factor-I axis dysfunction in patients with fibromyalgia. J Rheumatol. 1997 Jul;24(7):1384-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9228141</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennett RM, Clark SC, Walczyk J. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of growth hormone in the treatment of fibromyalgia. Am J Med. 1998 Mar;104(3):227-31.</citation>
    <PMID>9552084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 6, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bennett, Robert, M.D.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert Bennett MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine OHSU</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fibromyalgia</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Growth hormone</keyword>
  <keyword>IGF-1</keyword>
  <keyword>MK-0677</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral growth hormone secretagogue</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

