<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00113711</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>184</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL052577</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00113711</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Promoting Smoking Cessation and Reducing Weight Gain</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To test whether a behavioral intervention could indeed achieve the dual goals of promoting
      smoking cessation and minimizing weight gain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      When the study began in 1995, more females were initiating cigarette smoking, and a growing
      proportion cited fear of gaining weight as a major reason for refusing to even attempt
      quitting smoking. It had not yet been possible, however, to prevent post- cessation weight
      gain through dieting or behavioral treatment without undermining abstinence from smoking. The
      investigators proposed that prior interventions had been unsuccessful because: (a) their
      weight management interventions were too complex; (b) the programs thwarted a need of the
      patient in nicotine withdrawal to eat hedonically appealing, high-carbohydrate snacks; and
      (c) the programs heightened patients' emphasis on weight control at the expense of their
      emphasis on smoking cessation by asking them to initiate weight control before or
      simultaneously with quitting smoking.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      The investigators collected pilot data on a promising 16-week intervention that they called
      the LATE WEIGHT PLAN because it emphasized smoking cessation for the first half of treatment
      and integrated weight management for the last half. The weight management module included a
      pre-packaged meal plan; high-carbohydrate, low-fat snacks; and low-intensity aerobic
      exercise. All patients continued in the weight management phase of treatment, regardless of
      whether they had succeeded in quitting smoking or were preparing to make new quit attempts.
      Based on pilot findings, the investigators estimated the point prevalence of smoking
      cessation for the LATE WEIGHT PLAN group to be 74% at the end of treatment, with weight gain
      less than 5 lb. An EARLY WEIGHT PLAN group controlled for the timing of the intervention,
      using the same target quit smoking date and 16 week program but integrating the weight
      management module into the first 8 weeks of treatment. Like others, they found that EARLY
      weight management efforts, while they may have prevented weight gain, apparently did so at
      some cost to smoking cessation, which they estimated to be 42% at 4 months. Finally, a
      CESSATION ONLY group controlled for the presence of a weight management intervention, by
      dealing exclusively with smoking cessation for the entire 16 week program. The CESSATION ONLY
      group had attained the worst outcome in terms of weight control and an intermediate outcome
      in terms of abstinence at the end of treatment (50%). By randomizing 315 female smokers to
      the three treatments and comparing abstinence and weight gain after 4 months of treatment and
      6 month follow-up (10 months), they tested whether a behavioral intervention could indeed
      achieve the dual goals of promoting smoking cessation and minimizing weight gain.

      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1999</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>smoking cessation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>reducing diet</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        A total of 315 female smokers.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bonnie Spring</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Illinois at Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Persky I, Spring B, Vander Wal JS, Pagoto S, Hedeker D. Adherence across behavioral domains in treatment promoting smoking cessation plus weight control. Health Psychol. 2005 Mar;24(2):153-60.</citation>
    <PMID>15755229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sánchez-Johnsen LA, Spring BJ, Sommerfeld BK, Fitzgibbon ML. Weight concerns and smoking in Black and White female smokers. Addict Behav. 2005 Mar;30(3):601-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15718079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sánchez-Johnsen LA, Fitzgibbon ML, Ahluwalia JS, Spring BJ. Eating pathology among Black and White smokers. Eat Behav. 2005 Feb;6(2):127-36.</citation>
    <PMID>15598599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spring B, Pagoto S, Pingitore R, Doran N, Schneider K, Hedeker D. Randomized controlled trial for behavioral smoking and weight control treatment: effect of concurrent versus sequential intervention. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2004 Oct;72(5):785-96.</citation>
    <PMID>15482037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doran N, Spring B, McChargue D, Pergadia M, Richmond M. Impulsivity and smoking relapse. Nicotine Tob Res. 2004 Aug;6(4):641-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15370160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katsutani N, Shionoya H. Drug-specific immune responses induced by procainamide, hydralazine and isoniazid in guinea-pigs. Int J Immunopharmacol. 1992 May;14(4):673-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1521934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cook JW, Spring B, McChargue D, Hedeker D. Hedonic capacity, cigarette craving, and diminished positive mood. Nicotine Tob Res. 2004 Feb;6(1):39-47.</citation>
    <PMID>14982686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spring B, Pagoto S, McChargue D, Hedeker D, Werth J. Altered reward value of carbohydrate snacks for female smokers withdrawn from nicotine. Pharmacol Biochem Behav. 2003 Sep;76(2):351-60.</citation>
    <PMID>14592688</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spring B, Pingitore R, McChargue DE. Reward value of cigarette smoking for comparably heavy smoking schizophrenic, depressed, and nonpatient smokers. Am J Psychiatry. 2003 Feb;160(2):316-22.</citation>
    <PMID>12562579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnsen L, MacKirnan D, Spring B, Pingitore R, Sommerfeld BK. Smoking as subculture? Influence on Hispanic and non-Hispanic White women's attitudes toward smoking and obesity. Health Psychol. 2002 May;21(3):279-87.</citation>
    <PMID>12027034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richmond M, Spring B, Sommerfeld BK, MeChargue D. Rumination and cigarette smoking: a bad combination for depressive outcomes? J Consult Clin Psychol. 2001 Oct;69(5):836-40.</citation>
    <PMID>11680561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borrelli B, Spring B, Niaura R, Kristeller J, Ockene JK, Keuthen NJ. Weight suppression and weight rebound in ex-smokers treated with fluoxetine. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1999 Feb;67(1):124-31.</citation>
    <PMID>10028216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 10, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 13, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

