<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00112320</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>188</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P50HL074734</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P50HL074734-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00112320</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Two Pulmonary Valve Replacement Methods to Treat Tetralogy of Fallot</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Trial of Pulmonary Valve Replacement in Tetralogy of Fallot</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Repair of tetralogy of Fallot (TOF), the most common form of cyanotic congenital heart
      disease, usually involves surgery on the outflow of the right ventricle (RV) and the
      pulmonary valve in order to relieve obstruction to blood flow from the RV to the lungs. This
      procedure often leads to regurgitation (leakage) of the pulmonary valve, which puts the
      burden of handling a larger than normal amount of blood flow on the RV. Over the years, that
      extra burden leads to enlargement of the RV and to a decrease in its function. Treatment
      often includes surgical insertion or replacement of a new pulmonary valve. Replacement of the
      damaged pulmonary valve aims to minimize the leakage and help the RV function better. This
      study is designed to compare two methods of how the operation (called pulmonary valve
      replacement [PVR]) is performed. In the first method, a new valve is inserted and only the
      area of the old valve is operated on; this is the standard PVR. The second method involves
      inserting the new valve in the same way as the standard method but, in addition, areas of the
      right ventricular wall that are scarred and not functioning well are removed (PVR plus right
      ventricular remodeling). This study will evaluate which method is more effective based on the
      size and function of the RV measured by cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMR) six months
      following surgery, as compared to its size and function before the operation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Surgical repair of TOF often results in chronic pulmonary regurgitation (PR) with associated
      RV dilatation and dysfunction. Mounting evidence indicates that PR leads to significant
      long-term morbidity and mortality, including arrhythmias, sudden death, and right heart
      failure. Using CMR, there is a high prevalence of regional dysfunction and aneurysms in the
      RV in patients with repaired TOF. Current standard clinical practice in patients with
      repaired TOF, severe PR, ventricular dysfunction, and/or clinical deterioration is to insert
      a bioprosthetic pulmonary valve to reduce the volume load on the RV. Although PVR can be
      achieved with low mortality, research has shown a persistent or worsening RV dysfunction
      postoperatively, despite a competent pulmonary valve. In patients with left ventricular (LV)
      aneurysms, surgical remodeling with aneurysm resection has been shown to improve LV
      mechanics. In view of the potentially deleterious effects of aneurysmal and akinetic wall
      segments on RV mechanics, researcher have recently modified their PVR surgical technique in
      selected patients to include surgical remodeling of the RV with resection of the akinetic
      wall segments. However, no studies have systematically compared the efficacy of PVR plus
      surgical RV remodeling to PVR alone.

      Research Question:

      Is there a difference between two surgical strategies—PVR alone (bioprosthetic pulmonary
      valve insertion and, when present, resection of right ventricular outflow tract [RVOT]
      aneurysm) versus PVR and surgical RV remodeling (bioprosthetic pulmonary valve insertion and
      resection of akinetic scarred areas on the anterior RV wall to reduce RV volume)—on RV
      mechanics and on the incidence of adverse events in patients with repaired TOF and chronic
      pulmonary regurgitation?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in ventricular mechanics compared with the preoperative ventricular mechanics</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of one or more postoperative adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Tetralogy of Fallot</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Valve Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Ventricular Dysfunction, Right</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard PVR</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PVR plus RV remodeling</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PVR plus RV remodeling</intervention_name>
    <description>PVR and surgical RV remodeling, which includes bioprosthetic pulmonary valve insertion and resection of akinetic scarred areas on the anterior RV wall to reduce RV volume</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard PVR</intervention_name>
    <description>PVR alone, which includes bioprosthetic pulmonary valve insertion and, when present, resection of right ventricular outflow tract (RVOT) aneurysm</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Undergoing PVR to repair TOF at Children's Hospital Boston

          -  Pulmonary regurgitation fraction greater than or equal to 25% (measured by CMR) and
             two or more of the following criteria:

               1. RV end-diastolic volume index greater than or equal to 150 ml/m2 (Z score greater
                  than 5)

               2. RV end-systolic volume index greater than or equal to 70 ml/m2

               3. LV end-diastolic volume index less than or equal to 65 ml/m2

               4. RV ejection fraction less than 45%

               5. RVOT aneurysm

               6. Clinical criteria: exercise intolerance, symptoms and signs of heart failure, and
                  use of cardiac medications

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of either severe RV outflow tract obstruction (defined as peak-to-peak
             systolic gradient of greater than or equal to 60 mm Hg by cardiac catheterization) or
             severe RV hypertension at systemic or higher level

          -  Additional sources of RV volume overload other than PR and tricuspid valve
             regurgitation

          -  Contraindications to CMR
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tal Geva, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Cardiology, Children's Hospital Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 3, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 3, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Judith Geva</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Study coordinator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Valve Regurgitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Right Ventricular Dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Diseases</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetralogy of Fallot</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Dysfunction, Right</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

