<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02996461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>170024</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>17-I-0024</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02996461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VRC 320: A Phase I, Randomized Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of a Zika Virus DNA Vaccine, VRC-ZKADNA090-00-VP, Administered Via Needle and Syringe or Needle-free Injector, PharmaJet, inHealthy Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>VRC 320: A Phase I, Randomized Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of a Zika Virus DNA Vaccine, VRC-ZKADNA090-00-VP, Administered Via Needle and Syringe or Needle-free Injector, PharmaJet, in Healthy Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      People get Zika virus from infected mosquitos. They usually don t get very sick. But birth
      defects were reported in babies born to mothers who had Zika infection. In rare cases, people
      with Zika infection had a nervous system disease that causes severe muscle weakness and can
      be life threatening. A new vaccine made from DNA in the code for a Zika virus protein could
      help the body build an immune response against the virus.

      Objectives:

      To see if a new vaccine against Zika virus disease is safe and causes any side effects. To
      study specific immune responses to the vaccine.

      Eligibility:

      Healthy people ages 18-50

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with:

      Medical history

      Physical exam

      Urine tests

      Participants will have 18 visits over 2 years.

      Participants will be randomly assigned to 1 of 3 groups. All will get 3 vaccines at 3
      separate monthly visits. They will receive the vaccine in the upper arm muscle. Some will get
      it by needle and syringe, others by a device that uses high pressure to push the vaccine
      through the skin.

      Vaccine visits last 4-6 hours. Participants will get a thermometer to measure their
      temperature and a ruler to measure any skin changes at the injection site. They will record
      this data for 7 days after each injection.

      Other visits last 1-2 hours. These include:

      Evaluation of any health changes or problems

      Blood tests: Some samples may be used for future research.

      Participants with side effects may have extra visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY DESIGN:

      This is a Phase I, randomized clinical study to evaluate the safety, tolerability, and
      immunogenicity of a 3 dose vaccination regimen with the Zika virus (ZIKVwt) DNA vaccine,
      VRC-ZKADNA090-00-VP. Subjects will be randomized to one of three groups to receive a full 4
      mg dose: 1) full dose by one intramuscular (IM) injection with needle and syringe; 2) split
      dose given as two 0.5 mL IM injections with needle and syringe; 3) split dose given as two
      0.5 mL IM injections with PharmaJet, a needle-free injection device. The primary hypothesis
      is that the investigational ZIKVwt DNA vaccine will be safe and well tolerated in healthy
      adults. A secondary hypothesis is that the vaccine will elicit a ZIKV-specific immune
      response. The primary objectives are to evaluate the safety and tolerability of the vaccine
      in healthy adults. Secondary objectives are related to the immunogenicity of the vaccine and
      vaccination regimens.

      PRODUCT DESCRIPTION:

      The investigational vaccine, VRC-ZKADNA090-00-VP, was developed by the Vaccine Research
      Center (VRC), National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID), National
      Institutes of Health (NIH) and is composed of a single closed-circular DNA plasmid (VRC 5283)
      that encodes the wild type (wt) precursor membrane M (prM) and envelope (E) proteins from the
      H/PF/2013 strain of ZIKV. ZIKVwt

      SUBJECTS:

      Healthy adults 18 to 50 years of age.

      STUDY PLAN:

      Forty-five subjects will be enrolled at the NIH Clinical Center and randomized to 3 groups to
      receive study product on Day 0, Week 4 and Week 8. The protocol requires about 18 scheduled
      clinic visits and a telephone follow-up contact after each study product administration.
      Solicited reactogenicity will be evaluated using a 7-day diary card. Assessment of vaccine
      safety will include clinical observation and monitoring of hematological and chemical
      parameters at clinical visits throughout the study.

      VRC 320 STUDY SCHEMA:

        -  Group 1:

             -  Administration Method = Single Dose Needle and Syringe;

             -  Subjects = 15;

             -  Administration Schedule = Day 0 (ZIKVwt DNA(1 (1 mL) injection)), Week 4 (ZIKVwt
                DNA (1 (1 mL) injection)), Week 8 (ZIKVwt DNA (1 (1 mL) injection))

        -  Group 2:

             -  Administration Method = Split Dose Needle and Syringe;

             -  Subjects = 15;

             -  Administration Schedule = Day 0 (ZIKVwt DNA(2 (0.5 mL) injections)), Week 4 (ZIKVwt
                DNA (2 (0.5 mL) injections)), Week 8 (ZIKVwt DNA (2 (0.5 mL) injections))

        -  Group 3:

             -  Administration Method = Split Dose PharmaJet;

             -  Subjects = 15;

             -  Administration Schedule = Day 0 (ZIKVwt DNA(2 (0.5 mL) injections)), Week 4 (ZIKVwt
                DNA (2 (0.5 mL) injections)), Week 8 (ZIKVwt DNA (2 (0.5 mL) injections))

             -  Subjects Total = 45 (All injections total a dose of 4 mg. ** Up to 50 total
                enrollments are permitted if additional subjects are needed to assess safety or
                immunogenicity.)

      STUDY DURATION:

      Subjects will be evaluated for safety and immune responses throughout the study for 44 weeks
      following the first vaccine administration. Durability of immune responses will be evaluated
      at two long term follow-up visits, occurring at 18 and 24 months
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 16, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 28, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 28, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of v ZIKV DNA vaccine administered at 4mg IM by needle and syringe.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 44 weeks of study participation.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of ZIKV DNA vaccine administered at 4 mg IM by Pharma jet.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 44 weeks of study participation.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the magnitude and the frequency of ZIKV-specific antibody response as measured by neutralization assay.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four weeks after the first, second and third injections for each regimen.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Prevention of Zika Infection</condition>
  <condition>Zika-Specific Immune Response</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ZIKV DNA vaccine administered IM via needle and syringe at a single dosage of 4 mg on Day 0, week 4 and week 8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ZIKV DNA vaccine administered IM via needle and syringe as a split dose of two .5 ml injections on Day 0, week 4 and week 8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ZIKV DNA vaccine administered IM via needle-free injection device, PharmaJet, as a split dose of two .5 ml injections on Day 0, week 4 and week 8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VRC-ZKADNA090-00-VP</intervention_name>
    <description>VRC-ZKADNA090-00-VP is an investigational ZIKV DNA vaccine that is intended to prevent Zika virus infection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A subject must meet all of the following criteria:

          -  18 to 50 years old

          -  Available for clinic visits for 24 months after enrollment

          -  Able to provide proof of identity to the satisfaction of the study clinician
             completing the enrollment process

          -  Able and willing to complete the informed consent process

          -  Willing to donate blood for sample storage to be used for future research

          -  In good general health without clinically significant medical history

          -  Physical examination and laboratory results without clinically significant findings
             and a Body Mass Index (BMI) less than or equal to 40 within the 56 days prior to
             enrollment

          -  Agrees not to receive licensed or investigational flavivirus vaccines through 4 weeks
             after last product administration

          -  Laboratory Criteria within 56 days prior to enrollment:

               -  Hemoglobin within institutional normal limits or accompanied by the site
                  Principal Investigator (PI) or designee approval

               -  WBC and differential either within institutional normal range or accompanied by
                  site PI or designee approval

               -  Total lymphocyte count greater than or equal to 800 cells/mm^3

               -  Platelets = 125,000 - 500,000/mm^3

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) less than or equal to 1.25 x institutional upper
                  limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.1 x institutional ULN

               -  Negative for HIV infection by an FDA approved method of detection

          -  Criteria applicable to women of childbearing potential:

               -  Negative human chorionic gonadotropin (beta-HCG) pregnancy test (urine or serum)
                  on day of enrollment

               -  Agrees to use an effective means of birth control from at least 21 days prior to
                  enrollment through 12 weeks after the last study vaccination

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A subject will be excluded if one or more of the following conditions apply:

          -  Female-specific: Breast-feeding or planning to become pregnant while participating
             through 12 weeks after the last study vaccination

          -  Subject has received any of the following:

               -  More than 10 days of systemic immunosuppressive medications or cytotoxic
                  medications within the 4 weeks prior to enrollment or any within the 14 days
                  prior to enrollment

               -  Blood products within 16 weeks prior to enrollment

               -  Inactivated vaccines within 2 weeks prior to enrollment

               -  Live attenuated vaccines within 4 weeks prior to enrollment

               -  Investigational research products within 4 weeks prior to enrollment or planning
                  to receive investigational products while on the study

               -  Current allergen immunotherapy with antigen injections, unless on maintenance
                  schedule

               -  Current anti-TB prophylaxis or therapy

          -  Subject has a history of any of the following clinically significant conditions:

               -  Laboratory confirmed ZIKV infection by self-report at the time of enrollment

               -  Serious reactions to vaccines that preclude receipt of study vaccinations as
                  determined by the site investigator

               -  Hereditary angioedema, acquired angioedema, or idiopathic forms of angioedema

               -  Asthma that is not well controlled

               -  Diabetes mellitus (type I or II), with the exception of gestational diabetes

               -  Evidence of autoimmune disease or immunodeficiency

               -  Idiopathic urticaria within the past year

               -  Hypertension that is not well controlled

               -  Bleeding disorder diagnosed by a doctor (e.g. factor deficiency, coagulopathy, or
                  platelet disorder requiring special precautions) or significant bruising or
                  bleeding difficulties with IM injections or blood draws

               -  Malignancy that is active or history of malignancy that is likely to recur during
                  the period of the study

               -  Seizure disorder other than: 1) febrile seizures, 2) seizures secondary to
                  alcohol withdrawal more than 3 years ago, or 3) seizures that have not required
                  treatment within the last 3 years

               -  Asplenia, functional asplenia or any condition resulting in the absence or
                  removal of the spleen

               -  Guillain-Barre Syndrome, Bell's palsy or similar neurological conditions

               -  Psychiatric condition that precludes compliance with the protocol; past or
                  present psychoses; or within 5 years prior to enrollment, a history of suicide
                  plan or attempt

               -  Any medical, psychiatric, social condition, occupational reason or other
                  responsibility that, in the judgment of the investigator, is a contraindication
                  to protocol participation or impairs a volunteer's ability to give informed
                  consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Grace L Chen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2017-I-0024.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dowd KA, Ko SY, Morabito KM, Yang ES, Pelc RS, DeMaso CR, Castilho LR, Abbink P, Boyd M, Nityanandam R, Gordon DN, Gallagher JR, Chen X, Todd JP, Tsybovsky Y, Harris A, Huang YS, Higgs S, Vanlandingham DL, Andersen H, Lewis MG, De La Barrera R, Eckels KH, Jarman RG, Nason MC, Barouch DH, Roederer M, Kong WP, Mascola JR, Pierson TC, Graham BS. Rapid development of a DNA vaccine for Zika virus. Science. 2016 Oct 14;354(6309):237-240. Epub 2016 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>27708058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ledgerwood JE, Graham BS. DNA vaccines: a safe and efficient platform technology for responding to emerging infectious diseases. Hum Vaccin. 2009 Sep;5(9):623-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19779298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graham BS, Ledgerwood JE, Nabel GJ. Vaccine development in the twenty-first century: changing paradigms for elusive viruses. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2009 Sep;86(3):234-6. doi: 10.1038/clpt.2009.128.</citation>
    <PMID>19707212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 8, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 16, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 19, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Zika Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune Response</keyword>
  <keyword>Flavivirus</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthropod-Borne Virus</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

