<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02990793</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MeRT-TBI-005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02990793</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of MeRT Treatment in Persistent Post-Concussive Symptoms (PPCS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>MeRT-TBI-005</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Double-Blind, Randomized, Sham-Controlled, Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of MeRT Treatment of Persistent Post-Concussive Symptoms (PPCS) Following Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Newport Brain Research Laboratory</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>U.S. Special Operations Command</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Henry M. Jackson Foundation for the Advancement of Military Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>KAI Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Newport Brain Research Laboratory</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of individualized,
      Biometrics-guided Magnetic e-Resonance Therapy (MeRT) treatment of Persistent Post-Concussive
      Symptoms (PPCS) following Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      MeRT-TBI-005 is a prospective, double blind, randomized, sham-controlled, parallel group,
      adaptive clinical trial designed to evaluate the efficacy of EEG/EKG-guided MeRT in active
      duty military service men and women, reservists on active duty orders, and military retirees
      with Persistent Post-Concussion Symptoms (PPCS) and Traumatic Brain Injury. A total of 150
      participants will be randomized, with blinded adaptive sample size reassessment up to 250
      participants, and a contingent group-sequential single look at interim efficacy data by the
      Data and Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB).

      Participants will be recruited from military bases, and their vicinities, in two locations.
      Eligible participants will be randomly assigned to either MeRT or Sham MeRT treatment groups
      in a 1:1 allocation ratio, with stratification on recruitment site and two levels of PTSD
      co-morbidity (+/-). Treatment will be initiated on Day 1 of the study, following eligibility
      evaluation and data collection at the Screening Visit (SC) and Baseline (BL) Visit. Following
      the SC and BL visits, there will be a 4-week treatment period. Main study outcomes will be
      collected at the second follow-up visit (F2) at the conclusion of the 4-week treatment
      period. An abbreviated data collection visit will occur at the conclusion of the second
      treatment week (the F1 follow-up visit). Participants, clinicians, and all personnel who
      participate in evaluation, or who interface with treatment protocol downloading software,
      will be blind to study treatment group assignment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 24, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in PPCS</measure>
    <time_frame>Four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in Persistent Post-Concussion Symptoms; arithmetic reduction in Rivermead Post-Concussion Symptoms Questionnaire (RPQ-16) total severity score between time points SC and F2.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PTSD Symptom Reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>Four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in PTSD symptoms will be measured by change in PCL-5 scores between SC and F2 in the subgroup of participants with comorbid PTSD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep quality improvement; arithmetic reduction in Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Outcomes - Incidents and types of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Four weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Arithmetic number of Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Postconcussive Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain INjury</condition>
  <condition>PostTraumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active MeRT Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active treatment will consist of 6 seconds a minute for 30 minutes a day, 5 days a week for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham MeRT Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham treatment will consist of 6 seconds a minute for 30 minutes a day, 5 days a week for 4 weeks. Sham treatment mimicks same noise and sensation of active treatment but provides no treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active MeRT Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>A personalized biometrics-guided protocol known as magnetic EEG/EKG resonance therapy (MeRT) treatment that is tailored specifically to each patient's higher harmonic frequency of heart rate, which is nearest to the characteristic frequency of alpha EEG frequency.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active MeRT Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>rTMS Active Stimulator</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham MeRT Treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>A personalized biometrics-guided protocol similar to MeRT treatment that mimics magnetic EEG/EKG resonance therapy (MeRT) but does not emit active stimulation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham MeRT Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>rTMS Sham Stimulator</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        Participants must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to qualify for enrollment in
        the study:

          1. Willing and able to consent to participate in the study

          2. Active duty, reservist on active duty orders, National Guard on active duty orders, or
             military retiree, United States military service men and women

          3. Age 18 - 55 years

          4. TBI according to the following American Congress of Rehabilitation Medicine (ACRM)
             criteria for mTBI, excepting that the severity of injury associated with focal
             neurological deficit(s) may exceed the ACRM criteria for mild injury:

             Sustaining of a traumatically induced physiological disruption of brain function, as
             manifested by at least one of the following -

               -  Any period of loss of consciousness

               -  Any loss of memory for events immediately before or after the accident

               -  Any alteration in mental state at the time of the accident

               -  Focal neurological deficit(s) that may or may not be transient

          5. The TBI was followed within a maximum of 4 weeks by symptoms persisting for at least 6
             months as of the Screening Visit in at least 3 of the following 6 categories listed in
             the ICD-10 criteria for Post-Concussive syndrome:

               -  Headache, dizziness, malaise, fatigue, noise tolerance

               -  Irritability, depression, anxiety, emotional lability

               -  Subjective concentration, memory, or intellectual difficulties without
                  neuropsychological evidence of marked impairment

               -  Insomnia

               -  Reduced alcohol tolerance

               -  Preoccupation with above symptoms and fear of brain damage with hypochondriacal
                  concern and adoption of sick role

          6. Rivermead Post-Concussion Questionnaire (RPQ-16) score ≥ 16

        Exclusion Criteria

        Participants will be excluded from study participation if one or more of the following
        exclusion criteria apply:

          1. History of open skull injury

          2. History of a neurological disorder including, but not limited to:

               -  Seizure disorder

               -  Any condition likely to be associated with increased intracranial pressure

               -  Space occupying brain lesion

          3. History of cerebrovascular accident

          4. History of cerebral aneurysm

          5. EEG abnormalities that indicate risk of seizure, i.e., abnormal focal or general
             slowing, or ictal spikes, during the EEG recording

          6. Participation in any interventional research protocol within 3 months prior to the
             Screening Visit

          7. History of any type of ECT, MeRT, or rTMS

          8. Treated within 30 days of the Screening Visit with any antipsychotic medication

          9. Treated within 30 days of the Screening Visit with any anticonvulsant or anxiolytic
             medications listed as exclusionary in this protocol

         10. Intracranial implant (e.g., aneurysm clips, shunts, stimulators, cochlear implants,
             stents, or electrodes) or any other metal object within the head, excluding the mouth,
             or on the head, that cannot be safely removed

         11. Biomedical devices, including those not in or on the head, that are either implanted
             or not safe to remove, that may be affected by the magnetic field of the stimulator
             (e.g., cardiac pacemaker, cardioverter defibrillator (ICD), or medication dispensing
             device)

         12. Clinically significant medical illness or condition, including, but not limited to,
             any uncontrolled thyroid disorders, hepatic, cardiac, pulmonary and renal malfunction,
             or chronic excessive alcohol consumption, that in the Investigator's judgment might
             pose a potential safety risk to the participant or limit the interpretation of trial
             results

         13. Clinically significant psychopathology, including, but not limited to, schizophrenia
             or bipolar disorder, or other psychiatric disorder that in the Investigator's judgment
             might pose a potential safety risk to the participant, or limit the interpretation of
             trial results

         14. An elevated risk of suicide or violence to others

         15. Current psychotherapeutic treatment, expected to continue throughout the trial, that
             was begun in the preceding 30 days at the time of the Screening Visit

         16. Current treatment with any prohibited concomitant medication (i.e., Gabapentin,
             Pregabalin, Topiramate) that has not been stable for the preceding 30 days at the time
             of the Screening Visit

         17. Inability to acquire a satisfactory EEG/ECG at Baseline, or on a routine basis

         18. Pregnant, or female unwilling to use effective birth control during the course of the
             trial

         19. Plan to move away from the area, or knowledge that there will be a deployment, prior
             to 9 weeks from the Screening Visit

         20. Unwilling or unable to adhere to the study treatment, data collection schedule, or
             study procedures, or any condition, including inability to communicate in English,
             which in the judgment of the Investigator would prevent the participant from
             completing the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott Cota, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>SOCOM</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Chung, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Naval Hospital Camp Pendleton</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Keyser, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>301-816-8461</phone>
    <email>david.keyser@usuhs.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dmitry Mirochnitchenko</last_name>
    <phone>301-816-8462</phone>
    <email>dmitry.mirochnitchenko.ctr@usuhs.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Naval Special Warfare</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diana Lee</last_name>
      <phone>619-255-2112</phone>
      <email>dianamerts202@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christa Cooper</last_name>
      <phone>619-255-2112</phone>
      <email>christa.merts201@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Chung, DO</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MacDill Air Force Base</name>
      <address>
        <city>Macdill Air Force Base</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33621</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>MaLisa Lewis</last_name>
      <phone>801-989-0656</phone>
      <email>malisa.lewis.ctr@us.af.mil</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Katryna Deary</last_name>
      <phone>813-831-9911</phone>
      <email>katryna.deary.ctr@socom.mil</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scott Cota, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abelson JL, Curtis GC, Sagher O, Albucher RC, Harrigan M, Taylor SF, Martis B, Giordani B. Deep brain stimulation for refractory obsessive-compulsive disorder. Biol Psychiatry. 2005 Mar 1;57(5):510-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15737666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Achard S, Delon-Martin C, Vértes PE, Renard F, Schenck M, Schneider F, Heinrich C, Kremer S, Bullmore ET. Hubs of brain functional networks are radically reorganized in comatose patients. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2012 Dec 11;109(50):20608-13. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1208933109. Epub 2012 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23185007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>ACRM: Mild Traumatic Brain Injury Committee. (1993). Definition of mild traumatic brain injury. J Head Trauma Rehabil, 8, 86-87.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Psychiatric Association Task Force on DSM-IV. (2000). Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders: DSM-IV-TR. 4th ed. Washington, DC: American Psychiatric Association.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arciniegas DB, Silver JM. Regarding the search for a unified definition of mild traumatic brain injury. Brain Inj. 2001 Jul;15(7):649-52.</citation>
    <PMID>11429094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bae EH, Schrader LM, Machii K, Alonso-Alonso M, Riviello JJ Jr, Pascual-Leone A, Rotenberg A. Safety and tolerability of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation in patients with epilepsy: a review of the literature. Epilepsy Behav. 2007 Jun;10(4):521-8. Epub 2007 May 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17493877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blyth BJ, Bazarian JJ. Traumatic alterations in consciousness: traumatic brain injury. Emerg Med Clin North Am. 2010 Aug;28(3):571-94. doi: 10.1016/j.emc.2010.03.003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20709244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonita JD, Ambolode LC 2nd, Rosenberg BM, Cellucci CJ, Watanabe TA, Rapp PE, Albano AM. Time domain measures of inter-channel EEG correlations: a comparison of linear, nonparametric and nonlinear measures. Cogn Neurodyn. 2014 Feb;8(1):1-15. doi: 10.1007/s11571-013-9267-8. Epub 2013 Sep 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24465281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carroll LJ, Cassidy JD, Holm L, Kraus J, Coronado VG; WHO Collaborating Centre Task Force on Mild Traumatic Brain Injury. Methodological issues and research recommendations for mild traumatic brain injury: the WHO Collaborating Centre Task Force on Mild Traumatic Brain Injury. J Rehabil Med. 2004 Feb;(43 Suppl):113-25.</citation>
    <PMID>15083875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castellanos NP, Bajo R, Cuesta P, Villacorta-Atienza JA, Paúl N, Garcia-Prieto J, Del-Pozo F, Maestú F. Alteration and reorganization of functional networks: a new perspective in brain injury study. Front Hum Neurosci. 2011 Sep 21;5:90. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2011.00090. eCollection 2011.</citation>
    <PMID>21960965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castellanos NP, Paúl N, Ordóñez VE, Demuynck O, Bajo R, Campo P, Bilbao A, Ortiz T, del-Pozo F, Maestú F. Reorganization of functional connectivity as a correlate of cognitive recovery in acquired brain injury. Brain. 2010 Aug;133(Pt 8):2365-81. doi: 10.1093/brain/awq174.</citation>
    <PMID>20826433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen YH, DeMets DL, Lan KK. Increasing the sample size when the unblinded interim result is promising. Stat Med. 2004 Apr 15;23(7):1023-38.</citation>
    <PMID>15057876</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Comerchero MD, Polich J. P3a and P3b from typical auditory and visual stimuli. Clin Neurophysiol. 1999 Jan;110(1):24-30.</citation>
    <PMID>10348317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>CONSORT Group. (2010). CONSORT 2010. Retrieved January 13, 2016, from CONSORT Transparent Reporting of Trials: http://www.consort-statement.org/consort-2010</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Beaumont L, Mongeon D, Tremblay S, Messier J, Prince F, Leclerc S, Lassonde M, Théoret H. Persistent motor system abnormalities in formerly concussed athletes. J Athl Train. 2011 May-Jun;46(3):234-40.</citation>
    <PMID>21669091</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dhamne SC, Kothare RS, Yu C, Hsieh TH, Anastasio EM, Oberman L, Pascual-Leone A, Rotenberg A. A measure of acoustic noise generated from transcranial magnetic stimulation coils. Brain Stimul. 2014 May-Jun;7(3):432-4. doi: 10.1016/j.brs.2014.01.056. Epub 2014 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>24582370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Stefano G, Bachevalier J, Levin HS, Song JX, Scheibel RS, Fletcher JM. Volume of focal brain lesions and hippocampal formation in relation to memory function after closed head injury in children. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2000 Aug;69(2):210-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10896695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dupont WD, Plummer WD Jr. Power and sample size calculations. A review and computer program. Control Clin Trials. 1990 Apr;11(2):116-28.</citation>
    <PMID>2161310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dupont, W. D., &amp; Plummer, W. D. (1997). Power and Sample Size software. Controlled Clinical Trials, 18, 274.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dupont WD, Plummer WD Jr. Power and sample size calculations for studies involving linear regression. Control Clin Trials. 1998 Dec;19(6):589-601.</citation>
    <PMID>9875838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eckberg, D. L. (2004). Correlations among heart rate variability components and autonomic mechanisms. In M. Malik, &amp; J. A. Camm (Eds.), Dynamic Electrocardiology (pp. 31-39). Elmsford, NY, US: Blackwell/Futura.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>García-González MA, Fernández-Chimeno M, Ferrer J, Escorihuela RM, Parrado E, Capdevila L, Benítez A, Angulo R, Rodríguez FA, Iglesias X, Bescós R, Marina M, Padullés JM, Ramos-Castro J. New indices for quantification of the power spectrum of heart rate variability time series without the need of any frequency band definition. Physiol Meas. 2011 Aug;32(8):995-1009. doi: 10.1088/0967-3334/32/8/001. Epub 2011 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>21654027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geuze E, Vermetten E, Bremner JD. MR-based in vivo hippocampal volumetrics: 2. Findings in neuropsychiatric disorders. Mol Psychiatry. 2005 Feb;10(2):160-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15356639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gevins A, Cutillo B. Spatiotemporal dynamics of component processes in human working memory. Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol. 1993 Sep;87(3):128-43.</citation>
    <PMID>7691540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gondusky JS, Reiter MP. Protecting military convoys in Iraq: an examination of battle injuries sustained by a mechanized battalion during Operation Iraqi Freedom II. Mil Med. 2005 Jun;170(6):546-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16001610</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gordon WA, Haddad L, Brown M, Hibbard MR, Sliwinski M. The sensitivity and specificity of self-reported symptoms in individuals with traumatic brain injury. Brain Inj. 2000 Jan;14(1):21-33.</citation>
    <PMID>10670659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hardmeier M, Hatz F, Bousleiman H, Schindler C, Stam CJ, Fuhr P. Reproducibility of functional connectivity and graph measures based on the phase lag index (PLI) and weighted phase lag index (wPLI) derived from high resolution EEG. PLoS One. 2014 Oct 6;9(10):e108648. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0108648. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25286380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoge CW, Goldberg HM, Castro CA. Care of war veterans with mild traumatic brain injury--flawed perspectives. N Engl J Med. 2009 Apr 16;360(16):1588-91. doi: 10.1056/NEJMp0810606.</citation>
    <PMID>19369664</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoge CW, McGurk D, Thomas JL, Cox AL, Engel CC, Castro CA. Mild traumatic brain injury in U.S. Soldiers returning from Iraq. N Engl J Med. 2008 Jan 31;358(5):453-63. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa072972. Epub 2008 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18234750</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ingebrigtsen T, Waterloo K, Marup-Jensen S, Attner E, Romner B. Quantification of post-concussion symptoms 3 months after minor head injury in 100 consecutive patients. J Neurol. 1998 Sep;245(9):609-12.</citation>
    <PMID>9758300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>International Committee of Medical Journal Editors. (2015, December). Recommendations for the Conduct, Reporting, Editing, and Publication of Scholarly Work in Medical Journals. Retrieved February 24, 2016, from 2016 International Committee of Medical Journal editors: www.icmje.org</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janicak PG, O'Reardon JP, Sampson SM, Husain MM, Lisanby SH, Rado JT, Heart KL, Demitrack MA. Transcranial magnetic stimulation in the treatment of major depressive disorder: a comprehensive summary of safety experience from acute exposure, extended exposure, and during reintroduction treatment. J Clin Psychiatry. 2008 Feb;69(2):222-32.</citation>
    <PMID>18232722</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>King NS, Crawford S, Wenden FJ, Moss NE, Wade DT. The Rivermead Post Concussion Symptoms Questionnaire: a measure of symptoms commonly experienced after head injury and its reliability. J Neurol. 1995 Sep;242(9):587-92.</citation>
    <PMID>8551320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ling G, Bandak F, Armonda R, Grant G, Ecklund J. Explosive blast neurotrauma. J Neurotrauma. 2009 Jun;26(6):815-25. doi: 10.1089/neu.2007.0484. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19397423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu Y, Liang M, Zhou Y, He Y, Hao Y, Song M, Yu C, Liu H, Liu Z, Jiang T. Disrupted small-world networks in schizophrenia. Brain. 2008 Apr;131(Pt 4):945-61. doi: 10.1093/brain/awn018. Epub 2008 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>18299296</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loo CK, McFarquhar TF, Mitchell PB. A review of the safety of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation as a clinical treatment for depression. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol. 2008 Feb;11(1):131-47. Epub 2007 Sep 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17880752</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lopes da Silva, F. (2005(a)). EEG analysis: theory and practice. In E. Niedermeyer, &amp; F. Lopes da Silva (Eds.), Electroencephalography; Basic Principles, Clinical Applications and Related Fields (pp. 1199-1231). Philadelphia, PA, USA: Lippincott, Williams and Wilkins.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lopes da Silva, F. (2005(b)). Events-related potentials: methodology and quantification. In E. Niedermeyer, &amp; F. Lopes da Silva, Electroencephalography: Basic Principles, Clinical Applications and Related Fields (pp. 991-1001). Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, US: Lippincott, Williams and Wilkins.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luck, S. J. (2005). An Introduction to the Event-Related Potential Technique. Cambridge, MA, US: MIT Press.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Madulara, M. D., Francisco, P. A., Nawang, S., Arogancia, D. C., Cellucci, C. J., Rapp, P. E., &amp; Albano, A. M. (2012). EEG transfer entropy tracks changes of information transfer on the onset of vision. International Journal of Modern Physics, 17, 9-18.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayer G, Aviram S, Walter G, Levkovitz Y, Bloch Y. Long-term follow-up of adolescents with resistant depression treated with repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation. J ECT. 2012 Jun;28(2):84-6. doi: 10.1097/YCT.0b013e318238f01a.</citation>
    <PMID>22531199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayo Clinic Staff. (n.d.). Post-concussion syndrome. Retrieved September 15, 2015, from Mayo Clinic: http://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/post-concussion-syndrome/basics/treatment/con-20032705</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCrea, M, ed; American Academy of Clinical Neuropsychology. (2008). Mild traumatic brain injury and postconcussion syndrome: the new evidence base for diagnosis and treatment. Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menon DK, Schwab K, Wright DW, Maas AI; Demographics and Clinical Assessment Working Group of the International and Interagency Initiative toward Common Data Elements for Research on Traumatic Brain Injury and Psychological Health. Position statement: definition of traumatic brain injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2010 Nov;91(11):1637-40. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2010.05.017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21044706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mittenberg W, Strauman S. Diagnosis of mild head injury and the postconcussion syndrome. J Head Trauma Rehabil. 2000 Apr;15(2):783-91. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10739967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mittenberg W, Wittner MS, Miller LJ. Postconcussion syndrome occurs in children. Neuropsychology. 1997 Jul;11(3):447-52. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9223149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okie S. Traumatic brain injury in the war zone. N Engl J Med. 2005 May 19;352(20):2043-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15901856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Owen AM, McMillan KM, Laird AR, Bullmore E. N-back working memory paradigm: a meta-analysis of normative functional neuroimaging studies. Hum Brain Mapp. 2005 May;25(1):46-59.</citation>
    <PMID>15846822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peskind ER, Petrie EC, Cross DJ, Pagulayan K, McCraw K, Hoff D, Hart K, Yu CE, Raskind MA, Cook DG, Minoshima S. Cerebrocerebellar hypometabolism associated with repetitive blast exposure mild traumatic brain injury in 12 Iraq war Veterans with persistent post-concussive symptoms. Neuroimage. 2011 Jan;54 Suppl 1:S76-82. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2010.04.008. Epub 2010 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20385245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinna GD, Maestri R, Torunski A, Danilowicz-Szymanowicz L, Szwoch M, La Rovere MT, Raczak G. Heart rate variability measures: a fresh look at reliability. Clin Sci (Lond). 2007 Aug;113(3):131-40.</citation>
    <PMID>17381425</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polich J, Criado JR. Neuropsychology and neuropharmacology of P3a and P3b. Int J Psychophysiol. 2006 May;60(2):172-85. Epub 2006 Feb 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16510201</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Porges SW. The polyvagal perspective. Biol Psychol. 2007 Feb;74(2):116-43. Epub 2006 Oct 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17049418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Porta A, Bari V, Marchi A, De Maria B, Cysarz D, Van Leeuwen P, Takahashi AC, Catai AM, Gnecchi-Ruscone T. Complexity analyses show two distinct types of nonlinear dynamics in short heart period variability recordings. Front Physiol. 2015 Mar 10;6:71. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2015.00071. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25806002</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdul Razak F, Jensen HJ. Quantifying 'causality' in complex systems: understanding transfer entropy. PLoS One. 2014 Jun 23;9(6):e99462. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0099462. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24955766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richman JS, Moorman JR. Physiological time-series analysis using approximate entropy and sample entropy. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2000 Jun;278(6):H2039-49.</citation>
    <PMID>10843903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rossi S, Hallett M, Rossini PM, Pascual-Leone A; Safety of TMS Consensus Group. Safety, ethical considerations, and application guidelines for the use of transcranial magnetic stimulation in clinical practice and research. Clin Neurophysiol. 2009 Dec;120(12):2008-39. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2009.08.016. Epub 2009 Oct 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19833552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Runge J, Heitzig J, Marwan N, Kurths J. Quantifying causal coupling strength: a lag-specific measure for multivariate time series related to transfer entropy. Phys Rev E Stat Nonlin Soft Matter Phys. 2012 Dec;86(6 Pt 1):061121. Epub 2012 Dec 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23367907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sakkas P, Mihalopoulou P, Mourtzouhou P, Psarros C, Masdrakis V, Politis A, Christodoulou GN. Induction of mania by rTMS: report of two cases. Eur Psychiatry. 2003 Jun;18(4):196-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12814856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sigurdardottir S, Andelic N, Roe C, Jerstad T, Schanke AK. Post-concussion symptoms after traumatic brain injury at 3 and 12 months post-injury: a prospective study. Brain Inj. 2009 Jun;23(6):489-97. doi: 10.1080/02699050902926309.</citation>
    <PMID>19484622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silver JM, McAllister TW. Forensic issues in the neuropsychiatric evaluation of the patient with mild traumatic brain injury. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci. 1997 Winter;9(1):102-13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9017537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spencer, K. M. (2005). Averaging, detection and classification of single-trial ERPs. In T. M. Handy (Ed.), Event Related Potentials. A Methods Handbook (pp. 209-227). Cambridge, MA, US: MIT Press.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein MB, McAllister TW. Exploring the convergence of posttraumatic stress disorder and mild traumatic brain injury. Am J Psychiatry. 2009 Jul;166(7):768-76. doi: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2009.08101604. Epub 2009 May 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19448186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taghva A, Oluigbo C, Corrigan J, Rezai AR. Posttraumatic stress disorder: neurocircuitry and implications for potential deep brain stimulation. Stereotact Funct Neurosurg. 2013;91(4):207-19. doi: 10.1159/000343148. Epub 2013 Mar 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23548850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taghva A, Silvetz R, Ring A, Kim KY, Murphy KT, Liu CY, Jin Y. Magnetic Resonance Therapy Improves Clinical Phenotype and EEG Alpha Power in Posttraumatic Stress Disorder. Trauma Mon. 2015 Nov;20(4):e27360. doi: 10.5812/traumamon.27360. Epub 2015 Nov 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26839865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tanelian, T L; Jaycox, L, eds. (2008). Invisible wounds of war: psychological and cognitive injuries, their consequences, and services to assist recovery. RAND Center for Military Health Policy Research. Santa Monica, CA: RAND Corporation.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs. (2015, December 3). PTSD Checklist for DSM=5 (PCL-5). Retrieved from U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs PTSD: National Center for PTSD: http://www.ptsd.va.gov/professional/assessment/adult-sr/ptsd-checklist.asp</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>United States Army Medical Command. (2014, March 4). OSTG/MEDCOM Policy Memo 14-019. Inpatient and Emergency Department (ED) Aftercare; MEMORANDUM FOR COMMANDERS, MEDCOM REGIONAL MEDICAL COMMANDS. JBSA Fort Sam Houston, Texas, USA.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services FDA Center for Drug Evaluation and Research; U.S. Department of Health and Human Services FDA Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research; U.S. Department of Health and Human Services FDA Center for Devices and Radiological Health. Guidance for industry: patient-reported outcome measures: use in medical product development to support labeling claims: draft guidance. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2006 Oct 11;4:79.</citation>
    <PMID>17034633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Management of Concussion/mTBI Working Group. VA/DoD Clinical Practice Guideline for Management of Concussion/Mild Traumatic Brain Injury. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2009;46(6):CP1-68.</citation>
    <PMID>20108447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valenza G, Garcia RG, Citi L, Scilingo EP, Tomaz CA, Barbieri R. Nonlinear digital signal processing in mental health: characterization of major depression using instantaneous entropy measures of heartbeat dynamics. Front Physiol. 2015 Mar 13;6:74. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2015.00074. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25821435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vinck M, Oostenveld R, van Wingerden M, Battaglia F, Pennartz CM. An improved index of phase-synchronization for electrophysiological data in the presence of volume-conduction, noise and sample-size bias. Neuroimage. 2011 Apr 15;55(4):1548-65. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2011.01.055. Epub 2011 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21276857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wade DT, King NS, Wenden FJ, Crawford S, Caldwell FE. Routine follow up after head injury: a second randomised controlled trial. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1998 Aug;65(2):177-83.</citation>
    <PMID>9703167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warden D. Military TBI during the Iraq and Afghanistan wars. J Head Trauma Rehabil. 2006 Sep-Oct;21(5):398-402.</citation>
    <PMID>16983225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wassermann EM. Risk and safety of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation: report and suggested guidelines from the International Workshop on the Safety of Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation, June 5-7, 1996. Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol. 1998 Jan;108(1):1-16.</citation>
    <PMID>9474057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wippold FJ 2nd; Expert Panel on Neurologic Imaging. Focal neurologic deficit. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 2008 Nov;29(10):1998-2000.</citation>
    <PMID>19008324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization, editors. (1993). The ICD-10 Classification of Mental and Behavioural Disorders Diagnostic Criteria for Research. Geneva: World Health Organization.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>Concussion</keyword>
  <keyword>TBI</keyword>
  <keyword>TMS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Post-Concussion Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

