<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02994355</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00001851</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1K24HD088229-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02994355</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HIV Testing at Family Planning Clinics in Mombasa County, Kenya</brief_title>
  <official_title>HIV Testing at Family Planning Clinics in Mombasa County, Kenya: A Cluster-Randomized Trial Comparing the Systems Analysis and Improvement Approach (SAIA) to Usual Procedures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Nairobi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kenyatta National Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Health, Mombasa County</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Location: Family Planning Clinics in Mombasa County, Kenya

      Introduction:

      Integration of HIV treatment and prevention with family planning (FP) services is a promising
      approach for optimizing delivery of comprehensive healthcare for HIV-positive women, as well
      as prevention services for those who are negative. In Mombasa County, the USAID-supported
      AIDS Population and Health Integrated Assistance II Program revised the FP Clinic Register to
      capture HIV testing in 2008. However, the rate of HIV testing in FP clinics remains low. Our
      overarching objective is to assess the effectiveness, costs, and budget impact of
      implementing the systems analysis and improvement approach (SAIA) to increase HIV testing in
      FP clinics in Mombasa County.

      Methods:

      The investigators aim to conduct a cluster-randomized trial comparing the effect of the SAIA
      approach versus usual procedures on rates of HIV testing in first-time attendees at 20
      intervention versus 20 control FP clinics in Mombasa County. The investigators will compare
      HIV testing rates for first-time FP clinic attendees in SAIA intervention versus control
      facilities after an additional year, during which FP clinics in the intervention arm will be
      encouraged to continue to use the SAIA tools with minimal support from the study team as the
      Mombasa County Ministry of Health will take ownership of implementation. Lastly, the
      investigators aim to estimate the incremental cost and budget impact of applying SAIA versus
      standard of care using an activity-based approach.

      Anticipated Results:

      The investigators anticipate that SAIA will produce significant and sustained improvement in
      HIV-testing rates in first-time FP clinic attendees in intervention clinics compared to
      control facilities. The use of a rigorous study design will provide strong evidence to guide
      integration of HIV testing into FP services in a wide range of settings. The inclusion of
      costing and budget impact analyses will assist policy makers in reaching informed decisions
      about implementation.

      Anticipated Conclusion:

      By addressing the crucial first step in the linkage of HIV and FP services, this research
      holds considerable promise for improving women's health by opening the gateway to HIV care
      and prevention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Integration of HIV treatment and prevention with family planning (FP) services is a promising
      approach for optimizing delivery of comprehensive healthcare for HIV-positive women, as well
      as prevention services for those who are negative. The need for integration of services is
      evident in Africa, which bears a disproportionate burden of HIV, high birth rates, and
      maternal mortality. A high and increasing proportion of African women use FP services, making
      this a potentially efficient venue for reaching them.

      Testing for HIV is the gateway to care and prevention. Integrating HIV testing into FP
      clinics could open this essential gateway, decreasing stigma associated with seeking HIV
      testing while reducing costs. The antenatal setting provides a useful example. In many
      African countries, testing for HIV in antenatal clinics (ANCs) has become routine. Diagnosis
      of HIV during pregnancy has paved the way to substantial reductions in mother-to-child
      transmission of HIV and AIDS-related deaths in women of reproductive age. These achievements
      demonstrate the feasibility and impact of wide-scale HIV testing through existing
      reproductive health services. In contrast to ANCs, integration of HIV testing into FP
      services remains at a formative stage in much of Africa. Recent reviews support the
      feasibility of integrating these services, but invariably conclude that additional research
      is needed.

      In Kenya, the National AIDS and STD Control Program (NASCOP) states that the FP clinic is a
      setting in which, &quot;Failure to offer HIV testing and counseling is unacceptable, and will be
      considered negligent.&quot; However, there has been almost no operational assessment of HIV
      testing in Kenyan FP clinics. In Mombasa County, the USAID-supported AIDS Population and
      Health Integrated Assistance II Program revised the FP Clinic Register to capture HIV testing
      in 2008. However, the rate of HIV testing in FP clinics remains low, and the County has
      requested our assistance in addressing this prevention gap. Colleagues at the University of
      Washington Department of Global Health have developed a systems analysis and performance
      enhancement approach, using industrial and systems engineering techniques, that the
      investigators believe will be useful in this setting. The overarching objective is to assess
      the effectiveness, costs, and budget impact of implementing this systems analysis and
      improvement approach (SAIA) to increase HIV testing in FP clinics in Mombasa County. The
      investigators specific aims are as follows:

      AIM 1: To conduct a cluster-randomized trial comparing the effect of the SAIA approach versus
      usual procedures on rates of HIV testing in first-time attendees at 12 intervention versus 12
      control FP clinics in Mombasa County, Kenya.

      HYP 1: After one year of study team support implementing SAIA vs. usual procedures, a higher
      proportion of first-time FP clinic attendees will be tested for HIV at intervention compared
      to control facilities

      AIM 2: To determine whether the SAIA training results in a lasting effect, the investigators
      will compare HIV testing rates for first-time FP clinic attendees in SAIA intervention versus
      control facilities after an additional year, during which FP clinics in the intervention arm
      will be encouraged to continue to use the SAIA tools with minimal support from the study
      team. The Mombasa County Ministry of Health will take ownership of implementation during this
      phase.

      HYP 2: After an additional year with minimal support from the study team, there will continue
      to be significantly higher rates of HIV testing in first-time FP clinic attendees at
      intervention compared to control facilities.

      AIM 3: To estimate the incremental cost and budget impact of applying SAIA versus standard of
      care. Using an activity-based approach, the investigators will perform a costing analysis,
      estimating cost per new HIV diagnosis, both during active support from the study team and
      after a period without active support. The investigators will also estimate cost to scale up,
      and conduct a budget impact analysis from a Department of Health (DOH) perspective.

      Expected Outcome and Significance:

      The investigators anticipate that the SAIA approach will produce significant and sustained
      improvement in HIV-testing rates in first-time FP clinic attendees in intervention clinics
      compared to control facilities. The use of a rigorous study design to evaluate this scalable
      approach will provide strong evidence to guide integration of HIV testing into FP services in
      a wide range of settings. The inclusion of costing and budget impact analyses will assist
      policy makers in reaching informed decisions about implementation. By addressing the crucial
      first step in the linkage of HIV and FP services, this research holds considerable promise
      for improving women's health by opening the gateway to HIV care and prevention. Preliminary
      data on linkage to care and prevention services will inform development of future grant
      proposals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in proportion of eligible (not known HIV+) new FP clients who are tested for HIV at baseline and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and then following 12 months of SAIA training</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in proportion of new FP clients who are counseled about HIV testing at baseline and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and then following 12 months of SAIA training</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in proportion of new FP clients who are counseled about HIV testing at baseline, after intervention, and after year of minimal support</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, following 12 months of SAIA training and then additional year of minimal study support</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Clinics</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinics randomized to the intervention will be introduced to the Systems Analysis and Improvement Approach (SAIA) to understand barriers to HIV testing in family planning clinics. Sequential process flow mapping will be used to highlight areas for improvement and then specific interventions will be implemented for the clinics with the goal of increasing HIV testing rates.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Clinics</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinics randomized to the control arm of the study will continue HIV testing as per usual procedures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Systems Analysis and Improvement Approach</intervention_name>
    <description>Understanding the cascade from FP clinic enrollment to HIV testing
Use process mapping to identify modifiable bottlenecks
Define and implement workflow adaptations to eliminate modifiable bottlenecks
Monitor change in performance
Repeat the analysis and improvement cycle (steps 1-4)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Clinics</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SAIA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria for in-depth interviews:

          -  Adult family planning clinic staff

          -  If staff younger than 18 are encountered, they will be allowed to participate only if
             they qualify as emancipated minors in Kenya (14 years or older and married or
             pregnant).

          -  Able to provide written informed consent for in-depth interviews

        Inclusion criteria for FP clinics in Mombasa:

        -Clinics providing assent for participation in both the preliminary review and
        randomizations

        Exclusion Criteria for FP clinics:

          -  Clinics planning to be closed during the study period

          -  Clinics unwilling to be randomized or to participate in the SAIA intervention/approach
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond S McClelland, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Professor of Medicine, Epidemiology, Global Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>McKenna C Eastment, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>574-210-1120</phone>
    <email>mceast@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>WHO, UNFPA, IPPF, UNAIDS, UCSF. Sexual and reproductive health and HIV linkages: evidence review and recommendations. Geneva: 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>UNAIDS. Global Report: UNAIDS Report on the Global AIDS Epidemic 2013. Geneva: 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Department of Health South Africa, Medical Research Council South Africa, Human Sciences Research Council South Africa. South African demographic and health survey (SADHS). 2003.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uganda Bureau of Statistics, MEASURE DHS. Uganda demographic and health survey. 2011.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Central Statistical Office Zambia, Ministry of Health Zambia, Tropical Diseases Research Centre Zambia, University Teaching Hospital Virology Laboratory Zambia, University of Zambia, The DHS Program II. Zambia Demographic and Health Survey 2013-14: Preliminary Report. Rockville, MD: 2014 September 2014.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oberzaucher N, Baggaley R. HIV voluntary counselling and testing: a gateway to prevention and care. Geneva, Switzerland: UNAIDS, 2002 June, 2002.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kenya National Bureau of Statistics, Ministry of Health Kenya, National AIDS Control Council, Kenya Medical Research Institute, National Council for Population and Development Kenya. Kenya Demographic and Health Survey 2014: Key Indicators. Nairobi, Kenya: 2015 March 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National AIDS/STD Control Programme MoPHaS. Guidelines for HIV testing and counselling in Kenya. Nairobi: NASCOP, 2008.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bloom DE. 7 billion and counting. Science. 2011 Jul 29;333(6042):562-9. doi: 10.1126/science.1209290. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21798935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hogan MC, Foreman KJ, Naghavi M, Ahn SY, Wang M, Makela SM, Lopez AD, Lozano R, Murray CJ. Maternal mortality for 181 countries, 1980-2008: a systematic analysis of progress towards Millennium Development Goal 5. Lancet. 2010 May 8;375(9726):1609-23. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60518-1. Epub 2010 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>20382417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lozano R, Wang H, Foreman KJ, Rajaratnam JK, Naghavi M, Marcus JR, Dwyer-Lindgren L, Lofgren KT, Phillips D, Atkinson C, Lopez AD, Murray CJ. Progress towards Millennium Development Goals 4 and 5 on maternal and child mortality: an updated systematic analysis. Lancet. 2011 Sep 24;378(9797):1139-65. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61337-8. Epub 2011 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21937100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindegren ML, Kennedy CE, Bain-Brickley D, Azman H, Creanga AA, Butler LM, Spaulding AB, Horvath T, Kennedy GE. Integration of HIV/AIDS services with maternal, neonatal and child health, nutrition, and family planning services. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Sep 12;(9):CD010119. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD010119. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22972150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kennedy CE, Spaulding AB, Brickley DB, Almers L, Mirjahangir J, Packel L, Kennedy GE, Mbizvo M, Collins L, Osborne K. Linking sexual and reproductive health and HIV interventions: a systematic review. J Int AIDS Soc. 2010 Jul 19;13:26. doi: 10.1186/1758-2652-13-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20642843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spaulding AB, Brickley DB, Kennedy C, Almers L, Packel L, Mirjahangir J, Kennedy G, Collins L, Osborne K, Mbizvo M. Linking family planning with HIV/AIDS interventions: a systematic review of the evidence. AIDS. 2009 Nov;23 Suppl 1:S79-88. doi: 10.1097/01.aids.0000363780.42956.ff. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20081392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Madon T, Hofman KJ, Kupfer L, Glass RI. Public health. Implementation science. Science. 2007 Dec 14;318(5857):1728-9.</citation>
    <PMID>18079386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Vinson C, Chambers D, Khoury MJ, Kaplan RM, Hunter C. National Institutes of Health approaches to dissemination and implementation science: current and future directions. Am J Public Health. 2012 Jul;102(7):1274-81. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2012.300755. Epub 2012 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22594758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>UNAIDS. The GAP Report. Geneva: Joint United National Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS), 2014.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Scott McClelland</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Medicine, Epidemiology, and Global Health</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Family planning clinics</keyword>
  <keyword>Implementation Science</keyword>
  <keyword>Systems Analysis and Improvement Approach (SAIA)</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

