<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02994420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-0525</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02994420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endocrine and Neural Control of Eating in Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Steroid Hormones in the Peripheral and Central Control of Eating in Women - Physiological Reactions to Eating in Normal- and Overweight Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Zürich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to better understand how female sex hormones influence the food
      intake in the gut system through the release of satiety hormones as well as through central
      regulative mechanisms in the brain that subsequently contribute to the control of eating in
      healthy women at different stages of the ovarian cycle.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obesity and the associated severe consequences for health, i.e. cardiovascular diseases or
      Diabetes Type 2 reach the world-wide level of an epidemic with excessive eating as major
      cause of this development. Study results of veterinary physiology as well as in women let
      assume that steroid hormones, such as estrogen or progesterone are highly involved in the
      regulation of eating behavior and the female body weight. This connection is underpinned with
      the fact that prevalence of adiposity is increased in women in comparison to men in the
      United States, Switzerland and further countries. A better understanding of the underlying
      regulatory mechanisms, which in turn influence the food intake in the gut system through the
      release of satiety hormones as well as through central regulative mechanisms in the brain,
      provides important foundation in long-term development of new prophylactic and therapeutic
      options in reduction and prevention of obesity. This gets even more important, as current
      therapeutic options - beside bariatric surgery - could only show limited success.

      Satiety is a process in the brain that leads to a meal being ended, whereby the ingested food
      causes a reflexive negative feedback mechanism. This mechanism is both fundamentally and
      specifically in the acute situation strongly influenced through subjective parameters, e.g.
      eating desires, socio-cultural factors, current social circumstances and individual relation
      towards eating. Furthermore, food intake is also influenced by genetic factors, whereas e.g.
      TaqIA1 allele is known to be associated with obesity. According to current knowledge,
      regulation takes place on peripheral as well as on central level, whereas not only steroid
      hormones but also satiety hormones - especially cholecystokinin (CCK) and glucagon-like
      peptide-1 (GLP-1) - are involved on both levels.

      The current study aims to examine the connection of steroid hormones, gastrointestinal
      satiety hormones and neuronal activity in the brain through fMRI. Through the obtained data,
      the interaction between defined hormone constellations, gastrointestinal satiety hormones and
      the activation of specific brain areas in obese and normal-weight women should be evaluated.
      The study design involves the comparison of subjective, hedonic evaluation of different
      flavoured liquids with different caloric content each through a rating scale as well as
      objective peripheral (release of CCK and GLP-1) and central (activation of involved brain
      centres through fMRI) regulation processes in fasted and fed condition of each woman in the
      two study groups (obese and normal-weighted) in late follicular compared with the luteal
      phase of ovarian cycle.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fMRI responses to food cues</measure>
    <time_frame>90 min per study day</time_frame>
    <description>Change in blood oxygen dependent signal (BOLD) in exposure to visual food cues will be measured during a fMRI scan and the difference between responses in the fed condition compared with those in the fasted condition</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CCK (satiety hormone) response curve</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min per study day</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at 0, 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30 min following the ingestion of the meal at each experimental visit, giving a specific curve and analyzed to determine the gut hormone responses. The results will be compared between fast and fed condition, between obese and normal weight women and depending on ovarian cycle phase.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in GLP-1 (satiety hormone) response curve</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min per study day</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at 0, 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30 min following the ingestion of the meal at each experimental visit, giving a specific curve and analyzed to determine the gut hormone responses. The results will be compared between fast and fed condition, between obese and normal weight women and depending on ovarian cycle phase.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in food preference indicating motivation to purchase food items</measure>
    <time_frame>20 min per study day</time_frame>
    <description>The willingness-to-pay task measures the motivation to obtain food on a gLMS scale. The results will be compared between fast and fed condition, between obese and normal weight women and depending on ovarian cycle phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in food preference indicating motivation to exert effort</measure>
    <time_frame>20 min per study day</time_frame>
    <description>The willingness-to-exert-effort task measures the motivation to obtain food on a gLMS scale. The results will be compared between fast and fed condition, between obese and normal weight women and depending on ovarian cycle phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary intake</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min per study day</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of the calorie intake</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hedonic ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>20 min per study day</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective ratings of flavor pleasantness will be collected using psychophysical rating scales (gLMS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective sensory ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>20 min per study day</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective ratings of hunger sensation will be collected using psychophysical rating scales (gLMS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Normal Body Weight</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lean women</arm_group_label>
    <description>BMI 18-25, weight in kg / height in m2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Obese women</arm_group_label>
    <description>BMI 30-35, weight in kg / height in m2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole blood to determine hormonal parameters (gut hormones and reproductive hormones) and the
      presence of the gene TaqIA1.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Normal-weight and obese women with regular menstrual cycles.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Physically and psychiatrically healthy women

          -  Stable body weight (no changes ≥ 5 kg in past year)

          -  Age 18-35 years

          -  Regular menses (26-32 d cycles)

          -  Right-handed

          -  German language fluency

          -  Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Life history of eating disorders

          -  Aversion to the test foods

          -  Pacemaker or neurostimulator

          -  Hearing aid

          -  Surgery to head or heart

          -  Potential metal parts in body (pacemakers, metal splinters, gun wounds, shrapnel or
             surgical clips)

          -  Neurological or psychiatric problems or serious brain injury (such as alcohol or drug
             abuse, depression, schizophrenia, bipolar disorders, anxiety disorder, claustrophobia,
             Parkinson's disease, multiple sclerosis, epilepsy)

          -  High blood pressure, low blood pressure, history of heart disease, irregular heart
             rate

          -  Emphysema, chest or respiratory problems (including difficulty breathing through the
             nose)

          -  Pregnancy, nursing or pregnancy planned in next three months

          -  History of gall bladder disease or symptoms (right upper abdominal quadrant pain after
             meals)

          -  Polycystic ovary syndrome, as gauged by testosterone levels

          -  Allergy or sensitivity to lactose

          -  Allergy to quinine

          -  Current or previous malignancies

          -  History of difficult blood sampling
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brigitte Leeners, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinic for Reproductive Endocrinology, University Hospital Zurich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Loredana Asarian, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Veterinary Physiology, Universirty of Zurich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Tobler, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Economics, University of Zurich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brigitte Leeners, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+41 44 255 5001</phone>
    <email>Brigitte.Leeners@usz.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinic for Reproductive Endocrinology, University Hospital Zurich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <zip>8091</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brigitte Leeners, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 44 255 5001</phone>
      <email>brigitte.leeners@usz.ch</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Menstrual Cycle</keyword>
  <keyword>Gonadal Steroid Hormones</keyword>
  <keyword>Satiety Response</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucagon-Like Peptide 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholecystokinin</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Body Weight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

