<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02992990</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-40414</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02992990</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bladder Tumor Biopsy Study to Improve Preoperative Determination of Stage and Grade</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Study To Assess Whether A Preoperative Tumor Biopsy Can Improve Upon The Endoscopic Impression Determination Of Stage And Grade In Non-Muscle-Invasive Urothelial Carcinoma Of The Bladder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess whether the addition of a bladder tumor biopsy improves the level of agreement
      between the pretreatment endoscopic impression and the final postoperative pathology
      determination of stage and grade in non-muscle-invasive urothelial carcinoma of the bladder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Non-invasive bladder cancer is challenging to treat because it is a condition characterized
      by frequent recurrences that lead to numerous invasive procedures for detection and
      treatment. The mainstay of therapy for non-muscle invasive bladder cancer, which has remained
      unchanged for decades, relies on surgical resection (TUR) associated with utilization of
      intravesical immunotherapy and chemotherapy. Despite our best efforts, these tumors continue
      to have suboptimal rates of recurrence and require long-term follow-up with costly and
      invasive procedures. The rationale for this study is to show that the preoperative biopsy,
      taken at the time of the office cystoscopic evaluation, improves pre-TUR staging and grading
      correlation with the final pathology of the resection. Indirectly, this will suggest that the
      routine use of pre-TUR biopsy provides more accurate information for intraoperative
      decision-making that can ultimately lead to better management of these patients with
      non-muscle-invasive bladder cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of the kappa agreement score between preoperative and postoperative assessment of stage and grade in non-muscle-invasive bladder tumors.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of grade, which is the main endpoint will be dichotomous defining lesions between low versus high grade. Stage classification of non-muscle-invasive papillary lesions is also dichotomous between Ta and T1 lesions. CIS can be annotated, but since these are flat, diffuse and non &quot;resectable&quot; in the bladder, they are not part of our main analysis, endpoints, or sample size calculations. The only exception is when the presence of CIS is used to determine grade (high-grade lesion).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bladder tumor biopsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects will undergo a bladder tumor biopsy followed by transurethral resection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bladder tumor biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Bladder tumor biopsy performed at the time of the preoperative office flexible cystoscopic evaluation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bladder tumor biopsy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or females, age 21 or older;

          -  Clinical evidence of urothelial carcinoma of the bladder;

          -  Clinically (endoscopic, by physical examination, and/or axial-imaging) deemed
             non-muscle-invasive tumor of the bladder (cTis-Ta-T1), of any grade, single or
             multiple, at initial occurrence or recurrent with &gt;12 months interval free of disease;

          -  Surgically eligible for the TUR;

          -  Patient or authorized proxy needs to have signed the informed consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of any muscle-invasive or non-organ confined bladder tumors (T2 or higher);

          -  Patients with sessile appearing bladder tumors, which may be T2 or higher stage;

          -  Diagnosis of urothelial carcinoma involving the prostatic urethra or upper urinary
             tract;

          -  Concurrent use of anticoagulation medication or chronic use of NSAIDs, including
             aspirin (other than cardio protective doses of 80mg daily) that has not been
             appropriately interrupted before the office cystoscopic evaluation;

          -  Patient deemed medically or psychologically unfit for the surgical procedure;

          -  Subject has received any investigational medication within 30 days prior to the
             registration or is scheduled to receive an investigational drug during the course of
             the study;

        Women Exclusion

          -  Pregnant or lactating women.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Guilherme Godoy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Urology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

