<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03439735</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>J17118</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03439735</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Determinants of Resistance to First-line Therapy With an AI and Palbociclib for HR+ MBC</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Evaluation of Determinants of Resistance to First-line Therapy With an Aromatase Inhibitor and the Cyclin-dependent Kinases 4 and 6 Inhibitor Palbociclib in Hormone Receptor Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this research study is to determine if we can predict which participants will
      respond to an aromatase inhibitor and palbociclib for metastatic breast cancer and which
      participants will not. Investigators will use information from the tumor tissue and serial
      blood samples. Investigators hope that a deeper understanding of which participants will
      respond to this combination and how resistance emerges will allow the investigators to better
      tailor therapies for metastatic breast cancer.

      Subjects will have archived tissue or new biopsy collected at study enrollment. This tissue
      will undergo special molecular testing. Subjects will also have blood collected at study
      enrollment and periodically thereafter. This blood will also undergo special molecular
      testing. Information from this testing will not be available to subjects or their treating
      physicians as the investigators do not know how this information should impact treatment.

      The investigators will collect information about which treatment the subjects receive and how
      their cancer responds.

      Any man or woman being seen at Johns Hopkins for treatment of newly diagnosed estrogen
      receptor positive (ER+) and/or progesterone receptor positive (PR+) metastatic breast cancer
      may be eligible.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Resistance to endocrine therapy (ET) invariably develops in patients with estrogen and/or
      progesterone receptor (ER/ PR) positive metastatic breast cancer (MBC). Data regarding
      primary resistance and patterns of emergence of acquired resistance in treatment naïve
      patients treated with aromatase inhibitor (AI) and cyclin dependent kinase 4 and 6 (CDK4/6)
      inhibitors are limited. Understanding these mechanisms could result in improved selection of
      treatment options and provide new targets for therapy development. In this study, we aim to
      identify and characterize determinants of intrinsic and acquired resistance to endocrine
      therapy in patients with hormone receptor (HR) positive, human epidermal growth factor
      receptor 2 (HER2) negative MBC treated with the combination of an AI and the CDK4/6 inhibitor
      palbociclib in the first -line setting.

      Investigators will determine the prevalence of genomic alterations at baseline in the primary
      tumor, metastatic tissue and plasma tumor DNA (ptDNA). This will include in the gene encoding
      estrogen receptor- alpha (ESR1). The mutational tumor burden in the primary tumor, metastatic
      tumor and blood will be assessed. Blood samples will be collected at several time points,
      allowing the detection of changes in molecular markers over time. The investigators will
      further characterize tissue markers associated with progression and duration of response by
      evaluating these markers in available tissue obtained at progression. The investigators goal
      is to evaluate the prevalence and role of known alterations determining endocrine resistance
      in patients previously untreated for metastatic disease, as knowledge regarding this
      population remains limited. The investigators also hope to unveil novel markers of endocrine
      resistance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic Mutation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who have an ESR1 mutation prior to receiving an aromatase inhibitor and palbociclib.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic Mutation</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of time from receiving palbociclib and aromatase inhibitor to the first detectable ESR1 mutation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic Mutation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quantify the proportion of participants with an ESR1 mutation at the time of progression for those who received treatment with an aromatase inhibitor and palbociclib.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Palbociclib and Aromatase Inhibitor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will undergo blood collection (intervention) at time of initiating treatment with an aromatase inhibitor and palbociclib, at 4 weeks after initiating this treatment, and every 3-4 months while on treatment. If a participant progresses on this treatment, they will have a blood collection at that time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aromatase Inhibitor and Palbociclib</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants that are initiating treatment with an AI and Palbociclib.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Palbociclib and Aromatase Inhibitor</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AI and palbo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or Female

          -  18 years or older

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-2

          -  Metastatic (stage IV) breast cancer or locally advanced breast cancer

          -  Estrogen Receptor (ER) and/or Progesterone Receptor (PR) positive, HER2- negative

          -  Treatment naïve in metastatic or locally advanced setting and planning to undergo
             treatment with an aromatase inhibitor (AI) and palbociclib OR receiving first-line AI
             and palbociclib for metastatic or locally advanced disease.

          -  Premenopausal women and men must be treated with concurrent luteinizing
             hormone-releasing hormone (LHRH) agonist as would be standard-of-care.

          -  Evaluable or measurable disease.

          -  Tissue from a metastatic site must be available within past 6 months prior to therapy
             initiation.

          -  Ability to give voluntary informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any pregnant or nursing woman

          -  No history of another primary malignancy within past 5 years. Patients with prior
             history of in situ cancer or basal or localized squamous cell skin cancer are
             eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria (Raquel) Nunes, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University/Sibley Memorial Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hopkins Breast Trials</last_name>
    <phone>410-614-1361</phone>
    <email>hopkinsbreasttrials@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Centers Clinical Research Office</last_name>
    <phone>410-955-8866</phone>
    <email>jhcccro@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 8, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Aromatase Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Palbociclib</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormone Receptor Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Palbociclib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aromatase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

