<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03439501</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-05-046</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MS100070_0018</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03439501</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Avelumab in Relapsed or Refractory Stage III/IV Extranodal Natural Killer/T-cell Lymphoma[AVENT STUDY]</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Avelumab in Relapsed or Refractory Stage III/IV Extranodal Natural Killer/T-cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Samsung Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck KGaA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Samsung Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was conducted to evaluate the complete response rate of avelumab in patients with
      NK / T-cell lymphoma besides relapsed or refractory stage lymphoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Extranodal natural killer/T-cell lymphoma (ENKTL) generally has poorer prognosis than other
      lymphomas because the majority of patients are present as advanced disease and show poor
      response to treatment.

      In particular, treatment of relapsed or refractory stage ENKTL is very poor and there is no
      standard treatment.

      ENKTL is entirely infected with Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) and the prevalence of this disease
      is closely related to EBV.

      Therefore, the biological properties of ENKTL may be affected by EBV-related protein and LMP1
      may induce activation of molecules in various sub-channels, such as PI3K/Akt and NF-kB, and
      affect the aggressiveness of lymphoma.

      As an increase in PDL1 has been reported recently among the major roles of LMP1, the role of
      Immuno-oncology drug targeting PDL1 among ENKTL is expected.

      Therefore, Avelumab that inhibits PDL1 may effectively treat NK/T-cell lymphoma besides
      relapsed or refractory stage lymphoma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The rate of response of avelumab.</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment until the date first documented disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, whichever came first, assessed up to 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the efficacy of disease control including complete response (CR), partial response (PR) and stable disease (SD)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>the time between the date of treatment start and the date of death due to any cause or date of disease progression..assessed up to 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>It is a measure of the period of survival without disease progression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time between the start of treatment and the date of death.assessed up to 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>It measures the time from start of treatment to death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>from the date of informed consent signature to 30 days after last drug administration.</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical and laboratory toxicity/symptomatology will be graded based on the NCIC CTG v4.03. Adverse events not reported in NCIC CTG will be categorized into mild, moderate, severe, and fatal and further classified to CTCAE Grades 1-4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Extranodal NK-T-Cell</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>avelumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 Cycle: 10mg/kg Avelumab administered via IV every 2 weeks (1st, 15th)
Interval of 1 cycle: 28 days ③ Administration schedule: Repeated until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity and dose adjustments may be permitted based on the toxicity that occurs every cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>avelumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Study drug: Avelumab (PD-L1 inhibitor; MSB0010718C)
Dosage: 10 mg per body weight (kg) of a subject every two weeks
One cycle consists of two injection of avelumab (28 days).
The treatment cycle will be repeated until progression of disease or unacceptable toxicity and dose adjustments are permitted for patients who are unable to tolerate the side effects of drugs within each cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>avelumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Historologically diagnosed ENKTL: The standards of WHO Classification 2016 for
             diagnosis of ENKTL satisfied.

          2. Became relapsed or refractory after at least one kind of treatment after initial
             diagnosis.

          3. If in stage 3/4 at initial diagnosis or in stage 3/4 as a result of evaluating the
             progression of disease in relapsed or refractory stage.

          4. If there is at least one measurable lesion.

          5. In case full-body activity (ECOG PS) is levels 0-2.

          6. In case of written consent to participation in clinical test: Must sign the subject
             consent form that states the sampling done at the time of diagnosis or relapse (must
             provide sample): 10, 4um (at least 5) and biomarker (3~5 ml peripheral blood drawn
             during screening period, must provide sample) and that the subject has comprehended
             the purpose and the necessary procedures of clinical test with intention to
             participate in the clinical test (or signed by the subject's representative).

          7. If older than 19 years of age.

          8. If the following hematological results are satisfied:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count is 1500/mm3 or greater regardless of growth factor
                  supply.

               -  Platelet count is 100,000/mm3 or greater regardless of blood supply.

               -  Hemoglobin is 9.0 g/dL or greater.

          9. If the following biochemical results are satisfied:

               -  Alanine transaminase (ALT) and Aspartate transaminase (AST) ≤ 2.5 x upper limit
                  (ULN): If liver blood enzyme count is increasing due to a disease, such as the
                  lymphoma's hepatic intrusion, may register up to ≤ 5 x ULN at researcher's
                  discretion.

               -  If bilirubin is increasing due to the Gilbert Syndrome, total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x
                  ULN unless non-hepatic.

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 2 x ULN or glomerular filtration rate (Cockroft Gault) ≥ 30
                  mL/min/1.73m2

         10. Highly efficient birth control that meets the local regulations must be adopted for
             birth control of subjects that participate in the clinical study during or after the
             clinical study for women in fertility or sexually active men (in case of women in
             fertility, effective birth control must be used during the administration of test drug
             and for 1 month after that and men must use it during the administration of test drug
             and for 3 months after that).

         11. Women in fertility must show negative results at platelet (beta-chorionic
             gonadotropin) or pregnancy test by urine at screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. If there is history of carcinomatous meningitis, symptomatic leptomeningeal diseases
             or evidence of secondary intrusion on the central nervous system based on CT or MRI
             scanning.

          2. In case there are other carcinomas besides the target disease or in case of anamnesis
             of other malicious tumers during the past 3 years from the start of clinical study:
             Excluding basal cell carcinoma and cervical intraepithelial neoplasia that are
             appropriately treated.

          3. In case of radiological radiation on the lymphs around the pelvis or the aorta within
             28 days of registration for the clinical study or radiological treatment for symptom
             relief within 14 days.

          4. If any toxicity from the previous chemotherapy has not recovered to grade 1 or lower
             at the time of screening; however hair loss and bone marrow inhibition are excluded
             and peripheral polyneuropathy may be registered at researcher's discretion if there is
             no risk of safety at Grade≤ 2.

          5. In case of major operation within 4 weeks from registration for the clinical study or
             failure to recover from a major complication of such operation.

          6. If using immunosuppressant drugs at the time of registration for the clinical study:
             Excluding local steroid injections such as nasal or inhalated steroid, steroid
             ointment, and injections in articular cavities. In case of full-body steroid
             administration, 10 mg or smaller prednisolonum a day is permissible and steroid
             injections used for pre-treatment before CT or other examination are also permitted.

          7. In case of uncontrolled or symptomatic arrhythmia, congestive heart failure,
             myocardial infarction, cerebral infarction, or other clinically significant
             cardiovascular diseases or Class 3 (Moderate) or Class 4 (Severe) cardiac diseases
             functionally classified by New York Heart Association within 6 months of screening.

          8. In case of history of serious hypersensitivity against the test drug used for this
             study or its substances including serious hypersensitivity against monoclonal antibody
             (NCI CTCAE v4.03 Grade ≥ 3).

          9. In case of known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), active type C
             hepatitis virus, or active type B hepatitis virus or uncontrolled active full-body
             infection that requires intravenous (IV) antibiotics.

         10. In case of life-threatening diseases, medical conditions, or respiratory failure that
             may threaten the safety of subjects or put the results of clinical test in danger.

         11. In case of homogeneous hematopoietic stem cell transplant.

         12. In case of active autoimmune disease that may affect the administration of study drug;
             excluding type 1diabetes, psoriasis, vitiligo, hyperthyroidism, or hypothyroidism that
             does not require immunosuppressant.

         13. If the candidate cannot comprehend the clinical study or comply with the rules of
             clinical study including an active attempt to commit suicide or hurt oneself recently
             or in the past and other severe acute or chronic diseases such as immunocolitis,
             ulcerative colitis, immunopneumonia, pulmonary fibrosis, or mental conditions; or if
             determined by investigator that participation in the study is inappropriate due to any
             risk of participation or treatment in the study that may increase due to adverse
             effects or the interpretation of study results that may be hindered.

         14. If candidate is pregnant or breast-feeding at the time of screening.

         15. In case of a major operation or live attenuated vaccine within 4 weeks of registration
             for the clinical study.

         16. In case of the following hepatic diseases:

               -  Chronic hepatitis or liver cirrhosis related to type B or type C hepatitis.

               -  Positive reaction for surface antigen of type B hepatitis without symptoms.

               -  Positive reaction to RNA of type C hepatitis without symptoms.

         17. Past immunotherapy (ex: anti-CTLA-4 or anti-PD-1/PD-L1 treatment).

         18. Use of other anticancer treatment or other study drugs within 4 weeks of registration
             for the clinical study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wonseog Kim, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Samsung Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>81, Irwon-ro, Gangnam-gu, Seoul, Republic of Korea</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>06351</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Samsung Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Won Seog Kim</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Extranodal NK-T-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

