<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03433235</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMC 2018-0033</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03433235</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Administration of Edoxaban After Acute Ischemic Stroke in Patients With Non-valvular Atrial Fibrillation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Administration of Edoxaban After Acute Ischemic Stroke in Patients With Non-valvular Atrial Fibrillation: a Randomized, Multi-center, Parallel-group Trial (PILOT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jong Sung Kim</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kyung Hee University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Soon Chun Hyang University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asan Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesize that earlier initiation of edoxaban in AF-related stroke
      patients may significantly reduce the early recurrence of ischemic stroke, compared with
      conventional strategy of anticoagulation following 1-3-6-12 rule. To expedite the
      verification of the hypothesis, the investigators are planning to use diffusion weighted
      imaging (DWI), which has been reported to be a surrogate to predict both short-term and
      long-term prognosis after stroke, to detect the recurrent ischemic events. Because data on
      the early anticoagulation in patients with AF-related stroke are limited, the investigators
      decided to perform a pilot study before establishing an appropriate clinical trial protocol.
      This study will help estimate the efficacy and safety of early administration of edoxaban,
      and determine the sample size of a following clinical trial. To ensure the safety in this
      pilot exploration, the investigators will not include patients with severe ischemic strokes,
      who are often prone to experience hemorrhagic transformation in the acute post-stroke period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In patients with ischemic stroke and atrial fibrillation (AF), the risk of stroke recurrence
      is high, especially shortly after the event. Because AF-related strokes are usually larger in
      their size and more fatal than other types of ischemic stroke, it is important to prevent
      recurrent cardioembolic strokes with adequate secondary prevention. However, as damaged brain
      tissues and vessels are prone to bleed, early anticoagulation may be harmful.

      For this reason, urgent anticoagulation has not been recommended in stroke patients with AF,
      and the appropriate time point to start anticoagulation remains controversial. Guideline
      recommends 1-3-6-12 rule* in initiating anticoagulation. However, this rule is not derived
      from a scientifically proven study results. Furthermore, although the risk of intracranial
      hemorrhage may be reduced to some extent with this strategy, the risk of early recurrence of
      embolic stroke may outweigh the potential benefit of delayed anticoagulation.

      Edoxaban, which selectively blocks factor Xa, has a lower risk of hemorrhage, but with a
      similar efficacy in preventing ischemic events in patients with AF compared with warfarin.
      Even compared with the other factor Xa inhibitors, it is considered to have a lower risk of
      bleeding. Therefore, edoxaban may be safely given in the early phase in patients with stroke
      associated with AF, while not significantly increasing the risk of hemorrhages.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>recurrent ischemic strokes</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 10−14</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence rate of symptomatic or asymptomatic recurrent ischemic strokes on DWI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrent ischemic lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>until Day 10−14</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence rate of recurrent ischemic lesions with significant clinical worsening (≥NIHSS 4)
The National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale, or NIH Stroke Scale (NIHSS) is a tool used by healthcare providers to objectively quantify the impairment caused by a stroke. The NIHSS is composed of 11 items, each of which scores a specific ability between a 0 and 4. For each item, a score of 0 typically indicates normal function in that specific ability, while a higher score is indicative of some level of impairment. The individual scores from each item are summed in order to calculate a patient's total NIHSS score. The maximum possible score is 42, with the minimum score being a 0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical neurological deterioration</measure>
    <time_frame>until Day 10−14</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of clinical neurological deterioration, rapid worsening of an existing focal neurological deficit (≥ 24 hours) that is clinically judged by the investigator not to be attributable to non-ischemic etiology (≥NIHSS 2)
The National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale, or NIH Stroke Scale (NIHSS) is a tool used by healthcare providers to objectively quantify the impairment caused by a stroke. The NIHSS is composed of 11 items, each of which scores a specific ability between a 0 and 4. For each item, a score of 0 typically indicates normal function in that specific ability, while a higher score is indicative of some level of impairment. The individual scores from each item are summed in order to calculate a patient's total NIHSS score. The maximum possible score is 42, with the minimum score being a 0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>recanalization (full or partial) of occluded vessels</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 10−14</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of recanalization (full or partial) of occluded vessels on follow-up intracranial TOF</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intracranial hemorrhages</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 10−14</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence rate of intracranial hemorrhages on follow-up gradient echo (GRE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Functional status (modified Rankin Scale [mRS])
The modified Rankin Scale (mRS) is a commonly used scale for measuring the degree of disability or dependence in the daily activities of people who have suffered a stroke or other causes of neurological disability.
The scale runs from 0-6, running from perfect health without symptoms to death. 0 - No symptoms.
- No significant disability. Able to carry out all usual activities, despite some symptoms.
- Slight disability. Able to look after own affairs without assistance, but unable to carry out all previous activities.
- Moderate disability. Requires some help, but able to walk unassisted.
- Moderately severe disability. Unable to attend to own bodily needs without assistance, and unable to walk unassisted.
- Severe disability. Requires constant nursing care and attention, bedridden, incontinent.
- Dead.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early edoxaban initiation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low dose of edoxaban (15 or 30 mg) once daily from Day 2, then standard dose of edoxaban (30 or 60 mg) according to '3-6' rule.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional edoxaban initiation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>No antithrombotic treatment† -- then standard dose of edoxaban (30 or 60 mg) according to '3-6' rule.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Edoxaban</intervention_name>
    <description>1-3-6-12 rule*
Anticoagulation in patients with acute ischemic stroke and atrial fibrillation can be initiated from the following days after stroke event.
After 1 day: transient ischemic attacks
After 3 days: mild ischemic strokes (NIHSS &lt;8)
After 6 days: moderate ischemic strokes (NIHSS 8−16)
After 12 days: severe ischemic strokes (NIHSS &gt;16)
- NIHSS: National Institute of Health Stroke Scales</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early edoxaban initiation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional edoxaban initiation group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lixiana</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Acute ischemic strokes (&lt; 48 h from symptom onset) showing ischemic lesions confirmed
             by DWI, which are attributable to atrial fibrillation

          2. Evidence of persistent or paroxysmal atrial fibrillation (already known or newly
             detected)

          3. Age ≥20 y

          4. Patients who provided informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Transient ischemic attack with no DWI lesions or severe ischemic strokes (NIHSS &gt;16)

          2. Significant hemorrhagic transformation (parenchymal hematoma type I or type II by the
             ECASS definition or those accompanying with worsening of an existing focal
             neurological deficit [NIHSS ≥4])10 on baseline MRI

          3. Mechanical heart valve, rheumatic heart valve disease, or any other conditions
             requiring strong anticoagulation such as vitamin K antagonist or heparin treatment

          4. Concomitant significant atherosclerotic stenosis (&gt;50%) in the proximal arteries,
             which are possibly responsible for stroke lesions

          5. Recent (&lt;3 months) history of cerebral bleeding

          6. Active internal bleeding or clinically significant bleeding

          7. Severe anemia (Hb &lt;10 g/dL) or bleeding diathesis (platelet count &lt;100,000/uL or
             PT-INR &gt;1.7)

          8. Uncontrolled hypertension: persistent systolic pressure &gt;180 mmHg or diastolic
             pressure &gt;110 mmHg

          9. Active, advanced medical diseases (liver, kidney, pulmonary disease or cancer) with a
             life expectancy &lt;6 months

         10. Renal impairment (CrCl &lt;30 mL/min) or undergoing Hemodialysis (or Peritoneal Dialysis)

         11. Treatment with a strong inducer of p-glycoprotein (carbamazepine, dexamethasone,
             doxorubicin, nefazodone, pentobarbital, phenobarbital, prazocin, rifampin, St.John's
             wort, tenofovir, tipranavir, trazodone, vinblastine)

         12. Contraindication to MRI

         13. Pregnancy, breast-feeding or having a plan to be pregnant

         14. Participation in the other investigational drug trials simultaneously or within 3
             months before the first administration of the study medication. Observational studies
             without an intervention (eg study medication) are allowed.

         15. Any clinical conditions (eg abnormal lab tests) unsuitable for undergoing clinical
             trials at the discretion of the clinical investigators

         16. Known hypersensitivity to the study drug (edoxaban), its ingredients, or formulation
             excipients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jong Sung Kim, M.D.,Ph D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Asan Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jong Sung Kim, M.D.,Ph D.</last_name>
    <phone>82-2-3010-3442</phone>
    <email>jongskim@amc.seoul.kr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin HJ, Wolf PA, Kelly-Hayes M, Beiser AS, Kase CS, Benjamin EJ, D'Agostino RB. Stroke severity in atrial fibrillation. The Framingham Study. Stroke. 1996 Oct;27(10):1760-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8841325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jauch EC, Saver JL, Adams HP Jr, Bruno A, Connors JJ, Demaerschalk BM, Khatri P, McMullan PW Jr, Qureshi AI, Rosenfield K, Scott PA, Summers DR, Wang DZ, Wintermark M, Yonas H; American Heart Association Stroke Council; Council on Cardiovascular Nursing; Council on Peripheral Vascular Disease; Council on Clinical Cardiology. Guidelines for the early management of patients with acute ischemic stroke: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2013 Mar;44(3):870-947. doi: 10.1161/STR.0b013e318284056a. Epub 2013 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>23370205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heidbuchel H, Verhamme P, Alings M, Antz M, Hacke W, Oldgren J, Sinnaeve P, Camm AJ, Kirchhof P. EHRA practical guide on the use of new oral anticoagulants in patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation: executive summary. Eur Heart J. 2013 Jul;34(27):2094-106. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/eht134. Epub 2013 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23625209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heidbuchel H, Verhamme P, Alings M, Antz M, Diener HC, Hacke W, Oldgren J, Sinnaeve P, Camm AJ, Kirchhof P; ESC Scientific Document Group. Updated European Heart Rhythm Association practical guide on the use of non-vitamin-K antagonist anticoagulants in patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation: Executive summary. Eur Heart J. 2017 Jul 14;38(27):2137-2149. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehw058.</citation>
    <PMID>27282612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giugliano RP, Ruff CT, Braunwald E, Murphy SA, Wiviott SD, Halperin JL, Waldo AL, Ezekowitz MD, Weitz JI, Špinar J, Ruzyllo W, Ruda M, Koretsune Y, Betcher J, Shi M, Grip LT, Patel SP, Patel I, Hanyok JJ, Mercuri M, Antman EM; ENGAGE AF-TIMI 48 Investigators. Edoxaban versus warfarin in patients with atrial fibrillation. N Engl J Med. 2013 Nov 28;369(22):2093-104. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1310907. Epub 2013 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24251359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulman S. New oral anticoagulant agents - general features and outcomes in subsets of patients. Thromb Haemost. 2014 Apr 1;111(4):575-82. doi: 10.1160/TH13-09-0803. Epub 2014 Jan 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24452881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kang DW, Han MK, Kim HJ, Sohn H, Kim BJ, Kwon SU, Kim JS, Warach S. Silent new ischemic lesions after index stroke and the risk of future clinical recurrent stroke. Neurology. 2016 Jan 19;86(3):277-85. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000002289. Epub 2015 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26683639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee EJ, Kang DW, Warach S. Silent New Brain Lesions: Innocent Bystander or Guilty Party? J Stroke. 2016 Jan;18(1):38-49. doi: 10.5853/jos.2015.01410. Epub 2015 Oct 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26467195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hacke W, Kaste M, Fieschi C, von Kummer R, Davalos A, Meier D, Larrue V, Bluhmki E, Davis S, Donnan G, Schneider D, Diez-Tejedor E, Trouillas P. Randomised double-blind placebo-controlled trial of thrombolytic therapy with intravenous alteplase in acute ischaemic stroke (ECASS II). Second European-Australasian Acute Stroke Study Investigators. Lancet. 1998 Oct 17;352(9136):1245-51.</citation>
    <PMID>9788453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulman S, Kearon C; Subcommittee on Control of Anticoagulation of the Scientific and Standardization Committee of the International Society on Thrombosis and Haemostasis. Definition of major bleeding in clinical investigations of antihemostatic medicinal products in non-surgical patients. J Thromb Haemost. 2005 Apr;3(4):692-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15842354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duchin K, Duggal A, Atiee GJ, Kidokoro M, Takatani T, Shipitofsky NL, He L, Zhang G, Kakkar T. An Open-Label Crossover Study of the Pharmacokinetics of the 60-mg Edoxaban Tablet Crushed and Administered Either by a Nasogastric Tube or in Apple Puree in Healthy Adults. Clin Pharmacokinet. 2018 Feb;57(2):221-228. doi: 10.1007/s40262-017-0554-0.</citation>
    <PMID>28512699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seiffge DJ, Traenka C, Polymeris A, Hert L, Peters N, Lyrer P, Engelter ST, Bonati LH, De Marchis GM. Early start of DOAC after ischemic stroke: Risk of intracranial hemorrhage and recurrent events. Neurology. 2016 Nov 1;87(18):1856-1862. Epub 2016 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>27694266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Asan Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jong Sung Kim</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Edoxaban</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

