<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03434613</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4-2017-1168</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03434613</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized, Prospective, Open Label, Active Control, Phase IV Study to Evaluate the Effects of Statin Monotherapy or Statin / Ezetimibe Combination Therapy on Hepatic Steatosis in Patients With Hyperlipidemia and Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Prospective, Open Label, Active Control, Phase IV Study to Evaluate the Effects of Statin Monotherapy or Statin / Ezetimibe Combination Therapy on Hepatic Steatosis in Patients With Hyperlipidemia and Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yonsei University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yonsei University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the therapeutic effect of ezetimibe on nonalcoholic fatty liver disease, the
      effect of rosuvastatin 5mg monotherapy and rosuvastatin 5mg / ezetimibe 10mg combination
      therapy n patients with hyperlipidemia and fatty liver will be compared and analyzed.

      This study included a total of 70 patients (35 per subgroup) for randomized controlled trials
      with prospective, open label, randomized, single-institution clinical trials.

      The drug will be maintained for a total of six months. The primary endpoint is the difference
      of liver fat change measured by MRI-PDFF in colocalized regions of interest within nine liver
      segments between two groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study will conduct to evaluate the efficacy of liver fat lowering and safety of rosuvastatin 5mg alone or in combination with rosuvastatin 5mg / ezetimibe 10mg for 6 months.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Open label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>liver fat change measured by MRI-PDFF in colocalized regions of interest within each of nine liver segments</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>MRI is used to measure the fat fraction in 9 liver segments, and this test has been reported to be more sensitive than the biopsy-based steatosis grade assessment in confirming liver fat changes in previous studies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver fibrosis measured by MRE(magnetic resonance elastography)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary endpoint is to analyze the changes before and after drug administration for the following items: Liver fibrosis measured by MRE(magnetic resonance elastography)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dyslipidemias</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rosuvastatin monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rosuvastatin 5mg 1T daily for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rosuvastatin + ezetimibe combination therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rosuvastatin 5mg / Ezetimibe 10mg combination 1T daily for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rosuvastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Rosuvastatin 5mg 1T daily for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rosuvastatin monotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rosuvastatin/ezetimibe combination</intervention_name>
    <description>Rosuvastatin 5mg / Ezetimibe 10mg combination 1T daily for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rosuvastatin + ezetimibe combination therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men or women ages 19 and over, under 80 years of age

          -  Patients diagnosed with fatty liver by abdominal ultrasonography or liver fibroscan.
             (In case of patients who were diagnosed fatty liver by liver scan, we will conduct
             abdominal ultrasonography for screening purposes)

          -  In the Domestic Dyslipidemia Treatment Guideline, patients with hyperlipidemia A.
             LDL-C is more than 130mg / dL when there is less than 1 major risk factor B. LDL-C 100
             mg / dL or more if there are two or more major risk factors C. High-risk patients with
             carotid stenosis&gt; 50%, abdominal aortic aneurysm, and diabetes mellitus had LDL-C&gt; 70
             mg / dL

        D. The main risk factors are as follows:

        i. smoking ii. Hypertension - systolic blood pressure greater than 140 mmHg or diastolic
        blood pressure greater than 90 mmHg or antihypertensive iii. Low HDL cholesterol (&lt;40 mg /
        dL) iv. Age - Male 45+, Female 55+ v. Family history of early onset coronary artery disease
        - Parents, siblings with a history of coronary artery disease in men under 55 and women
        under 65 vi. High HDL cholesterol (60 mg / dL) or more is regarded as a protective factor
        and one of the total risk factors is reduced

          -  Even if it does not meet the criteria for hyperlipidemia, it is possible to select the
             subject when there is evidence of atherosclerosis on the test (carotid ultrasonography
             etc)

          -  Those who already use statin as a treatment for hyperlipemia should participate after
             a washout period of 1-2 weeks.

          -  Controlled diabetic patients (HbA1c ≤9.0%), no change in type of oral or injectable
             hypoglycemic agents for the last 12 weeks

          -  Those who voluntarily agreed to participate in clinical trials after hearing the
             explanation of the clinical trial

          -  Those who understand the content of the clinical trial and are able to participate in
             the trial by the end of the clinical trial

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diabetic patients other than type 2 diabetes, including type 1 diabetes and
             gestational diabetes

          -  Those who have a previous history of medication with ezetimibe or discontinuation due
             to side effects after medication

          -  Patients who have had a history of discontinuation of statin therapy due to side
             effects after medication,

          -  Unregulated diabetic patients (those who have changed the type of oral or injectable
             hypoglycemic agent within 12 weeks prior to Visit 1 or who have HbA1c&gt; 9.0% at
             screening time (Visit 1)

          -  patients with acute or chronic metabolic acidosis, including diabetic ketoacidosis
             with or without coma, and patients with a history of ketonic acidosis (within 6
             months)

          -  Those who use thiazolidinedione and SGLT2i drugs which can affect fatty liver as a
             diabetes treatment drug

          -  Patients who meet the criteria for alcoholism in fatty liver disease (210 g / week for
             men in the last two years, 140 g / week for women)

          -  Chronic liver disease (including hemochromatosis, liver cancer, autoimmune liver
             disease, Child-Pugh score&gt; 7points, platelet &lt;75,000mm2, prothrombin time&gt; 16s), viral
             hepatitis -A, B,

          -  People who take drugs that can cause fatty liver (amiodarone, methotrexate, tamoxifen,
             valproate, corticosteroids, etc.)

          -  Patients who are allergic or hypersensitive to the drug or its constituents

          -  Patients who were treated with oral or parenteral corticosteroids chronic (within
             consecutive 14 days) within 8 weeks before screening

          -  Patients with genetic problems such as galactose intolerance, Lapp lactose
             dehydrogenase deficiency or glucose-galactose uptake disorder

          -  Patients with malnutrition, starvation, weakness (including severe infections, pre-
             and post-operative trauma patients), pituitary dysfunction or adrenal insufficiency

          -  Serum levels of alanine aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase or alkaline
             phosphatase are increased over 5-fold elevation of the normal range upper limit [ULN]
             or 5-fold elevation of the serum total bilirubin level. )

          -  Currently taking medication for weight loss

          -  Patients with a history of malignant tumors within the past 2 years or malignant
             tumors that are currently undergoing treatment or progression

          -  Patients with a history of substance abuse or alcohol intoxication within 12 weeks

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  Patients with severe infection, pre- and post-operative, and severe trauma

          -  Patients with acute cardiovascular disease within 12 weeks (patients with unstable
             angina, myocardial infarction, transient ischemic attack, cerebrovascular disease,
             coronary artery bypass grafting, or coronary intervention)

          -  Patients with renal failure, chronic renal disease (estimated glomerular filtration
             rate &lt;60 mL / min / 1.73 m2)

          -  Anemic patients with a Hb level of less than 10.5 g / dl

          -  Surgical or medical conditions that may affect the absorption, distribution,
             metabolism and excretion of a drug, including, but not limited to, gastrectomy,
             gastroenterostomy, History of major gastrointestinal surgery such as small bowel
             resection, gastrointestinal bypass, gastrointestinal stapling, current active
             gastritis, gastrointestinal / rectal bleeding, active inflammatory bowel syndrome
             within the last 12 months, etc.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yonsei University College of Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Endocrinology, Severance Hospital, Diabetes center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>03722</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yong-ho Lee, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>82-2-2228-1943</phone>
      <email>yholee@yuhs.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loomba R, Sirlin CB, Ang B, Bettencourt R, Jain R, Salotti J, Soaft L, Hooker J, Kono Y, Bhatt A, Hernandez L, Nguyen P, Noureddin M, Haufe W, Hooker C, Yin M, Ehman R, Lin GY, Valasek MA, Brenner DA, Richards L; San Diego Integrated NAFLD Research Consortium (SINC). Ezetimibe for the treatment of nonalcoholic steatohepatitis: assessment by novel magnetic resonance imaging and magnetic resonance elastography in a randomized trial (MOZART trial). Hepatology. 2015 Apr;61(4):1239-50. doi: 10.1002/hep.27647. Epub 2015 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>25482832</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyslipidemias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperlipidemias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperlipoproteinemias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rosuvastatin Calcium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ezetimibe</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

