<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03435497</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34MH111460</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03435497</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Intervention to Empower HIV Clients as Prevention Advocates in Uganda</brief_title>
  <official_title>Game Changers: Pilot Intervention to Empower HIV Clients as Prevention Advocates in Uganda</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RAND</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Infectious Diseases Institute, Uganda</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RAND</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized controlled pilot study of the &quot;Game Changers&quot; program will:

        1. Assess the feasibility and acceptability of implementing an HIV prevention advocacy
           intervention with people living with HIV who are in HIV care, and who will be trained to
           be advocates of HIV protective behaviors within their social networks.

        2. Assess preliminary intervention effects on a) protective behavior of the HIV-positive
           clients (condom use, partner concurrency/number of partners, engagement in HIV care, ART
           adherence); and b) diffusion of prevention messages across the network, as assessed by
           the content and extent of communication with network members about protective behaviors
           (condom use, partner concurrency/number of partners, HIV testing, engagement in HIV
           care, circumcision), HIV disclosure, and HIV stigma.

        3. Explore characteristics of HIV-positive clients who more effectively engage in
           prevention advocacy (in terms of socio-demographics, network characteristics, and
           network position and type of alters receiving advocacy).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      People living with HIV (PLWH) have a critical role to play in HIV prevention, not only in the
      context of Prevention for Positives and Treatment as Prevention, but as powerful change
      agents for HIV protective behaviors among others. Our research suggests that as PLWH receive
      HIV treatment and restore their health and functioning, many are motivated to protect their
      loved ones and engage in prevention advocacy (i.e., to encourage friends and family to seek
      HIV testing and treatment, and to reduce risk behavior); however, the quality of this
      advocacy is hampered by challenges related to message content, style and timing of delivery,
      and selection of advocacy recipients. With effective advocacy training, mobilizing PLWH to be
      change agents within their social networks has the potential to be a &quot;game changer&quot; for HIV
      prevention, particularly in high prevalence settings such as Uganda, where virtually every
      family is touched by someone living with HIV. Drawing upon theoretical frameworks for
      network-based interventions, such as theories of social diffusion, cognitive consistency, and
      social influence, the proposed study will develop and pilot test &quot;Game Changers&quot;-- an
      intervention that aims to empower and mobilize PLWH to be agents for HIV prevention and
      behavioral change in their social networks. In Phase 1, separate focus groups of PLWH and
      members of their social networks (family and friends) were conducted to explore barriers to
      and facilitators of mobilizing clients to advocate for HIV prevention, perceptions on how
      advocacy could be most effective in motivating behavior change, and how to best structure the
      intervention and its content. In Phase 2 findings from Phase 1 and network-based intervention
      models were used to develop the structure and content of an intervention designed to help
      clients cope with stigma, manage their disease, live positively, and develop motivation and
      skills for HIV disclosure and prevention advocacy. In Phase 3 a pilot group intervention will
      be conducted in a controlled trial of 96 clients, with 48 randomly assigned to receive the
      intervention and 48 to the wait-list control. Assessments will be administered to all
      participants at baseline, 3-4 months later, and again 6-7 after baseline, after which the
      control group will receive the intervention (but not the interviews). PLWH interviews and
      social network assessments will examine intervention effects on protective behaviors of the
      participant (condom use, HIV treatment adherence), and diffusion of prevention messages
      across the network, as assessed by the content and extent of communication with network
      members about protective behaviors (condom use, partner concurrency/number of partners, HIV
      testing, engagement in HIV care, circumcision), HIV disclosure, and HIV stigma. At the end of
      the intervention period a focus group with program participants will be conducted to get
      feedback on the intervention. To help understand how participation in the program might
      affect health, date of HIV diagnosis, last two CD4 counts and HIV viral loads, and prescribed
      HIV medications will be obtained from PLWH participant medical charts. Participants (about
      15/arm) will be asked to recruit up to 3 alters each, who know the participant's serostatus,
      to be interviewed to assess their HIV protective behaviors (e.g., condom use) and receipt of
      prevention advocacy from the intervention participant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Engagement HIV Prevention Advocacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Past 3 months, measured at baseline and about 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported increased communication with social network members about protective behaviors</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sexual Risk Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and about 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Increased self-reported condom use in past 3 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HIV treatment adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and about 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Increased antiretroviral treatment adherence (self-reported % doses taken in past month)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Internalized HIV Stigma</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and about 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Decreased rates of internalized HIV-related stigma on Internalized AIDS Stigma Scale (range=1-5, higher values = high stigma)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HIV Disclosure</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and about 3 and 6 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Increased self-reported rates of HIV status disclosure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Game Changers Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Game Changers is an intervention that aims to empower and mobilize people living with HIV to be agents for HIV prevention and behavioral change in their social networks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will receive standard of care during the intervention assessment period. All control participants will be offered the Game Changers program once all assessments for the primary study outcomes have been completed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Game Changers</intervention_name>
    <description>Game Changers is an intervention that aims to empower and mobilize PLHA to be agents for HIV prevention and behavioral change in their social networks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Game Changers Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (People living with HIV):

          -  18+ years old

          -  In HIV care for &gt; 1 year

          -  Having disclosed serostatus to at least one person

        Inclusion Criteria (Social network members):

          -  18+ years old

          -  Referred by a patient participant because they are family members, friends, or other
             people in patients' social network

          -  knows patient participant's serostatus

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who meet the inclusion criteria above will be eligible to participate, and
             no other exclusion criteria apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura Bogart, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>RAND</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Laura M Bogart, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3103930411</phone>
    <phone_ext>7281</phone_ext>
    <email>lbogart@rand.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Glenn J Wagner, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3103930411</phone>
    <phone_ext>7698</phone_ext>
    <email>gwagner@rand.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Infectious Diseases Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kampala</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew Kambugu, MD</last_name>
      <email>akambugu@idi.co.ug</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

