<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03430648</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00042050</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30AG021332</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03430648</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Is Tau Protein Linked to Mobility Function?</brief_title>
  <acronym>SYNERGY</acronym>
  <official_title>Is Tau Protein Linked to Mobility Function?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project will provide new data to address an important question linking Alzheimer's
      disease neuropathology to physical disability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Impaired mobility is strongly linked to cognitive function and vice versa. Cognitive
      functions are strongly associated with mobility function, most commonly assessed using gait
      speed. In the Health ABC Study, Digit Symbol Substitution Test (DSST) and Modified Mini
      Mental Status (3MS) scores were significantly associated with gait speed and gait speed
      decline. Poor lower extremity performance predicts faster age-related cognitive decline and
      increased incidence of mild cognitive impairment (MCI) and dementia. This study will explore
      the role of tau protein as the neuropathologic basis for these associations.

      Brain imaging markers may be the link between cognitive measures and gait. White matter
      disease is commonly measured by quantifying white matter (WM) lesion load, which is
      associated with small vessel ischemic disease. More subtle microstructural changes can be
      observed by calculating fractional anisotropy (FA) from diffusion tensor imaging (DTI). Aging
      is accompanied by changes in cortical volume, white matter microstructure and an increased
      prevalence of WM lesions. WM lesions have been strongly implicated in declining physical
      function. These brain changes are associated with impaired balance, slower movement speeds,
      slower chair stand times and increased falls risk.Recently, Aâ accumulation in the brain has
      also been linked to slow gait. This finding suggests a pathologic mechanism linking Alzheimer
      s disease processes to gait impairments. However, Aâ accumulation itself may not be the
      critical neuropathic change. In recent studies of Aâ42 and phosphorylated tau protein in
      cerebral spinal fluid, it has been found that low Aâ42 levels themselves are not associated
      with impaired cognition, but that elevated tau levels are also required. If the process of
      cognitive impairment parallels the process of gait impairment, it might be that tau levels
      are more important correlates of gait changes. To the investigators' knowledge the
      relationship between CSF tau levels and mobility has never been explored. PET ligands for
      brain tau have recently become available, but the relationship between brain tau accumulation
      and gait has yet to be determined. In this study, investigators will relate gait
      characteristics to CSF Aâ42 and phosphorylated tau levels, and perform brain PET imaging in a
      subset to related tau protein accumulation to gait characteristics for the first time. Both
      mobility impairment and Alzheimers disease (AD) occur in the context of the aging vascular
      system. Over the past 15 years, it has been recognized that abnormalities of thoracic aortic
      stiffness are associated with the development of abnormalities in small vessels supplying the
      brain and kidneys. As the aorta stiffens, the propagation speed of the systolic flow wave
      increases through the aortic lumen. (Stiffness within the thoracic aorta can be accomplished
      through measurement of aortic pulse wave velocity.) In hypertensive patients, aortic archway
      pulse wave velocity has been associated with increases in left ventricular mass as well as
      lacunar brain infarcts independent of age, sex, and the duration of hypertension. In the
      Multi-Ethnic Dallas Heart Study aortic arch pulse wave velocity is an independent predictor
      of white matter hyper-intensities. In those with diabetes, increasing aortic stiffness
      contributes to the development of small vessel microvascular dysfunction which is associated
      with deep white matter atrophy as well as cognitive decline. Recently, a stiffness mismatch
      between the thoracic aorta and small vessels within the cerebral microcirculation has been
      described. This mismatch impacts microvascular pulsatility and appears to diminish diffusion
      anisotrophy between the cerebral spinal fluid and the CNS microcirculation. This observation
      may contribute to retained amyloid type protein in those with AD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between CSF total and phosphorylated tau levels and gait speed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>This will be done using the 400m walk test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between CSF total and phosphorylated tau levels and gait variability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>This will be done using the gaitrite mat.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between CSF total and phosphorylated tau levels and standing balance.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>This will be done using the AMTI force plate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the association between Digit Symbol Substitution Test and gait speed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitively and metabolically normal</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group has been defined as being cognitively and metabolically normal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitively normal with prediabetes</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group has been defined as being cognitively normal but showing signs of prediabetes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Persons with Mild Cognitive Impairment</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group has been defined as being mildly cognitively impaired.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Persons with early Alzheimer's disase</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group has been defined as having early Alzheimer's disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Investigators plan to recruit a total of 60 people age 50 and older from the Wake Forest
        Alzheimer's Disease Research Center's Clinical Core group.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  50+ years of age and participated in the Wake Forest Alzheimer's Disease Core Center
             study

          -  Willing to provide informed consent

          -  Not dependent on a walker

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recent cardiac event in the last 6 months

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (BP &gt;200/110 mmHg)

          -  Neurological (e.g., Parkinson's) or hematological disease

          -  Participants with a knee replacement in last 6 months

          -  Participants with recent eye surgery in last 6 months

          -  Severe musculoskeletal impairment (e.g., sciatica, fibromyalgia, severe leg/back pain)

          -  If willing to get an MRI, must not have indwelling metal-contraining prosthesis,
             pacemaker or defibrillator, history of welding, permanent make up or head/neck tattoo,
             or any other contraindication to MRI
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Kritchevsky, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tau protein</keyword>
  <keyword>PET imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

