<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03439332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPV-2018-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03439332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multicentre Validation of How Vascular Biomarkers From Tumor Can Predict the Survival of the Patient With Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>ONCOhabitats</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicentre Validation of Hemodynamic Multiparametric Tissue Signature (MTS) Biomarkers From Preoperative and Postradiotherapy MRI in Patients With Glioblastoma: Predictors of Overall Survival</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Juan M Garcia-Gomez</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital of Liege</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital de Manises</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital de la Ribera</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Vall d'Hebron</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Parma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitat Politècnica de València</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite an aggressive therapeutic approach, the prognosis for most patients with glioblastoma
      (GBM) remains poor. The relationship between non-invasive Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)
      biomarkers at preoperative, postradiotherapy and follow-up stages, and the survival time in
      GBM patients will be useful to plan an optimal strategy for the management of the disease.

      The Hemodynamic Multiparametric Tissue Signature (HTS) biomarker provides an automated
      unsupervised method to describe the heterogeneity of the enhancing tumor and edema areas in
      terms of the angiogenic process located at these regions. This allows to automatically draw 4
      reproducible habitats that describe the tumor vascular heterogeneity:

        -  The High Angiogenic enhancing Tumor (HAT)

        -  The Less Angiogenic enhancing Tumor (LAT)

        -  The potentially tumor Infiltrated Peripheral Edema (IPE)

        -  The Vasogenic Peripheral Edema (VPE)

      The conceptual hypothesis is that there is a significant correlation between the perfusion
      biomarkers located at several HTS habitats and the patient's overall survival.

      The primary purpose of this clinical study is to determine if preoperative vascular
      heterogeneity of glioblastoma is predictive of overall survival of patients undergoing
      standard-of-care treatment by using the HTS biomarker.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter observational retrospective study with data collected from Hospital
      Information System (HIS) and Picture Archiving and Communication System (PACS) of each center
      involved in the study. The cohort is built with patients diagnosed with glioblastoma (GBM)
      with a Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) pre-treatment since 1st of January of 2012 until the
      Study Start Date.

      The main objective of the study is to determine if the habitats obtained by the Hemodynamic
      Multiparametric Tissue Signature (HTS) biomarker, which describe the tumor vascular
      heterogeneity of the enhancing tumor and edema areas, are predictive of the overall survival
      of patients undergoing standard-of-care treatment.

      The specific objectives of the study are:

        -  To identify four habitats within the GBM using MRI and HTS

        -  To analyse the relation between the HTS habitats obtained from the first preoperative
           MRI and the overall survival of the patient

        -  To analyse the relation between HTS habitats obtained from the first preoperative MRI
           and the progression-free survival of the patient

        -  To analyse the relation between the HTS habitats obtained from the postradiotherapy MRI
           and the overall survival of the patient

        -  To analyse the relation between HTS habitats obtained from the postradiotherapy MRI and
           the progression-free survival of the patient

        -  To discover other interesting relations between the HTS habitats obtained from
           preoperative, postradiotherapy and follow-up images and the clinical conditions of the
           patients

      Cox regression, Kaplan-Meier estimator and multiple linear regression analysis will be used
      to assess survival significance of each biomarker at each HTS habitat. The predictive value
      will be compared with models based on clinical and volumetric image variables: Age, Karnofsky
      Performance Status (KPS) Scale and Visually AcceSAble Rembrandt Images (VASARI) features.
      Moreover, the HTS-based models will be compared to models based on hemodynamic biomarkers,
      such as Cerebral Blood Flow (CBF), Cerebral Blood Volume (CBV), capillary permeability
      (Ktrans) and fractional Volume of Extravascular-Extracellular space (Ve), and diffusion
      biomarkers, such as Apparent Diffusion Coefficient (ADC), extracted from automatic
      segmentations of the edema and the enhancing tumor. Finally, Sørensen-Dice coefficient will
      be used to measure the correlation between MTS habitats in longitudinal studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 7, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between overall survival (in days) of patients undergoing standard-of-care treatment and the tumor vascular heterogeneity described by the four habitats obtained by the Hemodynamic Multiparametric Tissue Signature (HTS) biomarker</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of the first MRI acquisition until the date of death from any cause, assessed up to 80 months</time_frame>
    <description>The overall survival for each patient is estimated since the date of the preoperative Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) to the exitus date. Exitus date will be collected from clinical records and should be confirmed by the main investigator from each center.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between progression-free survival (in days) of patients undergoing standard-of-care treatment and the tumor vascular heterogeneity described by the four habitats obtained by the HTS biomarker</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of the first MRI acquisition until the date of first documented progression, assessed up to 80 months</time_frame>
    <description>The progression-free survival for each patient is estimated since the date of the preoperative MRI to the date of recurrence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between MTS habitats in longitudinal studies</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of the first MRI acquisition until the date of death from any cause, assessed up to 80 months</time_frame>
    <description>In order to study this outcome, the postradiotherapy and the follow-up images in combination with the preoperative ones, will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The population of the target group is formed by patients diagnosed with Glioblastoma grade
        IV World Health Organization (WHO) with histopathological confirmation
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with Glioblastoma grade IV WHO with histopathological confirmation

          -  Age &gt;18 years at diagnosis

          -  Patients with access to the preoperative and postradiotherapy MRI studies using 1.5
             Tesla (T) or 3T scanners, including: pre and post gadolinium T1-weighted MRI,
             T2-weighted MRI, FLAIR MRI, Dynamic Susceptibility Contrast (DSC) T2*-weighted
             perfusion, Dynamic Contrast Enhancement (DCE) T1-weighted perfusion (optional) and
             Diffusion Weighted Imaging (DWI) (optional)

          -  WHO performance score between 0 and 2

          -  Patients with Karnofsky Performance Score (KPS) of ≥ 70%

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with congestive heart failure within 6 months prior to study entry (New York
             Heart Association ≥ Grade 3)

          -  Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease, including: myocardial infarction
             and transient ischemic attack or stroke within 6 months prior to enrollment,
             uncontrolled angina within 6 months, diagnosed or suspected congenital long QT
             syndrome, any history of clinically significant ventricular arrhythmia (such as
             ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation or Torsades de pointes) and
             clinically significant abnormality on electrocardiogram (ECG)

          -  Pulmonary disease including or greater than grade 2 dyspnea or laryngeal edema, grade
             3 pulmonary edema or pulmonary hypertension according to CTCAE 4.03
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Juan M Garcia Gomez, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitat Politècnica de València</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fuensanta Bellvis Bataller, Biomedical</last_name>
    <phone>+34 963877000</phone>
    <phone_ext>75278</phone_ext>
    <email>fuebelba@etsii.upv.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elies Fuster i Garcia, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34 963877000</phone>
    <phone_ext>75278</phone_ext>
    <email>elfusgar@mat.upv.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitat Politècnica de València</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46022</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fuensanta Bellvis Bataller, Biomedical</last_name>
      <phone>+34 963877000</phone>
      <phone_ext>75278</phone_ext>
      <email>fuebelba@etsii.upv.es</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Juan M Garcia Gomez, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34 963877000</phone>
      <phone_ext>75278</phone_ext>
      <email>juanmig@ibime.upv.es</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elies Fuster i Garcia, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Javier Juan Albarracin, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fernando Aparici, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carlos Botella, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jose Muñoz, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raquel Faubel, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sabina Asensio, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.oncohabitats.upv.es/</url>
    <description>In order to allow the scientific community to test the biomarker, a non-commercial research purposes platform has been created. It offers the opportunity to upload cases of glioblastoma on which different services can be applied.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juan-Albarracín J, Fuster-Garcia E, Pérez-Girbés A, Aparici-Robles F, Alberich-Bayarri Á, Revert-Ventura A, Martí-Bonmatí L, García-Gómez JM. Glioblastoma: Vascular Habitats Detected at Preoperative Dynamic Susceptibility-weighted Contrast-enhanced Perfusion MR Imaging Predict Survival. Radiology. 2018 Jun;287(3):944-954. doi: 10.1148/radiol.2017170845. Epub 2018 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>29357274</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juan-Albarracín J, Fuster-Garcia E, Manjón JV, Robles M, Aparici F, Martí-Bonmatí L, García-Gómez JM. Automated glioblastoma segmentation based on a multiparametric structured unsupervised classification. PLoS One. 2015 May 15;10(5):e0125143. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0125143. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25978453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universitat Politècnica de València</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Juan M Garcia-Gomez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Highly infiltrative</keyword>
  <keyword>Deeply invasive</keyword>
  <keyword>Strong vascular proliferation</keyword>
  <keyword>Robust angiogenesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular heterogeneity</keyword>
  <keyword>Perfusion Biormarker</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-Invasive Biomarker</keyword>
  <keyword>Predictor of overall survival</keyword>
  <keyword>Predictor of progression-free survival</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

