<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03432143</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-00374</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03432143</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community Members as Reviewers of Medical Journal Manuscripts</brief_title>
  <official_title>Community Members as Reviewers of Medical Journal Manuscripts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MetroHealth Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MetroHealth Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Manuscripts submitted to medical journals are typically reviewed by physicians or
      researchers, with no input from patients or other community members. However, involvement of
      community members in other phases of the research process suggests that they provide distinct
      and useful expertise. Such involvement may lead to enhanced understanding of community
      priorities, refinement of study designs to minimize participant burden, and increased
      recruitment and retention of subjects.

      The investigators propose a randomized controlled trial involving 24 community members who
      will receive training and mentoring in reviewing manuscripts. A total of 568 manuscripts
      submitted to 2 medical journals will be randomly assigned to an intervention or control
      group. Intervention manuscripts will be reviewed by both a community member and by scientific
      reviewers while control manuscripts will be reviewed only by scientific reviewers. Journal
      editorial teams will use all reviews to help them make decisions about acceptance, revision,
      or rejection of manuscripts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Manuscripts submitted to medical journals are typically reviewed by physicians or
      researchers, with no input from patients or other community members. However, involvement of
      community members in other phases of the research process suggests that they provide distinct
      and useful expertise. Such involvement may lead to enhanced understanding of community
      priorities, refinement of study designs to minimize participant burden, and increased
      recruitment and retention of subjects. In general, community involvement in research is more
      common in the earlier phases of the research process (selection of research question and
      development of a study protocol) and less common in later phases (dissemination and
      implementation of findings). In the investigators' previous work, they conducted a pilot
      study that recruited and trained community members to review medical journal manuscripts.
      They found that community reviewers were much more likely than scientific reviewers to
      comment on i) the relevance of the study to patients and communities, ii) the diversity and
      complexity of the study participants, iii) the social context of the condition studied, and
      iv) barriers to implementation of study findings by patients and communities.

      The investigators now propose a randomized controlled trial involving 24 community members
      who will receive training and mentoring in reviewing manuscripts. A total of 568 manuscripts
      submitted to 2 medical journals will be randomly assigned to an intervention or control
      group. Intervention manuscripts will be reviewed by both a community member and by scientific
      reviewers while control manuscripts will be reviewed only by scientific reviewers. Community
      reviewers will follow each journal's instructions regarding electronic access to manuscripts,
      use of drop-down menus and free-text boxes to address specific aspects of the review, and
      completion within the time frame specified by the journal. Journal editorial teams will use
      all reviews to help them make decisions about acceptance, revision, or rejection of
      manuscripts. Quantitative and qualitative analyses will i) compare the content of community
      and scientific reviews, ii) determine the usefulness of community reviews to journal editors,
      and iii) explore how community reviewer comments are integrated into published articles.

      The proposed project is a novel approach to engaging health disparity populations and other
      community members in dissemination of research findings. This approach has the potential to
      provide new and distinct perspectives, to increase the quality and relevance of articles
      published in medical journals, and to enhance dissemination and implementation of research
      findings.

      Primary Aim A. To compare community member reviews with those of scientific reviewers.

      Hypothesis: Compared to scientific reviewers, community reviewers will be more likely to
      comment on relevance to patients and communities, subject diversity, social context, and
      implementation barriers.

      Primary Aim B. To determine the usefulness of community member reviews to editors.

      Hypothesis: Editors will report utilizing community reviewer comments in manuscript
      decisions.

      Secondary Aim C. To explore how community reviews are integrated into published articles.

      Hypothesis: Community perspectives that were not present in manuscripts at the time of
      original submission will subsequently be discernible in published articles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>24 community members will receive training and mentoring in reviewing manuscripts. The trial will involve 568 manuscripts that will be randomly assigned to two groups using a random number generator.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare community member reviews with those of scientific reviewers.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will examine community and scientific reviewer ratings of intervention group manuscripts, including overall recommendations and ratings of specific aspects of the manuscripts. The overall recommendation categories will be converted into a 4 point Likert scale and combine data across journals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the usefulness of community member reviews to editors.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will examine editor ratings of the usefulness of intervention group manuscript reviews submitted by community and scientific reviewers. The investigators will use qualitative analyses to identify specific themes present in editors' responses to open-ended questions about the usefulness of community reviews.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>To explore how community reviews are integrated into published articles.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will examine how specific community reviewer comments are addressed by authors. They will also examine how often community and patient perspectives are present in published articles.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">568</enrollment>
  <condition>Peer Review, Research</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Community Reviewers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>24 community members will receive training and mentoring in reviewing manuscripts. Approximately 284 manuscripts will be randomized into the intervention group over the duration of the study. Manuscripts will be reviewed by both a community member and scientific reviewers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Scientific Reviewers Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Approximately 284 manuscripts will be randomized into the control group over the duration of the study. Manuscripts will be reviewed by multiple scientific reviewers. Community reviewers will not be involved in reviewing these manuscripts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community Reviewers</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention manuscripts will be reviewed by both a trained community member and scientific reviewers. Community reviewers will follow each journal's instructions regarding electronic access to manuscripts, use of drop-down menus and free-text boxes to address specific aspects of the review, and completion within the time frame specified by the journal.The journal editorial team will use all reviews to make decisions about acceptance, revision, or rejection of manuscripts.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Community Reviewers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Community Reviewer Eligibility:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  At least a high school diploma

          -  Proficient in English speaking, reading, and writing

          -  Computer access

          -  Personal experience (having the condition or being a caregiver to someone with the
             condition) with 1 or more of these conditions: Cancer, diabetes, dementia, heart
             disease, hypertension, liver disease, lung disease, kidney disease, and stroke

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children under 18 years of age

          -  Non-high school graduates

          -  Individuals who work in health care settings

          -  Individuals who have formal training in health care or scientific research

        Manuscript Eligibility:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Full length

          -  Original research
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashwini Sehgal</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Western Reserve University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katrice D Cain, MA</last_name>
    <phone>(216) 778-8467</phone>
    <email>kcain@metrohealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MetroHealth Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katrice Cain</last_name>
      <email>kcain@metrohealth.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Israel BA, Schulz AJ, Parker EA, Becker AB. Review of community-based research: assessing partnership approaches to improve public health. Annu Rev Public Health. 1998;19:173-202. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9611617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Minkler M. Community-based research partnerships: challenges and opportunities. J Urban Health. 2005 Jun;82(2 Suppl 2):ii3-12. Epub 2005 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>15888635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caron-Flinterman JF, Broerse JE, Teerling J, Bunders JF. Patients' priorities concerning health research: the case of asthma and COPD research in the Netherlands. Health Expect. 2005 Sep;8(3):253-63.</citation>
    <PMID>16098155</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hewlett S, Wit Md, Richards P, Quest E, Hughes R, Heiberg T, Kirwan J. Patients and professionals as research partners: challenges, practicalities, and benefits. Arthritis Rheum. 2006 Aug 15;55(4):676-80.</citation>
    <PMID>16874772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Resnik DB, Kennedy CE. Balancing scientific and community interests in community-based participatory research. Account Res. 2010 Jul;17(4):198-210. doi: 10.1080/08989621.2010.493095.</citation>
    <PMID>20597018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wallerstein NB, Duran B. Using community-based participatory research to address health disparities. Health Promot Pract. 2006 Jul;7(3):312-23. Epub 2006 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>16760238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fleurence RL, Forsythe LP, Lauer M, Rotter J, Ioannidis JP, Beal A, Frank L, Selby JV. Engaging patients and stakeholders in research proposal review: the patient-centered outcomes research institute. Ann Intern Med. 2014 Jul 15;161(2):122-30. doi: 10.7326/M13-2412.</citation>
    <PMID>25023251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Domecq JP, Prutsky G, Elraiyah T, Wang Z, Nabhan M, Shippee N, Brito JP, Boehmer K, Hasan R, Firwana B, Erwin P, Eton D, Sloan J, Montori V, Asi N, Dabrh AM, Murad MH. Patient engagement in research: a systematic review. BMC Health Serv Res. 2014 Feb 26;14:89. doi: 10.1186/1472-6963-14-89. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24568690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Forsythe LP, Frank L, Walker KO, Anise A, Wegener N, Weisman H, Hunt G, Beal A. Patient and clinician views on comparative effectiveness research and engagement in research. J Comp Eff Res. 2015 Jan;4(1):11-25. doi: 10.2217/cer.14.52.</citation>
    <PMID>25565066</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reich SM, Reich JA. Cultural competence in interdisciplinary collaborations: a method for respecting diversity in research partnerships. Am J Community Psychol. 2006 Sep;38(1-2):51-62.</citation>
    <PMID>16807789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Supple D, Roberts A, Hudson V, Masefield S, Fitch N, Rahmen M, Flood B, de Boer W, Powell P, Wagers S; U-BIOPRED PIP group. From tokenism to meaningful engagement: best practices in patient involvement in an EU project. Res Involv Engagem. 2015 Jun 25;1:5. doi: 10.1186/s40900-015-0004-9. eCollection 2015. Erratum in: Res Involv Engagem. 2015 Nov 16;1:12.</citation>
    <PMID>29062494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barber R, Boote JD, Parry GD, Cooper CL, Yeeles P, Cook S. Can the impact of public involvement on research be evaluated? A mixed methods study. Health Expect. 2012 Sep;15(3):229-41. doi: 10.1111/j.1369-7625.2010.00660.x. Epub 2011 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21324054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Staley K. 'Is it worth doing?' Measuring the impact of patient and public involvement in research. Res Involv Engagem. 2015 Jul 31;1:6. doi: 10.1186/s40900-015-0008-5. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>29062495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright D, Foster C, Amir Z, Elliott J, Wilson R. Critical appraisal guidelines for assessing the quality and impact of user involvement in research. Health Expect. 2010 Dec;13(4):359-68. doi: 10.1111/j.1369-7625.2010.00607.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20629767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frank L, Forsythe L, Ellis L, Schrandt S, Sheridan S, Gerson J, Konopka K, Daugherty S. Conceptual and practical foundations of patient engagement in research at the patient-centered outcomes research institute. Qual Life Res. 2015 May;24(5):1033-41. doi: 10.1007/s11136-014-0893-3. Epub 2015 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25560774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>MetroHealth Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ash Sehgal</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peer Review</keyword>
  <keyword>Community-Based Research</keyword>
  <keyword>Community Perspectives</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

