<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03431558</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SLAB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03431558</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bovine Lactoferrin and Neonatal Survival in Low Birth Weight Babies.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can Bovine Lactoferrin Prevent Neonatal Infections in Low Birth Weight Babies in Karachi, Sindh, Pakistan.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aga Khan University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Sydney</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Agency for International Development (USAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Aga Khan University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pakistan has the third highest number of neonatal deaths worldwide. During the last two
      decades (1990-2013), neonatal mortality rate in the country has declined by only 1.0% per
      year. Severe infection is the second most leading cause of neonatal mortality, account for
      28% of all deaths in Pakistan. Majority of neonatal deaths occur in infants who LBW (birth
      weight &lt;2500g) and LBW comprises of both preterm / small for gestational age newborns.
      Breastfeeding helps protect infants from infections by serving as a source of nutrition
      uncontaminated by environmental pathogens. The protection is due to the multiple
      anti-infective, anti-inflammatory, and immuno regulatory factors transmitted through milk
      including secretory antibodies, glycan's, Lactoferrin, leukocytes, cytokines &amp; other
      components produced by the mother's immune system.

      Reduction in neonatal infections and deaths is the aim of this study. The study is being
      conducted at the Aga Khan University in collaboration with University of Sydney.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Globally, severe infection is the second leading cause of neonatal mortality. It is one of
      the indirect leading causes of death in a world. According to Annual report, 28% neonatal
      deaths were due to preterm baby, 26% due to severe infection , 23% due to asphyxia and 7%
      neonatal tetanus. Every year, three - fourth deaths occurred in first week and four million
      babies die each year within first four weeks of birth, whereas, 99% of cases were reported by
      low and middle income countries.Severe infections are the second major cause of death among
      neonates in Pakistan. Breastfeeding helps to protect infants from infections due to the
      multiple anti-infective, anti-inflammatory, and immuno regulatory factors such as secretory
      antibodies, glycan, Lactoferrin etc. Lactoferrin, the second most abundant protein in human
      milk has multiple putative functions. A trial in Italy found that the incidence of late-onset
      sepsis and sepsis related deaths were significantly lower in very LBW infants who were given
      daily (Bovine Lactoferrin) bLF compared to placebo. One small trial from India, found there
      was a 79% reduction in neonatal infections in LBW infants who received daily bovine
      Lactoferrin (bLF) from birth until 28 days. Evidence gaps remain about the appropriate daily
      prophylactic dose, the optimal method to deliver, and the effectiveness of bLF to prevent
      neonatal sepsis in LBW infants in low &amp; middle-income countries.The overall goal of the
      project is to improve newborn survival among low birth weight (LBW) Pakistani infants through
      provision of a daily prophylactic dose of bLF. The project aim is to prevent neonatal
      infections, as opposed to the current approach which treats neonatal infections when they
      occur. The current approach depends on early detection of infections in newborns through
      post-natal care and treatment with antibiotics, with the potential risk of inappropriate use
      of antibiotics.A two stage study will be conducted including formative research followed by
      RCT to evaluate the appropriate daily dose of bLF. At the end of the study the investigators
      will have developed and tested an appropriate method to deliver bLF to newborns at home &amp;
      identified the most appropriate dose of bLF to prevent neonatal sepsis in LBW newborns.

      This study will be conducted at the Aga Khan University and Hospital, Karachi in two phases.
      A qualitative study will be conducted followed by a RCT. 300 LBW new born babies will be
      recruited;all standard operating procedures will be followed for administration of bLF to the
      neonates. Each arm of the study will be allocated 100 newborns.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Group 1: bLF (150 mg) will be administered after 48 hours of age with a single daily dose mixed with milk (preferentially breast milk otherwise premature formula milk).
Group 2: bLF will be administered (300mg) after 48 hours of life with a single daily dose mixed with milk (preferentially breast milk otherwise premature formula milk).
Group 3: Placebo will be administered after 48 hours of life (Placebo will be physically identical to the bLF mixed with breast milk or premature formula milk).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Randomization will be carried out by Data management unit and all investigators /dispensers and participants will be masked to the randomization.
Clinical Trial Unit (CTU) of the Aga khan university will dispense the randomized supplemnt/placebo</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Late onset sepsis (LOS) in Low Birth Weight.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in late onset sepsis (LOS) in Low Birth Weight babies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimal dosage of bLF</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Deduce optimal dosage of bLF in LBW babies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Necrotizing Enterocolitis in LBW babies</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of Necrotizing Enterocolitis in Low Birth Weight babies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neonatal Mortality at 1 month of life.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of Neonatal Mortality at 1 month of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Neonatal Sepsis</condition>
  <condition>Necrotizing Enterocolitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>bLF (Bovine Lactoferrin plus Glucan D 99.4%) Dose: 150 mg Frequency: a single daily dose mixed with milk (preferentially breast milk otherwise formula milk).
Duration: 1 month</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>bLF (Bovine Lactoferrin plus Glucan D 99.4%) Dose: 300mg Frequency: a single daily dose mixed with milk (preferentially breast milk otherwise formula milk).
Duration: 1 month</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo: Only Glucan-D (99.4% glucoseDose: 150 mg Frequency: a single daily dose mixed with milk (preferentially breast milk otherwise formula milk).
Duration: 1 month</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bLF (Bovine lactoferrin)</intervention_name>
    <description>BLF administration in two different strengths (150 &amp; 300mg) will be given on the third day of life with a single daily dose mixed with milk for 1 month.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucon-D 99.4% (Placebo)</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will be given 100mg Glucon-D (99.4% glucose) placebo which will be similar in shape, color to the bLF.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Neonates with:

        birth weight ≤ 2500 g and ≥ 1000 grams. gestational age ≥ to 28 +0 weeks to 36+6. family
        planned on staying in the study area for at least 1 month • parents/ caretaker willing to
        provide consent. newborn initiated enteral feeding via (gavage feeding with expressed
        breast milk or formula, direct breast feeding or cup and spoon feeding at or within 48
        hours of birth.)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Neonate with congenital anomalies. early-onset sepsis. birth weight less than 1000 g.
        gestational age less than or equal to 27weeks+6 days. history of Chorioamnionitis or
        maternal group B streptococcus colonization. Reversed or absent end-diastolic flow on
        maternal umbilical artery Doppler where available.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>72 Hours</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shabina Ariff, MBBS,FCPS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Aga Khan University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael J Dibley, BSc(Med), MB BS, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sydney</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Almas Aamir, MSC</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Aga Khan University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sajid B Soofi, MBBS,FCPS</last_name>
    <phone>+922134864798</phone>
    <phone_ext>4798</phone_ext>
    <email>sajid.soofi@aku.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Asghar Ali, MRA ,MBA</last_name>
    <phone>92 213 493 0051</phone>
    <phone_ext>2279</phone_ext>
    <email>asghar.ali@aku.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aga Khan University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karachi</city>
        <state>Sindh</state>
        <zip>74800</zip>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shabina Ariff, FCPS MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>+92 21 34864357</phone>
      <phone_ext>4357</phone_ext>
      <email>Shabina.ariff@aku.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dr. Saajid B Soofi Soofi, FCPS MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>+92 21 99244230</phone>
      <phone_ext>8186</phone_ext>
      <email>Sajid.soofi@aku.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Neeloy A Alam</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William T Mordi</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.DYN.NMRT</url>
    <description>The World Bank Mortality rate ,Neonatal (per,1000 live births) 29/02/2016</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/health</url>
    <description>United.Nations Sustainable development goals</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khan A, Kinney MV, Hazir T, Hafeez A, Wall SN, Ali N, Lawn JE, Badar A, Khan AA, Uzma Q, Bhutta ZA; Pakistan Newborn Change and Future Analysis Group. Newborn survival in Pakistan: a decade of change and future implications. Health Policy Plan. 2012 Jul;27 Suppl 3:iii72-87. doi: 10.1093/heapol/czs047.</citation>
    <PMID>22692418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawn JE, Cousens S, Zupan J; Lancet Neonatal Survival Steering Team. 4 million neonatal deaths: when? Where? Why? Lancet. 2005 Mar 5-11;365(9462):891-900.</citation>
    <PMID>15752534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hug L, Sharrow D, You D. Levels &amp; trends in child mortality: report 2017. Estimates developed by the UN Inter-agency Group for Child Mortality Estimation. 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farnaud S, Evans RW. Lactoferrin--a multifunctional protein with antimicrobial properties. Mol Immunol. 2003 Nov;40(7):395-405. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14568385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson BF, Baker HM, Dodson EJ, Norris GE, Rumball SV, Waters JM, Baker EN. Structure of human lactoferrin at 3.2-A resolution. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1987 Apr;84(7):1769-73.</citation>
    <PMID>3470756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The World Bank. Mortality rate, neonatal (per 1,000 live births) [29/02/2016]. Available from: http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.DYN.NMRT.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kramer MS. Determinants of low birth weight: methodological assessment and meta-analysis. Bull World Health Organ. 1987;65(5):663-737. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3322602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rahman S, Hameed A, Roghani MT, Ullah Z. Multidrug resistant neonatal sepsis in Peshawar, Pakistan. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2002 Jul;87(1):F52-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12091293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morrow AL, Rangel JM. Human milk protection against infectious diarrhea: implications for prevention and clinical care. Semin Pediatr Infect Dis. 2004 Oct;15(4):221-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15494945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Aga Khan University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Shabina Ariff</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bovine Lactoferrin, Neonatal infection, Low Birth Weight</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Birth Weight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enterocolitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enterocolitis, Necrotizing</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neonatal Sepsis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lactoferrin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

