<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00592085</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2007-0111</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00592085</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combined Treatment for Tobacco and Alcohol Use</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combined Treatment for Tobacco and Alcohol Use</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aims are to:

        -  Develop a &quot;Motivational Relapse Prevention Plus Alcohol Risk Reduction&quot; (MRP+) approach
           to simultaneously treating both smoking and &quot;at-risk&quot; alcohol use among smokers
           attempting to quit smoking.

        -  Estimate the effect size for MRP+ relative to Motivational Relapse Prevention without a
           focus on alcohol (MRP) with respect to alcohol at-risk behaviors. The estimated effect
           size will be utilized to help guide sample size estimates for a potential clinical
           trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Participation If you agree to take part in this study, you will come to M. D. Anderson
      and use a computer to complete a series of questionnaires. You will be asked questions about
      your living situation, mood, depression, anxiety, appetite, smoking and alcohol use habits,
      social status, finances, job, physical activity, and support from family and/or friends.
      These questionnaires may take a total of about 1 hour to complete.

      After completing the questionnaires, you will be randomly assigned (as in the toss of a coin)
      to one of two groups. One group will receive counseling (called motivational relapse
      prevention counseling), which will focus on smoking cessation. The other group will also
      receive counseling (called motivational relapse prevention plus alcohol risk reduction
      counseling), which will focus on smoking cessation as well but will also include discussion
      about at-risk alcohol use. Both groups will receive reading materials related to smoking
      cessation. The motivational relapse prevention plus alcohol risk reduction group will also
      receive reading materials related to alcohol use.

      You will receive a total of 6 counseling calls during this study. Your first counseling call
      will be to set up your quit date. You will then have 5 additional counseling calls within the
      12 weeks after your enrollment in the study. The timing of these calls will be determined
      between you and your counselor. Depending on which group you are in, you will be counseled on
      strategies for quitting smoking and/or decreasing alcohol use to help decrease your risk of
      cancer. These calls will take about 20 to 30 minutes each to complete. You will be asked to
      provide contact information for friends and/or relatives. The research staff will contact
      them only if you are unable to be contacted after multiple attempts.

      Final Visit At Week 12, you will be requested to return to M. D. Anderson to complete the
      last computerized series of questionnaires.

      Your counseling calls will be tape recorded so researchers can make sure that correct
      procedures are being followed. Only the study staff will be allowed to listen to these tapes.
      Your identity will be kept secure and confidential. These tapes will be erased when this
      study has ended.

      Study Length Your participation in this study will be over after the evaluation visit at Week
      12.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    No patients registered; study terminated.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>December 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall at-risk drinking status</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>At-risk drinking, defined by National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism, refers to a constellation of alcohol use behaviors that increase risk for physical and psychosocial problems including (a) an average of &gt; 2 alcoholic beverages/day during the past 30 days for men or &gt;1 drink/day for women, OR (b) two or more occasions of consuming &gt; 5 alcoholic beverages during the past 30 days for men or &gt;4 drinks for women, OR (c) driving after consuming &gt;3 drinks in the past 30 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness of certain type of telephone counseling ability to help participants decrease both their smoking and at-risk alcohol use as measured by Smoking Cessation and At-Risk Drinking Evaulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 months for baseline and repeat assessments at 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Effectiveness evaluated using descriptive data from questionnaires to evaluate theoretically- and empirically-based &quot;Motivational Relapse Prevention Plus Alcohol Risk Reduction&quot; (MRP+) approach for simultaneously intervening on both smoking and at risk alcohol use. Evaluation through questionnaire results, smoking cessation and overall at-risk drinking status, a dichotomous variable defined previously.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse Prevention Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Motivational Relapse Counseling: 6 counseling calls over two weeks accompanied by questionnaires</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse Prevention + Alcohol Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Motivational Relapse Prevention Plus Alcohol Risk Reduction Counseling: 6 counseling calls over two weeks for both smoking cessation and at-risk alcohol use accompanied by questionnaires</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will use a computer to complete a series of questionnaires.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse Prevention Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse Prevention + Alcohol Counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motivational Relapse Prevention Counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Total of 6 counseling calls for Smoking Relapse: First counseling call will be to set up your quit date; then 5 additional counseling calls within 12 weeks after enrollment, each 20 to 30 minutes to complete.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse Prevention Counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Relapse Plus Alcohol Risk Reduction Counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Total of 6 counseling calls for both Smoking Relapse and Alcohol Risk: First counseling call will be to set up your quit date; then 5 additional counseling calls within 12 weeks after enrollment, each 20 to 30 minutes to complete.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse Prevention + Alcohol Counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current daily smoker who averages 5 or more cigarettes/day.

          -  Exhibit at least one of the following criteria for at-risk drinking: a) an average of
             &gt; or equal to 2 alcoholic beverages/day during the past 30 days for men or &gt; or equal
             to 1 drink/day for women, OR b) two or more occasions of consuming &gt; or equal to 5
             alcoholic beverages during the past 30 days for men or &gt; or equal to 4 drinks for
             women, OR c) driving after consuming &gt; or equal to 3 drinks in the past 30 days,

          -  Age 18 or above

          -  Motivated to quit smoking in the next 30 days

          -  Viable (working) telephone number and home address

          -  No other household member enrolled in this protocol

          -  Score equal to or less than 15 on the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test
             (AUDIT) measure.

          -  Must be able to speak English.

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Wetter, PHD, MS, BA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>MD Anderson Cancer Center website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 27, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 20, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tobacco Use</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol Use</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking Cessation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

