<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00473174</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HYCCRA-2006/01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Eudract-2006-006107-37</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00473174</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Awakening Versus Bedtime Dosing of Ramipril in Subjects With Essential Hypertension</brief_title>
  <acronym>HYCCRA</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Open Label, Blinded-endpoint Study to Compare Awakening Versus Bedtime Administration of 5-10 mg Ramipril in Terms of Systolic Blood Pressure Lowering Determined by ABPM in Subjects With Mild-to-moderate Essential</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Vigo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>King Pharmaceuticals is now a wholly owned subsidiary of Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Vigo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This prospective chronotherapy trial will investigate the potential differing efficacy of
      ramipril in doses from 5 to 10 mg/day when administered, as a monotherapy either upon
      awakening from nighttime sleep or at bedtime, to diurnally active patients with grade 1 or 2
      essential hypertension, who will be evaluated by 48-hour ABPM before and after pharmacologic
      intervention. The benefits from this trial may be extremely important, taking into account

        1. the high prevalence of non-dipping among patients with essential hypertension

        2. the need for a proper 24-hour BP control with particular emphasis on the regulation of
           nighttime resting BP mean

        3. the lacking information on the administration-time dependent effects on BP of ramipril,
           a widely used ACEI in doses of 5-10 mg/day.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Several attributes of the cardiovascular system, including blood pressure (BP) and heart rate
      (HR), are characterized by predictable changes during the 24 hours for the most part in
      synchrony with the rest-activity cycle. During the past two decades specific features of the
      24-hour BP pattern have been assessed as potential sources of injury to target tissues and as
      triggers of cardiac and cerebrovascular events in hypertensive patients. A growing number of
      studies indicate the reduction of the normal 10 to 20% sleep-time BP decline (non-dipper
      pattern) is associated with elevated risk of end-organ injury, particularly to the heart
      (left ventricular hypertrophy and myocardial infarct), brain (stoke) and kidney (albuminuria
      and progression to end-stage renal failure). Accordingly, there is growing interest in how to
      tailor the treatment of hypertensive patients according to their circadian BP pattern.

      Clinical studies demonstrated a different effect of the ACEIs benazepril, enalapril,
      perindopril, quinapril, spirapril, and trandolapril when dosed in the morning versus the
      evening. A small trial on 33 patients with essential hypertension showed that a low dose of
      2.5 mg/day ramipril more effectively reduced daytime BP when it was administered in the
      morning and more effectively reduced nighttime BP when it was administered in the evening. In
      the HOPE (Heart Outcomes Prevention Evaluation) study patients in the active treatment group
      received ramipril at bedtime. Results from a small substudy, in which hypertensive patients
      were evaluated with 24-hour ambulatory BP monitoring (ABPM), showed a marked BP reduction
      particularly during nighttime sleep, thereby reducing the prevalence of non-dippers. The
      authors concluded that the effects on cardiovascular morbidity and mortality seen with
      ramipril in the HOPE study may relate to its improved effect (i.e., increase in the
      diurnal/nocturnal BP ratio) on the non-dipping BP patterns.

      In keeping with the documented administration-time dependent effects on BP regulation of
      other ACEI, this prospective chronotherapy trial will investigate the potential differing
      efficacy of ramipril in doses from 5 to 10 mg/day when administered, as a monotherapy either
      upon awakening from nighttime sleep or at bedtime, to diurnally active patients with grade 1
      or 2 essential hypertension, who will be evaluated by 48-hour ABPM before and after
      pharmacologic intervention. The benefits from this trial may be extremely important, taking
      into account 1) the high prevalence of non-dipping among patients with essential
      hypertension, 2) the need for a proper 24-hour BP control with particular emphasis on the
      regulation of nighttime resting BP mean, and 3) the lacking information on the
      administration-time dependent effects on BP of ramipril, a widely used ACEI in doses of 5-10
      mg/day.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate the efficacy of bedtime administration of ramipril in subjects with essential hypertension by testing the hypothesis of superior nocturnal SBP lowering in ABPM measurements compared with ramipril administered on awakening</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate that ramipril at bedtime is more effective than ramipril upon awakening in terms of nocturnal DBP lowering in ABPM</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate that ramipril at bedtime is not inferior to ramipril upon awakening in terms of 24-hour SBP/DBP lowering in ABPM</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate that ramipril at bedtime is more effective than ramipril upon awakening in terms of increasing the diurnal/nocturnal SBP and DBP ratio determined by ABPM</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate that ramipril at bedtime offers a similar safety profile than ramipril upon awakening</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate that compliance with ramipril at bedtime is similar to compliance of ramipril upon awakening</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ramipril on awakening</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ramipril at bedtime</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ramipril</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosing on awakening versus bedtime</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ambulatory blood pressure monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood pressure measured at 20-min intervals from 07:00 to 23:00 hours and at 30-min intervals at night for 48 consecutive hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Essential hypertension

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe hypertension.

          -  Secondary hypertension.

          -  Grade III/IV hypertensive retinopathy.

          -  Type 1 diabetes.

          -  Cerebrovascular or cardiovascular event during the last 12 months prior to inclusion.

          -  Pregnant or lactating females.

          -  History of malignancy within the past five years.

          -  Shift workers.

          -  Obstructive sleep apnea.

          -  Use of disallowed concomitant medication.

          -  Intolerant to ABPM.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ramon C Hermida, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Vigo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico Universitario de Santiago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago de Compostela</city>
        <zip>15701</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hermida RC, Ayala DE. Chronotherapy with the angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor ramipril in essential hypertension: improved blood pressure control with bedtime dosing. Hypertension. 2009 Jul;54(1):40-6. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.109.130203. Epub 2009 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19433778</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 14, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 2, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Ramon C. Hermida</name_title>
    <organization>University of Vigo</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ramipril</keyword>
  <keyword>Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Circadian</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-dipper</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ramipril</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

