<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00470977</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Protocol: FVF4140S</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00470977</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Exudative and Vasogenic Chorioretinal Diseases Including Variants of AMD and Other CNV Related Maculopathy</brief_title>
  <acronym>FVF4140S</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment of Exudative and Vasogenic Chorioretinal Diseases Including Variants of AMD and Other CNV Related Maculopathy With Intravitreal Injection of Lucentis (Ranibizumab Injection)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Manhattan Eye, Ear &amp; Throat Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Manhattan Eye, Ear &amp; Throat Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of intravitreal
      injections of ranibizumab in the treatment of AMD variants and other choroidal
      neovascularization (CNV) related conditions (Coats' disease, idiopathic perifoveal
      telangiectasia, retinal angiomatous proliferation, polypoidal vasculopathy, pseudoxanthoma
      elasticum, pathological myopia, multi-focal choroiditis, rubeosis iridis) using the incidence
      and severity of adverse events.

      Limited forms of treatment are available that limit the loss of visual acuity. However, the
      patients may not have any substantial improvement in acuity or function. Therefore there
      remains a significant unmet need for therapeutic options managing the neovascularization and
      its consequences.

      Lucentis (ranibizumab) injection will be considered as an attempt to control the growth of
      the abnormal vessels because of evidence suggesting that angiogenic factors, such as vascular
      endothelial growth factor (VEGF), play a role in the pathogenesis of neovascular non-AMD
      conditions.

      The rationale for the study design is as follows:

      A 0.5 mg dose of Lucentis (ranibizumab), a commercially available preparation that is Food
      and Drug Administration (FDA) approved and labeled for intravitreal injection use for
      neovascular (wet) age-related macular degeneration will be used.

      In AMD variants and other CNV related conditions, vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)
      plays a role in the pathogenesis as in neovascular AMD.

      Intravitreal injection of ranibizumab delivers maximal concentration of the antibody fragment
      to the vitreous cavity with minimal systemic exposure. The dosing schedule, based on
      considerations of the half-life and the clinical response in patients with neovascularization
      suggests that a 1-month interval is optimal.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of intravitreal injections of ranibizumab in the treatment of non-AMD variants and other CNV related conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in central retinal thickness as measured by OCT at month 12 compared to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in leakage area seen during fluorescein angiography at month 12 as compared with baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of additional injections required following the initial 3 injections</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Coats' Disease</condition>
  <condition>Idiopathic Retinal Telangiectasia</condition>
  <condition>Retinal Angiomatous Proliferation</condition>
  <condition>Polypoidal Choroidal Vasculopathy</condition>
  <condition>Pseudoxanthoma Elasticum</condition>
  <condition>Pathological Myopia</condition>
  <condition>Multi-focal Choroiditis</condition>
  <condition>Rubeosis Iridis</condition>
  <condition>Von Hippel Lindau Disease</condition>
  <condition>BEST VITELLIFORM MACULAR DYSTROPHY, MULTIFOCAL (Disorder)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(Ranibizumab) Lucentis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>(Ranibizumab)Lucentis 0.5%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ranibizumab injection (0.5 mg)</intervention_name>
    <description>ranibizumab 10mg mg/ml. , 0.3ml/vial, 0.05 ml./injection intravitreally for 3months then prn for the next 21 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>(Ranibizumab) Lucentis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lucentis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects will be eligible if the following criteria are met:

          1. Ability to provide written informed consent and comply with study assessments for the
             full duration of the study

          2. Age &gt; 18 years

          3. Clinical diagnosis of the following conditions: Coats' disease, idiopathic perifoveal
             telangiectasia, retinal angiomatous proliferation, polypoidal vasculopathy,
             pseudoxanthoma elasticum, pathological myopia, multi-focal choroiditis, rubeosis
             iridis.

          4. Visual acuity of 20/40 to 20/320 in the study eye on the ETDRS visual acuity chart.

          5. Media clarity, pupillary dilation and patient cooperation sufficient to allow OCT
             testing and retinal photography

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from this study:

          1. Any other condition that the investigator believes would pose a significant hazard to
             the subject if the investigational therapy is initiated

          2. Participation in another simultaneous medical investigation or trial

          3. Patient with significantly compromised visual acuity in the study eye due to
             concomitant ocular conditions.

          4. Patients who have undergone intraocular surgery within the last 2 months.

          5. Patient participating in any other investigational drug study.

          6. Use of an investigational drug or treatment related or unrelated to the patient's
             condition within 30 days prior to receipt of study medication (verteporfin,
             pegaptanib, or other AMD therapy in the study eye)

          7. Patient treated with systemic anti-VEGF or pro-VEGF agents within 3 months before
             enrollment.

          8. Previous treatment (in either eye) with intravitreal or intravenously administered
             Avastin (bevacizumab).

          9. Inability to obtain photographs to document CNV (including difficulty with venous
             access).

         10. Patient with a known adverse reaction to fluorescein dye.

         11. Patient has a history of any medical condition which would preclude scheduled visits
             or completion of the study.

         12. Patient has had insertion of scleral buckle in the study eye

         13. Patient has received radiation treatment.

         14. Aphakia or absence of the posterior capsule in the study eye. Previous violation of
             the posterior capsule in the study eye is also excluded unless as a result of yttrium
             aluminum garnet (YAG) posterior capsulotomy in association with posterior chamber lens
             implantation.

         15. Pregnancy (positive pregnancy test) or lactation.

         16. Premenopausal women not using adequate contraception. The following are considered
             effective means of contraception: surgical sterilization or use of oral
             contraceptives, barrier contraception with either a condom or diaphragm in conjunction
             with spermicidal gel, an intrauterine device (IUD), or contraceptive hormone implant
             or patch.

         17. History of glaucoma filtering surgery in the study eye.

         18. Concurrent use of more than two therapies for glaucoma.

         19. Uncontrolled glaucoma in the study eye (defined as intraocular pressure &gt; 30 mm Hg
             despite treatment with anti-glaucoma medication)

         20. Inability to comply with study or follow-up procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lawrence A. Yannuzzi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>LuEsther T. Mertz Retinal Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lenox Hill Hospital/Manhattan Eye Ear and Throat Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lenox Hill Hospital/Manhattan Eye, Ear &amp; Throat Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 8, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 25, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Manhattan Eye, Ear &amp; Throat Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Lawrence A. Yannuzzi, M.D.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Telangiectasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Von Hippel-Lindau Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pseudoxanthoma Elasticum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myopia, Degenerative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Choroiditis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitelliform Macular Dystrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Telangiectasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ranibizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

