<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02119767</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CE002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02119767</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Detect Biomarker Gradients in Coronary Arteries Using the Liquid Biopsy System</brief_title>
  <acronym>CS1</acronym>
  <official_title>Study to Detect Biomarker Gradients in Coronary Arteries Using the Liquid Biopsy System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PlaqueTec Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Papworth Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PlaqueTec Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Liquid Biopsy System (LBS) is a new catheter (thin tube) designed for sampling blood
      directly from coronary arteries. These arteries supply blood to muscles of the heart and can
      become blocked by 'plaques' leading to chest pain (angina) and heart attacks. Recent research
      has shown that development of ' plaques' inside coronary arteries is controlled by chemicals
      (biomarkers) released into the blood from damaged areas of the artery wall. The LBS is
      designed to collect blood samples at the exact site of plaque formation. By testing these
      blood samples for biomarkers of plaque formation, it is hoped that new diagnostic tests and
      treatments for heart disease may be developed. The proposed investigation is use the LBS in
      humans to detect these biomarkers. The safety of the LBS has already been demonstrated in
      both human and animal studies. The study will enroll 70 patients with coronary artery disease
      who are undergoing routine percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI). PCI is a procedure used
      to open up a blocked coronary artery. It uses a catheter on the end of which is a special
      balloon that is inflated inside the blocked artery to open up the vessel and restore blood
      flow. A small metal spring (stent) is usually inserted to keep the blood vessel open. This
      study will test if the LBS device, when used just prior to a PCI procedure, can detect
      biomarkers released by diseased coronary arteries. The study will also determine if the
      presence of these biomarkers is linked to the long term health of the patient. The study will
      take place at Papworth Hospital, over a period of approximately 8 months (including telephone
      based patient followup calls 30 days, 6 months, 1, 2 and 3 years after the procedure to
      determine patient health).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this Clinical Investigation is to use the PlaqueTec Liquid Biopsy System (LBS)
      to determine which biomarkers detected locally within the coronary artery can give
      information on the state of atherosclerotic disease. The LBS is a novel CE-marked class III
      coronary catheter designed for sampling blood directly from the coronary arteries. The LBS is
      unique in that it can capture &quot;gradients&quot; of biological molecules within the coronary artery
      and by analysing the samples it collects it can unequivocally identify which biomarkers have
      been locally released within the coronary artery. The samples can then be analysed for a
      variety of biomarkers using standard analytical techniques. Cardiologists should find this of
      great benefit as recent studies have shown that coronary artery disease is controlled and
      directed by the release of specific biological molecules into the blood from diseased areas
      of the coronary arteries. The safety and performance of the LBS has been proved previously in
      a recent First In Man study. The Clinical Investigation study will enroll 70 patients and
      will be observational in nature. The study is designed to use the device in its intended
      application (i.e. as an adjunct to a PCI procedure, such as the deployment of a stent) and to
      collect biomarker gradients released locally within the coronary artery. It will then follow
      up on the health status of the patients and see if the release of certain biomarkers is
      associated with particular clinical outcomes. The device will be used to look for locally
      released biomarkers at two different stages of the deployment of a stent, i.e. before and
      after its deployment. The first stage is prior to the deployment of the stent and the LBS
      will collect blood samples to look for the release of &quot;natural&quot; biomarkers gradients, i.e.
      those biomarkers that are naturally released during the progression and development of
      diseased regions within the artery. The second stage is to use the LBS to collect blood
      samples across a diseased artery that has just be perturbed (by &quot;pre-ballooning&quot;, a procedure
      carried out just prior to stent insertion) and will looked for &quot;induced&quot; biomarker gradients,
      i.e. those molecules that are released by a diseased plaque when it ruptures. The insights
      gained by collecting biomarker gradients at these two stages will give very important
      information on what causes a region of artery to become diseased and how diseased portions of
      the artery affect the blood and cause heart attacks. The samples that are collected by the
      LBS in the above clinical settings will be analysed for a series of biomarker gradients
      previously selected by PlaqueTec' s Scientific Advisory Panel (SAP) for their potential role
      in causing atherosclerosis. The data collected by the LBS will be for research only and will
      not be used to affect the patient treatment. In summary, the LBS study will deliver
      completely new insights into coronary artery disease and will significantly increase the
      understanding of this hugely significant disease. Patients who need an elective percutaneous
      transluminal interventional coronary procedure will be considered for this study. Patients
      requiring emergency interventional procedures will be excluded. The study duration is
      estimated to be about 8 months with a three year follow up period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Local release of biomarkers by diseased regions of the coronary artery</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>That biomarkers are released locally by diseased regions of the coronary artery (either naturally or during pre-ballooning for stenting) of patients with cardiovascular disease (CVD) and detectable using the LBS and associated assays</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome of detected coronary gradients (by telephone for all patients)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>This will test whether the local release of biomarkers detected by the LBS has an association with clinical outcome. Clinical outcome will be assessed for all patients (between 40 and 70 patients will be included in this study) by telephone follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Natural gradients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients requiring an elective PCI who present with either non-ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (NSTEMI) or chronic stable angina who will have natural gradients sampled using the LBS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Induced gradients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients requiring an elective PCI who present with either non-ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (NSTEMI) or chronic stable angina who will have induced gradients sampled using the LBS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be recruited at secondary care cardiology facilities. All subjects who need a
        percutaneous transluminal interventional coronary procedure (excluding those with an ST
        elevation myocardial infarction) will be considered for this study.

        Potential participants will be identified from pre-admission clinic lists and screened for
        suitability by members of the clinical team. Eligible patients will be approached for
        participation in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects that are candidates for percutaneous transluminal interventional coronary
             procedures

          2. Subjects undergoing elective PCI

          3. Subjects presenting for PCI after NSTEMI

          4. Subjects who have been preloaded with dual antiplatelet therapy (aspirin and
             clopidogrel (or prasugrel or ticagrelor)) as per usual local PCI practice.

          5. Subjects who are willing and able to sign an informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects for whom the LBS is contra-indicated:

               1. The LBS is contraindicated for use in severely stenosed, excessively tortuous or
                  calcified coronary vessels.

               2. The LBS is contraindicated in coronary vessels with a reference diameter of less
                  than 2.5 mm.

               3. The LBS is contraindicated for use in regions of coronary vessels that contain a
                  stent.

               4. The LBS is contraindicated for use in the carotid arteries, cerebral vessels or
                  any of their side branches.

               5. The LBS is contraindicated for use with patients in whom anticoagulant or
                  antiplatelet therapy is contraindicated, or have uncorrected bleeding disorders
                  or an allergy to heparin.

               6. Use of the LBS is contraindicated in patients with ongoing sepsis that is
                  considered relevant to cardiac catheterization.

               7. The LBS is contraindicated for use in the acute phase of an ST Segment Elevation
                  Myocardial Infarction, in patients with severe hemodynamic instability or shock.

               8. The LBS is contraindicated for use in the presence of angiographic evidence of
                  intracoronary thrombus.

          2. Subjects who are unwilling or unable to sign an informed consent

          3. Subjects undergoing immunosuppressive therapies

          4. Severe left ventricular dysfunction (left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;30%)

          5. Cardiogenic shock

          6. PCI target in left main stem

          7. PCI target lesion with low pre-procedure chance of success or high pre-procedure risk
             of complication (e.g. chronic total occlusion, thrombus load)

          8. Subjects &lt;18 years (there is no upper age limit but there is a requirement that
             patients are considered to be &quot;fit&quot; enough by the operating cardiologist for the LBS
             procedure to not cause significant additional risk)

          9. Pregnancy

         10. Contraindication to dual antiplatelet therapy or inability to take dual antiplatelet
             therapy for at least 4 weeks post-procedure

         11. Serum creatinine above 125 µmol/L.(i.e. the upper limit for normal)

         12. Subjects on warfarin at the time of procedure

         13. Subjects with active chronic inflammatory disease, e.g. systemic lupus erythematosus,
             rheumatoid arthritis, seropositive arthropathies and known seropositivity to HIV,
             Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nick West, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Papworth Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Papworth Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Papworth Everard</city>
        <state>Cambridgeshire</state>
        <zip>PE28 9QT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 22, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

