<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02110472</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLP-12-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02110472</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation of the Presbia Flexivue Microlens™</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective, Non-randomized, Unmasked, Multicenter Clinical Investigation of the Presbia Flexivue Microlens™ for the Improvement of Near Vision in Emmetropic Presbyopes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PresbiBio, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PresbiBio, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Presbia Flexivue Microlens is a corneal inlay.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Presbyopia is a multifactorial physiological aging mechanism that leads to a progressive
      functional loss of near vision. In addition to the use of reading glasses for presbyopia, a
      wide variety of procedures have been investigated by ophthalmologists to correct this
      refractive error. Cornea laser surgery with multifocal patterns or monovision approaches were
      developed including LASIK, PresbyLASIK, photorefractive keratectomy (PRK), laser epithelial
      keratomileusis (LASEK), thin-flap femto-LASIK or sub-Bowman's keratomileusis (SBK).
      Conductive keratoplasty (CK), clear lens extraction or cataract surgery using multifocal,
      pseudo-accommodative intraocular lenses (IOLs) or monovision monofocal IOLs are also some of
      the techniques that have been used for the treatment of presbyopia.

      Corneal laser surgery and CK are minimally invasive methods, but they provoke irreversible
      changes of the corneal anatomy, whereas scleral surgery and clear lens extraction are more
      invasive techniques. The necessity to develop a minimally invasive, reversible, and safe
      surgical technique with an easy learning curve for patients between 45 and 60 years, led to
      the development of refractive intracorneal lenses (inlays) (such as the AcuFocus, Inc.
      KAMRA™, ReVision Optics® PresbyLens®, and the Presbia Flexivue Microlens™) placed inside the
      corneal stroma. These inlays are refractive lenses that have a central zone free of
      refractive power and a peripheral zone with a standard positive refractive power. These
      inlays are inserted inside the corneal stroma of the non-dominant eye, generally offering two
      different focal points, one for the far vision and a different for the near vision
      respectively. The pocket of the cornea is created using a laser (details to be provided later
      in this protocol).

      The Presbia Flexivue Microlens is intended to improve near vision and decrease dependence on
      reading glasses in presbyopic adults who are tolerant of monovision (as evaluated by
      participation in a monovision tolerance trial (5 to 7 days minimum)), who require a reading
      add of +1.50 D to +3.50 D, who have MRSE between +1.00 D and 0.75 D with no more than 0.75 D
      of refractive cylinder, and who have stable MRSE within 0.50 D over the past 12 months.

      Objective: The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of
      the Presbia Flexivue Microlens™ (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;Microlens&quot;) implanted in
      presbyopes for improvement of near vision.

      Investigational Plan: This is a prospective, non-randomized, unmasked, multicenter clinical
      investigation. A total of 412 subjects at up to 11 investigational sites in the United States
      will undergo insertion of the Microlens in non-dominant eyes, and will be followed through 36
      months postoperative (assuming an estimated 10% per year lost to follow-up). Each site will
      contribute a targeted minimum of 20 treated subjects, but no more than 25% of the total
      subjects treated in the study. Data on a minimum of 300 subjects with 24 month data will be
      submitted as part of the Premarket Approval; all subjects will be followed through 36 months
      postoperative. Subjects from outside the United States will not be enrolled in this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Uncorrected near visual acuity - operated eyes</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Uncorrected near visual acuity at 40 cm of 20/40 or better</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uncorrected near visual acuity - operated eyes</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>- Number of lines of improvement uncorrected near visual acuity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">412</enrollment>
  <condition>Presbyopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Presbia Flexivue Microlens Corneal Inlay</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Presbia Flexivue Microlens implanted in corneal pocket in nondominant eye</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Corneal inlay</intervention_name>
    <description>Presbia Flexivue Microlens implantation in corneal pocket created in nondominant eyes of emmetropic presbyopes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Presbia Flexivue Microlens Corneal Inlay</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Presbia Flexivue Microlens</other_name>
    <other_name>Presbia Microlens</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must be emmetropes with presbyopia, between ≥ 45 years and ≤ 60 years of age
             at time of eligibility visit.

          -  Subjects must need a reading add of +1.50 D to +3.50 D.

          -  Subjects must have uncorrected near visual acuity of 20/50 or worse.

          -  Subjects must have near visual acuity correctable to 20/20 or better in each eye.

          -  Subjects must have distance visual acuity correctable to 20/25 or better in each eye.

          -  Subjects must have a preoperative spherical equivalent of +1.00 D to -0.75 D with no
             more than 0.75 D of refractive cylinder as determined by cycloplegic refraction in
             each eye.

          -  Subjects must have a photopic pupil size of &gt; 1.6 mm in the eye to be implanted.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects in whom the non-dominant eye cannot be determined using one of the methods
             identified in the test of ocular dominance.

          -  Subjects who do not complete the monovision tolerance trial (minimum of 5 to 7 days).

          -  Subjects who report that they were not completely satisfied with their vision during
             the monovision tolerance trial.

          -  Subjects who report that they experienced debilitating or significant visual symptoms
             such as halos, glare, double vision, etc. during the monovision tolerance trial.

          -  Subjects with a difference of ≥ 1.00 D between the spherical equivalent manifest
             refraction and the spherical equivalent cycloplegic refraction.

          -  Subject with a preferred near working distance of &lt; 35 cm or &gt; 45 cm.

          -  Subjects with corneal thickness &lt; 500 microns in the eye to be implanted.

          -  Subjects with clinically significant anterior segment pathology, including cataracts,
             in either eye.

          -  Subjects with residual, recurrent, active ocular or uncontrolled eyelid disease or any
             progressive corneal abnormalities (including endothelial dystrophy, guttata in the
             central cornea, etc.) in the eye to be treated.

          -  Subjects with keratoconus (or keratoconus suspect), amblyopia, recurrent erosion
             syndrome or corneal dystrophy in the eye to be treated.

          -  Subjects with a history of chronic dry eye not controlled on therapy or with
             superficial punctuate keratitis (SPK) grade &gt; II (i.e., greater than mild) based on
             Oxford Grading Scale in the eye to be treated.

          -  Subjects with abnormal corneal mires on topography maps of the eye to be treated.

          -  Subjects who require canthotomy to generate a corneal tunnel in the eye to be treated.

          -  Subjects with progressive retinal pathology with a reasonable chance of causing a
             reduction in BCVA from preoperative in the eye to be treated.

          -  Subjects who have undergone previous intraocular or corneal surgery including cataract
             and refractive surgery (e.g., LASIK surgery) in either eye.

          -  Subjects using ophthalmic medication(s) other than artificial tears for treatment of
             ocular pathology.

          -  Subjects with a history of autoimmune disease, connective tissue disease, or
             clinically significant atopic syndrome.

          -  Subjects with a history of herpes zoster or herpes simplex keratitis.

          -  Subjects with a history of steroid-responsive rise in intraocular pressure (IOP), or a
             preoperative IOP &gt; 21 mmHg or glaucoma.

          -  Subjects with distorted, non-reactive, or decentered pupils.

          -  Subjects taking medication for the control of diabetes.

          -  Subjects on chronic systemic or topical corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive
             therapy that may affect wound healing, and any immuno-compromised subjects (use of
             intranasal steroids for seasonal allergies are acceptable).

          -  Subjects using systemic medications (e.g., amiodarone) or medications with significant
             ocular side effects.

          -  Subjects who are pregnant, or are considering becoming pregnant during the time of the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert K Maloney, MD, MA</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Maloney Vision Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mickey Gordon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Gordon-Weiss-Schanzlin Vision Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assil Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beverly Hills</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gordon-Weiss-Schanzlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maloney Vision Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Eye and Laser Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Sight</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sarasota</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kraft Eye Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60602</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Physicians Protocol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greensboro</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27410</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Eye Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brecksville</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44141</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Berkeley Eye and Laser Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hoopes Vision, Laser Correction Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Draper</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84020</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fairfax</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22031</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.TossYourReaders.com</url>
    <description>Website dedicated to patient recruitment (approved by WIRB on 4/3/2014).</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 8, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 10, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Emmetropic presbyopes</keyword>
  <keyword>Presbyopic</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Presbyopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

