<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02118870</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>9207</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-005571-40</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>14.0102</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02118870</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Short-term Dual Anti Platelet Therapy in Patients With ACS Treated With the COMBO Dual-therapy Stent</brief_title>
  <acronym>REDUCE</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Evaluation of Short-term DUal Anti Platelet Therapy in Patients With Acute Coronary Syndrome Treated With the COMBO Dual-therapy stEnt</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Diagram B.V.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Diagram B.V.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      The optimal duration of dual antiplatelet therapy in ACS patients treated with DES is still
      under debate. This is especially true for STEMI patients in the era of new anticoagulants and
      antiplatelet agents. Yet, the potential benefits of longterm dual antiplatelet therapy in
      avoiding thrombotic complications may be clearly counterbalanced by a higher risk of major
      bleeding complications. In particular, the COMBO dual therapy stent, being associated with
      early re-endothelization, may allow for a reduction of the duration of DAPT (dual anti
      plateled therapy) without increasing the thrombotic risk, while reducing the risk of severe
      bleeding complications.

      Study Objective:

      Aim of the current study is to demonstrate a non-inferiority of a strategy of short-term DAPT
      (90 days) as compared to standard 360 days DAPT in ACS patients treated with Combo stent.

      Study Design:

      This study is a prospective, multicenter, randomized, investigator-initiated study designed
      to enroll 1500 patients with ACS receiving a COMBO dual-therapy stent who will be randomized
      1:1 to either short term (90 days) or to standard (360 days) DAPT. Patients will be
      randomized within hospitalization (before discharge in case additional revascularization is
      deemed necessary and performed during hospitalization). Clinical visit is scheduled at 90,
      and 360 days, whereas a telephone contact will be performed at 180 and 720 days.

      Patient Population:

      The study population will consist of up to 1500 ACS patients (male and female) older than 18
      years amenable to percutaneous treatment and treated with a COMBO stent. Subjects must meet
      all of the eligibility criteria and provide written informed consent.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study sites:

      Up to 40 investigational sites in Europe and Asia

      Patients follow-up:

      Follow-up (clinic) visits are scheduled at 90 and 360 days, whereas a telephone contact will
      be performed at 180 and 720 days. Patients randomized to short-term DAPT will continue on
      monotherapy with ASA after 90 days unless contraindicated.

      Antiplatelet therapy:

      Subjects will be treated with Aspirin and P2Y12 inhibitor. Prasugrel (10 mg/day) or
      Ticagrelor (180 mg/day) are strongly recommended as compared to Clopidogrel (75 mg/day)).
      Long term DAPT arm: will continue DAPT with P2Y12 inhibitors and ASA up to 360 days, after
      which patients will continue on monotherapy with ASA only, unless contraindications for ASA
      emerge Short term DAPT arm: will continue DAPT with P2Y12 inhibitors and ASA up to 90 days,
      after which patients will continue.

      Timelines:

      First Enrollment: June 2014 Last Enrollment: May 2016 One year Follow-up: May 2018 Two year
      Follow-up: May 2019
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 10, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of all cause mortality, Myocardial Infarction (MI), ST, stroke, taret vessel revascularization (TVR) and bleeding (BARC II, III and V) at 360 days</measure>
    <time_frame>At 360 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding (BARC II, III, V) at 360 days</measure>
    <time_frame>360 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality, MI, ST, stroke, TVR, bleeding (BARC II, III, V) at 360 and 720 days</measure>
    <time_frame>720 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality, MI, ST, stroke and TVR at 360 and 720 days</measure>
    <time_frame>360 and 720 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality at 360 and 720 days</measure>
    <time_frame>360 and 720 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac Mortality at 360 and 720 days</measure>
    <time_frame>360 and 720 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Any MI at 360 and 720 days</measure>
    <time_frame>360 and 720 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ST at 360 and 720 days</measure>
    <time_frame>360 and 720 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Repeat revascularization at 360 and 720 days</measure>
    <time_frame>360 and 720 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to event as defined by the occurrence of one of the following: all cause mortality, MI, ST, stroke, TVR or bleeding (BARC II, III, V) within 360 and 720 days</measure>
    <time_frame>360 and 720 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prespecified landmark analysis of Primary Endpoint (without TVR) from 90 days to 360 days</measure>
    <time_frame>from 90 days to 360 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Coronary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DAPT 360 days</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment 360 days DAPT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DAPT 90 days</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment 90 days DAPT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment 90 days DAPT</intervention_name>
    <description>Short term DAPT arm: will continue DAPT with P2Y12 inhibitors and ASA up to 90 days, after which patients will continue.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DAPT 90 days</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Subjects will be treated with Aspirin and P2Y12 inhibitor. Prasugrel (10</other_name>
    <other_name>mg/day) or Ticagrelor (180 mg/day) are strongly recommended as compared</other_name>
    <other_name>to Clopidogrel (75 mg/day)).</other_name>
    <other_name>Short term DAPT arm: will continue DAPT with P2Y12 inhibitors and ASA up</other_name>
    <other_name>to 90 days, after which patients will continue.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment 360 days DAPT</intervention_name>
    <description>Long term (360 days) DAPT arm: will continue DAPT with P2Y12 inhibitors and ASA up to 360 days, after which patients will continue on monotherapy with ASA only, unless contraindications for ASA emerge</description>
    <arm_group_label>DAPT 360 days</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Subjects will be treated with Aspirin and P2Y12 inhibitor. Prasugrel (10</other_name>
    <other_name>mg/day) or Ticagrelor (180 mg/day) are strongly recommended as compared</other_name>
    <other_name>to Clopidogrel (75 mg/day)).</other_name>
    <other_name>Long term (360 days) DAPT arm: will continue DAPT with P2Y12 inhibitors and ASA up</other_name>
    <other_name>to 360 days, after which patients will continue on monotherapy with ASA</other_name>
    <other_name>only, unless contraindications for ASA emerge</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The patient must be ≥18 years of age

          2. The patient has been diagnosed with STEMI, NSTEMI or UA

          3. The Patient is willing to comply with specified follow-up evaluations

          4. The Patient has been informed of the nature of the study, agrees to its provisions and
             has been provided written informed consent, approved by the appropriate Medical Ethics
             Committee (MEC), Institutional Review Board (IRB), or Human Research Ethics Committee
             (HREC)

          5. Successful COMBO stent implantation (TIMI 3 flow with residual stenosis &lt; 20% based
             visual estimation), with no clinical adverse event during hospitalization (Death, ST,
             stroke, TVR, bleeding (BARC II, III, V))

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients presenting with cardiogenic shock

          2. Patients with recent major bleeding complications or contraindication to DAPT, such
             as:

               1. Hypersensitivity to Aspirin, Clopidogrel, Prasugrel or Ticagrelor

               2. Need for oral anticoagulation

               3. History of bleeding diathesis or known coagulopathy (including heparin-induced
                  thrombocytopenia) or refusal of blood transfusions

               4. History of intracerebral mass, aneurysm, arteriovenous malformation, or
                  hemorrhagic stroke

               5. Stroke or transient ischemic attack within the past 6 months or any permanent
                  residual neurologic defect

               6. Gastrointestinal or genitourinary bleeding within the last 2 months or major
                  surgery within 6 weeks

               7. Recent history or known current platelet count &lt;100 000 cells/mm3 or hemoglobin
                  &lt;10 g/dL

               8. An elective surgical procedure is planned that would necessitate interruption of
                  thienopyridines during the first 12 months post enrollment

          3. Planned need for concomitant cardiac surgery (e.g., valve surgery or resection of
             aortic or left ventricular aneurysm etc.)

          4. Planned intervention of another lesion (target vessel or non-target vessel) after
             index hospital discharge

          5. Any revascularization performed within index hospitalization with other stents than
             COMBO

          6. Potential for non-compliance towards the requirements in the trial protocol
             (especially the medical treatment) or follow-up visits

          7. Patients requiring permanent DAPT due to comorbidities

          8. Patient has received any organ transplant or is on a waiting list for any organ
             transplant

          9. Life expectancy of less than 2 years

         10. Pregnancy or intention to become pregnant during the course of the trial

         11. Any significant medical or mental condition, which in the Investigator's opinion may
             interfere with the patient's optimal participation in the study

         12. Currently participating in another investigational drug or device study

         13. Patients who have been treated with another DES within 9 months prior to the index
             procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>H. Suryapranata, Prof. dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University Medical Center, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>G. de Luca, Prof. dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eastern Piedmont University, Novara, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ACS patients</keyword>
  <keyword>Older than 18 years</keyword>
  <keyword>PCI</keyword>
  <keyword>Combo stent</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clopidogrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prasugrel Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ticagrelor</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

