<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02113891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P101004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02113891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Eculizumab Therapy for Subclinical Antibody-mediated Rejection in Kidney Transplantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>TAMARCIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment of Subclinical Antibody-mediated Acute Rejection in Kidney Transplant Recipients With the Complement Inhibitor Eculizumab.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alexion Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Advances in renal transplantation have increased life-expectancy in patients with end-stage
      kidney disease. Conventional immunosuppressive drugs prevent efficiently early allograft
      losses due to T-cell mediated rejection. However, emerging data suggest that the majority of
      late kidney failures may be attributable to antibody-mediated rejection (AMR), which poorly
      responds to the currently available therapeutics. Complement-fixing donor-specific anti-HLA
      antibodies are associated with the worst outcome in keeping with the well-established role of
      the complement in AMR pathogenesis. Eculizumab, the first licenced complement blocker, has
      been found efficient in reducing the occurrence of AMR lesions in highly sensitized patients.
      A few reports also suggest that complement blockade may be of great value as salvage therapy
      for graft-threatening severe AMR. However, no information is available in the literature
      about the interest of complement blockade in curbing the progression of subclinical acute AMR
      to chronic AMR.

      The purpose of this study is to determine whether complement blockade with eculizumab is
      effective and safe in the treatment of subclinical AMR in sensitized kidney transplant
      recipients.

      Despite appropriate therapies, up to 75% of patients having received a renal transplant with
      preformed donor-specific antibody display subclinical AMR on their 3-month protocol biopsy.
      Subclinical AMR is defined by histological lesions of AMR concomitant with stable graft
      function. Moreover, the extent of these lesions at 3 month post-transplant correlates with
      the occurrence of irreversible scars and chonic antibody-mediated rejection on the 12-month
      biopsy.

      This study aims to explore the efficacy and safety of eculizumab in patients exhibiting
      subclinical AMR on their 3 month-post-transplant biopsy, to reduce or even normalize
      microcirculation inflammation, and to prevent chronic rejection (transplant glomerulopathy)
      on the 12 month-screening biopsy. Eculizumab-treated patients will be compared with
      historical controls, matched for the lesions on the 3 month biopsy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Advance in renal transplantation for the treatment of patients with end-stage kidney failure
      have led to significant improvements in patient survival. T-cell directed immunotherapeutic
      agents are capable of preventing early allograft loss and represent the cornerstone of
      current maintenance immunosuppressive regimens. However, recent studies have pointed out that
      the majority (63%) of late kidney failures could be attributable to antibody-mediated
      rejection. Microcirculation inflammation (poly and mononuclear cells within glomerular and
      peritubular capillaries) correlates best with alloantibody-induced endothelial damages and
      complement-fixing anti-HLA antibodies, predicts evolution toward chronic antibody mediated
      rejection (transplant glomerulopathy), and is associated with a poor outcome.
      Microcirculation inflammation, the hallmark lesions of AMR, are frequently observed (75%) on
      screening biopsies performed in sensitized patients having received a renal transplant across
      a positive crossmatch due to preformed DSA, despite intensive prophylactic therapy (including
      polyclonal immunoglobulin, plasma exchanges and rituximab).

      Altogether these findings underscore the need for innovative treatment to better control the
      humoral arm of chronic rejection in patients with donor-specific anti-HLA antibodies.
      Short-term eculizumab treatment might be a promising avenue. Complement blockade with
      eculizumab has been found efficient in reducing the occurrence of AMR lesions in highly
      sensitized patients. A few reports also suggest that complement blockade may be of great
      value as salvage therapy for graft-threatening severe AMR. However, no information is
      available in the literature about the efficacy of complement blockade in curbing the
      progression of subclinical AMR to chronic AMR.

      The primary objectives of this study are:

      • To determine the effectiveness of eculizumab in reducing durably alloantibody-induced
      microcirculation inflammation and preventing chronic microcirculation damages on 12-month
      screening biopsies.

      The secondary objectives of this study are:

        -  To assess the effect of eculizumab on serum creatinine levels, amount of proteinuria,
           and measured and estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (mGFR) between 3 and 12 months
           post-transplant.

        -  To determine the effectiveness of eculizumab in hampering the appearance of interstitial
           fibrosis and tubular atrophy (IF/TA), and dampening down alloantibody-induced
           accelerated arteriosclerosis on 1-year-post-transplant biopsy.

        -  Incidence of biopsy-proven antibody-mediated acute rejection (rise of creatinine value
           higher than 20% above the baseline value).

        -  To monitor DSA levels at 3, 6 and 12 months post-transplant with solid-phase assay
           (Luminex).

        -  To assess vital signs (such as systolic, diastolic blood pressure, heart rate, weight,
           temperature) and laboratory parameters at every eculizumab administration.

        -  To collect safety data on infections, cardiovascular events, and malignancies

        -  To monitor endothelial, platelet and leukocyte microparticles as well as endothelial
           cell progenitors

        -  To quantify the number of endothelial and NK expressed genes that correlate with AMR

      This is an open-label exploratory study which evaluates eculizumab administration in
      sensitized patients with subclinical antibody-mediated rejection at 3 month-post-transplant.
      Ten patients fulfilling inclusion/exclusion criteria will be enrolled into the study and
      compared with 20 historical controls matched for the sensitization and histological lesions
      at 3 months. The patients enrolled in this study will be given eculizumab from 3 to 12 month
      post-transplant, according to the standard protocol in adults heavier than 40 kg (900 mg
      weekly for 4 weeks, 1200 mg for the fifth infusion and 1200 mg every other week thereafter).

      Clinical and laboratory evaluations including vital signs and safety laboratory values will
      be monitored at predetermined time points.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    disengagement of the sponsor Alexion Pharmaceuticals
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microcirculation inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>12-month screening biopsies</time_frame>
    <description>Compare trajectories of g (0-3) and ptc (0-3) Banff scores</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transplant glomerulopathy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month screening biopsies</time_frame>
    <description>Compare trajectories of cg (0-3) Banff score</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microcirculation inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month screening biopsies</time_frame>
    <description>Compare trajectories of g (0-3) and ptc (0-3) Banff scores</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transplant glomerulopathy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month screening biopsies</time_frame>
    <description>Compare trajectories of cg (0-3) Banff score</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measured Glomerular Filtration Rate (Iohexol clearance)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Compare trajectories of GFR change and percent GFR change between the study group and historiacl controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse effects</measure>
    <time_frame>at 15 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Monitoring of adverse events as well as evaluation of changes in laboratory parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of biopsy-proven acute rejection</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>graft biopsy for cause (rise in creatinine level…)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CH50</measure>
    <time_frame>at 15 months post-transplant (baseline, each infusion, study completion)</time_frame>
    <description>Monitoring of eculizumab pharmacodynamic with an in vitro complement activity assay (CH50).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endothelial Microparticles and Progenitors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1, 3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of endothelial and leukocyte-derived microparticules, as well as circulating endothelial progenitors as a biomarker of the graft endothelium insult.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Molecular diagnosis of AMR</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 12-month post-transplant biopsy</time_frame>
    <description>Compare trajectories of endothelial and NK expressed genes between the study group and historiacl controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Donor Specific Antibody titers (Luminex SA)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor the persistence of DSA in the study group in comparison with historical controls.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measured Glomerular Filtration Rate (Iohexol clearance)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Compare trajectories of GFR change and percent GFR change between the study group and historiacl controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Donor Specific Antibody titers (Luminex SA)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor the persistence of DSA in the study group in comparison with historical controls.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Donor Specific Antibody titers (Luminex SA)</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor the persistence of DSA in the study group in comparison with historical controls.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Donor Specific Antibody titers (Luminex SA)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor the persistence of DSA in the study group in comparison with historical controls.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Subclinical Acute Antibody-mediated Rejection in Kidney Transplantation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eculizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eculizumab will be given in addition to standard immunosuppression regimen (tacrolimus, mycophenalte mofeti, prednisone)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eculizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Eculizumab induction: 900 mg IV every 7 days for 4 doses, a fifth 1200 mg dose 7 days later Eculizumab maintenance: 15 1200 mg doses every 14 days.
(each patient will receive a total of 20 eculizumab doses during the whole treatment period from 3 month to 12 month post-transplant).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eculizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Soliris</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients aged 18 -75 years.

          -  Patients having received a kidney transplant from a living or deceased donor

          -  Patients with stable renal function

          -  Sensitized patient with at least one anti-HLA class II DSA (MFI &gt; 1000) within the
             first 3 months.

          -  Adequate 3-month-protocol biopsy exhibiting microcirculation inflammation defined by
             glomerulitis Banff score (g) superior or egal 2 and /or peri-tubular capillaritis
             Banff score (ptc) superior or egal 2, AND the sum of scores g + ptc superior or egal
             3.

          -  C4d positive staining on 3-month-protocol biopsy

          -  Adequate 3-month-protocol biopsy exhibiting limited scarred areas as defined as IF/TA
             score (ci + ct) inferior or egal 2 and no or minimal transplant glomerulopathy (cg
             inferior or egal 1)

          -  Patients who have given written informed consent to participate in all aspects of the
             study.

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within 48 hours
             prior to the first eculizumab administration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with known hypersensitivity to eculizumab or drugs with similar chemical
             structure.

          -  Patients having experienced and having been treated for an acute antibody-mediated
             rejection within the first 3 months post-transplant

          -  Patients with multi-organ transplant

          -  Female patients who are pregnant, lactating or of child bearing potential and not
             practicing an approved method of birth control.

          -  Patients with a known malignancy or history of malignancy other than excised basal or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

          -  HBV, HCV or HIV-chronically infected patients

          -  Patients with evidence of severe liver disease, including abnormal liver profile
             (aspartate aminotransferase [AST], alanine aminotransferases [ALT] or total bilirubin
             &gt; 3 times upper limit of normal at screening.

          -  Patients with current severe infection.

          -  Ongoing meningococcal infection

          -  Patient with systemic lupus erythematosus disease and / or anti-phospholipid
             antibodies

          -  Patients with any surgical or medical condition, which in the opinion of the
             investigator precludes enrollment in this trial

          -  Patients who live far from the transplant center and are unable to comply with all
             study visits.

          -  Long-term anticoagulation therapy or other contraindication to graft biopsies

          -  Positive BKV viremia during the first three months post-transplant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christophe LEGENDRE, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Service de Transplantation Rénale, Hôpital Necker Université Paris Descartes 149 rue de Sèvres 75015 Paris, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loupy A, Suberbielle-Boissel C, Hill GS, Lefaucheur C, Anglicheau D, Zuber J, Martinez F, Thervet E, Méjean A, Charron D, Duong van Huyen JP, Bruneval P, Legendre C, Nochy D. Outcome of subclinical antibody-mediated rejection in kidney transplant recipients with preformed donor-specific antibodies. Am J Transplant. 2009 Nov;9(11):2561-70. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-6143.2009.02813.x. Epub 2009 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>19775320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stegall MD, Diwan T, Raghavaiah S, Cornell LD, Burns J, Dean PG, Cosio FG, Gandhi MJ, Kremers W, Gloor JM. Terminal complement inhibition decreases antibody-mediated rejection in sensitized renal transplant recipients. Am J Transplant. 2011 Nov;11(11):2405-13. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-6143.2011.03757.x. Epub 2011 Sep 22. Erratum in: Am J Transplant. 2013 Jan;13(1):241.</citation>
    <PMID>21942930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loupy A, Lefaucheur C, Vernerey D, Prugger C, Duong van Huyen JP, Mooney N, Suberbielle C, Frémeaux-Bacchi V, Méjean A, Desgrandchamps F, Anglicheau D, Nochy D, Charron D, Empana JP, Delahousse M, Legendre C, Glotz D, Hill GS, Zeevi A, Jouven X. Complement-binding anti-HLA antibodies and kidney-allograft survival. N Engl J Med. 2013 Sep 26;369(13):1215-26. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1302506.</citation>
    <PMID>24066742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zuber J, Le Quintrec M, Krid S, Bertoye C, Gueutin V, Lahoche A, Heyne N, Ardissino G, Chatelet V, Noël LH, Hourmant M, Niaudet P, Frémeaux-Bacchi V, Rondeau E, Legendre C, Loirat C; French Study Group for Atypical HUS. Eculizumab for atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome recurrence in renal transplantation. Am J Transplant. 2012 Dec;12(12):3337-54. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-6143.2012.04252.x. Epub 2012 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22958221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 25, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Antibody-mediated rejection</keyword>
  <keyword>Complement blockade</keyword>
  <keyword>Eculizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney transplantation</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Complement System Proteins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

