<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02114008</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>179.017/2012 CEP UFMT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02114008</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Residual Gastric Volume in Morbidly Obesa Diabetics. A Comparison of 3 Hour Versus Hour Fasting.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Residual Gastric Volume in Morbidly Obesa Diabetics. A Comparison of 3 Hour Versus Hour Fasting.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cuiaba University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cuiaba University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To reduce the risk of aspiration for elective procedures, residual gastric volumes (RGV) have
      traditionally been minimized with overnight fasting. However, prolonged fasting can also have
      some adverse consequences and has been abandoned for some procedures in several patient
      populations with the exception of obese and/or diabetic patients. The aim of this study was
      to assess RGV in morbidly obese diabetic patients after traditional or abbreviated fasting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients underwent two endoscopic examinations within two weeks. RGV was measured by
      aspiration of gastric contentes into a graduated cylinder after traditional fasting (at least
      8 hours before the test) and after abbreviated fasting (3 hours with 200ml of water
      containing 25g of 12.5% maltodextrin). All patients received both oral and written
      information about the protocol at the outpatient clinic.

      All the endoscopic procedures began at 9 AM, and were performed by the same board-certified
      endoscopist, JMS, who was blinded as to the duration of the fast. The endoscopies were
      conducted at Gastroclinica, Cuiaba, MT, in the period from April to June, 2013. Sedation was
      performed by a board-certified anesthesiologist, who was also blinded as to the duration of
      the fast. The anesthetic regimem included a intravenous bolus of 2 ml of lidocaine
      hydrochloride (Astra Zeneca, São Paulo, Brazil) followed by 100 to 150mg of propofol before
      endoscopy. Digital oximetry was monitored throughout the procedure. Patients were positioned
      in the lateral recumbent position. A flexible electronic videoendoscope (EG2770K; Pentax
      Corporation, Tokyo, Japan) of 9 mm in outer diameter was used. The main outcome variable was
      the RGV measured by the endoscopist after aspiration of gastric residue.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Residual gastric volume (RGV) in morbidly obese diabetics. A comparison of 3 hour versus 8 hour fasting</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This was a prospective, randomized, double-blind, and cross-over design in 8 morbidly obese type II diabetics with informed consent. RGV was measured endoscopically after three and eight hour fasts.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Fasting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Abbreviated fasting</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients underwent two endoscopic examinations within two weeks. RGV was measured by aspiration of gastric contentes into a graduated cylinder after traditional after abbreviated fasting (3 hours with 200ml of water containing 25g of 12.5% maltodextrin).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional fasting</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients underwent two endoscopic examinations within two weeks. RGV was measured by aspiration of gastric contentes into a graduated cylinder after traditional fasting (at least 8 hours before the test).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endoscopic examinations</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients underwent two endoscopic examinations within two weeks. RGV was measured by aspiration of gastric contentes into a graduated cylinder after traditional fasting (at least 8 hours before the test) and after abbreviated fasting (3 hours with 200ml of water containing 25g of 12.5% maltodextrin). All patients received both oral and written information about the protocol at the outpatient clinic.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Abbreviated fasting</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional fasting</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: patients between 18 and 55 years of age, of both sexes, with Body Index
        Mass (BMI) which is equal or greater than 40 Kg/m2, and type II diabetic that were using
        oral drugs or insulin to control the disease.

        Exclusion Criteria: patients who were using medications for gastrointestinal symptoms
        and/or who had prior abdominal operations.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gunther P Pimenta, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cuiaba University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gunther Peres Pimenta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cuiaba</city>
        <state>MT</state>
        <zip>78040500</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 14, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cuiaba University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gunther Peres Pimenta</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gastric emptying.</keyword>
  <keyword>Residual gastric volume.</keyword>
  <keyword>Preoperative fasting.</keyword>
  <keyword>Morbid Obesity.</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes.</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

