<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02118493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201400129</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02118493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endo-biliary Laser Excision of Biliary Stenoses</brief_title>
  <official_title>Endo-biliary Laser Excision of Biliary Stenoses: Initial Experience and Feasibility</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Spectranetics Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The biliary system normally empties into the intestines, however, some patients have biliary
      system narrow areas (&quot;stenosis&quot;) that prevent the bile to drain normally. These may be
      related to an underlying disease or previous surgery. Patients with this problem usually
      require tubes to be inserted into the biliary system to drain bile into a bag outside of
      their body, impacting their quality of life.

      The purpose of this research study is to use a laser device to try to re-open the biliary
      drainage system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current preferred minimally invasive treatment for surgically related or in-situ benign
      biliary stenosis (BBS) involves open surgical revision, endoscopic retrograde
      cholangiographic (ERCP) or percutaneous transhepatic cholangiographic (PTC) balloon
      angioplasty and/or stent/biliary catheter placement. Unfortunately, most patients are poor
      open surgical operative candidates. Although ERCP is the preferred secondary approach,
      anatomical restrictions often require PTC. Additionally, previously placed biliary
      stents/catheters have poor long term patency and require routine exchange every 3-6 months.
      The vast majority of surgically related BBS patients are non-operative candidates for
      surgical revision of their BBS, and do not have favorable anatomy for ERCP access. For
      patients who have failed aggressive PTC balloon angioplasty of their stenoses, treatment
      consists of indefinite biliary catheter exchanges every 3 months. Lifelong biliary catheter
      dependence severely impacts the quality of life in an otherwise healthy patient with no
      additional evidence of their initial disease process.

      A potential long-term therapy to alleviate BBS that has not been explored is the use of laser
      excision of the fibrotic tissue responsible for these stenoses. Therapeutic applications of
      lasers in medicine is not a novel concept. Its use has been well documented in the urologic
      tract to ablate tissue (benign prostatic hypertrophy) and renal stones. Recent laser
      therapeutic use in the biliary tract to dissolve gallstones has been described. The laser
      excision of BBS has potential to provide long term alleviation of BBS. The primary endpoint
      of this feasibility study is to assess the safety and initial efficacy of BBS laser excision.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The protocol has been withdrawn for re-evaluation.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients free of post-interventional complications after use of the endo-biliary laser.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be assessed for safety after the endo-biliary laser use. Specifically, intraprocedural, immediate post-procedural (up to 4 hours), phone conversation 1 week post-procedure, and regularly scheduled 4 week post-procedure follow-up appointments will document the patient's tolerance of the procedure and any deviations from patients receiving biliary tube exchanges. Particular attention will be placed on regularly monitored signs/symptoms, such as cholangiographic appearance, total bilirubin, jaundice/fever/abdominal pain, etc. As each patient follows up on an ~4 week basis, any potential post-intervention complication will be documented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical success of endo-biliary laser excision via cholangiographic imaging.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Intraprocedural ability to excise fibrotic biliary tissue with the laser will be assessed by comparing pre- and immediately post-cholangiographic imaging.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients able to have internal-external biliary drainage catheters removed after endo-biliary laser excision.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Although this study is not powered to truly measure efficacy of this intervention, the investigators will monitor patient's for possible removal of required internal-external biliary drainage after the laser intervention. This will be monitored by 1) post-intervention follow-up cholangiograms 2) capping of the internal-external biliary drainage tube while monitoring patient symptoms and total bilirubin level and 3) possible removal of internal-external biliary tube post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Biliary Tract Disease</condition>
  <condition>Bile Duct Obstruction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Benign Biliary Stenosis, Laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects that undergo the experimental intervention, that being single use of a laser excision catheter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Benign Biliary Stenosis, Laser</intervention_name>
    <description>Single use of laser to attempt excision of biliary ductal tissue causing stenosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Benign Biliary Stenosis, Laser</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Spectranetics Turbo-Tandem Laser Guide Catheter with Laser Atherectomy Catheter</other_name>
    <other_name>Spectranetics CVX-300 Excimer Laser System</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with diagnosed benign biliary stenosis

          -  Initial total serum bilirubin &gt; 1.9 mg/dL

          -  Subjects currently having an internal/external percutaneous biliary drain

          -  Subjects that have failed at least 3 separate biliary stenosis balloon angioplasties
             and are deemed non-surgical candidates by the transplant and/or pancreaticobiliary
             surgical services at the University of Florida
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beau Toskich, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida Dept of Interventional Radiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laasch HU, Martin DF. Management of benign biliary strictures. Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol. 2002 Nov-Dec;25(6):457-66. Epub 2002 Oct 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12391514</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shimada H, Endo I, Shimada K, Matsuyama R, Kobayashi N, Kubota K. The current diagnosis and treatment of benign biliary stricture. Surg Today. 2012 Dec;42(12):1143-53. doi: 10.1007/s00595-012-0333-3. Epub 2012 Sep 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23001533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>García-Cano J. Endoscopic management of benign biliary strictures. Curr Gastroenterol Rep. 2013 Aug;15(8):336. doi: 10.1007/s11894-013-0336-2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23857116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zarrabi A, Gross AJ. The evolution of lasers in urology. Ther Adv Urol. 2011 Apr;3(2):81-9. doi: 10.1177/1756287211400494.</citation>
    <PMID>21869908</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peng Q, Juzeniene A, Chen J, et al. Lasers in medicine. Reports Prog Phys. 2008;71(5):056701. doi:10.1088/0034-4885/71/5/056701.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kow AW, Wang B, Wong D, Sundeep PJ, Chan CY, Ho CK, Liau KH. Using percutaneous transhepatic cholangioscopic lithotripsy for intrahepatic calculus in hostile abdomen. Surgeon. 2011 Apr;9(2):88-94. doi: 10.1016/j.surge.2010.08.002.</citation>
    <PMID>21342673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rimon U, Kleinmann N, Bensaid P, Golan G, Garniek A, Khaitovich B, Winkler H. Percutaneous transhepatic endoscopic holmium laser lithotripsy for intrahepatic and choledochal biliary stones. Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol. 2011 Dec;34(6):1262-6. doi: 10.1007/s00270-010-0058-x. Epub 2010 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21161660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shammas NW, Shammas GA, Hafez A, Kelly R, Reynolds E, Shammas AN. Safety and One-Year revascularization outcome of excimer laser ablation therapy in treating in-stent restenosis of femoropopliteal arteries: A retrospective review from a single center. Cardiovasc Revasc Med. 2012 Nov-Dec;13(6):341-4. doi: 10.1016/j.carrev.2012.08.012. Epub 2012 Oct 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23043953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steinkamp HJ, Wissgott C, Rademaker J, Scheinert D, Werk M, Settmacher U, Felix R. Short (1-10 cm) superficial femoral artery occlusions: results of treatment with excimer laser angioplasty. Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol. 2002 Sep-Oct;25(5):388-96. Epub 2002 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>12042997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karaca I, Ilkay E, Akbulut M, Yavuzkir M. Treatment of in-stent restenosis with excimer laser coronary angioplasty. Jpn Heart J. 2003 Mar;44(2):179-86.</citation>
    <PMID>12718480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuo WT, Cupp JS. The excimer laser sheath technique for embedded inferior vena cava filter removal. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2010 Dec;21(12):1896-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jvir.2010.08.013. Epub 2010 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21050774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dave RM, Patlola R, Kollmeyer K, Bunch F, Weinstock BS, Dippel E, Jaff MR, Popma J, Weissman N; CELLO Investigators. Excimer laser recanalization of femoropopliteal lesions and 1-year patency: results of the CELLO registry. J Endovasc Ther. 2009 Dec;16(6):665-75. doi: 10.1583/09-2781.1.</citation>
    <PMID>19995111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dachman AH, McGehee JA, Beam TE, Venbrux AC, Hoyt RF, Burris JA. Animal model for fluoroscopically guided laser application in the biliary tree. Radiology. 1990 Mar;174(3 Pt 2):1021-5.</citation>
    <PMID>2305083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Benign Biliary Stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Laser Excision</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholestasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Biliary Tract Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

