<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02113527</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC192014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02113527</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gastric Activity and Gastrointestinal Peptides in Patients With Functional Dyspepsia</brief_title>
  <acronym>DYSMOT-RIII</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Gastric Emptying Time, Gastric Electrical Activity and Gastrointestinal Peptides to Identify Dyspeptic Patients With Epigastric Pain Syndrome From Those With Postprandial Distress Syndrome According to the Rome III Proposed Subdivision of Functional Dyspepsia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliera Specializzata in Gastroenterologia Saverio de Bellis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Ospedaliera Specializzata in Gastroenterologia Saverio de Bellis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rome III criteria defined functional dyspepsia (FD) as the presence of symptoms from the
      gastroduodenal region in the absence of any organic, systemic or metabolic disease that is
      likely to explain the symptoms. FD can be further subdivided into two diagnostic categories:
      postprandial distress syndrome (PDS) and epigastric pain syndrome (EPS).

      Disorders of gastric electric activity and abnormal gastric emptying are probably actively
      involved in the FD onset. Different noninvasive procedures may be applied in order to
      evaluate the gastric motor functions such as 13C breath testing and cutaneous
      electrogastrography. Besides, different gastrointestinal peptides (i.e. CCK, peptide YY,
      Neurotensin, Somatostatin, Leptin, Ghrelin, Motilin, Gastrin, Pepsinogen I and II) are
      involved in the control of gastroduodenal motility.

      Aims of the present study are: 1) to evaluate the GI peptide circulating concentrations, the
      gastric electrical activity and gastric emptying time by applying noninvasive procedures in
      patients suffering from functional dyspepsia and 2) to test whether a significant difference
      exists between the two diagnostic categories of meal-induced dyspeptic symptoms
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Functional dyspepsia is one of the most relevant functional gastrointestinal disorders
      (FGIDs) among general population. Rome III criteria defined functional dyspepsia as the
      presence of symptoms from the gastroduodenal region (early satiation, postprandial fullness,
      epigastric pain or burning) in the absence of any organic, systemic or metabolic disease that
      is likely to explain the symptoms. Etiological causes are still unclear, and the
      pathophysiological mechanisms still largely unknown. Besides, Helicobacter pylori infection
      is often present in these patients and contributes to complicate the clinical presentation.
      One of the main problem in the management of these patients is the lack of reliable
      biohumoral markers. Thus, functional disorders are usually diagnosed on the bases of
      symptomatic patterns. The Rome consensus has proposed to further subdivide FD into two
      diagnostic categories of meal-induced dyspeptic symptoms: postprandial distress syndrome
      (PDS), characterized by postprandial fullness and early satiation, and epigastric pain
      syndrome (EPS), characterized by epigastric pain and burning.

      Central processing of visceral stimuli, and its role in the pathogenesis of functional
      dyspepsia, as well as low-grade inflammation in the duodenum are important emerging topics in
      pathophysiology research. In this framework, disorders of gastric electric activity and
      abnormal gastric emptying are probably actively involved in the onset of symptomatology.
      Different noninvasive procedures may be applied in order to evaluate the gastric motor
      functions. Among them, gastric emptying time evaluation by 13C breath testing and cutaneous
      electrogastrography have raised attention for their reliability and potentiality. Another
      important pathophysiological concern of FD is represented by the possible alterations in
      circulating concentrations of different gastrointestinal peptides at various degree involved
      in the control of gastroduodenal motility [namely Cholecystokinin (CCK), peptide YY,
      Neurotensin, Somatostatin, Leptin, Ghrelin, Motilin, Gastrin, Pepsinogen I and II]. In
      previous studies significant lower levels of motilin was found in dyspeptic patients with
      altered antroduodenal motility was found. CCK mediates satiety by acting on the CCK receptors
      distributed widely throughout the central nervous system as well as effects on the vagus
      nerve. Other experimental data suggest that somatostatin and neurotensin may affect muscle
      contractility and delay the intestinal transit.

      On these bases aims of the study will be: 1) to evaluate the GI peptide circulating
      concentrations, the gastric electrical activity and gastric emptying time by applying
      noninvasive procedures in patients suffering from functional dyspepsia and 2) to test whether
      a significant difference exists between the two diagnostic categories of meal-induced
      dyspeptic symptoms
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting plasma concentration of GI peptides, gastric emptying time and dyspepsia subtype.</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of 4-hour study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Exploration of relationships between GI peptide concentrations (CCK, peptide YY, Neurotensin, Somatostatin, Leptin, Ghrelin, Motilin, Gastrin, Pepsinogen I and II), solid gastric emptying, and dyspepsia subtype.
Blood samples will be compared pre/post test meal for FD cohorts (EPS/PDS) and controls: 0 time/baseline and 16 times/post meal.
Associations of plasma GI peptides pre and postprandial levels &amp; gastric emptying will be studied.
Amount of 13CO2 will be determined for each time point (1 pre/ 16 post meal) using equation nested in software package with IRMS.
The concentration of 13CO2 and 12CO2 in the exhaled breath samples will be measured by mass spectrometry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastric electrical activity and GI peptides according functional dyspepsia subtype</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of 4-hour study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Correlations between plasma GI peptide concentrations and gastric electrical activity to be measured during gastric emptying time evaluation.
Gastric electrical activity will be measured by cutaneous electrogastrography.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyspepsia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epigastric pain syndrome (EPS)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients suffering from functional dyspepsia characterized by epigastric pain syndrome according to Rome III criteria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postprandial distress syndrome (PDS)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients suffering from functional dyspepsia characterized by postprandial distress syndrome according to Rome III criteria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy subjects as control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      breath specimen, whole blood, serum, white cells.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients will be recruited in this observational study from the out-patients of the
        National Institute of Digestive Diseases, I.R.C.C.S. Saverio de Bellis, Castellana Grotte,
        Bari, Italy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients suffering from dyspeptic symptoms according to Rome III;

          -  Helicobacter pylori negative subjects;

          -  age 19-70 yr.;

          -  willingness to complete the study;

          -  not recent administration (in the 2 months before the examination) of
             anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), antibiotics, bismuth, antacids, H2-receptor
             antagonists, proton pump inhibitor, sucralfate or misoprostol;

          -  at least one endoscopic/radiological GI evaluation in the last 5 yrs.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  previous history of gastric tumors or gastric surgery

          -  lactose intolerance;

          -  celiac disease, wheat sensitivity;

          -  alarm symptoms (GI bleeding, weight loose etc.);

          -  psychiatric diseases;

          -  familial history of peptic ulcer;

          -  gastric cancer or IBD;

          -  abnormal thyroid function;

          -  other exclusion criteria (namely, pregnancy, breast-feeding, and drug allergies).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francesco Russo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IRCCS &quot;S. de Bellis&quot;</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Digestive Diseases IRCCS &quot;Saverio de Bellis&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Castellana Grotte</city>
        <state>Bari</state>
        <zip>70013</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chasen M, Bhargava R. Gastrointestinal symptoms, electrogastrography, inflammatory markers, and PG-SGA in patients with advanced cancer. Support Care Cancer. 2012 Jun;20(6):1283-90. doi: 10.1007/s00520-011-1215-8. Epub 2011 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21688162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miwa H, Watari J, Fukui H, Oshima T, Tomita T. [Pathogenesis and management of functional dyspepsia]. Nihon Rinsho. 2010 Jul;68(7):1391-401. Review. Japanese.</citation>
    <PMID>20662226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khoo J, Rayner CK, Feinle-Bisset C, Jones KL, Horowitz M. Gastrointestinal hormonal dysfunction in gastroparesis and functional dyspepsia. Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2010 Dec;22(12):1270-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2982.2010.01609.x. Epub 2010 Oct 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20939851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Smet B, Mitselos A, Depoortere I. Motilin and ghrelin as prokinetic drug targets. Pharmacol Ther. 2009 Aug;123(2):207-23. doi: 10.1016/j.pharmthera.2009.04.004. Epub 2009 May 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19427331</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geeraerts B, Mimidis K, van Oudenhove L, Vos R, Karamanolis G, Tack J. Role of endogenous opioids in the control of gastric sensorimotor function. Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2008 Oct;20(10):1094-102. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2982.2008.01144.x. Epub 2008 May 15.</citation>
    <PMID>18482249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 26, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 2, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliera Specializzata in Gastroenterologia Saverio de Bellis</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Francesco Russo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Electrogastrography</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional dyspepsia</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastric emptying</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastrointestinal peptides</keyword>
  <keyword>Rome III criteria</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyspepsia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

