<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02116946</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H13-00254</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02116946</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Plasma Injections Plus Exercise for Patellar Tendinopathy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PHS</acronym>
  <official_title>Intratendinous Injections of Platelet Rich Plasma With or Without Leukocyte Enrichment for Patellar Tendinopathy: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rizzoli Orthopaedic Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Norwegian Olympic Sports Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Oslo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Steadman Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled clinical trial to investigate the effectiveness, safety and
      tolerability of platelet-rich plasma (PRP) injections for treatment of patellar tendinopathy
      in adults 18-50 years of age. Subjects will be randomly assigned to three parallel treatment
      groups:

        1. Leukocyte-rich PRP injection + exercise

        2. Leukocyte-poor PRP injection + exercise

        3. Saline injection + exercise (control) Primary endpoints are (1) the number (rate) and
           severity of adverse events as reported by both patients and study physicians during the
           first 12 weeks after initiation of treatment, (2) patient-rated tolerability of
           treatment; (3) the change in function (VISA score) and treatment success (global
           improvement scale) over six months of a post-injection exercise protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number and frequency of adverse events will be assessed/reported weekly for the first 12 weeks and at the 6 month visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in function over time measured by VISA Score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in function (VISA score) between participants randomized to the three treatment groups over six months, 1 year, and 2 years of a post-injection exercise protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of treatment success measured by Likert Global Improvement Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in treatment success (Likert global improvement scale) between participants randomized to the three treatment groups over six months, 1 year, and 2 years of a post-injection exercise protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in activity levels over time measured by Tegner Activity Score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in activity levels (Tegner Activity Score) between participants randomized to the three groups over six months, 1 year, and 2 years of an exercise protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in activity-related pain over time measured by Pain Numeric Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in activity-related pain (Pain Numeric Rating Scale) between participants randomized to the three groups over six months, 1 year, and 2 years of an exercise protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Patellar Tendinopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Leukocyte-rich Platelet Rish Plasma + exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Leukocyte-rich PRP injection and a 12 week exercise program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Leukocyte-poor Platelet Rich Plasma + exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Leukocyte-poor PRP injection and a 12 week exercise program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline + exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Saline injection and a 12 week exercise program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Platelet Rich Plasma (PRP)</intervention_name>
    <description>Injection of Leukocyte-rich or Leukocyte-poor Platelet Rich Plasma prepared by the Angel cPRP System along with a 12 week exercise program for treatment of patients with patellar tendinopathy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Leukocyte-rich Platelet Rish Plasma + exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Leukocyte-poor Platelet Rich Plasma + exercise</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>The device Angel cPRP System will be used to make (Leukocyte-rich or -poor) PRP injections</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline + exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Peritendinous saline injection plus 12 week exercise program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline + exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female ≥ 18 and ≤ 50 years of age at Enrollment Visit

          -  Documentation of a clinical diagnosis of patellar tendinopathy, grade-IIIB Blazina
             stage, confirmed on ultrasound

          -  Previously tried an exercise program of at least six weeks duration

          -  Fluent in official language of study site

          -  Written informed consent obtained from subject

          -  Normal values on screening laboratory panels (CBC, PT, PTT, INR, serum creatine, ALT,
             ALP, AST, bilirubin, albumin)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  For women of child-bearing potential, positive pregnancy test at enrollment visit

          -  Major surgery in the past three months

          -  Surgery on the symptomatic knee

          -  Bleeding disorder

          -  Systemic inflammatory disease

          -  Arthritis or degenerative knee condition

          -  Recent fluoroquinolone use

          -  Subjects who have any requirement for the use of systemic steroids or
             immunosuppressants

          -  Subjects who are known to be HIV positive

          -  Uncooperative patient, or patients who are incapable of following directions or who
             are predictably unwilling to return for follow-up examinations

          -  Presence of a condition or abnormality that in the opinion of the Investigator would
             compromise the safety of the patient or the quality of the data
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander Scott, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Steadman Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vail</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>81657</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert LaPrade, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>970-479-5881</phone>
      <email>rlaprade@thesteadmanclinic.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Laprade, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kimberly Harmon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>206-520-5000</phone>
      <email>kharmon@uw.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kimberly Harmon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Britich Columbia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6T 1Z4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alex Scott, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>604-875-4111</phone>
      <phone_ext>21810</phone_ext>
      <email>alex.scott@ubc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alex Scott, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rizzoli Orthopaedic Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizaveta Kon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>39-051-6366567</phone>
      <email>e.kon@biomec.ior.it</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizaveta Kon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oslo Sports Trauma Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lars Engebretsen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>47 22 85 50 50</phone>
      <email>lars.engebretsen@medisin.uio.no</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lars Engebretsen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roald Bahr, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lian OB, Engebretsen L, Bahr R. Prevalence of jumper's knee among elite athletes from different sports: a cross-sectional study. Am J Sports Med. 2005 Apr;33(4):561-7. Epub 2005 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>15722279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferretti A. Epidemiology of jumper's knee. Sports Med. 1986 Jul-Aug;3(4):289-95.</citation>
    <PMID>3738327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lian O, Engebretsen L, Ovrebø RV, Bahr R. Characteristics of the leg extensors in male volleyball players with jumper's knee. Am J Sports Med. 1996 May-Jun;24(3):380-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8734892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engebretsen L, Steffen K, Alsousou J, Anitua E, Bachl N, Devilee R, Everts P, Hamilton B, Huard J, Jenoure P, Kelberine F, Kon E, Maffulli N, Matheson G, Mei-Dan O, Menetrey J, Philippon M, Randelli P, Schamasch P, Schwellnus M, Vernec A, Verrall G. IOC consensus paper on the use of platelet-rich plasma in sports medicine. Br J Sports Med. 2010 Dec;44(15):1072-81. doi: 10.1136/bjsm.2010.079822.</citation>
    <PMID>21106774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott, A, KM Khan, J Cook, and V Duronio, Human tendon overuse pathology: histopathologic and biochemical findings, in Tendinopathy in Athletes, S.L. Woo, S.P. Arnoczky, and P. Renstrom, Editors. 2007, Blackwell Publishing Ltd: Malden, Massachusetts. p. 69-84.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kongsgaard M, Qvortrup K, Larsen J, Aagaard P, Doessing S, Hansen P, Kjaer M, Magnusson SP. Fibril morphology and tendon mechanical properties in patellar tendinopathy: effects of heavy slow resistance training. Am J Sports Med. 2010 Apr;38(4):749-56. doi: 10.1177/0363546509350915. Epub 2010 Feb 12.</citation>
    <PMID>20154324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsson ME, Käll I, Nilsson-Helander K. Treatment of patellar tendinopathy--a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc. 2012 Aug;20(8):1632-46. doi: 10.1007/s00167-011-1825-1. Epub 2011 Dec 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22186923</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bahr R, Fossan B, Løken S, Engebretsen L. Surgical treatment compared with eccentric training for patellar tendinopathy (Jumper's Knee). A randomized, controlled trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2006 Aug;88(8):1689-98.</citation>
    <PMID>16882889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warden SJ, Metcalf BR, Kiss ZS, Cook JL, Purdam CR, Bennell KL, Crossley KM. Low-intensity pulsed ultrasound for chronic patellar tendinopathy: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2008 Apr;47(4):467-71. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/kem384. Epub 2008 Feb 12.</citation>
    <PMID>18270224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kongsgaard M, Kovanen V, Aagaard P, Doessing S, Hansen P, Laursen AH, Kaldau NC, Kjaer M, Magnusson SP. Corticosteroid injections, eccentric decline squat training and heavy slow resistance training in patellar tendinopathy. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2009 Dec;19(6):790-802. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0838.2009.00949.x. Epub 2009 May 28.</citation>
    <PMID>19793213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rees JD, Maffulli N, Cook J. Management of tendinopathy. Am J Sports Med. 2009 Sep;37(9):1855-67. doi: 10.1177/0363546508324283. Epub 2009 Feb 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19188560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Ark M, Zwerver J, van den Akker-Scheek I. Injection treatments for patellar tendinopathy. Br J Sports Med. 2011 Oct;45(13):1068-76. doi: 10.1136/bjsm.2010.078824. Epub 2011 May 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21543346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Filardo G, Kon E, Della Villa S, Vincentelli F, Fornasari PM, Marcacci M. Use of platelet-rich plasma for the treatment of refractory jumper's knee. Int Orthop. 2010 Aug;34(6):909-15. doi: 10.1007/s00264-009-0845-7. Epub 2009 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>19641918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kon E, Filardo G, Delcogliano M, Presti ML, Russo A, Bondi A, Di Martino A, Cenacchi A, Fornasari PM, Marcacci M. Platelet-rich plasma: new clinical application: a pilot study for treatment of jumper's knee. Injury. 2009 Jun;40(6):598-603. doi: 10.1016/j.injury.2008.11.026. Epub 2009 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19380129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banfi G, Corsi MM, Volpi P. Could platelet rich plasma have effects on systemic circulating growth factors and cytokine release in orthopaedic applications? Br J Sports Med. 2006 Oct;40(10):816. Epub 2006 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>16920768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sheth U, Simunovic N, Klein G, Fu F, Einhorn TA, Schemitsch E, Ayeni OR, Bhandari M. Efficacy of autologous platelet-rich plasma use for orthopaedic indications: a meta-analysis. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2012 Feb 15;94(4):298-307. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.K.00154. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22241606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thanasas C, Papadimitriou G, Charalambidis C, Paraskevopoulos I, Papanikolaou A. Platelet-rich plasma versus autologous whole blood for the treatment of chronic lateral elbow epicondylitis: a randomized controlled clinical trial. Am J Sports Med. 2011 Oct;39(10):2130-4. doi: 10.1177/0363546511417113. Epub 2011 Aug 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21813443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castillo TN, Pouliot MA, Kim HJ, Dragoo JL. Comparison of growth factor and platelet concentration from commercial platelet-rich plasma separation systems. Am J Sports Med. 2011 Feb;39(2):266-71. doi: 10.1177/0363546510387517. Epub 2010 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21051428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dragoo JL, Braun HJ, Durham JL, Ridley BA, Odegaard JI, Luong R, Arnoczky SP. Comparison of the acute inflammatory response of two commercial platelet-rich plasma systems in healthy rabbit tendons. Am J Sports Med. 2012 Jun;40(6):1274-81. doi: 10.1177/0363546512442334. Epub 2012 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22495144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dworkin RH, Turk DC, Farrar JT, Haythornthwaite JA, Jensen MP, Katz NP, Kerns RD, Stucki G, Allen RR, Bellamy N, Carr DB, Chandler J, Cowan P, Dionne R, Galer BS, Hertz S, Jadad AR, Kramer LD, Manning DC, Martin S, McCormick CG, McDermott MP, McGrath P, Quessy S, Rappaport BA, Robbins W, Robinson JP, Rothman M, Royal MA, Simon L, Stauffer JW, Stein W, Tollett J, Wernicke J, Witter J; IMMPACT. Core outcome measures for chronic pain clinical trials: IMMPACT recommendations. Pain. 2005 Jan;113(1-2):9-19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15621359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Briggs KK, Steadman JR, Hay CJ, Hines SL. Lysholm score and Tegner activity level in individuals with normal knees. Am J Sports Med. 2009 May;37(5):898-901. doi: 10.1177/0363546508330149. Epub 2009 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19307332</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 15, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 17, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alexander Scott</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tendinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

