<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00674531</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0608071</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2007-A00895-48</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DGS2007-0534</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00674531</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Detection of Enterovirus RNA in Atheromatous Lesions</brief_title>
  <acronym>ATH-ENTE</acronym>
  <official_title>Detection of Enterovirus RNA by RT-PCR in Atheromatous Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Saint Etienne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Health, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Saint Etienne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atherosclerosis is one of the first causes of morbidity-mortality in industrialized
      countries. Numerous works suggest that some infectious agents could be involved in the
      inflammatory process leading to the development of this pathology, such as Chlamydophila
      pneumoniae, cytomegalovirus or herpes simplex virus. Enteroviruses are small RNA viruses that
      have been incriminated in various acute or chronic cardiac diseases (pericarditis,
      myocarditis, dilated cardiomyopathy) and exhibit a tropism for vascular endothelia. Different
      clinical and experimental arguments suggest that they could play a cofactor role in the
      occurrence or maintenance of atherosclerosis lesions. A multicenter study developed in
      collaboration with colleagues of the University Hospital of Reims (France) showed that it was
      frequent to detect enterovirus RNA in cardiac biopsies from patients with myocardial
      infarction. Furthermore, a pilot study conducted in the University Hospital of Saint-Etienne
      (France) on atheromatous arterial samples from 18 patients allowed the detection of
      enterovirus RNA in 20% of them.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: In order to complete these data and to answer clearly to the question of the role
      of persistent infection by enteroviruses in atherosclerosis, we propose this research program
      involving the Departments of Vascular Surgery of three University hospitals of the
      &quot;Rhône-Alpes&quot; region and of three laboratories of Virology interested by the relationship
      between chronic diseases and enterovirus infection..

      Methods: It is projected to include about one hundred voluntary adults exhibiting carotid
      atheromatous lesions requiring a surgical removal. Because of the difficulty to define a
      pertinent control group, each patient will be his/her own control. In addition to the
      fragment of pathologic carotid, it will be taken arterial and venous fragments from vessels
      that are never the seat of atherosclerosis lesions. To reach the best sensitivity,
      enterovirus RNA will be detected by nested RT-PCR.

      Evaluation criteria: The main evaluation criterion will be the percentage of detection of
      enterovirus RNA by RT-PCR in atheromatous lesions by comparison to control arteries by
      Mac-Nemar test. These results will be correlated to anatomic and histological lesions of the
      atheromatous plaques. Other markers will be analysed secondarily: detection of enterovirus
      RNA in control venous samples, detection of stigmata of viral replication by immunochemistry
      or detection of negative RNA strands, analysis of the antibody response to enterovirus in
      blood, molecular typing of enteroviruses detected in the lesions… Expected benefits: This
      study should allow to better understand the putative involvement of enteroviruses in
      atherosclerosis-linked diseases. If the hypothesis of a relationship was confirmed, a more
      ambitious research project would be proposed in order to investigate the mechanisms by which
      enterovirus can favour atherosclerosis and to discuss the opportunity of preventive
      strategies (notably vaccination) to reduce the risk.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prévalence of detection of enteroviral RNA by RT-PCR in atherosclerotic carotid artery in comparison with sound carotid artery</measure>
    <time_frame>artery resection</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of detection of enteroviral RNA by RT-PCR in atherosclerotic carotid artery in comparison with sound vein</measure>
    <time_frame>Artery resection</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of detection of enteroviral RNA by RT-PCR in sound carotid artery in comparison with sound vein</measure>
    <time_frame>Artery resection</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of detection of enteroviral RNA by RT-PCR in calm and active atherosclerotic lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>Artery resection</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of detection of antibodies between different groups of patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>Artery resection</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of detection of enteroviral RNA by RT-PCR in atherosclerotic carotid artery in comparison with circulating blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Artery resection</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Arteriosclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Enterovirus RNA analysis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Artery resection</intervention_name>
    <description>Artery resection</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Indication of artery resection

          -  affiliated or a beneficiary of a social security category

          -  having signed the inform consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant women

          -  contra-indication to clamping

          -  scheduled resection at friday after-noon, week-end or legal holidays
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xavier BARRAL, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU de Saint-Etienne</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Clermont-Ferrand</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont-ferrand</city>
        <zip>63000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Saint-Etienne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-etienne</city>
        <zip>42055</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schanen C, Nasri D, Bourlet T, Barral X, Favre JP, Bourrat D, Péoc'h M, Ginevra C, Andréoletti L, Pozzetto B, Pillet S. Enterovirus in arteriosclerosis: a pilot study. J Clin Virol. 2007 Jun;39(2):106-12. Epub 2007 May 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17499019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andréoletti L, Ventéo L, Douche-Aourik F, Canas F, Lorin de la Grandmaison G, Jacques J, Moret H, Jovenin N, Mosnier JF, Matta M, Duband S, Pluot M, Pozzetto B, Bourlet T. Active Coxsackieviral B infection is associated with disruption of dystrophin in endomyocardial tissue of patients who died suddenly of acute myocardial infarction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2007 Dec 4;50(23):2207-14. Epub 2007 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18061067</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 8, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 8, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 8, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 9, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arteriosclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Enterovirus</keyword>
  <keyword>Artery resection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enterovirus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

