<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00678236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20070237</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00678236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Migration and Bone Density Study Comparing 2 Types of Bone Cement in the OptiPac Bone Cement Mixing System</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Migration and Bone Density Study Comparing Refobacin Bone Cement R vs. Refobacin Plus Bone Cement in the OptiPac Bone Cement Mixing System. A Prospective Randomized Study on Primary Total Knee Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aarhus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Zimmer Biomet</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aarhus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this scientific study is to determine whether there are differences in early
      migration and prosthesis-near bone density when a standard knee prosthesis is fixed with
      Refobacin Bone Cement R or with Refobacin Plus Bone Cement. Migration will be evaluated with
      RSA and bone density around the prosthesis with DEXA. The study will be successful if the
      prosthesis is fixed and remains in place throughout the entire period of the study, that is,
      that there is no increasing migration as measured by RSA. The cement type that ensures the
      largest number of solidly fixed prostheses during the two-year evaluation period will be &quot;the
      best&quot;.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Loosening of prosthetic components continues to play a large role in total knee alloplasty
      (TKA) and need for revision. Osteolysis is an important part of prosthesis loosening, but we
      still do not completely understand the mechanism. Research has shown that mechanical factors
      such as weak bone cement and poor contact between cement/bone or cement/implant interphase
      contribute to loosening of implants. Survival of cemented TKA components also depend on a
      careful balancing of soft tissues around the knee, repair of lower extremity dislocations,
      design of the prosthesis and the level of patients' activities. Sclerosis of the proximal
      tibia can present a problem with regard to getting the cement to penetrate into the bone.
      Poor operative technique, such as high volume or high pressure lavage of the prepared bone
      surface, can result in reduced penetration of cement into the spongiosa and early failure of
      the prosthesis, measured as progressive radiolucent lines (RLLs). En tourniquet counter acts
      bleeding at the implant site and provides for better penetration of cement into the
      trabeculae of the bone. If the bone surface at the implantation site is contaminated with
      blood before the cement is applied, the shear strength in the bone/cement interphase can be
      reduced by up to 50%.

      In prosthesis used in this study includes a tibial plateau with a central stem with
      stabilizing wings, the bottom surface of which is recessed by about 1 mm, so that a pocket is
      formed surrounded by a lip that provides for an even thickness of the cement layer beneath
      the tibial plateau. This assures that the cement is pressed down into the spongiosa during
      fixation of the implant. This design doubles the penetration of the cement compared with
      prostheses without a depressed baseplate. The company behind this design has had a successful
      follow-up of this system for more than 15 years. A good cement/implant interphase lessens the
      risk of penetration of debris into the interphase and thus reduces the risk for the
      development of osteolysis and aseptic loosening of the implant.

      Fixation of knee alloplasties is done in 70% of cases with use of cement. It is uncertain
      whether there is a difference in the long-term survival of knee prostheses with the two types
      of cement used in this project. Both types of cement in this study are used today in knee
      surgery with good, short-term clinical results. It is important to investigate new types of
      cement in order to assure future patients the best possible results after knee alloplasty and
      fewer re-operations.

      The goal of this scientific study is to determine whether there are differences in early
      migration and prosthesis-near bone density when a standard knee prosthesis is fixed with
      Refobacin Bone Cement R or with Refobacin Plus Bone Cement. Migration will be evaluated with
      RSA and bone density around the prosthesis with DEXA. The study will be successful if the
      prosthesis is fixed and remains in place throughout the entire period of the study, that is,
      that there is no increasing migration as measured by RSA. The cement type that ensures the
      largest number of solidly fixed prostheses during the two-year evaluation period will be &quot;the
      best&quot;.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tibial implant migration evaluated by RSA</measure>
    <time_frame>2013</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Refobacin Bone Cement R vs. Refobacin Plus Bone Cement</measure>
    <time_frame>2013</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Refobacin Bone Cement R</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Refobacin Plus Bone Cement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Refobacin Bone Cement R</intervention_name>
    <description>Insertion of a knee prosthesis fixed by Refobacin Bone Cement R</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Biomet Europe: Refobacin Bone Cement R</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Refobacin Plus Bone Cement</intervention_name>
    <description>Insertion of a knee prosthesis fixed by Refobacin Plus Bone Cement</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Biomet Europe: Refobacin Plus Bone Cement</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  primary or secondary knee osteoarthritis

          -  sufficient bone quality for total knee arthroplasty

          -  age above 70 years

          -  no upper age limit if the patient is capable

          -  informed and written consent

          -  patient can only enter the project with one knee

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  neuromuscular or vascular disease in the affected leg

          -  preoperatively not found suitable for a knee arthroplasty

          -  patients with osteoporosis based on former diagnosis or preoperative DEXA-scan

          -  fracture sequelae or previous PTO or previous extensive knee surgery

          -  patients with need of a stem-elongation

          -  patients who cannot refrain from taking NSAID post-operatively

          -  continuous medical treatment with vitamin K antagonists (Warfarin) which is known to
             reduce the bon emineral density by a factor of 5

          -  patients with metabolic bone disease

          -  patients with rheumatoid arthritis

          -  postmenopausal women in estrogenic hormone substitution

          -  patients with a continuous need of systemic cortisone treatment

          -  non-Danish citizenship

          -  patients who do not comprehend the Danish language (read and speak)

          -  senile dementia

          -  alcoholism - defined as men drinking more than 21 units a week and women drinking more
             than 14 units a week

          -  drug abuse

          -  major psychiatric disease

          -  metastatic cancer disease and treatment with radiation therapy or chemotherapy

          -  severe systemic disease (e.g. hemi paresis and Parkinson disease)

          -  systemic hip and spine disease

          -  employee at the orthopaedic department, Aarhus University Hospital

          -  ongoing case regarding industrial injury insurance of the knee

          -  patients with poor dental status (risk of infection)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kjeld Soballe, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Orthopaedic Center, Aarhus University Hospital, Tage-Hansens Gade 2, 8000 Århus C, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orthopaedic Center, Aarhus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 15, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 19, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 19, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>RSA</keyword>
  <keyword>Gonarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Cement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cimetidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

