<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03364127</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-0885</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03364127</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Acupuncture on Patient Vulvodynia Outcomes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Double-blind Phase 2 RCT: Effect of Acupuncture on Patient Vulvodynia Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Illinois at Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Illinois at Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates acupuncture for the treatment of vulvodynia; specifically if it reduces
      vulvar pain and pain with intercourse. It also examines how long the effect of acupuncture
      lasts in women with vulvodynia. Half of the women will receive acupuncture and the other half
      will receive placebo acupuncture. Women who get a reduction in pain will monitor there pain
      once a week for up to 12 weeks to see how long the acupuncture effect lasts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators' goal is to demonstrate the effects of acupuncture for the treatment of
      vulvodynia. Up to 14 million American women have vulvodynia, a debilitating pain syndrome
      characterized by pain (burning, irritation, stinging or rawness) in the vulva and dyspareunia
      that renders sexual intercourse virtually impossible and leaves these women desperate for
      relief. Not only are women in pain, but they often lose their partners or have relationship
      difficulties due to their inability to have sexual intercourse. No therapies have been proven
      efficacious and rapid pain relief is unpredictable and rarely possible. After exhausting
      Western Medicine options, these women often turn to acupuncture. But in contrast to other
      pain conditions, there have been no acupuncture sham control studies of vulvodynia.

      Only four studies, including one of the investigators', provide some evidence of the effect
      of acupuncture on vulvodynia. In three, single-group acupuncture studies, women had less
      pain, better quality of life, improved sexual health, and improved mental health. The
      investigators' randomized wait-list controlled pilot study of 36 women with vulvodynia showed
      great promise. The investigators found a statistically significant and clinically meaningful
      reduction in vulvar pain and dyspareunia, and an increase in overall sexual function after a
      5-week, 13-needle, 10 session acupuncture protocol. This newly developed, standardized
      acupuncture treatment protocol is the first breakthrough in the treatment of this puzzling
      disorder. It includes acupuncture points that relieve pain in the genitals. The results of
      the investigators' initial pilot study provided the first evidence from a two-group design
      that the acupuncture protocol could reduce pain intensity, pain during intercourse, and
      increase overall sexual function. These findings, however, warrant stronger evidence to
      support the inference that the effect is indeed due to the acupuncture since ours or no other
      study included a sham control or provided follow-up data beyond immediate posttest, which
      means that the duration of the acupuncture effect is unknown. The investigators' recent
      feasibility study paves the way to overcome this gap by use of double-blind acupuncture
      needles. Findings from these two studies support the investigators' proposal for the world's
      first double-blind randomized controlled trial (RCT) of acupuncture for vulvodynia while
      exploring its duration of effect.

      The investigators propose a phase 2 double-blind, pretest/posttest RCT to compare effects of
      penetrating needles or the skin touch placebo needles on vulvar pain in our 13-needle,
      10-session acupuncture treatment protocol. A sample of 130 women, with a diagnosis of
      vulvodynia, either generalized or provoked vestibulodynia, 18 to 45 years of age will be
      recruited from clinical and community settings and 80 subjects are expected to complete the
      study. Stratified by type of vulvodynia, participants will be randomized 1:1 either to the
      penetrating needle group or the skin touch placebo needle group. These double-blind needles
      will provide a strong sham procedure to mask both the acupuncturist and subject to the type
      of needle used for the 10-treatment protocol.

      Specific aims are to:

      Aim 1. Compare the penetrating needle group and the skin touch placebo needle group for
      effects on the: (a) primary outcome: vulvar pain (PAINReportIt® average pain intensity,
      0-10), and (b) secondary outcomes: dyspareunia (FSFI dyspareunia) and sexual function (FSFI
      total). The investigators hypothesize that controlling for baseline values, at posttest there
      will be statistically significant less vulvar pain (primary) and dyspareunia and better
      sexual function in the penetrating needle group compared to the skin touch placebo group.

      Aim 2. In participants with a clinically meaningful reduction in pain intensity (at least 1.5
      points) at posttest compared to pretest, describe the duration of the acupuncture treatment
      and placebo effects weekly until pain returns to pretest or up to 12 weeks after posttest.
      The investigators will describe the variability over time in vulvar pain intensity (0-10)
      after a tampon insertion-removal stimulus and thereby explore the duration of the effect by
      intervention group, vulvodynia subgroups, and demographic subgroups (e.g., age, race,
      occupation). These findings will provide insights to guide future research on initial and
      maintenance acupuncture for vulvodynia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average Pain Intensity will be measured with the Pain Intensity Numbers Scale (PINS).</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and after the 10th acupuncture treatment week 5</time_frame>
    <description>The subject calls the pain intensity a number between 0 and 10, where 0 is &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 is &quot;pain as bad as it could be.&quot; The PINS will include three items (pain now, least and worst pain in the past 24 hours), which are used to calculate the average of pain intensity. The PINS with the three items and standardized instructions is part of PAINReportIt® which is an electronic version of the 1970 version of the McGill Pain Questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dyspareunia Subscale of the Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and after the 10th acupuncture treatment week 5</time_frame>
    <description>The FSFI is a 19-item, multi-dimensional, self-report measure that examines six areas of sexual response: desire, arousal, lubrication, orgasm, satisfaction, and dyspareunia. In addition to the six subscale scores, there is a total combined score (FSFIt) that is a measure of overall sexual function. Possible scores range from zero to five for each item and higher scores indicate improved function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total score of the Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and after the 10th acupuncture treatment week 5</time_frame>
    <description>The FSFI is a 19-item, multi-dimensional, self-report measure that examines six areas of sexual response: desire, arousal, lubrication, orgasm, satisfaction, and dyspareunia. In addition to the six subscale scores, there is a total combined score (FSFIt) that is a measure of overall sexual function. Possible scores range from zero to five for each item and higher scores indicate improved function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average Pain Intensity will be measured with the Pain Intensity Numbers Scale (PINS).</measure>
    <time_frame>after the 10th acupuncture treatment weekly up to 12 weeks post last acupuncture treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>The subject calls the pain intensity a number between 0 and 10, where 0 is &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 is &quot;pain as bad as it could be.&quot; The PINS will include three items (pain now, least and worst pain in the past 24 hours), which are used to calculate the average of pain intensity. The PINS with the three items and standardized instructions is part of PAINReportIt® which is an electronic version of the 1970 version of the McGill Pain Questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Vulvodynia</condition>
  <condition>Vulvodynia, Generalized</condition>
  <condition>Vulvar Vestibulitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Active Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active Acupuncture two times per week for 5 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Acupuncture two times per week for 5 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active Acupuncture</intervention_name>
    <description>Active Acupuncture two times per week for 5 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Active Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Penetrating Acupuncture Needle</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Acupuncture</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo Acupuncture two times per week for 5 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Skin-touch Placebo Needle</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. a previous diagnosis of generalized vulvodynia or provoked vestibulodynia

          2. 18 to 45 years old

          3. a pain now score 4 or higher with tampon insertion and removal performed at the
             initial screening exam

          4. speak and read English

        Exclusionary Criteria:

          1. infectious conditions of the vulva/vagina

          2. inflammatory conditions of the vulva/vagina

          3. neoplastic disorders of the vulva/vagina

          4. neurologic disorders of the vulva/vagina

          5. trauma to the genitals

          6. iatrogenic conditions of the genitals

          7. hormonal deficiencies

          8. co-morbid pelvic pain conditions (to avoid confounding pain outcomes) such as pelvic
             inflammatory disease and documented history of endometriosis

          9. menopause

        Patients may have a history of but not have active in the last 6 months migraine headaches,
        temporomandibular joint disease (TMJ), irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), interstitial
        cystitis, painful bladder syndrome, or fibromyalgia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judith M. Schlaeger, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Illinois at Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marie Suarez, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(312) 413-5449</phone>
    <email>msuarez@uic.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Judith M Schlaeger, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3124134669</phone>
    <email>jschlaeg@uic.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois at Chicago College of Nursing</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie Suarez, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>312-413-5449</phone>
      <email>msuarez@uic.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Judith Schlaeger</last_name>
      <phone>7083341097</phone>
      <phone_ext>schlaeger</phone_ext>
      <email>judithschlaeger@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Judith M Schlaeger, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 30, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 30, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vulvar Pain, Dyspareunia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vulvodynia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vulvar Vestibulitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

