<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03361384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-068</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AA022301</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03361384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Alcohol and Implicit Process in Sexual Risk Behavior in MSM</brief_title>
  <official_title>Alcohol and Implicit Process in Sexual Risk Behavior in MSM</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Syracuse University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of South Dakota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Syracuse University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The current study is the first empirical investigation that directly addresses the
      correspondence between responses regarding indicators of risky sexual behavior while under
      the influence of alcohol in the laboratory and the occurrence of sexually risky behavior
      while under the influence of alcohol in the natural environment, by use of Ecological
      Sampling Methodology (ESM). The study will allow us to compare and contrast implicit and
      explicit assessments of sexual risk in respect to future behavior in the natural environment.
      The data obtained will thus provide new information regarding the external validity of
      alcohol administration studies of sexual risk behavior and will provide information to
      optimize the selection of dependent measures. The current study also represents the first
      attempt to test a causal model linking alcohol intoxication and risky sexual behavior as a
      function of both automatic, reflexive, approach tendencies and effortful, deliberative,
      self-control (operationalized by executive working memory in this application). The ESM study
      will augment the findings of the experiment by providing a detailed assessment of contextual
      factors that affect sexual risk behavior as well as replicating and extending the findings of
      the experiment to sexual risk situations in the natural environment. Finally, to our
      knowledge there has been only one experimental study of alcohol and sexual risk in MSM
      (Maisto, Palfai, Vanable, Heath, &amp; Woolf-King, 2012), which is remarkable given that MSM have
      been identified as the population at highest risk to contract the HIV in the U.S. since the
      virus was identified in the early 1980s. Thus the proposed research is only the second
      attempt to add to an understanding of the connections among alcohol, cognitive processes, and
      sexual risk behaviors in MSM.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants are randomly assigned to a beverage condition: alcohol, placebo, or control (water).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>Post beverage administration (completed 30-45 minutes following beverage consumption)</time_frame>
    <description>Behavioral skills and risk exposure will be measured with two interactive videos developed for the Maisto et al. (2012) experiment. For the risk exposure component, each video begins by setting a scene in which &quot;Jim&quot; (the protagonist) and &quot;Dave&quot; (the character with whom the participant will be asked to identify) meet up with each other. The participant will be asked to make a series (5 choice points) of binary choices (yes/no) about engaging in various increasingly high-risk sexual activities with Jim. Participants will receive 1 point for each time they answer &quot;yes&quot; and thus make a progressively risky choice. The risk exposure portion of the video will terminate with the first &quot;no&quot; response to the choice points. Subsequently, the participant will go to the fifth choice point to begin the behavioral skills component of the video. The risk exposure score will represent the mean score from the two interactive videos. Higher scores represent higher risk exposure scores.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral skills</measure>
    <time_frame>Post beverage administration (completed 30-45 minutes following beverage consumption)</time_frame>
    <description>The behavioral skills portion of the video will require participants to negotiate sexual situations using verbal communication skills in an interactive role-play. Participants will be asked to respond first to Jim's comment that he desires to have unprotected anal sex and that there is no cause for concern because he is safe (&quot;prompt 1&quot;) and = a second, more insistent comment that was a reminder to the participant that UAI would not be risky and would be pleasurable and that the participants could trust Jim (&quot;prompt 2&quot;). Participants' responses to each of the prompts will be scored on a 0-2 scale (higher score = better communication skills). The behavioral skills score will represent the mean score from the two interactive videos.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intentions to engage in unprotected sex</measure>
    <time_frame>Post beverage administration (completed 30-45 minutes following beverage consumption)</time_frame>
    <description>Intention to engage in unprotected sex after viewing each of two sexual video vignettes (Maisto et al., 2012) will be rated on a 7-point rating scale (Bishop &amp; Maisto, 2011). The intentions to engage in unprotected sex score will represent the mean score from the two interactive videos. Higher scores represent greater intentions to engage in unprotected sex.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">330</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Drinking</condition>
  <condition>Sex Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Men</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alcohol condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The amount of alcohol received in the alcohol condition will be determined by an algorithm developed by Curtin (Curtin, 2000). Participants in the alcohol condition will receive a dose of alcohol (target BAC = .08%), administered in a chilled beverage of 80-proof vodka mixed with tonic water and lime juice in a 1:4 ratio.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo participants will receive tonic water and lime juice served to enhance alcohol cues in an amount comparable to the amount that they would have received if assigned to the alcohol condition.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (water)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the water control condition will receive a glass of chilled water in volume of liquid comparable to the amount that they would have received if assigned to the alcohol or placebo condition.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alcohol</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Alcohol condition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo (non-alcoholic beverage)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo condition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be between the ages of 21-50

          -  Moderate or heavy drinkers based on classifications from the
             Quantity-Frequency-Variability Questionnaire (QFV; Cahalan, Cisin, &amp; Crossley, 1969)

          -  Self-identify with the sexual orientation equivalent of a 3 or higher on the Kinsey
             Scale (Kinsey et al., 1948; Kinsey et al., 1953), a 7-point scale used to assess
             self-identified sexual orientation, with zero representing exclusive heterosexuality
             and 6 representing exclusive homosexuality.

          -  Participants must also have engaged in sex with other men at least once/month for the
             past 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  a) under the age of 21 or b) do not have a government issued ID or c) are not able to
             provide medical records or other official documents with a birthdate (e.g., birth
             certificate), accompanied by a photo ID

          -  Scores ≥ 5 on the Brief Michigan Alcoholism Screening Test (Brief MAST; Pokorny,
             Miller, &amp; Kaplan, 1972)

          -  Any ASSIST substance involvement score of ≥ 27 (National Institute on Drug Abuse;
             http://www.drugabuse.gov/sites/default/files/pdf/nmassist.pdf)

          -  Score ≥ 15 on the Patient Health Questionnaire-8 (PHQ-8; Kroenke et al., 2009)

          -  4 subscales of the Brief Symptom Inventory (BSI; Derogatis &amp; Melisaratos, 1979),
             Somatization, Obsession-compulsion, Paranoid ideation, and Psychoticism will be
             administered; Individuals experiencing severe psychological health symptoms (score &gt; 2
             on any item) will be further questioned by a research assistant in order to determine
             if there is psychiatric distress or problems present

          -  Report current medications or current medical problems (e.g., liver disorders, heart
             disease, HIV+ serostatus) that contraindicate alcohol use using the Medical Condition
             Questionnaire; Participants who confirm that they are using (i.e., have used in the
             past week) any prescribed drugs for which alcohol use is contraindicated
             (http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/drug_Aa.html) will be excluded.
             Participants also currently regularly taking (i.e., past 24 hours) any herbals and
             vitamins, including sleep aids (chamomile) and herbal preparations for anxiety and
             depression (Kava Kava or St. John's Wort) that contraindicate alcohol use will be
             excluded

          -  Persons with cognitive and or psychomotor deficits will be excluded from the
             experiment (based on RA and PI determination)

          -  Endorse currently being in a committed, exclusive monogamous relationship

          -  Report treatment for emotional or substance use disorders (defined by current
             treatment or treatment in the past 3 months) or recent history of significant alcohol
             problems as indicated by inpatient/outpatient alcohol treatment or alcohol self-help
             group attendance (e.g., AA) within the past 3 years.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steve A Maisto, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Syracuse University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Simons, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of South Dakota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tibor P.A. Palfai, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steve A Maisto, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(315) 425-6546</phone>
    <email>samaisto@syr.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tibor P.A. Palfai, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(617) 353-9345</phone>
      <email>palfai@bu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Syracuse University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13244</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steve A Maisto, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>315-425-6546</phone>
      <email>samaisto@syr.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Dakota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vermillion</city>
        <state>South Dakota</state>
        <zip>57069</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>men who have sex with men</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

