<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03360422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201701367 N</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UH2AA026214-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03360422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ANCHORS Study: UH2 Project</brief_title>
  <acronym>ANCHORS</acronym>
  <official_title>Advancing New Computer-based Help On Risky Sex (ANCHORS) Study: UH2 Project</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      According to the National HIV/AIDS Strategy, men who have sex with men (MSM), young adults,
      Black and Latino men and people in the Southern U.S. are at highest HIV risk and should be
      targeted with cost-effective, scalable interventions. The study team propose a synergistic
      mobile intervention to reduce alcohol and HIV risk in young adult MSM that combines 3
      efficacious approaches.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      New prevention efforts must address alcohol and HIV and be directed to the highest-risk
      groups. While interventions have targeted MSM, few have targeted young MSM specifically.
      Young people and MSM bring particular challenges. Thus, it is important that prevention be
      targeted to them and developed with their input. To that end, the goal of this project is to
      lay the groundwork for a synergistic, mobile intervention to reduce alcohol use and risky sex
      and prevent HIV among young adult MSM. This research study is made up of three related
      sub-projects: 1) a web-based survey; 2) a series of focus groups and 3) a small, preliminary
      acceptability and usability to study to test the mobile intervention. The proposed
      intervention to be tested on a preliminary basis in this study combines brief motivational
      intervention with daily interactive voice response (IVR) monitoring including personalized
      feedback. Ultimately, this combined intervention will also include pre-exposure prophylaxis
      (PrEP), however there will be no medication in this particular study. Each of these
      components has efficacy in enhancing treatment adherence, reducing alcohol and/or HIV risk
      but requires other interventions to maximize its potential benefit. Combining them will
      capitalize on the strength of each, leading to a higher impact alcohol and HIV preventive
      intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantity of alcohol consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrospective self-report from past 1-3 months on web survey</time_frame>
    <description>Determine levels of alcohol consumption in study population</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>High-risk sexual behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrospective self-report from past 1-3 months on web survey</time_frame>
    <description>Determine levels of unprotected sex during and outside of drinking occasions in study population</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Study participant opinions on intervention content</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one month</time_frame>
    <description>Interactive Voice Response System Questions are Yes no responses to focusing on the degree to which it is culturally appropriate for study population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">723</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1-infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Survey group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Collect alcohol and sexual activity data via web survey from 683 young MSM to yield normative data for the alcohol and HIV preventive intervention in a follow-up study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Focus Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 young MSM who drink regularly to inform the content of the alcohol and HIV preventive intervention tested in the UH3 phase and ensure the intervention is culturally appropriate for MSM.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usability Study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 young adult MSM will test the mobile intervention in development for 30 days in order to establish usability, acceptability and correct any functionality issues.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Respondents meeting inclusion criteria will be informed they were selected for the longer survey and continue to the survey. Upon completion, the survey will generate a study identification (ID) that respondents will provide to study staff with additional contact information via phone, text or email to be compensated</description>
    <arm_group_label>Survey group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Focus Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Usability Study</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Focus Group</intervention_name>
    <description>After informed consent, participants will complete the web-based intervention component in development. Afterward, participants will be engaged by an experienced facilitator in a discussion of aspects of the intervention they liked and disliked and suggestions they have for enhancing its cultural appropriateness to young MSM.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Focus Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usability study</intervention_name>
    <description>After informed consent, participants will utilize the mobile intervention in development for 30 days to establish usability, acceptability and correct any functionality issues.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usability Study</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Web-survey:

          -  Male sex

          -  Young adult age

          -  Ability to read and write English

          -  Recent sexual activity with another man

        Focus group: All inclusion criteria will be the same as the web survey

        Usability phase:

          -  Past-month alcohol use

          -  Recent sexual activity with another man

          -  Willingness to try pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Focus group:

          -  A current undergraduate or graduate student at any level in one of the 3 departments
             that make up the College of Health and Human Performance (HHP) at the University of
             Florida (UF), where Dr. Leeman's faculty appointment is.

          -  Do not want to engage in open discussion regarding substance use or sexual
             activity/orientation in a group setting. It will be possible for participants to
             contribute to focus group discussions without providing detailed information about
             their own substance use or sexual activity, however focus group participants must have
             a degree of openness to discussing these topics with others. These groups will take
             place with 6-7 other people and some people may be made uncomfortable by the
             discussions that may take place with regard to participants' drinking, substance use
             or sexual behavior.

          -  Not willing to be recorded via an electronic recording device
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Leeman, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert Leeman, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>352-294-1808</phone>
    <email>robert.leeman@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MSM, young adult</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

