<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03360058</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GN17DI319</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03360058</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Small Talk Big Difference</brief_title>
  <acronym>STBD</acronym>
  <official_title>OBESITY AND TYPE 2 DIABETES - RAISING THE ISSUE OF WEIGHT MANAGEMENT IN PRIMARY CARE</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Glasgow</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To ensure that patients who are overweight or obese and have type 2 diabetes are identified,
      receive personalised diabetes care, have the issue of weight raised and explained in a
      non-judgemental manner by staff in primary care, and are referred on to weight management
      services as appropriate ensuring equity of access across NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde.

      Specific aims of the whole project:

        1. To improve GP/ primary care staff knowledge of the evidence base for the management of
           diabetes when there is co-existing obesity and local care pathways

        2. To increase GP/ primary care staff knowledge of and confidence in their role in raising
           the issue of weight management,

        3. To improve primary care referral rates of appropriate patients who are overweight or
           obese and have type 2 diabetes, and are &quot;ready to change&quot; to NHS funded weight
           management services

        4. To improve patient uptake of and attendance at NHS funded weight management services NB
           This is a service evaluation of a training programme being delivered by NHS Greater
           Glasgow and Clyde Health Improvement. Full ethical approvals are being sought due to the
           randomised design and so that results can be generalised and published.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Glasgow and Clyde weight management service (GCWMS) delivers a specialist
      multi-disciplinary, multi-component weight management programme throughout the Glasgow and
      Clyde area. In a recent evaluation of the service, the authors highlighted that 27% of the
      patients who are referred to the programme do not opt into the service. This describes
      patients who are referred via their GP practice and do not contact the service to opt into an
      initial assessment.

      Similarly, Brook et al described initial uptake and engagement of a small weight management
      programme of 502 patients. In addition to completing an extensive questionnaire, patients
      were requested to call to make an appointment with the service personally. Of those referred
      to the programme, 46% did not opt in.

      Engaging patients in a weight management programme is especially difficult, even when the
      intervention is provided via the primary care route. For example, The Counterweight Project,
      a weight management programme delivered via the GP surgery, has been taken up by a number of
      surgeries in Scotland, however after 2 years, one fifth of enlisted practices failed to enrol
      patients onto the programme.

      Even when GP's do address matters of weight related behaviour, there is often disagreement
      from the patient that the topic has been raised. In a sample of 456 patients, 39% of patients
      disagreed with GP reporting about the content of the discussion during consultations
      regarding weight, diet and physical activity. In particular, GP's reported more occasions of
      discussing weight than patients in 12.5% of consultations. Patients' likeliness to engage in
      a weight management programme is also influenced by practice endorsement and opinion of the
      GP of the intervention available in addition to other factors: clear understanding of the
      programme, clear understanding of the programme goals, structured pro-active follow-up and
      perception of positive outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effectiveness of an online training programme, practice implementation toolkit and face to face training for primary care staff</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>which will be measured as number of patient referrals and patient attendance at NHS funded weight management services</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implementation/ Normalization</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>NOMAD questionnaire will be used to ascertain how STBD impacts on primary care clinicians work</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of diabetes reviews with recorded weight management discussion in LES template</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Training uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>o Training uptake - online, face to face and experiential
By practice
By GP and practice Nurse
By diabetes lead</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Weight Management</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate access to STBD training materials</arm_group_label>
    <description>In order to allow us to assess the impact of the training, practices will be randomly assigned to either immediate or delayed access (after 4 months) to the training resources.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed access to STBD training materials</arm_group_label>
    <description>In order to allow us to assess the impact of the training, practices will be randomly assigned to either immediate or delayed access (after 4 months) to the training resources.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Small Talk Big Difference Immediate access training</intervention_name>
    <description>Immediate access to 1 hour online training and supporting print materials for implementation in primary care practice</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate access to STBD training materials</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Delayed access to Small Talk Big Difference</intervention_name>
    <description>Delayed access (by 4 months) to 1 hour online training and supporting print materials for implementation in primary care practice</description>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed access to STBD training materials</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Primary care clinicians - mainly GP's and practice nurses - responsible for providing
        weight management advice (and onward NHS referral) to patients with type 2 diabetes
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  GP practices in NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde which:

          -  Have a contract for local enhanced services for long term conditions (Diabetes)

          -  Have a unique clinical database (i.e. not shared with another practice)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &quot;17c&quot; practices (those with a separate contract for long term conditions)

          -  Those practices with a database shared with another practice (8 practices in area)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Logue, MBChB PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Glasgow University and NHS GGC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katriona Brooksbank, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0141 330 2627</phone>
    <email>katriona.brooksbank@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Glasgow Cardiovascular Research Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <state>Scotland</state>
        <zip>G12 8TA</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katriona Brooksbank, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0141 330 2627</phone>
      <email>katriona.brooksbank@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jennifer Logue, MBChB PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0141 330 3375</phone>
      <email>jennifer.logue@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 30, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>motivational techniques</keyword>
  <keyword>primary care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

