<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03360071</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00107909</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03360071</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Novel Biologic Therapy for Perennial Allergic Rhinitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-blind, Prospective, Parallel Group Evaluation of a Novel Biologic Therapy for Perennial Allergic Rhinitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, parallel-group, double-blind, phase 2, single center, proof-of-concept
      study which will evaluate the effect of a preparation of FDA approved allergens (PMA) used as
      a sub-cutaneously administered immunotherapy for the management of allergic rhinitis
      (perennial and seasonal).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, parallel-group, double-blind, phase 2, single center, proof-of-concept
      study which will evaluate the effect of a proprietory mixed preparation of FDA approved
      allergens (PMA) used as a sub-cutaneously administered immunotherapy for the management of
      allergic rhinitis (perennial and seasonal). Participating study subjects will be required to
      manifest the signs and symptoms of allergic rhinitis and test positive to at least six
      allergens using a multi aeroallergen screen at the time of study recruitment . All subjects
      will undergo standard allergen skin prick testing using six Multi-Test® PC skin prick test
      devices (Lincoln Diagnostics, Decator, IL) or comparable skin testing technique for a total
      of 48 Skin Prick Test (SPT). Approximately 36 total subjects will be enrolled.

      Following a successful screening study visit and two week medication washout period, a 8 week
      treatment period will be initiated with bi-weekly study visits being undertaken, through to
      the end of immunotherapy, for assessment of therapeutic response and safety evaluations.
      Efficacy evaluation will be monitored using validated instruments that assess study subject
      clinical response, physician global assessment, and medication use. A safety assessment will
      be undertaken one month following completion of treatment.

      At the screening visit (Screening Visit) a potential study subject will be required to
      fulfill the requirements of the study inclusion and exclusion criteria, will have a clinical
      evaluation including medical history and physical examination, blood draw and performance of
      skin testing. The study subject will then abstain from using intranasal steroids and
      antihistamines for two weeks and then return to the clinic for administration of
      sub-cutaneous PMA and post-treatment in-clinic safety evaluation. The latter evaluation
      period will comprise approximately 60 minutes to assess the study subject's response to PMA
      immunotherapy. Follow up clinic study visits will continue bi-weekly through 8 weeks and at
      each of these visits the study subject will receive increasing doses of PMA immunotherapy and
      will be evaluated for safety. Twice weekly clinical evaluation will also be performed.
      Following the final administration of PMA immunotherapy, a one month follow-up safety and
      clinical efficacy evaluation will be conducted by telephone or in the clinic. The duration of
      the study will be approximately 14 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 19, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Combined symptoms and rescue medication use score</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate whether there is a difference in the signs and symptoms of moderate to severe allergic rhinitis when treated with a proprietory mixed preparation of FDA approved allergens, administered sub-cutaneously over a 8-week period, versus the response to placebo and standard of care.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary clinical survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Mini RQLQ use will be followed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rescue medication use</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Rescue medication use will be followed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>continuous review of safety up to 14 week</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and adverse events (AES) will be followed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Allergic Rhinitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allergen Immunotherapy Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allergen Immunotherapy Extract</intervention_name>
    <description>Allergen Immunotherapy treatment mixture to be delivered subcutaneously</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allergen Immunotherapy Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allergen Immunotherapy Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Allergen Immunotherapy Control Solution to be delivered subcutaneously</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, the subject is capable of understanding and
             complying with protocol requirements.

          -  The subject signs and dates a written, informed consent form and any required privacy
             authorization prior to the initiation of any study procedures.

          -  The subject is a male or a non-pregnant, non-lactating female between the ages of 18
             and 65.

          -  The subject is actively manifesting symptoms and signs of moderate to severe Perennial
             Allergic Rhinitis (PAR) with or without Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis (SAR) component
             defined as score of at least 28 on the Rhinoconjunctivitis Quality of Life
             Questionnaire (RQLQ) and 6 on the Total Nasal Symptom Score (TNSS) scale. Scores will
             be determined on the first and second visit (after the 14 day medication washout
             period). Both scores exceeding their threshold on either day will qualify.

          -  Skin test strongly positive (wheal at least 5mm diameter and 2mm greater than negative
             control) to at least 6 of 48 allergy skin prick tests including at least one species
             of dust mite.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The subject has received any investigational compound within 30 days prior to
             screening.

          -  The subject has received allergen immunotherapy or SLIT in a previous clinical study
             or as a therapeutic agent within the past two years.

          -  The subject has a history or clinical manifestations of significant medical conditions
             (cardiovascular, hepatic, infectious or renal disease, etc.) which in the opinion of
             the investigator renders them unacceptable study subjects.

          -  The subject has a history of drug abuse (defined as any chronic illicit drug use) or a
             history of alcohol abuse within 5 years prior to the screening visit.

          -  The subject is required to take excluded medications listed in Section 6.3.

          -  If female, the subject is pregnant or lactating or intending to become pregnant
             before, during, or within 1 month after participating in this study; or intending to
             donate ova during such time period.

          -  Subjects found to have on physical exam significant nasal polyps, septal deviation or
             infectious sinusitis.

          -  The subject has a history of allergic rhinitis but is not currently manifesting active
             signs and symptoms of the disorder.

          -  Subject has a history of cancer, other than squamous cell or basal cell carcinoma of
             the skin that has not been in full remission for at least 5 years prior to Screening.
             (A history of treated Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia (CIN) I, II, or CIN III is
             allowed.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeanne Hoddinott, RN</last_name>
    <phone>410-550-8017</phone>
    <email>hoddin1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jody Tversky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>410-550-2301</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeanne Hoddinott, RN</last_name>
      <phone>410-550-8017</phone>
      <email>hoddin1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tammy Fallis</last_name>
      <phone>410-550-2301</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic, Perennial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

