<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03360825</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-006680</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03360825</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Electrophysiological Comparison of mAP and mADM Using EMG</brief_title>
  <official_title>Electrophysiological Comparison of mAP and mADM Using EMG</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this clinical investigation is to examine a prototype of a quantitative
      monitoring instrument that will meet most, if not all, of the clinical requirements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a blinded, single-center, prospective study in patients during surgery, requiring use
      of neuromuscular blockade. Neurostimulation will be used to monitor objective responses, as
      per current clinical routine. Data collection of Tetragraph EMG responses will be unavailable
      to the clinician for clinical decision-making, as per current clinical routine, but will be
      stored on the interfaced SD card.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 9, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 9, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary performance assessment of TetraGraph device</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Agreement between the mAP and mADM EMG based TOF ratios</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary performance assessment of TetraGraph device</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Agreement between the mAP and mADM EMG based TOF counts</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary performance assessment of TetraGraph device</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between stimulation current and T1 twitch height in the two muscles</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary performance assessment of TetraGraph device</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of EMG to the quantitative AMG monitor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TetraGraph</intervention_name>
    <description>The TetraGraph is a dedicated neuromuscular stimulator / recorder intended to evoke, record, and analyze muscle action potentials during surgical procedures</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population for this study includes patients receiving neuromuscular blocking
        agents during a surgical procedure.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Age 18 years or older.

          2. American Society of Anesthesiology (ASA) physical status I-III criteria (Table I).

          3. Subject has provided verbal consent

          4. BMI &lt;39

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Presence of an underlying neuromuscular disease.

          2. Presence of renal or hepatic disease.

          3. Subject has open skin sores in the locations needed for electrode application
             (forearms).

          4. Patients on oral anticholinesterase, anti-seizure medications, and magnesium sulfate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>J R Renew</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gätke MR, Viby-Mogensen J, Rosenstock C, Jensen FS, Skovgaard LT. Postoperative muscle paralysis after rocuronium: less residual block when acceleromyography is used. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2002 Feb;46(2):207-13.</citation>
    <PMID>11942873</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cammu G, De Witte J, De Veylder J, Byttebier G, Vandeput D, Foubert L, Vandenbroucke G, Deloof T. Postoperative residual paralysis in outpatients versus inpatients. Anesth Analg. 2006 Feb;102(2):426-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16428537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim KS, Lew SH, Cho HY, Cheong MA. Residual paralysis induced by either vecuronium or rocuronium after reversal with pyridostigmine. Anesth Analg. 2002 Dec;95(6):1656-60, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>12456433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berg H, Roed J, Viby-Mogensen J, Mortensen CR, Engbaek J, Skovgaard LT, Krintel JJ. Residual neuromuscular block is a risk factor for postoperative pulmonary complications. A prospective, randomised, and blinded study of postoperative pulmonary complications after atracurium, vecuronium and pancuronium. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 1997 Oct;41(9):1095-1103.</citation>
    <PMID>9366929</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy GS, Szokol JW, Marymont JH, Greenberg SB, Avram MJ, Vender JS. Residual neuromuscular blockade and critical respiratory events in the postanesthesia care unit. Anesth Analg. 2008 Jul;107(1):130-7. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e31816d1268.</citation>
    <PMID>18635478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy GS, Szokol JW, Marymont JH, Greenberg SB, Avram MJ, Vender JS, Nisman M. Intraoperative acceleromyographic monitoring reduces the risk of residual neuromuscular blockade and adverse respiratory events in the postanesthesia care unit. Anesthesiology. 2008 Sep;109(3):389-98. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318182af3b.</citation>
    <PMID>18719436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy GS, Szokol JW, Avram MJ, Greenberg SB, Marymont JH, Vender JS, Gray J, Landry E, Gupta DK. Intraoperative acceleromyography monitoring reduces symptoms of muscle weakness and improves quality of recovery in the early postoperative period. Anesthesiology. 2011 Nov;115(5):946-54. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3182342840.</citation>
    <PMID>21946094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy GS, Brull SJ. Residual neuromuscular block: lessons unlearned. Part I: definitions, incidence, and adverse physiologic effects of residual neuromuscular block. Anesth Analg. 2010 Jul;111(1):120-8. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3181da832d. Epub 2010 May 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20442260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hemmerling TM, Le N. Brief review: Neuromuscular monitoring: an update for the clinician. Can J Anaesth. 2007 Jan;54(1):58-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17197470</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brull SJ, Silverman DG. Visual and tactile assessment of neuromuscular fade. Anesth Analg. 1993 Aug;77(2):352-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8394051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grayling M, Sweeney BP. Recovery from neuromuscular blockade: a survey of practice. Anaesthesia. 2007 Aug;62(8):806-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17635429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claudius C, Viby-Mogensen J. Acceleromyography for use in scientific and clinical practice: a systematic review of the evidence. Anesthesiology. 2008 Jun;108(6):1117-40. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318173f62f. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18497614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fuchs-Buder T, Claudius C, Skovgaard LT, Eriksson LI, Mirakhur RK, Viby-Mogensen J; 8th International Neuromuscular Meeting. Good clinical research practice in pharmacodynamic studies of neuromuscular blocking agents II: the Stockholm revision. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2007 Aug;51(7):789-808.</citation>
    <PMID>17635389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Connelly NR, Silverman DG, O'Connor TZ, Brull SJ. Subjective responses to train-of-four and double burst stimulation in awake patients. Anesth Analg. 1990 Jun;70(6):650-3.</citation>
    <PMID>2160781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>CHURCHILL-DAVIDSON HC, RICHARDSON AT. The action of decamethonium iodide (C.10) in myasthenia gravis. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1952 May;15(2):129-33.</citation>
    <PMID>14928082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liang SS, Stewart PA, Phillips S. An ipsilateral comparison of acceleromyography and electromyography during recovery from nondepolarizing neuromuscular block under general anesthesia in humans. Anesth Analg. 2013 Aug;117(2):373-9. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3182937fc4. Epub 2013 Jul 2. Erratum in: Anesth Analg. 2017 May;124(5):1745.</citation>
    <PMID>23821356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips S, Stewart PA, Freelander N, Heller G. Comparison of evoked electromyography in three muscles of the hand during recovery from non-depolarising neuromuscular blockade. Anaesth Intensive Care. 2012 Jul;40(4):690-6.</citation>
    <PMID>22813498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>J. Ross Renew, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, College of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

