<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03368469</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-001007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03368469</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS) in Children and Adolescents With Epilepsy and Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of the Tolerability and Efficacy of Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS) in Children and Adolescents With Epilepsy and Comorbid Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study seeks to obtain preliminary signal of the tolerability and efficacy of
      transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) for depressive symptoms in a sample of
      adolescents with depression and epilepsy. Additionally, effects of tDCS will be assessed via
      electroencephalographic, cognitive, and psychosocial measures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) has been investigated extensively in recent
      years for the treatment of depression. Meta-analysis of individual patient data indicates
      that tDCS results in improvement in depressive symptoms, with efficacy comparable to
      antidepressant medications and repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS), while
      tDCS offers advantages over other treatments, including side effect profile, cost, and
      portability. tDCS has been employed to a more limited extent in children and adolescents for
      psychiatric conditions other than depression, as well as in both adults and children with
      epilepsy, with excellent tolerability and a mild adverse effect profile. The proposed
      protocol aims to extend the use of tDCS for treatment of depression in children with epilepsy
      (CWE), a population with a very high prevalence of depression and a significant need for
      additional treatment options, particularly nonpharmacologic treatments, due to challenges
      with the use of antidepressant medications and other non-invasive brain stimulation (NIBS)
      techniques in CWE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Depression Rating Scale - Revised (CDRS-R) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>clinician-rated continuous measure of depression severity based on participant and parent interviews</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Depression Rating Scale - Revised (CDRS-R) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>clinician-rated continuous measure of depression severity based on participant and parent interviews</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptoms - Adolescent - Self-Report (QIDS-A17-SR) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1, day 5, day 10, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>participant-reported continuous measure of depression severity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>tDCS Adverse Effects Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1-10, 2 weeks, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>standardized self-report questionnaire for active reporting of adverse effects; will be used to calculate incidence of all adverse effects (AEs) and severe adverse effects (SAEs) as well as incidence of specific AEs/SAEs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1, day 5, day 10, 2 weeks, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure of suicidal ideation and behavior based on clinician interview</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>day 5, 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>measure of manic symptoms based on clinician interview/observation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Affective Reactivity Index (ARI)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>parent- and participant-report questionnaires regarding symptoms of irritability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mayo Seizure Frequency Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>parent- and participant-report questionnaires regarding seizure frequency</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liverpool Seizure Severity Scale (1998 revision)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>parent-/participant-report questionnaire regarding seizure severity and quality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of Pediatric Epilepsy Scale (IPES)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>parent-report questionnaire regarding impact of epilepsy of quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life in Epilepsy Inventory for Adolescents (QOLIE-AD-48)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>participant-report questionnaire regarding impact of epilepsy of quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NIH Toolbox® for Assessment of Neurological and Behavioral Function</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>validated and age-normed computer-administered battery of measures assessing cognitive functioning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electroencephalography (EEG)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>objective electrophysiologic data on brain activity; a board-certified epileptologist will manually quantify the maximal number of spike-wave discharges per 20-second recording, the longest run of epileptiform discharges, and, if sleep EEG is obtained, the spike-wave index; additionally, broadband EEG will be obtained to assess indices of cortical excitability, such as relationships between slow oscillations, interictal epileptiform discharges, and sleep architecture</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Generalized Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>transcranial direct current stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Transcranial direct current stimulation (35 sq cm anode over left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, 35 sq cm cathode over right supraorbital area, 1 mA current, 20 min per treatment session, 1 session per day, 10 treatment sessions over two weeks)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>transcranial direct current stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The Soterix Medical 1×1 Low Intensity Transcranial DC Stimulator Model 1300A is an investigational device manufactured by Soterix Medical, Inc. (New York, NY, USA). It is designed for use in noninvasive transcranial stimulation of the brain by delivering low-intensity electrical current to the scalp through two electrodes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>transcranial direct current stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Soterix Medical Model 1300A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of generalized epilepsy (confirmed by neurologist)

          -  Diagnosis of depressive disorder (confirmed by psychiatrist), with CDRS-R score ≥ 40

          -  Parent/guardian ability to provide written informed consent in English, with
             child/adolescent participant able to provide assent (for participants &lt;18 years of
             age), or participant ability to provide written informed consent in English (for
             participants ≥18 years of age)

          -  Antidepressant medications (SSRI or SNRI) permitted, provided that no dosing change
             has occurred in two months prior to baseline assessments; antidepressant medication
             not required for enrollment

          -  AED medications (with exceptions listed below in exclusion criteria) permitted,
             provided that no change in AED regimen has occurred in two months prior to baseline
             assessments (except for weight/growth-related dosing changes); AED not required for
             enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of pacemaker or metallic implant (with the exception of orthodontic hardware)

          -  Prior surgical intervention for epilepsy

          -  More than one generalized tonic-clonic (GTC) seizure during two months prior to
             enrollment

          -  AED regimen change during two months prior to baseline assessments (except dosing
             adjustments made strictly due to growth/weight change)

          -  Antidepressant medication change during two months prior to baseline assessments

          -  Lifetime history of manic/hypomanic episode or psychotic disorder

          -  Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) diagnosis

          -  Documented history of intellectual disability (documented full-scale IQ greater than
             two standard deviations below mean)

          -  Current or recent (two months prior to baseline assessments) active substance use
             disorder

          -  Imminent risk of suicide or medically serious self-injurious behavior (as evaluated by
             board-certified child and adolescent psychiatrist)

          -  Current pregnancy or positive urine pregnancy test

          -  Prohibited concomitant medications include: regularly scheduled benzodiazepines
             (except clobazam); barbiturates; neuroleptic/antipsychotic medications; lithium.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul E Croarkin, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marjorie Gresbrink, MA</last_name>
    <phone>507-255-0624</phone>
    <email>gresbrink.marjorie@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Paul E Croarkin, DO</last_name>
    <phone>(507) 293-2557</phone>
    <email>croarkin.paul@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marjorie A Gresbrink, MA</last_name>
      <phone>507-255-0624</phone>
      <email>gresbrink.marjorie@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Paul E Croarkin, DO</last_name>
      <phone>(507) 293-2557</phone>
      <email>croarkin.paul@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee JC, Lewis CP, Daskalakis ZJ, Croarkin PE. Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation: Considerations for Research in Adolescent Depression. Front Psychiatry. 2017 Jun 7;8:91. doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2017.00091. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28638351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hameed MQ, Dhamne SC, Gersner R, Kaye HL, Oberman LM, Pascual-Leone A, Rotenberg A. Transcranial Magnetic and Direct Current Stimulation in Children. Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep. 2017 Feb;17(2):11. doi: 10.1007/s11910-017-0719-0. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28229395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muszkat D, Polanczyk GV, Dias TG, Brunoni AR. Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation in Child and Adolescent Psychiatry. J Child Adolesc Psychopharmacol. 2016 Sep;26(7):590-7. doi: 10.1089/cap.2015.0172. Epub 2016 Mar 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27027666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Godinho MM, Junqueira DR, Castro ML, Loke Y, Golder S, Neto HP. Safety of transcranial direct current stimulation: Evidence based update 2016. Brain Stimul. 2017 Sep - Oct;10(5):983-985. doi: 10.1016/j.brs.2017.07.001. Epub 2017 Jul 8.</citation>
    <PMID>28751225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krishnan C, Santos L, Peterson MD, Ehinger M. Safety of noninvasive brain stimulation in children and adolescents. Brain Stimul. 2015 Jan-Feb;8(1):76-87. doi: 10.1016/j.brs.2014.10.012. Epub 2014 Oct 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25499471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 1, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul E. Croarkin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transcranial</keyword>
  <keyword>Stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy, Generalized</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

