<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00252213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1218-02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>I704.358</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00252213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BELIEVE Study: Nesiritide and Post Myocardial Infarction Left Ventricular Modeling</brief_title>
  <official_title>B-Type Natriuretic Peptide (Nesiritide) and Post Myocardial Infarction Left Ventricular Remodeling: Pilot Study Assessing Safety</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done to determine the effects (good and bad) of intravenous infusion of a
      human brain natriuretic peptide (BNP), Natrecor (nesiritide), a hormone produced by the heart
      in persons who have just suffered a heart attack. The human BNP, Natrecor (nesiritide) has
      been approved by the United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) to be given
      intravenously for the management of acute heart failure. It is unknown if human BNP may have
      good effects on the pumping function of the heart after a heart attack.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the 72 hours of intravenous (IV) nesiritide infusion, if the systolic blood pressure
      decreases to less than 90 mmHg for 5 minutes, the coronary care unit (CCU) sx will be
      notified and if the systolic blood pressure has not increased to &gt; or equal to 90 mmHg within
      45 minutes, the nesiritide infusion will be stopped. All patients will receive other medical
      therapy as determined appropriate by the physician except for angiotensin converting enzyme
      inhibitor (ACEI), which will be started 24 hours after IV nesiritide. Lisinopril will be
      started 24 hours after the start of IV nesiritide at an initial dose of 2.5 mg and to be
      titrated up by the participants' physician according to their clinical status. The window for
      the lisinopril doses would be +/- 1 hour.

      Patients with any signs or symptoms of post revascularization ischemia will be discontinued
      from the study.

      Blood for the measurement of renin, angiotensin II (Ang II), aldosterone (Aldo), endothelin
      (ET)-1, norepinephrine, atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP), brain natriuretic peptide (BNP),
      cGMP, C reactive protein, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-alpha, matrix metalloproteinase (MMP)-2
      and tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase (TIMP)-2 will be drawn before the initiation of IV
      nesiritide, six hours into the infusion before the initiation of ACEI and just before
      completion of the 72 hour infusion. The window for the blood draw for the six hour time point
      would be +/- 1 hour and the 72 hour time point would be +/-1 hour or just prior to discharge
      but not less than 66 hours.

      MUGA will be performed within 24 hours after the initiation of the IV nesiritide to assess
      systolic and diastolic volumes and LV ejection fraction (EF).

      Follow up at 4 weeks:

      All patients, whether they complete the entire 72 hours of the nesiritide infusion or not,
      will return 1 month later for a repeat MUGA and blood draw for the neurohumoral profiling and
      pregnancy test if required by nuclear cardiology. The visit window for the one month return
      would be 30 to 40 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    recruitment of subjects was halted prematurely. recruiting subjects halted prematurely
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>August 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the safety of nesiritide at two different dose levels of 0.003 µg/Kg/min and 0.006 µg/Kg/min focusing on the occurrence of hypotension (yes versus no)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dosing finding comparing the efficacy of 0.003 µg/Kg/min and 0.006 µg/Kg/min on the suppression of aldosterone at 6 hours after the start of infusion as compared to baseline, as a marker of the neurohumoral activity of BNP</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the safety of the two doses on left ventricular (LV) remodeling by determining the LV volume and function by multiple gate acquistion scan (MUGA)</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>24</enrollment>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Human BNP</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with acute ST elevation myocardial infarction of at least &gt; 2mV ST elevation
             in two or more anterior precordial leads, with successful revascularization
             (Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction [TIMI] grade 3 flow) of the lesion within 24
             hours of chest pain as documented by coronary angiogram.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Horng H. Chen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 10, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 9, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 9, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 11, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Natriuretic Peptide, Brain</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

