<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03032068</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-1051</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03032068</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Home Monitoring After Primary Total Knee Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility of Home Monitoring After Primary Total Knee Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Cleveland Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Home monitoring technologies have recently emerged in many different areas of healthcare.
      These technologies are being used to provide rehabilitation to patients, and to prevent,
      identify, and manage complications. The investigators are proposing a method to monitor and
      communicate with patients during the first 12 weeks after total knee arthroplasty (TKA) using
      an electronic home-based patient monitoring system with unique connectivity capabilities and
      prescriptive controls. The investigators will prospectively, electronically capture range of
      motion and gait parameters at specified intervals using Bluetooth sensors worn by the
      patient. The unique in-home patient monitoring platform will be utilized by 10 TKA patients
      once they return home following surgery. The investigators hypothesize that the use of an
      internet based home patient monitoring technology platform will reliably provide information
      related to the patients' pain and function and enhance patient feedback and communication
      after TKA. The hypothesis will be tested with the following aim: 1) To test the reliability
      of all technology utilized within the patient's home including but not limited to the
      sensors, the communication controller, the patient interface (Android tablet) and the
      internet by prospectively comparing between data collected through the home monitoring
      technology and traditional clinical measurements taken during physical therapy and surgical
      follow-up visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over one million primary total hip and total knee arthroplasty (TKA) surgeries are being
      performed annually in the U.S. and this number is expected to increase over the next seven
      years, along with a simultaneously projected shortage of trained orthopaedic surgeons to care
      for these patients. This proposal addresses the optimization of the surgeons' clinical time
      through utilization of innovative home based technologies to monitor and communicate with
      patients during the first 12 weeks after total knee arthroplasty. This will be accomplished
      by establishing home monitoring connectivity with novel technology and measure validated
      patient-reported outcomes, knee ROM and gait parameters in a postoperative TKA patient's
      native living environment. It will allow the investigators to prospectively, electronically
      capture clinically relevant TKA outcomes at the patient's home and provide insight into
      postoperative rehabilitation progress, predictors of suboptimal clinical outcomes, and guide
      future randomized controlled trial development to improve outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>At-Home Monitoring Reliability, measured as the proportion of actual data received from the patient's home compared to the amount of data expected over the 12 week study period.</measure>
    <time_frame>daily, from the date of discharge until the 12 week postoperative follow-up appointment has occurred</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will determine the reliability of the at-home monitoring technology for recording and transmitting data from the patient's home to the healthcare provider. This will be measured for each patient individually and then combined to form an aggregate measurement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>At-Home Monitoring Accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>Once preoperatively and then postoperatively at the following time points: 4 Homecare visits within the first 4 weeks postoperatively, a 4 week follow-up, 8 week follow-up, and 12 week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Data recorded by the sensors and home monitoring application are verified manually during clinical visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rehab Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Percentage of exercises completed 2-3 times daily, from the date of discharge up to approximately 4 weeks postoperatively when outpatient physical therapy begins</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of required at-home therapy exercises completed each session, as well as the total percentage completed during all home therapy sessions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee Range of Motion</measure>
    <time_frame>Once preoperatively then postoperatively 2-3 times daily from the date of discharge until the 12 week postoperative follow-up appointment has occurred</time_frame>
    <description>Knee range of motion is recorded daily using sensors above and below the knee. This data will be compared to the knee range of motion measurements recorded by a therapist during postoperative home care or clinical visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed Up and Go Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Once preoperatively then postoperatively 2-3 times daily from the date of discharge until the 12 week postoperative follow-up appointment has occurred</time_frame>
    <description>The time that a patient takes to rise from a chair, walk three meters, turn around, walk back to the chair, and sit down. This time will be recorded electronically by the patient at home and compared to the times recorded by the therapist during home care and clinical visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Once preoperatively then postoperatively 2-3 times daily from the date of discharge until the 12 week postoperative follow-up appointment has occurred</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Analog Scale for Pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) - KOOS Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Once preoperatively then postoperatively once weekly from the date of discharge until the 12 week follow-up appointment has occurred</time_frame>
    <description>We will assess KOOS Pain using 9 questions, each response given a point value from 0 to 4. The sum of these points will total between 0 and 36 points, where 0 means no pain and 36 is extreme pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) - KOOS Function</measure>
    <time_frame>Once preoperatively then postoperatively once weekly from the date of discharge until the 12 week follow-up appointment has occurred</time_frame>
    <description>We will assess KOOS Function using 7 questions, each response given a point value from 0 to 4. The sum of these points will total between 0 and 28 points, where 0 means no functional difficulty and 28 is extreme difficulty.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) - KOOS QOL</measure>
    <time_frame>Once preoperatively then postoperatively once weekly from the date of discharge until the 12 week follow-up appointment has occurred</time_frame>
    <description>We will assess KOOS QOL using 4 questions, each response given a point value from 0 to 4. The sum of these points will total between 0 and 16 points, where 0 means the knee does not affect quality of life and 16 indicates that the knee is a constant problem affecting quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>At-Home Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will follow-up in clinic postoperatively at 4, 8, and 12 weeks and their recovery will also be monitored using sensors and communication devices while they are at home after surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>At-Home Monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient reported outcomes, functional measures such as the maximum attainable range of motion (AROM) and the number of steps taken will be tracked using sensors worn by the patient. The AROM sensor values will be verified with range of motion measurements taken using a goniometer during therapy and MD visits.</description>
    <arm_group_label>At-Home Monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Unilateral primary TKA

          -  Surgery is performed at Cleveland Clinic Main Campus or at Lutheran Hospital

          -  Patient must reside within 75 miles (driving distance) from Cleveland Clinic Main
             Campus

          -  Patient expected to utilize Cleveland Clinic Home Care Services after surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Revision or simultaneous bilateral TKA

          -  English is not the patient's preferred language for healthcare discussions

          -  Currently participating in any other research study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos Higuera, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Staff Surgeon</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 28, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 26, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carlos Higuera-Rueda</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff Surgeon</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 27, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

