<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03035409</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0655</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-00188</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03035409</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Anamorelin on Cancer-Related-Fatigue in Patients With Advanced Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Anamorelin on Cancer-Related-Fatigue in Patients With Advanced Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Helsinn Healthcare SA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if anamorelin can help to decrease
      cancer-related fatigue in patients with advanced cancer.

      The safety of this drug in combination with physical activity will also be studied.

      This is an investigational study. Anamorelin is not FDA approved or commercially available.
      Its use in combination with physical activity is investigational. The study doctor can
      explain how the study drug is designed to work.

      Up to 38 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Baseline Tests:

      If after the screening procedures and pregnancy test (if applicable) participant is found to
      be eligible to take part in this study, participant will be asked to:

        -  Participant will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests and cytokine testing. Cytokines
           are proteins that may affect the immune system.

        -  Participant will complete 8 questionnaires about participant's symptoms, emotional and
           physical health, level of fatigue, appetite, and regular exercise habits. It should take
           about 40 minutes to complete all questionnaires.

        -  Participant will meet with an exercise specialist to discuss participant's current
           strength and fitness level.

        -  Participant will meet with a dietitian to complete 2 online questionnaires about
           participant's dietary intake in the past 24 hours. It should take about 30 minutes to
           complete each questionnaire. Both questionnaires can be completed on a smartphone or
           computer, but 1 should be completed in the clinic and the other can be completed on
           participant's own time. Participant will also be asked to complete 1 online
           questionnaire about participant's frequency of food consumption in the past month.
           Participant may complete this on a computer. It should take about 20 minutes to
           complete.

        -  Participant will complete a 6-minute walk test where participant will be timed while
           participant walks a 100-foot loop as many times as participant can.

        -  Participant will complete a chair-stand test where participant will sit in a chair and
           stand and sit down as many times as participant can in 30 seconds.

        -  Participant will have participant's resting energy expenditure (REE) measured to see how
           much oxygen participant uses at rest. To measure participant's REE, participant will
           hold a device called a calorimeter and will breathe into the mouthpiece for 5 minutes.

        -  Participant will have participant's body mass index (BMI) measured while participant
           stands on a scale and holds a device for about 20 seconds.

        -  Participant will be taught how to do resistance exercises to complete at home.

      Study Drug Administration:

      Participant will take anamorelin by mouth 1 time each day for 6 weeks. Participant should
      take anamorelin with 1 cup (8 ounces) of water and should be fasting (having nothing to eat
      or drink except water) overnight and for at least 1 hour before participant's first meal of
      the day.

      Physical Activities:

      Participant will be asked to complete resistance exercises and a walking program at home for
      6 weeks while also taking anamorelin.

      Participant will be given an accelerometer to wear while exercising for 5 days before each
      study visit. An accelerometer is a small device that measures participant's physical
      activity. Participant can clip the accelerometer to participant's waistband or belt.

      For the resistance exercises, participant will use color-coded tubes that have 3 levels of
      resistance: light, moderate, or hard. Participant will begin with 1 set of 10-12 repetitions
      at the lightest resistance and progress to 2 sets of 12 repetitions as participant gets
      stronger. Once participant has mastered a resistance level, participant will move up in
      resistance as participant's strength and endurance increases. Participant should begin the
      next level of resistance with 2 sets of 12 repetitions. Participant will complete these
      exercises 3 days a week with at least 48 hours between each session.

      For the walking program, participant will be asked to walk at least 5 days per week. The
      study staff will recommend how long each walk should be and how many times to walk each day.

      Participant will wear a pedometer at all times while participant is on study. A pedometer is
      a device that shows the number of steps participant has taken. Participant will receive
      instructions on how to use the pedometer. Participant will also receive a diary to record the
      number of steps participant takes each day. Participant should bring this diary to each study
      visit.

      Length of Study:

      Participant will receive anamorelin while performing the physical activities for 6 weeks.

      If participant and the doctor think it is in participant's best interest, participant may
      continue to take the study drug for an additional 6 weeks and repeat all study visits and
      procedures. Participant will no longer be able to take the study drug or perform the physical
      activities as part of this study if the disease gets worse, if intolerable side effects
      occur, or if participant is unable to follow study directions.

      Participation on the study will be over after the follow-up period.

      Study Visits:

      One (1) time each week, on or about Days 8, 15, 29, and 36, participant will be called to ask
      about participant's physical activity progress and how participant is doing. These calls
      should last about 10-15 minutes each time.

      On or about Days 8, 15, 21, 29, 36, and 43, participant will complete the same 8
      questionnaires that participant completed at baseline.

      On or about Days 15, 29, and 43 participant will complete a questionnaire about any symptoms
      participant may be having. This questionnaire should take about 5 minutes to complete each
      time.

      On or about Day 21, participant will meet with an exercise specialist to discuss
      participant's physical activity progress and a dietitian for nutrition counseling. If
      participant has difficulty tasting food, participant will be given zinc oxide and amino acids
      to take every day for 4 weeks to help increase participant's appetite. Participant will meet
      with a dietitian to complete 2 online questionnaires about participant's dietary intake in
      the past 24 hours. It should take about 30 minutes to complete each questionnaire. Both
      questionnaires can be completed on a smartphone or computer, but 1 should be completed in the
      clinic and the other can be completed on participant's own time. Blood (about 1 tablespoon)
      will be drawn for routine and cytokine testing, and to check participant's liver function and
      fasting blood glucose levels.

      On or about Day 43:

        -  Participant will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 tablespoon) will be drawn for routine and cytokine testing, and to check
           participant's liver function and fasting blood glucose levels.

        -  Participant will complete the same physical performance tests participant did at
           baseline.

        -  Participant will complete 2 questionnaires about participant's regular exercise habits
           and participant's symptoms after treatment. It should take about 10 minutes to complete
           these questionnaires.

        -  Participant will complete 1 online questionnaire about participant's frequency of food
           consumption in the past month. Participant may complete this on a computer. It should
           take about 20 minutes to complete.

        -  Participant will have your REE and BMI measured.

      Follow-Up Period:

      On or about Day 71, participant will be called by a member of the study staff and asked about
      participant's health. This call should last about 10 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 8, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference Between the Functional Assessment of Cancer Illness Therapy-Fatigue (FACIT-F) Subscale Score at Baseline and Day 43</measure>
    <time_frame>43 Days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Anamorelin and Standardized Physical Activity as Measured by The Multidimensional Fatigue Symptom Inventory-Short Form[MFSI-SF]</measure>
    <time_frame>43 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Anamorelin and Standardized Physical Activity as Measured by PROMIS Fatigue Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>43 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Anamorelin and Standardized Physical Activity as Measured by Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale (HADS)</measure>
    <time_frame>43 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Anamorelin and Standardized Physical Activity as Measured by Edmonton Symptom Assessment Scale (ESAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>43 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Anamorelin and Standardized Physical Activity as Measured by Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy (FACT-G)</measure>
    <time_frame>43 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Anamorelin and Standardized Physical Activity as Measured by Functional Assessment of Anorexia/Cachexia Treatment (FAACT)</measure>
    <time_frame>43 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasms of Independent (Primary) Multiple Sites</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic or Recurrent Incurable Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anamorelin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants take Anamorelin by mouth 1 time each day for 6 weeks.
Participants perform resistance exercises and a walking program at home for 6 weeks while also taking Anamorelin.
Assessment questionnaires completed at baseline, on Days 8, 15, 21, 29, 36, and 43.
Participants meet with a dietitian for nutrition counseling on Day 21, and an exercise specialist on Day 15.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anamorelin</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg by mouth 1 time each day for 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anamorelin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Activity</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants perform resistance exercises and a walking program at home for 6 weeks while also taking Anamorelin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anamorelin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Assessment Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Assessment questionnaires completed at baseline, on Days 8, 15, 21, 29, 36, and 43.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anamorelin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surveys</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants meet with a dietitian for nutrition counseling on Day 21, and an exercise specialist on Day 15.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anamorelin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient with a diagnosis of advanced cancer (metastatic or recurrent incurable solid
             tumors excluding prostate cancer)

          2. Presence of fatigue on FACIT-F subscale of &lt;/= 34 on a 0 to 52 scale (in which 52 = no
             fatigue and 0 =worst possible fatigue)

          3. Patient should describe fatigue as being present for a minimum of 2 weeks prior to
             screening

          4. CRP must be &gt;/= 3mg/l* in the absence of any other more likely cause of increased CRP
             like an infection or an autoimmune disorder.

          5. No evidence of moderate to severe depression as determined by a HADS depression score
             of &lt;/=13

          6. Presence of unintentional weight loss ranging from &gt;/= 2 - &lt;/=15% in last 12 months

          7. Uncontrolled pain; If patient is on opioids for the treatment of cancer pain, he/she
             must have had no major dose change (&gt;25%) for at least 48 hours prior to study entry.
             The dose of morphine equivalent daily should not exceed 120mg/day unless approved by
             the PI. Change in opioid dose after study entry is allowed;

          8. Patient must be 18 years of age or older. The questionnaires used in this study have
             been validated only in the adult population

          9. Patient must be willing to engage in telephone follow up with research staff

         10. Patient must have telephone access to be contacted by the research staff

         11. Hemoglobin level of &gt;/=9 g/dL

         12. Estimated life expectancy of &gt; 4 months at the time of screening

         13. Adequate hepatic function, defined as aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine
             transaminase (ALT) levels &lt;/= 5 × upper limit of normal (ULN)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Major contraindications to anamorelin e.g. hypersensitivity

          2. Regularly engaged in moderate or vigorous-intensity exercise for at least 5 times a
             week

          3. Inability to complete the baseline assessment forms or to understand the
             recommendations for participation in the study

          4. Pregnant or lactating women, childbearing age women who are not on birth control.
             Negative pregnancy test for women of childbearing potential, as defined by intact
             uterus and ovaries, and a history of menses within the last 12 months. Pregnancy test
             to be performed no greater than 14 days prior to consent in study. In cases of women
             with elevated b-HCG, these candidates will be eligible to participate so long as the
             level of b-HCG is not consistent with pregnancy. Women of childbearing potential need
             to be on or use contraception, or be abstinent during the study period. Their male
             partners must also use contraception (condom) or maintain abstinence. Birth controls
             specifications: Women who are able to become pregnant must use birth control during
             the study and for 30 days after the last Anamorelin dose. Acceptable forms of birth
             control include barrier methods (such as condom or diaphragm) with spermicide.

          5. Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus ( Fasting Blood Sugar &gt;200mg/dl) at screening

          6. Male patients with a history of untreated hypogonadism

          7. Patients on drugs with strong CYP 3A4 inhibitors within the previous two weeks
             (ketoconazole, clarithromycin, itraconazole, nefazodone, telithromycin)

          8. Patients on drugs that may prolong the PR or QRS interval durations, such as any of
             the Class I/Sodium (Na+) Channel blocking antiarrhythmic medications should be avoided
             (e.g. Flecainide, Procainamide, Propafenone, Quinidine).

          9. Patients with untreated clinically relevant hypothyroidism

         10. Patients currently on investigational therapies will be evaluated by the PI on a case
             by case basis and study participation approval will be obtained from the treating
             oncologist.

         11. Patients with prostate cancer.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sriram Yennu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sriram Yennu, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-6085</phone>
    <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Research Operations</last_name>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 26, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 30, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malignant neoplasms of independent (primary) multiple sites</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic or recurrent incurable solid tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Anamorelin</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Surveys</keyword>
  <keyword>Dietary Counseling</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise Counseling</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

