<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03039088</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-A01288-39</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03039088</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PREDICT-SpA - French Epidemiological Study of the Evaluation of the Impact of Fibromyalgia in the TNF Alpha Treatment Effect in Axial Spondyloarthritis in Both Anti-TNF naïve and - Experienced Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREDICT_SpA</acronym>
  <official_title>PREDICT-SpA - French Epidemiological Study of the Evaluation of the Impact of Fibromyalgia in the TNF Alpha Treatment Effect in Axial Spondyloarthritis in Both Anti-TNF naïve and - Experienced Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Association de Recherche Clinique en Rhumatologie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RCTs</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Association de Recherche Clinique en Rhumatologie</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective observational national (France) study with 2 visits 3 months apart
      (baseline and 12 weeks after TNF alpha blockers initiation). The objective of recruitment is
      500 SpA patients (diagnosis according to their treating rheumatologist) initiating a TNF
      alpha blocker.

      The main objective of the study is to evaluate the impact of a concomitant fibromyalgia on
      the anti-TNF treatment effect in axial Spondyloarthritis in both anti-TNF naïve and
      pre-exposed patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Diagnosis of SpA in the absence of objective signs of inflammation or structural
      damage can be challenging, and especially difficult to differentiate from Fibromyalgia.
      Furthermore, such patients can easily be classified as active and refractory to NSAIDs, and
      inappropriately receive TNF alpha blockers.

      Objective: Primary objective: To evaluate the impact of fibromyalgia in the TNF alpha
      treatment effect in axial Spondyloarthritis in both anti-TNF naïve and - experienced
      patients.

      Methods: Design: Prospective observational national (France) study with 2 visits 3 months
      apart (baseline and 12 weeks after TNF alpha blockers initiation). Patients: 500 SpA patients
      (diagnosis according to their treating rheumatologist) initiating a TNF alpha blocker. Data
      collection: items permitting the calculation of the ASAS criteria, the FIRST questionnaire
      (Fibromyalgia Rapid Screen Test), patients and disease characteristics, disease activity and
      severity items, and the domain leading the doctor's decision for initiating the TNF alpha
      blocker (CRP/Imaging/Symptoms) will be collected at baseline. Effectiveness measures (e.g.
      BASDAI and patient's global) and the doctor's decision to continue/discontinue the TNF alpha
      blocker will be collected during the second visit. Statistical analysis: for the main
      objective, evaluation of the predictive factors of a TNF alpha response in real life, and the
      impact of Fibromyalgia in such response (e.g. logistic regression to estimate BASDAI
      reduction of 50%). For the secondary objectives: evaluation of the relative attributable
      risks of the doctor's domains leading the TNF alpha blocker initiation (Imaging/CRP/Symptoms)
      in order to explain the anti-TNF therapy response; evaluation of the concordance existing
      between the current recommendations and the daily practice.

      Expected results: A positive finding might results into a change in the way of managing
      patients (e.g. carefully checking for the co-existence of fibromyalgia before confirming a
      spondyloarthritis diagnosis, an active disease and also before initiating a specific therapy
      such as biologics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 4, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 4, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the presence of fibromyalgia (defined by a FIRST questionnaire &gt;= 5/6) as a predisposing factor for lower treatment response rates to TNF alpha blockers</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks after TNF alpha blockers initiation</time_frame>
    <description>The difference in BASDAI50 response at week 12 between the patients with and those without fibromyalgia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The relative attributable risks of the doctor's reported outcomes versus the patients reported outcomes in the decision to initiate/switch anti-TNF therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks after TNF alpha blockers initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pourcentage of patients with fibromyalgia (as co-morbidity or as single disease)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks after TNF alpha blockers initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the concordance existing between the current recommendations for the initiation of anti-TNF in non-radiographic axial SpA and the daily practice as represented by this study.</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at 12 weeks after TNF alpha blockers initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">527</enrollment>
  <condition>Axial Spondyloarthritis</condition>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-TNF naïve patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Anti-TNF naïve patients at the inclusion of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-TNF experienced patients.</arm_group_label>
    <description>Anti-TNF pre-exposed patients at the inclusion of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Follow-up after 12 weeks after TNF alpha blockers initiation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-TNF naïve patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-TNF experienced patients.</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients suffering from SpA based on the opinion of the treating rheumatologist initiating
        a TNF alpha blocker.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients aged &gt; 18 years old and suffering from SpA based on the opinion of the
             treating rheumatologist

          -  Patients in whom the decision of initiating of switching an anti-TNF because of an
             axial involvement of SpA has been made by the treating rheumatologist. In case of
             previous exposure to antiTNF a washout period of at least 4 weeks be asked.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients unable to understand the questionnaire

          -  Patients not giving their informed written consent

          -  Patients with absolute contraindications to anti-TNF as per label
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 30, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 1, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spondylarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adrenergic alpha-Antagonists</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>January 9, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

