<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03031808</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AB3383</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03031808</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Two Induction Regimens Using Topical Lidocaine or Muscle Relaxant on Sore Throat and Hemodynamics</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Two Induction Regimens Using Topical Lidocaine or Muscle Relaxant; Impact on Postoperative Sore Throat and Haemodynamics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ostfold Hospital Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ostfold Hospital Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      When a surgical procedure is performed under general anesthesia, the Airways are often
      secured With an endotracheal tube. Some patients experience sore throat thereafter. Studies
      have shown a reduction of these side effects when by use of muscle relaxants or a lidocain
      spray prior to the intubation. At Ostfold Hospital Trust, the investigators use one of the
      two methods or nothing. These methods will be studied systematically.

      Heart rate and blood pressure rise during the intubation procedure. The investigators will
      also study the differences between the groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Post-operative sore throat and cough are common complications of endotracheal intubation and
      occurs in 30% to 70% of patients. Spraying with Lidocaine reduces this incident of
      postoperative sore Throat (POST). The use of neuromuscular blocking agents (NMBA) alone will
      also diminish the incidence of adverse postoperative upper airway symptoms. The use of
      topical Lidocaine is shown to reduce the cardiovascular responses during and after
      endotracheal intubation.

      Hypertension and tachycardia as a response to endotracheal intubation are probably of little
      consequence in healthy individuals. These reactions might though be harmful in patients with
      cardiovascular diseases.

      Postoperative sore throat is an undesired outcome for the patient. Topical or systemic
      pharmacological interventions is shown to reduce the POST.

      Our anesthetists practice very different. The investigators sometime use topical lidocaine 2%
      as a spray, sometime muscle relaxants and often nothing but propofol and remifentanil prior
      to laryngoscopy an endotracheal intubation.

      The objective of this study is to determine, whether the use of topical administered
      lidocaine, 2 %, has a better impact on POST compared with NMBA alone in general anesthesia
      with propofol and remifentanil. Patients receiving nothing but propofol and remifentanil will
      be the reference group. Assessment of the intubation conditions will be done according to a
      standard scheme

      The primary endpoint:

        -  Differences in the intubation conditions between the three groups.

        -  Cardiovascular responses caused by the laryngoscopy and intubation.

      The secondary endpoint:

      • Post operative upper airways symptoms. Power and Sample Size Calculator To detect a
      decrease in the incidence of pharyngolaryngeal symptoms from 60% to 45%, we calculated that
      we needed 150 patients per study arm (power of the study, 0,8; type I error, 0,05).

      450 adult patients have to be scheduled for the study.

      The study is double blind, randomized:

        -  Group Topical lidocaine 4%:

        -  Group NMBA

        -  Control group Premedication: Paracetamol 2g General anaesthesia: TCI (Target Control of
           Infusion is a principle, an anesthesia infusion after protocol): Propofol and
           Remifentanil Surgical procedure: Not specified short lasting (&lt;1 h) procedures The
           experienced anesthesiologist performing the intubating procedure will not be in the room
           until immediately before the intubation.

      Postoperatively:

        -  Oral paracetamol and codeine-fixed combination up to 1000 mg and 60 mg, respectively,
           every 6 h

        -  When nausea and vomiting occurs postoperatively, ondansetron 4 mg IV administers as the
           drug of first choice followed by droperidol 0,625 mg IV if the nausea/vomiting persists.

      Collected data:

        -  Patient characteristics inclusive smoke habits

        -  Intubation conditions according to the Copenhagen score

        -  Blood pressure prior to laryngoscopy and after 1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 13 and 15 minutes,
           then every 15 min.

        -  Cuff pressure

        -  Pharyngolaryngeal discomfort 2 and 24 hours (telephone interview if released from
           hospital) after extubation
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 31, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sore Throat postoperative. Assessment of complaints and changes in complaints</measure>
    <time_frame>2 h and 24 h after extubation</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative sore throat, described 2 h and 24 h after extubation. If the patient has sore throat or is hoarse, the complaint is assessed on a VAS (Visual Analogue Scale) 1 - 10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intubation conditions directly after induction of anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>90 sec. after established general anesthesia</time_frame>
    <description>Describes the intubation conditions: Jaw relaxation, resistance to laryngoscopy blade, the position and movement of vocal cords, the movement of limbs and coughing. Each variable rates as excellent, good or poor. Intubation conditions are many variables described once and should not be divided into several outcomes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic parameters, change in HR (Heart Rate) is being assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to induction, then every second minute the next 15 minutes, thereafter every 15 minute until end of surgery (max. 2 h.)</time_frame>
    <description>Describes changes in HR (Heart Rate)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic parameters, change in BP (blood pressure) is being assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to induction, then every second minute the next 15 minutes, thereafter every 15 minute until end of surgery (max. 2 h.)</time_frame>
    <description>Describes changes in BP(Blood Pressure)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Intubation Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lidocaine spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endotracheal lidocaine spray prior to intubation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Muscle relaxant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Muscle relaxant prior to intubation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Muscle relaxant, no Lidocaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>'No Muscle relaxant, no Lidocaine Control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lidocaine spray (2%)</intervention_name>
    <description>Spraying trachea from 2 cm above the vocal cords and 5 cm down with a straw with multiple side holes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lidocaine spray</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xylocain 2% Astra Zeneca</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Muscle Relaxant (Rocuronium)</intervention_name>
    <description>After induction of anesthesia, the participants are given 0,6 mg/kg bodyweight intravenously.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Muscle relaxant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Esmeron MSD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No Muscle relaxant, no Lidocaine</intervention_name>
    <description>This group get general anesthesia without Rocuronium or Lidocaine</description>
    <arm_group_label>No Muscle relaxant, no Lidocaine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Scheduled elective surgery with general anesthesia and planned endotracheal
             intubation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ASA≥3,

          -  20&gt;BMI&lt;35

          -  Allergy to local anesthetics or neuromuscular blocking agents.

          -  The ASA physical status classification system is a system for assessing the fitness of
             patients before surgery. BMI is Body Mass Index measured in kilograms/square meter.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jan Sverre Vamnes, MD, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Senior consultant</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jan Sverre Vamnes, MD, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+47 913 05 016</phone>
    <email>jan.sverre.vamnes@so-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Knut Inge Solbakk, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+47 909 33 106</phone>
    <email>knut.inge.solbakk@so-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ostfold Hospital Trust, Moss</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grålum</city>
        <state>Ostfold</state>
        <zip>1714</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jan Sverre Vamnes, MD, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+47 91608896</phone>
      <email>janvam@so-hf.no</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Knut Inge Solbakk, md</last_name>
      <phone>+47 90933106</phone>
      <email>knisol@so-hf.no</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banihashem N, Alijanpour E, Hasannasab B, Zarei A. Prophylactic Effects of Lidocaine or Beclomethasone Spray on Post-Operative Sore Throat and Cough after Orotracheal Intubation. Iran J Otorhinolaryngol. 2015 May;27(80):179-84.</citation>
    <PMID>26082898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blobner M, Mirakhur RK, Wierda JM, Wright PM, Olkkola KT, Debaene B, Pendeville P, Engbaek J, Rietbergen H, Sparr HJ. Rapacuronium 2.0 or 2.5 mg kg-1 for rapid-sequence induction: comparison with succinylcholine 1.0 mg kg-1. Br J Anaesth. 2000 Nov;85(5):724-31.</citation>
    <PMID>11094588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Combes X, Andriamifidy L, Dufresne E, Suen P, Sauvat S, Scherrer E, Feiss P, Marty J, Duvaldestin P. Comparison of two induction regimens using or not using muscle relaxant: impact on postoperative upper airway discomfort. Br J Anaesth. 2007 Aug;99(2):276-81. Epub 2007 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>17573390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Domaoal AM, Weniger FC, Wolfson B. &quot;Precurarization&quot; using pancuronium. Anesth Analg. 1975 Jan-Feb;54(1):71-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1167764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doyle DJ. Airway anesthesia: theory and practice. Anesthesiol Clin. 2015 Jun;33(2):291-304. doi: 10.1016/j.anclin.2015.02.013. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25999003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalil DM, Silvestro LS, Austin PN. Novel preoperative pharmacologic methods of preventing postoperative sore throat due to tracheal intubation. AANA J. 2014 Jun;82(3):188-97. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25109156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin C, Bonneru JJ, Brun JP, Albanese J, Gouin F. Vecuronium or suxamethonium for rapid sequence intubation: which is better? Br J Anaesth. 1987 Oct;59(10):1240-4.</citation>
    <PMID>2890365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mostafa SM, Murthy BV, Barrett PJ, McHugh P. Comparison of the effects of topical lignocaine spray applied before or after induction of anaesthesia on the pressor response to direct laryngoscopy and intubation. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 1999 Jan;16(1):7-10.</citation>
    <PMID>10084094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koller ME, Husby P. High-dose vecuronium may be an alternative to suxamethonium for rapid-sequence intubation. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 1993 Jul;37(5):465-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7741805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qi DY, Wang K, Zhang H, Du BX, Xu FY, Wang L, Zou Z, Shi XY. Efficacy of intravenous lidocaine versus placebo on attenuating cardiovascular response to laryngoscopy and tracheal intubation: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Minerva Anestesiol. 2013 Dec;79(12):1423-35. Epub 2013 Jul 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23839320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tanaka Y, Nakayama T, Nishimori M, Sato Y, Furuya H. Lidocaine for preventing postoperative sore throat. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009 Jul 8;(3):CD004081. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004081.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;7:CD004081.</citation>
    <PMID>19588349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Viby-Mogensen J, Engbaek J, Eriksson LI, Gramstad L, Jensen E, Jensen FS, Koscielniak-Nielsen Z, Skovgaard LT, Ostergaard D. Good clinical research practice (GCRP) in pharmacodynamic studies of neuromuscular blocking agents. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 1996 Jan;40(1):59-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8904261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 26, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ostfold Hospital Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jan Sverre Vamnes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior consultant, Ph.D.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharyngitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscle Hypotonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rocuronium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No sharing plan so far.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

