<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01147913</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F32MH088065-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01147913</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Computerized Information-Processing Bias Retraining in Depressed Adolescents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Computerized Information-Processing Bias Retraining in Adolescents With Depression: A Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine how well a novel four-session computerized program, designed to help
      adolescents learn to interpret ambiguous situations less negatively, reduces symptoms of
      depression and decreases negative information-processing biases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major Depression is a markedly impairing disorder that affects up to 20% of adolescents
      before adulthood, and is associated with significant impairment in adolescents' emotional and
      social development. While antidepressant medication and psychotherapy are effective in
      treating some depressed adolescents, approximately 30% fail to respond to a combination of
      these treatments. Furthermore, many families are reluctant to pursue antidepressant
      medication for depressed adolescents because of concerns about potentially increasing risk of
      suicidal ideation. Thus, there is a critical need for effective, non-pharmacological
      treatments for this population. One promising new intervention consists of modifying negative
      information-processing biases associated with depression. Recent research has suggested that
      these biases may be modified using a computerized program that provides repeated exposure to
      positive interpretations of salient, ambiguous situations, with the goal of interpreting
      ambiguity less negatively. These modification programs have been efficacious in altering
      interpretation biases and reducing anxiety in adults with social and specific phobias.
      Therefore, the proposed study aims to examine the efficacy of an adapted interpretation bias
      modification program for depressed adolescents. Specifically, the study will examine the
      efficacy of four sessions of the modification program in altering interpretation biases and
      reducing symptoms of depression, anxiety, and negative affect. A total of 60 adolescents
      (ages 14-21) with symptoms of major depression will be randomly assigned to either the active
      intervention condition (four sessions of the modification program over two weeks) or an
      attention control condition. Measures will include a diagnostic interview, self-report
      measures of depression, anxiety, and negative affect, and a test of interpretation bias in
      response to ambiguous situations. It is hypothesized that: 1) Compared to adolescents in the
      attention control condition, adolescents who receive four sessions of the positive
      interpretive training will experience a significantly larger decrease from baseline to
      post-treatment in negative interpretation bias (e.g., more positive and fewer negative
      interpretations of ambiguous situations) on a measure of interpretation bias; and, 2)Compared
      to adolescents in the attention control condition, adolescents who receive the positive
      interpretation training will experience a significantly larger decrease from baseline to
      post-treatment in self-reported state depression, anxiety, and negative affect.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Test of Interpretation Bias (TIB)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 day post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The TIB consists of 10 scenarios, similar to the training scenarios except that the last word of all of the scenarios remains ambiguous in valence. Following exposure to each of these ambiguous scenarios, adolescents are given a series of four statements regarding the scenario and asked to rate on a 4-point scale how similar the statement is to their interpretation of the scenario. Two target statements are presented, one with the positive interpretation and one with the negative interpretation. Scores for negative and positive interpretations across the situations can then be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Test of Interpretation Bias</measure>
    <time_frame>2-Week Follow-Up</time_frame>
    <description>See above</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kiddie-Schedule of Affective Disorders and Schizophrenia-Epidemiologic Version (K-SADS-E; Orvaschek &amp; Puig-Antich, 1987)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one day Post-Treatment and at 2-Week Follow-Up</time_frame>
    <description>DSM-IV structured interview for children up to age 16 years old; assesses for major depression, dysthymia, and mania.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory, 2nd Version</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 day Post-Treatment and at 2-Week Follow-Up</time_frame>
    <description>The BDI-II is a questionnaire the measures symptoms of depression over the previous two weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>State-Trait Anxiety Scale (STAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 day Post-Treatment and 2-Week Follow-Up</time_frame>
    <description>The STAI is a self-report measure of anxiety symptoms over the past week (trait) and currently (state).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV (SCID-IV; First et al, 1997), Mood Disorder Modules only</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 day Post-Treatment and 2-Week Follow-Up</time_frame>
    <description>DSM-IV structured interview for adults (17 years old and older); assesses for major depression, dysthymia, and mania</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dysfunctional Attitudes Scale (DAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 day post-treatment and at two-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The DAS-A is a 40-item self-report measure of depressogenic beliefs. The scale has two factors: Perfectionism and Need for Social Approval (Imber et al., 1990). Internal consistency and concurrent validity have been found to be acceptable (Imber et al, 1990; Blatt et al, 1995).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CANTAB Affective Go-No Go Task (AGN)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 day post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The AGN test assesses information processing biases for positive and negative stimuli and takes 10 minutes to administer. The test consists of several blocks, each of which presents a series of words from two of three different Affective categories: Positive (for example, joyful), Negative (for example, hopeless), and Neutral (for example, element). The subject is given a target category, and is asked to press the press pad when they see a word matching this category. There are twelve outcome measures covering latency and errors of commission and omission.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Positive Interpretation Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Four sessions of positive information-processing training for interpretation of ambiguous scenarios relevant to themes of depression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Attention Control Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Four sessions of interpretation training for &quot;filler&quot; or neutral scenarios, unrelated to themes associated with depression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computerized Information-Processing Bias Retraining</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention consists of the presentation of three-line ambiguous scenarios via a computer program, one line at a time. A disambiguating word fragment completes the scenario (in either a positive or neutral valence, depending on the scenario), after which participants will type the first letter of the word on the keyboard to ensure they are encoding the interpretation valence. The computer will indicate if they have correctly identified the word. This is followed by a Y/N comprehension question. Each session presents 100 training scenarios.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Positive Interpretation Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Attention Control Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Four sessions of interpretation training for &quot;filler&quot; or neutral scenarios, unrelated to themes associated with depression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Attention Control Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be between 14-21 years old

          -  A score of 14 or higher on the Beck Depression Inventory, 2nd Edition (BDI-II)

          -  Working command of the English language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Psychosis, current mania, or acute suicidality

          -  Previous diagnosis of pervasive developmental disorder, mental retardation, or severe
             dyslexia

          -  Changes in psychiatric medication or psychotherapy within two weeks of entering the
             study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jamie A Micco, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical and Research Program in Pediatric Psychopharmacology at Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02138</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jamie A. Micco, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant in Psychology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Major Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Dysthymia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

