<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01147965</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ETBX-011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01147965</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Active Immunotherapy CEA Vaccine in Patients With Malignancies Expressing CEA</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of Active Immunotherapy With Ad5[E1-,E2b-]-CEA Vaccine in Patients With Advanced or Metastatic Malignancies Expressing CEA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Etubics Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Etubics Corporation</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out what effects (good and bad) that a cancer vaccine
      has on you and your cancer. The cancer vaccine is called Ad5 [E1-, E2b-]-CEA(6D)or ETBX-011
      and is made by Etubics. This vaccine is based on a virus called an adenovirus but it has been
      changed to express the protein CEA that is found on some cancer cells. Therefore, the vaccine
      can tell the immune system to attack cancer cells which make CEA. The investigators are
      trying to determine whether giving this virus is safe and whether this causes a strong immune
      system attack on the cancer. ETBX-011 is an investigational drug.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I/II study with the primary purpose to determine the safety of immunization
      with Ad5 [E1-, E2B-]-CEA(6D), in patients with advanced or metastatic CEA-expressing
      malignancies. The secondary objectives are to evaluate CEA-specific immune responses to the
      immunizations and to obtain preliminary data on clinical response rate. The study population
      consists of patients with a histologically confirmed diagnosis of metastatic malignancy that
      is CEA positive who were previously treated with standard therapy known to have a possible
      survival benefit or refused such therapy. The study will determine the safety of three dosage
      levels of Ad5 [E1-, E2B-]-CEA(6D) vaccine (phase I component), and the maximally tolerated
      dose of Ad5 [E1-, E2B-]-CEA(6D) vaccine (phase II component). The study drug is Ad5 [E1-,
      E2B-]-CEA(6D) given by subcutaneous (SQ) injection every 3 weeks for 3 immunizations. We will
      evaluate safety in each cohort at least 3 weeks after the last patient in the previous cohort
      has received their first injection. A dosing scheme will be considered safe if &lt;33% of
      patients treated at a dosage level experience DLT (e.g., 0 of 3, ≤1 of 6, ≤3 of 12 or ≤5 of
      18 patients).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objective of this protocol is to determine the safety of immunization with Ad5 [E1-, E2B-]-CEA(6D), in patients with advanced or metastatic CEA-expressing malignancies, including Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD).</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary objectives of this protocol are to evaluate CEA-specific immune responses to the immunizations and to obtain preliminary data on clinical response rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ad5 CEA Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm dose escalation study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AD5 CEA Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>AD5[E1-, E2b-]-CEA Vector Vaccine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ad5 CEA Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Criteria for Patient Eligibility

          1. Histologically confirmed diagnosis of malignancy expressing CEA. Because this is a
             safety and immunogenicity study, patients are NOT required to have measurable or
             evaluable disease by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST).

          2. For all tumor types other than colorectal, the tumor must express CEA as defined by
             immunohistochemical staining (at least 50% of the tumor with at least moderate
             intensity of staining) or a tumor known to be universally CEA positive (i.e. colon and
             rectal cancer). If colorectal cancer then, pathologic or clinical confirmation of
             adenocarcinoma is required.

          3. Patients must have received treatment with standard therapy known to have a possible
             overall survival benefit.

             For the following common cancers, the following eligibility criteria apply:

               -  Colorectal cancer: Must have received and progressed through at least one line of
                  palliative chemotherapy consisting of one of the following regimens:

                    -  Palliative chemotherapy for metastatic colorectal cancer with 5 fluorouracil
                       (or capecitabine) and oxaliplatin.

                    -  Palliative chemotherapy for metastatic colorectal cancer with 5 fluorouracil
                       (or capecitabine) and irinotecan.

                    -  Palliative chemotherapy regimen for metastatic colorectal cancer that
                       includes bevacizumab.

                    -  Colorectal cancer patients currently receiving palliative single-agent
                       bevacizumab or cetuximab will be eligible for this trial and may continue
                       these therapies concomitant with study treatment (if they have been on these
                       single agent therapies for at least 3 months).

               -  Breast cancer: Must have received and progressed through at least one line of
                  chemotherapy for metastatic breast cancer consisting of one of the following
                  regimens:

                    -  Palliative anthracycline- or taxane-based chemotherapy

                    -  Patients with tumors that over express HER2 (IHC 3+ or FISH+) must have
                       received and progressed through at least one line of palliative therapy that
                       combines trastuzumab with chemotherapy.

                    -  Breast cancer patients currently receiving palliative endocrine therapy or
                       single-agent trastuzumab will be eligible for this trial and may continue
                       these therapies concomitant with study treatment (if they have been on these
                       single agent therapies for at least 3 months).

                    -  Patients who have been treated or offered the options of treatment with
                       Bevacizumab (option clearly stated in the consent form).

                    -  Patients who have been treated or offered the options of treatment with
                       Lapatinib (option clearly stated in the consent form).

               -  Lung cancer: Must have received and progressed through chemotherapy for
                  metastatic disease consisting of one of the following regimens:

                    -  Palliative platinum-based (cisplatin or carboplatin) chemotherapy if the
                       patient has not received chemotherapy previously.

                    -  Palliative taxane-based (docetaxel or paclitaxel) or vinorelbine
                       chemotherapy if the patient has received chemotherapy previously.

                    -  Lung cancer patients currently receiving palliative single-agent erlotinib
                       or gefitinib will be eligible for this trial and may continue these
                       therapies concomitant with study treatment (if they have been on these
                       single agent therapies for at least 3 months).

               -  Pancreatic cancer: Must have received and progressed through chemotherapy
                  including gemcitabine.

                  - Pancreatic cancer patients currently receiving palliative single-agent
                  erlotinib will be eligible for this trial and may continue this therapy
                  concomitant with study treatment (if they have been on this single agent therapy
                  for at least 3 months).

               -  For other malignancies, if a first line therapy with survival or palliative
                  benefit exists, it should have been administered and there should have been
                  progressive disease.

               -  Patients who have received and progressed through first-line palliative
                  chemotherapy must be advised regarding second-line therapy before being enrolled
                  on this investigational study.

          4. Karnofsky performance score of 70% or higher

          5. Estimated life expectancy &gt; 3 months

          6. Age ≥ 21 years, but &lt; 75

          7. Adequate hematologic function, with WBC ≥ 3000/microliter, hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL (it is
             acceptable to have had prior transfusion), platelets ≥ 75,000/microliter; PT-INR &lt;1.5,
             PTT &lt;1.5X ULN

          8. Adequate renal and hepatic function, with serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dL, bilirubin &lt;
             1.5 mg/dL (except for Gilbert's syndrome which will allow bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dL), ALT
             and AST ≤ 2.5 x upper limit of normal.

          9. Patients who have received prior CEA-targeted immunotherapy are eligible for this
             trial, if this treatment was discontinued at least 3 months prior to enrollment.

         10. Patients who are taking medications that do not have a known history of
             immunosuppression are eligible for this trial.

         11. Ability to understand and provide signed informed consent that fulfills Institutional
             Review Board's guidelines.

         12. Ability to return to the clinical site for adequate follow-up, as required by this
             protocol.

        Criteria for Patient Exclusion

          1. Patients with concurrent cytotoxic chemotherapy or radiation therapy should be
             excluded. There are no exclusions based on the number of prior chemotherapy, biologic,
             hormonal, or experimental regimens. Except for the permitted concomitant therapies
             (bevacizumab, cetuximab, trastuzumab, erlotinib, gefitinib, or hormonal therapy which
             patients must have been on for at least 3 months at the time of enrollment if they
             intend to continue them with the vaccine), there must be at least 3 months between any
             prior CEA-targeted immunotherapy and study treatment and at least 4 weeks between any
             other prior therapy (including radiotherapy) and study treatment. Patients must have
             recovered to grade 1 acute toxicities from prior treatment.

          2. Patients with a history of or current brain metastases will not be permitted.

          3. Patients with a history of autoimmune disease, such as but not restricted to,
             inflammatory bowel disease, systemic lupus erythematosus, ankylosing spondylitis,
             scleroderma, or multiple sclerosis. Autoimmune related thyroid disease and vitiligo
             are permitted.

          4. Patients with serious intercurrent chronic or acute illness, such as cardiac disease
             (NYHA class III or IV), hepatic disease, or other illness considered by the Principal
             Investigator as unwarranted high risk for investigational drug treatment.

          5. Patients with a medical or psychological impediment to probable compliance with the
             protocol should be excluded.

          6. Concurrent (or within the last 5 years) second malignancy other than non melanoma skin
             cancer, cervical carcinoma in situ, controlled superficial bladder cancer, or other
             carcinoma in situ that has been treated.

          7. Presence of an active acute or chronic infection including: a urinary tract infection,
             HIV (as determined by ELISA and confirmed by Western Blot). Patients with HIV are
             excluded based on immunosuppression, which may render them unable to respond to the
             vaccine; patients with chronic hepatitis are excluded because of concern that
             hepatitis could be exacerbated by the injections.

          8. Patients on steroid therapy (or other immunosuppressives, such as azathioprine or
             cyclosporin A) are excluded on the basis of potential immune suppression. Patients
             must have had 6 weeks of discontinuation of any steroid therapy (except that used as
             pre-medication for chemotherapy or contrast-enhanced studies) prior to enrollment.

          9. Pregnant and nursing women should be excluded from the protocol since this research
             may have unknown and harmful effects on an unborn child or on young children. If the
             patient is sexually active, the patient must agree to use a medically acceptable form
             of birth control while receiving treatment and for a period of 4 months following the
             last vaccination therapy. It is not known whether the treatment used in this study
             could affect the sperm and could potentially harm a child that may be fathered while
             on this study.

         10. Patients with acute or chronic skin disorders that will interfere with injection into
             the skin of the extremities or subsequent assessment of potential skin reactions will
             be excluded.

         11. Patients will be allowed warfarin 1mg po qd other than for port prophylaxis.

         12. Patients with metastatic disease which is determined to be resectable will be
             excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Morse, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Cancer Research Institute, Duke University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Oncology Associates, PS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 22, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Colon Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>CEA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>October 25, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>December 16, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>April 25, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>May 30, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

