<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01889407</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IDA20130517</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IDA20130517</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01889407</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Idarubicin Overcomes MDR1 Induced Chemoresistance With Higher Induction Remission Rate and Quality Than Daunorubicin in Acute Myeloid Leukemia Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Idarubicin Overcomes Multidrug Resistant-1(MDR1) Induced Chemoresistance With Higher Induction Remission Rate and Remission Quality Than Daunorubicin in de Novo Acute Myeloid Leukemia Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nanfang Hospital of Southern Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nanfang Hospital of Southern Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Whether Idarubicin can overcomes multidrug resistant 1 induced chemoresistance with higher
      induction remission rate than daunorubicin in de novo acute myeloid leukemia patients.Whether
      induction therapy with IA regimen has a higher remission quality with AML patients than that
      of DA regimen in high MDR1 expression AML patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The long-term survival rate of acute myeloid leukemia (AML) has been significantly prolonged
      due to the improvement of chemotherapeutic protocols and hemopoietic stem cell
      transplantation. However, about 20%-40% of the patients with refractory AML fail to achieve
      complete remission (CR) and approximately 50% of the CR patients will relapse eventually. 1-3
      The refractoried and relapsed AML patients have very poor prognosis, therefore refractoriness
      and relapse are the major challenges for the chemotherapy of AML.

      Chemoresistance is one of the major obstacle for the success of AML treatment.4 One of the
      main mediators for AML chemoresistance is the multi-drug resistance-1(MDR1) gene and MDR1
      protein, also known as permeability-glycoprotein or P-gp.5,6,7 Studies on leukemic blast
      cells demonstrated the association of MDR1 expression with a lower intracellular retention of
      cytostatic drugs leading to cancer cell resistance to several commonly used anti-cancer drugs
      in chemotherapy. Several subsequent studies indicated the influence of MDR1 expression levels
      in the treatment response and survival of leukemia patients, the frequency of resistance to
      the chemotherapy increased with increasing MDR1 expression.8,9,10 Previous methods for
      determination of MDR1 expression have included demonstration of P-glycoprotein by flow
      cytometry and/or immunohistochemistry, and molecular polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based
      assays for RNA expression. However, these assays have either proven difficult to standardize
      or tedious to perform and they are mainly focused on qualitative or semi-quantitative assays.
      11,12 A real-time fluorescence quantitative PCR will increase the sensitivity and also
      maintain the high specificity. The false positivity caused by pollution of amplification
      production can also be decreased by hermetization operation. RQ- PCR is a novel methodology
      which enables sensitive and quantitative measurement of gene expression. 12We have
      established RQ-PCR method for determination expression of MDR1 gene. We have performed a
      pilot study with a small cohort of AML patients to determine the relationship of MDR1
      expression and CR rate of AML patients. The data shows MDR1 expression has been found in most
      cases of AML. However, the MDR1 expression levels vary widely from case to case. This result
      indicated that RQ-PCR method would provide an accurate quantitative measurement for detection
      of MDR1 expression level in different AML cases who were both positive by qualitative RT-PCR
      method. 13,14 The pilot results indicated that the complete response rate to induction
      therapy was compromised by the expression of high levels of MDR1. 15

      Minimal residual disease (MRD) is the major cause of leukemia relapse. It has been reported
      that the treatment intensity in human leukemia can be assessed by the expression status of
      MRD gene. However, more than 50% of acute leukemia, especially in AMLs, lack known genetic
      lesions or clonegenic markers suitable for MRD monitoring. WT1 gene is located on chromosome
      11p13 coding for a zinc-finger transcription factor, has been identified in most AML
      patients. It has been reported that detection of WT1 levels can effectively monitor the MRD
      expression status in AML.16,17 Therefore, WT1 expression can be used to monitor the MRD and
      evaluation the remission quality in AML patients. By detecting WT1 levels we can evaluate the
      efficacy of different induction therapies.

      By employing multiple fluorescence quantitative PCR, several target genes can be
      simultaneously and quantitatively amplified. Therefore multiple fluorescence quantitative PCR
      is more suitable for clinical application. This technology will not only provide higher
      accuracy, specificity and reproducibility but also simplify procedure and reduce measurement
      cost. The recombinant plasmids of MDR1 and WT1 gene have been constructed and the methodology
      of multiple fluorescence quantitative PCR has also been developed in our group .14

      High MDR1 gene expression is a common feature of AML resistance to conventional
      chemotherapeutic regimen.18,19 One of the strategies that overcome MDR is to increase the
      pharmacal liposolubility and elevate the intracellular drug concentration, so as to
      counteract drug efflux pumped by P-glycoprotein. Idarubicin (IDA), a new anthracycline, has
      more strengthened liposolubility and can easily permeate the cell membrane in comparison with
      traditional marcellomycin. Also, the in vivo metabolite of IDA (4-IDA) has the same
      antineoplastic activity as IDA and a longer half-life in vivo. It can also permeate blood
      brain barrier. As a result, IDA has a stronger antileukemia activity than other marcellomycin
      and can partially overcome P-glycoprotein-mediated drug resistance.20, 21 In our recently
      pilot study, we have detected the expression of MDR1 in pre-treated bone marrow samples from
      160 de novo AML patients and the median value of MDR1/GAPDH ratio in the de novo AML cases
      was 0.016（0-81.865）. The median value of MDR1 gene expression was taken as the cut-off point
      of high or low MDR1 gene expression levels. For high MDR1 expression patients, a lower CR
      rate (61.3%) was observed compared with low-MDR1 expression patients (80.0%, P =0.009). In
      this retrospective pilot study, 123 patients were received daunorubicin (DNR 35~45mg/m2/d,3
      days) or idarubicin (IDA 6~8 mg/m2/d, 3 days) in combination with cytarabine (Ara-c100~200
      mg/m2/d, 7 days) for remission induction and significant difference were also observed after
      2 courses of chemotherapy between those who receive IA regimen (57 cases) and DA regimen (66
      cases) regarding to CR rate (80.7% vs 57.6%, P=0.006). Significant difference could also be
      discovered between two treatment arm with regard to CR rate (75.9% vs 43.6%, P=0.011) in
      those who had high MDR1 expression AML patients. Our data shows that IDA may overcome MDR1
      induced chemoresistance with a higher CR rate than DNR in de novo high MDR1 expresser AML
      patients.These results provide rationale for development of randomized, prospective trial to
      compare the CR rate of IA regimen and DA regimen in de novo AML patients with high MDR1
      expression and to identify whether Idarubicin can overcomes MDR1 induced chemoresistance with
      higher induction remission rate than daunorubicin in de novo acute myeloid leukemia patients.
      We speculated that the more favorable outcome in high-MDR1 patient group with IA regimen may
      be associated with a higher remission rate.

      It had been reported that AML patients achieved lower MRD level had an extremely lower
      relapse rate. It had also been reported that patients treated with IA regimen had a
      significant higher long-term survival than those with DA regimen .22-24 Therefore, we
      speculated that the more favorable outcome in IA group may be associated with a lower MRD
      level and higher remission quality. This study is also to conduct a prospective analysis on
      the alteration of WT1 and MDR1 gene expression level after induction therapy with IA or DA
      separately to identify whether induction therapy with IA regimen has a lower MRD level and a
      higher remission quality than that of DA regimen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>complete remission rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>WT1 and MDR1 expression level change after 2 courses of chemotherapy with IA regimen or DA regimen in high-MDR1 expression AML patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Identify whether induction therapy with IA regimen has a higher remission quality with AML patients than that of DA regimen in high MDR1 expression AML patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IA regimen</arm_group_label>
    <description>IA regimen: Patients receive idarubicin (8mg/m2.d) iv drip on days 1-3 and cytarabine (100-200mg/ m2.d) iv drip on days 1-7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DA regimen</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients receive daunomycin (45mg/ m2.d) iv drip on days 1-3 and cytarabine (100－200mg/ m2.d) iv drip on days 1-7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Idarubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>8 mg/m2, iv drip on days 1-3</description>
    <arm_group_label>IA regimen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Bone marrow
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        • Patients aged 16 to 60 years are eligible. Patients must be chemo-naïve, i.e. not have
        received any prior chemotherapy (except hydrea) for AML. They could have received
        transfusion, hematopoietic growth factors or vitamins. Temporary measures such as pheresis
        or hydrea (0.5 to 5g daily or more for up to 3 days) are allowed
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Diagnosis of AML (WHO classification definition of &gt;/= 20% blasts).

               -  Patients aged 16 to 60 years are eligible. Patients must be chemo-naïve, i.e. not
                  have received any prior chemotherapy (except hydrea) for AML. They could have
                  received transfusion, hematopoietic growth factors or vitamins. Temporary
                  measures such as pheresis or hydrea (0.5 to 5g daily or more for up to 3 days)
                  are allowed.

               -  The relative expression level of MDR1 mRNA (MDR1/GAPDH ratio using the
                  quantitative real-time PCR) in pre-treated bone marrow samples should over 0.016
                  (cut-off point from our results of preliminary experiment data )

               -  ECOG PS of 0, 1, 2 at screening.

               -  Serum biochemical values with the following limits: - creatinine &lt;/= 2.0 mg/dl -
                  total bilirubin &lt;/= 2.0 mg/dL, unless increase is due to hemolysis -
                  transaminases (SG PT) &lt;/= 3x ULN

               -  Ability to understand and provide signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  • Subjects with Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia (APL).

               -  Presence of active systemic infection.

               -  Any coexisting medical condition that in the judgment of the treating physician
                  is likely to interfere with study procedures or results.

               -  Nursing women, women of childbearing potential with positive urine pregnancy
                  test, or women of childbearing potential who are not willing to maintain adequate
                  contraception (such as birth control pills, IUD, diaphragm, abstinence, or
                  condoms by their partner) over the entire course of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bing Xu, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Hematology, Nanfang Hospital, The Southern Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bing Xu, M.D</last_name>
    <phone>13189096353</phone>
    <phone_ext>510515</phone_ext>
    <email>xubingzhangjian@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Xutao Guo, M.D</last_name>
    <phone>13802426709</phone>
    <phone_ext>510515</phone_ext>
    <email>gxt827@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bing Xu</name>
      <address>
        <city>GuangZhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510515</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bing Xu, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>13189096353</phone>
      <email>xubingzhangjian@126.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Xutao Guo, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>13802426709</phone>
      <email>gxt827@126.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bing Xu, M.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nfyy.com/</url>
    <description>Nanfang Hospital, The Southern Medical University</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shi P, Zha J, Guo X, Chen F, Fan Z, Huang F, Meng F, Liu X, Feng R, Xu B. Idarubicin is superior to daunorubicin in remission induction of de novo acute myeloid leukemia patients with high MDR1 expression. Pharmacogenomics. 2013 Jan;14(1):17-23. doi: 10.2217/pgs.12.182.</citation>
    <PMID>23252945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Idarubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

