<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01888692</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B2006;089</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01888692</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Evaluate the Impact of PET/CT on Radiation Treatment Planning in Relation to Changes in GTV in Stage 3 NSCLC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Observational Study to Evaluate the Impact of PET/CT Simulation on Radiation Treatment Planning in Relation to Changes in GTV in Locally Advanced Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manitoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manitoba</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acknowledging that level I evidence already exists regarding the general beneficial impact on
      FDG PET in the staging and subsequent management of lung cancer the investigators postulate
      that fusing PET/CT data sets with RT CT simulation data sets for adult patients with
      conventionally/clinically assessed stage III non-small cell lung cancer will have a
      significant impact on GTV as well as normal tissue irradiation. This research will also
      estimate inter and intra-observer variability of treatment planning, relative to GTV, between
      and amongst radiation oncologists.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary objectives of the study:

      1.To determine the impact of PET/CT fusion on gross tumor volume ( GTV ) for primary(GTVP)
      and nodal (GTVN) disease for each patient by comparing GTV contours using two separate data
      sets.

      (A) GTVP CT+ ve and GTVN CT+ ve

      (B) GTVP PET+ve and GTVN PET +ve

      GTV will be measured and recorded in cubic centimeters for each volume.

      Secondary Endpoints:

      1.Normal tissue toxicity:3D conformal Computerized radiation plans will be generated for the
      data sets GTVP and GTVN A and B .Dose Volume Histogram (DVH) will be determined and compared
      for the following normal tissue toxicity parameters.

      I. V 20 Both lungs (Combined total lung volumes including PTV): Volume of both lungs
      receiving ≥ 20 G y, including planning target volume.

      II. Mean lung dose: Mean radiation dose received by both lungs in a given radiation plan,
      calculated by the planning computer.

      III. V 55 Esophagus: Volume of esophagus receiving≥ 55Gy.

      IV. Mean esophageal dose : Mean radiation dose received by whole esophagus in a given
      radiation plan, calculated by the planning computer

      V. Spinal cord dose: Maximum dose received by the spinal cord in a given radiation plan.

      V1.. V40 Whole heart: Volume of heart receiving ≥ 40Gy

      2A Inter observer variation: This will be determined for the data sets GTV A and B only
      delineated by 4 radiation oncologists blinded to each other, for first 20 patients. The
      resident involved in this project will be responsible to co-ordinate this part of the
      project. GTV will be measured and recorded in cubic centimeters for each volume.

      2B Intra observer variation: This will be determined for the data sets GTV A and B only
      delineated by the same radiation oncologist (treating physician) at two different occasions,
      for first 20 patients. Minimum time interval between the two contours will be one month .The
      resident involved in this project will be responsible to co-ordinate this part of the
      project. GTV will be measured and recorded in cubic centimeters for each volume.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Poor accural
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of PET/CT fusion on gross tumor volume for primary and nodal disease for each patient by comparing GTV contours using three separate data sets.</measure>
    <time_frame>From April 2007 -upto two years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pathologically proven NSCLC Clinical stage III A (inoperable) or stage IIIB where there is
        intent to pursue radical curative RT/chemo, staged with conventional imaging as outlined in
        standard work up section
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be eligible for the Oncology FDG PET Winnipeg PET Program/Edmonton Cross
             Cancer Institute Extended Phase III Clinical Trial - Protocol 001, and in addition;

          -  Pathologically proven NSCLC

          -  Clinical stage III A (inoperable) or stage IIIB where there is intent to pursue
             radical curative RT/chemo, staged with conventional imaging as outlined in standard
             work up section.

          -  ECOG Performance status 0-2

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  FEV1 ≥ 1.0 L

          -  No prior or concurrent malignancy except non-melanomatous skin cancer unless
             disease-free for one year or more for non primary bronchogenic cancers and two years
             for primary bronchogencic cancers;

          -  No prior RT to thorax.

          -  Must be able to start RT within 4 weeks after PET/CT simulation

          -  Participants may be treated with radical radiation only or without concurrent
             chemotherapy, adjuvant chemotherapy or neo-adjuvant therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  As per Oncology FDG PET Winnipeg PET Program/Edmonton Cross Cancer Institute Extended
             Phase III Clinical Trial - Protocol 001 and more specifically:

          -  Unable/unwilling to give informed consent.

          -  Uncontrolled hyperglycemia ( Blood sugar&gt; 12 mmol/L)

          -  Pregnant or lactating females
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Naseer Ahmed, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>CancerCare Manitoba</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Care Manitoba</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winnipeg</city>
        <state>Manitoba</state>
        <zip>R3E0V9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PET/CT</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

