<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01883414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ULT-136 Avram</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01883414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility Study: Evaluation of the Ulthera® System for Improvement of Surgical Scars.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility Study: Evaluation of the Ulthera® System for Improvement of Surgical Scars.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ulthera, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merz North America, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Up to 25 subjects will be enrolled. Enrolled subjects will received on Ulthera® treatment on
      one half of their surgical scar. Follow up visits will occur at 30, 90 and 180 days after
      treatment. Study images will be obtained before treatment, immediately after treatment and at
      each follow-up visit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, single-center, pilot clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy of the
      Ulthera® system to improve the appearance of scar tissue on the neck, abdomen or back.
      Changes from baseline of the Patient Observer Scar Assessment Scale score will be assessed at
      study follow-up visits. Images will be obtained prior to treatment and at each follow up
      visit. Patient satisfaction questionnaires will also be obtained.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of resources to manage trial; lack of efficacy.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint is improvement in appearance of scar tissue as determined by a masked, qualitative assessment of photographs at 90-days post-treatment time points comparing the treated to untreated side of the scar.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Masked assessors will compare baseline images to images obtained at the 90 day follow up time point in a blinded fashion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1. Improvement in POSAS score of the treated half of the scar as assessed by the observer using the Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale (POSAS) at 90-days post-treatment compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 Days</time_frame>
    <description>The observer will complete the Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale (6 questions) prior to treatment and at each follow up visit on both halves of the scar (treated and untreated). Scores will be tabulated and compared for improvement at 90 days after treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2. Difference in POSAS score as assessed by the patient using the Patient Observer Scar Assessment Scale (POSAS) between the treated and untreated half of the scar at 90-days post-treatment compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 Days</time_frame>
    <description>The subject will complete the Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale (6 questions) prior to treatment and at each follow up visit on both halves of the scar (treated and untreated). Scores will be tabulated and compared for improvement at 90 days after treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3. Patient satisfaction questionnaire at the 90-day follow-up visit.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Each subject will complete a Patient Satisfaction Questionnaire (PSQ) at the 90 follow-up visit. These results will be tabulated to assess subjects satisfaction with the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Surgical Scar</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to Group A will receive Ultherapy™ treatment on the superior or lateral half of the scar.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to Group B will receive Ultherapy™ treatment on the inferior or medial half of the scar.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultherapy™</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will receive an Ultherapy™ treatment at triple depth using the 4-4.5mm, 7- 3.0mm, 10-1.5mm transducers on one half of the scar and no treatment on the other half of the scar. Treatments will be provided to the defined scar area, treating with a density of lines that is equivalent to 30 lines per transducer per 2.5cm in scar length for a total of 90 lines in a 2.5cm X 2.5cm square area.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female, age 18 to 70 years.

          2. Subject in good health.

          3. Subjects will have regularly shaped surgical scars on the chest, abdomen or back that
             are at least 4 cm long, are no wider than 1 cm, and are at least 6 months old.

          4. Understands and accepts the obligation not to undergo any other procedures in the
             areas to be treated through the follow-up period.

          5. Willingness and ability to comply with protocol requirements, including returning for
             follow-up visits and abstaining from exclusionary procedures for the duration of the
             study.

          6. Subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test result
             and must not be lactating at the Screening Visit and be willing and able to use an
             acceptable method of birth control (e.g. barrier methods used with a spermicidal
             agent, hormonal methods, IUD, surgical sterilization, abstinence) during the study.
             Women will not be considered of childbearing potential if one of the following
             conditions is documented on the medical history:

               -  Postmenopausal for at least 12 months prior to study;

               -  Without a uterus and/or both ovaries; or

               -  Bilateral tubal ligation at least six months prior to study enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of an active systemic or local skin disease that may affect wound healing.

          2. Allergy to any pain medications used in the study (lidocaine, NSAIDs, narcotics, etc.)

          3. Severe solar elastosis.

          4. Open wounds or lesions in the area(s) to be treated.

          5. Severe or cystic acne on the area(s) to be treated.

          6. Presence of a metal stent or implant in the area(s) to be treated.

          7. Inability to understand the protocol or to give informed consent.

          8. Microdermabrasion, or prescription level glycolic acid treatment to the treatment
             area(s) within three months prior to study participation or during the study.

          9. Intralesional kenalog in the past 6 months.

         10. History of chronic drug or alcohol abuse.

         11. History of autoimmune disease.

         12. Concurrent therapy that, in the investigator's opinion, would interfere with the
             evaluation of the safety or efficacy of the study device.

         13. Subjects who anticipate the need for surgery or overnight hospitalization during the
             study.

         14. Subjects who, in the investigator's opinion, have a history of poor cooperation,
             noncompliance with medical treatment, or unreliability.

         15. Concurrent enrollment in any study involving the use of investigational devices or
             drugs.

         16. Current smoker or history of smoking in the last year.

         17. History of the following treatments in the area(s) to be treated:

               1. Skin tightening procedure within the past year;

               2. Injectable filler of any type within the past:

             i. 12 months for Hyaluronic acid fillers (e.g. Restylane) ii. 12 months for Ca
             Hydroxyapatite fillers (e.g. Radiesse) iii. 24 months for Poly-L-Lactic acid fillers
             (e.g. Sculptra) iv. Ever for permanent fillers (e.g. Silicone, ArteFill) c.
             Neurotoxins within the past three months; d. Ablative resurfacing laser treatment; e.
             Nonablative, rejuvenative laser or light treatment within the past six months; f.
             Surgical dermabrasion or deep peels; g. Any history of contour threads.

         18. History of using the following prescription medications:

               1. Accutane or other systemic retinoids within the past six months;

               2. Topical Retinoids within the past two weeks;

               3. Antiplatelet agents/Anticoagulants (Coumadin, Heparin, Plavix, etc.);

               4. Psychiatric drugs that in the investigators opinion would impair the subject from
                  understanding the protocol requirements or understanding and signing the informed
                  consent.

               5. Subjects that are immunocompromised or are on immunosuppressive therapy

         19. Subjects that are immunocompromised or are on immunosuppressive therapy

         20. History of keloids
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mathew Avram, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MGH Dermatology, Laser and Cosmetic Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MGH Dermatology Laser and Cosmetic Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 21, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ulthera, Ultherapy, Surgical scar, scar,</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

