<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01882829</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 13-0389</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IF1463152</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01882829</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nuedexta in Treatment-Resistant Major Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Targeting the NMDA Glutamate Receptor as Novel Antidepressant Strategy: A Pilot Clinical Trial of Nuedexta in Treatment-Resistant Major Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>James Murrough</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is an urgent need, therefore, to identify well-tolerated, orally available compounds
      that target the NMDA receptor as a novel treatment approach for TRD. The current project aims
      to test the safety, tolerability and efficacy of Nuedexta - containing the NMDA antagonist
      dextromethorphan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately one-third of patients with major depressive disorder do not achieve adequate
      symptom control despite a series of multiple treatment trials with currently available
      antidepressant medication (for example a serotonin-selective reuptake inhibitor). This group
      of patients - representing treatment-resistant depression (TRD) - accounts for an alarmingly
      high public health burden and signifies a critical area of need in pharmaceutical treatment
      development. While current treatments are slow to act and only partially effective, new basic
      and clinical research focusing on the glutamate system is yielding promising new avenues for
      novel drug discovery. Ketamine - a glutamate N-methyl-d-aspartate (NMDA) receptor antagonist
      - has now been demonstrated in several studies to bring about a rapid and robust
      antidepressant effect, even in patients suffering from TRD. Ketamine is limited as a
      treatment for TRD by the need for intravenous administration and the potential for untoward
      medical or psychiatric adverse effects. There is an urgent need, therefore, to identify
      well-tolerated, orally available compounds that target the NMDA receptor as a novel treatment
      approach for TRD. The current project aims to test the safety, tolerability and efficacy of
      Nuedexta - containing the NMDA antagonist dextromethorphan.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and visit 6 (week 10)</time_frame>
    <description>The Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale is a 10-item instrument used for the evaluation of depressive symptoms in adults and for the assessment of any changes to those symptoms. Each of the 10 items is rated on a scale of 0 to 6, with differing descriptors for each item. These individual item scores are added together to form a total score, which can range between 0 and 60 points. The MADRS is specifically designed to detect changes in depression severity in the context of a medication treatment trial and is the used as the primary outcome of the current study.
Primary outcome is change in MADRS at Visit 6 (Week 10)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire Short Form</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and Visit 6 (week 10)</time_frame>
    <description>The Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire Short Form is a reliable and valid self-report measure designed to obtain sensitive measures of the degree of enjoyment and satisfaction experienced by individuals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Range of Impaired Functioning Tool</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and Visit 6 (week 10)</time_frame>
    <description>The Range of Impaired Functioning Tool a brief scale for assessing functional impairment related to medical or psychiatric illness and has been demonstrated to possess good psychometric properties.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sheehan Disability Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and Visit 6 (week 10)</time_frame>
    <description>The Sheehan Disability Scale is a self-rated scale which assesses illness-related disability in three areas of functioning: work, social and family.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Rated Inventory of Side Effects (PRISE)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of observed adverse events over the study treatment period as captured by the PRISE. The Patient Rated Inventory of Side Effects (PRISE) assesses the presence of treatment side effects in nine organ/function systems (gastrointestinal, nervous system, heart, eyes/ears, skin, genital/urinary, sleep, sexual functioning, and other).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) is a comprehensive, semi-structured interview measure that uniquely measures the full spectrum of suicidality including passive and active suicidal ideation, suicidal intent as well as suicidal behaviors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology, Self Report (QIDS-SR)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology, Self Report (QIDS-SR) is a 16-item self rated instrument designed to assess the severity of depressive symptoms (30). The 16 items cover the nine symptom domains of major depression, and are rated on a scale of 0-3. Total score ranges from 0 to 27, with ranges of 0-5 (normal), 6-10 (mild), 11-15 (moderate), 16-20 (moderate to severe), and 21+ (severe).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression (CGI) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Clinical Global Impression (CGI) scale assesses overall treatment response in psychiatric patients and has good reliability and validity metrics. The administration time is 2 minutes. This scale consists of three items: Severity of Illness (item 1); Global Improvement (item 2); and Efficacy Index (item 3). Item 1 is rated on a seven-point scale (1 = normal, 7 = among the most extremely ill patients) as is item 2 (1 = very much improved, 7 = very much worse).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Massachusetts General Hospital Cognitive and Physical Functioning Questionnaire (CPFQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and Visit 6 (week 10)</time_frame>
    <description>The Massachusetts General Hospital Cognitive and Physical Functioning Questionnaire (CPFQ) is a brief scale to measure cognitive and executive dysfunction in mood and anxiety disorders, and possesses good reliability and validity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Treatment Resistant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nuedexta (dextromethorphan/quinidine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>45/10 mg every 12 hours x 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dextromethorphan/quinidine</intervention_name>
    <description>up to 45/10 mg every 12 hours in patients with TRD with a short 7 day tapering period in which subjects are tapered off 45/10 mg dose from twice a day to once daily for an additional 7 days at post 8-week treatment period to minimize the potential for discontinuation effects</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nuedexta (dextromethorphan/quinidine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nuedexta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female participants, 18-65 years of age;

          -  Current primary Axis I diagnosis of major depressive disorder according to DSM-IV-TR
             criteria as determined by a psychiatrist and confirmed with the Structured Clinical
             Interview for DSM-IV Axis I Disorders (SCID);

          -  Current treatment-resistant depression defined by a history of inadequate response to
             a minimum of 2 adequate antidepressant treatment trials determined by patient history
             and chart review and confirmed with the Antidepressant Treatment History Form (ATHF);

          -  Participants must be willing to discontinue treatment with concomitant medications
             that are disallowed by the study protocol;

          -  Participants must have a level of understanding of the English language sufficient to
             agree to all tests and examinations required by the study and must be able to
             participate fully in the informed consent process.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lifetime diagnosis of schizophrenia or any psychotic disorder, bipolar disorder,
             pervasive developmental disorders or mental retardation

          -  Diagnosis of a substance use disorder within the past 1 year ;

          -  Female participants who are pregnant, nursing, for may become pregnant;

          -  Any unstable medical illnesses including hepatic, renal, gastroenterologic,
             respiratory, cardiovascular (including ischemic heart disease); endocrinologic,
             neurologic (including history of severe head injury), immunologic, or hematologic
             disease;

          -  Participants with clinically significant abnormalities of laboratories, physical
             examination, or ECG;

          -  Prolonged QT interval, congenital long QT syndrome, history suggestive of torsades de
             pointes, or heart failure;

          -  Complete atrioventricular (AV) block without implanted pacemaker, or patients at high
             risk of complete AV block

          -  Participants with a history of quinidine, quinine or mefloquine-induced
             thrombocytopenia, hepatitis, or other hypersensitivity reactions;

          -  Participants judged to be at serious suicidal risk by the PI;

          -  Concomitant use with quinidine, quinine, or mefloquine;

          -  Participants with known hypersensitivity to dextromethorphan;

          -  Use with an MAOI or within 14 days of stopping an MAOI;

          -  Concomitant use with drugs that prolong QT interval and are metabolized by CYP2D6
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Murrough, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mssm.edu/map</url>
    <description>Mood and Anxiety Disorders Program</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 20, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Murrough</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>major depressive disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment resistant</keyword>
  <keyword>Nuedexta</keyword>
  <keyword>dextromethorphan</keyword>
  <keyword>antidepressant</keyword>
  <keyword>glutamate</keyword>
  <keyword>NMDA receptor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antidepressive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dextromethorphan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Quinidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Quinidine gluconate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 5, 2017</submitted>
    <submission_canceled>Unknown</submission_canceled>
    <submitted>October 11, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>November 8, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>January 15, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>February 12, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>May 10, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

