<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01882764</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HMPL-004-04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01882764</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase III Maintenance Placebo Controlled Maintenance Trial Of HMPL-004 in Subjects With Mild to Moderate Ulcerative Colitis</brief_title>
  <acronym>NATRUL-4</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase III Double Blind, Multi-Center Placebo Controlled Maintenance Trial of HMPL-004 in Subjects With Mild to Moderate Ulcerative Colitis With Clinical Remission or Response From Induction Therapy. (NATRUL-4)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hutchison Medipharma Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nutrition Science Partners Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hutchison Medipharma Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A study with an 8 week open label phase study followed by a year long placebo controlled
      maintenance phase in subjects with active mild to moderate ulcerative colitis (UC), with a
      modified Mayo Score 4-10 and an endoscopy subscore of 2-3, taking mesalamine (or equivalent)
      as a concomitant medication. Subjects are required to be in clinical remission or clinical
      response to enter the year long maintenance phase. This study will help evaluate if HMPL-004
      is effective in subjects maintaining clinical remission following successful induction
      therapy achieving clinical remission or clinical response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A two-phase multi-center study with an open label 8-week induction phase and a randomized,
      double-blind, placebo controlled maintenance phase to evaluate the efficacy and safety of
      HMPL-004 for a 52-week maintenance therapy in adults with mild to moderate UC and who have
      demonstrated a sub-optimal response to mesalamine treatment. The study participants will
      consist of subjects who have completed either the HMPL-004-03 or HMPL-004-05 induction study,
      complemented by the enrollment of additional subjects in the open label induction phase who
      meet the entry criteria of this study. . Subjects entering this maintenance study from one of
      the HMPL-004 induction studies will have their modified Mayo baseline score from that study
      as their baseline score for this study. All subjects enrolled in the open label induction
      phase of the study will be re-evaluated for clinical response and remission after the 8-week
      open label 2400 mg HMPL-004 treatment period. Clinical responders and remitters will be
      randomized 2:1 (HMPL-004: placebo) to HMPL-004 1800 mg/day or placebo group for the 52-week
      maintenance phase of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Efficacy of HMPL-004 in the maintenance of clinical remission</measure>
    <time_frame>After 1 year of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the proportion of subjects who are in clinical remission after 52 weeks of maintenance treatment, following successful induction therapy to achieve clinical remission or clinical response. Clinical remission is defined as a modified Mayo Score ≤2 along with no individual score &gt;1 AND rectal bleeding score = 0. The Mayo Scoring system used for this study has been modified to allow mild friability to be scored as a 2 (moderate disease). Clinical response is defined as a decrease in the modified Mayo Score from baseline by ≥ 3 points AND ≥ 30% decrease in the modified Mayo Score, along with either a decrease in the rectal bleeding score ≥ 1 OR an absolute rectal bleeding score ≤ 1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HMPL-004 1800 mg/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HMPL-004 600 mg tablet given t.i.d.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>600 mg Placebo tablet given t.i.d.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HMPL-004 tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>HMPL-004 tablet given at a strength of 1800 mg/day, (600 mg t.i.d.)</description>
    <arm_group_label>HMPL-004 1800 mg/day</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Tablet</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Completion of induction study HMPL-004-03 or HMPL-004-05 and achieving clinical
             remission or response with no disruption of study treatment in the transition to
             HMPL-004-04, or, for the open label induction phase of the study: have active mild to
             moderate Ulcerative Colitis defined by a modified Mayo Score of 4 to 10 and with
             endoscopy score activity of 2-3 points confirmed by a full colonoscopy within 2 weeks
             prior to study.

          2. Subjects must be currently receiving mesalamine ≥ 2.4 g/day (or the equivalent) for at
             least 6 weeks prior to randomization and on a stable dosage for at least 2 weeks prior
             to entering the screening phase of the study to ensure a stable dose is established at
             least 2 weeks prior to the endoscopic procedures.

          3. Have adequate renal, hepatic and bone marrow function (see exclusion criteria).

          4. Age ≥ 18 years

          5. All fertile male and female subjects must agree to use one of the following types of
             contraception: intrauterine device, implantable progesterone device, progesterone
             intramuscular injection, oral contraceptive which has been started at least one month
             prior to visit one and continues for the duration of the trial, contraceptive patch,
             or condom with spermicide.

          6. Show evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating
             that the subject (or legally acceptable representative) has been informed of all
             pertinent aspects of the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with intolerance to mesalamine (or equivalent medications).

          2. Diagnosed with Crohn's disease or with lesions such as fistulas or granulomas on
             biopsy noted either in history or at baseline endoscope, which would be suspicious for
             Crohn's disease, or with a diagnosis of indeterminate colitis.

          3. Severe disease with a Ulcerative Colitis modified Mayo Clinic score above 10 points at
             baseline.

          4. Positive stool test for pathogens on sample taken within the 2 weeks prior to study
             entry.

          5. Active clostridium difficile (C. diff) infection.

          6. Use of Inflammatory Bowel Disease related herbal supplements including supplements
             containing andrographis or the use of probiotics two weeks prior to study entry or
             during the study.

          7. Toxic megacolon or toxic colitis.

          8. Probable requirement for intestinal surgery within 12 weeks after the start of
             investigational product.

          9. Receiving oral or rectal steroids within 1 month prior to study entry.

         10. Receiving rectal mesalamine within 1 week prior to study entry.

         11. Receiving azathioprine, 6-mercaptopurine, methotrexate, tacrolimus, cyclosporine, or
             other immunosuppressive therapy at the time of screening or within the preceding 6
             weeks.

         12. Receiving anti-TNF-α agents such as infliximab, adalimumab, golimumab, or certolizumab
             pegol at the time of screening or within the preceding 8 weeks.

         13. Receiving other investigational drugs or biologics within 1 month or five half-lives,
             whichever is longer.

         14. Receiving antibiotics within 2 weeks of study entry.

         15. Hemoglobin concentration &lt;9 g/dl.

         16. WBC below 3,000/cm3, or platelets below 100,000/cm3.

         17. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), and/or alkaline
             phosphatase &gt;2.5 upper limit of normal.

         18. Serum creatinine &gt;1.5 times upper limit of normal.

         19. Significant concurrent medical diseases including: active peptic ulcer disease;
             uncompensated congestive heart disease; myocardial infarction within the last 12
             months; unstable angina pectoris; uncontrolled hypertension; and pulmonary disease
             requiring oxygen therapy.

         20. Chronic Hepatitis B or any history of Hepatitis C.

         21. Previous colonic surgery except for simple polypectomy.

         22. History of cancer within the last 5 years other than resected cutaneous basal and
             squamous cell carcinomas, and/or in situ cervical cancer.

         23. Subjects with a history of or concurrent colonic dysplasia associated with UC, except
             those with completely excised sporadic colorectal polyps.

         24. Women who are pregnant or breast feeding.

         25. Subjects known to be seropositive for HIV, or who have had an AIDS defining illness,
             or a known immunodeficiency disorder.

         26. History of alcohol or drug abuse that would interfere with the ability to be compliant
             with the study procedure.

         27. Known allergy to plants of the Acanthaceae family.

         28. Unwillingness to participate in the study.

         29. Any underlying medical condition that in the Investigator's opinion will make the
             administration of study drug hazardous to the subject or would obscure the
             interpretation of Adverse Events.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Research Management, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Agawam</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 20, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

