<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01881412</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACP-231928-N</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ACP-231928-N</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01881412</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Inhaled Steroids at Discharge After Emergency Department Visits for Children With Uncontrolled Asthma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimizing Discharge After Emergency Department Visits for Children With Uncontrolled Asthma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rhode Island Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Lung Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rhode Island Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Many children have asthma and this causes problems with their health. A lot of children with
      uncontrolled asthma use emergency departments for asthma care, and so this is an ideal place
      for an intervention for these children. One intervention is prescribing inhaled steroids to
      children with uncontrolled asthma, but currently this is rarely done in the emergency
      department. Inhaled steroids have been shown to be good at making children better long-term
      when they have uncontrolled asthma.

      This study identifies children in the emergency department with uncontrolled asthma using a
      tool called the Pediatric Asthma Control and Communication Instrument (PACCI). If children
      meet criteria for uncontrolled asthma they will be randomly assigned to either: 1) routine
      asthma care which includes close follow up with their doctor or 2) prescribing of an inhaled
      corticosteroid from the emergency department. The investigators hypothesize that children who
      are prescribed inhaled steroids for uncontrolled asthma from the emergency department will
      have better 6 month asthma control than children who receive routine asthma care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific aim 1 - An ED-based RCT to determine if ICS prescription in children identified
      using the PACCI as having uncontrolled asthma results in less asthma morbidity compared to
      routine asthma care. We hypothesize that children receiving ICS prescriptions will have fewer
      unscheduled health care use for asthma exacerbations (doctor's office visits, ED visits, or
      hospitalizations), and greater quality of life.

      Specific aim 2 - Thematic analysis of interviews with parents who are adherent versus
      non-adherent with ICS prescription filling and use to determine the factors associated with
      adherence. We hypothesize that factors will include: 1) Parent beliefs about the chronic
      versus episodic nature of asthma, 2) Parent's knowledge of benefits and risks of ICS, and 3)
      Provision and use of an asthma action plan.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Funding complete
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality-of-life (using ITG-CASF)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The ITG-CASF has been validated in the ED setting for children 2 to 17 years old, is reliable (Cronbach's α =0.70), and can be administered by telephone. Each item is rated on a 5-point scale. Each response is scaled as a percentage of the maximum response, and the total score is the maximum percentage based on the number of questions answered. The scores range from 0 - 100, with higher scores reflecting better quality of life. The change in ITG-CASF scores for children with improved overall clinical status are 10 points higher than when children have not improved.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unscheduled Health Care Use</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>These measures will include unscheduled visits to primary care providers (PCPs) for asthma, emergency department visits for asthma, and hospitalizations. We will use parent reports for the 6 month period. Hospital and PCP medical records will be used to corroborate reported data, and for families that are unable to be contacted.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication fills</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Preferred pharmacies as indicated by participants will be contacted to quantify the number of asthma-related medication refills during the time period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">118</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inhaled corticosteroid (fluticasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Child receives: 1) standardized asthma discharge instructions, and the intervention which is 2) inhaled corticosteroid prescription with accompanying instructions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Routine Asthma Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Child receives: 1) Standard Asthma Discharge Instructions. No intervention in this arm (placebo controlled)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluticasone</intervention_name>
    <description>During discharge, the study MD/nurse informs the family that the child has been randomized to the inhaled corticosteroid (ICS) group, and will be prescribed fluticasone to help control the asthma. The families preferred pharmacy is determined and a prescription for a fluticasone multi-dose inhaler (MDI) provided. Dosing follows the NHLBI asthma guidelines for low dose ICS in this age group (88 mcg administered twice per day, dispense one inhaler, 3 refills). In addition to standard asthma discharge instructions, the family receives specific instructions for ICS administration, possible side effects of medication use, and distinction between controller and quick-relief rescue medications. Parents are instructed to discuss with their primary care provider the length of ICS use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inhaled corticosteroid (fluticasone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>inhaled corticosteroid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Asthma Discharge Instructions</intervention_name>
    <description>Study MD or nurse provides asthma discharge instructions using a standardized checklist. The topics covered include 1) description of asthma manifestations related to current visit, 2) signs of respiratory distress family should be looking for, 3) instructions to follow up with the child's primary care provider within one week, 4) provision and review of an asthma action plan, 5) provision of a spacer device to be used with inhalers (if family does not already possess), and 6) smoking cessation advice. (if indicated)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inhaled corticosteroid (fluticasone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Routine Asthma Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  3 - 12 years of age

          -  child has asthma diagnosed by a doctor based on parental/caregiver report

          -  child is not already properly using an ICS or being discharged with an ICS

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The child has previously participated in this study

          -  The child has major co-morbid disease of the heart or lungs (examples include cystic
             fibrosis, heart disease, muscular dystrophy and cerebral palsy with immobility. It
             does not include allergic rhinitis or a history of respiratory infections such as
             pneumonia or bronchiolitis.

          -  The child's parents/caregivers do not speak English

          -  The child is not going to be discharged from the emergency department (e.g.
             hospitalization)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aris C Garro, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brown University and Rhode Island Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rhode Island Hospital / Hasbro Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02906</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 19, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Inhaled Corticosteroids</keyword>
  <keyword>Emergency Department</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

