<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01887587</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO00020384</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01887587</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Study Of Vincristine, Doxorubicin, And Dexamethasone (VXD) Plus Ixazomib In Adults With Relapsed Or Refractory Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia/Lymphoma, Lymphoblastic Lymphoma Or Mixed Phenotype Acute Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study Of Vincristine, Doxorubicin, And Dexamethasone (VXD) Plus Ixazomib In Adults With Relapsed Or Refractory Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia/Lymphoma, Lymphoblastic Lymphoma Or Mixed Phenotype Acute Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ehab L Atallah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I study of vincristine, doxorubicin and dexamethasone (modified VXD) plus
      MLN9708 in adults with relapsed or refractory acute lymphoblastic leukemia/lymphoma,
      lymphoblastic lymphoma or mixed phenotype acute leukemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this phase I study, escalating doses of MLN9708 will be combined with a fixed dose mVXD
      regimen. MLN 9708 will be administered on day 1, 8, and 15. If the patient experiences a DLT
      the dose of MLN maybe reduced to the next dose level on day 8 or day 15 in that patient. DLT
      would be any grade 3 or more toxicity which is thought to be probably or definitely related
      to MLN9708. Three patients will be treated per dose level unless dose limiting toxicity (DLT)
      is observed. The starting dose of MLN9708 will be 2.3 mg orally on days 1, 8 and 15. If
      toxicity is seen at this level then dose may be reduced to 1.5 mg (dose level -1) . If no DLT
      is seen in the first 3 patients, the dose will be increased to 3 mg and then to 4 mg orally
      on days 1, 8 and 15 in a classic 3 +3 phase I design. We will not attempt to increase the
      dose beyond 4 mg orally which, if achieved with acceptable toxicity, would be accepted as the
      recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D). 0 of 3 DLTs would allow escalation to the next dose level. 1
      of 3 DLTs will require expanding to six patients; 1 of 6 DLTs will allow escalation again. 2
      DLTs will require dose de-escalation. The maximum tolerated dose (MTD) will be the highest
      dose administered at which no more than 1 DLT was observed. All patients will be evaluated
      for hematopoetic stem cell transplantation. If patients achieve CR and are eligible for HSCT,
      they will proceed to HSCT. If they are not eligible, no donor is identified or if HSCT will
      be delayed, and the patient has achieved benefit, then treatment maybe repeated at the
      discretion of the investigator. A total of 9-18 patients will be enrolled on the study. The
      study duration would be about 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    SAE- risk of overall protocol treatment outweighs benefits
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the number of patients with adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety, tolerability will be assessed by number of participants with adverse events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the optimal dose of MLN9708</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Optimal dose will be assessed by number of participants with adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsed or Refractory Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Relapsed or Refractory Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Mixed Phenotype Acute Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>(modified VXLD) plus MLN9708</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vincristine-1.5 mg/m2 to a max dose of 2 mg IV on days 1, 8, 15 and 22
Dexamethasone- 10 mg/m2 orally or IV on days 1-14
Doxorubicin- 60 mg/m2 on day 1 by IV bolus.
For patients without CNS involvement:
Cytarabine 100 mg will be administered intrathecally on day 1 (+/-1 day) (cytarabine dose should be reduced to 50 mg if given through a central ommaya reservoir)
Methotrexate 12 mg will be administered intrathecally on day 8 (+/-1 day)
For patients with CNS involvement:
-Cytarabine 100 mg will be administered intrathecally on day 1 (+/-1 day) (cytarabine dose should be reduced to 50 mg if given through a central ommaya reservoir) Triple intrathecal chemotherapy with cytarabine 30 mg, methotrexate 15 mg and hydrocortisone 15 mg on (Day 1, 8, 15 and 22 (+/-1 day)).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MLN9708</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>(modified VXLD) plus MLN9708</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vincristine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>(modified VXLD) plus MLN9708</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Oncovin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doxorubicin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>(modified VXLD) plus MLN9708</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Doxil</other_name>
    <other_name>hydroxydaunorubicin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>(modified VXLD) plus MLN9708</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Each patient must meet all of the following inclusion criteria to be enrolled in the study:

        Inclusion

          -  Male or female patients 18 years or older

          -  Have relapsed B or T-precursor acute lymphocytic leukemia/lymphoma, lymphoblastic
             lymphoma or mixed phenotype acute leukemia with increased bone marrow or peripheral
             blood blasts by morphology with or without CNS involvement

          -  Prior therapy: At least two prior treatment attempts to induce remission with no limit
             on the number of prior treatment regimens.

          -  Patients are eligible after allogeneic stem cell transplantation

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          -  Patients must meet the following clinical laboratory criteria:

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x the upper limit of the normal range (ULN).

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 3 x ULN.

               -  Calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 30 mL/min

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 1,000/cmm and platelets &gt; 75,000/cmm unless the
                  cytopenias are secondary to disease

          -  Life expectancy reasonably adequate for evaluating the treatment effect

          -  Patients must be at least 2 weeks from major surgery, radiation therapy, participation
             in other investigational trials and have recovered from clinically significant
             toxicities of these prior treatments

          -  Female patients who:

               -  Are postmenopausal for at least 1 year before the screening visit, OR

               -  Are surgically sterile, OR

               -  If they are of childbearing potential, agree to practice 2 effective methods of
                  contraception, at the same time, from the time of signing the informed consent
                  form through 90 days after the last dose of study drug, OR

               -  Agree to practice true abstinence when this is in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the subject. (Periodic abstinence [eg, calendar, ovulation,
                  symptothermal, post-ovulation methods] and withdrawal are not acceptable methods
                  of contraception.)

          -  Male patients, even if surgically sterilized (ie, status post-vasectomy), must agree
             to one of the following:

               -  Agree to practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study
                  treatment period and through 90 days after the last dose of study drug, OR

               -  Agree to practice true abstinence when this is in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the subject. (Periodic abstinence (eg, calendar, ovulation,
                  symptothermal, post-ovulation methods] and withdrawal are not acceptable methods
                  of contraception.).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients meeting any of the following exclusion criteria are not to be enrolled in the
        study:

          -  Patients who are Ph+ ALL who are naive to therapy with an approved tyrosine kinase
             inhibitor.

          -  Prior exposure to ≥350 mg/m2 of anthracycline (in doxorubicin equivalent dosing), or
             left ventricular fractional shortening less than 50%.

          -  Failure to have fully recovered (ie, ≤ Grade 2 toxicity) from the effects of prior
             chemotherapy regardless of the interval since last treatment.

          -  Major surgery within 14 days before enrollment.

          -  Chemotherapy in the last 14 days. (Steroids or Intrathecal chemotherapy will be
             allowed).

          -  Systemic treatment, within 7 days before study enrollment, with strong inhibitors of
             CYP1A2 (fluvoxamine, enoxacin, ciprofloxacin), strong inhibitors of CYP3A
             (clarithromycin, telithromycin, itraconazole, voriconazole, ketoconazole, nefazodone,
             posaconazole) or strong CYP3A inducers (rifampin, rifapentine, rifabutin,
             carbamazepine, phenytoin, phenobarbital), or use of Ginkgo biloba or St. John's wort.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirements. Patients receiving
             intravenous antibiotics for infections that are under control may be included in this
             study.

          -  Known allergy to any of the study medications, their analogues, or excipients in the
             various formulations of any agent.

          -  Inability to swallow oral medication, inability or unwillingness to comply with the
             drug administration requirements, or GI procedure that could interfere with the oral
             absorption or tolerance of treatment.

          -  Diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 2 years before study enrollment or
             previously diagnosed with another malignancy and have any evidence of residual
             disease. Patients with nonmelanoma skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of any type are
             not excluded if they have undergone complete resection.

          -  Patient has ≥ Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy.

          -  Participation in clinical trials with other investigational agents not included in
             this trial, within 14 days of the start of this trial and throughout the duration of
             this trial.

          -  Female patients who are breastfeeding or have a positive serum pregnancy test during
             the screening period or a positive urine pregnancy test on Day 1 before first dose of
             study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ehab L Atallah, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Froedtert Hospital and the Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 24, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ehab L Atallah</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ixazomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vincristine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

