<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01882985</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCI 10-11</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2010-7765</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2011-00037</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01882985</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Docetaxel Plus Lycopene in Castration Resistant, Chemotherapy-Naïve Prostate Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study to Evaluate the Effects of Docetaxel Plus Lycopene in Castration Resistant, Chemotherapy-Naïve Prostate Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Irvine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Irvine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial evaluated the impact of giving docetaxel together with lycopene
      supplements in treating patients with hormone-resistant prostate cancer not previously
      treated with chemotherapy. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as docetaxel, work in different
      ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from
      dividing. Chemoprevention is the use of certain drugs, such as lycopene, to keep cancer from
      forming. Giving docetaxel together with lycopene may be an effective treatment for prostate
      cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To define the prostate-specific antigen (PSA) response rate according to the criteria of
      Bubley, et al., in subjects treated with a combination of docetaxel and lycopene.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To define the prostate-specific antigen (PSA) response rate according to the criteria of
      Bubley, et al. (&gt;50% reduction from baseline) in subjects treated with a combination of
      docetaxel and lycopene.

      II. To define the time to PSA progression, according to the response criteria of Scher, et
      al., in subjects treated with docetaxel and lycopene.

      III. To determine the safety and tolerability of lycopene in combination with docetaxel.

      IV. To determine the effects of docetaxel + lycopene therapy on the functioning of the
      insulin-like growth factor receptor (IGFRI), selected biomarkers, and docetaxel blood levels
      in plasma and peripheral blood mononuclear cells (correlative studies).

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive 75 mg/m2 docetaxel intravenously (IV) over 1 hour q 21 days and lycopene 30
      mg capsules orally (PO) once daily on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 21 days for at least
      4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response (proportion of subjects achieving a &gt;= 50% reduction in PSA from baseline)</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 12 of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Data analysis for the primary endpoint will involve estimation of the PSA response rate (and 95% confidence interval) defined as the proportion of subjects achieving a &gt;= 50% reduction in PSA from a baseline value of at least 2ng/ml at any point after the start of treatment. 95% confidence intervals will be estimated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate as assessed by RECIST criteria in either visceral or lymph node metastases</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The percent of subjects achieving an objective response by RECIST criteria in either visceral or lymph node metastases, and the percent achieving clinical complete disappearance of disease at any site, will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to PSA progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The definition of time to PSA progression is the date (after the initiation of chemotherapy on day 2) that a 25% or greater increase, and an absolute increase of 2ng/mL or more, from the nadir PSA is documented. If there is no decrease in PSA following chemotherapy, then PSA progression is the date for documentation of a 25% increase from the baseline value along with an increase in absolute value of 2ng/mL or more.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity of combined docetaxel + lycopene therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of subjects experiencing grade 3-4 hematologic and non-hematologic toxicity will be recorded, as well as the reason for ending treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of the Prostate</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIA Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIB Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel and lycopene)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive docetaxel IV over 1 hour on day 2 and lycopene PO once daily on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 21days for at least 4 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel and lycopene)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>114977-28-5</other_name>
    <other_name>40466</other_name>
    <other_name>628503</other_name>
    <other_name>RP 56976</other_name>
    <other_name>RP56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>TXT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lycopene</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel and lycopene)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>407322</other_name>
    <other_name>502-65-8</other_name>
    <other_name>all-trans-Lycopene</other_name>
    <other_name>Lyc-O-Mato</other_name>
    <other_name>LYCO</other_name>
    <other_name>psi</other_name>
    <other_name>psi-Carotene</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must have a histological diagnosis of adenocarcinoma of the prostate and 2
             rising pre-study PSA values &gt;= 1 ng/ml at least 1 week apart within 28 days prior to
             enrollment

          -  Patients must be unresponsive to androgen-deprivation therapy (ADT), as indicated by a
             rising PSA level above the ADT nadir

          -  Patient must not have received chemotherapy, biologic therapy, or any other
             investigational drug for any reason within 28 days prior to start of therapy, and must
             have recovered from toxicities of prior therapy to grade 1 or less

          -  Patients must have been surgically or medically castrated; if the patient is being
             treated with medical castration, he must be willing to continue this treatment for the
             duration of the study; ADT should not be initiated, terminated, or dose-adjusted
             during the study

          -  Prior external beam radiation therapy (to less than 30% of the bone marrow only) is
             allowed; at least 28 days must have elapsed since the completion of radiation therapy
             and the patient must have recovered from side effects; prior treatment with
             samarium-153 or strontium-86 is allowed if at least eight weeks have elapsed since
             dosing, and all toxicities have resolved to grade 1; soft tissue disease which has
             been radiated in the prior 2 months is not assessable as measurable disease

          -  Patients may have received prior surgery; however, at least 21 days must have elapsed
             since completion of surgery and the patient must have recovered from all side effects

          -  Normal serum bilirubin and serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) or serum
             glutamic pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) =&lt; 1.5 x the institutional upper limit of normal
             obtained within 14 days prior to start of therapy; liver function tests should be
             evaluated prior to each treatment

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x the institutional upper limit of normal obtained within 14
             days prior to start of therapy

          -  Men of child bearing potential must be willing to consent to using effective
             contraception while on treatment and for at least 3 months thereafter

          -  Patient must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/microliter (mcL)

          -  Hemoglobin of &gt;= 8.0gm/dL

          -  White blood cell count &gt; 2,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Patients with lower values may participate if, in the opinion of the investigator, the
             cytopenias are the result of bone marrow involvement with active prostate cancer

          -  Patients must be able to take oral medications

          -  All patients must be informed and must sign and give written informed consent in
             accordance with institutional and federal guidelines; patients who are unable to
             comply with study and/or follow-up procedures are ineligible

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncontrolled brain or spinal cord metastases

          -  History of congestive heart failure or myocardial infarction within the previous six
             months

          -  History of allergy or hypersensitivity to any component of the study drugs

          -  Evidence or history of a bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy, including therapy-induced
             coagulopathy

          -  Presence of chronic diarrhea (&gt; grade 1 by Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC)), short
             bowel syndrome, pancreatic insufficiency, or malabsorption

          -  Presence of any severe or uncontrolled concurrent medical condition which, in the
             opinion of the investigator, would increase the risk of serious toxicity from the
             study drugs

          -  Concurrent use of any vitamin, herb, or mineral supplements for at least 14 days prior
             to start of therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John P. Fruehauf, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Irvine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chao Family Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 21, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Irvine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John P. Fruehauf</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Clinical Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>docetaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>lycopene</keyword>
  <keyword>prostate cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lycopene</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carotenoids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 2, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>March 28, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>May 1, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

