<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00727428</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>112219</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00727428</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunogenicity and Safety of GSK Biologicals' FluLaval® TF</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity and Safety Study of GSK Biologicals' Trivalent Split Virion Influenza Vaccine Fluviral®, Thimerosal-free (FluLaval® TF), in Adults 18 to 60 Years of Age.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present study is intended to assess a novel formulation of FluLaval. The idea is to
      obtain preliminary data on the safety and immune response to the FluLaval TF influenza
      vaccine in adults. These data will serve as a basis for further studies involving different
      populations. This protocol posting deals with objectives &amp; outcome measures of the primary
      phase/study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 5, 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 17, 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 29, 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean titers (GMTs) of hemagglutination inhibition (HI) antibody against each of the 3 vaccine influenza strains</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 0 and 21</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroconversion Rates (SCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 21</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroprotection Rates (SPR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 0 and 21</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroconversion Factors (SCF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 21</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence, intensity and investigator's assessment of relationship to vaccine of solicited local and general signs and symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 4-day follow-up period after vaccination.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence, intensity, and investigator's assessment of relationship to vaccine of unsolicited local and general signs and symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 21-day follow-up period after vaccination.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence, intensity and investigator's assessment of relationship to vaccine of SAEs and medically attended events</measure>
    <time_frame>During the entire study period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FluLaval® TF</intervention_name>
    <description>One IM injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who the investigator believes can and will comply with the requirements of
             the protocol

          -  Male and female adults, 18 to 60 years of age.

          -  Written informed consent obtained from the subject.

          -  Satisfactory baseline medical assessment by history and physical examination (stable
             health status with no exclusionary medical or psychiatric conditions).

          -  Access to a consistent means of telephone contact, which may be either in the home or
             at workplace, land line or mobile, but not a pay phone or other multiple-user device.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute disease at the time of enrollment.

          -  Significant acute or chronic, uncontrolled medical or psychiatric illness.
             &quot;Uncontrolled&quot; is defined as:

               -  Requiring institution of new medical or surgical treatment within 1 month prior
                  to study enrollment, or

               -  Requiring the re-institution of a previously discontinued medication or medical
                  treatment within one month prior to study enrollment, or

               -  Requiring a change in medication dosage in the one month prior to study
                  enrollment due to uncontrolled symptoms or drug toxicity (elective dosage
                  adjustments in stable subjects are acceptable), or

               -  Hospitalization or an event fulfilling the definition of a SAE within 1 month
                  prior to study enrollment.

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive condition including:

               -  History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection,

               -  Cancer or treatment for cancer, within 3 years of study enrollment.

          -  History of renal impairment.

          -  History of hepatic dysfunction due to hepatitis B, C or toxins including alcohol.

          -  Complicated insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus.

          -  Unstable cardiopulmonary disease requiring chronic medical therapy or associated with
             functional impairment.

          -  Presence of blood dyscrasias, including hemoglobinopathies and myelo- or
             lymphoproliferative disorder.

          -  Receipt of systemic glucocorticoidswithin 1 month of study enrollment, or chronic use
             of any cytotoxic or immunosuppressive drugs within six months of study enrollment.
             Inhaled and topical steroids are allowed.

          -  History of any demyelinating disease including Multiple Sclerosis and Guillain-Barré
             syndrome.

          -  Presence of an active neurological disorder.

          -  History of chronic alcohol consumption and/or drug abuse.

          -  Any significant disorder of coagulation that increases the risk of intramuscular
             injections or treatment with coumadin derivatives or heparin

          -  Receipt of an influenza vaccine during the 2007-8 influenza immunization season.

          -  Administration of any vaccines within 30 days prior to study enrollment or during the
             study period. Subjects who receive such treatment after enrollment will be followed
             per protocol and included in the safety analysis, but excluded from the
             according-to-protocol cohort.

          -  Use of any investigational or non-registered product (drug or vaccine) other than the
             study vaccine(s) within 30 days preceding the vaccination or planned use during the
             study period.

          -  Administration of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within the 3 months
             preceding the administration of the study vaccine or planned during the study.

          -  Any known or suspected allergy to any constituent of FluLaval and/or any flu vaccines
             and/or history of anaphylactic-type reaction to consumption of eggs.

          -  A history of severe adverse reaction to a previous influenza vaccination.

          -  If the subject is female, she must be of non-childbearing potential or if she is of
             childbearing potential, she must practice adequate contraception for 30 days prior to
             vaccination, have a negative pregnancy test and continue such precautions for the
             duration of the study.

          -  Lactating/nursing female.

          -  Any condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, prevents the subject from
             participation in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.gsk-clinicalstudyregister.com/study/112219?search=study&amp;#rs</url>
    <description>Results for study 112219 can be found on the GSK Clinical Study Register</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 1, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 4, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>FluLaval® TF</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunogenicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

