<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00726349</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HD 06.084</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00726349</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transfusion Requirements in Orthopedic Surgery (PHASE 2)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRIOS</acronym>
  <official_title>Transfusion Requirements in Orthopedic Surgery (Phase 2): A Prospective Observational Evaluation of the Optimal Transfusion Trigger.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of our research program is to determine the transfusion threshold required to
      maximize functional recovery after major orthopedic surgery (total hip/knee replacement) in
      these, most often, elderly patient with serious comorbidities.

      Hypothesis: we hypothesize that a threshold hemoglobin concentration exists below which
      functional recovery becomes difficult, even if the vital prognosis of patients is not
      impaired.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anemia is frequent after a surgical procedure. Postoperative anemia is associated with an
      increased incidence of transfusions and, probably, with an increased incidence of morbidity
      and mortality. However, the majority of studies evaluating the consequences of postoperative
      anemia are retrospective and, since anemic patients were transfused, they are unable to
      distinguish between the effects of anemia per se and those of transfusion. In orthopedic
      surgery, only two randomized controlled trials (RCT) have attempted to determine the benefits
      of transfusions in this patient population. The first evaluated the benefits of allogeneic
      transfusions in patients undergoing surgery for a fractured hip while the second evaluated
      autologous transfusions in patients undergoing total knee replacement. The small number of
      patients included in both studies did not allow definitive conclusions on the benefits (or
      lack thereof) of transfusions in orthopedic surgery.

      Traditionally, a transfusion trigger of 100 g/L has been recommended in the postoperative
      period, especially in older patients and in those with serious comorbidities. In the
      Transfusion Requirements in Critical Care trial, a much lower transfusion threshold (70 g/L)
      was adopted in the group of patients in whom transfusions were restricted. This prospective
      randomized trial that included 838 patients, is, to this day, the most important in the field
      and generated unexpected results. Serious morbidity (cardiac and respiratory in particular)
      and mortality were not increased by the adoption of a low transfusion trigger while the
      number of transfusions was decreased significantly.

      On the other hand, it is common to observe fatigue, decreased exercise capacity and muscle
      strength, and impaired performance of activities of daily life in the presence of anemia,
      especially when the hemoglobin concentration decreases below 90 - 100 g/L. In orthopedic
      surgery, a decrease in &quot;postoperative vigor&quot; can prevent patients from undertaking the
      rehabilitation program required to improve functional recovery after hip fracture repair.

      The objective of our research program is to determine the transfusion threshold required to
      maximize functional recovery after major orthopedic surgery (total hip/knee replacement) in
      these, most often, elderly patient with serious comorbidities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Distance walked in 6 minutes after the operation. This is a simple, objective and reliable measure of functional recovery.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 to 6 days after surgery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue, dizziness, difficulty to mobilize, difficulty/inability to participate in physiotherapy, prolonged hospital stay, major adverse events (especially cardiac, respiratory, neurological or infectious), death, impact of anemia on quality of life.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4-6 days after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term functional status</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months following surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months following surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term complications related to perioperative anemia</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Evidence of myocardial ischemia, respiratory tract infections or other majors infections</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">305</enrollment>
  <condition>Total Hip or Knee Arthroplasty</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients undergoing isolated elective total hip or knee arthroplasty (primary or revision surgery for a non-malignant condition), aged 60 years or older and able to walk prior to surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Observational study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Observation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients undergoing isolated elective total hip or knee arthroplasty (primary or revision
        surgery for a non-malignant condition), aged 60 years or older and able to walk prior to
        surgery.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing isolated elective total hip or knee arthroplasty (primary or
             revision surgery for a non-malignant condition), aged 60 years or older and able to
             walk prior to surgery.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Since this an observational study, all patients conforming to inclusion criteria will
             be included.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-François Hardy, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre Hospitalier Université Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHUM-Hôpital Notre-Dame</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2L 4M1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 29, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 29, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 31, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr Jean-François Hardy</name_title>
    <organization>Centre de recherche du CHUM (CRCHUM)</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

