<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00723281</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H627-29905</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00723281</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of CT Angiography With Conventional Angiography and Intravascular Ultrasound in Heart Transplant Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of CT Angiography With Conventional Angiography and Intravascular Ultrasound in Heart Transplant Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Roentgen Ray Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall goal of this study is to determine if non-invasive imaging with state of the art
      CT coronary angiography can be used to screen for transplant coronary artery disease in the
      setting of heart transplant.

      Our current protocol at UCSF for heart transplant patients involves screening with stress
      tests as well as coronary angiograms with intravascular ultrasound to assess the diameter of
      the lumen of the coronary arteries and to assess wall thickness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our hypothesis is that state of the art CT coronary angiography can be used to acquire data
      regarding the coronary arteries in the setting of heart transplant and be used to risk
      stratify patients with regards to the developments of transplant coronary artery disease.

      Specific Aim 1- To test the hypothesis that coronary CTA can accurately measure
      cross-sectional vessel wall area using conventional coronary angiography with intra-vascular
      ultrasound as the standard of reference.

      Specific Aim 2- To test the hypothesis that coronary CTA can accurately measure
      cross-sectional vessel wall thickness, vessel area and luminal area using conventional
      coronary angiography with intra-vascular ultrasound as the standard of reference.

      Secondary Aim - To asses the correlation of cross-sectional vessel wall area, vessel wall
      thickness, vessel area, luminal area and vessel wall index with global and regional left
      ventricular function using coronary CTA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Based on these considerations, 18 patients will be recruited to participate in this study, including at least 10 patients with coronary allograft vasculopathy. Only CTA of patients with positive echocardiographic stress test will be included in the study</measure>
    <time_frame>CTA studies will be done in an interval of 1 day to 30 days before the invasive studies</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All heart transplant patients at UCSF with known transplant coronary artery disease will be
        candidates for the study
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient referred for coronary angiography and IVUS as part of their standard clinical
             care;

          2. Patients must be 18 years of age or older.

          3. Any ethnic background is acceptable.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with contraindications for the use of iodinated contrast (allergic reaction,
             renal failure, multiple myeloma, etc) will be excluded.

          2. Patients with heart rate higher than 65 bpm and contraindications for the use of
             beta-blockers, listed below:

             Systolic blood pressure &lt; 90mmHg Decompensated congestive heart failure; COPD or
             asthma in use of bronchodilator; Second or third degree heart block; Severe aortic
             stenosis, defined by a pressure gradient higher than 50 mmHg and/or the presence of
             symptoms.

          3. Patients with contraindications for the use of nitroglycerin, listed below:

             Severe anemia; Increased intracranial pressure; Known hypersensitivity; Use of
             Sildenafil Citrate (Viagra®)

          4. Children and pregnant women will be excluded because of risks associated with
             radiation exposure.

          5. Patients must have no atrial fibrillation, as this will interfere with cardiac gating
             for the examination.

          6. Patients unable to give informed consent will be excluded as well.

          7. Patients with a coronary stent placed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles B Higgins, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCSF Department of Radiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehra MR, Ventura HO, Chambers R, Collins TJ, Ramee SR, Kates MA, Smart FW, Stapleton DD. Predictive model to assess risk for cardiac allograft vasculopathy: an intravascular ultrasound study. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1995 Nov 15;26(6):1537-44.</citation>
    <PMID>7594082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zakliczynski M, Swierad M, Zakliczynska H, Maruszewski M, Buszman P, Zembala M. Usefulness of stanford scale of intimal hyperplasia assessed by intravascular ultrasound to predict time of onset and severity of cardiac allograft vasculopathy. Transplant Proc. 2005 Mar;37(2):1343-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15848715</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leber AW, Becker A, Knez A, von Ziegler F, Sirol M, Nikolaou K, Ohnesorge B, Fayad ZA, Becker CR, Reiser M, Steinbeck G, Boekstegers P. Accuracy of 64-slice computed tomography to classify and quantify plaque volumes in the proximal coronary system: a comparative study using intravascular ultrasound. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2006 Feb 7;47(3):672-7. Epub 2006 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>16458154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moselewski F, Ropers D, Pohle K, Hoffmann U, Ferencik M, Chan RC, Cury RC, Abbara S, Jang IK, Brady TJ, Daniel WG, Achenbach S. Comparison of measurement of cross-sectional coronary atherosclerotic plaque and vessel areas by 16-slice multidetector computed tomography versus intravascular ultrasound. Am J Cardiol. 2004 Nov 15;94(10):1294-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15541250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sigurdsson G, Carrascosa P, Yamani MH, Greenberg NL, Perrone S, Lev G, Desai MY, Garcia MJ. Detection of transplant coronary artery disease using multidetector computed tomography with adaptative multisegment reconstruction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2006 Aug 15;48(4):772-8. Epub 2006 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16904548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gregory SA, Ferencik M, Achenbach S, Yeh RW, Hoffmann U, Inglessis I, Cury RC, Nieman K, McNulty IA, Laffan JA, Pomerantsev EV, Brady TJ, Semigran MJ, Jang IK. Comparison of sixty-four-slice multidetector computed tomographic coronary angiography to coronary angiography with intravascular ultrasound for the detection of transplant vasculopathy. Am J Cardiol. 2006 Oct 1;98(7):877-84. Epub 2006 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>16996866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferencik M, Moselewski F, Ropers D, Hoffmann U, Baum U, Anders K, Pomerantsev EV, Abbara S, Brady TJ, Achenbach S. Quantitative parameters of image quality in multidetector spiral computed tomographic coronary imaging with submillimeter collimation. Am J Cardiol. 2003 Dec 1;92(11):1257-62.</citation>
    <PMID>14636899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Obuchowski NA. Estimating and comparing diagnostic tests' accuracy when the gold standard is not binary. Acad Radiol. 2005 Sep;12(9):1198-204.</citation>
    <PMID>16099683</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Obuchowski NA. An ROC-type measure of diagnostic accuracy when the gold standard is continuous-scale. Stat Med. 2006 Feb 15;25(3):481-93.</citation>
    <PMID>16287217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Efron B, Tibshirani R. An Introduction to the Bootstrap. New York: Chapman and Hall; 1993</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kish. Survey Sampling. New York: Wiley &amp; Sons; 1965.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lachin JM. Introduction to sample size determination and power analysis for clinical trials. Control Clin Trials. 1981 Jun;2(2):93-113.</citation>
    <PMID>7273794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pannu HK, Alvarez W Jr, Fishman EK. Beta-blockers for cardiac CT: a primer for the radiologist. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2006 Jun;186(6 Suppl 2):S341-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16714607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karen Ordovas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>transplant coronary artery disease</keyword>
  <keyword>CT angiography</keyword>
  <keyword>conventional angiography</keyword>
  <keyword>intravascular ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart transplant patients with known transplant coronary artery disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

