<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00605657</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>080053</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>08-I-0053</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00605657</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Valproic Acid (Depakote[Registered Trademark]) to Treat Autoimmune Lymphoproliferative Syndrome (ALPS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot (Phase I-II) Study of Valproic Acid (Depakote) for the Treatment of the Autoimmune Lymphoproliferative Syndrome (ALPS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Koneti Rao</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test whether valproic acid (Depakote[Registered Trademark]) can shrink
      enlarged lymph glands and spleen in patients with autoimmune lymphoproliferative syndrome
      (ALPS). Depakote has been used for more than 30 years for treating various medical disorders
      in adults and children, including migraine headaches, seizures and psychiatric disorders. In
      animal studies, it was effective in shrinking both lymph nodes and spleen in animals with
      conditions similar to ALPS.

      People with ALPS who are between 2 and 70 years of age and who have had an enlarged spleen or
      lymph glands for at least 1 year may be eligible for this study.

      Participants take Depakote as a tablet or liquid or sprinkled on food twice a day for 16
      weeks. The drug dose is increased slowly over the first 3 to 4 weeks until the maximum
      tolerated dose is reached. Blood tests are done at 2, 4, 6, 8 and 10 weeks after starting the
      drug and 1 week after the drug is stopped to check for treatment side effects. Valproic acid
      blood levels will be checked during drug escalation, half way through therapy, and just
      before the end of treatment. A physical examination and CT scan (or ultrasound of the abdomen
      for patients who cannot undergo CT) are done before starting treatment and at the end of the
      16-week treatment period to evaluate the response to treatment.

      Patients who tolerate the treatment well and show shrinkage of the lymph glands or spleen may
      be offered extended treatment for up to 1 year in consultation with their primary physician.
      During the extended treatment period, blood tests are done at home every 6 to 8 weeks to
      monitor for drug side effects. Follow up evaluation visits are scheduled at the NIH Clinical
      Center every 3 months during the extended treatment period and 3, 6, and 12 months after
      treatment has ended.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Autoimmune Lymphoproliferative Syndrome (ALPS) is an inherited disease associated with a
      defect of lymphocyte apoptosis that leads to lymphoproliferation and autoimmunity. Although,
      there are immunosuppressive treatments for many of its complications, there currently is no
      safe and effective therapy for this syndrome itself.

      Valproic acid has been recently used as a histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitor for inducing
      apoptosis in malignancies and is being incorporated as part of hematology/oncology clinical
      trials. A pilot study will be conducted on the safety and efficacy of the drug valproic acid
      (Depakote [R]) for the treatment of ALPS. Twelve subjects with ALPS, will be treated
      initially for 4 months with twice-daily administration of valproic acid at escalating doses
      adjusted by weight, with close monitoring of toxicity and side effects including laboratory
      parameters related to the drug. The effects of valproic acid treatment on lymph node and/or
      spleen size will be assessed by computerized tomography scan, ultrasound and physical
      examination. If valproic acid is effective in reducing the size of lymph nodes and/or spleen
      size as defined in the study design, subjects may be offered the option to continue further
      therapy with valproic acid for up to 1 year. The effect of treatment on other laboratory
      features specific to ALPS will also be assessed. Evaluating the effects of valproic acid on
      these clinical and laboratory parameters will help to determine if this drug demonstrates
      sufficient activity to warrant study in a larger randomized controlled trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Response</measure>
    <time_frame>3 monthly (12 week) intervals</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction of lymph node and/or spleen size measured by CT imaging, or physical exam and abdominal ultrasound. A clinical response is defined as a greater than 40% reduction in lymph node size and/or greater than 40% reduction in spleen size. A CT scan with contrast measured lymph node size as well as spleen size.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To Determine Whether the Treatment Alters, in Favorable Directions, Laboratory Markers of ALPS (e.g., Number of DNT Cells, Immunoglobin Levels, Vitamin B12 Levels, IL-10 Levels, Autoantibody Titers, Fas Mediated Apoptosis)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 monthly (12 week) intervals</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>ALPS</condition>
  <condition>Hypersplenism</condition>
  <condition>Lymphadenopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Valproic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm study involving oral administration of valproic acid and monitoring of its efficacy by CT scans done before and after the intervention. Blood samples were also obtained to monitor safety labs and biomarkers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Valproic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral administration of valproic acid</description>
    <arm_group_label>Valproic acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Depakote</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CT Scan</intervention_name>
    <description>CT scans were done before and after treating the patient with valproic acid</description>
    <arm_group_label>Valproic acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Computerized Tomography</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Sample</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood samples were collected before and after the intervention to monitor blood counts and biomarkers of ALPS</description>
    <arm_group_label>Valproic acid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. All subjects must fulfill the published criteria for the diagnosis of ALPS
                  (documented nonmalignant lymphadenopathy and/or splenomegaly of at least 1-year
                  duration; greater than1% TCR alpha/beta+ CD4-CD8- T cells in the peripheral
                  blood). This must include clinically documented lymphadenopathy involving more
                  than 2 nodes in more than 1 regional group of nodes measuring greater than 2cm in
                  size and/or a palpable spleen.

               2. Age greater than or equal to 2 years through less than or equal to 70 years.

               3. Must have a personal primary care physician who is willing to follow the protocol
                  required evaluations during the study period.

               4. Must be willing to sign a consent form.

               5. Patients on immunosuppression (e.g., corticosteroid, mycophenolate mofetil,
                  azathioprine, cyclophosphamide) are eligible if the dose of the immunosuppressive
                  drug has been stable for at least 3 months prior to enrollment and their
                  hematologic parameters do not meet the exclusion criteria (1) as outlined below.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. A hemoglobin concentration of less than 8 gm/dL, a platelet count of less than 75
             K/mm(3), or an absolute neutrophil count of less than 500/mm(3), at study entry.

          2. Liver disease determined by an alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate
             aminotransferase (AST), or bilirubin 2.5 times greater than the upper limit of normal.

          3. History of pancreatitis by clinical features and/or laboratory abnormalities in the
             last 12 months.

          4. Renal dysfunction determined by a calculated urine creatinine clearance of less than
             70 mL/min/1.73 m(2) in children and less than 60 mL/min in adults, or using the
             Schwartz formula or Levy formula based on serum creatinine.

          5. Patients clinically suspected of suffering from urea cycle disorders will be excluded.

          6. Patients with history of seizure disorders and/or those already receiving valproic
             acid will be excluded.

          7. Sensitive to or have ever had an allergic reaction to Depakote.

          8. Not able to abstain from alcohol during the length of the study.

          9. Pregnancy. Female adults and adolescents who have attained menarche must have a
             negative pregnancy test at study entry and commit to using an acceptable method of
             barrier or hormonal contraception (e.g., condoms, diaphragms, oral contraceptives, or
             long acting progestin agents) if sexually active during the study and for 3 months
             after the last dose of valproic acid.

         10. Lactating mothers who are breast feeding their babies will not be eligible.

         11. ALPS patients who have been treated with bone marrow toxic chemotherapy regimens for
             Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma or other malignancies are not eligible for this pilot study.

         12. Unwilling or unable to comply with the need to have periodic blood tests to monitor
             possible side effects of treatment, or other major requirements of this study will be
             an exclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Koneti Rao, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DIR, NIAID, NIH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sneller MC, Straus SE, Jaffe ES, Jaffe JS, Fleisher TA, Stetler-Stevenson M, Strober W. A novel lymphoproliferative/autoimmune syndrome resembling murine lpr/gld disease. J Clin Invest. 1992 Aug;90(2):334-41.</citation>
    <PMID>1386609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rao VK, Straus SE. Causes and consequences of the autoimmune lymphoproliferative syndrome. Hematology. 2006 Feb;11(1):15-23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16522544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rao VK, Carrasquillo JA, Dale JK, Bacharach SL, Whatley M, Dugan F, Tretler J, Fleisher T, Puck JM, Wilson W, Jaffe ES, Avila N, Chen CC, Straus SE. Fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) for monitoring lymphadenopathy in the autoimmune lymphoproliferative syndrome (ALPS). Am J Hematol. 2006 Feb;81(2):81-5. Erratum in: Am J Hematol. 2006 May;81(5):389.</citation>
    <PMID>16432855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 15, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>February 14, 2013</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2013</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">March 21, 2013</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 21, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Koneti Rao</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ALPS</keyword>
  <keyword>Valproic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphadenopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Splenomegaly</keyword>
  <keyword>Histone Deacytelase (HDAC) Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoimmune Lymphoproliferative Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphadenopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autoimmune Lymphoproliferative Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersplenism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Valproic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>All patients were started on valproic acid at the NIH Clinical Center then followed locally</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Valproic Acid</title>
          <description>valproic acid administered starting at 10 mg/kg/day in divided doses twice daily x 3 days, increase to 15mg/kg/day x 3 days, increase to 20 mg/kg/day on day 7, increase to 30 mg/kg/day on day 14, maximum dose of 40mg/kg/day on day 21, if tolerated, to achieve plasma level 50-100 mcg/mL.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Adverse Event</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Protocol Violation</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Valproic Acid</title>
          <description>valproic acid administered starting at 10 mg/kg/day in divided doses twice daily x 3 days, increase to 15mg/kg/day x 3 days, increase to 20 mg/kg/day on day 7, increase to 30 mg/kg/day on day 14, maximum dose of 40mg/kg/day on day 21, if tolerated, to achieve plasma level 50-100 mcg/mL.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="5"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants With Response</title>
        <description>Reduction of lymph node and/or spleen size measured by CT imaging, or physical exam and abdominal ultrasound. A clinical response is defined as a greater than 40% reduction in lymph node size and/or greater than 40% reduction in spleen size. A CT scan with contrast measured lymph node size as well as spleen size.</description>
        <time_frame>3 monthly (12 week) intervals</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Valproic Acid</title>
            <description>valproic acid administered starting at 10 mg/kg/day in divided doses twice daily x 3 days, increase to 15mg/kg/day x 3 days, increase to 20 mg/kg/day on day 7, increase to 30 mg/kg/day on day 14, maximum dose of 40mg/kg/day on day 21, if tolerated, to achieve plasma level 50-100 mcg/mL.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants With Response</title>
          <description>Reduction of lymph node and/or spleen size measured by CT imaging, or physical exam and abdominal ultrasound. A clinical response is defined as a greater than 40% reduction in lymph node size and/or greater than 40% reduction in spleen size. A CT scan with contrast measured lymph node size as well as spleen size.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="3"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>To Determine Whether the Treatment Alters, in Favorable Directions, Laboratory Markers of ALPS (e.g., Number of DNT Cells, Immunoglobin Levels, Vitamin B12 Levels, IL-10 Levels, Autoantibody Titers, Fas Mediated Apoptosis)</title>
        <time_frame>3 monthly (12 week) intervals</time_frame>
        <population>outcome measure not assessed because 0 participants had a response</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Valproic Acid</title>
            <description>valproic acid administered starting at 10 mg/kg/day in divided doses twice daily x 3 days, increase to 15mg/kg/day x 3 days, increase to 20 mg/kg/day on day 7, increase to 30 mg/kg/day on day 14, maximum dose of 40mg/kg/day on day 21, if tolerated, to achieve plasma level 50-100 mcg/mL.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>To Determine Whether the Treatment Alters, in Favorable Directions, Laboratory Markers of ALPS (e.g., Number of DNT Cells, Immunoglobin Levels, Vitamin B12 Levels, IL-10 Levels, Autoantibody Titers, Fas Mediated Apoptosis)</title>
          <population>outcome measure not assessed because 0 participants had a response</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Valproic Acid</title>
          <description>valproic acid administered starting at 10 mg/kg/day in divided doses twice daily x 3 days, increase to 15mg/kg/day x 3 days, increase to 20 mg/kg/day on day 7, increase to 30 mg/kg/day on day 14, maximum dose of 40mg/kg/day on day 21, if tolerated, to achieve plasma level 50-100 mcg/mL.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>No source vocabulary</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>low serum IgG</sub_title>
                <assessment>Systematic Assessment</assessment>
                <description>possibly related to treatment</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>pneumomediastinum</sub_title>
                <description>not treatment related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>No source vocabulary</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>decreased platelets</sub_title>
                <description>Only probably related in one patient. Other patients had baseline low platelets.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>decreased hemoglobin</sub_title>
                <description>unlikely or unrelated in all patients</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>decreased neutrophil count</sub_title>
                <description>unlikely or unrelated in all cases</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>leukopenia</sub_title>
                <description>unlikely or unrelated</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>elevated alkaline phosphatase</sub_title>
                <description>unrelated</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>vomiting</sub_title>
                <assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</assessment>
                <description>vomiting unrelated, due to the flu in one case. Possibly related in other</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>elevated AST</sub_title>
                <description>one probably related and one unlikely related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>elevated ALT</sub_title>
                <description>probably related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>diarrhea</sub_title>
                <description>possibly related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>gastroenteritis</sub_title>
                <description>possibly related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>abdominal pain</sub_title>
                <description>possibly related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>nausea</sub_title>
                <description>possibly related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>fever</sub_title>
                <description>unrelated</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>hyperglycemia</sub_title>
                <description>unrelated</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>fatigue</sub_title>
                <description>not related in two cases, possibly related in one case.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>rhinorrhea</sub_title>
                <description>unrelated</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>cough</sub_title>
                <assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</assessment>
                <description>unrelated</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>sinus congestion</sub_title>
                <assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</assessment>
                <description>unrelated</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>pruritis</sub_title>
                <assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</assessment>
                <description>probably related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>rash</sub_title>
                <description>probably related</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>V. Koneti Rao, MD</name_or_title>
      <organization>NIAID</organization>
      <phone>301-496-6502</phone>
      <email>korao@niaid.nih.gov</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

