<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00603135</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MNeuro_Keppra_</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EKBB 272/27</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00603135</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intravenous Levetiracetam as First-line Anticonvulsive Treatment in Patients With Non-convulsive Status Epilepticus</brief_title>
  <acronym>Keppra</acronym>
  <official_title>Intravenous Levetiracetam as First-line Anticonvulsive Treatment in Patients With Non-convulsive Status Epilepticus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland, Dr. med. Stephan Rüegg, Neurology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clinical Trial Unit, University Hospital Basel, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Status epilepticus (SE) represents the most common life-threatening neurological emergency
      requiring treatment on an intensive care unit. The incidence in Western European countries is
      about 12-18/100'000. Immediate and effective treatment of SE is obviously essential because
      of the deleterious effects of continuous seizures on the brain and the whole organism.
      Guidelines emphasize the use of benzodiazepines (BZD) as first-line anticonvulsive drugs.
      Alternatively, i/v Phenytoin (PHE), fosphenytoin (FOS), and valproate (VPA) were also tested
      as first-line anticonvulsants in SE. Direct comparison of PHE with lorazepam (LZP) showed
      significant superiority of LZP (evidence class I). Other trials i/v PHE or -VPA are of
      evidence class III or IV. BZD, VPA, and PHE have clinical and pharmacological disadvantages.
      BZD may cause respiratory depression or sedation and may be not suitable for patients with
      COPD or ambiguous in patients with BZD addiction. Some compounds also may induce
      tachyphylaxis or accumulate under concomitant renal failure. PHE has saturable metabolism
      subject to Michaelis-Menten kinetics increasing the risk of overdosing in an acute setting
      causing liver damage, serious cardiac arrhythmias, hypotension, cerebellar degeneration,
      peripheral neuropathy and local/systemic skin reactions. Although of unequivocal efficacy,
      PHE should no longer be used for long-term because of its adverse effects after chronic
      administration (irreversible cerebellar degeneration causing debilitating ataxia, painful
      polyneuropathy, and osteopenia increasing the risk of fractures). Metabolism by and
      self-induction of the hepatic CYP450 system make PHE prone to interactions with several other
      drugs, notably other antiepileptics. VPA may cause liver failure, hemorrhagic complications,
      pancreatitis, and hyperammonemic encephalopathy. To summarize, these three first-line agents
      for the treatment of SE may cause serious side effects in several patients with SE.

      Levetiracetam (LEV) is broad-spectrum antiepileptic drug. It binds to the presynaptic
      vesicular protein 2A abundantly present in different regions of the brain; LEV
      presynaptically modulates transmitter release, but the exact mechanism(s) remain unclear.
      Data also revealed that LEV stabilizes GABAA receptors upon repetitive activation what is
      important in treatment of SE because GABAA receptors undergo significant changes of subunit
      conformation within minutes after sustained activation like during SE. These changes render
      GABAA receptors the less anticonvulsive, the longer SE lasts. Levetiracetam has a favorable
      pharmacological profile with large safety margins. Its partly extrahepatic hydrolyzation
      bypasses the CYP450 system; renal excretion is 60-70% unchanged, and 23-27% metabolized.
      Dosage needs adjustment when renal function is impaired. LEV lacks interactions with any
      drugs yet. Drowsiness is the most common side-effect while respiration, liver and kidney
      function, and the blood system are not affected. LEV shows an important clinical effect even
      after the first dose and maximal efficacy within the first week of drug-intake. The favorable
      clinico-pharmacological profile predilects LEV for the first-line treatment of SE, especially
      in patients with multi-organ failure, sepsis, coma etc.. About 10 % of comatous patients may
      be in non-convulsive SE (NCSE) on ICU's. These patients are under polymedication whereby
      interactions of the anticonvulsants approved yet for the treatment of NCSE with their other
      drugs may have fatal effects. Conversely, non-interacting anticonvulsants would represent an
      advantage for the treatment of NCSE for these patients.

      Recently, the i/v formulation of LEV was approved by the FDA for the use in patients, but not
      specifically for the treatment of SE. Data about the single-dose bioavailability of i/v-LEV
      in comparison to oral tablets as well as multiple-dose pharmacokinetics and tolerability in
      healthy subjects were recently published. In addition, the administration of i/v-LEV dosages
      ranging from 2000-4000 mg within 15 minutes and of dosages ranging from 1500-2500 mg within 5
      minutes was safe and well tolerated, and led to efficacious drug levels in a randomized,
      single-blind, placebo-controlled safety and pharmacokinetic study in healthy volunteers.

      Slight somnolence is expected to be the only adverse effect of i/v LEV, sharply contrasting
      with the sedation up to coma after i/v benzodiazepines. Thus, even severely ill patients will
      be accessible to neurological tests under LEV which is a big advantage in this clinical
      difficult setting of NCSE.

      I-v LEV is considered an ideal candidate for the first-line use (before benzodiazepines) in
      patients with NCSE, especially in those with important comorbidity and concomitant
      polymedication. Thus, we would like to test the feasibility, safety, and efficacy of i/v-LEV
      as first-line medication in a open-label, single-center, prospective pilot study as outlined
      below.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy/ Clinical and/or electroencephalographic cessation of SE</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Status Epilepticus, Non-Convulsive</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>first-line i/v-levetiracetam</intervention_name>
    <description>No effect after 30 min, standard therapy with f.e. lorazepam for NCSE</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients 18 years old or older with NCSE. NCSE includes the following subtypes:

               -  simple partial NCSE

               -  complex partial status epilpeticus

          -  Absence status

          -  NCSE in critical illness

          -  Written informed consent should be signed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age below 20

          -  Known intolerance to the study drug levetiracetam

          -  Known pregnancy

          -  Postanoxic SE

          -  Subtle SE
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephan Rüegg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Neurology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephan Rüegg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Neurology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Basel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <zip>4031</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rupprecht S, Franke K, Fitzek S, Witte OW, Hagemann G. Levetiracetam as a treatment option in non-convulsive status epilepticus. Epilepsy Res. 2007 Mar;73(3):238-44. Epub 2006 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>17161587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rüegg SJ, Dichter MA. Diagnosis and Treatment of Nonconvulsive Status Epilepticus in an Intensive Care Unit Setting. Curr Treat Options Neurol. 2003 Mar;5(2):93-110.</citation>
    <PMID>12628059</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ramael S, Daoust A, Otoul C, Toublanc N, Troenaru M, Lu ZS, Stockis A. Levetiracetam intravenous infusion: a randomized, placebo-controlled safety and pharmacokinetic study. Epilepsia. 2006 Jul;47(7):1128-35.</citation>
    <PMID>16886975</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ramael S, De Smedt F, Toublanc N, Otoul C, Boulanger P, Riethuisen JM, Stockis A. Single-dose bioavailability of levetiracetam intravenous infusion relative to oral tablets and multiple-dose pharmacokinetics and tolerability of levetiracetam intravenous infusion compared with placebo in healthy subjects. Clin Ther. 2006 May;28(5):734-44.</citation>
    <PMID>16861095</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 10, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr. med. Stephan Rüegg</name_title>
    <organization>Neurology,University Hospital Basel</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Status Epilepticus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etiracetam</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Piracetam</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

