<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03450915</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BVX-010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03450915</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pivotal Trial to Assess the Safety and Clinical Efficacy of the M-001 as a Standalone Universal Flu Vaccine</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pivotal Multi-center, Randomized, Modified Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Phase 3 Trial to Assess the Safety and Clinical Efficacy of M-001 Influenza Vaccine Administered Intra-muscularly Twice in Older Adults and Elderly (≥50 Years).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>BiondVax Pharmaceuticals ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>BiondVax Pharmaceuticals ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The pivotal Phase 3 trial plans to enroll a total of 9,630 participants aged 50+ over two
      years. Participants will be immunized twice with the M-001 universal influenza vaccine
      candidate or placebo and then followed for up to 2 seasons. The trial will evaluate the
      number of influenza cases in each group and the severity of illness during the follow up
      period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The placebo-controlled pivotal clinical efficacy Phase 3 trial plans to enroll a total of
      9,630 participants over two years. Participants will be immunized twice with the M-001
      influenza vaccine candidate or placebo. Influenza incidence and illness severity will be
      evaluated throughout the follow-up period of up to two years. Participants will be 50 years
      and older, with at least half over 65 years of age.

      The trial is expected to take place in eastern European countries and begin prior to the
      2018/19 Northern Hemisphere flu season.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Experimental group: 2 immunizations with M-001 Control group: 2 injection of saline (placebo)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>All parties are blinded except for the person who prepares the syringe for injection. The M-001 is cloudy white and its appearance is different from the transparent saline that is used for placebo. The person prepares the syringe with an opaque sticker that fully covers the syringe contents. People administering the syringe are not involved or present during syringe preparation, and are thus fully blinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Efficacy: PCR and Culture Confirmed Influenza</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 flu seasons (approximately 1.5 years)</time_frame>
    <description>If a participant presents with ILI, then we will run Polymerase chain reaction (PCR). If the PCR is positive, then we will culture confirm. Outcome measure is percentage of PCR and culture confirmed influenza cases in the M-001 experimental group vs. placebo caused by any influenza A or B virus in association with Influenza-like illness (ILI) symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Occurrence of vaccine-related serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of vaccine-related serious adverse events (SAEs) such as solicited and unsolicited injection site and systemic reactogenicity events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Efficacy: PCR Confirmed Influenza</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 flu seasons (approximately 1.5 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of PCR confirmed influenza cases in the M-001 experimental group vs. placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lot consistency</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of T-cell subsets from participants in the experimental group, expressing interferon gamma (IFN-g) in cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4+) peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) after stimulation with M-001 16 days after the second dose of M-001 as compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Reduced severity of illness</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 flu seasons (approximately 1.5 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Average time to alleviation of each influenza symptom</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">9630</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>M-001</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be vaccinated with 1mg dose of M-001 twice: Once at Day 0, and once at Day 21.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be vaccinated with saline twice: Once at Day 0, and once at Day 21.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>M-001</intervention_name>
    <description>A recombinant protein containing 9 conserved epitopes from Influenza A and B that are common to the vast majority of influenza viruses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>M-001</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Multimeric-001</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>0.9% sodium chloride (NaCl)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male and female subjects 50 years of age (inclusive) or older, mentally competent,
             willing and able to give the written informed consent prior to study entry

          2. Able to comply with the trial procedures and be available for all study visits.

          3. Medically stable. (Subjects may have underlying chronic conditions such as
             hypertension, diabetes, ischemic heart disease, or hypothyroidism, as long as their
             symptoms/signs are controlled. If they are on medication for a condition, the
             medication dose must have been stable for at least 3 months preceding vaccination).

          4. Women of childbearing potential (not surgically sterile or postmenopausal for greater
             than or equal to one year) and men must agree to practice adequate contraception
             (barrier or hormone methods or intra uterine device (IUD) for women and a condom for
             men) throughout the study treatment and for at least up to day 51 (for female) and day
             111 (for male) of the trial (i.e. 30 (for female) and 90 (for male) days after the
             last dose of the IMP)

          5. Female subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy test within 24 hours prior to study vaccination.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of neurological symptoms or signs, or anaphylactic shock following
             administration of any vaccine.

          2. Known or suspected (or have a high risk of developing) impairment/alteration of immune
             function (excluding that normally associated with advanced age).

          3. Receipt of: a) Immunosuppressive drugs: i) systemic glucocorticoids &gt;/= 10 mg
             prednisone per day ii) cytotoxic drugs b) Investigational drugs within 30 days before,
             or planned during, the study c) Blood products within 3 months before, or planned
             during, the study d) Influenza vaccine within 6 months before the study) Other
             vaccines within 30 days before, or planned during, the study

          4. Any serious disease such as: cancer, autoimmune disease, advanced arteriosclerotic
             disease or complicated diabetes mellitus, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)
             that requires oxygen therapy, acute or progressive hepatic disease, acute or
             progressive renal disease, or congestive heart failure, as judged by the PI.

          5. An acute illness, including an axillary temperature greater than 38 Celsius (38ºC),
             occurred within 1 week before first vaccination

          6. Positive positive urine pregnancy test prior to vaccination or women who are
             breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tamar Ben-Yedidia, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>BiondVax Pharmaceuticals ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tamar Ben-Yedidia, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+97289302529</phone>
    <email>benyedidia@biondvax.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>universal</keyword>
  <keyword>M-001</keyword>
  <keyword>Multimeric-001</keyword>
  <keyword>Flu</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

