<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03451552</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20171215</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03451552</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Navigation in Primary Care and Access to Resources in the Community</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARC</acronym>
  <official_title>Patient Navigation in Primary Care and Access to Resources in the Community - A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Ottawa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Ontario Institute of Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laurentian University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bruyere Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ontario Ministry of Health and Long Term Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Some people living with health problems require extra support to properly manage their
      conditions, as family doctors are only able to spend limited time in the office with these
      patients. There are many resources and programs in the community that can provide the
      necessary time and support for these patients, yet many patients are unaware that such
      resources exist. Patient navigators have been shown to be useful in helping patients with
      certain conditions (such as cancer) to get to the resources they need, especially when they
      have social challenges that make it difficult for them to reach these programs (for example,
      language or transportation barriers, poverty, or poor social support). This study will look
      at how helpful Navigators are to link patients at family doctors' offices to community
      resources. To do this, family doctors' offices in Ottawa and Sudbury will be recruited. All
      offices will receive training on directing patients to CRs and will be assigned a patient
      navigator to support patients access CRs. Half of the patients referred to CRs by their
      providers will have access to the navigator (intervention) assigned to the practice. This
      study will assess whether access to a navigator increases patients' access to community
      health and social services compared to usual standard of care. In addition, the study aims to
      understand whether English and French speaking individuals are as likely to benefit from a
      navigator in accessing community resources in the language of their choice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed project builds on work conducted between 2013 and today. The Canadian Institutes
      of Health Research's Community Based Primary Health Care Team Grant SPOR initiative funded a
      five-year program of research (known as IMPACT: Innovative Models Promoting Access-to-Care
      Transformation, http://www.impactresearchprogram.com/). The goal of the IMPACT Project is to
      increase access to community-based primary health care for vulnerable populations. The lead
      for the Ontario arm of the IMPACT project, Simone Dahrouge, has undertaken a community
      engagement initiative within the Champlain Local Health Integration Network (LHIN) to
      understand the barriers patients face to adequately access community based health and social
      resources (CRs) and how these can be overcome. Under that funding, the team undertook an
      extensive consultation process to identify a regional priority gap, select and adapt an
      intervention, and implement and evaluate a single arm intervention. The investigators are
      currently in the last phase of that project, which is serving as a feasibility phase for the
      randomized controlled trial. The feasibility study is evaluating the acceptability, demand,
      implementation, adaption, integration, and practicality of the study intervention and related
      activities to optimize appropriate access to CRs for primary care patients. Enrolment for
      that project will be completed by March 2018. This study received ethics approval from the
      OHSN Research Ethics Board (Protocol #20160914-01H), Bruyère Continuing Care Research Ethics
      Board (Protocol #M16-1616-055), Hôpital Montfort Research Ethics Board (Protocol #
      SD-DP-27-02-17), and the University of Ottawa Research Ethics Board (Protocol #
      A05-17-04).That trial is a registered clinical trial: NCT03105635.

      During the feasibility phase the team established a regional stakeholder advisory group
      (Champlain LHIN). The composition of the advisory group has been adapted to meet the needs of
      the study. In the initial phase the composition was broad until the region identified the
      priority area and approach to addressing the gap. The committee is now composed of patients
      of various minority communities who contribute their lived experience, primary care providers
      from different care models and leaders from organizations responsible for community services
      (Community Care Access Centres and Community Health Centres) who inform the feasibility of
      the approach for each context, and best approach to integrating of the two sectors, health
      planners (the LHIN Primary Care Lead, senior integration specialist and others) who bring
      their broader context health services knowledge as well as resources (such as practice
      transformation facilitation services) to the project, as well as other stakeholders that
      inform specific components of the intervention (Ontario 211, Champlain Healthline). That
      Committee meets regularly and contributes directly to the direction of the study design,
      implementation, evaluation and dissemination. Because the committee fundamentally represents
      the interests of the region, it is often referred to in this document as 'the region&quot;.

      The initial consultative phase identified poor access to CRs as a priority access gap. The
      research team relied on a scoping review conducted for the IMPACT program and conducted
      several interviews and focus groups with community stakeholders to inform the best approach
      addressing this gap. The region selected to implement a patient navigator who can assist
      patients for whom the use of a community service is recommended by their primary care
      provider achieve access to that service. Primary care providers rarely make specific
      recommendations to access CRs; largely because they are unaware of these. They make general
      recommendations to improve healthy behaviours, but do not refer to specific types of
      services. Two realist reviews have been commissioned and completed by a team of experts to
      help us understand the critical success factors and shape our intervention. One review is
      focused on &quot;community navigators&quot; and the other on &quot;primary care referral to community
      services&quot; to help the team understand the factors that support us. This information was used
      to develop the ARC intervention. A number of themes identified in these reviews including
      training for clinical staff to identify and refer to relevant CRs to address patients' social
      barriers; implementing a champion within practice to integrate referral into usual care; use
      of electronic health records to prompt provider referral and share information between
      provider and the community; and developing a screening process and promotional material to
      prompt referral.

      As a result, the region developed the Access to Resources in the Community/Accès aux
      Resources Communautaires (ARC) intervention. The ARC project will build on this work by
      focussing on improving access to community resources in patients' language of choice and
      emphasizing access to French-language resources for Francophones in Ontario.

      PURPOSE

      The purpose of this project is to optimize appropriate access to community based services for
      socially complex primary care patients, including Franco-Ontarians living in minority
      situations, and promote the continuity of information across primary and community care.

      OBJECTIVES AND DELIVERABLES

      Objective A: Optimize equitable utilization of community based resources

      Deliverable 1: Effectiveness of a patient navigator on utilization of CRs

      Deliverable 2: Make policy recommendations to address remaining gaps

      Deliverable 3: Establish a model of navigation that is transferable and scalable.

      Objective B: Support continuity of information across Primary and Community Care

      Deliverable 4: Establish a process that support appropriate exchange of information across
      the two sectors
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a prospective, mixed method (patient) randomized controlled trial of navigation services provided by Ontario 211 vs. navigation services provided by a lay Patient Navigator. Randomization is 1:1 control:intervention.
The mixed method design is a sequential, explanatory design. Patients having consented to participate in the study will complete a survey, after which their random assignment to one of two arms (intervention or control) will be revealed.
The randomization schedule will be blocked at the practice level to ensure a balance of control and intervention patients for each practice, including all providers.
Patients randomized to the intervention arm will have access to services provided by the ARC Patient Navigator, whereas patients randomized to the control arm will be directed to the Ontario 211 navigation service.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>There is no masking in the study.The participant, their primary care provider, and the study team will know which arm the patient is in.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Access to Community Resources</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is access to CRs amongst the patients participating in the study. This outcome reflects the ability of the navigator to help patients overcome barriers to access and reach the community resource. We will assess this outcome in both arms (control and intervention) three months after enrolment in the study through a patient survey. The outcome will be a count of the CRs accessed (as a patient may access more than one CR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability of the intervention to address equity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) as well three months later, at the end of the patient three months intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Patient sociodemographic characteristics captured in the baseline survey (e.g. income, language, sex, age, immigration status) will be used to evaluate the intervention's success in supporting patients access the desired resource (main outcome variable) across various social strata.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Needs/Difficulties</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) as well three months later, at the end of the patient three months intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Section B in patient survey - related to ability to pay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of Healthcare</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) as well three months later, at the end of the patient three months intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Section B in patient survey - related to relationship with providers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability to engage</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) as well three months later, at the end of the patient three months intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Section C in the patient survey, one scale (including three concepts)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life VR-12</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) as well three months later, at the end of the patient three months intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Section F in patient survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Action Process Approach</measure>
    <time_frame>Time Frame: baseline (i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) as well three months later, at the end of the patient three months intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Section L in the patient survey - related to self efficacy and behaviour change</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Activation Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) as well three months later, at the end of the patient three months intervention period</time_frame>
    <description>Section M of patient survey - related to knowledge, confidence, and motivation to access services</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Community service evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed after the three month patient intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>Section O in Patient Survey: used to evaluate whether the community service(s) were appropriate for the needs of the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Navigator Assessment (intervention arm only)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed after the three month patient intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>An assessment of the Patient Navigator service received by patients in the intervention arm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attitudes with reference to vulnerable populations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>An assessment of primary care providers attitudes with reference to socially vulnerable populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Practices with reference to vulnerable populations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>An assessment of primary care providers practices with reference to socially vulnerable populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge with reference to vulnerable populations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>An assessment of primary care providers' Knowledge with reference to socially vulnerable populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contextual factors (e.g., organizational structure)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>An assessment of the organization's (primary care organizations) organizational structure (section B of Provider survey)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change valence</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>Section C of the provider survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change Climate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>Section D of the provider survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Organizational readiness for change</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>Section E of Provider Survey; An assessment of the organization's readiness to implement the navigator intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implementation effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>Section F of Provider SurveyAn assessment of the effectiveness of the navigator intervention within the primary care practice</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Experience with the Navigator</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(i.e. the time of referrals (Pre-intervention) and 10 months into the study intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>Section G of Provider Survey; An assessment of the providers' experience with the patient navigator, and how the intervention has affected their practice</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">368</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Care Inequity, Patient Navigation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (211 services)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients allocated to the control arm will be directed to the Ontario 211 navigation service, which is already available to the general public free of charge. After consenting to participate in the study and completing the telephone survey, the research assistant will inform these patients that they can use existing navigation services provided by Ontario 211 to help them access the CR referred to them by their PHCP. The research assistant will instruct patients to dial 2-1-1 to obtain additional information on the nature of this service.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (Patient Navigator)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients allocated to the intervention arm will be offered the services of the ARC Patient Navigator. After consenting to participate in the study and completing the telephone survey, the research assistant will inform these patients that they can use the services offered by the ARC patient navigator to help them access the CR referred to them by their PHCP. Following a brief description of the services provided by the navigator (e.g., arrange transportation, make appointments, fill out forms, etc.), patients will be offered to be contacted by the navigator by telephone or to meet with the navigator in person on a day and time that is most convenient for them.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Navigator</intervention_name>
    <description>Navigators will support patients to access community based resources for healthy living and self-management, rather than providing specific information about health issues. Navigators will teach patients how to identify available and relevant programs to meet their health-related goals, in their language of choice. The navigator will ensure that the individual understands the reason for referral and potential benefits. They will discuss social barriers potentially affecting patients' access to community health resources, and assist patients to prioritize their health goals and relevant resources to achieve these. The navigator will then assist patients to access the community-based services in the language of their choice to which they have been referred. The navigator may assist the patient in making appointments, coordinating transportation, and/or accompaniment to resources as required).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (Patient Navigator)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        There are 3 levels of participation in this study: primary care practices, primary care
        providers, and primary care patients.

        1) Primary care practices

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Any practice providing comprehensive primary care services (i.e. excludes practices
             that provide walk in services only), except for Community Health Centres. This
             includes Reformed Fee For Service (Family Health Groups, Comprehensive Care Model),
             Capitation based models (Family Health Networks, Family Health Organizations), and
             interprofessional models (Family Health Teams)

          -  Located in a neighbourhood of the Champlain (Ottawa area) or North East (Sudbury area)
             LHIN that has a francophone population of 20% of greater, as listed identified in the
             Ottawa Neighbourhood Study and in custom neighbourhoods created by the city of Greater
             Sudbury for city planning purposes, both linked to Statistics Canada's 2011 Population
             Census, respectively.

          -  Having at least one primary care provider agreeing to participate in the study

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  A Community Health Centre or clinics providing walk-in services only

          -  Practices that are under the traditional fee for service remuneration

          -  Located in a neighbourhood with less than 20% Francophone residents

        Primary care providers:

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Work in a practice that meets the eligibility criteria participating practice will be
             invited to participate in the study.

          -  Is a Primary Health Care Provider: A health professional that may refer patients to
             CRs such as physicians, nurses, and social workers.

        Exclusion criteria:

        Primary care patients:

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Patient identifies a primary care provider participating in the study as their main
             primary care provider

          -  Has received a recommendation for a CR from their PHCP

          -  Is able to communicate in English or French, or is willing to be served via a cultural
             interpreter/translator, preferably a family member.

          -  Is able to provide consent for the study (18 years of age or older), or has
             parental/guardian proxy to provide consent (minor patients, patients with cognitive
             deficits)

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Unable to provide consent and does not have a family member/guardian who can provide
             proxy consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simone Dahrouge, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bruyere Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Simone Dahrouge, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>1-613-562-6262</phone>
    <phone_ext>2913</phone_ext>
    <email>sdahrouge@bruyere.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrea Perna, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>1-613-562-6262</phone>
    <phone_ext>2920</phone_ext>
    <email>aperna@bruyere.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Community Resources, Patient Navigator</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

