<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03451955</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-17019986</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03451955</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of a Gluten Free Diet on the Permeability of the Blood Brain Barrier in Patients With CIS</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of a Gluten Free Diet on the Permeability of the Blood Brain Barrier in Patients With Clinically Isolated Syndrome Measured by Dynamic Contrast Enhanced Magnetic Resonance Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Copenhagen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Copenhagen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Disruption of the blood brain barrier (BBB) is associated with inflammatory conditions of the
      central nervous system (CNS). This clinical trial aims to investigate whether following a
      gluten-free diet (GFD) for six months can contribute to normalizing BBB permeability in
      patients with newly diagnosed clinically isolated syndrome (CIS) and multiple sclerosis (MS).
      Furthermore, the study seeks to identify possible effects of a GFD on markers of systemic as
      well as CNS inflammation. Lastly, gut permeability is measured in order to examine whether
      there are any correlations between the permeability of the gut and the BBB as well as the
      inflammatory state in the intestine and CNS. From a patient's view, potential positive
      effects of a GFD will be manifested through an alleviation of symptoms, improved quality of
      life and reduced risk of CIS progressing to MS. Evaluating a possible role of gluten in MS
      pathogenesis can contribute to directing future research and optimizing treatment protocols.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Disruption of the blood brain barrier (BBB) is believed to play a critical role in the
      pathogenesis of multiple sclerosis (MS). Cramer et al. (2014) found increased BBB
      permeability in MS patients compared to healthy controls (HC) with values being higher in
      cases with recent relapses (1). Furthermore, BBB permeability can contribute to predicting
      the conversion of optic neuritis (ON) to MS (2). In the same study, significant correlations
      were found between BBB permeability, leukocyte counts and levels of the chemokine CXCL10 in
      cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). Chemokines are believed to contribute to MS pathogenesis by
      attracting leukocyte populations to the CNS.

      Sørensen et al. (1999) found elevated levels of the cytokines CXCL9, CXCL10 and CCL5 together
      with their receptors CXCR3 and CCR5 on leukocytes in CSF from MS patients during attacks (3).
      CXCR3 is expressed in human enterocytes, endothelial cells in the BBB and a variety of immune
      cells. Elevated expression of CXCR3 has also been measured on T cells from MS patients
      compared to HC, and in patients during relapses compared to remission (4). Exposure of
      intestinal epithelial cell lines to gliadin has been shown to activate the chemokine receptor
      CXCR3 and hereby leading to release of zonulin (5). Ex vivo experiments illustrated that
      zonulin, which has been identified as pre-haptoglobin 2, leads to a time- and dose dependent,
      reversible reduction of the transepithelial electrical resistance (TEER) of murine small
      intestinal mucosa (6). The effects of zonulin on gut permeability are assumed to be due to
      disruption of tight junctional integrity.

      A pilot study (7) showed a higher proportion of individuals with increased intestinal
      permeability among patients with MS compared to sex-matched HC. A randomized clinical trial
      showed beneficial effects of a gluten-free diet (GFD) on annual relapse rate, lesional
      activity and expanded disability status scale (EDSS) in patients with relapsing-remitting MS
      (RRMS), when compared to a regular diet (8). Additionally, findings of significantly higher
      titers of IgA against gliadin, gluten and casein in MS patients compared to HC, could
      indicate a role of nutritional factors in MS (8).

      The role of gluten in the pathogenesis of celiac disease (CD) is established. In CD dietary
      intake of gluten leads to the development of autoantibodies against the enzyme
      transglutaminase 2 (TG2). White matter autopsies have shown TG2 immunoreactivity in
      astrocytes from activated MS lesions (9). Furthermore, treatment with TG2 inhibitors led to
      attenuation of demyelination and clinical deficits in rats with chronic-relapsing
      experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE) (10). A GFD has also been documented to
      protect against type 1 diabetes (T1D) in mice (11) and prolong the asymptomatic period after
      diagnosis of T1D in humans (12).

      Lastly, gliadin fragments have been documented to stimulate the production of TNF-α and IL-8
      in human monocytes directly (13). TNF-α has also been shown to have a regulatory effect on
      zonulin and to increase the permeability of the endothelial and epithelial cell layers (14),
      which could be an indirect mechanism through which gluten can induce alterations of gut and
      possibly also BBB permeability. A high gluten intake could thereby not only increase the
      influx of antigens, but also activate pathways of the innate immune system. This can
      theoretically contribute to establishing an inflammatory milieu and thereby facilitate the
      activation of autoreactive T cells. It could be hypothesized that the role of gluten in
      autoimmunity is not restricted to gluten itself being recognized as an antigen by people with
      specific HLA genotypes, but gluten might also increase the risk of losing tolerance against
      other antigens.

      Purpose:

      The study aims to investigate whether a GFD can contribute to decreasing BBB permeability in
      patients with ON, other clinically isolated syndrome (CIS) and MS. Furthermore, the study
      seeks to identify possible effects of a GFD on markers of systemic as well as CNS
      inflammation. Lastly, gut permeability is measured in order to examine whether there are any
      correlations between the permeability of the gut and the BBB as well as the inflammatory
      state in the intestine and CNS. Evaluating the effects of gluten intake on disease
      progression could contribute to identifying crucial mechanisms that underlie the pathogenesis
      of CIS and MS, directing future research and designing new, optimized treatment protocols.

      Hypothesis:

      Gluten may increase intestinal permeability and thereby elevate antigen influx possibly by
      activating CXCR3 on enterocytes. Increased gut permeability, gut inflammation and absorption
      of larger gliadin molecules may be associated with increased permeability of the BBB.
      Activation of BBB endothelial cells may lead to loss of tight junctional integrity, but also
      increased integrin expression and thereby enhanced extravasation of immune cells into the
      CNS.

      Expected research value:

      The study can contribute to a better understanding of the pathologies of ON and MS and
      provide a basis for the development of new treatment protocols. Conducting evidence-based
      research regarding the possible effects of gluten intake on the progression of autoimmune
      diseases will reduce misinformation as well as shed light on practical challenges associated
      with the implementation of dietary interventions for treatment purposes. The study is
      approved of the Scientific Ethics Committee.

      Methods:

      The trial is a clinically controlled, open label, intervention study including 40 patients
      with newly diagnosed CIS or MS. Patients will be divided into an intervention group and a
      control group, each of 20 patients. The intervention group will abstain from gluten for six
      months, while patients in the control group will retain their usual dietary habits. Before
      and after the intervention period, a variety of measurements will be conducted. These
      include:

        -  Anthropometric measurements: conducted to monitor possible effects of the GFD on
           participants´ body composition.

        -  Diet and lifestyle surveys: used to monitor participants´ dietary habits, smoking
           status, exercise, physical activity, sleeping pattern and quality of life.

        -  Clinical measures: Relapses, expanded disability status scale (EDSS), MS diagnosis,
           disease modifying treatment, T2 lesions count and lesion load. Treatment status and
           recent relapses will be used as covariates in the logistic regression analysis.

        -  Dynamic contrast-enhanced MRI: used to measure the permeability of the BBB in several
           tissue subtypes (normal appearing white matter and grey matter and MS lesions) as
           segmented on high resolution T2 FLAIR and 3D T1 weighted images. The number of new or
           enhancing lesions is being monitored.

        -  Intestinal permeability test: conducted to measure intestinal permeability and
           absorption capacity.

        -  Lumbar puncture: used to determine disease activity in the CNS. Analyses include
           pre-haptoglobin 2, oligoclonal bands, TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-8, INF-γ, CXCL9, CXCL10, CCL5,
           immune cell counts, expression of CXCR3 on immune cells.

        -  Blood samples: used to determine the grade of inflammation outside the CNS and diagnose
           celiac disease. Analyses include S100β, pre-haptoglobin 2, anti-gliadin antibodies, CRP,
           TNF-α, IL-1β, INF-γ, immune cell counts, expression of CXCR3 on immune cells, endotoxin,
           intestinal fatty acid binding protein, 25-(OH)-cholecalciferol.

        -  Fecal samples: used to measure gut microbiota profiling and short chain fatty acids.

      BBB and intestinal permeability will not only be measured through an MRI scan and an
      intestinal permeability test respectively, but also using the biomarker zonulin. Of notice is
      that our measurements of zonulin in CSF (for BBB permeability) and serum (for intestinal
      permeability) will be carried out in collaboration with Assistant Professor Dr. Ian Galea,
      who has established a unique analytical method, based on western blotting using a
      non-commercially, proprietary antibody manufactured by Biorad, for this purpose. Every other
      assay used in the scientific community measures both haptoglobin and zonulin, whereas our
      assay measures only zonulin and is therefore characterized by increased accuracy.

      Expected results:

      A gluten-free diet is expected to alleviate CIS symptoms, improve quality of life and reduce
      the risk of CIS progressing into MS. Mechanistically this is expected to be manifested
      through a normalized BBB and intestinal permeability, decreased lesional activity and by
      dampening the activity of a previously overactive immune system. If our hypothesis is proven
      to be correct, MS and CIS patients should be informed about the results of the study and the
      option of following a GFD could potentially become part of the standardized patient treatment
      in hospitals.

      Publication of results:

      Results will be published independent of study outcome. Positive, negative as well as
      inconclusive results will be published. Results are expected to be published in peer-reviewed
      international journals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Permeability of the blood brain barrier</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Blood brain barrier permeability measured by contrast enhanced magnetic resonance imaging as well as concentration of pre-haptoglobin 2 in CSF</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intestinal permeability</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by lactulose/mannitol intestinal permeability test and concentration of pre-haptoglobin 2 in blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intestinal absorption capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by D-xylose test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Counts of T cell subpopulations in peripheral blood and CSF</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Flow cytometry analysis using antibodies for CD3, CD8, CD4, CD45RA, CXCR3, CCR6, CCR4, CCR9, integrins alpha4, beta7 and beta1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Macrophage activation in peripheral blood and CSF</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Soluble CD163 in peripheral blood and CSF measured by ELISA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuroinflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured as neurofilament light chain in CSF and peripheral blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bacterial translocation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured as endotoxin in blood by ELISA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Osteopontin as a marker of disease activity in multiple sclerosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in blood and CSF by ELISA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Enterocyte damage</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured as intestinal fatty acid binding protein in blood by ELISA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gut microbiota profiling</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in feces by 16S rRNA sequencing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Optic Neuritis</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Clinically Isolated Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the intervention group follow a gluten-free diet for six months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the control group follow their usual diet for six months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gluten-free diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group abstain from gluten for 6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult men and women ≥18 and ≤59 years of age

          -  Patients with newly diagnosed CIS or MS deemed physically and mentally able to
             participate in a study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  More conflicting disorders in the same patient

          -  Pregnancy and lactating women and women planning pregnancy during the study period

          -  People with severe claustrophobia

          -  People with MR incompatible implants/ foreign objects, including implanted pacemakers,
             heart valve prostheses, prostheses in the middle ear, implanted devices (e.g. insulin
             pump), metal debris, e.g. metal splinters in the eyes, miscellaneous shunts and
             catheters, metal clips from operations

          -  Surgeries within the last 6 weeks

          -  Previous reactions to MR contrast agent, bronchial asthma or history of other
             allergies

          -  Elevated serum creatinine

          -  People already on a gluten restricted/ GFD
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jens Rikardt Andersen</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Copenhagen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jens Rikardt Andersen</last_name>
    <phone>35332504</phone>
    <email>jra@nexs.ku.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Copenhagen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <state>Frederiksberg</state>
        <zip>1958</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jens Rikardt Andersen, Ass. prof.</last_name>
      <email>jra@nexs.ku.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rigshopitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glostrup</city>
        <zip>2600</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jette Frederiksen, Professor</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cramer SP, Simonsen H, Frederiksen JL, Rostrup E, Larsson HB. Abnormal blood-brain barrier permeability in normal appearing white matter in multiple sclerosis investigated by MRI. Neuroimage Clin. 2013 Dec 10;4:182-9. doi: 10.1016/j.nicl.2013.12.001. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24371801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cramer SP, Modvig S, Simonsen HJ, Frederiksen JL, Larsson HB. Permeability of the blood-brain barrier predicts conversion from optic neuritis to multiple sclerosis. Brain. 2015 Sep;138(Pt 9):2571-83. doi: 10.1093/brain/awv203. Epub 2015 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26187333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sørensen TL, Tani M, Jensen J, Pierce V, Lucchinetti C, Folcik VA, Qin S, Rottman J, Sellebjerg F, Strieter RM, Frederiksen JL, Ransohoff RM. Expression of specific chemokines and chemokine receptors in the central nervous system of multiple sclerosis patients. J Clin Invest. 1999 Mar;103(6):807-15.</citation>
    <PMID>10079101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andalib A, Doulabi H, Najafi M, Tazhibi M, Rezaie A. Expression of chemokine receptors on Th1/Th2 CD4+ lymphocytes in patients with multiple sclerosis. Iran J Immunol. 2011 Mar;8(1):1-10. doi: IJIv8i1A1.</citation>
    <PMID>21427490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lammers KM, Lu R, Brownley J, Lu B, Gerard C, Thomas K, Rallabhandi P, Shea-Donohue T, Tamiz A, Alkan S, Netzel-Arnett S, Antalis T, Vogel SN, Fasano A. Gliadin induces an increase in intestinal permeability and zonulin release by binding to the chemokine receptor CXCR3. Gastroenterology. 2008 Jul;135(1):194-204.e3. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2008.03.023. Epub 2008 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>18485912</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tripathi A, Lammers KM, Goldblum S, Shea-Donohue T, Netzel-Arnett S, Buzza MS, Antalis TM, Vogel SN, Zhao A, Yang S, Arrietta MC, Meddings JB, Fasano A. Identification of human zonulin, a physiological modulator of tight junctions, as prehaptoglobin-2. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2009 Sep 29;106(39):16799-804. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0906773106. Epub 2009 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19805376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buscarinu MC, Cerasoli B, Annibali V, Policano C, Lionetto L, Capi M, Mechelli R, Romano S, Fornasiero A, Mattei G, Piras E, Angelini DF, Battistini L, Simmaco M, Umeton R, Salvetti M, Ristori G. Altered intestinal permeability in patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis: A pilot study. Mult Scler. 2017 Mar;23(3):442-446. doi: 10.1177/1352458516652498. Epub 2016 Jul 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27270497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Strien ME, Drukarch B, Bol JG, van der Valk P, van Horssen J, Gerritsen WH, Breve JJ, van Dam AM. Appearance of tissue transglutaminase in astrocytes in multiple sclerosis lesions: a role in cell adhesion and migration? Brain Pathol. 2011 Jan;21(1):44-54. doi: 10.1111/j.1750-3639.2010.00428.x. Epub 2010 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20731658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Strien ME, de Vries HE, Chrobok NL, Bol JGJM, Breve JJP, van der Pol SMP, Kooij G, van Buul JD, Karpuj M, Steinman L, Wilhelmus MM, Sestito C, Drukarch B, Van Dam AM. Tissue Transglutaminase contributes to experimental multiple sclerosis pathogenesis and clinical outcome by promoting macrophage migration. Brain Behav Immun. 2015 Nov;50:141-154. doi: 10.1016/j.bbi.2015.06.023. Epub 2015 Jun 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26133787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antvorskov JC, Josefsen K, Engkilde K, Funda DP, Buschard K. Dietary gluten and the development of type 1 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2014 Sep;57(9):1770-80. doi: 10.1007/s00125-014-3265-1. Epub 2014 May 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24871322</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Svensson J, Sildorf SM, Pipper CB, Kyvsgaard JN, Bøjstrup J, Pociot FM, Mortensen HB, Buschard K. Potential beneficial effects of a gluten-free diet in newly diagnosed children with type 1 diabetes: a pilot study. Springerplus. 2016 Jul 7;5(1):994. doi: 10.1186/s40064-016-2641-3. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27398272</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jelínková L, Tucková L, Cinová J, Flegelová Z, Tlaskalová-Hogenová H. Gliadin stimulates human monocytes to production of IL-8 and TNF-alpha through a mechanism involving NF-kappaB. FEBS Lett. 2004 Jul 30;571(1-3):81-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15280021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nouri M, Bredberg A, Weström B, Lavasani S. Intestinal barrier dysfunction develops at the onset of experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis, and can be induced by adoptive transfer of auto-reactive T cells. PLoS One. 2014 Sep 3;9(9):e106335. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0106335. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25184418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Copenhagen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jens Rikardt Andersen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>gluten</keyword>
  <keyword>gluten free diet</keyword>
  <keyword>blood brain barrier permeability</keyword>
  <keyword>intestinal permeability</keyword>
  <keyword>neuroinflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>autoimmunity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Neuritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

