<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03453749</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Ethics reference: 2013/144</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03453749</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anti-secretory Factor as a Treatment for Adults With Severe Traumatic Head Injury</brief_title>
  <acronym>SATSWEDEN</acronym>
  <official_title>Anti-secretory Factor as a Treatment for Adults With Severe Traumatic Head Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peter Siesjö</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Skane University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction/Background Brain swelling/brain edema can occur due to many pathologies of the
      brain, such as infections, ischemia and trauma.

      The edema can be either primarily intra-cellular or extra-cellular. The mechanisms by which
      edema arise are not fully known but it is proposed that inside the damaged brain, fluid will
      pass over the blood-brain barrier of the vessels into the extra-cellular space. The
      accumulation of fluid will lead to an increase in distance between the cell and its closest
      capillary, which may lead to energy failure and intra-cellular edema. The extra volume of the
      fluid leads to increased intracranial pressure, which in turn leads to an increase in blood
      pressure, aggravating the edema. In addition to the physiological changes that occur, the
      edema will be increased by the immunological response to the tissue damage with release of
      pro-inflammatory cytokines that give rise to both extra- and intra-cellular edema.

      Today, no treatment has been proven efficient against traumatic brain edema. AF -
      anti-secretory factor is a 41 kDa protein that exists in humans and most animals. It was
      discovered due to its ability to inhibit experimental diarrhea.

      AF has been proven to have an effect on Mb Menière and glaucoma. In animal models, AF has
      been proven efficient in reducing increased intracranial pressure caused by trauma and virus
      infection in the brain.

      Salovum®, an egg yolk powder enriched in AF, is registered in the European Union as a medical
      food.

      Methods: 5 adult patients with severe traumatic brain injury will be included in the trial
      via next of kin consent.

      Medical interventions are protocol based. The protocol includes first, second and third
      treatment levels.

      Patients included in the trial, will receive two micro-dialysis (MD) catheters in addition to
      standard treatment. One catheter will be placed in a separate burr hole close to the ICP and
      LICOX catheter, the other MD catheter will be placed in vicinity of the damaged barin tissue.

      Patients will receive Salovum® 6 hours after trial inclusion. Patient dosage is 1g/kg body
      weight/24 hours, divided into 6 doses and administered orally, via tubing every 4 hours for 5
      consecutive days.

      Objective: Primary end-point is to investigate if Salovum® has a beneficiary effect on ICP.

      Secondary endpoints are to investigate if Salovum® has a beneficiary effect on treatment
      intensity levels (TIL), brain-oxygenation, microdialysis bio-chemistry and cytokine
      expression in plasma and microdialysate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      MD will be analysed bedside hourly for patient management, and the remaining MD samples will
      be frozen in -70° C for later analysis of cytokines.

      An extra blood sample will be drawn twice daily, blood will be centrifuged and plasma will be
      frozen in -70° C for later analysis of cytokines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>5 consecutive adult patients with severe head trauma will receive treatment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ICP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Intracranial pressure in mm Hg</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PtO2</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Brain tissue oxygenation in mm Hg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Microdialysis biochemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of glucose, pyruvate and lactate from micro-dialysis fluid</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cytokine expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of cytokines from micro-dialysis fluid</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TIL</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment Intensity Level, scale 0-38</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Head Trauma</condition>
  <condition>Intensive Care Neurological Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Edema Brain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Salovum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be given Salovum 1g/kg body weight/24 hours, divided into 6 dosages and given during 5 consecutive days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Salovum</intervention_name>
    <description>Salovum is freeze dried egg yolk, highly enriched with anti-secretory factor. Salovum is registered as a medical food by the EU</description>
    <arm_group_label>Salovum</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult of either gender between 18 and 65 years.

          2. Non-penetrating, isolated severe traumatic brain injury

          3. GCS &gt;3 and GCS&lt;9 on admission or within 48 hours after injury*

          4. Admission to study hospital within 24 hours of injury*

          5. No known history of allergy to egg-protein

          6. Planned for intracranial pressure monitoring

          7. Absence of bilaterally dilated pupils

          8. CT scan with traumatic pathology that is more than an isolated epidural hematoma

               -  Within 24 hours of injury (for patients with GCS &lt; 9 on admission) or Within 24
                  hours of deterioration (among patients deteriorating to GCS &lt; 9 within 48 hours
                  of injury)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. No consent

          2. Systolic blood pressure below 90 mm Hg post resuscitation

          3. Epidural hematoma with no other signs of intra-cranial injury

          4. Penetrating injury

          5. Non-fulfillment of inclusion criteria after screening and inclusion procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Cederberg, Consultant</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dept of Neurosurgery, Skane University Hospital, Lund, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Cederberg, Consultatnt</last_name>
    <phone>0046702060344</phone>
    <email>david.cederberg@med.lu.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Peter Siesjö</last_name>
    <phone>+4646171274</phone>
    <email>peter.siesjo@med.lu.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eide PK, Eidsvaag VA, Hansson HA. Antisecretory factor (AF) exerts no effects on intracranial pressure (ICP) waves and ICP in patients with idiopathic normal pressure hydrocephalus and idiopathic intracranial hypertension. J Neurol Sci. 2014 Aug 15;343(1-2):132-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jns.2014.05.054. Epub 2014 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24928077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaman S, Aamir K, Lange S, Jennische E, Silfverdal SA, Hanson LÅ. Antisecretory factor effectively and safely stops childhood diarrhoea: a placebo-controlled, randomised study. Acta Paediatr. 2014 Jun;103(6):659-64. doi: 10.1111/apa.12581. Epub 2014 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24484450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leong SC, Narayan S, Lesser TH. Antisecretory factor-inducing therapy improves patient-reported functional levels in Meniere's disease. Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol. 2013 Oct;122(10):619-24.</citation>
    <PMID>24294684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alam NH, Ashraf H, Olesen M, Salam MA, Gyr N, Meier R. Salovum egg yolk containing antisecretory factor as an adjunct therapy in severe cholera in adult males: a pilot study. J Health Popul Nutr. 2011 Aug;29(4):297-302.</citation>
    <PMID>21957667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ulgheri C, Paganini B, Rossi F. Antisecretory factor as a potential health-promoting molecule in man and animals. Nutr Res Rev. 2010 Dec;23(2):300-13. doi: 10.1017/S0954422410000193. Epub 2010 Aug 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20684797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanner P, Rask-Andersen H, Lange S, Jennische E. Antisecretory factor-inducing therapy improves the clinical outcome in patients with Ménière's disease. Acta Otolaryngol. 2010 Feb;130(2):223-7. doi: 10.3109/00016480903022842.</citation>
    <PMID>19479454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaman S, Mannan J, Lange S, Lönnroth I, Hanson LA. B 221, a medical food containing antisecretory factor reduces child diarrhoea: a placebo controlled trial. Acta Paediatr. 2007 Nov;96(11):1655-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17937690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laurenius A, Wängberg B, Lange S, Jennische E, Lundgren BK, Bosaeus I. Antisecretory factor counteracts secretory diarrhoea of endocrine origin. Clin Nutr. 2003 Dec;22(6):549-52.</citation>
    <PMID>14613757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Olama M, Lange S, Lönnroth I, Gatzinsky K, Jennische E. Uptake of the antisecretory factor peptide AF-16 in rat blood and cerebrospinal fluid and effects on elevated intracranial pressure. Acta Neurochir (Wien). 2015 Jan;157(1):129-37. doi: 10.1007/s00701-014-2221-7. Epub 2014 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25248325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Olama M, Wallgren A, Andersson B, Gatzinsky K, Hultborn R, Karlsson-Parra A, Lange S, Hansson HA, Jennische E. The peptide AF-16 decreases high interstitial fluid pressure in solid tumors. Acta Oncol. 2011 Oct;50(7):1098-104. doi: 10.3109/0284186X.2011.562240. Epub 2011 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21375367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Skane University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Peter Siesjö</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Consultant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Traumatic brain injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Cerebral edema</keyword>
  <keyword>Microdialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory cytokines</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Craniocerebral Trauma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antisecretory factor</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

