<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03455660</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAR7164</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03455660</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Retrospective Comparison of Neonatal Acid-base Status After CD Before January, 2015 and After January, 2016</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Retrospective Comparison of Neonatal Acid-base Status After Cesarean Delivery (CD) at NYPresbyterian/Columbia University Medical Center (CUMC) Before January, 2015 and After January, 2016</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective is to retrospectively gather peri-operative data on neonatal outcomes,
      primarily neonatal acid-base status, based on umbilical cord gas analysis, for the 23 months
      preceding and 23 months following the conduct of the &quot;tilt versus supine study&quot;. The
      investigators hypothesize that there will be no difference in mean neonatal umbilical artery
      base excess in neonates delivered by cesarean section during the period before and after
      conduct of the study, for elective, urgent and emergent deliveries.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For decades, obstetric anesthesia dogma for term women undergoing cesarean delivery (CD)
      includes maintenance of left lateral tilt for uterine displacement until delivery, based on
      the premise that the supine position will result in aortocaval compression (ACC), maternal
      hypotension and fetal compromise. More recent evidence suggests that even in 15 degrees of
      left tilt, there is minimal relief of aortocaval compression. Furthermore, there is evidence
      that most practitioners never achieve 15 degrees of tilt anyway.

      Between January 2015 and January 2016, the investigators conducted a randomized clinical
      trial at NewYork Presbyterian/The Allen Hospital in which healthy women undergoing elective
      CD were randomized (non-blinded) to supine horizontal (SUPINE, N=50) or 15° left tilt of the
      surgical table (TILT, N= 50) following spinal anesthesia (hyperbaric bupivacaine 12 mg,
      fentanyl 15 μg, preservative-free morphine 150 μg). Lactated Ringer's 10ml/kg and a
      phenylephrine (PE) infusion titrated to 100% baseline systolic blood pressure (SBP) were
      initiated with intrathecal injection. The primary outcome was umbilical artery base excess
      (UA-BE). There were no differences in UA-BE or pH between groups. The mean UA-BE (± SD) was
      -0.5 mmol/L (± 1.6) in the SUPINE group (n=50) versus -0.6 mmol/L (± 1.5) in the TILT group
      (n=47) (p= 0.64). The conclusion was that maternal supine position during elective CD with
      spinal anesthesia in healthy term women does not impair neonatal acid-base status compared to
      15° left tilt, when maternal SBP is maintained with a coload and PE infusion. The
      investigators understood that the findings may not be generalized to emergency situations or
      non-reassuring fetal status.

      Since the end of the study, discussion of the findings with colleagues at Departmental grand
      rounds and national conferences, and a publication in the journal Anesthesiology,
      practitioners have reported feeling more comfortable with maternal supine position during
      cesarean delivery, as long as maternal SBP is kept at or near to baseline with crystalloid
      infusion and a PE infusion. It is routine practice at CUMC to use a prophylactic PE infusion
      for maintenance of maternal SBP close to or at baseline. It is also routine at CUMC to send
      samples of umbilical arterial and venous blood for analysis. Much of the dosing for neuraxial
      anesthesia (spinal, combined spinal epidural anesthesia and epidural doses) are standardized
      at CUMC. The investigators believe that since there has been a noticeable practice shift with
      practitioners anecdotally reporting that they have discontinued the routine use of left
      maternal tilt intraoperatively, the investigators will be able to collect useful data on
      cases which had not been studied - these include cases with preeclampsia, morbid obesity and
      emergencies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Umbilical artery base excess</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Base excess calculation of umbilical artery blood</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Umbilical artery pH</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>pH measurement of umbilical artery blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">101</enrollment>
  <condition>Cesarean Delivery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-January 2015</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who underwent cesarean delivery between February 2013 and December 2014.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-January 2016</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who underwent cesarean delivery between February 2016 and December 2017.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>no intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>no intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-January 2015</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Post-January 2016</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Retrospective cohorts of women who delivered between February 2013 and December 2014, and
        between February 2016 and December 2017
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who delivered between February 2013 and December 2014, and between February 2016
             and December 2017

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Allison Lee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NewYork Presbyterian/The Allen Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10034</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee AJ, Landau R. Aortocaval Compression Syndrome: Time to Revisit Certain Dogmas. Anesth Analg. 2017 Dec;125(6):1975-1985. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000002313. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28759487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Higuchi H, Takagi S, Zhang K, Furui I, Ozaki M. Effect of lateral tilt angle on the volume of the abdominal aorta and inferior vena cava in pregnant and nonpregnant women determined by magnetic resonance imaging. Anesthesiology. 2015 Feb;122(2):286-93. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000553.</citation>
    <PMID>25603203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones SJ, Kinsella SM, Donald FA. Comparison of measured and estimated angles of table tilt at Caesarean section. Br J Anaesth. 2003 Jan;90(1):86-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12488385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aust H, Koehler S, Kuehnert M, Wiesmann T. Guideline-recommended 15° left lateral table tilt during cesarean section in regional anesthesia-practical aspects: An observational study. J Clin Anesth. 2016 Aug;32:47-53. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2015.12.041. Epub 2016 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>27290944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee AJ, Landau R, Mattingly JL, Meenan MM, Corradini B, Wang S, Goodman SR, Smiley RM. Left Lateral Table Tilt for Elective Cesarean Delivery under Spinal Anesthesia Has No Effect on Neonatal Acid-Base Status: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Anesthesiology. 2017 Aug;127(2):241-249. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000001737.</citation>
    <PMID>28598894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Allison Lee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cesarean</keyword>
  <keyword>C-Section</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Will not share patient identifiable data with other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

