<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03454282</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INT157/17</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>B42F17000260006</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03454282</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Dietary Intervention on Tumor Immunity: the DigesT Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>DIgesT</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Dietary Intervention on Tumor Immunity: the DigesT Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milano</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Health Research Institutes, Taiwan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centro de Investigación en Nanomateriales y Nanotecnología (CINN)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Martin-Luther-Universität Halle-Wittenberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Milan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milano</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial aims to assess the immunological and metabolic changes induced by the Fasting
      Mimicking Diet (FMD) in the pre-operative and post-operative setting in breast cancer and
      melanoma patients. Three cohorts of patients will be enrolled: 1) Cohort A: patients with
      resectable breast cancer (cT1N0M0 stage or cT1cN1M0-cT2cN0M0 stages not requiring
      pre-operative systemic treatment at the judgment of the investigator) who are candidate to
      curative surgery; 2) Cohort B: patients with malignant melanoma patients candidate to
      dissection of the lymph node basin because of a positive sentinel lymph node (stage
      IIIA-IIIB-IIIC); 3) Cohort C: patients with resected malignant melanoma (including
      radicalization and, in case, lymph node dissection) who are not candidate to any adjuvant
      treatment, but only to clinical and radiological follow-up (stage IIB-IIC). Patients in
      cohorts A and B will undergo one 5-days FMD cycle about 13-15 days before surgical removal of
      primary tumor (breast) or lymph nodes (breast, melanoma). Patients in cohort C will undergo 4
      consecutive FMD cycles every 28 days, starting one month after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Preclinical evidences suggest that reducing the concentration of blood metabolites and growth
      factors reduces the in vivo growth of several tumor models, while protecting normal tissues
      from the cytotoxic effects of chemotherapeutical treatments. In recent years, a plant-based,
      calorie-restricted, low-carbohydrate, low-protein diet, also known as Fasting Mimicking Diet
      (FMD), has been proposed as a potential anticancer dietary intervention. The FMD is safe when
      administered cyclically (every 21-28 days) to healthy volunteers, and is capable of
      significantly reducing the concentration of plasma glucose, serum insulin and IGF-1, while
      increasing levels of plasma IGFBPs and ketone bodies. The FMD has been shown to inhibit the
      in vivo growth of several tumor models, including breast cancer and melanoma mice models. The
      anticancer effects of the FMD are likely mediated by two concomitant mechanisms: 1) one
      direct anticancer effect that is mediated by the inhibition of energy production and anabolic
      pathways, such as protein and fatty acid synthesis, in cancer cells; 2) one indirect effect
      that is mediated by the activation of antitumor immunity, with the result of enhanced tumor
      infiltration by cytotoxic CD8+ T-lymphocytes and reduced infiltration by immunosuppressive
      populations. According to the currently accepted model, the anticancer and immunomodulatory
      effects of the FMD mostly derive from the reduction of circulating glucose, insulin and IGF-1
      levels, and a parallel increase of ketone body and IGF-1 binding protein concentration.
      However, recent observations in healthy volunteers and cancer patients, suggest that
      FMD-mediated changes in many other metabolites, such as specific amino acids or fatty acids,
      could contribute to the cell-autonomous or immune-mediated anticancer effects of the FMD.
      While the study of the effects of the FMD in combination with standard treatments (e.g.
      chemotherapy, molecular targeted therapy) in advanced cancers represents the final objective
      of the ongoing studies, fully uncovering the metabolic and immunological effects of the FMD
      alone is essential to design future combination studies. From this perspective, the pre- and
      post-operative clinical settings in cancer patients who are not candidate to other medical
      treatments represent an ideal context to assess the effects of the FMD without other
      confounding factors. This trial primarily aims to assess the immunological and metabolic
      changes induced by the FMD in the pre-operative and post-operative setting in breast cancer
      and melanoma patients. Three cohorts of patients will be enrolled: 1) Cohort A: patients with
      resectable breast cancer (cT1N0M0 stage or cT1cN1M0-cT2cN0M0 stages not requiring
      pre-operative systemic treatment at the judgment of the investigator) who are candidate to
      curative surgery; 2) Cohort B: patients with malignant melanoma patients candidate to
      dissection of the lymph node basin because of a positive sentinel lymph node (stage
      IIIA-IIIB-IIIC); 3) Cohort C: patients with resected malignant melanoma (including
      radicalization and, in case, lymph node dissection) who are not candidate to any adjuvant
      treatment, but only to clinical and radiological follow-up (stage IIB-IIC). Patients in
      cohorts A and B will undergo one 5-days FMD cycle about 13-15 days before surgical removal of
      primary tumor (breast) or lymph nodes (breast, melanoma). Patients in cohort C will undergo 4
      consecutive FMD cycles every 28 days, starting one month after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Clinical trials with a single arm and three cohorts of patients</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute and relative changes in PBMCs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Absolute and relative changes in PBMCs by 10-color cytofluorimetry before and after the FMD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phenotypic modifications in PBMCs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Phenotypic modifications in PBMCs, as detected by by 10-colors citofluorimetry and single-cell &quot;mass cytometry&quot; (CyTOF)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional modifications in PBMCs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Functional modifications in PBMCs, as detected by by 10-colors citofluorimetry and single-cell &quot;mass cytometry&quot; (CyTOF)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional modifications in tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Functional modifications in tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes, as detected by by 10-colors citofluorimetry and single-cell &quot;mass cytometry&quot; (CyTOF)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phenotypic modifications in tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Phenotypic modifications in tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes, as detected by by 10-colors citofluorimetry and single-cell &quot;mass cytometry&quot; (CyTOF)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional modifications of immune cell population in LNs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Functional modifications of immune cell populations in LNs, as detected by single-cell &quot;mass cytometry&quot; (CyTOF).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mRNA profiling in tumor cells</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Gene expression profiling (through mRNA quantification) in tumor cells (Cohort A).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mRNA profiling in immune cells</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Gene expression profiling (through mRNA quantification) in PBMCs and immune cell populations inside lymph nodes (Cohort B).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>miRNA profiling in tumor cells</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>miRNA profiling in tumor cells (Cohort A)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>miRNA profiling in immune cells</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>miRNA profiling in PBMCs and immune cell populations inside lymph nodes (Cohort B).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the expression of metabolic genes in PBMCs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the expression of selected metabolic genes (including hexokinase 1, phosphofructokinase 1, pyruvate kinase 2) through mRNA quantification in PBMCs before and after the FMD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FMD-induced changes in blood metabolic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>FMD-induced changes in blood (glucose, triglycerides, fatty acids, cholesterol, amino acids)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FMD-induced changes in urine metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>FMD-induced changes in urine metabolites (ketone bodies)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FMD-induced changes in serum growth factors.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>FMD-induced changes in serum growth factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative changes in tumor-infiltrating immune cells</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Qualitative changes in the type of tumor-infiltrating immune cell populations before and after the diet in breast cancer patients undergoing curative surgery (Cohort A).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative changes in tumor-infiltrating immune cells</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative changes in the number of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes, machrophages, MDSCs before and after the diet in breast cancer patients undergoing curative surgery (Cohort A).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in tumor proliferation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in tumor proliferation index (Ki67) IHC in breast cancer patients (Cohort A).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in tumor cell apoptosis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in tumor cell apoptosis (caspase 3 by IHC) in breast cancer patients (Cohort A).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in tumor metabolic pathways</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in tumor levels of glycolytic enzymes by IHC (Glut1, HK1, PFK1/2, PK2) in breast cancer patients (Cohort A).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in expression of hormone receptors and HER2</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in expression of estrogen and/progesterone receptor and HER2 oncoprotein by IHC in breast cancer patients (Cohort A).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative changes in immune cell suspensions from lymph nodes</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the type of immune cells (CD8+ T-lymhocytes, CD 4+ lymphocytes, Treg) found in lymph node suspensions of melanoma patients undergoing one FMD cycle before lymph node dissection (Cohort B).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative changes in immune cell suspensions from lymph nodes</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative changes in the absolute and relative amount of immune cell populations in lymph node suspensions of melanoma patients undergoing one FMD cycle before lymph node dissection (Cohort B).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in DNA methylomic profiles in lymph node specimens</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in genome-wide DNA methylomic profiles with high-density arrays in lymph node specimens from patients undergoing the FMD before surgery (Cohorts A and B).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in DNA methylomic profiles in tumor specimens</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in genome-wide DNA methylomic profiles with high-density arrays in tumor specimens from patients undergoing the FMD before surgery (Cohorts A and B).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in gut microbiota composition.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in type of gut bacteria populations, as detected through 16S ribosomal RNA sequencing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short-term modification of blood nutritional parameters.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Short-term (before vs after each FMD cycle) modification of blood nutritional parameters (levels of plasma cholesterol, prealbumin, transferrin, total lymphocytes)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term modification of blood nutritional parameters.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Long-term (along subsequent FMD cycles) modification of blood nutritional parameters (levels of plasma cholesterol, realbumin, transferrin, total lymphocytes)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short-term and long-term modification of BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Short-term and long-term modification of BMI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FMD-induced changes in white blood cell populations</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>FMD-induced changes in neutrophils, macrophages, lymphocytes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FMD-induced changes in hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>FMD-induced changes in hemoglobin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of patient compliance to the FMD.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of patient compliance to the FMD, as measured by quantifying the number of major and minor deviations of patients' diet relative to the prescribed FMD scheme</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of FMD tolerability.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of FMD tolerability, as defined by the occurrence of G3-G4 adverse events, or serious adverse events (SAEs)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between FMD-induced changes in serum metabolites and changes in PBMCs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between FMD-induced changes in serum metabolites and changes in PBMCs, their activation status, and characteristics of tumor cell and immune infiltrate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between FMD-induced metabolic and immunological changes</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between FMD-induced metabolic and immunological changes with patient diet evaluated at study enrollment through food diaries.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma, Malignant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FMD Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention consists in 5-day FMD (Fasting Mimicking Diet) to be followed for one cycle (Cohorts A and B) or for 4 consecutive every-four week cycles postoperatively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FMD</intervention_name>
    <description>The Fasting Mimicking Diet (or FMD) consists in a 5-day plant-based, low-calorie (700 Kcal on day 1, followed by 300 KCal/day on days 2 to 4 and 450 Kcal on day 5), low-protein (as much as 5% of calorie intake consists of proteins), low carbohydrate (as much as 5-35% of total calorie intake depending on the day) diet</description>
    <arm_group_label>FMD Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fasting Mimicking Diet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 and ≤ 75 years.

          2. Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document (ICD) indicating
             that the patient has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the study before
             enrollment and FMD prescription.

          3. Willingness and ability to comply with the FMD protocol, the scheduled visits,
             treatment plans, laboratory tests and other procedures.

          4. Histologically confirmed diagnosis of invasive breast cancer candidate to curative
             surgery (Cohort A), or resected malignant melanoma requiring dissection of the
             regional lymph node basin for sentinel lymph node involvement (Cohort B), or malignant
             melanoma treated with curative surgery (including, in case, lymph node removal and
             lymph node dissection) (Cohort C). For breast cancer patients, any biological subgroup
             (including estrogen receptor-positive, HER2-positive, triple-negative breast cancer)
             will be admitted; HER2-positive tumors will be defined on the basis of an IHC score of
             3, or a score of 2 with ISH evaluation indicative of gene amplification.

          5. Availability of archival FFPE tissue blocks of primary breast cancer (Cohort A) or
             melanoma (Cohort B, Cohort C).

          6. Presence of an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 or 1.

          7. Presence of adequate bone marrow and organ function as defined by the following
             laboratory values:

               -  ANC ≥ 1.5 x 109/l

               -  platelets ≥ 100 x 109/l

               -  hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dl

               -  calcium (corrected for serum albumin) within normal limits or ≤ grade 1 according
                  to NCI-CTCAE version 4.03 if not clinically significant

               -  potassium within the normal limits, or corrected with supplements

               -  creatinine &lt; 1.5 ULN

               -  blood uric acid &lt; 10 mg/dl

               -  ALT and AST ≤ 2.5 x ULN

               -  total bilirubin &lt; ULN except for patients with Gilbert syndrome who may only be
                  included in the total bilirubin is &lt; 3.0 x ULN or direct bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x ULN

               -  Albumin &gt; 3 g/dL

          8. Fasting glucose ≤ 200 mg/dl.

          9. Total Cholesterol ≤ 300 mg/dl.

         10. Triglycerides ≤ 300 mg/dl.

         11. Female patients of childbearing potential must agree to sexual abstinence or to use
             two highly effective method of contraception throughout the study and for at least 30
             days after the end of the FMD. Abstinence is only acceptable if it is in line with the
             preferred and usual lifestyle of the patient. Examples of contraceptive methods with a
             failure rate of &lt; 1% per year include tubal ligation, male sterilization, hormonal
             implants, established, proper use of combined oral or injected hormonal
             contraceptives, and certain intrauterine devices. Alternatively, two methods (e.g.,
             two barrier methods such as a condom and a cervical cap) may be combined to achieve a
             failure rate of &lt; 1% per year. Barrier methods must always be supplemented with the
             use of a spermicide. A patient is of childbearing potential if, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, she is biologically capable of having children and is sexually active.

        Female patients are not of childbearing potential if they meet at least one of the
        following criteria:

          -  Have undergone a documented hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy

          -  Have medically confirmed ovarian failure

          -  Achieved post-menopausal status, defined as: (≥ 12 months of non-therapy-induced
             amenorrhea) or surgically sterile (absence of ovaries) and have a serum FSH level
             within the laboratory's reference range for postmenopausal females.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior systemic treatment for breast cancer or melanoma.

          2. Diagnosis of a concurrent malignancy other than breast cancer or melanoma, or
             malignancy other than breast cancer or melanoma diagnosed within 5 years of treatment
             enrollment, with the exception of adequately treated, basal or squamous cell
             carcinoma, non-melanomatous skin cancer or curatively resected cervical cancer.

          3. Body Mass Index (BMI) &lt; 20 Kg/m2.

          4. Anamnesis of alcohol abuse.

          5. Unintentional weight loss ≥ 5% in the last three months, unless the patient has a BMI
             &gt; 25 Kg/m2 at study enrollment. Intentional weight loss is permitted if &lt; 10% in the
             last three months and patient BMI is &gt; 22 kg/m2.

          6. Severe heart, liver, pulmonary, kidney comorbidities.

          7. Current status of pregnancy or lactation, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive hCG laboratory test (&gt; 5 mIU/mL).

          8. Active HBV or HCV infection.

          9. Severe infections within 4 weeks prior to FMD initiation, including, but not limited
             to, hospitalization for complications of infection, bacteremia, or severe pneumonia.

         10. Active autoimmune diseases that require systemic treatment (i.e. with use of disease
             modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive drugs).

         11. History of recent diagnosis of hypothyroidism for which replacement therapy (eg.,
             thyroxine) and blood endocrine profile are not stabilized yet.

         12. Established diagnosis of diabetes mellitus type I or diabetes mellitus type II that
             requires pharmacological treatment (including, but not limited to, insulin, insulin
             secretagogues and metformin).

         13. Severe impairment of the gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may alter
             the digestion and absorption of nutrients during the re-feeding phase (e.g. active
             ulcerative diseases of the stomach or intestine, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting,
             diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, or small bowel resection).

         14. Known history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection.

         15. Clinically significant heart disease and/or recent cardiac events including:

               -  history of angina pectoris, coronary artery bypass graft (CABG), symptomatic
                  pericarditis, or myocardial infarction within 12 months prior to the start of
                  study treatment;

               -  history of documented congestive heart failure (NYHA III-IV);

               -  documented cardiomyopathy.

         16. History of cardiac arythmias, (e.g. ventricular tachycardia, chronic atrial
             fibrillation), complete left bundle branch block, high grade AV block (e.g.
             bifascicular block, Mobitz type II and third degree AV block), supraventricular, nodal
             arrhythmias, or conduction abnormality in the previous 12 months.

         17. Uncontrolled hypertension defined by a Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) ≥ 160 mmHg and/or
             Diastolic Blood Pressure (DBP) ≥ 100 mmHg, with or without anti-hypertensive
             medication.

         18. Known reduction of left-ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) to less than 50%, as
             assessed by multigated radionuclide scintigraphic scan (MUGA) or echocardiography.

         19. Previous episodes of symptomatic hypotension causing unconsciousness.

         20. Baseline fasting plasma glucose ≤ 65 mg/dl.

         21. Ongoing therapy with systemic corticosteroids, or systemic corticosteroid therapy ≤ 2
             weeks before study enrollment, or who have not recovered from side effects of such
             treatment. The following uses of corticosteroids are permitted: topical applications
             (e.g. for rash), inhaled sprays (e.g. for obstructive airways diseases), eye drops.

         22. Any serious medical or psychiatric illness that in the assessment of the investigator
             renders the patient not suitable for participation in this clinical study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Filippo De Braud, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milan, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Filippo De Braud, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>0039 02/23902148</phone>
    <email>filippo.debraud@istitutotumori.mi.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Claudio Vernieri, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0039 02/23903066</phone>
    <email>claudio.vernieri@istitutotumori.mi.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <zip>20133</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanahan D, Weinberg RA. Hallmarks of cancer: the next generation. Cell. 2011 Mar 4;144(5):646-74. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2011.02.013. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21376230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vernieri C, Casola S, Foiani M, Pietrantonio F, de Braud F, Longo V. Targeting Cancer Metabolism: Dietary and Pharmacologic Interventions. Cancer Discov. 2016 Dec;6(12):1315-1333. Epub 2016 Nov 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27872127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vander Heiden MG, Cantley LC, Thompson CB. Understanding the Warburg effect: the metabolic requirements of cell proliferation. Science. 2009 May 22;324(5930):1029-33. doi: 10.1126/science.1160809. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19460998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Locasale JW, Grassian AR, Melman T, Lyssiotis CA, Mattaini KR, Bass AJ, Heffron G, Metallo CM, Muranen T, Sharfi H, Sasaki AT, Anastasiou D, Mullarky E, Vokes NI, Sasaki M, Beroukhim R, Stephanopoulos G, Ligon AH, Meyerson M, Richardson AL, Chin L, Wagner G, Asara JM, Brugge JS, Cantley LC, Vander Heiden MG. Phosphoglycerate dehydrogenase diverts glycolytic flux and contributes to oncogenesis. Nat Genet. 2011 Jul 31;43(9):869-74. doi: 10.1038/ng.890.</citation>
    <PMID>21804546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mankoff DA, Eary JF, Link JM, Muzi M, Rajendran JG, Spence AM, Krohn KA. Tumor-specific positron emission tomography imaging in patients: [18F] fluorodeoxyglucose and beyond. Clin Cancer Res. 2007 Jun 15;13(12):3460-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17575208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sullivan LB, Gui DY, Hosios AM, Bush LN, Freinkman E, Vander Heiden MG. Supporting Aspartate Biosynthesis Is an Essential Function of Respiration in Proliferating Cells. Cell. 2015 Jul 30;162(3):552-63. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2015.07.017.</citation>
    <PMID>26232225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menendez JA, Lupu R. Fatty acid synthase and the lipogenic phenotype in cancer pathogenesis. Nat Rev Cancer. 2007 Oct;7(10):763-77. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17882277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menendez JA, Vellon L, Mehmi I, Oza BP, Ropero S, Colomer R, Lupu R. Inhibition of fatty acid synthase (FAS) suppresses HER2/neu (erbB-2) oncogene overexpression in cancer cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2004 Jul 20;101(29):10715-20. Epub 2004 Jul 2.</citation>
    <PMID>15235125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang YA, Han WF, Morin PJ, Chrest FJ, Pizer ES. Activation of fatty acid synthesis during neoplastic transformation: role of mitogen-activated protein kinase and phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase. Exp Cell Res. 2002 Sep 10;279(1):80-90.</citation>
    <PMID>12213216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larkin J, Chiarion-Sileni V, Gonzalez R, Grob JJ, Cowey CL, Lao CD, Schadendorf D, Dummer R, Smylie M, Rutkowski P, Ferrucci PF, Hill A, Wagstaff J, Carlino MS, Haanen JB, Maio M, Marquez-Rodas I, McArthur GA, Ascierto PA, Long GV, Callahan MK, Postow MA, Grossmann K, Sznol M, Dreno B, Bastholt L, Yang A, Rollin LM, Horak C, Hodi FS, Wolchok JD. Combined Nivolumab and Ipilimumab or Monotherapy in Untreated Melanoma. N Engl J Med. 2015 Jul 2;373(1):23-34. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1504030. Epub 2015 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26027431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eggermont AM, Chiarion-Sileni V, Grob JJ, Dummer R, Wolchok JD, Schmidt H, Hamid O, Robert C, Ascierto PA, Richards JM, Lebbé C, Ferraresi V, Smylie M, Weber JS, Maio M, Bastholt L, Mortier L, Thomas L, Tahir S, Hauschild A, Hassel JC, Hodi FS, Taitt C, de Pril V, de Schaetzen G, Suciu S, Testori A. Prolonged Survival in Stage III Melanoma with Ipilimumab Adjuvant Therapy. N Engl J Med. 2016 Nov 10;375(19):1845-1855. Epub 2016 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>27717298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee C, Raffaghello L, Brandhorst S, Safdie FM, Bianchi G, Martin-Montalvo A, Pistoia V, Wei M, Hwang S, Merlino A, Emionite L, de Cabo R, Longo VD. Fasting cycles retard growth of tumors and sensitize a range of cancer cell types to chemotherapy. Sci Transl Med. 2012 Mar 7;4(124):124ra27. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3003293. Epub 2012 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22323820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brandhorst S, Wei M, Hwang S, Morgan TE, Longo VD. Short-term calorie and protein restriction provide partial protection from chemotoxicity but do not delay glioma progression. Exp Gerontol. 2013 Oct;48(10):1120-8. doi: 10.1016/j.exger.2013.02.016. Epub 2013 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23454633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee C, Safdie FM, Raffaghello L, Wei M, Madia F, Parrella E, Hwang D, Cohen P, Bianchi G, Longo VD. Reduced levels of IGF-I mediate differential protection of normal and cancer cells in response to fasting and improve chemotherapeutic index. Cancer Res. 2010 Feb 15;70(4):1564-72. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-3228. Epub 2010 Feb 9.</citation>
    <PMID>20145127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Safdie FM, Dorff T, Quinn D, Fontana L, Wei M, Lee C, Cohen P, Longo VD. Fasting and cancer treatment in humans: A case series report. Aging (Albany NY). 2009 Dec 31;1(12):988-1007.</citation>
    <PMID>20157582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Groot S, Vreeswijk MP, Welters MJ, Gravesteijn G, Boei JJ, Jochems A, Houtsma D, Putter H, van der Hoeven JJ, Nortier JW, Pijl H, Kroep JR. The effects of short-term fasting on tolerance to (neo) adjuvant chemotherapy in HER2-negative breast cancer patients: a randomized pilot study. BMC Cancer. 2015 Oct 5;15:652. doi: 10.1186/s12885-015-1663-5.</citation>
    <PMID>26438237</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dorff TB, Groshen S, Garcia A, Shah M, Tsao-Wei D, Pham H, Cheng CW, Brandhorst S, Cohen P, Wei M, Longo V, Quinn DI. Safety and feasibility of fasting in combination with platinum-based chemotherapy. BMC Cancer. 2016 Jun 10;16:360. doi: 10.1186/s12885-016-2370-6.</citation>
    <PMID>27282289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheng CW, Adams GB, Perin L, Wei M, Zhou X, Lam BS, Da Sacco S, Mirisola M, Quinn DI, Dorff TB, Kopchick JJ, Longo VD. Prolonged fasting reduces IGF-1/PKA to promote hematopoietic-stem-cell-based regeneration and reverse immunosuppression. Cell Stem Cell. 2014 Jun 5;14(6):810-23. doi: 10.1016/j.stem.2014.04.014. Erratum in: Cell Stem Cell. 2016 Feb 4;18(2):291-2.</citation>
    <PMID>24905167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brandhorst S, Choi IY, Wei M, Cheng CW, Sedrakyan S, Navarrete G, Dubeau L, Yap LP, Park R, Vinciguerra M, Di Biase S, Mirzaei H, Mirisola MG, Childress P, Ji L, Groshen S, Penna F, Odetti P, Perin L, Conti PS, Ikeno Y, Kennedy BK, Cohen P, Morgan TE, Dorff TB, Longo VD. A Periodic Diet that Mimics Fasting Promotes Multi-System Regeneration, Enhanced Cognitive Performance, and Healthspan. Cell Metab. 2015 Jul 7;22(1):86-99. doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2015.05.012. Epub 2015 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26094889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Biase S, Lee C, Brandhorst S, Manes B, Buono R, Cheng CW, Cacciottolo M, Martin-Montalvo A, de Cabo R, Wei M, Morgan TE, Longo VD. Fasting-Mimicking Diet Reduces HO-1 to Promote T Cell-Mediated Tumor Cytotoxicity. Cancer Cell. 2016 Jul 11;30(1):136-146. doi: 10.1016/j.ccell.2016.06.005.</citation>
    <PMID>27411588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milano</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Filippo de Braud</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Malignant</keyword>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Fasting Mimicking Diet (FMD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunity</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolic Effects</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunological Effects</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

