<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03459599</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-1016-31034</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03459599</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Antibiotic Prophylaxis in Ragged Placental Membranes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Antibiotic Prophylaxis in Ragged Placental Membranes: A Prospective, Multicenter, Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sarawak General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Malaysia Sarawak</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sarawak General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In some centres, women are routinely given a course of antibiotics postnatally if ragged
      placental membranes were present at delivery. The investigators examined the necessity such
      an intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postpartum endometritis resulting in sepsis remain one of the leading cause of maternal
      mortality in developing countries. Ragged placental membrane is a risk factor for
      endometritis and is not infrequently encountered. Several hospitals in Malaysia, largely
      those geographically-removed currently practice administering prophylactic antibiotics for
      women with ragged placental membranes. The aim is to reduce the risk of postpartum
      endometritis in a subgroup of women who may present in dire straits. The investigators sought
      to examine the necessity of such protocols.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postpartum endometritis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Postpartum endometritis is defined as follows, when presenting anytime within 6 weeks postpartum
Fever (Axillary temperature &gt; 37.5 degrees Celcius on 2 or more occasions at least 1 hour apart or temperature &gt; 38 degrees Celcius on one occasion), occurring in the absence of apparent source of infection or alternative foci of infection.
Increasing lochia loss or offensive lochia.
Lower abdominal pain or suprapubic tenderness on palpation.
The diagnosis is further supported by the following:
Elevated total white cell count &gt; 11.0 x 109 cells/L
Positive genital swab culture.
Incidence is calculated as follows:
Number of patients diagnosed with endometritis in each arm/total number of patients allocated to each arm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU admission rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>ICU admission as a result of endometritis. It is measured as follows:
a. ICU admission rate in prophylactic antibiotic group= (Number of patients requiring ICU admissions and given antibiotic prophylaxis, regardless of duration/total number of patients given antibiotics prophylaxis )
a. ICU admission rate in &quot;no prophylaxis&quot; group
= (Number of patients requiring ICU admissions and NOT given antibiotic prophylaxis, regardless of duration/total number of patients NOT given antibiotics prophylaxis)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of surgical evacuation of retained products of conception</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Surgical procedure required as a result of ragged placental membrane or its complications. It is calculated as follows
Surgical evacuation of retained products of conception in prophylaxis group= (Number of patients requiring surgical procedure and given antibiotic prophylaxis, regardless of duration/total number of patients given antibiotics prophylaxis )
Surgical evacuation of retained products of conception in &quot;no prophylaxis&quot; group= (Number of patients requiring surgical procedure and NOT given antibiotic prophylaxis, regardless of duration/total number of patients NOT given antibiotics prophylaxis )</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Blood transfusion</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Pack cell transfusion required as secondary to a complication from ragged placental membranes. This can be due to postpartum endometritis or surgical evacuation. It is calculated based on the number of patients requiring transfusion. The number of pack cells required per patient would be also be described.
Blood transfusion in prophylaxis group= (Number of patients requiring pack cell transfusion and given antibiotic prophylaxis, regardless of duration/total number of patients given antibiotics prophylaxis )
Blood transfusion in &quot;no prophylaxis group&quot;= (Number of patients requiring pack cell transfusion and were NOT given antibiotic prophylaxis, regardless of duration/total number of patients NOT given antibiotics prophylaxis )</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">716</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometritis Postpartum</condition>
  <condition>Endometritis</condition>
  <condition>Membranes; Retained</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylaxis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Current protocol of administering antibiotics maintained</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No prophylaxis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Antibiotics withheld, with appropriate observation and follow up</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prophylactic antibiotics</intervention_name>
    <description>Amox-clav given to eligible women as per existing protocol, which is 625mg three times a day, for a week</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylaxis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Amox-clav given as per protocol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No prophylaxis (Amox-clav withheld)</intervention_name>
    <description>Withholding Amox-clav, which is the current local practice for women with ragged placental membranes. This was replaced with appropriate counselling on signs and symptoms of endometritis, when and where women should present if the symptoms above occur. A follow up phone call was performed at 2 weeks and 6 weeks postpartum to ascertain well-being of patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>No prophylaxis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Expectant management</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All women who delivered vaginally beyond 24+0 weeks of gestation and were found to have
        ragged or retained placental membranes immediately after the third stage of labour were
        invited to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Fever, within 5 days preceding delivery (Axillary temperature &gt; 37.5oC on 2 or more
             occasions at least 1 hour apart or temperature &gt; 38oC on one occasion). This also
             includes intrapartum fever.

          2. Required oral or intravenous antibiotics for any other obstetric-related (ex. third or
             fourth degree tears, preterm prelabour rupture of membranes) or non- obstetric related
             (ex. pneumonia, acute pyelonephritis) reasons

          3. Prolonged rupture of membrane (&gt;18 hours)

          4. Retroviral disease, on long term oral or parenteral steroid or receiving other forms
             of immunosuppressants, including chemotherapy within the last one year.

          5. Vaginal delivery for an intrauterine death

          6. Penicillin allergy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hian Yan Voon, MRCOG</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sarawak General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meaney-Delman D, Bartlett LA, Gravett MG, Jamieson DJ. Oral and intramuscular treatment options for early postpartum endometritis in low-resource settings: a systematic review. Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Apr;125(4):789-800. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0000000000000732. Review. Erratum in: Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Aug;126(2):452-3.</citation>
    <PMID>25751198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newton ER, Prihoda TJ, Gibbs RS. A clinical and microbiologic analysis of risk factors for puerperal endometritis. Obstet Gynecol. 1990 Mar;75(3 Pt 1):402-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2406660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Schalkwyk J, Van Eyk N; INFECTIOUS DISEASES COMMITTEE. Antibiotic prophylaxis in obstetric procedures. J Obstet Gynaecol Can. 2010 Sep;32(9):878-884. doi: 10.1016/S1701-2163(16)34662-X. Review. English, French.</citation>
    <PMID>21050523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chongsomchai C, Lumbiganon P, Laopaiboon M. Prophylactic antibiotics for manual removal of retained placenta in vaginal birth. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Oct 20;(10):CD004904. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004904.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25327508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chibueze EC, Parsons AJ, Ota E, Swa T, Oladapo OT, Mori R. Prophylactic antibiotics for manual removal of retained placenta during vaginal birth: a systematic review of observational studies and meta-analysis. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2015 Nov 26;15:313. doi: 10.1186/s12884-015-0752-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26610697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernandez H, Gagnepain A, Bourget P, Peray P, Frydman R, Papiernik E, Daures JP. Antibiotic prophylaxis against postpartum endometritis after vaginal delivery: a prospective randomized comparison between Amox-CA (Augmentin) and abstention. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 1993 Aug;50(3):169-75.</citation>
    <PMID>8262292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sarawak General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Voon Hian Yan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Antibiotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Endometritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Placental membranes</keyword>
  <keyword>Prophylaxis</keyword>
  <keyword>Ragged membranes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amoxicillin-Potassium Clavulanate Combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

