<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03452332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-0548</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03452332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stereotactic Ablative Radiotherapy (SABR) in Combination With Durvalumab and Tremelimumab in Patients With Cervical, Vaginal, or Vulvar Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Multi-Center Study of Stereotactic Ablative Radiotherapy (SABR) in Combination With Durvalumab and Tremelimumab in Patients With Recurrent/Metastatic Advanced Cervical, Vaginal, or Vulvar Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if it is safe to give a special type of
      radiation called stereotactic ablative radiotherapy (SABR) in combination with durvalumab and
      tremelimumab to patients with advanced forms of cervical, vaginal, or vulvar cancer that is
      recurrent (has returned after treatment) and/or metastatic (has spread). Researchers also
      want to learn if this combination can help to control the disease.

      SABR is a type of radiation commonly used to treat various types of cancer with larger doses
      of radiation focused precisely at the tumor.

      This is an investigational study. Durvalumab is FDA approved for the treatment of urothelial
      cancer. Tremelimumab is not FDA approved or commercially available. The use of these drugs in
      combination with SABR is investigational. SABR is delivered using FDA-approved and
      commercially available methods.

      The study doctor can describe how the study drugs and radiation are designed to work.

      Up to 18 patients will enroll in this multi-center study. Up to 9 will take part at MD
      Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug and Radiation Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study and agree, you will receive
      durvalumab and tremelimumab in 4-week study cycles. You will receive tremelimumab by vein
      over about 1 hour on Day 1 of Cycles 1-4. You will receive durvalumab by vein over about 1
      hour on Day 1 of every cycle (about 1 hour after the end of the tremelimumab dose during
      Cycles 1-4).

      On Days 8, 10, and 12 of Cycle 1, you will also receive SABR over about 30-45 minutes each
      time.

      Length of Study:

      While you will only receive SABR during 1 cycle and tremelimumab over 4 cycles, you may
      continue to receive durvalumab for up to 8 cycles. You will no longer be able to receive the
      study drug(s) if the disease gets worse, if intolerable side effects occur, or if you are
      unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after the follow-up visits.

      Study Visits:

      On Day 1 of each Cycle:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests. At Cycles 1 and 4, this
           sample will also be used for biomarker testing.

      On Day 8 of Cycle 1, blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine and biomarker
      testing.

      On Day 15 of Cycles 1-4, blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      Every 8 weeks, you will have the same imaging scans you had at screening to check the status
      of the disease.

      Follow-Up:

      Every month for 12 months after radiation, you will may receive a call from or meet with a
      study team member to check on your side effects from radiation. Each call should last about
      15 minutes.

      About 30 days after your last dose of durvalumab:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests. If you can become pregnant,
           part of this sample will be used for a pregnancy test or urine may be collected.

      About 2 and 3 months after your last dose of durvalumab, blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be
      drawn for routine tests.

      Every 8 weeks during the follow up period, you will have the same imaging scans you had at
      screening to check the status of the disease.

      Every 2 months until it has been 12 months after your last dose of durvalumab, then every 6
      months after that, you will be called and asked about how you are doing. This call should
      take about 15 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Assessed Based on Dose Limiting Toxicities (DLTs) Based on Adverse Events (AEs) Assessed by NCI CTCAE v 4.03.)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 8 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Response Rate Measured by Tumor Response Based on RECIST Criteria v 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Defined as Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) by RECIST v1.1.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival Defined as the Time From the Start of Therapy to First Documented Disease Progression or Death From Any Cause</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival Defined as the Time From Start of Therapy to Death From any Cause.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Next Treatment (TTNT) Defined as the Time From the End of Immune-Checkpoint Inhibition Treatment on this Study to Institution of Next Therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasms of Female Genital Organs</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Vaginal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Vulvar Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Durvalumab + Tremelimumab + SABR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive Tremelimumab by vein over about 1 hour on Day 1 of Cycles 1-4. Participants receive Durvalumab by vein over about 1 hour on Day 1 of every cycle (about 1 hour after the end of the Tremelimumab dose during Cycles 1-4).
On Days 8, 10, and 12 of Cycle 1, participants also receive SABR over about 30-45 minutes each time.
Participants only receive SABR during cycle 1 and Tremelimumab over 4 cycles. Participants may continue to receive Durvalumab for up to 8 cycles.
Study conducted in 4 week cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Durvalumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Durvalumab 1500 mg by vein over about 1 hour on Day 1 of every cycle (about 1 hour after the end of the Tremelimumab dose during Cycles 1-4).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Durvalumab + Tremelimumab + SABR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MEDI4736</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tremelimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Tremelimumab 75 mg by vein given 1 week (+/- 3 days) prior to SABR then every 4 weeks for 4 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Durvalumab + Tremelimumab + SABR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ticilimumab</other_name>
    <other_name>CP-675,206</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stereotactic Ablative Radiotherapy (SABR)</intervention_name>
    <description>SABR administered during cycle 1, day 7 +/- 3 days. SABR given in 3 fractions, every other day, to a total dose of 24 Gy (8 Gy per fraction x 3 fractions) completed within one week and targeted to the largest easily accessible metastases.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Durvalumab + Tremelimumab + SABR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Radiation therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent obtained from subject prior to any protocol related
             procedures

          2. Adult female subjects (age 18 years or older) at time of study entry.

          3. Performance status ECOG 0-1

          4. Body weight &gt;30 kg

          5. Must have an average life expectancy of 6 months.

          6. Patient is able and willing to comply with protocol and study procedures for the
             duration of the study including undergoing treatment and scheduled visits and
             examinations including follow-up visits.

          7. Histological diagnosis of recurrent or metastatic cervical, vaginal, or vulvar cancer

          8. Metastatic disease in at least two distinct lesions (including the index lesion to be
             treated) with at least one site outside of the radiation field and evaluable by RECIST
             criteria for evaluation of response.

          9. At least one index lesion to be treated measuring 1-7 cm amenable to hypofractionated
             radiation therapy.

         10. Staging CT scans done prior to enrollment.

         11. Have had at least one line of prior platinum-based systemic chemotherapy once
             diagnosed with recurrence or metastatic disease.

         12. May have received 1 prior biologic regimen (i.e. avastin) but not within 4 weeks of
             enrollment.

         13. Full recovery from the acute effects of prior treatments, defined as effects having
             resolved to NCI CTCAE v4.03 Grade 0 or 1 with the exception of alopecia and certain
             laboratory values as outlined below. Subjects with irreversible toxicity that is not
             reasonably expected to be exacerbated by Durvalumab and Tremelimumab may be included
             (e.g., hearing loss, neuropathy) upon approval of the PI.

         14. In patients with central nervous system (CNS) metastases, metastases must be
             asymptomatic at the time of Day 1 of the study and meet the following criteria: (a)
             Brain metastases should have been treated with either WBRT, SRS/Gamma-knife, or
             surgical resection; (b) At least 28 days without progression of CNS metastases as
             evidenced by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) from last
             day of treatment with radiation to the CNS metastases; (c) At least 3 months from
             surgical resection (if had surgery) with stability on MRI brain at enrollment; (d) At
             least 14 days since last dose of corticosteroids; (e) Must not have leptomeningeal
             disease or cord compression

         15. Adequate hepatic and renal function documented within 3 weeks prior to initial
             treatment based on: (a) Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase
             (ALT) &lt;/= 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN). For subjects with liver metastasis, ALT
             and AST &lt;/= 5 x ULN; (b) Total bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5 x ULN except in patients with
             documented Gilbert's syndrome or liver metastasis, who must have a baseline total
             bilirubin ≤ 3.0 mg/dl; (c) Serum creatinine CL&gt;40 mL/min by the Cockcroft-Gault
             formula (Cockcroft and Gault 1976) or by 24-hour urine collection for determination of
             creatinine clearance: Females: CreatinineCL (mL/min) = [(Weight (kg) x (140-Age)) /
             (72 * serum creatinine (mg/dl)) ] * 0.85

         16. Negative screening test results for hepatitis B, hepatitis C, and human
             immunodeficiency virus

         17. Adequate hematological function documented prior to initial treatment based on: (a)
             Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;/= 1,500 cells/ul without growth factor support; (b)
             Hemoglobin &gt;/= 9 g/dL; (c) Platelet count &gt;/= 100,000 platelets/ul

         18. Subjects must either be of non-reproductive potential (ie, post-menopausal by history;
             OR history of hysterectomy, OR History of bilateral tubal ligation, OR History of
             bilateral oophorectomy) or must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test upon
             study entry. Women will be considered post-menopausal if they have been amenorrheic
             for 12 months without an alternative medical cause. The following age-specific
             requirements apply:

         19. Continued: (a) Women &lt;50 years of age would be considered post-menopausal if they have
             been amenorrheic for 12 months or more following cessation of exogenous hormonal
             treatments and if they have luteinizing hormone and follicle-stimulating hormone
             levels in the post-menopausal range for the institution or underwent surgical
             sterilization (bilateral oophorectomy or hysterectomy); (b) Women &gt;/= 50 years of age
             would be considered post-menopausal if they have been amenorrheic for 12 months or
             more following cessation of all exogenous hormonal treatments, had radiation-induced
             menopause with last menses &gt; 1 year ago, had chemotherapy-induced menopause with last
             menses &gt; 1 year ago, or underwent surgical sterilization (bilateral oophorectomy,
             bilateral salpingectomy or hysterectomy).

         20. Females of childbearing potential who are sexually active with a nonsterilized male
             partner must use highly effective method of contraception from the time of screening,
             and must agree to continue using such precautions for 180 days after the final dose of
             Durvalumab and Tremelimumab. Cessation of contraception after this point should be
             discussed with a responsible physician. They must also refrain from egg cell donation
             for 180 days after the final dose of Durvalumab and Tremelimumab. Note: A highly
             effective method of contraception is defined as one that results in a low failure rate
             (i.e., less than 1% per year) when used consistently and correctly. The acceptable
             methods of contraception include barrier methods (male condom plus spermicide, Copper
             T intrauterine device, Levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system) or hormonal
             methods (implants, hormone shot or injection, combined pill, minipill, patch).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Involvement in the planning and/or conduct of the study.

          2. Previous enrollment in the present study

          3. Female patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding or male or female patients of
             reproductive potential who are not willing to employ effective birth control from
             screening to 90 days after the last dose of durvalumab monotherapy or180 days after
             the last dose of durvalumab + tremelimumab combination therapy

          4. Received more than 2 prior systemic chemotherapy regimens, including adjuvant systemic
             chemotherapy following definitive chemoradiation (OUTBACK chemotherapy). Concurrent
             chemotherapy with prior radiation treatment is not to be counted

          5. Prior treatment with an anti-CTLA-4, including tremelimumab PD-1 or PD-L1 inhibitor,
             including durvalumab.

          6. Prior oncology vaccine therapy

          7. Prior radiation treatment to the index lesion to be treated.

          8. Prior radiation which overlaps and precludes hypofractionated treatment to the index
             lesion.

          9. Treatment with other investigational agent within 4 weeks to the first dose of
             Tremelimumab or Durvalumab

         10. Concomitant therapy with any of the following: IL-2, interferon, or other non-study
             immunotherapy regimens; cytotoxic chemotherapy; immunosuppressive agents; other
             investigational therapies; all such therapies must have been discontinued &gt; 4weeks.

         11. Any unresolved toxicity (CTCAE grade &lt;2) from previous anti-cancer therapy. (Subjects
             with irreversible toxicity that is not reasonably expected to be exacerbated by the
             investigational product may be included (e.g., hearing loss, peripherally neuropathy)

         12. Any prior Grade &gt;/= 3 immune-related adverse event (imAE) while receiving any previous
             immunotherapy agent, or any unresolved imAE &gt; Grade 1

         13. Treatment with a VEGF inhibitor within the last 6 weeks.

         14. Major surgical procedure (as defined by the treating physician) within 28 days prior
             to the first dose of Durvalumab and Tremelimumab or still recovering from prior
             surgery

         15. Active cardiac disease defined as unstable angina, uncontrolled hypertension,
             myocardial infarction in the last six months (unless successfully treated with CABG or
             PTCA), uncontrolled arrhythmia, or symptomatic congestive heart failure; &gt; 3
             heart-related hospitalizations in the past year.

         16. Mean QT interval corrected for heart rate (QTc) &gt;/= 470 ms calculated from 3
             electrocardiograms (ECGs) using Fredericia's Correction.

         17. Severe COPD requiring &gt; 3 hospitalizations in the past year

         18. Active or prior documented autoimmune or inflammatory disorders (including
             inflammatory bowel disease [eg, colitis or Crohn's disease], diverticulitis [with the
             exception of diverticulosis], systemic lupus erythematosus, Sarcoidosis syndrome, or
             Wegener syndrome [granulomatosis with polyangiitis, Graves' disease, rheumatoid
             arthritis, hypophysitis, uveitis, etc]). The following are exceptions to this
             criterion: (a) Patients with vitiligo or alopecia; (b) Patients with hypothyroidism
             (eg, following Hashimoto syndrome) stable on hormone replacement; (c) Any chronic skin
             condition that does not require systemic therapy; (d) Patients without active disease
             in the last 5 years may be included but only after consultation with the study
             physician; (e) Patients with celiac disease controlled by diet alone

         19. Active or prior documented interstitial lung disease

         20. Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 14 days before the first
             dose of Durvalumab and Tremelimumab with the exceptions of intranasal and inhaled
             corticosteroids, systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses not to exceed 10 mg/day
             of prednisone or equivalent, or steroids used transiently to control contrast agent
             allergies for radiographic studies.

         21. History of allogeneic organ transplant

         22. History of hypersensitivity to durvalumab or Tremelimumab or any CTLA4, PD1, or PDL-1
             inhibitor.

         23. Receipt of live attenuated vaccination within 30 days prior to study entry or within
             30 days of receiving durvalumab or tremelimumab

         24. Active infection including tuberculosis (clinical evaluation that includes clinical
             history, physical examination and radiographic findings, and TB testing in line with
             local practice), hepatitis B (known positive HBV surface antigen (HBsAg) result),
             hepatitis C, or human immunodeficiency virus (positive HIV 1/2 antibodies). Patients
             with a past or resolved HBV infection (defined as the presence of hepatitis B core
             antibody [anti-HBc] and absence of HBsAg) are eligible. Patients positive for
             hepatitis C (HCV) antibody are eligible only if polymerase chain reaction is negative
             for HCV RNA

         25. History of prior bowel fistula, ulcerations, or perforations.

         26. Evidence of progressive or symptomatic central nervous system (CNS) metastases or
             leptomeningeal disease.

         27. Uncontrolled inter-current illness, including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection requiring systemic treatment, current or history of prior radiation induced
             pneumonitis, interstitial lung disease, or psychiatric illness/social situations that
             would limit compliance with study requirement or compromise the ability of the subject
             to give written informed consent.

         28. Other active invasive malignancy. History of non-invasive malignancies such as ductal
             carcinoma in situ of the breast, non-melanomatous carcinoma of the skin, is allowed,
             as is history of other invasive malignancy that is in remission for &gt;/= 5 years after
             treatment with curative intent.

         29. Any medical, psychological, or social condition that, in the opinion of the treating
             physician would interfere with evaluation of the investigational product or
             interpretation of subject safety or study results
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lilie L. Lin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lilie L. Lin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-563-2300</phone>
    <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Research Operations</last_name>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malignant neoplasms of female genital organs</keyword>
  <keyword>Cervical Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaginal Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Vulvar Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Durvalumab</keyword>
  <keyword>MEDI4736</keyword>
  <keyword>Tremelimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Ticilimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>CP-675,206</keyword>
  <keyword>Stereotactic Ablative Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>SABR</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vulvar Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vaginal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Genital Neoplasms, Female</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tremelimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

