<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03450421</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ABS-03UE-2014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03450421</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Actamax™Adhesion Barrier in Women Undergoing Laparoscopic Abdominopelvic Surgery/Myomectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Multi-Center Study to Assess the Safety and Efficacy of Actamax™ Adhesion Barrier in Women Undergoing Laparoscopic Abdominopelvic Surgery With a Myomectomy Followed by Second Look Laparoscopy (SLL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Actamax Surgical Materials LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Actamax Surgical Materials LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Women undergoing laparoscopic abdominopelvic surgery with a planned, second look laparoscopy
      within 8-12 (+4) weeks will be enrolled. All subjects must undergo myomectomy with/without
      treatment of co-existing pathology e.g. (+/-) adhesions and/or (+/-) endometriosis, and/or
      (+/-) adenomyosis, and/or (+/-) ovarian cyst(s). The value of the second look laparoscopy
      (SLL) must be confirmed by the investigator to be of clinical benefit to the subject. The
      subject must be desirous of future fertility and willing to undergo the SLL to assess whether
      pathology (e.g. adnexal adhesions or endometriosis) exists which could be treated with a goal
      of improving their likelihood of conceiving and progressing to full term.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adhesion Free at Sites of Surgery at SLL</measure>
    <time_frame>8-12 weeks postoperatively but out to 16 weeks where circumstances require (vacations, etc.)</time_frame>
    <description>The primary efficacy outcome measure will be being adhesion free at sites of surgery throughout the whole abdominopelvic cavity at SLL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">152</enrollment>
  <condition>Uterine Fibroid</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Actamax™Adhesion Barrier</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following Myomectomy, subjects randomized to the Actamax™Adhesion Barrier Arm will have up to 30mL of product applied to all sites of surgery (area of treatment/trauma).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Myomectomy will be performed with no adhesion barrier application.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Actamax™Adhesion Barrier</intervention_name>
    <description>Actamax™Adhesion Barrier is a degradable hydrogel to be sprayed directly on surgically traumatized tissue. The aim of using the Actamax™ Adhesion Barrier (AB) in this way is to allow damaged and apposing tissue surfaces the opportunity to heal separately without becoming abnormally attached.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Actamax™Adhesion Barrier</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Preoperative Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Understand and be able to follow the requirements of the protocol including personally
             signing and dating an IRB approved Informed Consent Form prior to undergoing any
             protocol related procedures,

          -  Be a premenopausal female, &gt; 18 and &lt; 44 years old,

          -  Be thought to have uterine fibroids requiring laparoscopic abdominopelvic surgery that
             will require a &gt; 3 cm posterior uterine incision (including repeat myomectomy/previous
             uterine artery embolization for fibroid), and/or +/- adhesions, and/or +/-
             endometriosis, and/or +/- adenomyosis and/or ovarian cyst(s),

          -  Wish to retain her fertility and be considered to clinically benefit from a SLL, in
             the investigator's opinion,

          -  Have a willingness to undergo a second look laparoscopy if surgeon considers it
             clinically beneficial to the subject,

          -  Have a negative pregnancy test within 5 days of surgery,

          -  Agree to avoid pregnancy using adequate forms of contraception (oral contraceptive
             pill, condom, no sexual intercourse), and is aware and agrees to avoid pregnancy for a
             minimum of 12 weeks or to SLL (whichever is greater) to allow for healing of the
             uterine scar following myomectomy,

          -  Is willing, able and likely to fully comply with study procedures and restrictions
             including follow-up,

          -  Be in good health including an ASA (American Society of Anesthesiologists) score of 2
             or less,

          -  Have undergone a satisfactory physical and medical assessment with no clinically
             significant and relevant abnormalities.

        Intraoperative Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The subject underwent a laparoscopic myomectomy with at least (1) posterior uterine
             serosal incision of &gt; 3 cm in length,

          -  The subject meets all intraoperative inclusion/exclusion criteria prior to
             randomization,

        And

        • At the completion of the procedure, before randomization, the surgeon believes that the
        subject will clinically benefit from a second look laparoscopy to preserve fertility.

        Preoperative Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Are unable to give their own written informed consent,

          -  Have completed her family planning with no desire to maintain fertility,

          -  Are considered to have no potential clinical benefit from a second look laparoscopy,

          -  Are currently pregnant (including ectopic pregnancy),

          -  Are breastfeeding,

          -  Are within 6 weeks post-partum,

          -  Have received or are expected to receive another anti-adhesive treatment within 30
             days prior to enrollment or during enrollment up to adhesion evaluation at second look
             laparoscopy,

          -  Are currently or have been enrolled within the last 30 days in another interventional
             study.

          -  Have received or are expected to receive any other investigational product or
             technique within 30 days prior to or during enrollment,

          -  Have had cancer within 5 years of the initial surgery with the exception of basal cell
             carcinoma,

          -  Have known allergy to dextran, PEG, or FD&amp;C Blue #1,

          -  Have had bilateral salpingectomy,

          -  Have had a hysterectomy,

          -  Are scheduled to undergo concomitant non-gynecologic surgery,

          -  Have pre-operative imaging results with:

          -  Largest fibroid diameter &lt; 2 cm, or

          -  Largest intramural fibroid diameter &gt;10 cm, or

          -  More than 5 intramural fibroids with a diameter of &gt; 8 cm, and/or

          -  Adenomyoma &gt;10 cm.

          -  Have a history where it is expected that complete adhesiolysis will be impossible,

          -  Have clinically significant abnormal blood results,

          -  Have clinically relevant hemochromatosis, hepatic, renal, autoimmune, lymphatic,
             hematological or coagulation disorders,

          -  Have insulin dependent diabetes mellitus,

          -  Are receiving concurrent systemic corticosteroids, antineoplastic agents and/or
             radiation therapy,

          -  Have had previous abdominal or pelvic radiation therapy,

          -  Have active pelvic or abdominal infection, or other active infection with fever
             &gt;100°F/38°C,

          -  Have a known history of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA), HIV, HBV
             or HCV.

        Intraoperative Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have cancer detected at surgery,

          -  Are pregnant, including ectopic pregnancy,

          -  Have a non-gynecologic surgical procedure or entry into the bowel, bladder, or ureter,

          -  Have a hysterectomy or other gynecologic procedure that would render the subject
             unable to conceive,

          -  Have incomplete lysis of any pre-existing pathological adhesions,

          -  Have extensive enterolysis,

          -  Have incomplete surgical treatment of endometriosis,

          -  Receive the administration of a product that will interfere with the application of
             Actamax™ Adhesion Barrier,

          -  Receive the use of an approved or unapproved product or strategy for the purpose of
             preventing adhesion development,

          -  Receive fibrin glue, surgical sealant, or other hemostatic agent,

          -  Undergo an open procedure (other than mini laparotomy to remove fibroids),

          -  Undergo a posterior colpotomy,

          -  Undergo insufflation with a gas other than CO2,

          -  Undergo Laprolift or similar device for elevation of the abdominal wall, as an
             alternative to CO2 insufflation,

          -  Undergo abdominal cavity heating, humidification or oxygenation,

          -  Receive irrigants containing, glucocorticoids, antihistamines, heparin or antiseptic
             additives,

          -  Have any instillates left at the end of surgery,

          -  Have a postoperative drain,

          -  Undergo laparoscopic myomectomy without at least one posterior uterine serosal
             incision of &gt; 3 cm in length,

          -  Undergo a diagnostic hysteroscopy or polypectomy or therapeutic hysteroscopy which
             includes any of the following:

               1. Undertaken during or following the laparoscopic myomectomy,

               2. Treatment of fibroids &gt;3 cm,

               3. Solution other than Lactated Ringer's Solution (LRS) used for uterine distention,

               4. Laparoscopic filming commenced after removal of LRS.

          -  If, in the opinion of the surgeon, subject would have no clinical benefit for a SLL.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>44 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Trudy Estridge</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Actamax Surgical Materials LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Trudy D Estridge, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>650-245-6561</phone>
    <email>trudy.estridge@actamax.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leiomyoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofibroma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

