<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03316365</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>06-785</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03316365</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Long-term Training Effects of Rhythmic Auditory Stimulation on Gait in Patients With Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Long-term Training Effects of Rhythmic Auditory Stimulation on Gait in Patients With Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Poudre Valley Health System Fort Collins CO</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Colorado State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Falls are common among patients with Parkinson's Disease (PD) and are the biggest
      contributors to loss of independent living, long-term institutionalization, and increased
      mortality.

      The purpose of this study was to explore whether an at-home based Rhythmic Auditory
      Stimulation (RAS) gait training program will decrease the number of falls in persons with PD
      with a history of falling. We also evaluated changes in clinical and kinematic parameters
      used to assess fall risk in this population.

      Sixty participants diagnosed with idiopathic PD with at least 2 falls in the past 12 months,
      were randomly allocated into two groups. The experimental group trained daily with RAS for 24
      weeks. The control group also trained daily with RAS, but discontinued training between weeks
      8 and 16. During treatment patients walked for 30 minutes in a home based environment with
      metronome-click embedded music. Changes in clinical and kinematic parameters were assessed at
      baseline, weeks 8, 16, and 24.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 14, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 13, 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 13, 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Home training instructions were provided by a certified physical therapist and board-certified neurologic music therapist blinded to treatment allocation of the subjects.
The TUG and the BBS were administered by an experienced physical therapist blinded to the study design.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fall Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Change of the number of fall incidents and severity from baseline assessed by the Fall Index 8 weeks, 16 weeks, and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The Fall Index was computed based on self-reports by subjects or caregivers and classified as 1 (incomplete fall, lost balance but stabilized by another person or object), 2 (complete fall, no injuries) or 3 (complete fall, injury, medical attention required). A complete fall was defined as unintentionally coming to the ground with any body part above ankle. Higher Fall Index values indicate higher incidence of falls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls Efficacy Scale (FES)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in level of concern about falling from baseline assessed by Fear of the Falling Questionnaire/Short FES-1 at 8 weeks, 16 weeks, and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Falls Efficacy Scale (FES) (Tinetti et al 1990) is a 10-item scale to assess fear of falling in older persons. Individuals are asked to rate, on a 10-point scale with zero corresponding to not at all and 10 to completely, how confident he or she felt in performing 10 activities. The scores are added up to calculate a total score that ranges from 0 to 100. Higher scores indicate more confidence/less fear.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Berg Balance Scale (BBS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in balance from baseline assessed by Berg Balance Scale at 8 weeks, 16 weeks, and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 14 item list with each item consisting of a five-point ordinal scale ranging from 0 to 4, with 0 indicating the lowest level of function and 4 the highest level of function, and the final measure is the sum of all of the scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed Up and Go (TUG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in balance and function from baseline assessed by Timed Up and Go at 8 weeks, 16 weeks, and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of function (rise from a chair, walk three meters, turn around, walk back to the chair, and sit down) with correlates to balance and fall risk. A faster time indicates a better functional performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in gait from baseline at 8 weeks, 16 weeks, and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of gait parameters (velocity, stride length, cadence, ankle dorsiflexion) with a computerized stride analyzer system (B&amp;L Engineering).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Continuous Rhythmic Auditory Stimulation</condition>
  <condition>Intermittent Rhythmic Auditory Stimulation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous RAS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental group (continuous treatment) trained daily with RAS for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intermittent RAS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group (intermittent treatment) trained with RAS for 8 weeks, discontinued training for 8 weeks, and resumed training with RAS for 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rhythmic Auditory Stimulation (RAS)</intervention_name>
    <description>The experimental group (continuous treatment) trained daily with Rhythmic Auditory Stimulation (RAS) for 24 weeks. The control group (intermittent treatment) trained with RAS for 8 weeks, discontinued training for 8 weeks, and resumed training with RAS for 8 weeks. During treatment subjects walked for 30 minutes in a home-based environment with metronome-click embedded music downloaded to an MP3 player and listened to either free-field or via headphones. For the first 8 weeks subjects had 3 metronome rates available to choose from: 100, 105, and 110% of internal usual cadence. During the second 8 weeks available rates were 105, 110 and 115%; and during the last 8 weeks 110, 115, 120%. The control group started their last training segment at 105, 110, and 115%, but could request a change to the faster rates if comfortable.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous RAS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intermittent RAS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neurologic Music Therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hoehn &amp; Yahr (HY) stage III or IV

          -  At least 2 falls in the past 12 months

          -  Stable antiparkinsonian medication regime

          -  Ability to ambulate independently for at least 50 m.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other neurological or orthopedic conditions

          -  Medically diagnosed hearing loss

          -  Dementia (Mini Mental Status Exam score &lt; 24).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Thaut, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Toronto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael H. Thaut</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD will not be made available to external researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

