<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03317990</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>220262</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03317990</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Effects of Frozen Section Technology on Oncological and Functional Outcomes at Radical Prostatectomy.</brief_title>
  <acronym>NSAFEPROOF</acronym>
  <official_title>A Study to Evaluate the Feasibility of a Multicentre Randomised Controlled Trial of Frozen Section Technology to Improve Oncological and Functional Outcomes at Robotic Radical Prostatectomy.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cambridge University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>North Bristol NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer is common but can commonly be cured with surgery, however, this often leads
      to a loss of erections, because the nerves controlling erections run in the outer coverings
      of the prostate. Nerve sparing, where the outer layers of the prostate are peeled off,
      increases post-operative potency, but also increases the risk of cancer being left behind and
      the need for radiotherapy, which renders the men impotent, even if they had nerve sparing
      surgery. A new technique called NeuroSAFE incorporates an additional safety check designed to
      promote nerve sparing without compromising cancer control. During surgery, a pathologist
      examines the prostate near the nerves to check for exposed cancer. If cancer is found, the
      nerve tissue is removed so the recurrence risk is similar to when cancer cells are not
      exposed. The investigators eventual aim is to perform a large scale RCT comparing NeuroSAFE
      with current UK practice (nerve sparing based on MRI scan, biopsy results and clinical
      examination). This application is to fund a feasibility study to ensure that men are prepared
      to be randomised within an RCT, and that the technique can be taught to other UK centres, so
      allowing participation in the multi-centre RCT. The investigators will gather data to allow
      us to plan the larger study by defining the primary outcome measure and powering the study
      based on the size and confidence interval of observed effects. This study is needed because
      with evidence supporting observation of low risk small cancers, a higher proportion of men
      undergoing surgery have capsular involvement. The investigators do not have a reliable way to
      detect cancer which has spread through the capsule of the prostate in whom nerve sparing
      would cause a positive surgical margin. The NeuroSAFE technique addresses this need and will
      only be available at participating centres through this trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Localised prostate cancer is usually curable with surgery. Surgery often entails side effects
      of permanent impotence and temporary urinary incontinence. These side effects can be
      minimised by protecting the nerves that run in the outer layer of the prostate (nerve
      sparing), however this increases the risk of exposure of the underlying tumour (a positive
      surgical margin-PSM) and a need for extra treatment in the form of radiotherapy. PSMs are
      more likely to occur if the tumour is starting to grow out of the prostate (stage pT3a) and
      in areas where pT3a disease is suspected nerve sparing cannot safely be performed. At
      University College Hospital London (UCLH) the chance of a man being potent after radical
      prostatectomy is dependent on the amount of nervous tissue left behind. 80% of men in whom
      the nervous tissue is spared on both sides of the prostate would be expected to be able to
      get erections adequate for penetrative sexual intercourse using phosphodiesterase inhibitors
      (PDE5i's, viagra or similar). UK surgeons base a decision of whether to nerve spare or not on
      the degree of suspicion that pathological stage (pT) 3a disease is present, estimated from
      the patients prostate biopsies and MRI scan as well as a thorough clinical examination.

      Unfortunately, our ability to detect pT3a disease is limited. even with multiparametric
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), which is regarded as the best way to distinguish pT2 from
      pT3a disease resulting in uncertainty as to when nerve sparing is oncologically safe. In
      order to decrease this uncertainty a group from Germany have developed the NeuroSAFE
      technique, where after nerve sparing, a frozen section analysis of the area adjacent to the
      nerve spare, is performed, whilst the surgeon completes the rest of the operation, and if a
      PSM is detected the nerve tissue is then excised. NeuroSAFE has been shown in cohort studies
      to decrease PSM rate whilst promoting nerve sparing and potency. No level one data exist
      regarding the effectiveness of this technique.

      The German centre where the technique was developed now performs the technique on all cases
      meaning the opportunity to evaluate the technique in the setting of an RCT has been missed.
      The technique is only performed routinely in one NHS centre, Lister Hospital. The current
      situation provides a unique opportunity to fully evaluate the benefits of this technique for
      NHS patients. The proposed study, NeuroSAFE PROOF, is a multicentre RCT designed to compare
      short term oncological and functional outcomes after robotic radical prostatectomy with nerve
      sparing performed according to current UK practice (based on a perceived risk of pT3a disease
      from prostate biopsy, MRI and examination findings) with patients who have undergone the
      NeuroSAFE procedure. For the feasibility phase 50 patients will be randomised 1:1. A
      NeuroSAFE training academy will be established.

      The proposed study is to evaluate the potential benefit of a novel surgical technique for NHS
      patients before the procedure is taken up as it has been elsewhere and the opportunity to
      randomise/evaluate is lost.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Feasibility study. Parallel group, two-arm, randomised trial with 1:1 allocation ratio between nerve sparing guided by NeuroSAFE and current UK practice (guided by MRI, biopsy and clinical examination).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients and the research team collecting follow up data will be blinded as to whether the person has had NeuroSAFE procedure. The surgeon and pathologist cannot be blinded to this.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment rates</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Recruitment rates</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Study acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of eligible men accepting randomisation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short term oncological and functional outcome (compound outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of men who are potent and continent with undetectable PSA and negative surgical margins at 1 year post surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health economics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year from surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Short term - Cost of treatment for incontinence, impotence and adjuvant treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NeuroSAFE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>These patients will undergo robotic radical prostatectomy with bilateral nerve spare. The pathologist will remove the pre-painted surface of the gland (which had been in contact with the neurovascular bundles) using a sharp blade. The tissue sample will be snap frozen and embedded in OCT. Using a cryostat, 10 micron thick slices will be placed on slides. The entire length of the area of interest will be sampled in this way generating ≈10 frozen sections per side. The slides will be stained with H&amp;E and will be examined by a consultant pathologist . As soon as examination is complete the pathologist will telephone the operating surgeon to give the result. Presence of cancer cells at the margin of resection constitutes a positive margin and the neurovascular bundle on that side will be resected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>These patients will undergo robotic radical prostatectomy with a nerve sparing procedure based on surgical planning performed by a consultant radiologist. The mp-MRI will be reviewed by a consultant radiologist along with the details of the prostate biopsy and DRE a decision to perform unilateral, bilateral or non-nerve sparing will be established and recorded in the clinical record form (CRF) for each patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NeuroSAFE procedure</intervention_name>
    <description>When the prostate is removed from within the patient as it is disconnected from its attachments. The specimen will then be painted (right=blue, left =black) by the operating surgeon and delivered expediently to the pathologist who will perform frozen section analysis of the painted areas. The pathologist will remove the pre-painted surface of the gland (which had been in contact with the neurovascular bundles) using a sharp blade. The tissue sample will be snap frozen and embedded in OCT. If a positive margin is reported by the pathologist, the entire neurovascular bundle on the affected side will be removed and sent for formal pathological examination.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NeuroSAFE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Male life expectancy of &gt;10 years D'Amico intermediate or high risk (Prostate specific
        Antigen (PSA) &gt;= 10 , Gleason score &gt;= 7, clinical stage T2b-T3a) prostate cancer Opting to
        undergo Robot assisted Radical prostatectomy (RALP) Potent Continent of urine.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Unable to undergo RALP due to comorbidity (Glaucoma, previous Transient ischemic
        attack/cerebrovascular accident, Major abdominal surgery, morbid obesity - BMI&gt;35, Ischemic
        heart disease).

        Unable to give informed consent Impotence (IIEF score &lt;22) Unable to have an MRI
        (claustrophobia, metal implants)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Only males can develop prostate cancer</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Greg L Shaw, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University College, London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chris Brew - Graves, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>0207 679 9280</phone>
    <email>c.brew-graves@ucl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vasdev N, Agarwal S, Rai BP, Soosainathan A, Shaw G, Chang S, Prasad V, Mohan-S G, Adshead JM. Intraoperative Frozen Section of the Prostate Reduces the Risk of Positive Margin Whilst Ensuring Nerve Sparing in Patients with Intermediate and High-Risk Prostate Cancer Undergoing Robotic Radical Prostatectomy: First Reported UK Series. Curr Urol. 2016 May;9(2):93-103. doi: 10.1159/000442860. Epub 2016 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27390582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Beyer B, Schlomm T, Tennstedt P, Boehm K, Adam M, Schiffmann J, Sauter G, Wittmer C, Steuber T, Graefen M, Huland H, Haese A. A feasible and time-efficient adaptation of NeuroSAFE for da Vinci robot-assisted radical prostatectomy. Eur Urol. 2014 Jul;66(1):138-44. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2013.12.014. Epub 2013 Dec 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24411279</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Nerve sparing</keyword>
  <keyword>NeuroSAFE</keyword>
  <keyword>Frozen section</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All data will be anonymised at source. Only anonymised data will be shared.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

