<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03311204</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UNewSouthwales</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03311204</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Eyelid Margin Debridement on Contact Lens Discomfort</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect and Duration of Efficacy of Eyelid Margin Debridement on Signs and Secretions of Eyelids, Tear Film and Discomfort in Contact Lens Wearers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of New South Wales</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of New South Wales</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, clinical variables related to eyelids that potentially have an effect on
      contact lens discomfort will be investigated such as eyelid signs and secretions, eyelid
      sensitivity, eyelid microbiome, Demodex infestation and tear film properties. The main aim of
      this study is to understand the duration of efficacy of debridement of the eyelid margin and
      its impact on various eyelid signs (such as lid wiper epitheliopathy, lid-parallel
      conjunctival folds, eyelid sensitivity, meibomian gland morphology and meibum secretions,
      palpebral conjunctival reaction, eyelid microbiome and Demodex infestation, tear properties
      (both biophysical properties such as tear volume, tear meniscus height, tear evaporation,
      tear osmolarity and tear breakup time; and biochemical properties that are tear lipid
      analysis). To observe these variables, this study employs a cross-sectional design to study
      the effect of treatment at three instances, that is at baseline and two follow-up visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Contact lens discomfort (CLD) is a substantial problem experienced frequently by contact lens
      wearers and it is the primary factor associated with permanent discontinuation of lens wear.
      Studies report that between 43% and 72% of contact lens wearer's dropout due to discomfort.
      Reducing the number of contact lens (CL) patient dropouts has been a continuing challenge for
      eye care professionals. With more than 125 million contact lens wearers around the world,
      patient discontinuations can have a considerable economic impact on an eye care practice.

      Definition: Contact lens discomfort is a condition characterized by episodic or persistent
      adverse ocular sensations related to lens wear, either with or without visual disturbance,
      resulting from reduced compatibility between the contact lens and the ocular environment,
      which can lead to decreased wearing time and discontinuation of contact lens wear.

      Inferences from our earlier study (HC15119) showed that eyelid margin debridement
      significantly improves eyelid signs, tear film properties and comfort in contact lens
      wearers. But the previous study did not consider the duration of efficacy as the subjects
      were only followed up once after 7-10days from treatment. Observing subjects more frequently
      will help us understand the duration of efficacy of debridement therapy. Also, the previous
      study did not examine the biochemical changes to tear film lipids that are produced by the
      eyelids.

      We hypothesize that debridement of eyelid margins improves lipid secretions that then help to
      form a stable lipid layer over ocular surface, thereby improving the tear evaporation
      dynamics and comfort in contact lens wearers.

      Aim Aim of the study is to observe the duration of efficacy of debridement of the eyelid
      margins in improving secretions from eyelid glands and whether the debridement helps to form
      a stable tear film over ocular surface, thereby improving comfort in contact lens wearers.

      Objectives To determine the effect of BlephEx - debridement therapy (an in-office eyelid
      treatment) on eyelid signs and secretions, tear film and contact lens discomfort.

      To observe differences in discomfort in contact lens wearers To determine the duration of
      efficacy of BlephEx debridement therapy in contact lens wearers, by following up after 12-15
      days and 22-25days from the baseline (Treatment) visit.

      Methods

      The study employs cross-sectional study design, to observe the effect of treatment at three
      instances, one baseline (treatment) visit and two follow-up visits. At the baseline visit,
      informed consent will be obtained from the subjects and assessment of the study variables
      will be performed. Subjects will undergo treatment on the same day with BlephEx. At baseline,
      the measurements are performed prior to treatment to record preliminary scores and then
      treatment is performed. Subjects are asked to return to the clinic for follow-up visits
      during which no treatment will be performed, but variables are assessed to determine the
      difference from baseline measurements. The 2nd visit will be after 12 -16 days after the
      baseline visit. The last follow-up will be 22-26 days after the baseline visit. All study
      variables will be assessed during all three visits to the clinic.

      Treatment Procedure:

      BlephEx is an instrument that contains a handpiece used to spin a medical grade micro-sponge
      along the edge of eyelids and lashes that helps in removing scurf and debris from eyelids and
      helps in exfoliating the lids. A new micro-sponge will be used for every subject to avoid
      cross-contamination. This procedure lasts for 6-8 mins.

      Lid Hygenix, a commercially available formulated hypoallergenic foam cleanser will be used to
      moisten the BlephEx debridement tips.

      Both the products are commercially available. The procedure is safe, painless and regularly
      performed by optometrists.

      Study Procedures The study will be conducted in accordance with Declaration of Helsinki.

      Discomfort Rating:

      Discomfort will be measured using the CLDEQ-8 questionnaire that involves questions about
      subjects' experience of discomfort from past 2 weeks. This will be employed on all the study
      visits in the clinic.

      End of the day discomfort will be assessed using a visual analog scale, where questions will
      be posed to participants about their level of comfort with contact lens wear at a specific
      time of day. This questionnaire will be a web-based survey, sent in the form of an email on
      the day before the baseline visit, and day 4, 9, 14, 19 and 24 from baseline visit. Explained
      clearly in the flowchart for study visits.

      'Participant information sheet and informed consent' and 'web-based survey for the end of the
      day discomfort rating' will be sent out in the form of an email. Subjects who are interested
      in participation will respond to the survey and results will be used only after the subject
      signs the informed consent in the presence of the investigator, during the baseline visit.
      This survey response will be used as baseline data for the end of the day discomfort.

        -  The eyelids will be examined using a slit lamp before and after installation of sodium
           fluorescein. This stain helps to disclose changes to the eyelid surface.

        -  Lid Sensitivity: A Cochet Bonnet aesthesiometer will be used to assess the sensitivity
           thresholds of eyelids. This involves the use of a fine nylon thread to gently touch the
           eyelid. The thread length at which subject become aware of a sensation will be recorded.
           Subjects may feel nothing or a slight awareness of the thread on the eyelid.

        -  Confocal Microscopy: Highly magnified images of eyelids will be captured with a
           microscope. A lubricating tear gel will be placed in on the eye to enable the microscope
           probe to come into contact with eyelids and subject will be given an anesthetic drop to
           reduce any symptoms that may be associated with this procedure.

        -  Meibography: Meibomian gland (glands in eyelids) morphology will be studied using a
           non-contact meibographer which uses the infrared light source to observe and capture
           high-resolution images of meibomian glands.

        -  Lid Microbiota: Saline-moistened swabs will be gently rolled along the lid margin - and
           then sent to the microbiology laboratory for analysis of the types of microbes.

        -  Tear Osmolarity: An Ocusense TearLab osmometer will be used to measure tear osmolarity.
           The salt concentration of tears will be measured by collecting a very small amount of
           tears (less than a teardrop) from the lower eyelid using this sterile device.

        -  LipiView Interferometer: LipiView ocular surface interferometer measures the absolute
           thickness of the tear film lipid layer. It is an imaging device which uses infrared
           light to capture and store digital images of interferometric observations of the tear
           film which can be visually monitored and photographically documented.

        -  Phenol-Red Thread Test: The phenol-red thread will be used to assess the tear volume.
           The thread is inserted at lower eyelid margin and the subject asked to keep eyes open
           and blink normally for 15 seconds. The subject may feel a slight foreign body sensation
           when the thread is placed on the eye. The length of wetting of the thread is then
           measured after removal from the eye.

        -  Tear Evaporation: Evaporation rate of tears will be assessed using a vapometer. The
           vapometer is a portable non-invasive instrument used to assess the amount of tear
           evaporation based on an increase in relative humidity within a small chamber that is
           gently put around the eye.

        -  Tear Collection: Thin capillary micropipettes are placed at the temporal corner of the
           eye. Tears are then collected through capillary suction into the micropipettes and
           stored for further analysis.

        -  Meibum Collection: Meibomian glands at the eyelid margin secrete Meibum, that forms an
           important component of tear film that helps in preventing excessive evaporation of outer
           layer and maintains the stability of tears on the eye. Meibum will be collected using a
           sterile, single-use, golf spud by gently squeezing the eyelids against the eye, slightly
           everted outwards. Very minimal amount of meibum is expressed during this procedure and
           will not alter any of the normal functions of the tears. This meibum will then be stored
           for further analysis. Meibum and tear samples collected from the subjects will be stored
           in a -80ยบ C freezer in the microbiology laboratory, Room No. 2.028, School of Optometry
           and Vision Science, UNSW.

      All these study procedures will be repeated for each of the follow-up visits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single-center, randomized, cross-over, open-label interventional study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The clinical signs are photographed and an outcomes accessor grades the clinical signs. This process ensures that there is no bias in recording the results. This method was specially chosen, due to the lack or inability to mask the treatment procedures, due to their nature of treatment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lid Wiper Epitheliopathy</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The eyelids will be examined using a slit lamp before and after instillation of sodium fluorescein. This stain helps to disclose changes to the eyelid surface .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lid Sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>A Cochet Bonnet aesthesiometer will be used to assess the sensitivity thresholds of eyelids. This involves use of a fine nylon thread to gently touch the eyelid. The thread length at which subject become aware of a sensation will be recorded. Subjects may feel nothing or a slight awareness of the thread on eyelid.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demodex Infestation</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Highly magnified images of eyelids will be captured with a microscope. A lubricating tear gel will be placed in on the eye to enable the microscope probe to come into contact with eyelids and subject will be given an anaesthetic drop to reduce any symptoms that may be associated with this procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Meibography</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Meibomian gland (glands in eyelids) morphology will be studied using a non-contact meibographer which uses infrared light source to observe and capture high resolution images of meibomian glands.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lid Microbiota</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Saline-moistened swabs will be gently rolled along the lid margin - and then sent to the microbiology laboratory for analysis of the types of microbes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tear Osmolarity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>An Ocusense TearLab osmometer will be used to measure tear osmolarity. The salt concentration of tears will be measured by collecting a very small amount of tears (less than a tear drop) from the lower eyelid using this sterile device.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LipiView Interferometry</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>LipiView ocular surface interferometer measures the absolute thickness of the tear film lipid layer. It is an imaging device which uses infrared light to capture and store digital images of interferometric observations of the tear film which can be visually monitored and photographically documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Contact Lens Discomfort</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Microblepharon Exfoliation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This treatment is provided using BlephEx tool from Optimed Pty Ltd.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eyelid cleansing using Lid Hygenix</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Foam-based hypoallergenic cleanser used as a control treatment in this study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BlephEx</intervention_name>
    <description>BlephEx is an instrument that contains a hand piece used to spin a medical grade micro-sponge along the edge of eyelids and lashes that helps in removing scurf and debris from eyelids and helps in exfoliating the lids. A new micro-sponge will be used for every subject to avoid cross-contamination. This procedure lasts for 6-8 mins.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Microblepharon Exfoliation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lid Hygenix</intervention_name>
    <description>Foam-based hypoallergenic cleanser used to clean eyelid margins is used as a control intervention for the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eyelid cleansing using Lid Hygenix</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age of 18 years or above

          -  Understand their rights as a research subject

          -  Willing and able to sign a statement of informed consent

          -  Normal ocular status, defined as a minimum of 20/40 visual acuity in each eye; clear
             corneas without scarring, opacities, or vascularization, as determined by
             biomicroscopic examination

          -  Normal external examination

          -  Normal puncta without punctal plugs

          -  Ability to cooperate with the required procedures of diagnostic agent installation,
             eyelid eversion, and examination.

          -  Contact lens wearers who have worn lenses for at least 6 months, used contact lenses
             for 3 weeks before the evaluation visit and used these lenses at least four times a
             week. These contact lens wearers will be on daily wearing modality, where the subject
             is supposed to wear it for at least for 6 hours, only during the day and remove the
             lenses during sleep.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any ocular or systemic disease that might influence the tear film and especially
             subjects with a history of episodes of epilepsy.

          -  Subjects with eyelid inflammation of more than grade 2 will be excluded from the study
             as they need therapeutic intervention.

          -  All conjunctival abnormalities, including pingueculae greater than 1 mm in diameter,
             location closer than 2 mm to the limbus, or elevated more than 0.2 mm

          -  All forms of conjunctivitis, including allergic conjunctivitis

          -  Fluorescein corneal staining of grade 2 or more, after a single installation of
             non-preserved fluorescein solution followed by examination 1 minute after installation

          -  Current ocular infection or treatment of such infections with ocular or systemic
             medications

          -  Current use of any prescription or non-prescription ocular or systemic medications,
             including antihistamines

          -  Use of artificial tear preparations during the period 2 hours before the examination

          -  Use of any ocular ointment during the 3 days before the examination

          -  Any history of ocular surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Willcox, D Sc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of New South Wales</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jaya Sowjanya Siddireddy, M.Phil</last_name>
    <phone>+61426046147</phone>
    <email>j.siddireddy@student.unsw.edu.au</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ajay Vijay Kumar, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>02-938554503</phone>
    <email>v.ajaykumar@unsw.edu.au</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 17, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 17, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of New South Wales</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jaya Sowjanya Siddireddy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Ms</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Eyelid margin</keyword>
  <keyword>tear film</keyword>
  <keyword>debridement</keyword>
  <keyword>contact lens and ocular discomfort</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All participants will be given a unique study identification code. Data will be de-identified at the time of collection such that only patient initials and a study identification number will be used to identify the data for each patient. Any data included in reports, publications or presented at meetings will be provided in the form of group responses or study identity numbers, such that the participants cannot be identified. Personal and health information (either identifiable or potentially identifiable) about individuals will not be disclosed to any external parties without the individual's consent unless required by law. The unique study identification code can be broken by the research team if required (re-identifiable).</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

