<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03310775</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B-1611-371-303</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03310775</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Research on the Effect of Korean Version of PEERS Social Skills Training for Young Adults (PEERS-YA-K) With Autism Spectrum Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Research on the Effect of Korean Version of PEERS Social Skills Training for Young Adults (PEERS-YA-K) With Autism Spectrum Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Seoul National University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Seoul National University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite the psychosocial difficulties common among young adults with autism spectrum
      disorders(ASD), little to no evidence-based social skills interventions exist for this
      population. Using a randomized controlled trial(RCT) design, the current study tested the
      effectiveness of an evidence-based, caregiver-assisted social skills intervention known as
      PEERS for Young Adults with high-functioning young adults with ASD using self- and
      caregiver-report measures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Both the case and the control of this study shall be a high-functioning group consisting
           of young adults aged 18 to 35 years with ASD and an IQ of 70 or over. A total of 48
           young adults will be recruited and divided into two groups. One will be the case group
           and the other will be the waitlist control group. And the study will be going on 3
           institutions. Again, the case will be divided into two sub-groups of ten and carry out
           this new developed program for both parents and young adult. That is, the program will
           be carried out two times in each of both groups. The waitlist control group will be
           allowed to receive personal outpatient treatment and general therapeutic intervention
           from community while waiting.

        2. Effects of the program will be measured both at the case and the control by using a
           scale which measures social interaction, quality of peer relationship, disposition of
           autism and social anxiety. Equal assessments for both the case and the control will be
           conducted right before the beginning of the program and right after the completion of
           the program and four months after the completion of the program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 9, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule(ADOS) at 4 month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 month</time_frame>
    <description>The ADOS is a play-based, semistructured, standardized assessment of communication, social interaction, and play (i.e. imaginative use of materials) for individuals with a suspected diagnosis of autism or ASD. The ADOS consists of four modules, each of which can be selected on the basis of the participant's expressive language skills and chronological age. Module 4 of the ADOS is designed for adolescents and adults with fluent speech, and includes 10 essential and 5 optional activities. The scores from each activity are coded as well as those for five subdomains: language and communication, reciprocal social interaction, imagination, stereotyped behaviors and restricted interests, and other abnormal behaviors.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Test of Adolescent Social Skills Knowledge(TASSK) at 4 month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 4 month</time_frame>
    <description>The TASSK is a 22-item criterion-referenced test developed for this study to assess the teen's knowledge about the specific social skills taught during the intervention. Two items were derived from key elements of each of the 11 didactic lessons. Teens were presented with sentence stems and asked to choose the best option from two possible answers. Scores range from 0 to 22, with higher scores reflecting greater knowledge of teen social skills.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Korean Version of the Social Skills Rating System (K-SSRS) at 4 month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline,4 month</time_frame>
    <description>The SSRS consists of 38-items and took approximately 10 min to complete. Questionnaires were completed independently by the teen's parent and teacher. For example, items included ''Starts conversations rather than waiting for someone to talk first.'' The items were rated as either ''Never,'' ''Sometimes,'' or ''Very Often.'' The Social Skills and Problem Behaviors scales were derived from factor analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Social Responsiveness Scale (SRS) at 4 month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline,4 month</time_frame>
    <description>The SRS is a 65-item questionnaire that assesses the various dimensions of interpersonal behavior, communication, and repetitive/stereotypic behavior that are characteristics of ASD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Korean Version of the Child Behavior Checklist (K-CBCL) at 4 month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline,4 month</time_frame>
    <description>The CBCL is a parent-report questionnaire in which parents rate teens on various domains of psychopathology. It assesses internalizing and externalizing behaviors across 16 domain subscales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) at 4month</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline,4 month</time_frame>
    <description>The BDI consists of 21 items measuring the severity of subjective symptoms of depression, with emotional, cognitive, motivational, and physiological symptom profiles for adults. Each question has four possible answer choices, scored from 0 (no symptoms) to 3 (the most severe symptoms).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Autism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>case group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Behavioral: parent-assisted social skills training program for young adults with autism spectrum disorder The subjects will participate in the treatment program weekly for a total of 14 weeks. The final visit will be made at the point three months after the completion of treatment to see mid- and long-term effects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>waitlist control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For this group, same intervention with the Experimental group will be provided after waiting for 16 weeks.
Behavioral: Delayed intervention Intervention is provided to Waitlist Control Group after waiting for 16 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parent-assisted social skills training program for young adult with ASD</intervention_name>
    <description>The subjects will participate in the treatment program weekly for a total of 16 weeks. The final visit will be made at the point four months after the completion of treatment to see long-term effects.</description>
    <arm_group_label>case group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>waitlist control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18~35 years of age with ASD and IQ of 70 or over

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Young adults who are hard to understand the content of treatment and carry out the
             task due to their IQs or limited linguistic abilities

          -  Young adults who are uncooperative in the treatment, lack motives and are hard to
             participate voluntarily

          -  Young adults who have behavior problems so clinically significant that they affects
             the therapeutic procedure or problems in controlling their emotion and have psychotic
             symptoms
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Social skill training</keyword>
  <keyword>PEERS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

