<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03312075</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIMENT (29BRC17.0001)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03312075</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidemiology and Clinical Characteristics of Non-Tuberculous Mycobacteria Infections in Cystic Fibrosis Patients.</brief_title>
  <acronym>CIMENT</acronym>
  <official_title>Epidemiology and Clinical Characteristics of Non-Tuberculous Mycobacteria Infections in Cystic Fibrosis Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Brest</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Brest</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An increase in the prevalence of infections due to non-tuberculous mycobacteria (NTM) is
      observed in many countries and recent data suggest the circulation of dominant clones with a
      possibility of human-to-human contamination. The hypothesis is made that these infections are
      also increasing in France and that dominant NTM clones are circulating. The last French study
      carried out in 2004 already showed prevalences of up to 10% in certain French regions. It is
      essential to know the prevalence 8 years later, taking advantage of the new recommendations
      for the management of patients and samples, which will homogenize practices on French
      territory.

      No data are currently available in France on the prevalence of positive serological responses
      in cystic fibrosis patients. Serological analyzes of the sera collected during this study
      will enable us to evaluate the performance of serology in mycobacterial culture and to
      identify patients with no positive respiratory specimen in culture but with positive serology
      indicating potential contact with a mycobacterium. The establishment of a serological
      follow-up of these patients will allow to correlate this result with a clinical evolution and
      / or the detection of NTM in subsequent samples. Serology is an innovative aspect of the
      CIMENT study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Non-tuberculous mycobacteria (NTM) are important new pathogens in cystic fibrosis, with
      prevalence estimates ranging from 6% to 13%. The diagnosis of the disease in cystic fibrosis
      patients is difficult because the infection may remain indolent in some cases without
      evidence of clinical consequence, while in other patients NTM are associated with significant
      morbidity and mortality. Treatment requires antibiotic therapy over a prolonged period (at
      least 12 to 18 months) with several drugs and varies according to NTM and their antibiotic
      resistance profile. The development of a specialized approach (clinicians / biologists) in
      the management of this infection, combined with the diagnosis and treatment of NTM
      infections, in cystic fibrosis patients is a research priority. It is an indispensable
      long-term strategy for this high-risk population.

      Two main elements confirm the interest of a prevalence survey of NTM infections in cystic
      fibrosis (CF) patients: the diagnostic difficulty of &quot;true&quot; infections (as opposed to simple
      colonizations) to NTM, and the clinical impact on respiratory functions of NTM present in
      these patients. Two recent contradictory studies on the impact of NTM infections in CF
      patients have recently been published. The German monocentric study suggests a greater
      deterioration of respiratory function in CF patients not infected with NTM compared to CF
      patients infected with NTM. 26 patients were infected with NTM: 14/26 with M. avium complex
      (MAC), 10/26 with M. abscessus complex and 2/26 with M. gordonae. Only 5 patients out of a
      dozen positive to M. abscessus and 1 in 14 positive to MAC were treated. Comparatively, the
      other study found a significant deterioration in respiratory function (maximum expired volume
      in 1 seconde) of CF patients infected with M. abscessus. This Scandinavian national study
      reinforced its argument by the fact that an effective treatment made it possible to find
      changes in maximum expired volume in 1 seconde close to that observed before the infection.
      Some differences are observed in these two studies; including the age of the subjects
      included, older in the German study, and the number of positive lung samples per patient. The
      German study retained the criteria of the American Thoracic Society (ATS) / Infectious
      Disease Society of America (IDSA) for interpreting respiratory specimens positive for MNT.
      However, these criteria remain very difficult to apply for CF patients because the clinical
      and radiological manifestations of cystic fibrosis and mycobacterial infection are confounded
      and other criteria are necessary, such as the number of positive pulmonary samples: 5 vs. 2
      to 4 or the decline in maximum expired volume in 1 seconde in the year prior to colonization
      / MNT infection (-5.8% per year vs. 0.7% per year). We see here the necessity of
      complementary studies, in order to be able to identify the diagnostic difficulties and the
      impacts of the therapeutics administered in these patients. Indeed, on the one hand the
      therapeutic impact is very difficult to evaluate in the face of the very weak correlation
      between the results of the &quot;antibiograms&quot; and therefore in vitro and the therapeutic effect
      in vivo. On the other hand, precise diagnostic interpretation remains essential, as published
      observational studies show real discrepancies, largely due to diagnostic biases. Recently,
      under the auspices of the American Foundation and the European Cystic Fibrosis Society,
      guidelines for the management of NTM infections in CF patients have been published. To this
      is added the references of Microbiology.

      Several authors have shown that this diagnosis is an alternative in the context of NTM
      infections in cystic fibrosis patients. Indeed, as mentioned above, the microbiological
      diagnosis is often faulted, due to the difficulty of culturing the samples and their low
      yield in the context of NTM infections. An indirect diagnostic approach can only reinforce
      the screening of cystic fibrosis patients who have had contact with a NTM. Any serological
      response, although unable to date an infection, is the result of a potentially protective
      response of the host undergoing infection, and evidence of antibodies directed against the
      agent's bacterial products pathogen in circulating blood. A simple colonization does not
      allow the appearance of antibodies. An infectious process, even inapparent, must have taken
      place.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients screened positive for NTM by the culture</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients screened positive for NTM by the culture with regard of the number of expectorants collected will be evaluated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients screened positive for NTM by serology</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients screened positive for NTM by serology with regard of the number of expectorants collected will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>cystic fibrosis patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Sputum and blood samples</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sputum and blood samples</intervention_name>
    <description>The cystic fibrosis patient will have a first series of sputum as well as a blood sample. On the same day of consultation, a second expectoration will be performed as far as possible.</description>
    <arm_group_label>cystic fibrosis patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cystic fibrosis patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a confirmed diagnosis of cystic fibrosis regardless of CFTR genotype

          -  Affiliation to the social security system

          -  Patients able to expectorate spontaneously

          -  Patients enrolled in the French Register of Cystic Fibrosis

          -  Minor or major patients of expectorant age

          -  Consent signed by the patient or the holder of parental authority for the children

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient not registered in the French Register of Cystic Fibrosis

          -  Pulmonary transplant patients

          -  Persons deprived of liberty, persons under guardianship or curatorship, persons in
             emergency situations

          -  Person not affiliated to a social security system or not entitled
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Geneviève Hery-Arnaud, professor</last_name>
    <phone>0298145102</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>Genevieve.Hery-Arnaud@univ-brest.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Amiens</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amiens</city>
        <zip>80054</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claire Andrejak, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>03-22-45-59-03</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>clandrejak@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHRU Brest</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest</city>
        <zip>29200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Geneviève Hery-Arnaud, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>0298145102</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>Genevieve.Hery-Arnaud@univ-brest.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Côte de Nacre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caen</city>
        <zip>14033</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karine Campbell, MD</last_name>
      <phone>02-31-06-46-76</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>campbell-k@chu-caen.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHIC Créteil</name>
      <address>
        <city>Créteil</city>
        <zip>94000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurence Bassinet, MD</last_name>
      <phone>01-57-02-20-80</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>laurence.bassinet@chicreteil.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Boubou Camara, MD</last_name>
      <phone>04-76-76-58-46</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>BCamara@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Lille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne Prevotat, MD</last_name>
      <email>anne.prevotat@chru-lille.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AP-HP Hôpital Cochin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75679</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>pierre-Régis Burgel, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>01-46-33-82-53</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>pierre-regis.burgel@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Bordeaux</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie Macey, MD</last_name>
      <phone>05-57-62-32-90</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>julie.macey@chu-bordeaux.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de Perharidy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roscoff</city>
        <zip>29684</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>sophie Ramel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>02-98-29-39-39</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>sophie.ramel@ildys.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Rouen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <zip>76031</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hélène Morisse-Pradier, MD</last_name>
      <email>helene.morisse-pradier@chu-rouen.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHR Sud Réunion</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-Pierre</city>
        <zip>97410</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Céline Tasset, MD</last_name>
      <email>celine.tasset@chu-reunion.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Annabelle Payet-Charneau, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AP-HP Hôpital Foch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suresnes</city>
        <zip>92151</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dominique Grenet, MD</last_name>
      <phone>01-46-25-25-82</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>d.grenet@hopital-foch.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Toulouse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marlène Murris-Espin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>05-67-77-18-51</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>murris.m@chu-toulouse.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Tours</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tours</city>
        <zip>37044</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie Mankikian, MD</last_name>
      <phone>02-47-47-98-34</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>JMANKIKIAN@chu-tours.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qvist T, Gilljam M, Jönsson B, Taylor-Robinson D, Jensen-Fangel S, Wang M, Svahn A, Kötz K, Hansson L, Hollsing A, Hansen CR, Finstad PL, Pressler T, Høiby N, Katzenstein TL; Scandinavian Cystic Fibrosis Study Consortium (SCFSC). Epidemiology of nontuberculous mycobacteria among patients with cystic fibrosis in Scandinavia. J Cyst Fibros. 2015 Jan;14(1):46-52. doi: 10.1016/j.jcf.2014.08.002. Epub 2014 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25178871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albrecht C, Ringshausen F, Ott S, Wagner D, Rademacher J, Schneider M, Welte T, Pletz MW. Should all adult cystic fibrosis patients with repeated nontuberculous mycobacteria cultures receive specific treatment? A 10-year case-control study. Eur Respir J. 2016 May;47(5):1575-7. doi: 10.1183/13993003.01239-2015. Epub 2016 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>26846823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Griffith DE, Aksamit T, Brown-Elliott BA, Catanzaro A, Daley C, Gordin F, Holland SM, Horsburgh R, Huitt G, Iademarco MF, Iseman M, Olivier K, Ruoss S, von Reyn CF, Wallace RJ Jr, Winthrop K; ATS Mycobacterial Diseases Subcommittee; American Thoracic Society; Infectious Disease Society of America. An official ATS/IDSA statement: diagnosis, treatment, and prevention of nontuberculous mycobacterial diseases. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2007 Feb 15;175(4):367-416. Review. Erratum in: Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2007 Apr 1;175(7):744-5. Dosage error in article text.</citation>
    <PMID>17277290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martiniano SL, Sontag MK, Daley CL, Nick JA, Sagel SD. Clinical significance of a first positive nontuberculous mycobacteria culture in cystic fibrosis. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2014 Jan;11(1):36-44. doi: 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201309-310OC.</citation>
    <PMID>24251858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Floto RA, Olivier KN, Saiman L, Daley CL, Herrmann JL, Nick JA, Noone PG, Bilton D, Corris P, Gibson RL, Hempstead SE, Koetz K, Sabadosa KA, Sermet-Gaudelus I, Smyth AR, van Ingen J, Wallace RJ, Winthrop KL, Marshall BC, Haworth CS. US Cystic Fibrosis Foundation and European Cystic Fibrosis Society consensus recommendations for the management of non-tuberculous mycobacteria in individuals with cystic fibrosis: executive summary. Thorax. 2016 Jan;71(1):88-90. doi: 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2015-207983.</citation>
    <PMID>26678435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jeong BH, Kim SY, Jeon K, Lee SY, Shin SJ, Koh WJ. Serodiagnosis of Mycobacterium avium complex and Mycobacterium abscessus complex pulmonary disease by use of IgA antibodies to glycopeptidolipid core antigen. J Clin Microbiol. 2013 Aug;51(8):2747-9. doi: 10.1128/JCM.00702-13. Epub 2013 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23740728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qvist T, Taylor-Robinson D, Waldmann E, Olesen HV, Hansen CR, Mathiesen IH, Høiby N, Katzenstein TL, Smyth RL, Diggle PJ, Pressler T. Comparing the harmful effects of nontuberculous mycobacteria and Gram negative bacteria on lung function in patients with cystic fibrosis. J Cyst Fibros. 2016 May;15(3):380-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jcf.2015.09.007. Epub 2015 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26482717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qvist T, Pressler T, Taylor-Robinson D, Katzenstein TL, Høiby N. Serodiagnosis of Mycobacterium abscessus complex infection in cystic fibrosis. Eur Respir J. 2015 Sep;46(3):707-16. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00011815. Epub 2015 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25929948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 12, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycobacterium Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycobacterium Infections, Nontuberculous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

