<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03313921</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL61478.041.17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03313921</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The MORE Study: Manifest vs. Online Refraction Evaluation</brief_title>
  <acronym>MORE</acronym>
  <official_title>The MORE Study: Manifest vs. Online Refraction Evaluation. A Clinical Validation of Online Refraction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UMC Utrecht</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The assessment of the refractive state of the eye is a fundamental and important part of
      ophthalmic and optometric clinical practice. The development of an unsupervised online
      subjective refraction method makes a refraction more accessible and can be quite cost-saving.

      In this study, the investigators want to validate an online refraction method which was
      recently created in the Netherlands. The study comprises two different set of participants:
      Part one contains fifty healthy volunteers, 18-40 years of age, with a refractive error and
      no other ophthalmic pathology. Part two contains fifty patients with an ophthalmic pathology.

      The online refraction outcomes will be compared to a manifest refraction and automated
      refraction in a cross-sectional study design.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Uncorrected refractive errors cause significant economic implications in both high and low
      income countries in terms of the loss of potential productivity (Williams et al. (2015)). The
      prevalence of uncorrected refractive errors is, despite of the available clinical services,
      still huge; visual impairment is in 42 percent of the cases the result of an uncorrected
      refractive error worldwide (Williams et al. (2015)). Even in high income countries, this
      issue remains prevalent. Therefore, the access to the available clinical services has to be
      simplified. The development of an online refraction method will make a refraction more
      accessible for patients and can be cost-saving. Clinicians can easily take an online method
      to places where it's needed for example in low income countries.

      There are several methods to measure a refractive error. The 'golden standard' to prescribe
      spectacles is a manifest refraction (Thibos, Hong, Bradley &amp; Applegate (2004)). This method
      was already described by F.C. Donders in 1864 and is performed with trial lenses and a visual
      acuity chart to measure the refraction error (Donders (1864)). An automated refraction is a
      quick routine machine based assessment, mainly used as a starting point for a manifest
      refraction and is based on retinoscopy (Nissman et al., (2004)).

      At the moment, several online refraction methods are available. However, these methods are
      not scientifically validated, unavailable outside the United States of America (USA) or not
      designed for customers. One of these online refraction methods is Opternative (Opternative
      (2017)). Opternative is currently used in the USA and is still developing (Opternative
      (2017)). It's a self-directed online refraction method using a computer-based response to
      presented stimuli with the use of a smartphone and a computer. Another method is EyeNetra
      (EyeNetra (2017) &amp; Ohlendorf, Leube &amp; Wahl (2016)). The use of this method is limited due to
      the need of special equipment such as a portable autorefractor, an autolensometer and a
      phoropter. Therefore, EyeNetra is mainly designed for optometrists and ophthalmologists for
      low-income populations. The same applies to SVOne; this method uses a Hartmann-Shack
      wavefront aberrometer which the user can attach to a smartphone (Ohlendorf, Leube &amp; Wahl
      (2016)). Other online refraction methods are 6over6, but this method has not been released
      yet (6over6, (2017)), and Warby Parker (Warby Parker, (2017)).

      There are also online visual acuity tests to measure the visual acuity only. The mobile
      devices to test the visual acuity are PeekVision, 6over6, Opternative, Eyenetra and DigiSight
      (Ludwig et al., (2016)).

      Currently, digitalization is affecting our way of life. Technology can be used to design
      products to easily determine if someone has a refractive error. This can, in the future,
      solve a big part of the problem of uncorrected refractive errors and the leading cause of
      blindness worldwide. The aim of this study is to validate a recently created online
      refraction method by comparing the outcomes of the online refraction method with the 'golden
      standard' manifest refraction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>cross-sectional open-label non-inferiority assessment of a novel diagnostic entity compared to current gold-standard in two seperate groups of patients (healthy and diseased)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Refractive error</measure>
    <time_frame>All three measurements (automated refraction, manifest refraction and online refraction) will be performed subsequently on the same 1 day. Data collection will take place between november 2017 and january 2018. No follow up measurements are required.</time_frame>
    <description>The refractive error is recorded in a Sphere power (D), a Cylinder power (D) and a Cylinder axis (°). These are converted into vectors by Fourier analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum distance visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>The visual acuity test will take place on the same 1 day as the other measurements. Data collection will take place between november 2017 and january 2018. No follow up measurements are required.</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum visual acuity as assessed during the refraction procedure using an ETDRS visual acuity chart and converted into logMAR values.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>The questionnaire will be filled in on the same 1 day as the other measurements. Data collecting will take place between november 2017 and january 2018. No follow up measurements are required.</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire on user experience of the smartphone application.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Telemetry</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements of the duration of the online test will happen 1 day during the online refraction test. Collecting data will take place between November 2017 and January 2018. No follow up measurements are required.</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of the online test time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Refraction Error</condition>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <condition>Astigmatism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Online Manifest Refraction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will undergo three assessments of refractive error, in random order. All will perform an unsupervised manifest refraction with the use of a computer screen and their smartphone. Next, a regular manifest refraction assessment performed by an optometrist will function as active comparator. An automated refraction assessment will be performed to relate the quality and repeatability of the online refraction to another unsupervised method of refraction assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online Manifest Refraction</intervention_name>
    <description>The online manifest refraction is performed with a web-based application and consists of an assessment of visual acuity, an assessment of spherical refractive error, and an assessment of cylinder refractive error. The software is a class 1 CE-approved medical device.
The automated refraction is measured with a regular office-based autorefractor device; TOPCON RM-8000.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Online Manifest Refraction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Easee online refraction</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        inclusion criteria:

          1. Group one:

               -  Age: 18-40 years

               -  Master the Dutch language

               -  Capable to perform the tests adequately.

          2. Group two:

               -  Age: 18-40 years

               -  Master the Dutch language

               -  Capable to perform the tests adequately.

               -  Diagnosis of keratoconus.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Group one:

               -  No informed consent

               -  Diabetes

               -  Pregnancy or lactation

               -  High hyperopia/myopia (&gt;6D)

               -  An ophthalmic history besides ametropia

          2. Group two:

               -  No informed consent

               -  Diabetes

               -  Pregnancy or lactation

               -  High hyperopia/myopia (&gt;6D)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Wisse, MD PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMC Utrecht</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emma van Hamersveld, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>0031 88 7556781</phone>
    <email>e.vanhamersveld@umcutrecht.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anjo Riemens, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0031 88 7556781</phone>
    <email>j.a.riemens@umcutrecht.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <link>
    <url>https://easee.online/</url>
    <description>website of the online refractive assessment</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 17, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 17, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>UMC Utrecht</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>R.P.L. Wisse, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Ophthalmologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>myopia</keyword>
  <keyword>astigmatism</keyword>
  <keyword>online assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>refractive error</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myopia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Astigmatism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Refractive Errors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

