<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02543957</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-37346</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02543957</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Factors Associated With Increased Risk of Bacteremia and Cholangitis in ERCP With Cholangioscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Study of the Factors Associated With Increased Risk of Bacteremia and Cholangitis in ERCP With Cholangioscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An Endoscopic retrograde cholangio pancreatography (ERCP) with cholangioscopy (endoscope to
      directly visualize the bile duct ) is a procedure (a small flexible tube that is inserted
      into the participants mouth to the participants stomach and into the participants liver to
      visualize the bile duct) that is usually performed in patients for the following purposes :

        1. The removal of all stones from the participants bile duct (if present).

        2. Acquiring a tissue sample biopsy from any common bile mass to examine (if present).

        3. Acquiring tissue sample biopsy from common bile duct narrowing (if present). However
           this procedure is associated with an increase risk of infection compared with the
           standard ERCP (ERCP without cholangioscopy). Previous studies have shown that despite
           the administration of antibiotics prior to these procedures, infection still occurs.
           This leads to a suspicion that other factors may be the cause in these infections.
           Factors such as age, race, gender and ethnicity have not been fully explored yet. This
           study aims to examine these factors in addition to others in patients who are undergoing
           ERCP with cholangioscopy as part of their routine medical care. This examination will
           allow us to bring out if any of the above mentioned factors may be involved in the
           development of an infection after ERCP with cholangioscopy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ERCP with cholangioscopy is becoming a widespread technique to treat complicated
      choledocholithiasis, document CBD clearance after stone extraction and to assess biliary duct
      strictures. During the procedure, a large amount of water is used to irrigate the common bile
      duct in order to improve visualization. This can result in CBD distension and may increase
      the possibility of bacterial translocation and subsequent bacteremia or septicemia. According
      to the ASGE guidelines, antibiotic prophylaxis prior to ERCP is indicated when biliary duct
      obstruction is suspected prior to ERCP procedures . There are no current guidelines
      addressing antibiotics prophylaxis prior to ERCP with cholangioscopy. The investigators
      recent ACG funded prospective trial examining the risk of bacteremia in ERCP with
      cholangioscopy have shown the presence of bacteremia in 8.8% of patients undergoing ERCP with
      cholangioscopy, thus prompting the use of prophylactic antibiotics in patients undergoing
      these procedures. However the study was not powered to examine factors associated with
      increased bacteremia and infectious complications. In spite of the use of pre-procedural
      antibiotics in some of the published series, infectious complications such as cholangitis and
      sepsis were still reported after the procedure. In the landmark study by Chen et al, in which
      297 patients prospectively underwent single-operator cholangioscopy in 15 referral centers
      across the US and Europe, nine patients developed cholangitis. Antibiotics administration
      prior to the procedures was left to the standard of practice at each participating
      institution and was not reported in this study. In a retrospective study by Kalaitzakis et
      al, nine out of 179 patients who underwent cholangioscopy for CBD stricture or treatment of
      CBD stones developed cholangitis. Cholangitis was fatal in one case and required prolonged
      hospitalization in the other case. All patients in this study had antibiotics prophylaxis
      prior to the procedure. Manta et al had one case of cholangitis in their series of 52
      patients who underwent cholangioscopy for CBD stricture. Two patients out of 87 patients had
      cholangitis in the study by Osania et al., which prospectively included patients who
      underwent cholangioscopy for CBD stricture. The cholangitis rate in the previously mentioned
      studies ranged from 2% to 5%. This high rate of post procedure cholangitis in spite of the
      use of pre-procedural antibiotics suggest that post procedure antibiotics are of value in
      subsets of patients who will undergo ERCP with cholangioscopy. In the investigators
      preliminary data, bacteremia rate was significantly higher in patients with CBD strictures
      who had cholangioscopy with biopsies. It is possible that strictures could lead to
      colonization of biliary epithelium with bacteria. Obtaining biopsies may cause disruption of
      the endothelial barrier allowing bacterial translocation. In addition, cholangitis was seen
      in one patient in the investigators cohort who underwent laser lithotripsy for large stone.
      Choledocholithiasis is another source of bacterial colonization which could increase the risk
      of cholangitis after ERCP and cholangioscopy. The investigators protocol objective is to
      examine the factors that are potentially associated with increased frequency of bacteremia
      and subsequent infectious complication after ERCP with cholangioscopy in a setting of uniform
      pre-procedure antibiotics. The investigators hypothesize that biopsy of CBD strictures and
      Laser Lithotripsy are risk factors for increased rate of bacteremia and infectious
      complications after ERCP with cholangioscopy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the Incidence of new onset infectious complications</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>1- To examine the incidence and risk factors of new onset infectious complications such as fever, sepsis or cholangitis within one week after ERCP with cholangioscopy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the incidence of bacteremia in patients undergoing ERCP with cholangioscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Existing prospective data have shown bacteremia in 8.8% of patients undergoing ERCP with cholangioscopy, thus promoting the use of prophylactic antibiotics in patients undergoing these procedures. Three blood withdrawals from the patient undergoing ERCP with Cholangioscopy. One blood withdrawal will be taken before the procedure (Cholangioscopy), the second one will be taken 5 minutes after the procedure and the last blood withdrawal will be taken 30 minutes after the procedure with an overall 30 cc blood withdrawn from each patient. Aseptic techniques will be taken to minimize the contamination of the blood sample by the skin flora. Patients with positive blood culture for bacteremia will be monitored and only patients with fever and evidence of sepsis or cholangitis will be treated with antibiotics. The patient will receive a phone questionnaire about adverse affects that might have happened after the procedure 24 hours after the procedure and 1 week after the procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholangitis</condition>
  <condition>Bacteremia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cholangioscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive pre-procedural antibiotics per protocol. A blood culture will be drawn from patients prior to the procedure (before antibiotics administration), 5 minutes after the procedure and 30 minutes after the procedure. Patients will be followed up for 7 days after the procedure for fever and or sepsis.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study participants ages 18-80 will be recruited from patients undergoing an ERCP at the
        Baylor St Luke Medical center in Houston or at University of Texas Health Science Center at
        San Antonio. Both practices are university based practice and serve as a tertiary referral
        center for all complicated EUS and ERCP procedures in eastern Texas. Choledocholithiasis
        and its complications requiring ERCP are prevalent and represent a large share of this ERCP
        practice.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients (18-80) who are undergoing ERCP with cholangioscopy to ensure the
             clearance of the CBD from stones.

          2. Adult patients (18-80) who are undergoing ERCP with cholangioscopy for CBD stone
             removal using laser lithotripsy.

          3. Adult patients (18-80) who are undergoing ERCP with cholangioscopy for CBD mass.

          4. Adult patients (18-80) who are undergoing ERCP with cholangioscopy for tissue
             acquisition from CBD strictures with biopsies.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients younger than 18 yrs old or older than 80 yrs.

          2. Pregnant patients.

          3. Patient with ascending cholangitis, pneumonia or urinary tract infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamed Othman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mohamed O. Othman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-798-0950</phone>
    <email>Mohamed.Othman@bcm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nedaa Husainat</last_name>
    <phone>713-798-0947</phone>
    <email>Nedaa.Husainat@bcm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mohamed O. Othman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>713-798-0950</phone>
      <email>Mohamed.Othman@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mohamed Othman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.D. Director of Advanced Endoscopy Assistant Professor of Medicine - Gastroenterology Section</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ERCP</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholangitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Bacteremia</keyword>
  <keyword>Antibiotics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bacteremia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholangitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

