<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02548793</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>822593</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02548793</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CPR Education Via a Mobile Application Compared to VSI Kit</brief_title>
  <official_title>CPR Education for Families of Cardiac Patients Before Hospital Discharge</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prompt delivery of cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) is a crucial determinant of survival
      for many victims of sudden cardiac arrest (SCA), yet bystander CPR is provided in less than
      one third of witnessed SCA events. A number of barriers to bystander CPR training have been
      identified including time and cost of the training course. Since the large majority of arrest
      events occur in the home environment, studies have suggested that providing CPR training to
      family members of hospitalized cardiac patients may serve as a useful approach to address an
      environment in which bystander CPR is frequently not provided. Utilizing an existing
      in-hospital program to train adult family members, the investigators will assess the skills
      of those who learn CPR through two different educational methods: a mobile app and video
      self-instruction (VSI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The long term goal of the investigators work is to implement real world CPR training
      strategies that match training locales with at-risk populations, maximize resuscitation skill
      retention, and promote willingness to act. To accomplish this, the investigators will empower
      stakeholders at the University of Pennsylvania Health System (UPHS) and local area hospitals
      to develop local implementation approaches, using either volunteer hospital personnel or paid
      research assistants as training proctors. These stakeholders will be studied as a research
      subset. The training proctors will educate family members or friends of patients at risk for
      cardiac arrest using a mobile application &quot;app&quot; or VSI kit (RCT), and empower them with the
      lifesaving skill of CPR. The investigators will follow up with the study subjects and conduct
      CPR skills tests 6 to 12 months from the time of training to assess whether the subjects
      retained their skills or if they had an opportunity to use the skills that they learned. The
      investigators will also gather information on how the subjects would like to be encouraged to
      practice their skills. The investigators will send a reminder notification every two months
      following training, to encourage subjects to refresh their training skills. At the follow-up
      skills test at 6 to 12 months, the investigators will administer a survey to assess whether
      the prompting encouraged the subjects to practice their skills. Additionally the
      investigators will encourage the individuals trained in-hospital to share the kit or mobile
      app with others. The investigators will follow-up with those who are identified as secondary
      trainees to assess the environment in which secondary training took place.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Chest compression depth</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Depth of chest compression performed by the subject, recorded using the Laerdal SimPad®. This metric will be measured in millimeters (mm). This outcome measure will be collected by research coordinators during 6-month in-home follow-up visits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Chest compression rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of chest compressions performed by the subject, recorded using the Laerdal SimPad®. This metric will be measured as the number of compressions performed in a 2 minute window. This outcome measure will be collected by research coordinators during 6-month in-home follow-up visits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary CPR training rates</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Calculate the number of secondary trainees based on study participant self-reporting (via survey) collected during the 6-month follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of bystander CPR provided by subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>6-12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using 6 month and 12 month follow-up surveys, subjects will be asked if they had an opportunity to use their CPR skills in a real-life situation and whether or not they performed CPR in the aforementioned situation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative analysis of patient's perspective of the family member's receiving hands-only CPR training using semi-structured</measure>
    <time_frame>6-12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using semi-structured interviews, we will evaluate the impact that CPR training of the patient's family may have on the patient's sense of independence and self-care post-discharge. Analysis will be based on the grounded theory. A working set of thematic codes will be identified and applied to all interview transcriptions using NVivo10. Thematic domains from this descriptive aim will help inform future understanding of the cardiac patient's psychological well-being and preparedness around cardiac disease as well as thoughts towards CPR training.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Risk Factors</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VSI Kit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Education: CPR Training using the CPR Anytime VSI Kit Individuals will learn chest-compression only CPR (no rescue breaths) using the American Heart Association's Family and Friends CPR Anytime Kit. Subjects will undergo training in-hospital and will be encouraged to take the kit home to share with their family members and friends.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Application</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Education: CPR Training via Mobile App Individuals will learn chest-compression only CPR (no rescue breaths) using a newly developed mobile training application.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education: CPR Training via Mobile App</intervention_name>
    <description>Using a mobile app to train users on chest-compression only CPR. Subjects will be encouraged to share the app with family and friends.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mobile Application</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CPR Training Cellphone App</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education: CPR Training using the CPR Anytime VSI Kit</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be trained using the American Heart Association's Family and Friends CPR Anytime Kit. Subjects will undergo training in-hospital and will be encouraged to take the kit home to share with their family members and friends.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VSI Kit</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Family and Friends CPR Anytime</other_name>
    <other_name>American Heart Association Family and Friends CPR Anytime</other_name>
    <other_name>CPR Anytime Video Self Instruction (VSI)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must be present with their family member at the hospital

          -  The family member must be at high risk for cardiac arrest (CA), including:

          -  previous myocardial infarction (MI)

          -  previous CA

          -  history of diabetes

          -  history of high cholesterol

          -  history of high blood pressure

          -  This includes subjects with family members being discharged from the Cardiac
             Intermediate Care Unit (CICU), Telemetry units, ICU, Cardiac Care Unit (CCU),
             cardiology clinics, or physicians office within the participating hospitals/health
             systems

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Volunteers and subjects must be 18 years of age or older

          -  Individual must be fit and able to perform moderate physical activity

          -  Volunteers must be English speaking and/or Spanish speaking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Benjamin S Abella, MD, MPhil</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cooper University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Camden</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn Presbyterian Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennsylvania Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albert Einstein Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19141</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Crozer-Keystone Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Upland</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Chester County Hospital and Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Chester</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19380</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.med.upenn.edu/resuscitation/</url>
    <description>University of Pennsylvania - Center for Resuscitation Science</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/</url>
    <description>American Heart Association</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blewer AL, Leary M, Decker CS, Andersen JC, Fredericks AC, Bobrow BJ, Abella BS. Cardiopulmonary resuscitation training of family members before hospital discharge using video self-instruction: a feasibility trial. J Hosp Med. 2011 Sep;6(7):428-32. doi: 10.1002/jhm.847. Epub 2010 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21916007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blewer AL, Leary M, Esposito EC, Gonzalez M, Riegel B, Bobrow BJ, Abella BS. Continuous chest compression cardiopulmonary resuscitation training promotes rescuer self-confidence and increased secondary training: a hospital-based randomized controlled trial*. Crit Care Med. 2012 Mar;40(3):787-92. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e318236f2ca.</citation>
    <PMID>22080629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Go AS, Mozaffarian D, Roger VL, Benjamin EJ, Berry JD, Blaha MJ, Dai S, Ford ES, Fox CS, Franco S, Fullerton HJ, Gillespie C, Hailpern SM, Heit JA, Howard VJ, Huffman MD, Judd SE, Kissela BM, Kittner SJ, Lackland DT, Lichtman JH, Lisabeth LD, Mackey RH, Magid DJ, Marcus GM, Marelli A, Matchar DB, McGuire DK, Mohler ER 3rd, Moy CS, Mussolino ME, Neumar RW, Nichol G, Pandey DK, Paynter NP, Reeves MJ, Sorlie PD, Stein J, Towfighi A, Turan TN, Virani SS, Wong ND, Woo D, Turner MB; American Heart Association Statistics Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Executive summary: heart disease and stroke statistics--2014 update: a report from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2014 Jan 21;129(3):399-410. doi: 10.1161/01.cir.0000442015.53336.12.</citation>
    <PMID>24446411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rea TD, Helbock M, Perry S, Garcia M, Cloyd D, Becker L, Eisenberg M. Increasing use of cardiopulmonary resuscitation during out-of-hospital ventricular fibrillation arrest: survival implications of guideline changes. Circulation. 2006 Dec 19;114(25):2760-5. Epub 2006 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>17159062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stiell IG, Wells GA, Field B, Spaite DW, Nesbitt LP, De Maio VJ, Nichol G, Cousineau D, Blackburn J, Munkley D, Luinstra-Toohey L, Campeau T, Dagnone E, Lyver M; Ontario Prehospital Advanced Life Support Study Group. Advanced cardiac life support in out-of-hospital cardiac arrest. N Engl J Med. 2004 Aug 12;351(7):647-56.</citation>
    <PMID>15306666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bagai A, McNally BF, Al-Khatib SM, Myers JB, Kim S, Karlsson L, Torp-Pedersen C, Wissenberg M, van Diepen S, Fosbol EL, Monk L, Abella BS, Granger CB, Jollis JG. Temporal differences in out-of-hospital cardiac arrest incidence and survival. Circulation. 2013 Dec 17;128(24):2595-602. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.113.004164. Epub 2013 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>24045044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cobb LA, Fahrenbruch CE, Walsh TR, Copass MK, Olsufka M, Breskin M, Hallstrom AP. Influence of cardiopulmonary resuscitation prior to defibrillation in patients with out-of-hospital ventricular fibrillation. JAMA. 1999 Apr 7;281(13):1182-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10199427</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holmberg M, Holmberg S, Herlitz J; Swedish Cardiac Arrest Registry. Factors modifying the effect of bystander cardiopulmonary resuscitation on survival in out-of-hospital cardiac arrest patients in Sweden. Eur Heart J. 2001 Mar;22(6):511-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11320981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iwami T, Kawamura T, Hiraide A, Berg RA, Hayashi Y, Nishiuchi T, Kajino K, Yonemoto N, Yukioka H, Sugimoto H, Kakuchi H, Sase K, Yokoyama H, Nonogi H. Effectiveness of bystander-initiated cardiac-only resuscitation for patients with out-of-hospital cardiac arrest. Circulation. 2007 Dec 18;116(25):2900-7. Epub 2007 Dec 10.</citation>
    <PMID>18071072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson ML, Cox M, Al-Khatib SM, Nichol G, Thomas KL, Chan PS, Saha-Chaudhuri P, Fosbol EL, Eigel B, Clendenen B, Peterson ED. Rates of cardiopulmonary resuscitation training in the United States. JAMA Intern Med. 2014 Feb 1;174(2):194-201. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.11320.</citation>
    <PMID>24247329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nichol G, Thomas E, Callaway CW, Hedges J, Powell JL, Aufderheide TP, Rea T, Lowe R, Brown T, Dreyer J, Davis D, Idris A, Stiell I; Resuscitation Outcomes Consortium Investigators. Regional variation in out-of-hospital cardiac arrest incidence and outcome. JAMA. 2008 Sep 24;300(12):1423-31. doi: 10.1001/jama.300.12.1423. Erratum in: JAMA. 2008 Oct 15;300(15):1763.</citation>
    <PMID>18812533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sasson C, Rogers MA, Dahl J, Kellermann AL. Predictors of survival from out-of-hospital cardiac arrest: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2010 Jan;3(1):63-81. doi: 10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.109.889576. Epub 2009 Nov 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20123673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abella BS, Aufderheide TP, Eigel B, Hickey RW, Longstreth WT Jr, Nadkarni V, Nichol G, Sayre MR, Sommargren CE, Hazinski MF; American Heart Association. Reducing barriers for implementation of bystander-initiated cardiopulmonary resuscitation: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association for healthcare providers, policymakers, and community leaders regarding the effectiveness of cardiopulmonary resuscitation. Circulation. 2008 Feb 5;117(5):704-9. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.188486. Epub 2008 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18195177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cho GC, Sohn YD, Kang KH, Lee WW, Lim KS, Kim W, Oh BJ, Choi DH, Yeom SR, Lim H. The effect of basic life support education on laypersons' willingness in performing bystander hands only cardiopulmonary resuscitation. Resuscitation. 2010 Jun;81(6):691-4. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2010.02.021. Epub 2010 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>20347208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swor R, Compton S. Estimating cost-effectiveness of mass cardiopulmonary resuscitation training strategies to improve survival from cardiac arrest in private locations. Prehosp Emerg Care. 2004 Oct-Dec;8(4):420-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15626005</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brennan RT, Braslow A. Are we training the right people yet? A survey of participants in public cardiopulmonary resuscitation classes. Resuscitation. 1998 Apr;37(1):21-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9667334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Free C, Phillips G, Watson L, Galli L, Felix L, Edwards P, Patel V, Haines A. The effectiveness of mobile-health technologies to improve health care service delivery processes: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS Med. 2013;10(1):e1001363. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1001363. Epub 2013 Jan 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23458994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cardiac Arrest</keyword>
  <keyword>CPR</keyword>
  <keyword>Family-centered Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Literacy</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Education</keyword>
  <keyword>Education Dissemination</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

