<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02545413</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRC/2015/protocol/24</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02545413</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Determine Efficacy of Probiotics in Irritable Bowel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized,Double-blind, Placebo Controlled Trial to Study the Efficacy and Safety of Probiotics in Adult Patients With Irritable Bowel Syndrome-diarrhea Predominant (IBS-D)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Next Gen Pharma India Pvt. Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Gastroenterology, Govt. Medical College, Kozhikode, Kerala, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Next Gen Pharma India Pvt. Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) is the most common functional GI disorder in which abdominal
      pain and/or discomfort is associated with changes in bowel habit, and with features of
      disordered defecation. IBS affects 10-20% of the population and causes a marked reduction of
      quality of life in affected individuals.The high prevalence of IBS is accompanied by large
      societal economic burdens and negative effects on the quality of life in affected patients.
      It is divided into 3 types IBS-D diarrhea predominant, IBS-C constipation predominant, IBS-M
      mixed sub type.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) is the most common functional GI disorder affecting 10-20% of
      the population and causing a marked reduction of quality of life in affected individuals. An
      altered brain-gut axis has been accepted as a main pathogenetic mechanism of IBS, which is
      associated with a dysfunction of the GI autonomic nervous system. These alterations may lead
      to abnormal visceral hypersensitivity and aberrations of gut motility. Recently, additional
      potential mechanisms of IBS have emerged including alteration of gut microbiota and low-grade
      inflammation/immune activation. These factors might lead to abnormal motility and visceral
      hypersensitivity and contribute to the symptoms. Naïve gut microbiota plays important roles
      in the maintenance of gut homeostasis by direct bactericidal effects and the evolution of
      both innate and adaptive immune systems. Gut microbiota is thought to play important roles in
      the pathogenesis of IBS. This is evident from the fact that IBS occurs more frequently after
      intestinal infection or antibiotics treatment. Studies have shown that the alterations of the
      intestinal microbiota are observed in IBS patients.Considering the relationship between
      alteration of gut microbiota and inflammation of gut, manipulation of gut microbiota by
      probiotics appears to be an ideal treatment modality for IBS. However, the beneficial effects
      and efficacy of altering gut microbiota by probiotics to improve the symptoms of IBS have not
      been consistent in clinical trials and therefore it remains uncertain as an effective
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Investigator (Dr Amit) not interested to carry out the study
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the intensity of abdominal pain relief and change in stool consistency before and after treatment, between the two arms</measure>
    <time_frame>8 wks (after end of treatment)</time_frame>
    <description>The defecation component of the primary endpoint will be evaluated by assessing stool consistency as per &quot;Bristol Stool Form Scale&quot;. Abdominal pain component of primary end point will be accessed by using an 11-point (i.e., 0 to 10) numeric rating scale that asks patients daily to rate their worst abdominal pain over the past 24-hours</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Quality of Life parameters as measured by IBS-QoL Questionnaire before and after treatment, between the 2 arms</measure>
    <time_frame>8 wks (after end of treatment) and 20 weeks (12 weeks after end of follow-up period; at end of study)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Quality of Life parameters as measured by SF-36 Questionnaire before and after treatment, between the 2 arms</measure>
    <time_frame>8 wks (after end of treatment) and 20 weeks (12 weeks after end of follow-up period; at end of study)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Visceral hypersensitivity/Rectal sensitivity before and after treatment between the two arms</measure>
    <time_frame>8 wks (after end of treatment)</time_frame>
    <description>Visceral hypersensitivity/Rectal sensitivity as measured between and within arms using a lubricated rectal balloon catheter for the duration taken for first defecation, first instance of pain and the pain threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Probiotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Probiotic VSL#3 will be given at a dose of one capsule thrice daily for 8 weeks, amounting to a total of 337.5 billion CFU/day. Each capsule contains 112.5 billion viable lyophilized bacteria of four strains of Lactobacillus (L. acidophilus DSM 24735, L. plantarum DSM 24730, L. paracasei DSM 24733, L. delbrueckii subsp. bulgaricus DSM 24734), three strains of Bifidobacterium (B. longum DSM 24736, B. breve DSM 24732, B. infantis DSM 24737) and one strain of Streptococcus (S. thermophilus DSM 24731) and excipients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo capsules will be given at a dose of one capsule thrice daily for 8 weeks; Placebo capsules contain all excipients as present in capsules (without the 8 strains of bacteria as mentioned above).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probiotic VSL#3</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Probiotic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Positive diagnoses of IBS subtype IBS-D defined by Rome III criteria, and who meet the
             following criteria:

             a) Abdominal Pain Intensity: weekly average of worst daily (in past 24 hours) b)
             abdominal pain score of &gt; 3.0 on a 0 to 10 point scale &amp; c) Stool Consistency of at
             least one stool with a consistency of Type 6 or Type 7 Bristol stool score (BSS) on at
             least 2 days per week

          2. Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients currently using non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, corticosteroids and
             mast cell stabilizers, or topical or systemic antibiotics in the past 1 month.

          2. Patients with major abdominal surgery, a history of inflammatory bowel disease or
             diverticular disease, celiac disease (by detection of anti-transglutaminase and
             anti-endomysial antibodies), allergic diseases, including asthma (excluded by family
             and personal history and specific anti-IgE antibodies), and other organic or
             psychiatric disorders as assessed by medical history, appropriate consultations and
             laboratory tests.

          3. Females who are Pregnant, breast-feeding, or not using reliable methods of
             contraception
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shejal A Hanmant, DM Trainee</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Government Medical College, Kozhikide, Kerala, India</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Varghese Thomas, DM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Government Medical College, Kozhikide, Kerala, India</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Gastroeneterology, Government Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kozhikode</city>
        <state>Kerala</state>
        <zip>673008</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

