<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02546193</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-008988</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02546193</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Outpatient Foley Catheter Compared to Usual Inpatient Care for Labor Induction</brief_title>
  <official_title>Outpatient Foley Catheter Compared to Usual Inpatient Care for Cervical Ripening: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Induction of labor, or causing labor to start before it otherwise starts spontaneously, is
      sometimes necessary as pregnancy progresses to ensure the safety of both mother and infant.
      Labor induction often begins with cervical ripening, in which various methods are used to
      prepare the cervix for contractions and labor. Cervical ripening is beneficial and decreases
      the need for cesarean section; however, it can be a lengthy process. By tradition, pregnant
      women are admitted to the hospital at the start of this process and remain inpatient until
      after the baby is born.

      There is increasing interest in allowing the mother to return to her own home during the very
      first part of this process. She may be more satisfied in a more comfortable environment with
      her family. Growing scientific evidence supports use of the Foley catheter as an approach to
      outpatient cervical ripening. The Foley catheter is a safe, effective method that is already
      used often in the inpatient setting. It does not cause increased health risks for either
      mother or baby. Previous research studies have shown that it is just as safe and effective
      when women return to their own homes with a Foley catheter and that women spend less time in
      the hospital before delivery. More information is needed before this becomes a standard of
      care. This research study will allow pregnant women to return home for the first night of
      their labor induction with a Foley catheter in place. In the morning they will return to the
      hospital and stay until after delivery. They will be compared to a group of women who remain
      in the hospital for their entire labor induction. The benefits to going home during labor
      induction may include increasing maternal satisfaction and optimizing the use of resources in
      the hospital.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled trial. The intervention group is comprised of low risk
      pregnant women who will have a Foley catheter placed followed by dismissal home with return
      in the morning for continuation of the labor induction process. The control group consists of
      women who will remain inpatient during the entire cervical ripening phase followed by
      continuation of the labor induction process in the inpatient setting.

      Low risk pregnant women at term will be enrolled in clinic after their providers have
      recommended induction of labor for a specific indication. They will be educated about
      induction of labor, the Foley catheter, and the proposed research study. If they would like
      to participate, they will be consented in the clinic. Computer-generated randomization will
      occur on the morning of the planned induction, and the patients will be contacted by phone to
      inform them of their assigned group. The randomization will be stratified by parity and BMI.

      Outpatient Foley catheter group:

      If the patient is randomized to the intervention group (outpatient Foley), she will undergo
      the following. She will present to the Family Birth Center in the evening at 1900. She will
      undergo a nonstress test (NST), an ultrasound for fetal presentation and amniotic fluid
      index, and a cervical exam with calculation of a Bishop score. The patient will be asked if
      she is having regular, painful contractions, decreased fetal movement, vaginal bleeding,
      leakage of fluid from the vagina concerning for rupture of membranes, or fevers or chills. A
      Foley catheter will be placed if the following criteria have been met: the nonstress test is
      reactive and reassuring (without the presence of ≥ 3 variable decelerations in a 20 minute
      period, late-appearing decelerations, or any deceleration lasting ≥1 minute), the fetal
      presentation is cephalic, the amniotic fluid index is 5 centimeters or more, the Bishop score
      is &lt;6, the cervical dilation is &lt;3 cm, and she has no other clinical characteristics that
      exclude her from the trial as described in the inclusion/exclusion criteria. A 30 French
      Foley will be placed either digitally or with speculum assistance. It will be inflated with
      60 cc of normal saline and taped to the patient's inner thigh. The fetal heart rate tracing
      will be monitored for 1 hour after Foley placement. The patient will be sent home if the
      following criteria are met: the fetal heart rate tracing is reactive and category I; there is
      no evidence of rupture of membranes, spontaneous labor, or vaginal bleeding more than
      spotting; and no other exclusion criteria are present. Before discharge, the patient may
      receive pharmacologic pain relief in the form of one dose of acetaminophen and/or fentanyl.

      The patient will be instructed to return to the Family Birth Center at 0700 the following
      day. She will be given detailed verbal and written instructions of when to contact and return
      to the Family Birth Center before the morning. She will be provided with the 24 hour direct
      access line for the Family Birth Center to call with any questions or concerns. If the Foley
      catheter is expulsed at home, she is to record the time of expulsion. She does not need to
      return to the Family Birth Center earlier than planned due to expulsion.

      When the patient returns in the morning, the induction will be continued at the discretion of
      the providing obstetric team. The remainder of her care during the first, second, and third
      stages of labor will be at the discretion of the providing team. The patient will have
      continuous fetal monitoring. All patients' labor progress will be monitored using a
      partogram. Cesarean delivery will not be performed for arrest of labor or failed induction
      unless all criteria have been met as outlined by the Family Birth Center Workgroup protocol
      made effective 6/2/14.

      Inpatient usual care group:

      If the patient is randomized to the control group (inpatient usual care), she will arrive to
      the Family Birth Center at 1900 to undergo induction of labor. She will undergo a nonstress
      test (NST), an ultrasound for fetal presentation and amniotic fluid index, and a cervical
      exam with calculation of a Bishop score. The patient will be asked if she is having regular,
      painful contractions, decreased fetal movement, vaginal bleeding, leakage of fluid from the
      vagina concerning for rupture of membranes, or fevers or chills. She will be included or
      excluded from the study based on the above information. Induction of labor may proceed at the
      discretion of the providing obstetric team. Cervical ripening should be performed with either
      25 mcg vaginal misoprostol every 4 hours with a maximum of six doses or a 30 Fr Foley
      catheter filled with 60 cc normal saline. The patient may need both methods during her
      inpatient stay if her cervix is unfavorable. A Foley catheter will be favored during the
      cervical ripening phase if there is tachysystole and/or a nonreassuring fetal heart tracing
      precluding further misoprostol administration, provided the Bishop score is still &lt;6. The
      remainder of her care during the first, second, and third stages of labor will be at the
      discretion of the providing team. All patients' labor progress will be monitored using a
      partogram. Cesarean delivery will not be performed for arrest of labor or failed induction
      unless all criteria have been met as outlined by the Family Birth Center Workgroup protocol
      made effective 6/2/14.

      Follow up

      Each mother will be asked to complete a survey before leaving the hospital describing her
      experience and satisfaction with the cervical ripening process. Primary and secondary
      endpoints will be collected from neonatal and maternal charts through 42 days after the
      patient's delivery or the date of the patient's final postpartum clinic visit, whichever
      comes last.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Unable to recruit/accrue adequate numbers of participants within funding period.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 8, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 8, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre-delivery hospitalization time</measure>
    <time_frame>Delivery, approximately 16 hours after admission</time_frame>
    <description>The time from when the patient is admitted to the hospital until she delivers her infant will be recorded. For the outpatient group, this will be measured by adding together the time that the patient spends in the Family Birth Center during Foley placement in the evening with the time she spends inpatient the next day during the rest of her induction until delivery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean score on maternal satisfaction survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Discharge from the hospital, approximately 2-3 days after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>This survey will gauge the mother's experience during her induction with regard to pain, rest, concerns during the induction, satisfaction, and willingness to recommend their particular induction setting (inpatient vs. outpatient).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants per method of induction used</measure>
    <time_frame>End of the third stage of labor, approximately 16 hours after admission</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean dose of medication for pain relief</measure>
    <time_frame>End of the third stage of labor, approximately 16 hours after admission</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean time of delivery</measure>
    <time_frame>End of the third stage of labor, approximately 16 hours after admission</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants per mode of delivery</measure>
    <time_frame>End of the third stage of labor, approximately 16 hours after admission</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean estimated blood loss at delivery</measure>
    <time_frame>End of the third stage of labor, approximately 16 hours after admission</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with intrapartum complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Final postpartum visit, approximately 42 days after delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with postpartum complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Final postpartum visit, approximately 42 days after delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean readmission rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Final postpartum visit, approximately 42 days after delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of infants per gender</measure>
    <time_frame>Neonatal discharge from the hospital, approximately 2-3 days after delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean birth weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Neonatal discharge from the hospital, approximately 2-3 days after delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean APGAR scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Neonatal discharge from the hospital, approximately 2-3 days after delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean umbilical cord blood gases</measure>
    <time_frame>Neonatal discharge from the hospital, approximately 2-3 days after delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of infants with neonatal morbidity or mortality, categorized by reason</measure>
    <time_frame>Neonatal discharge from the hospital, approximately 2-3 days after delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Outpatient Foley catheter</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women randomized to the outpatient Foley catheter group will present to the Family Birth Center in the evening. They will undergo a basic history, fetal nonstress test, ultrasound for presentation and amniotic fluid index, and cervical exam, and then a Foley catheter will be placed for cervical ripening. After fetal monitoring, they will return to their own homes. They will return to the Family Birth Center in the morning for continuation of their labor inductions in the inpatient setting, unless other concerns prompt them to seek care sooner.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inpatient usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women randomized to the inpatient usual care group will present to the Family Birth Center in the evening for their scheduled induction of labor. They will undergo a basic history, fetal nonstress test, ultrasound for presentation and amniotic fluid index, and cervical exam. Cervical ripening will commence with either a Foley catheter or vaginal misoprostol per the discretion of the managing obstetric team. They will remain in the inpatient setting throughout their entire labor induction course.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Foley catheter</intervention_name>
    <description>The Foley catheter is a device used to achieve cervical ripening at the start of labor induction. It is a single balloon catheter placed transcervically by a provider, either digitally or using a speculum for visualization. The balloon is placed above the internal os but below the fetal head, amniotic membranes, and placenta and is inflated. In this study, it will be inflated with 60 cc of normal saline and taped to the patient's thigh for traction. Over several hours, the balloon gradually dilates the cervix. The catheter is typically expulsed when the cervix is 3-4 centimeters.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Outpatient Foley catheter</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Inpatient usual care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Misoprostol</intervention_name>
    <description>Misoprostol is a prostaglandin E1 analogue that is used for cervical ripening during labor induction. A 25 microgram tablet is placed in the vagina by a provider. A new 25 mcg tablet can be used vaginally every 4 hours for up to 6 total doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inpatient usual care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Pregnant women at ≥37 weeks gestation by reliable dating criteria as determined by the
             American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (i.e. gestational age supported by
             one of the following: ultrasound prior to 20 weeks of gestation, fetal heart tones
             auscultated by Doppler for 30+ weeks, or documented serum or urine pregnancy test 36+
             weeks ago)

          2. Scheduled induction of labor with indication and timing supported by the Family Birth
             Center induction of labor guideline entitled &quot;Induction of labor: Indications and
             Timing&quot;

          3. Singleton gestation

          4. Cephalic presentation

          5. Amniotic fluid index greater than or equal to 5 centimeters

          6. Formal prenatal ultrasound documenting the absence of placenta previa

          7. Bishop score &lt;6 and cervical dilation &lt;3cm

          8. The woman is able to give appropriate consent and has undergone an informed consent
             process.

          9. Maternal age ≥ 18 years old at the time of consent.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. New diagnosis requiring immediate hospitalization for monitoring (such as new onset
             hypertensive disease of pregnancy)

          2. Vaginal bleeding

          3. Active labor

          4. Premature rupture of membranes as determined by positive ferning and as supported by
             pooling of fluid in the vaginal vault.

          5. Uterine tachysystole (&gt;5 contractions in 10 minutes)

          6. Nonreassuring fetal heart tracing before or after Foley placement

          7. Chorioamnionitis or maternal fever

          8. Intrauterine fetal demise

          9. Contraindication to vaginal delivery, relative or absolute (i.e. transfundal uterine
             surgery)

         10. Abnormal placentation including a low lying placenta

         11. Prior cesarean delivery

         12. Intrauterine growth restriction (growth &lt;10th percentile by formal ultrasound)

         13. Known fetal anomaly

         14. Human immunodeficiency virus, Hepatitis C, or active herpes infection

         15. Maternal cardiopulmonary disease requiring cardiac monitoring during labor

         16. Pregestational diabetes

         17. Rh isoimmunization

         18. Non-English speaking

         19. Distance from the hospital over 60 minutes by car, unreliable communication via
             telephone, or unreliable transportation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vanessa E Torbenson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jozwiak M, Bloemenkamp KW, Kelly AJ, Mol BW, Irion O, Boulvain M. Mechanical methods for induction of labour. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Mar 14;(3):CD001233. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001233.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22419277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sciscione AC, Muench M, Pollock M, Jenkins TM, Tildon-Burton J, Colmorgen GH. Transcervical Foley catheter for preinduction cervical ripening in an outpatient versus inpatient setting. Obstet Gynecol. 2001 Nov;98(5 Pt 1):751-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11704164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henry A, Madan A, Reid R, Tracy SK, Austin K, Welsh A, Challis D. Outpatient Foley catheter versus inpatient prostaglandin E2 gel for induction of labour: a randomised trial. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 2013 Jan 29;13:25. doi: 10.1186/1471-2393-13-25.</citation>
    <PMID>23356673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 14, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vanessa Torbenson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Instructor in Obstetrics-Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Misoprostol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

