<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02546765</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014P000413</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02546765</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dexmedetomidine and IV Acetaminophen for the Prevention of Postoperative Delirium Following Cardiac Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>Delirium</acronym>
  <official_title>Dexmedetomidine and IV Acetaminophen for the Prevention of Postoperative Delirium Following Cardiac Surgery in Adult Patients 60 Years of Age and Older</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Investigators will assess the incidence and duration of postoperative delirium in patients
      ≥60 years old undergoing Coronary Artery Bypass Grafting (CABG), with/without valve surgery
      (aortic and/or mitral) based on different regimens for postoperative sedation and analgesia.
      Patients will receive either intravenous (IV) dexmedetomidine and IV acetaminophen or
      standard postoperative management using IV propofol with morphine or hydromorphine. The
      Confusion Assessment Method (CAM) will be used to assess delirium in these patients.
      Investigators also seek to compare postoperative (48 hours) analgesic requirements in
      patients with or without IV acetaminophen. Investigators will finally assess postoperative
      cognition in post-surgical patients up to one year post-discharge using a cognitive
      assessment scale.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blinded, factorial design study
      consisting of 120 patients. Intravenous dexmedetomidine and acetaminophen will be compared to
      the standard sedation/analgesic propofol and opioid regimen.

      After obtaining informed consent, study subjects will be randomized by an unblinded
      investigator and receive a specific combination of both sedatives and analgesic medications.
      Sedatives will include either IV propofol or IV dexmedetomidine, and analgesics IV
      acetaminophen or placebo (100 mL 0.9% NaCl equivalent to the administered volume of IV
      acetaminophen). Subjects will be allocated in a 1:1:1:1 fashion into the following four
      treatment arms: 1. IV acetaminophen with IV propofol, 2. IV acetaminophen with IV
      dexmedetomidine, 3. IV propofol with placebo, or 4. IV dexmedetomidine with placebo. Sedation
      and analgesia protocols will begin while patients are in the OR and continue as they are
      transferred to the Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit (CVICU). The medications for sedation
      will be weight based (loading infusion of 0.5 - 1 µg/kg given over 10 minutes followed by a
      maintenance infusion of 0.1-1.4 µg/kg/hr for IV dexmedetomidine, or 20-100 µg/kg/min for IV
      propofol). Postoperative sedation is administrated 4-6 hours before patients are woken up in
      the CVICU. IV Acetaminophen (1g or 100mL) will be given every 6 hours for 48 hours to
      patients randomized to this drug. The volume of the placebo will be administered in
      respective groups in the same timeframe. Oral acetaminophen will be continued until discharge
      in all patients. All groups will also receive bolus doses of opioids (IV morphine or
      hydromorphone) as needed for breakthrough pain.

      Patients will be administered a preoperative (baseline) and a series of post-operative
      evaluations to assess delirium by a blinded investigator. Baseline assessments will include
      the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA), days of the week (DOW), months of the year (MOY),
      Delirium Symptom Interview (DSI), the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS) and the Confusion
      Assessment Method (CAM). Daily cognitive assessments will include the DSI, CAM, and a
      standard cognitive assessment. At discharge, the MoCA, DOW, MOY, DSI, and CAM will be given.
      Follow-up assessments will be conducted at 1 month and 1 year post-discharge and will include
      the telephonic MoCA, DSI, GDS and CAM. The delirium research assessments will not be provided
      to the treating clinicians. Treating clinicians will assess and treat delirium as usual,
      including assessment and correction of reversible causes, behavioral management, and use of
      IV haloperidol as needed for agitation. Rescue doses of haloperidol will be recorded in the
      study.

      Blood will be collected from all subjects at the time of the baseline assessment,
      post-operation day 1 (POD1) while in ICU, POD 2 in the ICU, and within 48 hours of discharge.
      Two sets of 10 mL will be collected at each time point, with a total of 80mL of blood per
      patient. Efforts will be made to efficiently draw blood through the patient's arterial line
      at baseline or add onto to scheduled draws with phlebotomy. The plasma and buffy coat will be
      separated from the blood, aliquotted into labeled vials, and stored in a biomarker bank at
      -80°C for future use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of delirium between patients treated with and without IV acetaminophen</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, with an expected average of 5 days in the hospital</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of delirium will be analyzed between patients treated with and without IV acetaminophen, measured from 24 hours post-operation and daily until discharge. Delirium will be defined as an acute change in pre-operative baseline condition with additional features of inattention and either disorganized thinking and altered loss of consciousness, as defined by the Confusion Assessment Method (CAM).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, with an expected average of 5 days, and at 1 month and 1- year following the date of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of delirium will be analyzed, measured from 24 hours post-operation and daily until discharge. Additional measurements will be made at 1 month and 1 year after discharge. Delirium will be defined as an acute change in pre-operative baseline condition with additional features of inattention and either disorganized thinking and altered loss of consciousness, as defined by the Confusion Assessment Method (CAM).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow up incidence of delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be assessed for delirium at 1 month and 1 year following the date of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The follow up incidence of delirium will be analyzed at 1 month and 1 year after discharge. Delirium will be defined as an acute change in pre-operative baseline condition with additional features of inattention and either disorganized thinking and altered loss of consciousness, as defined by the MoCA/t-MoCA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Additional postoperative analgesic requirements</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, with an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the amount of additional opioid (IV morphine or hydromorphone) and oral acetaminophen medications required for post-operative pain control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured in days admitted in the hospital, with an expected average of 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the number of days admitted in the hospital following the completion of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU Length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured in days admitted in the ICU, with an expected average of 2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the number of days admitted in the ICU prior to transfer to the general cardiac surgical floor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Delirium</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IV acetaminophen &amp; IV propofol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20-100 µg/kg/min IV propofol given for 4-6 hours before the patients are woken up in the ICU
1g IV acetaminophen every 6 hours for 48 hours during the first 2 days postoperatively</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IV acetaminophen &amp; IV dexmedetomidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A loading infusion of 0.5 - 1 µg/kg given over 10 minutes will be administered. After the loading infusion, a maintenance infusion of 0.1-1.4 µg/kg/hr will be initiated.
1 g IV acetaminophen every 6 hours for 48 hours during the first 2 days postoperatively</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IV propofol &amp; placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20-100 µg/kg/min IV propofol given for 4-6 hours before the patients are woken up in the ICU Volume of the placebo (saline) will match that of IV acetaminophen at 100ml 0.9% NaCl.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IV dexmedetomidine &amp; placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>0.1-1.0 µg/kg/hour IV dexmedetomidine given for 4-6 hours before the patients are woken up in the ICU Volume of the placebo (saline) will match that of i.v. acetaminophen at 100ml 0.9% NaCl.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IV acetaminophen &amp; IV propofol</intervention_name>
    <description>use of IV tylenol and IV propofol for pain and sedation (respectively)</description>
    <arm_group_label>IV acetaminophen &amp; IV propofol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ofirmev</other_name>
    <other_name>Diprivan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IV acetaminophen &amp; IV dexmedetomidine</intervention_name>
    <description>use of IV tylenol and IV dexmedetomidine for pain and sedation (respectively)</description>
    <arm_group_label>IV acetaminophen &amp; IV dexmedetomidine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ofirmev</other_name>
    <other_name>Precedex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IV propofol &amp; placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>use of IV propofol for sedation and morphine, the drug of choice for cardiac pain</description>
    <arm_group_label>IV propofol &amp; placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Diprivan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IV dexmedetomidine &amp; placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>use of IV dexmedetomidine for sedation and morphine, the drug of choice for cardiac pain</description>
    <arm_group_label>IV dexmedetomidine &amp; placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Precedex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients ≥ 60 years of age

          -  Undergoing CABG with/without valve (aortic and/or mitral) procedure requiring bypass

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pre-operative Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) &lt; 30%

          -  Emergent or urgent procedures, aortic surgery

          -  Pre-existing cognitive impairment (defined based on a short screening assessment),
             Parkinson's disease, Alzheimer's disease, recent seizures (&lt;3 months)

          -  Prophylactic medications for cognitive decline

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 2 mg/dl

          -  Liver dysfunction (liver enzymes &gt; 4x the baseline, since patients will have a
             baseline liver function tests), history and exam suggestive of jaundice

          -  Known history of alcohol or drug abuse (&gt;10 drinks per week)

          -  Hypersensitivity to any of the study drug and percutaneous procedures

          -  Non-English speaking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Balachundhar Subramaniam, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Balachundhar Subramaniam, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>617-667-2721</phone>
    <email>bsubrama@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diana Cepeda</last_name>
      <phone>617-667-4113</phone>
      <email>dcepeda@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Balachundhar Subramaniam, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rudolph JL, Jones RN, Levkoff SE, Rockett C, Inouye SK, Sellke FW, Khuri SF, Lipsitz LA, Ramlawi B, Levitsky S, Marcantonio ER. Derivation and validation of a preoperative prediction rule for delirium after cardiac surgery. Circulation. 2009 Jan 20;119(2):229-36. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.795260. Epub 2008 Dec 31.</citation>
    <PMID>19118253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Inouye SK. Delirium in older persons. N Engl J Med. 2006 Mar 16;354(11):1157-65. Review. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2006 Apr 13;354(15):1655.</citation>
    <PMID>16540616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saczynski JS, Marcantonio ER, Quach L, Fong TG, Gross A, Inouye SK, Jones RN. Cognitive trajectories after postoperative delirium. N Engl J Med. 2012 Jul 5;367(1):30-9. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1112923.</citation>
    <PMID>22762316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin YY, He B, Chen J, Wang ZN. Can dexmedetomidine be a safe and efficacious sedative agent in post-cardiac surgery patients? a meta-analysis. Crit Care. 2012 Sep 27;16(5):R169. doi: 10.1186/cc11646.</citation>
    <PMID>23016926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corbett SM, Rebuck JA, Greene CM, Callas PW, Neale BW, Healey MA, Leavitt BJ. Dexmedetomidine does not improve patient satisfaction when compared with propofol during mechanical ventilation. Crit Care Med. 2005 May;33(5):940-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15891317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shehabi Y, Grant P, Wolfenden H, Hammond N, Bass F, Campbell M, Chen J. Prevalence of delirium with dexmedetomidine compared with morphine based therapy after cardiac surgery: a randomized controlled trial (DEXmedetomidine COmpared to Morphine-DEXCOM Study). Anesthesiology. 2009 Nov;111(5):1075-84. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181b6a783.</citation>
    <PMID>19786862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maldonado JR, Wysong A, van der Starre PJ, Block T, Miller C, Reitz BA. Dexmedetomidine and the reduction of postoperative delirium after cardiac surgery. Psychosomatics. 2009 May-Jun;50(3):206-17. doi: 10.1176/appi.psy.50.3.206.</citation>
    <PMID>19567759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dasta JF, Jacobi J, Sesti AM, McLaughlin TP. Addition of dexmedetomidine to standard sedation regimens after cardiac surgery: an outcomes analysis. Pharmacotherapy. 2006 Jun;26(6):798-805.</citation>
    <PMID>16716133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holmér Pettersson P, Jakobsson J, Owall A. Plasma concentrations following repeated rectal or intravenous administration of paracetamol after heart surgery. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2006 Jul;50(6):673-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16987360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Balachundhar Subramaniam</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Anesthesiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>analgesics</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>sedation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexmedetomidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acetaminophen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

