<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02545257</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>153/13/03/00/2015</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02545257</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of a Coordinated, Community-Based Medication Management Model for Home-Dwelling Aged in Primary Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development of a Coordinated, Community-Based Medication Management Model for Home-Dwelling Aged in Primary Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Helsinki University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>City of Lohja, Services for Aged People</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lohjan 1. Apteekki</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Social Insurance Institution, Finland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Helsinki University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this randomized controlled trial is to develop a coordinated,
      multiprofessional medication management model for home-dwelling aged in primary care and to
      study the effectiveness of this model. The main hypothesis is that the new model helps to
      identify aged people having potential risks with their medications and thus allows solving
      these risks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The demand for long-term home health care services is increasing due the demographic and
      societal developments. Aged people needing home care are increasingly older, have many
      chronic diseases and use multiple medicines and thus, are at high risk for drug-related
      problems (DRPs). In Finland, national and local healthcare and aged care strategies target to
      allowing aged people (over 65 years) living in their own homes as long as possible. This
      minimizes the costs of institutionalized care and also targets to add the quality of life of
      aged people. New approaches and service models are needed to meet these challenges.

      The present study focuses on the development of a coordinated medication management model
      which aims to ensure the safe medication practises for home-dwelling aged in primary care. In
      the previous parts of this study project were developed a model for comprehensive medication
      review process (CMR) and a Drug-Related Problem Risk Assessment Tool. The present study uses
      a multistage intervention in which medications are reviewed (prescription review) in a
      community pharmacy using the SFINX-database to identify clinically significant drug-drug
      interactions and the Salko-database which identifies potentially inappropriate medications
      for aged people. In the next stage practical nurses use the Drug-Related Problem Risk
      Assessment Tool to identify potential risks. The following stages are based on the results
      from the risk assessment tool. Potential options are, e.g.,physician consultation, more
      frequent home care visits, counselling given by the community pharmacy or comprehensive
      medication review (CMR). The CMR process is only targeted to a limited group of study
      participants with clinically significant DRP who probably will benefit from more
      comprehensive CMR.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>GDS-15 (Geriatric Depression Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MMSE (Mini-Mental State Examination)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive ability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MNA (Malnutrition Assessment)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to rise from a chair and return to the seated position 5 times (Lower extremity function).</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Orthostatic hypotension (Short test, Freeman et al. 2011)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUDIT-C (Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test, version C)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>UDI-6 (Urinary Distress Inventory)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rava (Functioning and disability, Finnish Consulting Group)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Potentially inappropriate medicines (PIM) (Clinically significant drug-drug interactions, potentially inappropriate medicines for aged), identified from medication list review chart</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>PIMs are identified with prescription review using SFINX database (clinically significant drug-drug interactions) and Salko database (e.g., for identifying potentially inappropriate medicines for the aged, anticholinergic and serotonergic load).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of health care services: visits to physician</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 and 24 months from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Number of visits (previous 3 months)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of health care services: hospital days</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 and 24 months from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Number of hospital days (previous 3 months)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of health care services: home care services</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 and 24 months from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Services delivered to home (previous 3 months)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">191</enrollment>
  <condition>Drug Therapy, Combination</condition>
  <condition>Inappropriate Prescribing</condition>
  <condition>Polypharmacy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active comparator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In addition to normal, standard care, participants allocated to intervention group will receive a coordinated medication management model containing prescription review, drug-related problems (DRP) risk assessment and required action based on the DRP risk assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group (standard care)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Normal, standard care (control group)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Coordinated medication management model</intervention_name>
    <description>Stage I: a prescription review conducted by community pharmacists Stage II: practical nurse-administered Drug-related Problem Risk Assessment Tool Stage III: Required health care action based on the result of the DRP -Risk Assessment Tool</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active comparator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Home-dwelling over 65 year-old persons receiving regular home care from the City of
             Lohja

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Home care is not given regularly
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marja SA Airaksinen, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Helsinki University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Juha T Puustinen, Docent</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Helsinki University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>1st Pharmacy of Lohja</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lohja</city>
        <zip>08100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Services for aged people</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lohja</city>
        <zip>08100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://urn.fi/URN:ISBN:978-952-10-7698-5</url>
    <description>Leikola S. Development and Application of Comprehensive Medication Review Procedure to Community-Dwelling Elderly. Doctoral Thesis, University of Helsinki, 2012</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://urn.fi/URN:ISBN:978-951-29-5710-1</url>
    <description>Puustinen J. Benzodiazepines and Cognitive Functioning in Older Adults. With Emphasis on Long-Term Use and Withdrawal. Doctoral Thesis, University of Turku, 2014</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dimitrow MS, Leikola SN, Kivelä SL, Passi S, Lukkari P, Airaksinen MS. Feasibility of a practical nurse administered risk assessment tool for drug-related problems in home care. Scand J Public Health. 2015 Nov;43(7):761-9. doi: 10.1177/1403494815591719. Epub 2015 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26152737</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dimitrow MS, Mykkänen SI, Leikola SN, Kivelä SL, Lyles A, Airaksinen MS. Content validation of a tool for assessing risks for drug-related problems to be used by practical nurses caring for home-dwelling clients aged ≥65 years: a Delphi survey. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 2014 Aug;70(8):991-1002. doi: 10.1007/s00228-014-1699-5. Epub 2014 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24879605</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dimitrow MS, Airaksinen MS, Kivelä SL, Lyles A, Leikola SN. Comparison of prescribing criteria to evaluate the appropriateness of drug treatment in individuals aged 65 and older: a systematic review. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2011 Aug;59(8):1521-30. doi: 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2011.03497.x. Epub 2011 Jul 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21797829</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bulajeva A, Labberton L, Leikola S, Pohjanoksa-Mäntylä M, Geurts MM, de Gier JJ, Airaksinen M. Medication review practices in European countries. Res Social Adm Pharm. 2014 Sep-Oct;10(5):731-40. doi: 10.1016/j.sapharm.2014.02.005. Epub 2014 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24661800</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Leikola S, Tuomainen L, Peura S, Laurikainen A, Lyles A, Savela E, Airaksinen M. Comprehensive medication review: development of a collaborative procedure. Int J Clin Pharm. 2012 Aug;34(4):510-4. doi: 10.1007/s11096-012-9662-y. Epub 2012 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22711383</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Leikola S, Dimitrow M, Lyles A, Pitkälä K, Airaksinen M. Potentially inappropriate medication use among Finnish non-institutionalized people aged ≥65 years: a register-based, cross-sectional, national study. Drugs Aging. 2011 Mar 1;28(3):227-36. doi: 10.2165/11586890-000000000-00000.</citation>
    <PMID>21329402</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Leikola SN, Tuomainen L, Ovaskainen H, Peura S, Sevón-Vilkman N, Tanskanen P, Airaksinen MS. Continuing education course to attain collaborative comprehensive medication review competencies. Am J Pharm Educ. 2009 Oct 1;73(6):108.</citation>
    <PMID>19885077</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Leikola SN, Virolainen J, Tuomainen L, Tuominen RK, Airaksinen MS. Comprehensive medication reviews for elderly patients: findings and recommendations to physicians. J Am Pharm Assoc (2003). 2012 Sep-Oct;52(5):630-3.</citation>
    <PMID>23023843</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dimitrow M, Leikola S, Kivelä SL, Airaksinen M, Mykkänen S, Puustinen J. [Inappropriate medication use among the aged. Review of the criteria]. Duodecim. 2013;129(11):1159-66. Review. Finnish.</citation>
    <PMID>23819202</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Puustinen J, Lähteenmäki R, Polo-Kantola P, Salo P, Vahlberg T, Lyles A, Neuvonen PJ, Partinen M, Räihä I, Kivelä SL. Effect of withdrawal from long-term use of temazepam, zopiclone or zolpidem as hypnotic agents on cognition in older adults. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 2014 Mar;70(3):319-29. doi: 10.1007/s00228-013-1613-6. Epub 2013 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24337417</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Puustinen J, Nurminen J, Vahlberg T, Lyles A, Isoaho R, Räihä I, Kivelä SL. CNS medications as predictors of precipitous cognitive decline in the cognitively disabled aged: a longitudinal population-based study. Dement Geriatr Cogn Dis Extra. 2012 Jan;2(1):57-68. doi: 10.1159/000336710. Epub 2012 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22619661</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Puustinen J, Nurminen J, Löppönen M, Vahlberg T, Isoaho R, Räihä I, Kivelä SL. Use of CNS medications and cognitive decline in the aged: a longitudinal population-based study. BMC Geriatr. 2011 Nov 1;11:70. doi: 10.1186/1471-2318-11-70.</citation>
    <PMID>22044595</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nurminen J, Puustinen J, Piirtola M, Vahlberg T, Lyles A, Kivelä SL. Opioids, antiepileptic and anticholinergic drugs and the risk of fractures in patients 65 years of age and older: a prospective population-based study. Age Ageing. 2013 May;42(3):318-24. doi: 10.1093/ageing/afs178. Epub 2012 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23204431</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Puustinen J, Nurminen J, Kukola M, Vahlberg T, Laine K, Kivelä SL. Associations between use of benzodiazepines or related drugs and health, physical abilities and cognitive function: a non-randomised clinical study in the elderly. Drugs Aging. 2007;24(12):1045-59.</citation>
    <PMID>18020536</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Helsinki University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Terhi Toivo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Project coordinator, MSc (Pharm), PhD student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Aged people</keyword>
  <keyword>Home care</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug related problems, DRPs</keyword>
  <keyword>Coordinated medication management model</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

