<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02541461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-04-026-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02541461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Body Composition After Laparoscopic Gastrectomy for Gastric Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Changes in Body Composition After Laparoscopic Gastrectomy for Stomach Cancer - Comparison Between Billoth I and Roux-en-Y Anastomosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hanyang University Seoul Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hanyang University Seoul Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nutritional status including changes of body composition is one of the most important
      clinical determinants of outcome after gastrectomy for gastric cancer. The laparoscopic
      gastrectomy is considered to be minimally invasive and to have favorable outcome that is
      widely used in South Korea. It was reported that several advantages of laparoscopic
      gastrectomy are the prevention of overt weight loss and enhanced recovery of muscle mass at 6
      months after surgery. But there have been no longitudinal studies evaluating changes in the
      body composition according to the different type of anastomosis of laparoscopic gastrectomy.

      This study will therefore evaluate which of these two surgical procedures is most effective
      for postoperative body composition in laparoscopic gastrectomy patients, by comparing whether
      there are any differences in the amount of weight lost, lean body mass, fat mass, and lipid
      profile. It will help to better define the influence of anastomosis on changes of body
      composition after laparoscopic gastrectomy. This information can then be used by physicians
      to better make a plan to the patient's body make up and medical comorbidities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  All patients will undergo a laparoscopic gastrectomy for their gastric cancer proved to
           be stage I or II by preoperative screening diagnostic procedure. They will receive
           laparoscopic gastrectomy with either Billoth 1 or Roux-en-Y anastomosis.

        -  Pre-operative and 6 months post-operative body composition measurement will be performed
           on each patient. The whole body composition measurement will be assessed by Hologic
           4500/A dual energy X-ray absorptiometry system. The software performs calculations of
           the differential attenuations of the two photon energies and present data of percentage
           of fat, fat mass (g), lean mass (g), bone mineral content (g), bone mineral density
           (g/cm2), and total mass (g).

        -  Laboratory analysis - There is a battery of labs that are ordered in both the
           pre-operative and 6 months post-operative time frame. These labs are ordered independent
           of the patient's participation in the study. These labs are ordered to evaluate and to
           assist management of the patient's medical comorbidities as well as to assess for
           adequate nutritional intake and balance.

        -  Queries on nutritional intake and exercise will be made at each post-operative
           appointment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body composition (changes in lean tissue mass and fatty tissue mass Using DEXA machine produced by Hologic)</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-surgery and 6 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Using DEXA machine produced by Hologic, changes in lean tissue mass and fatty tissue mass following either the laparoscopic Billoth I or Roux-en-Y anastomosis will be assessed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight loss</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-surgery and 6 months post-surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in lipid profile</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-surgery and 6 months post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Using laboratory analysis, changes in the lipid profiles following either the laparoscopic Billoth I or Roux-en-Y anastomosis will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopic gastrectomy with Billoth 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will undergo a laparoscopic gastrectomy with Billoth 1 anastomosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopic gastrectomy with Roux-en-Y</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will undergo a laparoscopic gastrectomy with Roux-en-Y anastomosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laparoscopic gastrectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient enrolled will undergo either a laparoscopic gastrectomy with Billoth 1 anastomosis or Roux-en-Y anastomosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopic gastrectomy with Billoth 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopic gastrectomy with Roux-en-Y</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with gastric cancer planning laparoscopic gastrectomy

          -  Stage I and II patients by preoperative screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Distant metastasis

          -  Severe comorbidity

          -  Malnourished state

          -  Inability of access to enteral feeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yun Young Choi, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hanyang University Seoul Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ji Young Kim, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+82-2-2290-9264</phone>
    <email>gift02@hanmail.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hanyang University Seoul Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Song J, Lee HJ, Cho GS, Han SU, Kim MC, Ryu SW, Kim W, Song KY, Kim HH, Hyung WJ; Korean Laparoscopic Gastrointestinal Surgery Study (KLASS) Group. Recurrence following laparoscopy-assisted gastrectomy for gastric cancer: a multicenter retrospective analysis of 1,417 patients. Ann Surg Oncol. 2010 Jul;17(7):1777-86. doi: 10.1245/s10434-010-0932-4. Epub 2010 Feb 12.</citation>
    <PMID>20151217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kitano S, Iso Y, Moriyama M, Sugimachi K. Laparoscopy-assisted Billroth I gastrectomy. Surg Laparosc Endosc. 1994 Apr;4(2):146-8. Erratum in: Surg Laparosc Endosc. 2013 Oct;23(5):480.</citation>
    <PMID>8180768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee HJ, Kim HH, Kim MC, Ryu SY, Kim W, Song KY, Cho GS, Han SU, Hyung WJ, Ryu SW; Korean Laparoscopic Gastrointestinal Surgery Study Group. The impact of a high body mass index on laparoscopy assisted gastrectomy for gastric cancer. Surg Endosc. 2009 Nov;23(11):2473-9. doi: 10.1007/s00464-009-0419-1. Epub 2009 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19343439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim MC, Kim W, Kim HH, Ryu SW, Ryu SY, Song KY, Lee HJ, Cho GS, Han SU, Hyung WJ; Korean Laparoscopic Gastrointestinal Surgery Study (KLASS) Group. Risk factors associated with complication following laparoscopy-assisted gastrectomy for gastric cancer: a large-scale korean multicenter study. Ann Surg Oncol. 2008 Oct;15(10):2692-700. doi: 10.1245/s10434-008-0075-z. Epub 2008 Jul 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18663532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim HH, Hyung WJ, Cho GS, Kim MC, Han SU, Kim W, Ryu SW, Lee HJ, Song KY. Morbidity and mortality of laparoscopic gastrectomy versus open gastrectomy for gastric cancer: an interim report--a phase III multicenter, prospective, randomized Trial (KLASS Trial). Ann Surg. 2010 Mar;251(3):417-20. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181cc8f6b.</citation>
    <PMID>20160637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liedman B, Svedlund J, Sullivan M, Larsson L, Lundell L. Symptom control may improve food intake, body composition, and aspects of quality of life after gastrectomy in cancer patients. Dig Dis Sci. 2001 Dec;46(12):2673-80.</citation>
    <PMID>11768259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiyama T, Mizutani T, Okuda T, Fujita I, Tokunaga A, Tajiri T, Barbul A. Postoperative changes in body composition after gastrectomy. J Gastrointest Surg. 2005 Mar;9(3):313-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15749590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdiev S, Kodera Y, Fujiwara M, Koike M, Nakayama G, Ohashi N, Tanaka C, Sakamoto J, Nakao A. Nutritional recovery after open and laparoscopic gastrectomies. Gastric Cancer. 2011 Jun;14(2):144-9. doi: 10.1007/s10120-011-0021-9. Epub 2011 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21327442</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aoyama T, Yoshikawa T, Hayashi T, Hasegawa S, Tsuchida K, Yamada T, Cho H, Ogata T, Fujikawa H, Yukawa N, Oshima T, Rino Y, Masuda M. Randomized comparison of surgical stress and the nutritional status between laparoscopy-assisted and open distal gastrectomy for gastric cancer. Ann Surg Oncol. 2014 Jun;21(6):1983-90. doi: 10.1245/s10434-014-3509-9. Epub 2014 Feb 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24499830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jeon TY, Lee S, Kim HH, Kim YJ, Lee JG, Jeong DW, Kim YJ. Long-term changes in gut hormones, appetite and food intake 1 year after subtotal gastrectomy with normal body weight. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2010 Aug;64(8):826-31. doi: 10.1038/ejcn.2010.83. Epub 2010 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>20485300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liedman B, Henningsson A, Mellström D, Lundell L. Changes in bone metabolism and body composition after total gastrectomy: results of a longitudinal study. Dig Dis Sci. 2000 Apr;45(4):819-24.</citation>
    <PMID>10759255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 1, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 3, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 4, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 10, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 10, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hanyang University Seoul Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ji Young Kim</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Procedure: Laparoscopic gastrectomy with Billroth I</keyword>
  <keyword>Procedure: Laparoscopic gastrectomy with Roux-en-Y</keyword>
  <keyword>Other: Body composition measurement</keyword>
  <keyword>Other: Lipid profile</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

