<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02546167</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCC 14415, 822756</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02546167</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CART-BCMA Cells for Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study Of Redirected Autologous T Cells Engineered To Contain an Anti-BCMA scFv Coupled To TCRζ And 4-1BB Signaling Domains in Patients With Relapsed and/or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Open-label, single-center, pilot study to assess the safety and feasibility of infusion of
      autologous T cells expressing BCMA (B-cell maturation antigen)-specific chimeric antigen
      receptors with tandem TCR and 4-1BB costimulatory domains (referred to as CART-BCMA ) in
      adult patients with multiple myeloma (MM). CART-BCMA cells will be given as a split dose
      intravenous infusion over 3 days. The duration of active intervention and monitoring is
      approximately 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>will receive 1-5x10^7 CART-BCMA cells given as a split dose infusion over 3 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cyclophosphamide infusion prior to 1-5x10^7 CART BCMA cells given as a split dose infusion over 3 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cyclophosphamide infusion prior to 1-5x10^8 CART BCMA cells given as a split dose infusion over 3 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CART-BCMA</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Subjects must have a confirmed prior diagnosis of active MM as defined by the updated
             IMWG criteria101..

          2. Subjects must have relapsed or refractory disease after either one of the following:

               1. At least 3 prior regimens, which must have contained an alkylating agent,
                  proteasome inhibitor, and immunomodulatory agent (IMiD).

                  OR

               2. At least 2 prior regimens if &quot;double-refractory&quot; to a proteasome inhibitor and
                  IMiD, defined as progression on or within 60 days of treatment with these agents.

             Note: Induction therapy, stem cell transplant, and maintenance therapy, if given
             sequentially without intervening progression, should be considered as 1 &quot;regimen&quot;.

          3. Subjects must have signed written, informed consent.

          4. Subjects must be ≥ 18 years of age.

          5. Subjects must be at least 90 days since autologous or allogeneic stem cell transplant,
             if performed.

          6. Subjects must have adequate vital organ function:

               1. Serum creatinine ≤ 2.5 or estimated creatinine clearance ≥30 ml/min and not
                  dialysis-dependent.

               2. Absolute neutrophil count ≥1000/μl and platelet count ≥50,000/μl (≥30,000/μl if
                  bone marrow plasma cells are ≥50% of cellularity).

               3. SGOT ≤ 3x the upper limit of normal and total bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dl (except for
                  patients in whom hyperbilirubinemia is attributed to Gilbert's syndrome).

               4. Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) ≥ 45%. LVEF assessment must have been
                  performed within 8 weeks of enrollment.

               5. Toxicities from prior therapies, with the exception of peripheral neuropathy
                  attributable to bortezomib, must have recovered to grade ≤ 2 according to the CTC
                  4.0 criteria or to the subject's prior baseline.

          7. Subjects must have an ECOG performance status of 0-2.

          8. Subjects must have measurable disease on study entry, which must include at least 1 of
             the following:

               1. Serum M-spike ≥ 0.5 g/dL*

               2. 24 hr urine M-spike ≥ 200mg

               3. Involved serum FLC ≥ 50 mg/L with abnormal ratio

               4. Measurable plasmacytoma on exam or imaging

               5. Bone marrow plasma cells ≥ 20% (bone marrow biopsy only required at screening if
                  no other measurable disease is present).

                    -  Note: Patients with IgA myeloma in whom serum protein electrophoresis is
                       deemed unreliable, due to co-migration of normal serum proteins with the
                       paraprotein in the beta region, may be considered eligible as long as total
                       serum IgA level is elevated above normal range.

          9. Subjects of reproductive potential must agree to use acceptable birth control methods.

        IMWG Criteria for Diagnosis of Multiple Myeloma Presence of an M-component in serum and/or
        urine plus clonal plasma cells in the bone marrow and/or a documented clonal plasmacytoma.
        In patients with no detectable M-component, an abnormal serum FLC ratio on the serum FLC
        assay can substitute and satisfy this criterion. For patients, with no serum or urine
        M-component and normal serum FLC ratio, the baseline bone marrow must have ≥10% clonal
        plasma cells; these patients are referred to as having 'non-secretory myeloma'. Patients
        with biopsy-proven amyloidosis and/or systemic light chain deposition disease (LCDD) should
        be classified as 'myeloma with documented amyloidosis' or 'myeloma with documented LCDD,'
        respectively if they have ≥30% plasma cells and/or myeloma-related bone disease.

        PLUS one or more of the following, which must be attributable to the underlying plasma cell
        disorder:

          -  Calcium elevation (&gt;11.5 mg/dl)

          -  Renal insufficiency (creatinine &gt;2 mg/dl)

          -  Anemia (hemoglobin &lt;10 g/dl or at 2 g/dl below normal)

          -  Bone disease (lytic lesions or osteopenia) OR one of the following &quot;myeloma-defining
             events&quot;

          -  Bone marrow plasma cells ≥60% of cellularity

          -  Serum free kappa:lambda ratio ≥100:1 (or ≤1:100), with involved free light chain ≥100
             mg/L

          -  More than 1 focal bone lesion on MRI

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Be pregnant or lactating.

          -  Have inadequate venous access for or contraindications to leukapheresis.

          -  Have any active and uncontrolled infection.

          -  Have active hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or HIV infection.

          -  Any uncontrolled medical or psychiatric disorder that would preclude participation as
             outlined.

          -  Have NYHA Class III or IV heart failure, unstable angina, or a history of recent
             (within 6 months) myocardial infarction or sustained (&gt;30 seconds) ventricular
             tachyarrhythmias.

          -  Have received prior gene therapy or gene-modified cellular immunotherapy. Subject may
             have received, however, non-gene-modified autologous T-cells in association with an
             anti-myeloma vaccine (e.g., hTERT or MAGEA3) or vaccination against infectious agents
             (e.g., influenza or pneumococcus) as was performed on our previous studies.

          -  Have active auto-immune disease, including connective tissue disease, uveitis,
             sarcoidosis, inflammatory bowel disease, or multiple sclerosis, or have a history of
             severe (as judged by the principal investigator) autoimmune disease requiring
             prolonged immunosuppressive therapy.

          -  Have a history of neurodegenerative or central nervous system movement disorder.

          -  Have prior or active central nervous system (CNS) involvement (e.g. leptomeningeal
             disease, parenchymal masses) with myeloma. Screening for this (e.g. with lumbar
             puncture) is not required unless suspicious symptoms or radiographic findings are
             present. Subjects with calvarial disease that extends intracranially and involves the
             dura will be excluded, even if CSF is negative for myeloma.

          -  Have active acute or chronic graft-versus-host-disease (GVHD), or require
             immunosuppressant medications for GVHD, within 4 weeks of enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adam Cohen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

