<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02566070</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>150311</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02566070</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>COntinuous vs BOlus Nasogastric Feeding in Mechanically Ventilated Pediatric Patients 2</brief_title>
  <acronym>COBO2</acronym>
  <official_title>COntinuous vs BOlus Nasogastric Feeding in Mechanically Ventilated Pediatric Patients 2</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Akron Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Akron Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This multi-center, prospective, randomized comparative effectiveness intervention study will
      evaluate continuous feeding (CGF) and bolus gastric feeding (BGF) protocols and their effect
      on delivery of prescribed nutrition and feeding intolerance in mechanically ventilated
      critically ill children for up through 12 hours post achievement goal feeds or exclusion from
      feeding protocol, whichever comes first, to a maximum of 10 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A significant number of children (&gt;30%) are malnourished upon admission to the Pediatric
      Intensive Care Unit (PICU). In addition, critically ill children are at risk to develop new
      or worsened malnutrition during their PICU stay. Adequate nutritional support of critically
      ill children reduces mortality and morbidities, such as hospital acquired health care
      infections. Inadequate nutrition during hospitalization results in poor healing, increased
      risk for hospital acquired conditions, and prolonged length of stay, all of which contribute
      to increased health care costs. Even previously healthy children experiencing critical
      illness are at high risk for malnourishment because of increased protein and/or caloric needs
      at a time when oral intake is inadequate to meet their metabolic needs. A gap in the
      literature exists regarding the effectiveness of 2 delivery modes for gastric enteral
      nutrition: continuous gastric (stomach) feeding (CGF), the steady infusion of liquid
      nutrition is delivered at an hourly volume via an infusion pump, and bolus gastric feeding
      (BGF), whereby nutrition is intermittently delivered over a prescribed period of time,
      followed by a period of rest.

      Enteral nutrition (EN, or tube feeding) in the PICU is commonly given via continuous gastric
      feeding. However, feeding by bolus or intermittent methods better mimics normal body function
      and may minimize interruptions to feedings improving nutritional intake. This study proposes
      to address the gap in the literature regarding the best method to deliver EN to achieve
      prescribed nutritional goals and avoid feeding interruptions in the mechanically ventilated,
      critically ill pediatric population.

      This multi-center, prospective, randomized, controlled study includes children 1-month to
      12-years who are on a ventilator and have EN started within 48-hours of admission. Subjects
      are randomized to CGF or BGF. Feeding volume is advanced in a weight-based manner every
      3-hours to target volume; caloric density is then increased to goal. Feeding intolerance
      measures are assessed every 3-hours. Study sites are assigned to follow one of two feeding
      intolerance criteria to better define the measures and thresholds necessary to halt and
      resume feeds for safety purposes. Incidence, duration and category of feeding interruptions
      are recorded. Statistical significance is defined as p &lt; 0.05. The findings will be submitted
      for oral and poster presentation and manuscripts submitted for publication.

      As the focus of nursing remains not on disease and cure, rather on healing and health,
      nutrition is embedded in this philosophy. Our vision of nursing is to put the patient in the
      best position to heal him or herself. Mitigating existing malnutrition and/or avoiding newly
      acquired nutritional deficits decreases the risk of mortality and hospital acquired adverse
      events in this population. This study seeks to optimize delivery of nutrition as therapy as
      imperative to optimize clinical and functional outcomes in the critically ill child.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to goal feeds (TTGF-defined as time to attain goal feeds) is decreased in a bolus compared to continuous gastric feeding protocol.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 48 hours post enteral feeding</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feeding interruptions as measured by minutes feeds are withheld.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 48 hours post enteral feeding</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastric residual volumes in milliliters</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 48 hours post enteral feeding</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of ventilator associated infections (VAI) as reported by Infection Control Department.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 48 hours post enteral feeding</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen Saturation Index as calculated by [(FiO2 x Mean Airway Pressure)/SpO2].</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 48 hours post enteral feeding</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emesis as a binary yes/no event</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 48 hours post enteral feeding</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abdominal girth in centimeters</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 48 hours post enteral feeding</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">860</enrollment>
  <condition>Dietary Modification</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous Gastric Feeding (CGF)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CGF group will have total daily enteral nutrition requirement delivered at a constant rate via infusion over the entire 24 hour period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bolus Gastric Feeding (BGF)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BGF group will have total daily enteral nutrition requirement delivered in interval, finite volumes over the course of the 24 hour period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous Gastric Feeding</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous Gastric Feeding (CGF)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bolus Gastric Feeding</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bolus Gastric Feeding (BGF)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all medical patients hospitalized in the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit (PICU)

          -  aged 1 month through 12 years of age

          -  mechanically ventilated within the first 24 hours of admission

          -  patients with an anticipated duration of mechanical ventilation greater than 48 hours

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of acute or chronic gastrointestinal pathology

          -  primary cardiac surgery or other surgical service patients

          -  enteral nutrition initiated greater than 48 hours post PICU admission, or

          -  enteral nutrition was initiated prior to admission to PICU
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ann-Marie Brown, PhD, CPNP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Akron Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Pitz, MPA, CRA</last_name>
    <phone>330-543-8272</phone>
    <email>jpitz@chmca.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Aris Eliades, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <phone>330-543-3193</phone>
    <email>AEliades@chmca.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shands Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32608</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charlene Leonard, MSN, CNP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcy N Singleton, ARNP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Medical Center of Akron</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akron</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital at Oklahoma University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73117</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christine Allen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>405-271-5211</phone>
      <email>Christine-Allen@ouhsc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sharon Irving, PhD, ARNP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Theresa Mikhailov, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehta NM, Bechard LJ, Cahill N, Wang M, Day A, Duggan CP, Heyland DK. Nutritional practices and their relationship to clinical outcomes in critically ill children--an international multicenter cohort study*. Crit Care Med. 2012 Jul;40(7):2204-11. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e31824e18a8.</citation>
    <PMID>22564954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mikhailov TA, Kuhn EM, Manzi J, Christensen M, Collins M, Brown AM, Dechert R, Scanlon MC, Wakeham MK, Goday PS. Early enteral nutrition is associated with lower mortality in critically ill children. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2014 May;38(4):459-66. doi: 10.1177/0148607113517903. Epub 2014 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24403379</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehta NM, McAleer D, Hamilton S, Naples E, Leavitt K, Mitchell P, Duggan C. Challenges to optimal enteral nutrition in a multidisciplinary pediatric intensive care unit. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2010 Jan-Feb;34(1):38-45. doi: 10.1177/0148607109348065. Epub 2009 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19903872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khorasani EN, Mansouri F. Effect of early enteral nutrition on morbidity and mortality in children with burns. Burns. 2010 Nov;36(7):1067-71. doi: 10.1016/j.burns.2009.12.005. Epub 2010 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>20403667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schindler CA, Mikhailov TA, Kuhn EM, Christopher J, Conway P, Ridling D, Scott AM, Simpson VS. Protecting fragile skin: nursing interventions to decrease development of pressure ulcers in pediatric intensive care. Am J Crit Care. 2011 Jan;20(1):26-34; quiz 35. doi: 10.4037/ajcc2011754.</citation>
    <PMID>21196569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen BM, Goonewardene LA, Field CJ, Joffe AR, Van Aerde JE, Olstad DL, Clandinin MT. Low energy intakes are associated with adverse outcomes in infants after open heart surgery. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2013 Mar;37(2):254-60. doi: 10.1177/0148607112463075. Epub 2012 Oct 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23064254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehta NM, Compher C; A.S.P.E.N. Board of Directors. A.S.P.E.N. Clinical Guidelines: nutrition support of the critically ill child. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2009 May-Jun;33(3):260-76. doi: 10.1177/0148607109333114.</citation>
    <PMID>19398612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown A-M, Forbes ML, Vitale VS, Tirodker UH, Zeller R. Effects of a gastric feeding protocol on efficiency of enteral nutrition in critically ill infants and children. ICAN: Infant, Child, &amp; Adolescent Nutrition. 2012;4(3):175-180.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tume L, Carter B, Latten L. A UK and Irish survey of enteral nutrition practices in paediatric intensive care units. Br J Nutr. 2013 Apr 14;109(7):1304-22. doi: 10.1017/S0007114512003042. Epub 2012 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>22853808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohr F, Steffen R. Physiology of gastrointestinal motility. In: Wyllie R, Hyams JS, Kay M, eds. Pediatric Gastrointestinal and Liver Disease. 4th ed. Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier/Saunders; 2011:39-49.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen YC, Chou SS, Lin LH, Wu LF. The effect of intermittent nasogastric feeding on preventing aspiration pneumonia in ventilated critically ill patients. J Nurs Res. 2006 Sep;14(3):167-80.</citation>
    <PMID>16967399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee JS, Auyeung TW. A comparison of two feeding methods in the alleviation of diarrhoea in older tube-fed patients: a randomised controlled trial. Age Ageing. 2003 Jul;32(4):388-93.</citation>
    <PMID>12851181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee JS, Kwok T, Chui PY, Ko FW, Lo WK, Kam WC, Mok HL, Lo R, Woo J. Can continuous pump feeding reduce the incidence of pneumonia in nasogastric tube-fed patients? A randomized controlled trial. Clin Nutr. 2010 Aug;29(4):453-8. doi: 10.1016/j.clnu.2009.10.003. Epub 2009 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19910085</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horn D, Chaboyer W. Gastric feeding in critically ill children: a randomized controlled trial. Am J Crit Care. 2003 Sep;12(5):461-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14503430</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hurt RT, McClave SA. Gastric residual volumes in critical illness: what do they really mean? Crit Care Clin. 2010 Jul;26(3):481-90, viii-ix. doi: 10.1016/j.ccc.2010.04.010.</citation>
    <PMID>20643301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skillman HE. Monitoring the efficacy of a PICU nutrition therapy protocol. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2011 Jul;35(4):445-6. doi: 10.1177/0148607111409046. Epub 2011 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21632953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reignier J, Mercier E, Le Gouge A, Boulain T, Desachy A, Bellec F, Clavel M, Frat JP, Plantefeve G, Quenot JP, Lascarrou JB; Clinical Research in Intensive Care and Sepsis (CRICS) Group. Effect of not monitoring residual gastric volume on risk of ventilator-associated pneumonia in adults receiving mechanical ventilation and early enteral feeding: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2013 Jan 16;309(3):249-56. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.196377.</citation>
    <PMID>23321763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skillman HE. How you can improve the delivery of enteral nutrition in your PICU. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2010 Jan-Feb;34(1):99-100. doi: 10.1177/0148607109344725.</citation>
    <PMID>20054060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weckwerth JA. Monitoring enteral nutrition support tolerance in infants and children. Nutr Clin Pract. 2004 Oct;19(5):496-503.</citation>
    <PMID>16215145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horn D, Chaboyer W, Schluter PJ. Gastric residual volumes in critically ill paediatric patients: a comparison of feeding regimens. Aust Crit Care. 2004 Aug;17(3):98-100, 102-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15493856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooper VB, Haut C. Preventing ventilator-associated pneumonia in children: an evidence-based protocol. Crit Care Nurse. 2013 Jun;33(3):21-9; quiz 30. doi: 10.4037/ccn2013204.</citation>
    <PMID>23727849</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas NJ, Shaffer ML, Willson DF, Shih MC, Curley MA. Defining acute lung disease in children with the oxygenation saturation index. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2010 Jan;11(1):12-7. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e3181b0653d.</citation>
    <PMID>19561556</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poulard F, Dimet J, Martin-Lefevre L, Bontemps F, Fiancette M, Clementi E, Lebert C, Renard B, Reignier J. Impact of not measuring residual gastric volume in mechanically ventilated patients receiving early enteral feeding: a prospective before-after study. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2010 Mar-Apr;34(2):125-30. doi: 10.1177/0148607109344745. Epub 2009 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19861528</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ukleja A. Altered GI motility in critically Ill patients: current understanding of pathophysiology, clinical impact, and diagnostic approach. Nutr Clin Pract. 2010 Feb;25(1):16-25. doi: 10.1177/0884533609357568. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20130154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown A-M. A Comparison of Two Gastric Feeding Approaches in Mechanically Ventilated Pediatric Patients. Akron, OH: The University of Akron; 2014:159.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 24, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Enteral feeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Continuous gastric feeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Bolus gastric feeding</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

