<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02560324</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>823286</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21DA040902</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02560324</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Ramelteon on Smoking Abstinence</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAP</acronym>
  <official_title>Repurposing Melatonin Receptor Agonists as Adjunct Treatments for Smoking Cessation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover study to test whether a
      medication called ramelteon (Brand Name: Remeron) will help smokers quit and whether it
      reduces sleep problems that smokers experience during a quit attempt.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ramelteon, an FDA-approved treatment for insomnia, is used to treat sleep problems (e.g.,
      specifically sleep onset latency) by enhancing melatonin receptor function. The investigators
      propose a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled crossover study.

      Fifty chronic smokers will complete a validated procedure for screening new medications. All
      subjects will receive 8mg ramelteon and placebo. The order in which ramelteon and placebo is
      received will be randomized across participants. This is a 6-week study consisting of two
      2-week medication phases separated by a 2-week washout. Each phase includes 1 week of ad
      libitum smoking (baseline) and 1 week of medication (ramelteon vs. placebo) plus transdermal
      nicotine patches while trying to abstain from smoking (quit assessment). Subjects will
      complete the same procedures during each study phase. Following completion of the study,
      participants will be offered standard smoking cessation treatment.

      For the duration of the study, subjects will be asked to keep sleep diaries and to wear an
      armband while sleeping, which provides objective indices of sleep duration and quality
      (SensewearPro® armband).

      The primary outcome will be the total number of days abstinent (out of 5) during each quit
      assessment period. Intermediate outcomes include sleep onset latency (self-report) and sleep
      efficiency (SensewearPro®).

      This study will provide information about the role of the melatonin system during brief
      abstinence and whether enhancing melatonin reduces abstinence-induced sleep problems that
      promote smoking relapse. Information obtained in this study may further establish the role of
      sleep disturbance in promoting smoking relapse.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total number of smoke-free days (biochemically verified) during each 5-day quit assessment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2 and Week 5</time_frame>
    <description>The quit assessment will begin the Monday morning of each quit week and will end that Friday. The total number of days of abstinence will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective sleep disturbance</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2 and Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep onset latency will be assessed via daily sleep diaries during each quit assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective sleep disturbance</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2 and Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep efficiency (the ratio of time spent asleep to the total time in bed) will be assessed via the SensewearPro armbands during each quit assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects of ramelteon</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (weeks 1 and 5); Quit assessments (weeks 2 and 6)</time_frame>
    <description>Side effects will be assessed at each in-person visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Tobacco Use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ramelteon</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will be performed using 8mg of ramelteon, which is currently marketed for the treatment of sleep problems. The proposed study follows the typical dosing regimen for ramelteon (8mg once a day) for 5 days during each quit assessment period.
Ramelteon will be purchased and packaged into blister packs by the Investigational Drug Service (IDS) at the University of Pennsylvania. In accordance with FDA recommendations, subjects will be instructed to take study medication within 30 min prior to going to bed and avoid taking study medication with or immediately after a high fat meal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>5-day placebo-controlled medication period.
Placebo ingredients will be purchased, encapsulated, and packaged into blister packs by the IDS at UPenn. Both active medication and placebo will look identical.
The study medication assignments for each participant in this project is randomized and counterbalanced. This means that approximately 50% of participants will take ramelteon during the first medication period, followed by the placebo in the second medication period. Alternatively, approximately 50% of participants will take the placebo during the first medication period, followed by ramelteon during the second medication period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ramelteon</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Ramelteon</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar Pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Smokers who are between 18 and 65 years of age who self-report smoking at least 10
             cigarettes per day for at least the last 6 months.

          2. Interest in quitting smoking in the next 2 to 4 months.

          3. Healthy as determined by the Study Physician, based on a medical evaluation including
             medical history and physical examination, and psychiatric evaluation.

          4. Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the combined consent and HIPAA form.

          5. Women of childbearing potential must consent to use a medically accepted method of
             birth control while participating in the study (e.g., condoms and spermicide, oral
             contraceptive, Depo-provera injection, contraceptive patch, tubal ligation).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Smoking Behavior:

          1. Current enrollment in a smoking cessation program, or use of other smoking cessation
             medications in the last month or plans to do either in the next 2 months.

          2. Daily use of chewing tobacco, snuff and/or snus, or electronic cigarettes.

          3. Provide a carbon monoxide (CO) breath sample reading less than 10 parts per million
             (ppm) at Intake.

        Alcohol/Drugs:

          1. Self-report current alcohol consumption that exceeds 25 standard drinks/week over the
             past 6 months. Subjects will be told to limit or avoid the use of alcohol while in the
             study to avoid any adverse reactions to the study medication.

          2. Self-reports substance use disorders (abuse or dependence involving alcohol, opiates,
             cocaine or other stimulants, or benzodiazepines; not nicotine) in the last 6 months.

          3. Providing a breath alcohol concentration (BrAC) reading of greater than or equal to
             0.01 during any session.

          4. A positive urine drug screen for cocaine, amphetamines, methamphetamines,
             benzodiazepines, PCP, methadone, barbiturates, marijuana, ecstasy (MDMA), oxycodone,
             tricyclic antidepressants, and opiates (low level cut-off 300 ng/mL) during any
             session.

        Psychiatric Exclusion (as determined by self-report on phone screen and/or through MINI
        during Intake):

          1. Current psychiatric disorders (depression, bipolar, schizophrenia, hypomanic/manic
             episode) as determined by self-report and/or MINI psychological interview.

          2. Past history of psychiatric disorders (including suicide attempt) other than
             depression as determined by self-report and/or MINI psychological interview.

          3. Suicide risk score on MINI greater than 1.

        Medical:

          1. Females who are currently pregnant, planning a pregnancy during the study, or
             currently breastfeeding/lactating. All female subjects shall undergo a urine pregnancy
             test at the Intake and must agree in writing to use an approved method of
             contraception. Following enrollment, pregnancy tests will be conducted at the
             beginning of each baseline week.

          2. For those with a history of jaundice/liver disease: liver function tests more than 20%
             outside of the normal range; Gamma-glutamyl Transpepsidase (GGT) values more than 20%
             outside of the normal range. If Albumin/Globulin ratios are 20% outside of normal
             range the abnormal value will be evaluated for clinical significance by the Study
             Physician and eligibility will determined on a case-by-case basis.

          3. Heart/Cardiovascular disease (e.g., angina, coronary heart disease, stroke, etc.) in
             the past 6 months.

          4. Endocrine or metabolic disorders (e.g., Type-I diabetes).

          5. Blood disorders (e.g., anemia or hemophilia).

          6. Uncontrolled hypertension (BP systolic greater than 159 and/or diastolic greater than
             99)*.

          7. Clinically significant dyssomnia (except insomnia; e.g. sleep apnea syndrome,
             narcolepsy).

               -  Participants presenting with SBP greater than 159 mmHg and/or DBP greater than 99
                  mmHg at the Intake visit will be instructed to sit quietly for 10 minutes. Then
                  the participant will have a second blood pressure reading taken after a 10 minute
                  period. If, after the second reading the SBP greater than 159 mmHg and the DBP
                  greater than 99 mmHg, the individual will be instructed to sit comfortably for 10
                  minutes and then have a third blood pressure reading. If, after the third reading
                  the SBP greater than 159 mmHg and the DBP greater than 99 mmHg, the individual
                  will be ineligible to participate.

        Medication:

          1. Current use or recent discontinuation (within the past month) of any of the following
             medications:

               1. Anti-anxiety or panic disorder medications (e.g., clonazepam, alprazolam).

               2. Anti-psychotic medications (e.g., thorazine, Seroquel).

               3. Mood-stabilizers (e.g., Lithium, Lamictal/lamotrigine, valproic acid,
                  Neurontin/gabapentin, Topamax/topiramate, Tegretol/carbamazepine).

               4. Prescription stimulants (e.g., Provigil, Ritalin, Adderall).

               5. Medications contraindicated with ramelteon (e.g., fluvoxamine, buprenorphine or
                  other medications metabolized by certain cytochrome P450 enzymes)

          2. Current use or recent discontinuation (within the past 2 weeks) of any of the
             following medications (subjects must agree to refrain from using any other sleep aids
             while enrolled in the study):

               1. Sleep medications (e.g., zolpidem/Ambien, eszopiclone/Lunesta)

               2. Over-the-counter sleep aids (e.g., melatonin, diphenhydramine/Benadryl)

          3. Daily use of opiate-containing medications for chronic pain (Duragesic/fentanyl
             patches, Percocet, Oxycontin). Smokers who report taking opiate-containing medications
             on an &quot;as-needed&quot; basis will be instructed to refrain from use until their study
             participation is over and that they will be tested to ensure they have complied with
             this requirement.

          4. Known allergy to study medication (e.g., angioedema).

        Subjects will be instructed to refrain from using any study prohibited drugs/medications
        (both recreational and prescription) throughout their participation in the study. After
        final eligibility is confirmed, subjects who report taking contraindicated medication(s)
        over the course of the study period may only remain eligible if the Study Physician and/or
        Principal Investigator determines that the contraindicated medication(s) do/did not impact
        the study design, data quality, and/or subject safety/welfare. Subjects are permitted to
        take necessary prescription medications not included within the exclusion list during the
        study.

        General Exclusion:

          1. Current, anticipated, or pending enrollment in another research program over the next
             2-3 months that could potentially affect subject safety and/or the study data/design
             as determined by the Principal Investigator and/or Study Physician.

          2. Not planning to live in the area for the next two months.

          3. Currently working night shift or rotating shift or other habitual alteration of the
             sleep/wake cycle.

          4. Allergy to latex or adhesive tape.

          5. Inability to provide informed consent or complete any of the study tasks as determined
             by the Principal Investigator.

          6. Not able to effectively communicate in English (reading, writing, speaking).

          7. Missing 2 or more doses during the medication period determined by self-report.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Ashare, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rebecca Ashare, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>215-746-5789</phone>
    <email>rlashare@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Interdisciplinary Research on Nicotine Addiction, School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rebecca Ashare, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>215-746-5789</phone>
      <email>rlashare@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Janet Audrain-McGovern, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Siegel, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David F Dinges, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 25, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ramelteon</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Insomnia</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco Dependence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

