<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02568540</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P00018023</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02568540</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>C Tracker, Hepatitis C, Care &amp; Collaboration - Patient Reported Outcomes Survey Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>CTracker</acronym>
  <official_title>preSmartphone App for Monitoring and Reporting of Hepatitis C Related Health Information: C Tracker Hepatitis C, Care &amp; Collaboration - Patient Reported Outcomes Survey Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Today's mobile devices (especially smartphones) are powerful ways to communicate new
      information to medical researchers. For this study, researchers at Boston Children's Hospital
      are asking people with hepatitis C to make use of their smartphones to help report
      information about themselves that may improve how hepatitis C is treated. This study uses a
      free app called C Tracker that can be installed from the Apple App Store onto the
      participants iPhone. The main goal of this research study is to use this app to report
      hepatitis C related health information to the researchers who are conducting this study. The
      investigators will ask participants about their health,activities, medications, and ways in
      which hepatitis C has impacted you. This information will be reported anonymously, which
      means that the researchers doing the study won't know who the participants are.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aims/Objectives

      Aim 1. Develop a free iPhone app (&quot;C TRACKER&quot;) designed to anonymously record and report
      Hepatitis C related health data to study investigators via periodic patient-reported surveys.

      Aim 2. Examine the feasibility of enrolling a large cohort of geographically dispersed cohort
      of subjects with hepatitis C who download and install the C TRACKER app, provide informed
      consent using the app, and complete study surveys using the app. The app will be made
      available to the public via the Apple App Store at no cost.

      Aim 3. Pilot usage of the app to track and analyze longitudinal measures of hepatitis C
      related health concerns, physical function, and physical activity via selected
      disease-specific as well as more broadly applicable patient-reported instruments, including
      regarding work productivity (WPAI-Hepatitis C), physical functioning (subsets/subscales of
      the MOS SF-36), physical activity (collected through Apple HealthKit), and prescribed
      medications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 4, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in hepatitis C medication therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>every 4 months for 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patient reported hepatitis C medication therapy. Medication type and timing will be compared against other patient-reported outcome measures looking at workforce productivity and physical health and function. Medication changes will be collected every 4 months (3 times a year).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Workforce Productivity and Activity Impairment Compared to changes in hepatitis C medication therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>every 2 weeks and data will be analyzed every 6 months, for a total of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Work Productivity and Activity Impairment Questionnaire: Hepatitis C V2.0 (WPAI:Hepatitis C, 6 questions in total) will be administered and compared to changes in Hepatitis C medication therapy. Measures will be collected every 2 weeks and data will be analyzed every 6 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Physical Function and Limitations Due to Physical Health Compared to changes in hepatitis C medication therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>every 4 months for 2 years; a subset will be analyzed every 2 weeks and data will be analyzed every 6 months, for a total of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>3. The Physical Function domain and Role Limitations Due to Physical Health domain of the Medical Outcomes Study (MOS) 36-Item Short Form Survey (14 questions in total) will be administered and compared to changes in Hepatitis C medication therapy. All questions will be collected every 4 months. A subset of The Physical Function domain and Role Limitations Due to Physical Health domain of the Medical Outcomes Study (MOS) 36-Item Short Form Survey (5 questions in total) will be administered every 2 weeks. Data will be analyzed every 6 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals who have been diagnosed with Hepatitis C.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Self-report a diagnosis of Hepatitis C

          -  English speaking individuals

          -  18 years or older

          -  Must have access to an iPhone that operates on iOS version 8 or higher

          -  Be able to download apps from the U.S. Apple iPhone Store, and enter data themselves
             or via a proxy on their behalf

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Individuals not meeting inclusion criteria will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02116</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://c-tracker.org</url>
    <description>Study website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kenneth Mandl</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chair in Biomedical Informatics and Population Health and Director, Computational Health informatics Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatitis C</keyword>
  <keyword>Smartphone</keyword>
  <keyword>app</keyword>
  <keyword>Tracker</keyword>
  <keyword>C Tracker</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

