<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02567266</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20150187</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH106536</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH064089</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02567266</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community Study of Outcome Monitoring for Emotional Disorders in Teens</brief_title>
  <acronym>COMET</acronym>
  <official_title>Community Study of Outcome Monitoring for Emotional Disorders in Teens</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Connecticut</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Emotional disorders, including an array of anxiety and depressive syndromes, are the most
      common psychiatric disorders among adolescents, are highly comorbid, and severely impair the
      lives of youth and their families. Extant evidence-based therapies target only single
      disorders or symptom domains, are often not adopted by community mental health center (CMHC)
      clinicians, and have only modest effect sizes. To improve the clinical outcomes of these
      youth, the proposed study tests the effectiveness of two novel interventions (a
      transdiagnostic intervention, the Unified Protocol for the Treatment of Emotional Disorders
      in Adolescents, and a measurement and feedback system, the Youth Outcomes Questionnaires)
      relative to usual care in CMHCs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Emotional disorders, encompassing a range of anxiety and depressive disorders, are the most
      prevalent and comorbid psychiatric disorders in adolescence. They are chronic, impairing,
      costly, and share overarching commonalities. Unfortunately, evidence-based therapies (EBTs)
      exist for only single disorders or domains (e.g., depression), are rarely adopted by
      community mental health center (CMHC) clinicians, and effect sizes are modest (40-50% of
      youth are treatment non-responders). Thus, methods for improving outcomes for these youth,
      particularly in CMHCs are needed. This study tests the effectiveness of two novel
      interventions to address this need. The first intervention is a transdiagnostic treatment
      (the Unified Protocol for the Treatment of Emotional Disorders in Adolescents, UP-A), a
      promising new approach that uses a small number of common strategies to treat a broad range
      of emotional disorders. Transdiagnostic models align with NIH's initiative to advance the
      understanding and treatment of psychopathology using the Research Domain Criteria (RDoC).
      Importantly, this treatment approach is expected to improve client outcomes and have quicker
      uptake by CMHC clinicians because:

        1. comorbidity is the rule, rather than the exception making this intervention more
           relevant for the patients seen in CMHCs, and

        2. protocols cutting across diagnostic boundaries reduce training burden.

      The second intervention is a standardized monitoring and feedback system (MFS; Youth Outcomes
      Questionnaires, YOQ). This intervention can be built into the existing electronic medical
      records infrastructure of CMHCs and thus has appeal for its acceptability, ease of transport
      into clinical practice, and sustainability. Emerging data suggests that MFS alone improves
      outcomes relative to TAU but has not been adequately tested in youth. As an added value, this
      study also addresses a common threat to the internal validity of previous RCTs evaluating an
      EBT by isolating the confounding effects of increased measurement and feedback to clinicians.
      Finally, addressing a central aim of this RFA and making a unique and critical contribution
      to the treatment literature, this study will examine theoretically-linked mechanisms (both
      patient and provider level) of treatment outcomes of both the UP-A and the YOQ. This
      collaborative R01 proposal (in response to RFA-MH-15-325) was prepared by Drs. Ehrenreich-May
      and Jensen-Doss at the University of Miami (Miami) and Dr. Ginsburg at The University of
      Connecticut School of Medicine (UConn; applications are identical). To test study aims, 222
      adolescents (ages 12-17) with anxiety and/or depressive disorders will be recruited in CMHCs
      in Miami and Hartford (111 adolescents and 9 clinicians at each site).

      Both adolescents and clinicians will be randomized to one of three conditions:

        1. TAU alone;

        2. TAU plus YOQ, and

        3. UP-A plus YOQ.

      Research assessments will occur at baseline, 8 weeks and 16 weeks after treatment initiation
      and a 3-month follow-up. If effective, these interventions have the potential to change
      clinical practice in CMHCs by equipping clinicians with more effective interventions that can
      be applied to a broad range of patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over time in Clinical Global Impression-Improvement (CGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks, 3 month follow up</time_frame>
    <description>This is a independent evaluator rated measure of improvement in symptoms and functioning</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over time in Clinical Global Impression-Severity (CGI-S)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks, 3 month follow up</time_frame>
    <description>This is a independent evaluator rated measure of severity of symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over time in Children's Global Assessment Scale (CGAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks, 3 month follow up</time_frame>
    <description>This is a independent evaluator rated measure of global functional impairment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">222</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unified Protocol for Adolescents (UP-A)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be treated with the Unified Protocol for the Treatment of Emotional Disorders in Adolescence. Their clinicians will also receive feedback using the Youth Outcomes Questionnaire feedback system.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual Plus (TAU+)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be treated by clinicians who receive feedback using the Youth Outcomes Questionnaire, but who otherwise use Treatment as Usual</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual (TAU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive Treatment as Usual provided at the study clinics.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Unified Protocol for Adolescents (UP-A)</intervention_name>
    <description>The UP-A is an emotion-focused, transdiagnostic approach for adolescents (ages 12-18) with a primary emotional disorder. It is a developmental adaptation of the Unified Protocol, a transdiagnostic treatment for adults with emotional disorders. Clinicians present all skills in the context of the emotions most salient to presenting concerns and adolescent/caregiver conceptualizations of treatment needs, thereby personalizing treatment. The UP-A is delivered in 8-21 weekly sessions, with clinician flexibility regarding the sequencing and depth with which various sections are presented to clients and caregivers, as well as the emotions targeted during the course of the intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Unified Protocol for Adolescents (UP-A)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Youth Outcomes Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>The YOQ consists of parent- and youth-report measures of symptoms and alliance administered weekly on a tablet computer. The YOQ online system then generates reports to provide clinicians with systematic feedback about client progress, flagging &quot;critical items&quot; that have been endorsed (e.g., suicidality, hallucinations), presenting graphs of ratings over time, and providing empirically-derived &quot;alerts&quot; when clients are failing to progress or showing deterioration. Clinicians will be trained to use this feedback to modify treatment as needed, share it with families as appropriate, and use it to enhance use of supervision.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Unified Protocol for Adolescents (UP-A)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual Plus (TAU+)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as Usual</intervention_name>
    <description>Clinicians assigned to the TAU condition will be instructed to use whatever treatment methods and outcome monitoring strategies they typically use with adolescents with internalizing disorders.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual Plus (TAU+)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual (TAU)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female adolescents between the ages of 12-18 years at the time of enrollment
             with clinically significant symptoms of anxiety or depression at baseline. Evidence of
             clinically significant symptoms will be defined as a Clinical Severity Rating (CSR)
             greater than or equal to 4 on any DSM-5 defined anxiety disorder (e.g., generalized
             anxiety disorder, social phobia, selective mutism, separation anxiety disorder) or
             depressive disorder (e.g., major depressive disorder, persistent depressive disorder),
             or an adjustment disorder with depressed mood, anxiety, or mixed anxiety and depressed
             mood.

          2. The adolescent is determined by the community mental health center to be eligible for
             outpatient psychosocial services at the clinic and determined by the study IE to be
             appropriate for outpatient psychosocial intervention (e.g., no major cognitive
             impairment or active suicidality) based on clinical interview.

          3. The adolescent lives (for at least 50% time) with legal guardian and this guardian is
             willing to attend treatment sessions and participate in study assessments (every
             effort will be made to encourage the same caregiver to participate in all
             assessments).

          4. Adolescent and parent/guardian are able to complete all study procedures in English or
             Spanish.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Adolescents will be excluded if they are receiving concurrent psychotherapy, family
             therapy or similar psychosocial interventions.

          2. Consistent with the prior RCT of the UP-A, the use of psychopharmacologic treatments
             for anxiety or depression is allowable; but the adolescent must be on a stable dosage
             for 2 months for SSRI or 1 month for benzodiazepine prior to consenting to the study.
             The type, dosage and frequency of medication will be monitored at all major study
             assessment points, but subsequent changes will not incur exclusion from the
             investigation. Adolescents on stable doses of a stimulant for ADHD for at least one
             month or on a SNRI (e.g., Strattera) for ADHD for at least two months can also be
             included.

          3. Adolescents who are currently suicidal or who have engaged in suicidal behaviors
             within the past 6 months will be excluded and referred for appropriate clinical
             intervention.

          4. Adolescents with a current substance abuse disorder as determined using the
             ADIS-5-C/P, will be excluded.

          5. Consistent with prior trials of the UP-A, youth with primary conditions not specified
             for exclusion (e.g., eating disorders, schizophrenia) will be screened. As long as
             study staff concur that an emotional disorder treatment focus is appropriate, these
             youth will be included.

          6. Adolescents with a reported history of intellectual disability or for whom there is
             substantial evidence (e.g., multiple learning disorders, extensive school-based
             accommodations for learning) that the cognitive level of the UP-A would make it
             inappropriate as an individual therapy modality, as determined via Family Background
             Questionnaire and/or based on PI judgement, will be excluded.

          7. Given additional complexities obtaining informed consent, adolescents who are
             currently placed in the foster care system will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Golda Ginsburg, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Connecticut</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amanda Jensen-Doss, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jill Ehrenreich-May, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amanda Jensen-Doss, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>305-284-8332</phone>
    <email>ajensendoss@miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jill Ehrenreich-May, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>(305) 284-6476</phone>
    <email>j.ehrenreich@miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Connecticut Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06119</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Golda Ginsburg, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>860-523-3788</phone>
      <email>Gginsburg@uchc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Coral Gables</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amanda Jensen-Doss, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>305-284-8332</phone>
      <email>ajensendoss@miami.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jill Ehrenreich-May, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>305-284-6476</phone>
      <email>j.ehrenreich@miami.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 1, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 1, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 2, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Amanda Jensen-Doss</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

