<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02298465</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>QueenMaryH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02298465</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ESWL for Distal Ureteric Stone: Supine Versus Prone</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Study on Extracorporeal Shockwave Lithotripsy for Distal Ureteric Stone: Transgluteal Versus Traditional Prone Approach</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Queen Mary Hospital, Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Queen Mary Hospital, Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Extracorporeal shockwave lithotripsy (ESWL) for urinary stone is common and widespread
      nowadays. Approximately 80% of urinary stones are treated by ESWL. Traditionally distal
      ureteric stones are treated with ESWL in the prone position. However, as some patients cannot
      tolerate lying in the prone due to medical illness such as chronic obstructive pulmonary
      disease (COPD), some authors have reported using the supine approach of ESWL for treatment of
      distal ureter stones. No serious complications had developed in the patients who underwent
      supine approach. Only minor complications such as self-limiting blood in the urine, painful
      passage of urine, or local pain that had responded to oral painkillers. There were no serious
      complications encountered in children as well. In the most recent retrospective review by
      Tolley et al, they had revealed that patients who had underwent supine ESWL for distal
      ureteric stones had an improved stone-free rate compared with the traditional prone approach.

      Patient with radio-opaque distal ureteric stones (stones below the sacroiliac joint) on KUB
      X-ray, who have opted for ESWL treatment, are randomized into two groups: one undergoing ESWL
      in the supine position and the other undergoing ESWL in the prone position. Patients will be
      observed for two hours after ESWL before being discharged. Oral painkillers as necessary will
      be provided to the patient. The patients will have a KUB Xray at 2 weeks post-ESWL, and then
      monthly afterwards if required. If there are residual stones at the 2-week follow-up, the
      patient will be offered ESWL again. Patients are free to withdraw from the study at any time
      and will continue to be managed as per usual.

      The investigators aim to have 130 patients, with 65 patients in each group with an interim
      analyses to be performed when 66 patients have been recruited (33 patients in each group).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Previous authors have reported using the greater and lesser sciatic foramina as a pathway for
      the shockwaves to reach the distal ureter. No serious complications had developed in the
      patients who underwent transgluteal approach. Only minor complications such as self-limiting
      hematuria, dysuria, or pain that had responded to oral analgesics. There were no serious
      complications encountered in children as well. In the most recent retrospective review by
      Tolley et al, they had revealed that patients who had underwent transgluteal ESWL for distal
      ureteric stones had an improved stone-free rate of 78% in the transgluteal group versus 40%
      in the prone group after one session of shockwave lithotripsy and a stone-free rate of 92%
      versus 63% respectively after two sessions of shockwave lithotripsy. This has been speculated
      to be due to the presence of bowel gas attenuating the shockwaves as well as a long
      skin-to-stone distance in the prone position.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stone-free rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks. If stone still present, then 6 weeks and 10 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>To review KUB to determine if distal ureteric stone have been passed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications rates concerning the two approaches of ESWL</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks. If stone still present, then 6 weeks and 10 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>To see if any complications arise from the procedures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain associated with the procedure for the two approaches of ESWL</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks. If stone still present, then 6 weeks and 10 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Using visual analogue scale to determine the pain scores of each intervention on the day of intervention
Number of tablets of analgesics used in-between follow up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Urinary Tract Stones</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Stones</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Calculi</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prone ESWL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ESWL for distal ureteric stone is performed in the traditional prone position</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Supine ESWL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ESWL for distal ureteric stone is performed in the supine position, with the shockwave generator head placed at a 30 degree angle to the vertical at the patient's gluteal muscles. Thus, the shockwaves will travel via the greater and lesser sciatic foramina to reach the stone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Supine ESWL</intervention_name>
    <description>ESWL to distal ureteric stone is performed in the supine position with the shockwave generator placed in the patient's buttock area. The aim is to direct the shockwaves through the greater and lesser sciatic foramina to reach the distal ureter.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Supine ESWL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prone ESWL</intervention_name>
    <description>ESWL to the distal ureteric stone is performed in the traditional prone position. The shockwave generator is placed on the patient's abdomen</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prone ESWL</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Transgluteal</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extracorporeal Shockwave Lithotripsy (ESWL)</intervention_name>
    <description>The ESWL machine we use is the Dornier S2 lithotriptor. ESWL is performed without any sedation or anesthesia under fluoroscopy. Painkillers are given upon request.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prone ESWL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Supine ESWL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients, over 18 years of age, with distal ureteric stones with stone size of
             ≥3mm on kidney-ureter-bladder (KUB) X-ray who opted for ESWL treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are unable to provide consent

          -  radiolucent stones

          -  active urinary tract infections

          -  pregnancy

          -  uncontrolled hypertension

          -  uncontrolled bleeding tendencies

          -  severe skeletal malformations

          -  arterial aneurysms within the vicinity of the stone (such as iliac artery aneurysms)

          -  unable to assume the appropriate position (prone or supine) for ESWL

          -  solitary kidneys

          -  transplanted kidneys

          -  presence of ureteric stents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Ho, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Queen Mary Hospital, Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brian Ho, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>(852)2255-3023</phone>
    <email>brianshho@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sau Loi Ng, BN, DN</last_name>
    <phone>(852)2255-3625</phone>
    <email>ngsauloi2009@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Mary Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Ho, MBBS, FCSHK</last_name>
      <phone>(852)2255-3023</phone>
      <email>brianshho@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sau Loi Ng, BN, DN</last_name>
      <phone>(852)2255-3625</phone>
      <email>ngsauloi2009@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason Wong, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jenkins AD, Gillenwater JY. Extracorporeal shock wave lithotripsy in the prone position: treatment of stones in the distal ureter or anomalous kidney. J Urol. 1988 May;139(5):911-5.</citation>
    <PMID>3361661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zehntner CH, Marth D, Zingg EJ. ESWL treatment with ventral shock-wave application: therapy of iliac and distal ureteral calculi. Urology. 1991 Jul;38(1):51-3.</citation>
    <PMID>1866859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lu J, Sun X, He L. Sciaticum majus foramen and sciaticum minus foramen as the path of SWL in the supine position to treat distal ureteral stone. Urol Res. 2010 Dec;38(6):417-20. doi: 10.1007/s00240-010-0285-2. Epub 2010 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20625895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sun X, He L, Lu J, Cong X, Shen L, Wang Y, Zhu H. Greater and lesser ischiadic foramina as path of shock wave lithotripsy for distal ureteral stone in children. J Urol. 2010 Aug;184(2):665-8. doi: 10.1016/j.juro.2010.03.060. Epub 2010 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>20639031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phipps S, Stephenson C, Tolley D. Extracorporeal shockwave lithotripsy to distal ureteric stones: the transgluteal approach significantly increases stone-free rates. BJU Int. 2013 Jul;112(2):E129-33. doi: 10.1111/j.1464-410X.2012.11738.x. Epub 2013 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23360696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Queen Mary Hospital, Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brian Ho</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Resident Specialist (Urology)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ESWL</keyword>
  <keyword>distal ureteric stone</keyword>
  <keyword>transgluteal</keyword>
  <keyword>supine ESWL</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calculi</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Calculi</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urolithiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ureteral Calculi</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ureterolithiasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

