<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02298855</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OC_F-UP_V3 28/07/2006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02298855</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Individualised Versus Conventional Medical Follow-up for Women After Primary Treatment for Ovarian Cancer.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised Study Comparing Satisfaction With Individualised Follow-up Led by a Trained Cancer Nurse Versus Conventional Medical Follow-up After Primary Treatment for Ovarian Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University College London Hospitals</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Southend University Hospital Foundation NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Basildon and Thurrock University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study in women who have completed primary treatment for ovarian cancer is
      to investigate the effects of individualised follow-up care delivered by a nurse compared to
      conventional medical follow-up on quality of life and mood. The investigators aim to
      determine if the individualised treatment is acceptable to women compared to the conventional
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is recent evidence that routine cancer follow-up is ineffective (Kew, 2011). Knowledge
      of how best to deliver follow-up remains inadequate and randomised studies are lacking. This
      trial compares individualised follow-up led by a cancer trained nurse to conventional medical
      follow-up.

      Aim:

      The investigators shall conduct the trial using experienced clinical nurse specialists (CNSs)
      to deliver self-management focused individual follow-up and evaluate whether this brings
      about greater improvement in quality of life, is acceptable and cost saving when compared to
      the standard (conventional) model.

      Design:

      Two arm randomised controlled trial.

      Setting:

      Specialist gynaecological cancer outpatient services at three cancer centres, one inner city
      and two urban.

      Sample size:

      A sample size of 100 patients, randomised equally to the 2 treatment groups, has been
      determined for this study. See statistical analysis section.

      Recruitment:

      Based on previous experience of recruiting in this population approximately 50% of women
      approached will agree to take part. The investigators need 1 year to recruit the sample.

      Randomisation:

      Participants will be subdivided into two groups those recruited at the inner city centre and
      those recruited at the suburban. Randomisation will be performed independently for both
      groups with participants randomly allocated to either the conventional or individualised
      follow-up in a 1:1 ratio. Allocation of the first participant from a pair to one of the 2
      follow-up strategies will be made using randomness derived from atmospheric noise
      (http://www.random.org); the second participant from each pair will then be allocated to the
      other group.

      The intervention:

      Trial follow-up is 2 years from baseline. Conventional follow-up/treatment as usual This will
      remain unchanged and involve: one post treatment appointment then appointments every 3 months
      with a doctor. Routinely a medical history is taken and investigations to monitor disease
      progression including serum cancer antigen 125 (CA125) tumour marker. A physical examination
      may be performed. The appointment will sometimes involve CNS input and patients may contact
      the non-study CNS on an ad hoc basis.

      Individualised follow-up Patients will meet the study CNS in clinic when they attend for
      their 4-6 week post treatment appointment. The nurse will negotiate with the patient to agree
      follow-up arrangements best suited to their needs. E.g. patient-initiated telephone or
      face-to-face appointments. The nurse will assess the patient at appointments using an
      assessment proforma.

      Data collection:

      Quantitative data Baseline qol questionnaires will be provided by the Research Assistant at
      the time of written consent and completed and returned prior to disclosure of randomisation.
      Subsequent questionnaires will be posted to participants with a reply paid envelope.

      Data will be entered on a 'Patient events' data base and then extracted for all patients for
      different types of service use during the two-year follow-up period. The investigators will
      also record primary care contacts and the reasons for these with a questionnaire to General
      Practitioners.

      Qualitative interview data Selected patients will take part in a 45-60 minute one-to-one
      interview at a location convenient to them. The interview will be audio-recorded following
      consent and anonymised to maintain confidentiality. A semi-structured interview guide will be
      used to ensure all important topic areas are covered.

      CNSs will be interviewed in a quiet room away from their clinical area as above.

      Data Analysis:

      Quantitative data Differences in mean patient qol and satisfaction and between the two groups
      will be assessed by 2 sample t-tests. Assuming a two-sided significance level of 5% with 40
      in each sample, to achieve 80% power any differences will have to be quite large to be
      detectable. For the satisfaction scale (0-100), where the estimated common standard deviation
      = 14.7 (de Bock et al (2004)), a difference between the two groups of 9.3 would be detectable
      with 80% power. For the anxiety (0-13) and depression (0-14) measures common standard
      deviation = 2.75 in both cases (de Bock et al 2004), such a difference would need to be 1.74
      in both cases. The investigators may be able to detect smaller differences with the planned
      sample size when taking into account adjustment for baseline values in the sample size
      calculation comparing the randomised groups (analysis of covariance).

      For the qol scales there are various sub-scales (0-100) and the evidence from literature
      sources suggest that for most scales the standard deviation is approximately 20-25 (Greimel
      et al 2003). Using such a value then, a difference in means, detectable with 80% power, would
      be between 12.7 and 15.9. Even if the ensuing results are not able to detect clinically
      important differences between the two groups, the scale scores will provide useful
      information and may justify further inquiry.

      The total cost of follow-up for each patient will be calculated by multiplying service use by
      unit costs obtained from relevant National Health Service (NHS) Reference Costs and summing
      across all types of use. Unadjusted service use and total costs will be compared between each
      group using Mann-Whitney two-sample statistics.

      Qualitative data Interviews will be fully transcribed and analysed according to principles of
      grounded theory (Strauss and Corbin, 1991).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) core quality of life questionnaire QLQ-C30 with ovarian cancer specific module Ov-28.</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of change over time from baseline and at 3, 6, 12,18, &amp; 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>is a 30-item questionnaire assessing five 5 functional domains (physical, role, cognitive, emotional and social), 3 symptom domains (nausea/vomiting, fatigue and pain), and a number of specific symptoms (dyspnoea, appetite loss, sleep disturbance, constipation, and diarrhoea) as well as the perceived financial impact of the disease and treatment.The site specific instrument (Ov-28) used with the QLQ-C30 consists of 28 items which are factor analysed into six factors: abdominal/gastrointestinal symptoms, peripheral neuropathy, other chemotherapy side effects specific to ovarian cancer treatments, hormonal symptoms, body image and sexuality, and attitude to disease/treatment. Higher scores for functioning subscales indicate better functioning. Higher scores in symptom subscales indicate worse symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS):</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of change over time from baseline and at 3, 6, 12, 18, &amp; 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS): Anxiety and depressive symptoms will be assessed with this 14-item self-rated scale designed for use in the medically ill.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ware Patient Satisfaction Questionnaire (PSQ-III) to measure patients' perceptions of care.</measure>
    <time_frame>Asssessment of change over time from baseline and at 3, 6, 12, 18, and 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>This provides a summary measure, general satisfaction, as well as six aspects of health care: technical competence, interpersonal manner, communication, time spent with clinician, financial aspects, and access to care. In the version we will use the financial items will be left out because these are not appropriate for the UK national socialised health system.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative interviews with 20-24 selected patients receiving conventional or individualised follow-up care.</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 1 &amp; 2 years on follow-up.</time_frame>
    <description>Findings from the questionnaires at 6 and 18 months will be used to purposively select a sub-sample of 10-12 women from each arm of the study for in-depth interview. Women will be selected to maximise variation in terms of quality of life scores, patient satisfaction and HADS scores in each arm of the study. Care will also be taken to include women of different ages and ovarian cancer stage. Patients' experiences of follow-up and their preferences for follow-up care will be elicited in one-to-one semi-structured interviews which will be conducted by the clinical psychologist, a co-investigator to the project.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative interviews with 4 clinical nurse specialists delivering the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>After 1 &amp; 2 years and during delivery follow-up care to study participants.</time_frame>
    <description>Nurses' experiences of delivering the follow-up care will be elicited in one-to-one semi-structured interviews to be conducted by the clinical psychologist, a co-researcher to the project.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">113</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional follow-up</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment as usual will involve: one post treatment appointment then 3 monthly appointments with a Dr. At appointments: medical history; investigations to monitor disease progression including CA125 tumour marker blood test if this were raised at diagnosis. A physical examination may be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individualised follow-up</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Follow-up is delivered by a nurse and frequency and type (telephone or face-to-face) is negotiated to suit their individual situation. Assessment by holistic guide. The intervention is informed by a model of health promoting interactions oriented towards improving self-efficacy. The nurses will provide information and support to help patients manage symptoms and psychological discomfort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Individualised follow-up</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients allocated to gynaecological cancer nurse specialist at the end of primary treatment. Follow-up is negotiated to suit their individual situation. Type of contact is flexible, primarily by telephone although some women may opt for face-to-face appointments. Patients will be assessed using a holistic guide to identify signs of disease progression, symptoms warranting intervention, and psychological issues. The nurses delivering the intervention are expert in the management of ovarian cancer and will work to a model of health promoting interactions oriented towards improving self-efficacy. The nurses will provide information and support to assist patients to manage troublesome symptoms and live with psychological discomfort.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Individualised follow-up</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Diagnosis of ovarian cancer (includes fallopian tube and peritoneal cancers)

          2. Within one month of completion of primary treatment including surgery &amp;
             chemotherapy/radiotherapy or surgery alone, irrespective of outcome with regard to
             remission

          3. Expected survival ≥3 months

          4. Agreement to be randomised

          5. Agreement to give written consent to participate in the study

          6. Sufficient grasp of English to engage in the self-management focused approach.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. A second cancer diagnosis

          2. Clinician estimated survival of ≤ 3 months

          3. Women receiving treatment for a mental health condition

          4. Women who have a learning disability.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne Lanceley, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University College, London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southend University Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westcliff-on-Sea</city>
        <state>Essex.</state>
        <zip>SS0 0RY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Basildon &amp; Thurrock University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basildon</city>
        <state>Essex</state>
        <zip>SS16 5NL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College London Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW1 2BU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greimel E, Bottomley A, Cull A, Waldenstrom AC, Arraras J, Chauvenet L, Holzner B, Kuljanic K, Lebrec J, D'haese S; EORTC Quality of Life Group and the Quality of Life Unit. An international field study of the reliability and validity of a disease-specific questionnaire module (the QLQ-OV28) in assessing the quality of life of patients with ovarian cancer. Eur J Cancer. 2003 Jul;39(10):1402-8. Erratum in: Eur J Cancer. 2003 Nov;39(17):2570.</citation>
    <PMID>12826043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kew F, Galaal K, Bryant A, Naik R. Evaluation of follow-up strategies for patients with epithelial ovarian cancer following completion of primary treatment. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2011 Jun 15;(6):CD006119. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD006119.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014;9:CD006119.</citation>
    <PMID>21678351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Bock GH, Bonnema J, van der Hage J, Kievit J, van de Velde CJ. Effectiveness of routine visits and routine tests in detecting isolated locoregional recurrences after treatment for early-stage invasive breast cancer: a meta-analysis and systematic review. J Clin Oncol. 2004 Oct 1;22(19):4010-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15459225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 21, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 21, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gynaecological cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Nurse-led care</keyword>
  <keyword>Aftercare</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient self-management</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapse free interval</keyword>
  <keyword>Watch and wait</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

