<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02292810</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-0194</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02292810</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Acute Effects of Inspiratory Muscle Exercise on Glucose Level and Glucose Variability in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Acute Effects of Inspiratory Muscle Exercise on Glucose Level and Glucose Variability in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Type 2 diabetes is associated with respiratory muscle weakness and autonomic neuropathy. The
      exercise of inspiratory muscles has been investigating in various clinical situations and may
      cause similar benefits as the conventional exercises. The assessment of glucose variability
      has been used as an alternative tool to evaluate the others mechanisms than the absolute
      values of glucose levels, special during the exercise. However, the effect of inspiratory
      muscle exercise on glucose levels and glucose variability is not clear yet. The aim of the
      proposed research is to evaluate the acute effects of inspiratory muscle exercise using a
      high load of 60% of MIP on glucose levels and glucose variability in patients with type 2
      diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      High-intensity exercise of inspiratory muscle was able to reduce glucose levels in previous
      studies, but the mechanisms underlying this reduction remain largely unknown. The present
      study will investigate this phenomenon, and whether confirmed, the inspiratory muscle loading
      would be a new approach for lowering glucose levels and glucose variability in type 2
      diabetes.

      The subjects with type 2 diabetes will be recruited from the ambulatory of the Hospital de
      Clinicas de Porto Alegre. The patients will be randomized to inspiratory muscle exercise with
      a high intensity load (MIP 60%) or to exercise with a load placebo (MIP 2%), on two different
      days. The subjects will come in the laboratory for three days consecutively during 2 weeks.
      On the first day will be placed the CGMS device. On the second day will be the controlled
      ventilation protocol with subsequently inspiratory muscle exercise, using 2% or 60% of MIP as
      randomized a priori. On the third day the CGMS will be removed. Individuals who are using
      beta-blockers will be advised to withdraw the medication 24 hours before the protocols.
      During all protocols will be recorded the continuous blood pressure to assess heart rate and
      blood pressure variabilities, both time and frequency domains will be analyzed. Also, the
      calf blood flow, inspiratory pressure, end-tidal carbon dioxide and oxygen saturation will be
      taking.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose level</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day (A session of inspiratory muscle exercise)</time_frame>
    <description>The glucose level will be assessed by continuous glucose monitoring (CGMS) before and after exercise.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose variability</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>The variability of the glucose will be assessed by continuous glucose monitoring (CGMS) 24 hours before exercise, during the protocol and 24 hours after exercise.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Autonomic control</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day (A session of inspiratory muscle exercise)</time_frame>
    <description>The autonomic control will be evaluated in the time domain and frequency through the Biopac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inspiratory muscle exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will exercise the inspiratory muscle using a load of 60% of maximum inspiratory mouth pressure (MIP 60%).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inspiratory muscle exercise placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will exercise the inspiratory muscle using a load of 2% of maximum inspiratory mouth pressure (MIP 2%).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inspiratory muscle exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>For inspiratory muscle exercise patients will breathe with a high load of 60% of MIP using a respiratory frequency of 15 breaths min and a prolonged duty cycle (TI/TTOT =0.7) until task failure. The blood flow, conductance and resistance arterial will be measured in the calf using plethysmography device. Arterial blood pressure and heart rate will be monitored continuously at the finger on a beat-by-beat basis by biopac equipment and the glucose levels will be captured by continuous glucose monitoring system.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inspiratory muscle exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inspiratory muscle exercise placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>For inspiratory muscle exercise patients will breathe with a very low load of 2% of MIP using a respiratory frequency of 15 breaths min and a prolonged duty cycle (TI/TTOT =0.7) for 10 minute. The blood flow, conductance and resistance arterial will be measured in the calf using plethysmography device. Arterial blood pressure and heart rate will be monitored continuously at the finger on a beat-by-beat basis by biopac equipment and the glucose levels will be captured by using the continuous glucose monitoring system.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inspiratory muscle exercise placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 2 diabetes;

          -  HbA1c from 7,5 to 10%;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects taking insulin;

          -  Pregnant women;

          -  Subjects taking betablocker only

          -  Documented arrythmia

          -  Documented fibrillation

          -  GFR&lt;30

          -  Documented pulmonary disease or asthma,

          -  Current smoking;

          -  Varicose vein problems;

          -  Musculoskeletal disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beatriz Schaan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Beatriz Schann, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>55513359 7640</phone>
    <email>beatrizschaan@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andressa Schein, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>555193040101</phone>
    <email>andressasilveiradeoliveira@yahoo.com.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>November 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 17, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 17, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

