<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02297360</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FHOTC 0413</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02297360</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Viviscal Extra-Strength Formulation To Promote Hair Growth And Decrease Shedding In Women With Thinning Hair</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 3-Month, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Study Evaluating The Ability Of Viviscal Extra-Strength Formulation To Promote Hair Growth And Decrease Shedding In Women With Self-Perceived Thinning Hair</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ablon Skin Institute Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Irish Response t/a Lifes2good</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ablon Skin Institute Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Viviscal Extra-Strength formulation is an oral food/dietary supplement specifically
      designed to promote hair growth for women suffering from temporary thinning hair. It does not
      contain hormones or drugs and has been marketed in Europe for over 15 years. Viviscal
      Extra-Strength is marketed as Viviscal Maximum Strength in some other territories.

      The hypothesis of this clinical research study is that the ingestion of Viviscal
      Extra-Strength over a three (3) month period will strengthen and promote the growth of
      terminal hairs in female subjects, ages 21-65 years of age with self-perceived thinning hair
      associated with poor diet, stress, hormonal influences or abnormal menstrual cycles when
      compared to using the placebo tablet.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The key ingredient of Viviscal Extra-Strength formulation is AminoMar C™ marine complex,
      Equisetum arvense sp. (horsetail), containing a naturally occurring form of silica),
      Malpighia glabra (acerola cherry) which contains Vitamin C, Biotin and Zinc. The AminoMar C™
      is an active ingredient which has been trademarked and comprises of a proprietary blend of
      shark powder and mollusc powder. It is derived from sustainable marine sources. Viviscal
      provides essential nutrients to nourish hair naturally from within. Viviscal works in many
      ways over several months of use to improve the appearance of thinning hair.

        -  Nourishes the hair follicles

        -  Strengthens and promotes the growth of terminal hairs. Terminal hair is defined as
           coarse hair, short or long, found on the scalp with minimum cross-sectional diameter of
           40 micrometers. Vellus hair is defined as fine, short hairs found on the scalp with
           maximum cross-sectional diameter of 40 micrometers.

        -  Supports the growth of hair where it has slowed down or temporarily stopped

        -  Hair becomes stronger, healthier and more vibrant

      Ingestion of Viviscal Extra-Strength over a three (3) month period will strengthen and
      promote the growth of terminal hairs in female subjects, ages 21-65 years of age with
      self-perceived thinning hair associated with poor diet, stress, hormonal influences or
      abnormal menstrual cycles when compared to using the placebo tablet. The primary endpoints
      will be individual hair counts and favorable analysis using the Nikon CoolPix 4300 with 3GEN
      Dermlite Foto37 for phototrichogram analysis at the end of the three (3) month period. The
      secondary endpoints will be statistically significant decreased hair shedding counts with
      hair washing, favorable improvement in terminal hair diameter measured by the Dino-Lite
      Digital Microscopic and positive feedback on the Quality of Life and Self-Assessment
      questionnaires after three (3) months of Viviscal Extra-Strength ingestion.

      All patients enrolled must be identifiable throughout the study. The Investigator will
      maintain a personal list of patient numbers and patient names to enable records to be found
      at a later date and the list will be stored in a locked cabinet. Subject numbers consist of a
      2 digit number from 01 to 60. Patients will be randomized to active or placebo supplements
      (1:1 ratio) using a randomization table prepared prior to the start of the study by a
      non-participating staff member at the office of the Investigator. The study blind will not be
      broken until the end of the study. All test product and placebo will be labeled with subject
      numbers per the non-participating staff member. Subjects will be assigned a subject number in
      numerical order as enrolled. Randomization will occur by assignment to either Viviscal
      Extra-Strength supplement or placebo with 1:1 ratio. Subjects who terminate their study
      participation for any reason, regardless of whether study medication was used or not, will
      retain their randomization number.

      Visit Procedures Pre-Study Procedures

        1. Candidate subjects will be screened with the eligibility requirements by telephone prior
           to Visit 1.

        2. Candidate subjects will be assigned an appointment time for visiting the clinic.

      Visit 1: Baseline, Day 0

        1. Individuals will be given an informed consent (IC) document &amp; photographic release form,
           HIPAA form, confidentiality agreement to read. They will have all of their study related
           questions answered by the Investigator or her designated staff and if they agree, they
           will sign two copies of the IC/Photography release form, two copies of the HIPAA form,
           and one copy of the confidentiality agreement. Subjects will be given one copy of the
           signed IC/Photography release and of the HIPAA agreement to keep, with one copy of each
           document remaining at the testing facility in the subject's file.

        2. Investigator and/or Study Coordinator will review with subject and complete the
           checklist for all inclusion and exclusion criteria.

        3. Investigator and/or Study Coordinator will review with subject and complete the
           checklist for medical history and concomitant medications.

        4. Investigator and/or Study Coordinator will review with subject and complete the General
           Lifestyle Questionnaire. The General Lifestyle Questionnaire may be found in Appendix V.

        5. Subjects will be given a Quality of Life Questionnaire to read and complete. The Quality
           of Life Questionnaire may be found in Appendix VI.

        6. Candidate subjects will receive a brief physical exam, including examination of the
           scalp, to rule out any immediately observable medical issues and any scalp
           alopecias/scalp disorders that are unacceptable for qualification. The physical will
           additionally include vital signs (pulse and blood pressure), weight and height.

        7. Candidate subjects of childbearing potential will complete a urine pregnancy test prior
           to product distribution.

        8. Candidate subjects who have completed all the initial paperwork and meet the
           inclusion/exclusion qualifications (to include findings of the physical exam) will be
           assigned a unique subject number. Subjects will be randomized to treatment group prior
           to dispensing the test product.

        9. Qualified subjects will have their scalp prepared for digital photography and initial
           measurements done (see Appendix I).

       10. Subjects will have the selected test site photographed (see Appendix I and II).

       11. Subjects will have ten (10) terminal hairs in the selected test site cut at the base of
           the scalp and the diameter of the hairs measured (see Appendix III).

       12. Subjects will be instructed to wash their hair at home 24 hours in advance of the study
           visit. Subjects will have their hair washed (shampooed) with Viviscal Gentle Shampoo
           over a sink containing cheesecloth (see Appendix IV). The cheesecloth will be positioned
           to collect shedding hair. The number of hairs collected in the cheesecloth will be
           counted and recorded. Subjects will be allowed to dry and style their hair.

       13. Subjects will be dispensed a three (3) month supply of the test product (three units of
           Viviscal Extra-Strength or Placebo, as randomized, containing 60 tablets each) and given
           written and verbal Usage and Lifestyle instructions (see Appendix VIII) and a calendar
           of future visit. Subjects will be instructed to ingest the test product per Sponsor
           instructions.

      Usage Instructions:

      Take two (2) tablets a day, one in the morning and one in the evening; take with water, after
      food.

      Subjects will be instructed to return all empty packets and unused test product at Visit 2.

      Lifestyle Instructions:

      Subjects will be instructed to maintain their normal hair care routine. Subjects will be
      instructed to use the same brand/type of hair care products and maintain the same haircut,
      color and style for the study duration.

      Subjects who have color treated hair will also be instructed to have the color treatment
      performed at the same time interval prior to each visit (ie. If on Visit 1, the color
      treatment was done one week prior then the color treatment is expected to occur at a similar
      interval of one week prior to Visit 2).

      Subjects will be instructed to come to each visit with clean (shampoo must be done 24 hours
      prior to the visit) and dry hair.

      Subjects will be instructed to use a medically sound form of birth control during the study.

      Visit 2: Month 3 (90 days) ± 1 week (7 days)

        1. A clinician will ask subjects if they have experienced any changes in their health or
           taken new/adjusted current medications since the last visit. If an AE or SAE is
           reported, the examining Investigator will be informed and the appropriate forms will be
           completed.

        2. The test product will be collected and counted for compliance.

        3. Subjects will receive a brief physical exam. The physical will include vital signs
           (pulse and blood pressure).

        4. Subjects will complete the Quality of Life Questionnaire and the Self-Assessment
           Questionnaire (see Appendix VI and VII).

        5. Subjects will have their scalp prepared for digital photography (see Appendix I).

        6. Subjects will have the selected test site photographed (see Appendix I and II).

        7. Subjects will have ten (10) terminal hairs in the selected test site cut at the base of
           the scalp and the diameter of the hairs measured (see Appendix III).

        8. Subjects will be instructed to wash their hair at home 24 hours in advance of the study
           visit. Subjects will have their hair washed (shampooed) with Viviscal Gentle Shampoo
           over a sink containing cheesecloth (see Appendix IV). The cheesecloth will be positioned
           to collect shedding hair. The number of hairs collected in the cheesecloth will be
           counted and recorded. Subjects will be allowed to dry and style their hair.

      All primary and secondary parameters will be collected at Visits 1 and 2. Missing data values
      will be minimized by intensive training of the interviewers in techniques of clarifying
      answers and checking questionnaires while participants are on-site. When missing values are
      identified, several approaches such as rescheduled within 24 hours of completion of tests or
      interviews will be employed to acquire the necessary data. Missing data will be also examined
      to assess randomness. Descriptive statistics will be obtained for all variables, tests of
      normality of continuous measures will be made and data will be examined for homogeneity of
      variance. An appropriate statistical method will be employed to correct for any
      abnormalities. All statistical tests will be two-tailed. Differences will be considered
      statistically significant provided a p-value of 0.05 or less is obtained but other p-values
      may be evaluated on a case-by-case basis. For each visit, the differences of the two groups
      from baseline Visit will be tested using analyses of variance with repeated measurements.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of terminal hairs in the target area of the scalp.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>The first primary efficacy parameter from the phototrichogram will be the number of terminal hairs in the target area of the scalp. Terminal hair is defined as coarse hair, short or long, found on the scalp with minimum cross-sectional diameter of greater than 40 micrometers. Phototrichogram macrophotographs will be taken of the selected target area of each subject at each visit as specified under the Schedule of Procedures. Digital macrophotography will be performed using a Nikon Coolpix 4300 camera with a 3GEN Dermlite Foto37 system for scalp photography. The macrophotographs are then read by the investigator to determine the terminal hair count.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of vellus hairs in the target area of the scalp.</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>The second primary efficacy parameter from the phototrichogram will be the number of vellus hairs in the target area of the scalp. Vellus hair is defined as fine, short hairs found on the scalp with maximum cross-sectional diameter of 40 micrometers. Phototrichogram macrophotographs will be taken of the selected target area of each subject at each visit as specified under the Schedule of Procedures. Digital macrophotography will be performed using a Nikon Coolpix 4300 camera with a 3GEN Dermlite Foto37 system for scalp photography. The macrophotographs are then read by the investigator to determine the terminal hair count.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dino-Lite microscopic photographs for terminal hair diameter measurements in the target area</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Dino-Lite Microscopic digital photographs to measure the diameter of the hair will be taken of the selected target area of each subject at each visit as specified under the Schedule of Procedures. Ten (10) terminal hairs in the target area will be randomly chosen throughout the area (not all from one direct area) and cut at the surface of the scalp thus not creating any bald patches. The hair diameter will then be measured at 1mm from the cut end of the hair. The ten (10) hair measurements will then be averaged to attain a median hair diameter for the target area.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hair washing (shampooing) in clinic for hair shedding counts (</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will be instructed to wash their hair at home 24 hours in advance of study visits 1 and 2. Subjects will then have their hair washed (shampooed) with Viviscal Gentle Shampoo in the office over a sink containing cheesecloth. The cheesecloth will be positioned to collect shedding hair. The number of hairs collected in the cheesecloth will be counted and recorded. Subjects will be allowed to dry and style their hair Subjects will have their hair washed and shedding hairs counted on Visits 1 and 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire about the subjects general lifestyle and how their life is affected by thinning hair.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Assessment Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire is the evaluation of the growth and qualities related to the subjects hair, nails and skin.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Hair Thinning</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Viviscal Extra-Strength Supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Viviscal Extra-strength tablets. One tablet taken by mouth in the morning and one tablet in the evening with food for 90 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablets. One tablet taken by mouth in the morning and one tablet in the evening with food for 90 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Viviscal Extra-Strength Supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>The key ingredient of Viviscal Extra-Strength Supplement is AminoMar C™ marine complex, Equisetum arvense sp. (horsetail), containing a naturally occurring form of silica), Malpighia glabra (acerola cherry) which contains Vitamin C, Biotin and Zinc. The AminoMar C™ is an active ingredient which has been trademarked and comprises of a proprietary blend of shark powder and mollusc powder. It is derived from sustainable marine sources. Viviscal provides essential nutrients to nourish hair naturally from within. The Viviscal supplement is compared to the placebo tablet which contains no active ingredients. One tablet is taken by mouth in the morning and evening with food.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Viviscal Extra-Strength Supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo tablet contains no active ingredients. One tablet is taken by mouth in the morning and evening with food.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Tablet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Females, ages 21-65 years of age

          2. Clinically-determined general good health as determined by responses to the initial
             study assessment

          3. Females with self-perceived thinning hair associated with poor diet, stress, hormone
             influences or abnormal menstrual cycle as determined on initial study assessment by
             the Investigator (This will not include patients with medically diagnosed telogen
             effluvium)

          4. Females willing to maintain their normal hair shampooing frequency

          5. Females willing to add the provided oral supplement to their current daily routine

          6. Females willing to not substantially change their current diet, medications, or
             exercise routines for the duration of the study. If a subject receives physician
             guidance during the study to change diet, medications, or exercise routine, the
             subject will need to notify the clinic as soon as possible

          7. Females willing to undergo a brief physical exam to include height, weight, blood
             pressure, pulse, general physical findings and a scalp exam. The physical exam will
             occur at Visits 1 and 2

          8. Females with Fitzpatrick I-IV photo skin types

          9. Willingness to have digital photography of the target area and scalp for hair counts
             at Visits 1 and 2

         10. Willingness to have ten (10) terminal hairs from the target area cut at the base of
             the scalp for microscopic hair measurements at Visits 1 and 2

         11. Willingness to have their hair washed (shampooed) with Viviscal Gentle Shampoo over a
             sink containing cheesecloth for hair shedding counts at Visits 1 and 2

         12. Willingness to maintain a consistent hair cut and hair color throughout the 3 month
             study period and to come to visits with clean (shampoo must be done 24 hours or more
             prior to the visit) and dry hair

         13. Willingness of subjects who have color treated hair to have the color treatment
             performed at the same time interval prior to each visit (ie. If on Visit 1 the color
             treatment was done one week prior then the color treatment is expected to occur at a
             similar interval of one week prior to Visit 2)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Females with a known history of intolerance or allergy to fish, seafood/shellfish or
             acerola

          2. Females with any known allergy or sensitivity to any shampoo/conditioner

          3. Females who are nursing, pregnant, planning to become pregnant during the study

          4. Females with known stressful incident within the last six months (ie. death in family,
             miscarriage)

          5. Females who are participating on any clinical research study at ASIRC or at another
             research center or doctor's office

          6. Females who have recently (within the last 6 months) started the use of hormones for
             birth control or hormone replacement therapy (HRT). Women currently using hormones for
             birth control or HRT must have been on a stable dose (6 months or longer) in order to
             be eligible for the study

          7. Females currently using the HairMax light treatment or other light therapy to treat
             thinning hair

          8. Females who have regularly used Rogaine (Minoxidil) within the last 3 months

          9. Females who have used prescription drugs known to affect the hair growth cycle within
             the last 6 months (e.g., hormone-based birth control for less than 6 months,
             cyproterone acetate, aldactone/spironolactone, Finasteride or any 5-alpha-reductase
             inhibitor)

         10. Females suffering from other hair loss disorders, such as alopecia areata, scarring
             alopecia, androgenetic alopecia and telogen effluvium as determined on initial study
             assessment by the Investigator

         11. Individuals with self-reported uncontrolled diseases (i.e. diabetes, hypertension,
             hyperthyroidism, hypothyroidism, etc.). Medical conditions that are under control with
             or without treatment will be considered on an individual basis by the Investigators

         12. Females with self-reported active hepatitis, immune deficiency, HIV or autoimmune
             disease

         13. Females having a known active dermatologic condition which, in the opinion of the
             examining Investigators, might place the subject at a greater risk or interfere with
             clinical evaluations (e.g., seborrheic dermatitis, psoriasis, atopic dermatitis,
             advanced skin cancer, etc.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Glynis Ablon, MD, FAAD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Director Ablon Skin Institute Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>November 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 19, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 21, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 19, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 19, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 21, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hair loss, hair thinning, women, marine protein supplement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alopecia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alopecia Areata</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypotrichosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

