<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02299180</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCPC IN14-0001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02299180</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Advance Care Planning on Care for Patients With Advanced Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Advance Care Planning on Care for Patients With Advanced Heart Failure: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart Centre Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Singapore General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aims: Advance care planning (ACP) is considered to be one of the most promising interventions
      to enable patients with life limiting illnesses to receive treatment at the end of life (EOL)
      according to their own preferences and to promote EOL conversations between patients and
      their health care providers. Through a 2-arm randomized controlled trial (RCT) of patients
      with Class III and IV heart failure (New York Heart Association Functional Classification),
      we propose to assess:

        1. Whether patients in the ACP arm have a greater likelihood of receiving EOL care
           consistent with their preferences as stated in the latter of the last ACP document or
           the last patient interview, compared to patients in the control arm.

        2. Heath care costs during study duration between patients in ACP and control arms.

        3. Patient's understanding of own illness and their participation in decision making
           between the ACP and control arms.

        4. Patient's quality of life, anxiety and depression between ACP and control arms.

      Methodology: A total of 254 patients with advance heart failure will be randomized to receive
      intervention (ACP arm; N=127) or usual care (control arm; N=127).

      The RCT will be conducted at the National Heart Centre and Singapore General Hospital.
      Patients in both arms will be followed for one year or till death, whichever is earlier, and
      interviewed every 4 months during this duration.

      Clinical Significance: If benefits of ACP are shown to add value through this trial, then
      this study will help to promote acceptance of ACP among patients and health care providers
      across Singapore and elsewhere.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients receiving end of life care consistent with their stated preferences</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's stated preferences for cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) and life prolonging treatments (e.g. mechanical ventilation, dialysis, feeding tube, intravenous antibiotics, blood transfusion) will be assessed from their last survey or their ACP document. The actual treatment received by the patient will be assessed from medical records after the patient's death. Proportion of patients who died and received treatment consistent with their stated preferences will be calculated and compared between ACP and control arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total health care expenditure of patients during study duration</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Total healthcare expenditures during the study duration will be assessed from institutional databases and compared between ACP and control arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient scores for Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>every four months for one year</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life will be assessed through McGill Quality of Life scale and compared between ACP and control arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's understanding of own illness</measure>
    <time_frame>every four months for one year</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's understanding of own prognosis will be assessed and compared between ACP and control arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient scores for anxiety and depression</measure>
    <time_frame>every four months for one year</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's anxiety and depression will be assessed through Hospital Anxiety and Depression scale and scores will be compared between ACP and control arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's participation in decision-making</measure>
    <time_frame>every four months for one year</time_frame>
    <description>Patient scores on decision conflict scale will be assessed and compared between ACP and control arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">282</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control arm patients will not take part in ACP discussions and documentation, but will continue to receive usual care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (ACP) arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patient and his/her family members will be referred to an ACP facilitator and will undergo ACP as an ongoing process, integrated with patient's care, from the facilitator, in coordination with a coordinator/nurse, and treating physician. The ACP facilitator will be certified in providing ACP and will possess sufficient knowledge of the risks, benefits, and harms of treatments and procedures available to the patient. The ACP facilitator will be supported by the physician with the specialized knowledge of treatment options, especially with regards to prognosis. Family members will be encouraged to be present during the ACP discussion so that the whole family unit will be able to explore goals, values and beliefs towards the patient's medical care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACP</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (ACP) arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patient participant:

          -  Patients must be 21 years old or older and must be diagnosed with advanced heart
             failure (New York Heart Association Class III and IV). Patients must be aware of their
             diagnosis

          -  Caregiver/Decision-maker participant: Subject must be 21 years old or older
             Participant must be either

               -  appointed substitute decision maker or

               -  most likely to be substitute decision maker for patient (if patient were to lose
                  decision-making capacity)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient participant: Patients must not have any psychiatric or cognitive disorders

          -  Caregiver/Decision-maker participant: Cannot be a maid or foreign domestic worker
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chetna Malhotra, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Singapore General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169608</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart Centre Singapore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169609</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 20, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chetna Malhotra</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced care planning</keyword>
  <keyword>End of life care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

