<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02299895</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LBG:1554</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02299895</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Professionals' Perspectives on Facilitating and Hindering Factors of Implementing Health Promotion Programs in Organizational Settings</brief_title>
  <acronym>SCS</acronym>
  <official_title>Professionals' Perspectives on Facilitating and Hindering Factors of Implementing Health Promotion Programs in Organizational Settings: a Qualitative Comparative Study in Austria</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ludwig Boltzmann Gesellschaft</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ludwig Boltzmann Institut Health Promotion Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ludwig Boltzmann Gesellschaft</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      In the field of health promotion, the 'setting approach' has gained increased attention over
      the last decades. Following this approach, organizations and governments are urged to invest
      in health and health promotion. However, the dissatisfaction with the broad definition of the
      term 'setting' has grown. As many health promotion programs are carried out in organizational
      settings, substantial work has been done on how to acknowledge organizational factors in
      designing and implementing health promotion programs. Organizational settings differ from
      others because they can also address their clients as beneficiaries of health promotion
      programs, also known as 'client-oriented health promotion'. Among the most prominent
      organizational settings for health promotion are schools and hospitals, and more recently,
      long-term care (LTC-) facilities. However, dissemination and implementation of
      client-oriented health promotion in organizational settings seem to be very challenging. Most
      approaches dealing with barriers to health promotion implementation in schools, hospitals,
      and LTC-facilities rarely reflect the specific organizational characteristics. This
      negligence constitutes both, a research gap in the setting approach and in the design of
      health promotion practice. Hence, the aim of this study is to explore professionals'
      (teachers', health professionals', care aids') views and attitudes that influence the
      implementation of client-oriented health promotion programs between schools, hospitals, and
      LTC-facilities in Austria.

      Methods:

      With that aim in mind, the investigators chose a comparative qualitative design.
      Semi-structured interviews will be conducted with 90 professionals (30 in schools, 30 in
      hospitals, and 30 in LTC-facilities). In addition, non-participant observations as well as an
      extensive document analysis in each setting will be undertaken. The data will be analyzed by
      thematic analysis. Comparisons within as well as between the organizational settings will be
      conducted using selected categories.

      Discussion:

      To date, this study is the first of its kind that compares results of individual
      semi-structured interviews between different organizational settings. This study investigates
      professionals' views and attitudes on facilitating and hindering factors of implementing
      client-oriented health promotion programs and thus will provide a solid basis for future
      research activities and evaluation studies in the field of health promotion implementation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Professionals' perspectives towards the implementation process of health promotion programs compositely measured by qualitative semi-structured interviews and non-participant observation</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Semi-structured interviews: During different stages of the implementation process, a number of professionals responsible for implementation in each organizational setting are invited for an in-depth interview to gain insight into the implementation of the health promotion program. An interview guide is used to ask participants about the program's content, recruitment, fidelity, and satisfaction with the dissemination strategy, and overall satisfaction with the health promotion program. Facilitators and barriers for implementation, as well as intentions and opportunities for future implementation of health promotion programs are discussed.
Non-participant observation: In addition, it is observed how professionals across schools, hospitals, and LTC-facilities implement the health promotion program. Non-participant observation is conducted two times in each organizational setting.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigation of formal prerequisites of the implementation process measured by extensive document analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Documentary data, such as organizational charts or program descriptions of the health promotion programs, are gathered. Therewith, the investigators analyze formal structures and processes within the organizations as well as the formal requirements and goals of the health promotion program.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Promotion</condition>
  <condition>Organizations</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The aim of this study is to investigate professionals' (teachers', health professionals',
        care aids') views and attitudes that influence the implementation of client-oriented health
        promotion programs in organizational settings in Austria. Therefore, 90 professionals will
        be interviewed: 30 in schools, 30 in hospitals, and 30 in LTC-facilities.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Professionals from different levels of the organizational hierarchies

          -  Professionals from different professional groups

          -  Professionals with preferably differing views on the usefulness of the health
             promotion program

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>November 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 20, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 20, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 20, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ludwig Boltzmann Gesellschaft</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wolfgang Dür</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PD Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>setting approach</keyword>
  <keyword>health promotion</keyword>
  <keyword>organization</keyword>
  <keyword>implementation research</keyword>
  <keyword>qualitative study</keyword>
  <keyword>comparison</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

