<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02299674</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1316</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02299674</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Medial-Lateral Center of Pressure Displacement in Unilateral Transfemoral Amputees</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of Medial Lateral Displacement of Center of Pressure and Center of Mass During Double Support in Men With Unilateral Transfemoral Amputations.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Southern California Institute for Research and Education</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Southern California Institute for Research and Education</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the path and velocity of the center of mass (CoM) and
      center of pressure (CoP) during double support of persons walking with a unilateral
      above-the-knee prosthesis and determine the effects of prosthetic foot stiffness and
      effective length on CoM and CoP.Persons with a lower limb amputation walk with compensatory
      movements that affect the smooth trajectory of the center of mass (CoM) during weight
      transfer. The lack of control in the foot/ankle complex reduces fine motor movements,
      influencing the progression of the CoM and transfer of ground reaction forces represented by
      the center of pressure (CoP). Without control of the ankle joint, prosthetic users &quot;fall&quot; off
      of their trailing prosthetic limb during weight transfer, resulting in much more abrupt CoM
      and CoP transfers from trailing to leading limb. These abrupt movements during transfer not
      only increase stress on the sound limb, but also decrease the subject's energy efficiency
      during ambulation. The current study will further examine the CoP path and velocity in
      relation to the CoM path and velocity during double support of men with a transfemoral
      prosthesis, as well as explore how prosthetic foot ankle stiffness and effective length
      affects the CoP path and velocity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Center of Pressure Velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>Double Support Phase of Gait Cycle (2.5 hour)</time_frame>
    <description>The Center of Pressure velocity in the X and Y direction [cm/sec] will be collected using a motion capture system and forceplates during a single session. This data will be collected during a single 2.5 hour data collection session. The time frame is specifically the Double Support phase of the gait cycle.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Unilateral Transfemoral Amputation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Persons with unilateral transfemoral amputation</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Level overground ambulation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Persons with unilateral transfemoral amputation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Persons with unilateral transfemoral amputation who are ambulatory with a prosthesis and no
        assistive device.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must have a transfermoral amputation and use an above-the-knee prosthesis
             with an articulating knee joint on a daily basis.

          -  Participants must be male.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years, but less than 65 years.

          -  Participants must have no known pathology or comorbidites that would affect their
             ambulatory ability

          -  Ability to tolerate walking for a minimum of 100 yards over the course of a two and a
             half hour time period.

          -  Ability to walk one block without needing to rest.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of ambulatory aids such as canes or crutches.

          -  Any medical or psychosocial condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, could
             jeopardize the subject's participation, and compliance with the study criteria.

          -  Bilateral amputations.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>V.A. Long Beach Healthcare System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Long Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90822</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Au, S. K., Weber, J., &amp; Herr, H. (2009). Powered Ankle-Foot Prosthesis Improves Walking Metabolic Economy. IEEE Transactions on Robotics, 25(1), 51-66.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Donelan JM, Kram R, Kuo AD. Simultaneous positive and negative external mechanical work in human walking. J Biomech. 2002 Jan;35(1):117-24.</citation>
    <PMID>11747890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herr HM, Grabowski AM. Bionic ankle-foot prosthesis normalizes walking gait for persons with leg amputation. Proc Biol Sci. 2012 Feb 7;279(1728):457-64. doi: 10.1098/rspb.2011.1194. Epub 2011 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>21752817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hof AL, van Bockel RM, Schoppen T, Postema K. Control of lateral balance in walking. Experimental findings in normal subjects and above-knee amputees. Gait Posture. 2007 Feb;25(2):250-8. Epub 2006 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>16740390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kadaba MP, Ramakrishnan HK, Wootten ME. Measurement of lower extremity kinematics during level walking. J Orthop Res. 1990 May;8(3):383-92.</citation>
    <PMID>2324857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nolan KJ, Yarossi M. Weight transfer analysis in adults with hemiplegia using ankle foot orthosis. Prosthet Orthot Int. 2011 Mar;35(1):45-53. doi: 10.1177/0309364610393061.</citation>
    <PMID>21515889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Orendurff MS, Segal AD, Klute GK, Berge JS, Rohr ES, Kadel NJ. The effect of walking speed on center of mass displacement. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2004 Nov-Dec;41(6A):829-34.</citation>
    <PMID>15685471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmid M, Beltrami G, Zambarbieri D, Verni G. Centre of pressure displacements in trans-femoral amputees during gait. Gait Posture. 2005 Apr;21(3):255-62.</citation>
    <PMID>15760740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turnbull GI, Charteris J, Wall JC. Deficiencies in standing weight shifts by ambulant hemiplegic subjects. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1996 Apr;77(4):356-62.</citation>
    <PMID>8607759</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 19, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Southern California Institute for Research and Education</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dana Craig</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Health System Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

