<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02298751</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Cue Exposure Study, RESCueH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02298751</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exposure Therapy as Aftercare for Alcohol Use Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Alcohol Cue Exposure: An Investigator-blinded, Randomized, Controlled Study of Exposure-based Aftercare in Alcohol Use Disorder Individuals</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: It is well documented that individuals with Alcohol Use Disorder (AUD) respond
      well during evidence-based psychological treatment, but also that a large proportion relapse
      when discharged from treatment and confronted with alcohol in real life. Cue Exposure Therapy
      (CET) focuses on confronting alcohol cues in order to reduce cravings as well as the
      likelihood of relapse. The aim of this study is to investigate whether CET as aftercare
      increases the efficiency of Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) among AUD individuals.

      Design and methods: The study is implemented as an investigator-blinded randomized controlled
      trial. A total of 300 consecutively enrolled AUD patients, recruited from an alcohol
      outpatient clinic will be randomized to one of the three following aftercare treatment
      groups: (A) CET as a smartphone application (n = 100); (B) CET as group therapy (n = 100),
      and (C) Aftercare as Usual (n = 100). It is hypothesized that the two experimental groups
      ((A) and (B)) will achieve better treatment outcomes as compared to the control group ((C)),
      and It will be explored whether CET as smartphone application is as effective as CET as group
      therapy. The groups will be compared in a number of parameters including alcohol intake,
      cravings and copings-strategies.

      Discussion: If the hypothesis, that CET increases the efficiency of CBT is verified, it will
      make sense to supplement CBT with CET as aftercare, hence, reintegrating CET within a CBT
      approach. Although, CET is most often regarded as one of the behavioral methods in CBT, there
      appears to be segregation in the empirical literature when it comes to treatment of addictive
      disorders. However, CET may allow the patient to practice and gain control over alcohol cue
      reactivity and associated high-risk situations in an inter-mediating therapeutic context
      before the patients inevitably are confronted by them. In this way, one might expect the
      transition from treatment to daily life less overwhelming and CET may help prevent relapse in
      the long term. Thus, CET may be particularly suitable as aftercare.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND It is well documented that individuals with Alcohol Use Disorders (AUD) respond
      well during Cognitive Behavioural Therapy, but that a large proportion of individuals relapse
      after treatment when confronted with alcohol in real life. Therefore, future treatment
      interventions for long-term prevention of relapse should aim to teach how to apply coping
      strategies and regain control over their alcohol cravings in their daily confrontations with
      alcohol and associated stimuli.

      Cue Exposure Treatment (CET) is a behavioural psychological approach that focuses on
      confronting alcohol cues in order to reduce cravings as well as the likelihood of relapse.
      During CET individuals are exposed to alcohol related stimuli whilst their usual drink
      responses are hindered. Thus, they are given the opportunity to practice coping strategies
      during exposure to alcohol. In this way, it is predicted that individual's learned automatic
      responses will extinguish over time and that their cognitive control over cue reactivity
      strengthens.

      Mental health care applications, has the potential to improve alcohol treatment and
      continuing care by offering psychological treatment anywhere and when the patient find it
      convenient. Because, psychological treatment is a substantial socio-economic burden when
      delivered in individual sessions, there has been a tendency to deliver the relevant treatment
      through group sessions. However, mental healthcare applications, have even more potential in
      order to reduce the burden on the health care system, in addition to increasing the
      availability of evidence-based treatment. Whilst group sessions are documented effective,
      behavioural healthcare applications targeting AUD needs further exploration.

      OBJECTIVES

      The objective of the study is three-fold:

        1. To investigate whether manual-based CET delivered via a smartphone or in group sessions
           increases the efficiency of CBT outpatient treatment in groups of AUD individuals.

        2. To investigate whether CET as a smartphone application is as or more effective than CET
           group therapy.

        3. To investigate whether CET as smartphone intervention will show to be more
           cost-effective than CET delivered in group sessions.

      DESIGN AND METHODS The study is implemented as an investigator-blinded, randomized controlled
      trial. A total of 300 consecutively enrolled AUD individuals, recruited from an alcohol
      outpatient clinic will be randomized to one of the three following aftercare treatment
      groups: (1) CET as a smartphone application; (2) CET as group therapy, and (3) Standard
      aftercare treatment. Individuals in group 1 are required to use the smartphone application
      five times a week for eight weeks. Individuals in group 2 are required to have CET group
      therapy every other week for eight weeks. Individuals in group 3 will receive one individual
      follow-up session eight weeks after the primary treatment has ended.

      It is hypothesized a priori that the two experimental groups will achieve better treatment
      outcomes as compared to the control group (3). No a priori hypotheses guides comparisons of
      the effect of CET delivered via group sessions and smartphone application. Two-sided analyses
      are conducted here, because there is no empirical literature in this specific area to
      generate a priori hypotheses.

      The groups will be compared pre- and post-aftercare treatment, according to the following
      parameters:

        1. Relapse and alcohol intake, as measured with the Time-Line-Follow-Back (TLFB) method;

        2. Cravings, measured with Desires for Alcohol Questionnaire (DAQ), Obsessive-Compulsive
           Drinking Scale (OCDS), and Visual Analogue Scale for Craving (VAS);

        3. Coping skills, operationalized with Urge-Specific Strategies Questionnaire (USS)

           Data will be collected at three different time-points: before entering aftercare
           treatment (baseline), after eight weeks (follow-up), and again after six month
           (follow-up). In addition, we will follow the patients through medical registers for one
           year in order to measure relapse in the longer term, without the challenges associated
           with getting contact one year after ended treatment.

        4. Data from registers: The National Patient Register, The National Health Service
           Register, The National Prescription Registry and The Psychiatric Central Research
           Register.

      Intention-to-treat analyses (ITT) will be carried out for all outpatients. With regard to
      incomplete data, &quot;last observation carried forward&quot; (LOCF) and multiple imputations will be
      used. Completer (on-treatment) analyses will be carried out for patients who have completed
      the respective interventions.

      Odense Patient data Explorative Network (OPEN) data manager develops electronic schemes for
      data entry. Data will be imported and stored in OPEN Projects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Abstinence or controlled use of alcohol in the last 30 days 26 weeks after treatment start as measured with the timeline follow-back method</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Abstinence or controlled use of alcohol in the last 30 days 8 weeks after treatment start as measured with the timeline follow-back method</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol related contact with the Health Care system</measure>
    <time_frame>One year after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Contact with the Health Care system one year after treatment start as measured by Danish registers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cravings as measured by the Visual Analogue Craving Scale, Obsessive-Compulsive Drinking Scale and Desires for Alcohol Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Cravings are measured by the Visual Analogue Craving Scale, Obsessive-Compulsive Drinking Scale and Desires for Alcohol Questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cravings as measured by the Visual Analogue Craving Scale, Obsessive-Compulsive Drinking Scale and Desires for Alcohol Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Cravings are measured by the Visual Analogue Craving Scale, Obsessive-Compulsive Drinking Scale and Desires for Alcohol Questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Coping skills as measured by The Urge-Specific Strategies Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Urge-Specific Strategies Questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Coping skills as measured by The Urge-Specific Strategies Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Urge-Specific Strategies Questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Use Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CET via smartphone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cue Exposure Treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CET via group sessions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cue Exposure Treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aftercare as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cue Exposure Treatment</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>CET via smartphone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CET via group sessions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Completed primary treatment with CBT

          -  Accept participating in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not Danish speaking

          -  Psychotic disorders

          -  Severe cognitive impairment

          -  Terminal somatic illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bent Nielsen, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>6541 4122</phone>
    <phone_ext>0045</phone_ext>
    <email>bent.nielsen@rsyd.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Angelina I. Mellentin, Ph.D. student</last_name>
    <phone>50517901</phone>
    <phone_ext>0045</phone_ext>
    <email>amellentin@health.sdu.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unit if Clinical Alcohol Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense</city>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bent Nielsen, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>6541 4122</phone>
      <phone_ext>0045</phone_ext>
      <email>bent.nielsen@rsyd.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Angelina I. Mellentin, Ph.D. student</last_name>
      <phone>50517901</phone>
      <phone_ext>0045</phone_ext>
      <email>amellentin@health.sdu.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elsebeth Stenager, Associate professor</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anette S. Nielsen, Associate professor</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kjeld Andersen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

