<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01360411</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17765</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01360411</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tissue Characterisation by Endoscopic GI-elastography</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tissue Characterisation Using Ultrasound Based Strain Imaging(Elastography)Examining Lesions in the Gastrointestinal Wall, Adjacent Lymph Nodes and Pancreatic Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Haukeland University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Bergen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Haukeland University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this single centre study we study the use of endoscopic ultrasonography (EUS) combined
      with elastography in order to separate malignant tissue from benign tissue in and adjacent to
      the upper gastrointestinal tract.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to use endoscopic ultrasonography (EUS) with strain based
      elastography to identify strain traits separating malignant from benign lesions. We are
      registering feasibility of endoscopic strain imaging and compare diagnostic accuracy of EUS +
      elastography with previous data on EUS alone.

      Inclusion criteria:

        -  Group 1: Focal subepithelial lesions in esophageal, ventricular or duodenal wall
           discovered by endoscopy or other imaging modality.

        -  Group 2: Pancreatic lesion discovered by other imaging modality.

        -  Group 3: Mediastinal or retroperitoneal lymph node or tumor discovered by other imaging
           modality.

      Histology of lesions should not be known at the time of examination. EUS elastography
      findings are evaluated shortly after the examination and categorised by different methods;
      categorical score, VAS, Strain Ratio. The result is then compared to histology or cytology
      results. Patients who do not undergo tissue sampling are followed up to discover disease
      progress.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Malignant or benign lesion</measure>
    <time_frame>Jan 2007 - September 2011 + 6 months( if no tissue sample)(4 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Imaged lesions are sampled, surgically removed or followed up &gt; 6 months to conclude on their nature. Images are evaluated, measured and categorised shortly after examination and compared to histological, cytological or follow up result. Elastography results do not interfere with surgical or oncological treatment planning in this study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Description of lesion elasticity</measure>
    <time_frame>2007- September 2011 (4 years)</time_frame>
    <description>To identify softer and harder areas within and adjacent to focal lesions which could identify smooth surface, necrotic centre, regional fibrosis or regional cacncer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Value of Strain Ratio measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>2007 - September 2011 (4 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Strain ratio provides opportunity to compare strain in user selected areas of the elastogram. This is a semi-quantification of strain differences and may be useful for a better distinction between malignant ond non-malignant lesions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Value of colour and pattern category</measure>
    <time_frame>2007 - September 2011 (4 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Categorisation of images of lesions using a published categorising scheme and comparision to cytology, histology or follow up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Value of a Visual Analog Scale for strain image categorisation</measure>
    <time_frame>2007 - September 2011 (4 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the use of a simple 100 mm Visual analog scale to classify if lesion appears softer, equal to or harder than the surrounding tissue is useful for creating semiquantitative cut-off levels between malignant and benign lesions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">137</enrollment>
  <condition>Disorder of Upper Gastrointestinal Tract</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Nodule</condition>
  <condition>Secondary and Unspecified Malignant Neoplasm of Retroperitoneal Lymph Nodes</condition>
  <condition>Secondary Malignant Neoplasm of Lymph Node</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pancreatic lesions</arm_group_label>
    <description>Any patient with a solid pancreatic lesion of unknown histology may be recruited. Cystic lesions are not included.
Elastography findings are classified and compared to cytology or histology if the standard procedures or treatment provide this. In other cases the patients are being followed up conservatively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intramural upper GI-lesions</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with intramural lesions discovered by endoscopy or other imaging modalities are recruited. Elastography findings are classified and compared to cytology or histology if the standard procedures or treatment provide this. In other cases the patients are being followed up conservatively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lymph nodes</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with visible mediastinal lymph nodes or retroperitoneal lymph nodes in patients with inflammatory or malignant diseases are recruited. Elastography findings are classified and compared to cytology or histology if the standard procedures or treatment provide this. In other cases the patients are being followed up conservatively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Tissue samples are stored as pathological slides in the diognostic biobank of Dep. of
      Pathology, Helse Bergen.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult patients referred to EUS examination or relevant surgery at Haukeland University
        Hospital, bergen, Norway within the inclusion period (2007- January 2011).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Solid focal lesions in pancreas or pancreatitis

          -  Intramural lesions in esophagus, ventricle or duodenum

          -  Lymph nodes or tumour &gt; 1 cm in mediastinum or retroperitoneum accessible by EUS

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cystic pancreatic lesions

          -  Patients where the histology or cytology of the lesion in question is known at the
             time of examination
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lars Birger Nesje, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Bergen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roald F. Havre, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Bergen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haukeland University Hospital/University of Bergen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergen</city>
        <zip>5021</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waage JE, Havre RF, Odegaard S, Leh S, Eide GE, Baatrup G. Endorectal elastography in the evaluation of rectal tumours. Colorectal Dis. 2011 Oct;13(10):1130-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1463-1318.2010.02440.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21040360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Havre RF, Elde E, Gilja OH, Odegaard S, Eide GE, Matre K, Nesje LB. Freehand real-time elastography: impact of scanning parameters on image quality and in vitro intra- and interobserver validations. Ultrasound Med Biol. 2008 Oct;34(10):1638-50. doi: 10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2008.03.009. Epub 2008 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18524458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Săftoiu A, Vilmann P, Gorunescu F, Janssen J, Hocke M, Larsen M, Iglesias-Garcia J, Arcidiacono P, Will U, Giovannini M, Dietrich C, Havre R, Gheorghe C, McKay C, Gheonea DI, Ciurea T; European EUS Elastography Multicentric Study Group. Accuracy of endoscopic ultrasound elastography used for differential diagnosis of focal pancreatic masses: a multicenter study. Endoscopy. 2011 Jul;43(7):596-603. doi: 10.1055/s-0030-1256314. Epub 2011 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21437851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Havre RF, Waage JR, Gilja OH, Odegaard S, Nesje LB. Real-Time Elastography: Strain Ratio Measurements Are Influenced by the Position of the Reference Area. Ultraschall Med. 2011 Jun 10. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>21667433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Săftoiu A, Vilmann P, Gorunescu F, Janssen J, Hocke M, Larsen M, Iglesias-Garcia J, Arcidiacono P, Will U, Giovannini M, Dietrich CF, Havre R, Gheorghe C, McKay C, Gheonea DI, Ciurea T; European EUS Elastography Multicentric Study Group. Efficacy of an artificial neural network-based approach to endoscopic ultrasound elastography in diagnosis of focal pancreatic masses. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2012 Jan;10(1):84-90.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2011.09.014. Epub 2011 Oct 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21963957</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 26, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 25, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 4, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 4, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Roald Flesland Havre</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>elastography</keyword>
  <keyword>strain ratio</keyword>
  <keyword>pancreas</keyword>
  <keyword>GI wall lesions</keyword>
  <keyword>lymph nodes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

