<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01361295</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CE-AF-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01361295</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cerebral Embolism (CE) in Catheter Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation (AF)</brief_title>
  <acronym>CE-AF</acronym>
  <official_title>The Occurrence of Cerebral Embolism (CE) in Catheter Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation (AF) Using Two Different Ablation Catheters</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Serge A. Trines</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Leiden University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Radiofrequency catheter ablation of atrial fibrillation (AF) induces a procoagulant state,
      which leads to an acute risk for symptomatic cerebral embolism (CE) of approximately 1%. The
      induction of a procoagulant state has been studied in pulmonary vein isolation (PVI) with a
      non-cooled tip catheter. The induction of a procoagulant state using a cooled-tip catheter
      has not been studied yet. Due to the avoidance of high endocardial temperatures, it can be
      expected that these procedures induce a lower level of procoagulation.

      Recent studies showed an 11% incidence of CE on diffusion weighted (DW) MRI in patients
      undergoing cooled-tip catheter ablation of AF. In this study there will be used to different
      catheters, the cooled-tip catheter and the PVAC Gold catheter. Since the PVAC Gold catheter
      is equipped with non-cooled electrodes, the risk of endothelial scarring, local thrombosis
      and CE may be increased.

      The goal of this study is to determine the effect of two different ablation catheters on the
      induction of a procoagulant state and the incidence of CE on DW-MRI in patients with AF
      undergoing PVI.

      Our hypothesis is that patients with AF undergoing PVI using the PVAC gold catheter will show
      a higher rise in procoagulation and a higher incidence of CE on DW-MRI than patients with AF
      undergoing PVI with the cooled-tip catheter.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A total of 70 patients scheduled for a first ablation of paroxysmal AF will be included.
      Patients will be 1:1 randomized to PVI using the PVAC gold catheter or the cooled-tip
      catheter. A control group of 20 patients with AF but without undergoing ablation is included
      for neuropsychological testing.

      Before the procedure, the procoagulant state will be assessed by measuring several markers of
      endothelial damage, activated coagulation, fibrinolysis and by measurement of fibrinogen and
      thrombin generation. Measurements will be repeated during and after the procedure.

      Documentation of the formation of CE will be established by performing a DW-MRI before and
      after the ablation. The proportion of symptomatic CE will be quantified by neuropsychological
      tests and questionnaires.

      Finally, transcranial doppler will be performed during the entire procedure to quantify the
      number and pattern of cerebral microembolic signals (MES).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerebral embolism</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 24 hours before the ablation and 24 hours after the ablation</time_frame>
    <description>Cerebral embolism will be documented with diffusion weighted MRI of the brain before and after ablation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Between a week before the ablation until 3 months after the ablation</time_frame>
    <description>A decrease in neuropsychological functioning will be assessed with a questionnaire before and after the procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rise in procoagulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 24 hours before the ablation and 24 hours after the ablation</time_frame>
    <description>The procoagulant state will be assessed before, during and after the procedure by measurement of markers of endothelial damage, markers of activated coagulation, markers of fibrinolysis and by measurement of APTT, PT-INR, fibrinogen and thrombin generation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PVI with PVAC gold</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient for pulmonal vein isolation using the PVAC Gold Catheter. Intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PVI with Cooled-RF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient for pulmonal vein isolation using the Cooled-RF catheter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PVI with PVAC gold</intervention_name>
    <description>Pulmonary vein isolation using the Medtronic PVAC gold catheter</description>
    <arm_group_label>PVI with Cooled-RF</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Medtronic AF solutions</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PVI with Cooled-RF</intervention_name>
    <description>Pulmonary vein isolation using the Biosense Webster Navistar Thermocool catheter</description>
    <arm_group_label>PVI with PVAC gold</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CARTO3 system</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  suffering from drug-refractory paroxysmal atrial fibrillation

          -  scheduled for first ablation procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  contra-indications for DW-MRI

          -  previous AF-ablation

          -  minors

          -  any patient unable to undergo neuropsychological testing due to mental retardation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Serge A. Trines, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cardiology, LUMC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leiden University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <state>Zuid-Holland</state>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sauren LD, VAN Belle Y, DE Roy L, Pison L, LA Meir M, VAN DER Veen FH, Crijns HJ, Jordaens L, Mess WH, Maessen JG. Transcranial measurement of cerebral microembolic signals during endocardial pulmonary vein isolation: comparison of three different ablation techniques. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2009 Oct;20(10):1102-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1540-8167.2009.01509.x. Epub 2009 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>19549035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schrickel JW, Lickfett L, Lewalter T, Mittman-Braun E, Selbach S, Strach K, Nähle CP, Schwab JO, Linhart M, Andrié R, Nickenig G, Sommer T. Incidence and predictors of silent cerebral embolism during pulmonary vein catheter ablation for atrial fibrillation. Europace. 2010 Jan;12(1):52-7. doi: 10.1093/europace/eup350.</citation>
    <PMID>19933517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bulava A, Slavík L, Fiala M, Heinc P, Skvarilova M, Lukl J, Krcová V, Indrák K. Endothelial damage and activation of the hemostatic system during radiofrequency catheter isolation of pulmonary veins. J Interv Card Electrophysiol. 2004 Jun;10(3):271-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15133367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Leiden University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Serge A. Trines</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior cardiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>cerebral embolism</keyword>
  <keyword>catheter ablation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intracranial Embolism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

