<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01363284</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>diabetic_Duloxetine09CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01363284</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pretreatment Identification of Duloxetine Success in Neuropathic Pain Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pretreatment Identification of Duloxetine Success in Neuropathic Pain Patients Based on Assessment of Endogenous Analgesia Capabilities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rambam Health Care Campus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rambam Health Care Campus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to identify, prior to prescribing, which neuropathic pain
      patients will benefit from duloxetine more specific the investigators aims are to:

        -  Verify whether presence of chronic pain alters the pain modulation mechanisms, such as
           DNIC (diffuse noxious inhibitory control) and TS (temporal summation).

        -  Investigate whether anti-neuropathic medications such as duloxetine indeed change the
           pain modulation profile, and whether this profile change is associated with a reduction
           of clinical pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is no accepted practice for selecting among recommended medications for the individual
      neuropathic pain patient. Guidelines published to date provided the evidence for their
      efficacy, however, data is not available on how to choose the right medication for the right
      patient in order to avoid long 'trial and error's. We hypothesize that medications affecting
      specific process of pain modulation will be more efficacious in patients expressing
      dysfunction of that specific process. Therefore, medications that enhance descending
      inhibition such as SSNRI will be more efficacious in patients with less-efficient pain
      inhibition. The latter is assessed by the conditioned pain modulation (CPM) paradigm.
      Accordingly, the aim of this study is to examine this hypothesis in painful diabetic
      neuropathy patients, using duloxetine, an SSNRI agent assumed to augment descending pain
      inhibition by reuptake inhibition of noradrenalin and serotonin in the spinal cord dorsal
      horn synapses. We expect to find better effect of duloxetine in those patients whose pain
      inhibition capability is less efficient, as expressed by their baseline CPM. Further, we aim
      to evaluate whether pro-nocieptive pattern of pain modulation indeed reverses in response to
      treatment. This will be explored by comparing the CPM responses before and after treatment,
      and by correlating pain alleviation with the possible changes in CPM.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prediction of duloxetine pain relief efficacy by pre-treatment extent of the CPM response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Regression model will assess predictive value of baseline pre-treatment extent of the CPM response and pain relief efficacy of duloxetine treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment-related increase in CPM response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>We propose that treatment-related increase in CPM response will be correlated with duloxetine pain relief efficacy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Painful Neuropathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Duloxetine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The first week of the treatment is the placebo treatment. The effect of placebo will be taken into consideration for further evaluation the duloxetine effect on clinical pain and descending pain inhibition capabilities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Duloxetine</intervention_name>
    <description>First week of placebo. then, initial dose of 30 mg/d will be given for one week, in order to minimize possible side effects and drop outs, and then a fixed dose of 60 mg/d will be given for additional 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Duloxetine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SSNRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed as having painful diabetic neuropathy.

          -  Pain is experienced for more than 3 months.

          -  Pain severity is ≥ 4 on a 0-10 scale (last month average).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient already receiving duloxetine or another SNRI/SSRI.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to duloxetine or any of the inactive ingredients.

          -  Treatment with a monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI) within 14 days of randomization or
             potential need to use an MAOI during the study or within 5 days of discontinuation of
             study drug.

          -  Uncontrolled narrow-angle glaucoma

          -  Because of the risk of serious ventricular arrhythmias and sudden death potentially
             associated with elevated plasma levels of thioridazine (Mellaril), Cymbalta and
             thioridazine should not be co-administered

          -  Inability to perform psychophysical testing, due to language or perceptual barriers.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Yarnitsky, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rambam Health Care Campus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rambam Medical center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rambam Health Care Campus</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>d_yarnitsky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Neurology Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Duloxetine Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

