<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01620216</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00007195</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01084</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CA180-392</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB00007195</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA069533</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R21CA159265</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01620216</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeted Therapy in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia or Acute Myelogenous Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Proof-of-Concept Trial to Study Kinase Inhibition in Relapsed/Refractory Acute Leukemias: Using a Comprehensive In Vitro Kinase Inhibitor Panel to Select Individualized, Targeted Therapies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well targeted therapy works in treating patients with acute
      lymphoblastic leukemia or acute myelogenous leukemia that has come back after a period of
      improvement or does not respond to treatment. Testing patients' blood or bone marrow to find
      out if their type of cancer may be sensitive to a specific drug may help doctors choose more
      effective treatments. Dasatinib, nilotinib, sunitinib malate, sorafenib tosylate, and
      ponatinib hydrochloride may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes
      needed for cell growth. Giving targeted therapy based on cancer type may be an effective
      treatment for acute lymphoblastic leukemia or acute myelogenous leukemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the clinical activity of kinase inhibitors using pre-clinical (in-vitro)
      activity to select individual therapy.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate overall objective response rates (complete response plus partial response).

      II. Determine overall survival (OS) and progression-free survival (PFS). III. Any changes in
      transfusion requirements.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Prioritize active/aberrant kinase pathways using an in vitro inhibitor screen using
      individual primary leukemia samples.

      II. Measure &quot;on target&quot; in vivo kinase inhibition and signal transducer and activator of
      transcription (STAT)-5 phosphorylation and correlate with response to treatment.

      III. Perform next generation sequencing (whole exome sequencing) for complete mutational
      analysis.

      IV. Identify aberrant gene expression in primary leukemia samples from study subjects.

      V. Evaluate pharmacokinetics for each individual kinase inhibitor during therapy.

      OUTLINE: Patients are assigned to 1 of 5 treatment groups based on pre-clinical kinase
      inhibitor activity.

      GROUP I: Patients receive dasatinib orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-28. Courses repeat
      every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      GROUP II: Patients receive nilotinib PO twice daily (BID) on days 1-28. Courses repeat every
      28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      GROUP III: Patients receive sunitinib malate PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days
      in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      GROUP IV: Patients receive sorafenib tosylate PO BID on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28
      days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      GROUP V: Patients receive ponatinib hydrochloride PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28
      days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up periodically.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 11, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical activity, defined as a decrease of at least 25% in bone marrow blast counts</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients achieving the endpoint along with its 95% exact binomial confidence interval will be presented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in transfusion requirements</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will measure any changes in transfusion requirements.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical activity (defined as a decrease of at least 25% in bone marrow blast counts) in subjects who have failed the initial inhibitor but are then treated with another inhibitor identified on repeat pre-clinical activity testing</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients achieving the endpoint along with its 95% exact binomial confidence interval will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of registration to date of death or disease progression defined as an increase of at least 50% in leukemic bone marrow blasts, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier method will be used to estimate the survival curve.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall objective response rates (complete and partial), determined using formal acute myelogenous leukemia and acute lymphoblastic leukemia response criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients achieving the endpoint along with its 95% exact binomial confidence interval will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of registration to death, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan-Meier method will be used to estimate the survival curve.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of active/aberrant kinase pathways</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be correlated with treatment response, mutational analysis using next generation sequencing, and characterization of aberrant gene expression in primary leukemia samples.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia Arising From Previous Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myelomonocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (dasatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive dasatinib PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (nilotinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive nilotinib PO BID on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group III (sunitinib malate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive sunitinib malate PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group IV (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive sorafenib tosylate PO BID on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group V (ponatinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive ponatinib hydrochloride PO QD on days 1-28. Courses repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antitumor Drug Screening Assay</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo pre clinical kinase inhibitor activity screening</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (dasatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (nilotinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group III (sunitinib malate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group IV (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group V (ponatinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Drug Screening Assays, Antitumor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dasatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (dasatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMS-354825</other_name>
    <other_name>Sprycel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (dasatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (nilotinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group III (sunitinib malate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group IV (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group V (ponatinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nilotinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (nilotinib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AMN 107</other_name>
    <other_name>Tasigna</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I (dasatinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group II (nilotinib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group III (sunitinib malate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group IV (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group V (ponatinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ponatinib Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group V (ponatinib hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AP24534 HCl</other_name>
    <other_name>Iclusig</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sorafenib Tosylate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group IV (sorafenib tosylate)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BAY 43-9006 Tosylate</other_name>
    <other_name>BAY 54-9085</other_name>
    <other_name>Nexavar</other_name>
    <other_name>sorafenib</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sunitinib Malate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group III (sunitinib malate)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SU011248</other_name>
    <other_name>SU11248</other_name>
    <other_name>sunitinib</other_name>
    <other_name>Sutent</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with &gt;= 18 years of age with relapsed/refractory leukemia with a confirmed
             diagnosis of acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) or acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)
             who meet the following criteria:

               -  Age 18-64: Salvage treatment failures only - defined as relapsed or refractory to
                  after least 1 cycle of salvage therapy

               -  Age &gt;= 65: Refractory to or have relapsed after induction chemotherapy defined as
                  no response to initial therapy

                    -  Given the clinical activity and use of hypomethylating agents in AML
                       patients, for all AML populations, initial therapy and salvage therapy may
                       include hypomethylating agents; furthermore, patients &gt;= 65 with hematologic
                       malignancies including chronic myelomonocytic leukemia (CMML) or
                       myelodysplasia (MDS) that transform to acute leukemia while actively
                       receiving hypomethylating agents (i.e. decitabine or azacytidine) will be
                       considered induction failures and thus are eligible; for Philadelphia
                       positive (Ph+) ALL, initial therapy and salvage therapy may include steroids
                       and imatinib or dasatinib or nilotinib

          -  Primary patient samples must show in vitro kinase inhibitor sensitivity as determined
             by the Oregon Health and Science University (OHSU) functional kinase inhibitor screen;
             for OHSU patients, functional kinase inhibitor screening may be performed as part of
             this study or through enrollment in eIRB4422 if the identical Food and Drug
             Administration (FDA)/Clinical Laboratory Improvement Act (CLIA) approved assay is used
             and a result is available within 2 weeks of starting on study drug treatment

          -  Have not received any leukemia treatment within 1 week prior to starting study drug;
             corticosteroids up to 20 mg of prednisone (or equivalent) is allowable throughout the
             study; doses &gt; 20 mg prednisone (or equivalent) are NOT permitted; doses of steroids
             =&lt; 20 mg of prednisone (or equivalent) are permitted; hydroxyurea is allowed prior to
             enrollment and after the start of the study drug for the control of peripheral
             leukemic blasts in subjects with leukocytosis per physician discretion

          -  Patients must have normal organ function as defined below:

               -  Serum creatinine &lt; 2.0 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  International normalized ratio (INR) &lt; 1.5 x institutional ULN

          -  Adequate hepatic function as defined by the following criteria:

               -  Total serum bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper normal limit (ULN), unless due to Gilbert?s
                  syndrome

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Discontinuation of anti-coagulants and anti-platelet drugs at least 7 days prior to
             start of study drug; aspirin 81 mg is permitted as long as platelet count is &gt; 50 and
             there is no evidence of active bleeding or coagulopathy (INR &gt; 1.5, fibrinogen &gt; 150)

          -  No uncontrolled infections as determined by the investigator

          -  No uncontrolled thyroid disease (e.g. hyperthyroid/hypothyroidism)

          -  No active graft versus host disease (GVHD): patients with a history of stem cell
             transplant are eligible but cannot have evidence of active GVHD as determined by the
             investigator

          -  Must be able to take oral medication

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             (sensitivity &lt; 25 IU human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG)/L) within 72 hours prior to
             the start of study drug

          -  Persons of reproductive potential must agree to use an adequate method of
             contraception throughout treatment and for at least 4 weeks after study drug is
             stopped; women of childbearing potential and men with a sexual partner of childbearing
             potential must be advised of the importance of avoiding pregnancy during trial
             participation and the potential risk factors for an unintentional pregnancy

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent and
             Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPPA) document

          -  Ponatinib

               -  Female and male patients who are fertile must agree to use an effective form of
                  contraception with their sexual partners from randomization through 4 months
                  after the end of treatment

               -  Discontinuation of any medications known to contribute significantly to the risk
                  of QT prolongation at least 48 hours prior to start of study drug; Levaquin and
                  Zofran are an exception; of note, certain agents that prolong the corrected QT
                  interval (QTc) may be allowed but only after discussion with the chemotherapy
                  pharmacist; should the investigator believe that therapy with a potentially QT
                  prolonging medication is vital to an individual subject?s care, then additional
                  electrocardiograms (ECGs) should be done at the investigator?s discretion to
                  ensure the subject?s safety

               -  Serum lipase =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

               -  Serum amylase =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Dasatinib

               -  Normal QTc interval on screening ECG evaluation, defined as &lt; 450 msec for men
                  and &lt; 470 msec for women; discontinuation of any medications known to contribute
                  significantly to the risk of QT prolongation at least 48 hours prior to start of
                  study drug; Levaquin and Zofran are an exception; of note, certain agents that
                  prolong the corrected QT interval may be allowed but only after discussion with
                  the chemotherapy pharmacist; should the investigator believe that therapy with a
                  potentially QT prolonging medication is vital to an individual subject?s care,
                  then additional ECGs should be done at the investigator?s discretion to ensure
                  the subject?s safety

               -  Serum Na, K, Mg, and total serum Ca or ionized Ca levels must be greater than or
                  equal to the institutional lower limit of normal; subjects with low K or Mg
                  levels, total serum Ca and/or ionized Ca must be replete for protocol entry

               -  Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative serum or urine
                  pregnancy test (minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L or equivalent units of HCG) within 24
                  hours prior to the start of study drug

               -  Men who are sexually active with WOCBP must agree to follow instructions for
                  method(s) of contraception for the duration of treatment with study drug plus 90
                  days (duration of sperm turnover) for a total of 90 days post-treatment
                  completion

               -  Azoospermic males and WOCBP, who are not heterosexually active, are exempt from
                  contraceptive requirements; however, WOCBP must still under pregnancy testing as
                  described in this section

               -  Investigators shall counsel WOCBP and male subjects who are sexually active with
                  WOCBP on the importance of pregnancy prevention and the implications of
                  unexpected pregnancy; investigators shall advise WOCBP and male subjects who are
                  sexually active with WOCBP on the use of highly effective contraception; highly
                  effective methods of contraception have a failure rate of &lt; 1% when used
                  consistently and correctly

               -  At a minimum, subjects must agree to the use of two methods of contraception,
                  with one method being highly effective and the other method being either highly
                  effective or less effective as listed

          -  Nilotinib

               -  Normal QTc interval on screening ECG evaluation, defined as &lt; 450 msec for men
                  and &lt; 470 msec for women

               -  Discontinuation of any medications known to contribute significantly to the risk
                  of QT prolongation at least 48 hours prior to start of study drug; Levaquin and
                  Zofran are an exception; of note, certain agents that prolong the corrected QT
                  interval may be allowed but only after discussion with the chemotherapy
                  pharmacist; should the investigator believe that therapy with a potentially QT
                  prolonging medication is vital to an individual subject?s care, then additional
                  ECGs should be done at the investigator?s discretion to ensure the subject?s
                  safety

          -  Sorafenib

               -  Creatinine (Crt) &lt; 1.5 X ULN

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients may not receive concurrent chemotherapy, radiotherapy or immunotherapy, nor
             have received any investigational agents within 7 days prior to drug sensitivity
             screening

          -  Patients with any of the following:

               -  Uncontrolled angina at time of consent OR

               -  &gt; New York Heart Association (NYHA) class II congestive heart failure at time of
                  consent OR

               -  Myocardial infarction (MI) within 6 months prior to start of study treatment

          -  Diagnosed congenital long QT syndrome

          -  Any history of clinically significant ventricular arrhythmias (such as ventricular
             tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, or torsades de pointes)

          -  History of significant bleeding disorder unrelated to cancer

          -  Drugs that affect the cytochrome P450 family 3 subfamily A polypeptide 4 (CYP3A4)
             system (inducers/inhibitors/substrates) are allowed but should be used with caution
             depending on specific kinase inhibitor used; dietary supplements will be discouraged;
             however, their use may be allowed on a case by case basis per the discretion of the
             investigator after consultation with an oncology pharmacist

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Pregnant or lactating women are excluded from this study

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients are excluded from the study

          -  Ponatinib

               -  History of acute pancreatitis within 1 year of study or history of chronic
                  pancreatitis

               -  History of alcohol abuse

               -  Uncontrolled hypertriglyceridemia (triglycerides &gt; 450 mg/dL)

               -  Clinically significant, uncontrolled, or active cardiovascular disease,
                  specifically including, but not restricted to:

                    -  Any history of myocardial infarction, stroke, or revascularization

                    -  Unstable angina or transient ischemic attack within 6 months prior to start
                       of study treatment

                    -  Congestive heart failure within 6 months prior to enrollment, or left
                       ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) less than lower limit of normal per
                       local institutional standards within 6 months prior to enrollment

                    -  History of clinically significant (as determined by the treating physician)
                       atrial arrhythmia

                    -  Any history of ventricular arrhythmia

                    -  Any history of venous thromboembolism including deep venous thrombosis or
                       pulmonary embolism

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension (diastolic blood pressure &gt; 90 mm Hg; systolic &gt; 140 mm
                  Hg); patients with hypertension should be under treatment on study entry to
                  effect blood pressure control; taking medications that are known to be associated
                  with torsades de pointes

               -  Taking any medications or herbal supplements that are known to be strong
                  inhibitors of CYP3A4 within at least 14 days before the first dose of ponatinib

               -  Ocular toxicity present as measured during a comprehensive eye exam

          -  Dasatinib

               -  Known pulmonary arterial hypertension

               -  Patients may not have pleural or pericardial effusion of any grade

               -  Patients may not have clinically significant pleural or pericardial effusion per
                  provider discretion

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension: inability to maintain blood pressure below the limit
                  of 140/90 mgHg

               -  Any history of second or third degree heart block (may be eligible of the subject
                  currently has a pacemaker)

          -  Sorafenib

               -  Major surgery, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury within 30 days

               -  Non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture

               -  Thrombotic or embolic venous or arterial events, such as cerebrovascular
                  accident, including transient ischemic attacks, arterial thrombosis, deep vein
                  thrombosis and pulmonary embolism within the past 6 months

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension

               -  Active bleeding during screening

               -  Hypersensitivity to sorafenib
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Spurgeon</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart Lung and Blood Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20824</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher S. Hourigan</last_name>
      <phone>301-803-8029</phone>
      <email>hourigan@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher S. Hourigan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc Loriaux</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-9383</phone>
      <email>loriauxm@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc Loriaux</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern/Simmons Cancer Center-Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert H. Collins</last_name>
      <phone>214-648-4155</phone>
      <email>robert.collins@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert H. Collins</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huntsman Cancer Institute/University of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tibor J. Kovacsovics</last_name>
      <phone>801-585-3229</phone>
      <email>tibor.kovacsovics@hci.utah.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tibor J. Kovacsovics</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 14, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stephen Spurgeon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Juvenile</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sunitinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ponatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dasatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antineoplastic Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

