<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03494608</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UIACGF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03494608</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Postoperative Cognitive Function, Anxiety, Depression and Quality of Life in Patients With Unruptured Intracranial Aneurysms</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Postoperative Cognitive Function, Anxiety, Depression and Quality of Life in Patients With Unruptured Intracranial Aneurysms: a Multi-center Prospective Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xuanwu Hospital, Beijing</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>West China Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tang-Du Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xuanwu Hospital, Beijing</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This prospective single-center cohort study aims to identify the incidence of cognitive
      dysfunction after unruptured aneurysm operation and explore the influencing factors. The
      primary end point is the cognitive dysfunction at 6 months after operation.The features of
      cognitive function, mental status, neurological function recovery, and quality of life of
      patients with unruptured intracranial aneurysms at different time points would be analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This main topics is to identify and screen the patients with unruptured aneurysm who likely
      to suffer from cognitive dysfunction. All examinations were administered by a trained
      neuropsychologist.The assessment of cognitive function and mental state would be performed
      before operation and 6 months after operation, with the use of Montreal Cognitive Assessment
      Scale (MoCA) for the cognitive function, the Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAMA) and the Hamilton
      Depression Scale (HDMA) tests for the mental state. The Cognitive dysfunction at 6 months
      after operation would be the primary end point, and the underlying factors responsible for
      the declined cognitive function would be analyze. The assessment of neurological function and
      quality of life would be performed before operation,3 months after operation and 6 months
      after operation, with the use of the Modified Rankin Scale(mRS) and the Functional Activities
      Questionnaire(FAQ) for the neurological function, the Richards—Campbell Sleep
      Questionnaire(RCSQ) and the 36-item short from health survey(SF-36) tests for the quality of
      life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the Incidence of cognitive dysfunction at 6 months after operation</measure>
    <time_frame>the 6th month after operation of the patient inclusion in the study</time_frame>
    <description>The Montreal Cognitive Assessment Scale (MoCA) scale contains 8 cognitive domain,11 items and is suitable for assess cognitive function which including: Attention and concentration, executive function, memory, language, visual structure skills, abstract thinking, calculation and orientation.. 1 point for each correct answer. No points if they make any errors. The total score is 30 points. For those who have been educated for 12 years or less and the total score of MoCA is less than 30, one point is added to the total MoCA score. According to the results of MoCA assessment, Patients were divided into two groups: cognitive dysfunction group and cognitive function normal group. MoCA score ≥26 points suggested normal cognitive function (CN).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the difference in the percentage of patients with HAMA score ≥14 before operation and 6 months after operation</measure>
    <time_frame>before operation and the 6th month after operation of the patient inclusion in the study</time_frame>
    <description>The Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAMA) scale contains 14 items and is suitable for the adults with anxiety. Each item is divided into 5 grades evaluated using 0 to 4 scores. The total scores of HAMA scale can reflect patients' anxious condition to some extent. The total scores of less than 7 is regarded as no anxiety, 7 or more possible anxiety, 14 or more definite anxiety, 21 or more marked anxiety, 29 or more severe anxiety. In this study, Anxiety is defined as≥14 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the difference in the percentage of patients with HDMA score ≥14 before operation and 6 months after operation</measure>
    <time_frame>before operation and the 6th month after operation of the patient inclusion in the study</time_frame>
    <description>The Hamilton Depression Scale (HAMD) scale contains 24 items and is suitable for the adults with depression. Each item is divided into 5 grades evaluated using 0 to 4 scores. The total scores of the HAMD scale can reflect patients' depressive condition to some extent. The total scores of less than 8 is regarded as no depression, 8 to 16 mild depression, 17 to 24 moderate depression, and more than 24 severe depression. In this study, Depression is defined as≥14 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the tendency of mRS scores and the difference in the percentage of patients with mRS scores 0-3 and 4-6 points before operation, 3 months after operation, and 6 months after operation</measure>
    <time_frame>before operation ,the 3th month and the 6th month after operation of the patient inclusion in the study</time_frame>
    <description>The Modified Rankin Scale (mRS) is a valid and clinically relevant instrument that is used to assess recovery (death, disability, and dependence) after stroke and is a commonly used outcome measure in SAH studies. The mRS ranges from 0 (no symptoms) to 6 (death). Unfavourable outcome in survivors is defined as mRS 3-5.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the tendency of SF-36 scores before operation, 3 months after operation, and 6 months after operation</measure>
    <time_frame>before operation ,the 3th month and the 6th month after operation of the patient inclusion in the study</time_frame>
    <description>36-item short form health survey(SF-36)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Intracranial Aneurysm</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        the patients with unruptured intracranial aneurysms who treated in neurosurgery at Xuanwu
        Hospital
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At least one imaging (CTA / MRI / DSA) study to confirm unruptured intracranial
             aneurysms for the patients who would undergo surgical treatment for the first time.;

          2. Patients who live independent with minimal care support, mRS score ≤3 points;

          3. Age &gt; 14 years old;

          4. Han ethnicity, Right handed, can complete the test;

          5. Patient or family agrees to sign informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Other cerebrovascular diseases，such as ischemic stroke, arteriovenous malformation,
             etc;

          2. With an unexplained subarachnoid hemorrhage;

          3. History of Neurological disease surgery;

          4. Previous psychiatric and dementia history that cannot communicate with other people;

          5. Patients who refused to follow up.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jun Wang, Master</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Xuanwu Hospital, Beijing</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jun Wang, Master</last_name>
    <phone>(86)010-83198899</phone>
    <phone_ext>8639</phone_ext>
    <email>wangj229@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Xuanwu Hospital, Beijing</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jun Wang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief nurse of Neurosurgery Department, professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cognitive function</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>neurological function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intracranial Aneurysm</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

