<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03491241</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>22.3.2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03491241</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Inflammatory Axis and Sirtuins' in Overweight Pre-diabetics Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Inflammatory Axis and Sirtuins' Expression in a Population of Overweight Pre-diabetics Patients From Metabolic Homeostasis Towards the Adipogonesis, and to Cardiac Redomelling.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Campania &quot;Luigi Vanvitelli&quot;</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Campania &quot;Luigi Vanvitelli&quot;</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In obese patients the superficial adipose tissue works as an endocrine active tissue to
      express different cytokines, and multiple molecular pathways implied in the cross talking
      with different part of the human body, such as the cardiovascular system. To date, adipocytes
      and adipose tissue-derived macrophages and adipose tissue synthesize, and secrete several
      cytokines, and sirtuins. In this setting, the excess of body fat is linked to heart
      contractile dysfunction. All these pathways are differently expressed in obese diabetic
      patients as compared to obese non diabetic patients. Intriguingly, in diabetic obese patients
      the hyper-expression of inflammatory cytokines is associated to a hypo-expression of
      sirtuins. Therefore, this molecular pattern in diabetic obese patients may correlate to
      altered myocardial performance, and to the development of heart failure disease. In this
      study authors will evaluate at baseline by peripheral blood samples and by the abdominal fat
      tissue, the expression of cytokines and sirtuins comparing pre-diabetics obese patients vs.
      non pre-diabetics obese patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In obese patients the visceral fat, and the superficial adipose tissue work as an endocrine
      active tissue to express different cytokines, and multiple molecular pathways implied in the
      cross talking with different part of the human body, such as the cardiovascular system. To
      date, adipocytes, and adipose tissue-derived macrophages and adipose tissue, synthesize and
      secrete several cytokines, like tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-5 and interleukin (IL)-6, and
      anti-apoptotic proteins, such as sirtuins. Sirtuins are NAD+-dependent deacetylase involved
      in the control of energy metabolism, adipocyte hypertrophy, and of different cardiac
      reparative, and rimodellative functions. In this setting, the excess of body fat is linked to
      heart contractile dysfunction. It is intuitive to speculate that, all these pathways are
      differently expressed in obese diabetic patients as compared to obese non diabetic patients.
      Intriguingly, in diabetic obese patients the hyper-expression of inflammatory cytokines is
      associated to a hypo-expression of sirtuins. Therefore, this molecular pattern in diabetic
      obese patients may correlate to altered myocardial performance, and to the development of
      heart failure disease. Authors' study hypothesis is that, this complex altered bidirectional
      pattern between the inflammatory and apoptotic pathways axis may be due to a progressive
      increase in adipose tissue, produced by long-term alterations in energy balance. However, all
      these alterations may be measured in adipocytes as well as in adipose tissue derived
      macrophages, and by peripheral blood assay. Intriguingly, no data evaluated these pathways in
      pre-diabetics obese patients, and their possible correlation to cardiac function worsening,
      and to the development of heart failure disease. Actually, the pre-diabetic obese subjects
      represent a population of patients associated to higher risk to develop cardiovascular
      disease, myocardial dysfunction, and heart failure. In these patients a not clear indication
      exists about the right dietetic and/or drug treatment to control the hyperglycemia. However,
      there is discussion about the necessity or not to introduce hypoglycemic drug therapy added
      to a hypocaloric diet therapy to control the hyperglycemic overload. Therefore, the aim of
      the present study will be to evaluate at baseline the abdominal fat tissue expression of
      cytokines and sirtuins (by direct tissue biopsy) and by peripheral blood samples in
      pre-diabetics obese patients vs. non pre-diabetics obese patients. As second, during six and
      twelve months of follow up by peripheral blood samples analysis authors will evaluate the
      abdominal fat tissue expression of cytokines and sirtuins in pre-diabetics obese patients
      treated by hypocaloric diet-therapy as compared to pre-diabetics obese patients treated by
      hypocaloric diet-therapy plus metformine. At the end, authors will report their correlation
      to myocardial performance index (MPI) as an index of myocardial performance in pre-diabetics
      obese patients treated by hypocaloric diet-therapy as compared to pre-diabetics obese
      patients treated by hypocaloric diet-therapy plus metformine. Authors may speculate to
      observe a different cytokines and sirtuins expression at visceral fat and peripheral blood in
      pre-diabetics obese patients vs. non pre-diabetics obese patients. As second, authors may
      find that, hypoglycemic drug therapy may induce a down regulation of peripheral blood
      cytokines, and a hyper expression of sirtuins involved in the control of energy metabolism,
      and of adipocyte hypertrophy, and secondary implied in a better cardiac function at follow
      up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>left ventricle ejection fraction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>authors will assess left ventricle ejection fraction by trans thoracic bidimensional echocardiographic measurements.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Pre-diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pre-diabetics obese patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>These pre-diabetic obese patients will be treated by hypocaloric diet therapy plus metformine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pre-diabetics patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>These pre-diabetic patients will be treated by hypocaloric diet therapy alone.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>obese patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>These obese patients will be treated by hypocaloric diet therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hypocaloric diet therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>all patients will receive an hypocaloric diet, with low carboidrates (&lt;50%) overload.</description>
    <arm_group_label>pre-diabetics obese patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>pre-diabetics patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>obese patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>all patients will receive a metformin therapy for hyperlgycemia, in addition to hypocaloric diet.</description>
    <arm_group_label>pre-diabetics obese patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  body mass index &gt; 30;

          -  prediabetes;

          -  normal glycemic blood profile;

          -  both gender;

          -  age &gt; 18 and &lt; 65 years old.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  body mass index &lt; 30;

          -  diabetes;

          -  age &lt; 18, and &gt; 65 years old.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Raffaele Marfella</name>
      <address>
        <city>Naples</city>
        <zip>80138</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Campania &quot;Luigi Vanvitelli&quot;</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Celestino Sardu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prediabetic State</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Intolerance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

