<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03493282</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COG0105</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03493282</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of CT1812 Treatment on Brain Synaptic Density</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Synaptic Vesicle Glycoprotein 2A (SV2A) PET Study to Evaluate the Effect of CT1812 Treatment on Synaptic Density in Participants With Mild to Moderate Alzheimer's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cognition Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cognition Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group study
      of two doses of CT1812 in adults with mild to moderate Alzheimer's Disease to evaluate the
      safety and tolerability of oral CT1812, administered for up 180 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effect of CT1812 on Activities of Daily Living (ADCS-ADL) in AD patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive outcomes in AD patients will be assessed by using the Alzheimer's Disease Clinical Study - Activities of Daily Living (ADCS-ADL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Treatment- CT1812 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>7 subjects randomized to 100 mg CT1812</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Treatment- CT1812 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>7 subjects randomized to 300 mg CT1812</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>7 subjects randomized to matching placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active Treatment- CT1812 100 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Active Study Drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Treatment- CT1812 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Study Drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-active study drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Matching placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active Treatment- CT1812 300 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Active Study Drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Treatment- CT1812 300 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Study Drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants may be included in the study only if they meet all of the following
             criteria:

               1. Men, and women of non-childbearing potential, 50-85 years of age inclusively,
                  with a diagnosis of mild to moderate Alzheimer's disease according to the 2011
                  NIA-AA criteria and at least a 6 month decline in cognitive function documented
                  in the medical record.

                    1. Non-childbearing potential for women is defined as postmenopausal [last
                       natural menses greater than 24 months; in women under age 55, menopausal
                       status will be documented with serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH)
                       test] or undergone a documented bilateral tubal ligation or hysterectomy.

                    2. Male participants who are sexually active with a woman of child-bearing
                       potential must agree to use condoms during the trial and for 3 months after
                       last dose unless the woman is using an acceptable means of birth control.
                       Acceptable forms of birth control include abstinence, birth control pills,
                       or any double combination of: intrauterine device (IUD), male or female
                       condom, diaphragm, sponge, and cervical cap.

               2. Neuroimaging (MRI) obtained during screening consistent with the clinical
                  diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease and without findings of significant exclusionary
                  abnormalities (see exclusion criteria, number 3).

               3. MMSE 18-26 inclusive

               4. A positive amyloid (Pittsburgh imaging compound B) scan at screening, or history
                  of a positive amyloid scan prior to study entry, or prior lumbar puncture with a
                  CSF Abeta concentration consistent with Alzheimer's disease.

               5. Formal education of eight or more years.

               6. Must have a caregiver who sees them at least 10 hours per week, oversees the
                  administration of study drug, and is willing and able to oversee administration
                  of study medication and participate in all clinic visits and some study
                  assessments. The caregiver must provide written informed consent to participate
                  in the study.

               7. Living at home or in the community (assisted living acceptable)

               8. Able to swallow CT1812 capsules.

               9. Stable pharmacological treatment of any other chronic conditions for at least 30
                  days prior to screening.

              10. Capable of providing either written informed consent or oral assent to the study
                  procedures and for use of protected health information [Health Insurance
                  Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) Authorization, if applicable]. If the
                  Participant can provide only assent, their legally authorized representative also
                  must provide written informed consent. Written informed consent also shall be
                  obtained from the responsible caregiver. All consent processes must be undertaken
                  in the presence of a witness and prior to any study procedures.

              11. Must consent to apolipoprotein E (ApoE) genotyping.

              12. Generally healthy with mobility (ambulatory or ambulatory-aided, i.e., walker or
                  cane), vision and hearing (hearing aid permissible) sufficient for compliance
                  with testing procedures.

              13. Able to complete all screening evaluations.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants will be excluded from the study if any of the following conditions apply:

               1. Hospitalization or change of chronic concomitant medication within one month
                  prior to screening.

               2. Patients living in a continuous care nursing facility

               3. Screening MRI of the brain indicative of significant abnormality, including, but
                  not limited to, prior hemorrhage or infarct &gt; 1 cm3, &gt;3 lacunar infarcts,
                  cerebral contusion, encephalomalacia, aneurysm, vascular malformation, subdural
                  hematoma, hydrocephalus, space-occupying lesion (e.g. abscess or brain tumor such
                  as meningioma).

               4. MRI incompatible implants and other contraindications for MRI, such as pacemaker,
                  artificial joints, non-removable body piercings, etc. Additionally, participants
                  who meet the following imaging exclusion criteria will not be included in this
                  study:

                    1. Claustrophobia that will result in significant anxiety and difficulty lying
                       still for brain imaging (MRI or PET).

                    2. Participation in other research studies involving ionizing radiation within
                       one year of the PET scans that would cause the participant to exceed the
                       yearly dose limits for healthy volunteers.

                    3. History of IV drug use that would prevent venous access for PET tracer
                       injection.

                    4. Severe motor problems that prevent the participant from lying still for
                       brain imaging.

                    5. Severe chronic pain (e.g., as the result of rheumatoid arthritis) that would
                       prevent them from lying still during brain imaging.

               5. Clinical or laboratory findings consistent with:

                    1. Other primary degenerative dementia, (dementia with Lewy bodies,
                       fronto-temporal dementia, Huntington's disease, Jacob-Creutzfeld Disease,
                       Down's syndrome, etc.)

                    2. Other neurodegenerative condition (Parkinson's disease, amyotrophic lateral
                       sclerosis, etc.)

                    3. Seizure disorder

                    4. Other infectious, metabolic or systemic diseases affecting the central
                       nervous system (syphilis, present hypothyroidism, present vitamin B12 or
                       folate deficiency, other laboratory values) etc.)

               6. A current DSM-V diagnosis of active major depression, schizophrenia or bipolar
                  disorder. Patients with depressive symptoms successfully managed by a stable dose
                  of an antidepressant are allowed entry.

               7. Clinically significant, advanced or unstable disease that may interfere with
                  outcome evaluations, such as:

                    1. Chronic liver disease, liver function test abnormalities or other signs of
                       hepatic insufficiency (ALT, AST, total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN)

                    2. Respiratory insufficiency

                    3. Renal insufficiency eGFR &lt; 45 mL/min based on the CKD‐EPI formula
                       (https://www.questdiagnostics.com/home/physicians/egfr-calculator)Heart
                       disease (myocardial infarction, unstable angina, heart failure,
                       cardiomyopathy within six months before screening)

                    4. Bradycardia (&lt;45/min.) or tachycardia (&gt;100/min.)

                    5. Poorly managed hypertension (systolic &gt;160 mm Hg and/or diastolic &gt;95 mm Hg)
                       or hypotension (systolic &lt;90 mm Hg and/or diastolic &lt;60 mm Hg)

                    6. Uncontrolled diabetes defined by HbA1c &gt;8

               8. History of cancer within 3 years of screening with the exception of fully excised
                  non-melanoma skin cancers or non-metastatic prostate cancer that has been stable
                  for at least 6 months.

               9. Seropositive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

              10. History of acute/chronic hepatitis B or C and/or carriers of hepatitis B
                  (seropositive for Hepatitis B surface antigen [HbsAg] or anti-Hepatitis C [HCV]
                  antibody).

              11. Clinically significant abnormalities in screening laboratory tests, including:

                    1. hematocrit less than 33% for males and less than 30% for females

                    2. absolute neutrophil cell count of 1200/uL (with the exception of a
                       documented history of a chronic benign neutropenia), or platelet cell count
                       of &lt; 120,000/uL

                    3. INR &gt;1.4 or other coagulopathy, confirmed by repeat.

              12. Disability that may prevent the patient from completing all study requirements
                  (e.g. blindness, deafness, severe language difficulty, etc.)

              13. Women who are fertile and of childbearing potential.

              14. Within 4 weeks of screening visit or during the course of the study, concurrent
                  treatment with antipsychotic agents (except risperidone ≤1.5 mg/day, quetiapine
                  ≤100 mg/day, olanzapine ≤5 mg/day, and aripiprazole ≤10 mg/day), antiepileptics
                  (except gabapentin and pregabalin for nonseizure indications), centrally active
                  anti-hypertensive drugs (e.g., clonidine, l-methyl dopa, guanidine, guanfacine,
                  etc.), opiate analgesics, systemic corticosteroids, psychostimulants,
                  antiparkinsonian medications (except for non-parkinsonian indications) and mood
                  stabilizers (e.g., valproate, lithium), sedatives and anxiolytics with the
                  exception that use of short- to medium-acting benzodiazepines for treatment of
                  insomnia is permitted, however, use of sedatives or hypnotics should be avoided
                  for 8 hours before administration of cognitive tests.

              15. Any disorder that could interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism
                  or excretion of drugs (e.g. small bowel disease, Crohn's disease, celiac disease,
                  or liver disease.)

              16. Nootropic drugs except stable AD meds (acetylcholinesterase inhibitors and
                  memantine

              17. Suspected or known drug or alcohol abuse, i.e. more than approximately 60 g
                  alcohol (approximately 1 liter of beer or 0.5 liter of wine) per day indicated by
                  elevated MCV significantly above normal value at screening.

              18. Suspected or known allergy to any components of the study treatments.

              19. Enrollment in another investigational study or intake of investigational drug
                  within the previous 30 days or five half-lives of the investigational drug,
                  whichever is longer.

              20. Previous exposure to anti Aβ vaccines

              21. Exposure to passive immunotherapies for AD (e.g. monoclonal antibodies) or BACE
                  inhibitors within the previous 180 days.

              22. Contraindication to undergoing an LP including, but not limited to: inability to
                  tolerate an appropriately flexed position for the time necessary to perform an
                  LP; international normalized ratio (INR) &gt; 1.4 or other coagulopathy; platelet
                  count of &lt; 120,000/μL; infection at the desired lumbar puncture site; taking
                  anti-coagulant medication within 90 days of screening (Note: low dose aspirin is
                  permitted); degenerative arthritis of the lumbar spine; suspected
                  non-communicating hydrocephalus or intracranial mass; prior history of spinal
                  mass or trauma.

              23. Use of NSAIDs more than 2 days in within any 7-day period. Each incidence of use
                  must be recorded in the source and CRF.

              24. Any condition, which in the opinion of the investigator or the sponsor makes the
                  patient unsuitable for inclusion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher van Dyck, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hugh Bartlett</last_name>
    <phone>203-764-8100</phone>
    <email>hugh.bartlett@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carol Gunnoud</last_name>
    <email>carol.gunnoud@yale.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hugh Bartlet</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

