<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03493932</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>180077</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>18-N-0077</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03493932</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cytokine Microdialysis for Real-Time Immune Monitoring in Glioblastoma Patients Undergoing Checkpoint Blockade</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cytokine Microdialysis for Real-Time Immune Monitoring in Glioblastoma Patients Undergoing Checkpoint Blockade</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Glioblastoma (GBM) brain tumors almost always return after treatment. When that happens the
      tumor can never completely be removed by surgery, so most people also receive drugs.
      Researchers want to see if combining the drugs nivolumab and BMS-986016 may help.

      Objectives:

      To study how nivolumab affects the brain s immune system in people who have had glioblastoma
      brain tumors return. To study how nivolumab and BMS-986016 affect brain tumors.

      Eligibility:

      Adults age 22 and older who have had a return of GBM

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with:

      Medical history

      Physical exam

      Cheek swab

      Heart, blood and urine tests

      Chest x-ray

      Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain scan. Participants will lie on a table that slides in
      and out of a cylinder in a strong magnetic field. A contrast agent will be injected in an arm
      vein.

      Participants will stay in the hospital. They will:

      Have surgery. A tube will be inserted into the back. Brain tumor and bone marrow samples will
      be taken. Tubes will be inserted into the brain.

      Have a computed tomography brain scan.

      Stay in Intensive Care (ICU) 7 days. Fluid from the brain and back will be collected every
      few hours. In the ICU, participants will get nivolumab by IV for 30 minutes.

      Have surgery to remove the tubes.

      Have standard surgery to remove as much of the GBM as possible. Bone marrow will be removed.

      After leaving the hospital, participants will have visits every 2 weeks to get the study
      drugs by IV and have physical exams and blood tests.

      Participants will have a brain MRI once a month.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

      This protocol is being performed to 1) characterize the clinical and 2) immunological
      response of patients with recurrent glioblastoma to treatment with Nivolumab, together with
      an anti-Lag-3 antibody, BMS-986016, and to evaluate the safety of brain tumor microdialysis
      in this patient population.

      Study Population

      10 patients (total, after replacement for any dropout), 22 years old and older with first
      recurrence of glioblastoma after standard treatment of surgery, chemotherapy, and radiation.

      Study Design

      Patients will be screened by study neurosurgeons or neuro-oncologists to verify their
      confirmed or likely diagnosis of a recurrent glioblastoma. Patients will be offered standard
      of care therapy, including repeat surgery and/or recommendations for chemotherapeutic agents
      and other trials. If the patients are deemed to be surgical candidates for their potential
      recurrence, they will be enrolled in the trial. Enrolled patients will then undergo a
      stereotactic brain biopsy. If a frozen section confirms a diagnosis of recurrent
      glioblastoma, two microdialysis catheters will be placed in the brain after the biopsy, and a
      lumbar drain will also be placed. These microdialysis catheters will sample interstitial
      fluid in and around the brain tumor every 6 hours. We will concurrently collect blood and
      cerebral spinal fluid samples for comparison. After two days (Day 3), the patients will be
      given one dose of Nivolumab, 240mg IV. We will continue to collect samples every six hours
      for 5 additional days, after which patients will undergo surgical resection of their tumors
      and removal of the microdialysis catheters and lumbar drain. Nivolumab, at a dose of 240mg IV
      over 30 minutes every 2 weeks, will be administered after surgery (starting on Day 17, two
      weeks after the first dose on Day 3) followed by BMS 986016, an anti-Lag-3 antibody at a dose
      of 80mg IV over 60 minutes, until the study neuroradiologist notes tumor progression on MRI
      or the patient experiences treatment toxicity. While on therapy with Nivolumab and
      BMS-986016, patients will be seen and examined every 2 weeks +/- two days for signs of
      toxicity. Patients will be followed for at least three months after the surgical procedure.

      Outcome Measures

      The primary outcome measures are the proportion of patients who have a measurable increase of
      interferon gamma levels in the brain tumor tissue after their first dose of Nivolumab as
      compared to the pre-treatment baseline, the safety of using brain tumor microdialysis to
      monitor response to immune modulators in patients with recurrent glioblastoma and the safety
      of the combination of Nivolumab and BMS-986016. Secondary outcome measures include: 1) To
      determine the change in interferon gamma production within the tumor microenvironment and in
      the rest of the body from before and after therapy with the immune checkpoint inhibitor,
      nivolumab; 2) To evaluate the pathological response of the immune microenvironment of brain
      tumor tissue to the first dose of Nivolumab; 3) To evaluate the clinical response
      (progression free survival, overall survival) of recurrent glioblastoma patients to this
      treatment combination; 4) To describe the difference in survival between responders and
      non-responders on this treatment combination; 5) To examine the differences in the immune
      cells and secreted factors of the tumor environment as compared to the immune cells and
      secreted factors of the cerebral spinal fluid, blood and bone marrow in response to this
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome measure is the proportion of patients that have a rise in interferon gamma levels within the tumor microenvironment of 4 pg/ml or higher before the first dose of Nivolumab as compared to after the first dose, the safety of th...</measure>
    <time_frame>5 Days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1)change in IFNg in body 2)response of immune environment of brain tumor tissue to Nivolumab 3)To evaluate clinical response of pts 4)the difference in survival between responders and non-responders 5)differences in the immune cells and secreted...</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recurrent Glioblastoma patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>OPDIVO is a human programmed death receptor-1 (PD-1) blocking antibody indicated for the treatment of patients with unresectable or metastatic melanoma and disease progression following ipilimumab and, if BRAF V600 mutation positive, a BRAF inhibitor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BMS-986016</intervention_name>
    <description>Anti-Lymphocyte Activation Gene-3 antibody undergoing clinical evaluation by Bristol-Myers Squibb</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        To be eligible for entry into the study, a candidate must meet all the following criteria:

          1. Be 22 years of age or older.

          2. Have solitary recurrent glioblastoma that is amenable to surgical resection.

          3. Agree to undergo brain surgery.

          4. Are eligible for 03-N-0164 &quot;Evaluation and Treatment of Neurosurgical Disorders&quot;
             protocol 5. Willing and able to appoint a durable power of attorney.

        6. Are not on steroids, or are on a stable (without an increase for the preceding 2 weeks)
        or decreasing dose of steroids

        7. Are willing to use an effective method of contraception during the clinical study as
        defined on the consent and for 5 months (for women) or 7 months (for men) after the last
        dose of the study drug.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Candidates will be excluded if they:

          1. Have a bleeding disorder that cannot be corrected before invasive testing or surgery,
             or other medical conditions that would make surgery unsafe, such as lung or cardiac
             disease that would render them unable to tolerate the risk of general anesthesia, or
             severe immunodeficiency or systemic cancer not related to a brain lesion.

          2. Are pregnant or breastfeeding

          3. Cannot have an MRI scan.

          4. Are claustrophobic

          5. Are not able to lie on their back for up to 60 minutes

          6. Have an absolute lymphocyte count less than 500

          7. Have multiple brain tumors, evidence of carcinomatous meningitis, gliomatosis cerebri,
             or primary CNS lymphoma.

          8. Have an unrelated autoimmune disease

          9. Have a significant cardiac history, such as 2 or more MIs OR 2 or more coronary
             revascularization procedures.

         10. Have abnormal findings on ECG such as prolonged QT interval, T-wave abnormalities or
             arrhythmia. Abnormal findings on ECG will prompt an evaluation by a cardiologist prior
             to enrollment in the study

         11. Are currently undergoing treatment with another therapeutic agent for glioblastoma

         12. Have a history of having been treated with immune therapy

         13. Have an ejection fraction less than 50% on screening echocardiogram

         14. Have positive serology for HIV, HBV and HCV

         15. Have an active infection that requires systemic antibacterial, antiviral or antifungal
             therapy

             Less than 7 days prior to initiation of study drug therapy

         16. Have a history of transfer of autologous or allogeneic T cells

         17. Have cardiac Troponin T or I greater than 2 times the institutional upper limit of
             normal at screening

         18. At the time of enrollment, lack of consent capacity due to cognitive impairment that
             would make them incapable of understanding the explanation of the procedures in this
             study. Cognitive capacity to consent will be determined at the time of enrollment.
             Patients with mental disorders or those patients who are cognitively impaired yet
             still retain consent capacity will not be excluded.

         19. Cannot speak English or Spanish fluently
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edjah K Nduom, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gretchen C Scott, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-2921</phone>
    <email>SNBrecruiting@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2018-N-0077.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Checkpoint Inhibition</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

