<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03497221</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>63247916500005327</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03497221</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Education Intervention as a Patient Safety Strategy in the Care of Nasoenteric Tube</brief_title>
  <official_title>Simulation and Visual Identity as a Patient Safety Strategy in the Care of Nasoenteric Tube: Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The safety of the patient using a nasoenteral tube depends on the constant evaluation of the
      nursing team. The most implemented strategies for safe practice are education interventions,
      however, seem insufficient to change behavior. Active methodologies may be more promising
      alternatives for the development of these competencies. The objective is evaluate the effect
      of an isolated education intervention and combined with a visual identity campaign on the
      safe practice in the use of nursing care to the patient in use nasoenteral tubes. The
      clinical trial will be carried out in 2017, in a university hospital. Two profiles of
      participants will be included in the study: the first one refers to the nursing technicians
      of the hospital areas, part of them will receive a set of interventions, and the second one
      refers to the patients in use nasoenteral tube, considering that the effect of intervention
      will be measured by assessing compliance with care routines.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The safety of the patient undergoing enteral nutritional therapy depends on the constant
      evaluation of the nursing team, which, through specific skills, allows the establishment of
      nutritional care and prevents incidents related to the diet administration process. The
      challenge is to adopt safe practices that contemplate all these specificities, knowing that
      only knowledge is insufficient for the development of these competences, but also depends on
      the ability and commitment of these professionals.

      Training and capacity are predominant strategies in the health area to increase patient
      safety in the execution of nursing staff's care activities, however, this type of approach,
      when applied in isolation, is sometimes insufficient to change behavior end development of
      skills and attitudes among these professionals. Combined strategies such as alerts and
      reminders systems, educational visits, auditing systems, clinical simulations, feedbacks and
      workshops, on clinical practice safety are being deployed and evaluated as a more effective
      way of changing behavior.

      In this sense, the research question of the present project is: The implementation of a
      strategy of safety in service through an educational intervention associated to the visual
      identity campaign is able to increase the adhesion of the nursing technicians to the
      fulfillment of routines in the use of nasoenteral tube? The objective is evaluate the effect
      of an isolated education intervention and combined with a visual identity campaign on the
      safe practice in the use of nursing care to the patient in use nasoenteral tubes. The
      clinical trial will be carried out in 2017, in a university hospital. Two profiles of
      participants will be included in the study: the first one refers to the nursing technicians
      of the hospital areas, part of them will receive a set of interventions, and the second one
      refers to the patients in use nasoenteral tube, considering that the effect of intervention
      will be measured by assessing compliance with care routines.

      The study will be conducted according to the following steps, respectively: (1) Evaluation of
      the agreement between observers, (2) Pre-intervention evaluation (baseline), (3) Intervention
      (Educational Intervention and Visual Identity Campaign) and (4) Post-intervention evaluation.
      Both groups (IG and CG) will be submitted to the same research procedures in the evaluation
      stages (pre- and post-intervention); However, only the nursing technicians of the GI will be
      submitted to an intervention stage.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absence of conformity of nursing care in enteral nutritional therapy (ENT) with recommendations of good practices according to institutional protocols.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome have been measured by means of a Nasoenteric Tube (NT) care checklist observed at the patient's bedside. The checklist contains 25 items that evaluate: Conference of labels and validity of the diets and water bottles and devices used for administration at NT; observation of head of bed routines during enteral infusions, correct NT fixation, hygiene of devices and infusion pumps used ENT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence of adverse event related to obstruction NT</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome have been measured through the evaluation of the records of the professional health team (nurses, doctors, nutritionists and nursing technicians).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence of adverse event related to displacement NT non-programmed</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome have been measured through the evaluation of the records of the professional health team (nurses, doctors, nutritionists and nursing technicians).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence of adverse event related to withdrawal NT non-programmed</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome have been measured through the evaluation of the records of the professional health team (nurses, doctors, nutritionists and nursing technicians).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence of adverse event related to administration of enteral diet by probe not positioned in the gastrointestinal tract</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome have been measured through the evaluation of the records of the professional health team (nurses, doctors, nutritionists and nursing technicians).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence of adverse event related to non-administration of enteral diet (partial or full) when suspension was not planned</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome have been measured through the evaluation of the records of the professional health team (nurses, doctors, nutritionists and nursing technicians).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence of adverse event related to cases of diarrhea (three or more episodes of soft or liquid stools within 24 hours)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome have been measured through the evaluation of the records of the professional health team (nurses, doctors, nutritionists and nursing technicians).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence of adverse event related to cases of constipation (a disorder characterized by persistent difficulty of evacuation or a sensation of incomplete evacuation and / or infrequent bowel movements for at least 3 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome have been measured through the evaluation of the records of the professional health team (nurses, doctors, nutritionists and nursing technicians).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1084</enrollment>
  <condition>Patient Safety</condition>
  <condition>Enteral Nutrition</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The educational intervention is based on a hospital institutional protocol for patient using enteral tubes. A clinical simulation will be performed using a low fidelity manikin, where nursing technicians will identify and correct erros, such as: inconsistency between the patient's identification and the diet label, the administration of the diet with a low headboard, fixation of tube not detached and dirty, delay of the diet and others. The simulation will be described through a guide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Visual identity campaign</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The visual identity will be given by a set of actions, called &quot;campaign&quot;. The campaign consists in the creation and implantation of different materials to be used at the bedside of the patients in use of diet by SNE, such as: (a) poster summarizing care, (b) colored adhesive label to identify devices (c) badge with safety care reminders.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The same description of arm Education intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Visual identity campaign</intervention_name>
    <description>The same description of arm Visual identity campaign.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Visual identity campaign</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Nursing technicians: All nursing technicians of the intervention units will be
             potentially eligible for the study.

          -  Patients: with nasoenteral tube, adults (18 years of age or older) and who are
             hospitalized in the IG or CG units.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Workers who are not working during data collection. The nursing technicians who are
             part of the IG will be that could be reassigned to one of the units of the CG and vice
             versa.

          -  Patient: unaccompanied patients who are confused and / or disoriented.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mariur G Beghetto, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mariur G Beghetto, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+55 (51) 999550264</phone>
    <email>mariurbeghetto@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ana Paula A Corrêa, PhD student</last_name>
    <phone>+55 (51) 998441460</phone>
    <email>anacorrea.enf@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Clínicas de Porto Alegre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>Rio Grande Do Sul</state>
        <zip>90035007</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eva D Gonçalves</last_name>
      <phone>5133597640</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nursing Education</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

