<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03493425</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EA3163</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-01364</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EA3163</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EA3163</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA180820</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03493425</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chemotherapy Before Surgery and Radiation Therapy or Surgery and Radiation Therapy Alone in Treating Patients With Nasal and Paranasal Sinus Cancer That Can Be Removed by Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Randomized Trial of Neo-Adjuvant Chemotherapy Followed by Surgery and Post-Operative Radiation Versus Surgery and Post-Operative Radiation for Organ Preservation of T3 and T4a Nasal and Paranasal Sinus Squamous Cell Carcinoma (NPNSCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase II trial studies how well chemotherapy before surgery and radiation
      therapy works compared to surgery and radiation therapy alone in treating patients with nasal
      and paranasal sinus cancer that can be removed by surgery. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such
      as docetaxel, cisplatin, and carboplatin work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor
      cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by stopping them from
      spreading. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to kill tumor cells and shrink tumors.
      Giving chemotherapy before surgery and radiation therapy may make the tumor smaller and
      reduce the amount of normal tissue that needs to be removed and treated with radiation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Evaluate the structure preservation rate for patients with locally advanced resectable
      nasal and paranasal sinus squamous cell carcinoma (NPNSCC) with or without neoadjuvant
      therapy; all patients will undergo surgical resection and postoperative standard care.

      II. Evaluate overall survival (OS) for patients with locally advanced resectable NPNSCC with
      or without neoadjuvant therapy followed by surgical resection and postoperative standard
      care.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Evaluate progression-free survival (PFS) for this patient population. II. Examine the rate
      of structure preservation for the orbit (freedom from orbital exenteration).

      III. Evaluate site reported p16 data and correlate with outcome. IV. Determine the accuracy
      of baseline/post-chemotherapy magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and fludeoxyglucose F-18
      positron emission tomography/computed tomography (FDG PET/CT)-based prediction of orbit and
      skull base preservation.

      V. Determine the accuracy of baseline/post-chemotherapy MRI and/or FDG PET/CT-based
      prediction of 2-year overall survival.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the effects of tobacco, operationalized as combustible tobacco (1a), other
      forms of tobacco (1b), and environmental tobacco exposure (ETS) (1c) on provider-reported
      cancer-treatment toxicity (adverse events [both clinical and hematologic] and dose
      modifications).

      II. To determine the effects of tobacco on patient-reported physical symptoms and
      psychological symptoms.

      III. To examine quitting behaviors and behavioral counseling/support and cessation medication
      utilization.

      IV. To explore the effect of tobacco use and exposure on treatment duration, relative dose
      intensity, and therapeutic benefit.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

      ARM A: Patients undergo standard of care surgery. Beginning 4-6 weeks after surgery, patients
      undergo image guided intensity modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) once daily (QD) for 5
      fractions per week for 30 fractions. Patients with positive margins/positive extracapsular
      spread (ECS) in lymph nodes undergo image guided IMRT QD for 5 fractions per week for 30
      fractions and cisplatin intravenously (IV) over 1-2 hours or carboplatin IV over 30 minutes
      (for patients who are ineligible to receive cisplatin) weekly for 6 weeks in the absence of
      disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM B: Patients receive docetaxel IV over 1 hour and cisplatin IV over 1-2 hours on day 1.
      Patients who are ineligible to receive cisplatin receive carboplatin IV over 30 minutes on
      day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then undergo standard of care surgery no later
      than 6 weeks following the last dose of chemotherapy. Beginning 4-6 weeks after surgery,
      patients undergo image guided IMRT QD for 5 fractions per week for 30 fractions. Patients
      with positive margins/positive ECS in lymph nodes undergo image guided IMRT QD for 5
      fractions per week for 30 fractions and cisplatin IV over 1-2 hours or carboplatin IV over 30
      minutes (for patients who are ineligible to receive cisplatin) weekly for 6 weeks in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months if &lt; 2 years
      from study entry and then every 6 months if 2-5 years from study entry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 28, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2028</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Structure preservation rate defined as both skull base and orbit being preserved</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Fisher?s exact test will be used to compare the structure preservation rate between the two arms. The comparison between the two arms for structure preservation will be conducted separately (each at one-sided 0.05 significance level).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization, censoring follow-up at last date of contact, assessed for up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Log rank test will be used to compare OS between the two arms. The comparison between the two arms for OS will be conducted separately (each at one-sided 0.05 significance level).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">134</enrollment>
  <condition>Stage III Nasal Cavity and Paranasal Sinus Squamous Cell Carcinoma AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Nasal Cavity and Paranasal Sinus Squamous Cell Carcinoma AJCC v7</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (surgery, IMRT, cisplatin, carboplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo standard of care surgery. Beginning 4-6 weeks after surgery, patients undergo image guided IMRT QD for 5 fractions per week for 30 fractions. Patients with positive margins/positive ECS in lymph nodes undergo image guided IMRT QD for 5 fractions per week for 30 fractions and cisplatin IV over 1-2 hours or carboplatin IV over 30 minutes (for patients who are ineligible to receive cisplatin) weekly for 6 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive docetaxel IV over 1 hour and cisplatin IV over 1-2 hours on day 1. Patients who are ineligible to receive cisplatin receive carboplatin IV over 30 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients then undergo standard of care surgery no later than 6 weeks following the last dose of chemotherapy. Beginning 4-6 weeks after surgery, patients undergo image guided IMRT QD for 5 fractions per week for 30 fractions. Patients with positive margins/positive ECS in lymph nodes undergo image guided IMRT QD for 5 fractions per week for 30 fractions and cisplatin IV or carboplatin IV weekly for 6 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (surgery, IMRT, cisplatin, carboplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blastocarb</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatin Hexal</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosol</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbotec</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
    <other_name>Displata</other_name>
    <other_name>Ercar</other_name>
    <other_name>JM-8</other_name>
    <other_name>Nealorin</other_name>
    <other_name>Novoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinwas</other_name>
    <other_name>Ribocarbo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (surgery, IMRT, cisplatin, carboplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abiplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Blastolem</other_name>
    <other_name>Briplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diammine-dichloroplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloridoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloro Platinum (II)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-diamminedichloroplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-dichloroammine Platinum (II)</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinous Diamine Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum II</other_name>
    <other_name>Cis-platinum II Diamine Dichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cismaplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatina</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cisplatyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Citoplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Citosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cysplatyna</other_name>
    <other_name>DDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Lederplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Metaplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Neoplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Peyrone's Chloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Peyrone's Salt</other_name>
    <other_name>Placis</other_name>
    <other_name>Plastistil</other_name>
    <other_name>Platamine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiblastin-S</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinex</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol- AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol-AQ VHA Plus</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinum Diamminodichloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Platiran</other_name>
    <other_name>Platistin</other_name>
    <other_name>Platosin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Docecad</other_name>
    <other_name>RP56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere Injection Concentrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Image Guided Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo image guided IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (surgery, IMRT, cisplatin, carboplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IGRT</other_name>
    <other_name>image-guided radiation therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensity-Modulated Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo image guided IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (surgery, IMRT, cisplatin, carboplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
    <other_name>Intensity Modulated RT</other_name>
    <other_name>Intensity-Modulated Radiotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (surgery, IMRT, cisplatin, carboplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (surgery, IMRT, cisplatin, carboplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapeutic Conventional Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo standard of care surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (surgery, IMRT, cisplatin, carboplatin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (docetaxel, cisplatin, carboplatin, surgery, IMRT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  General physical condition compatible with the proposed chemotherapy and surgery

          -  Stage T3 or T4a, histologically-confirmed NPNSCC requiring orbital or skull base
             resection:

               -  Stages T3 and T4a disease will be included regardless of nodal status (N0 or
                  N1-3), provided that surgical therapy would require orbital or skull base
                  resection

               -  The surgical oncologist in each institution will determine the need for resection
                  of the orbit OR base of skull at baseline for patients on both Arms A and B and
                  following neo-adjuvant chemotherapy for patients on Arm B

                    -  Resection of skull base will be deemed necessary according to skull base
                       bone erosion by CT or marrow involvement by MRI is noted; for any disease
                       abutting the skull base; or for ethmoid sinus or frontal sinus involvement

                    -  Resection of orbital contents will be deemed necessary according to skull
                       base society guidelines, based on involvement of periorbital fat documented
                       by MRI imaging

          -  Patients must be deemed surgically resectable by the surgical teams at each
             institution and must have a determination of degree of anticipated structure
             preservation of orbit and skull base; this needs to be determined prior to
             randomization

          -  Patients may not be receiving investigational agents at time of registration, or at
             any time while on study and during the 4 weeks preceding enrollment

          -  Patients with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to docetaxel and/or both platinum-based chemotherapy
             agents are excluded; patient must be able to receive at least one of the two proposed
             chemotherapy regimens

          -  Patients with evidence of distant metastases or leptomeningeal disease (LMD) are
             excluded

          -  Patients must not have received previous irradiation for head and neck tumor, skull
             base, or brain tumors

          -  Patients with uncontrolled inter-current illnesses which in the opinion of the
             investigator will interfere with the ability to undergo therapy including chemotherapy
             are excluded

          -  Patients with a history of a different malignancy are excluded, unless the disease has
             not progressed for &gt;= 2 years

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 1500/mm^3 =&lt; 2 weeks prior to randomization

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &gt; 8.0 g/dL =&lt; 2 weeks prior to randomization

          -  Platelet count &gt; 100,000/mm^3 =&lt; 2 weeks prior to randomization

          -  Creatinine clearance of &gt; 60 ml/min; creatinine clearance may be measured or
             calculated; if calculating, creatinine clearance, use the Cockroft-Gault formula =&lt; 2
             weeks prior to randomization

          -  Total bilirubin within normal limits (must be obtained =&lt; 2 weeks prior to
             randomization)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) must be within the
             range allowing for eligibility, must be obtained &lt; 2 weeks prior to randomization

          -  Alkaline phosphatase must be within the range allowing for eligibility, must be
             obtained &lt; 2 weeks prior to randomization

          -  Patients with a prior history of squamous cell or basal carcinoma of the skin or in
             situ cervical cancer must have been curatively treated

          -  No current peripheral neuropathy &gt; grade 2 at time of randomization

          -  Patients must not have any co-existing condition that would preclude full compliance
             with the study; no prior history of severe hypersensitivity reaction to docetaxel or
             other drugs formulated with polysorbate 80

          -  Women must not be pregnant or breast-feeding

               -  All females of childbearing potential must have a blood test or urine study
                  within 2 weeks prior to registration to rule out pregnancy

               -  A female of childbearing potential is any woman, regardless of sexual orientation
                  or whether they have undergone tubal ligation, who meets the following criteria:
                  1) has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or 2) has not been
                  naturally postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e., has had menses
                  at any time in the preceding 24 consecutive months)

          -  Women of childbearing potential and sexually active males must be strongly advised to
             use an accepted and effective method of contraception or to abstain from sexual
             intercourse for the duration of their participation in the study

          -  Patients must have measurable disease; MRI and/or PET/CT scans need to be performed
             within 2 weeks prior to registration
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nabil Saba</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nabil F. Saba</last_name>
      <phone>404-778-1868</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nabil F. Saba</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

