<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01281943</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201104170</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01281943</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin and Temsirolimus in Patients With Advanced Hepatocellular Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (Doxil®) and Temsirolimus (Torisel®) in Patients With Advanced Hepatocellular Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase II study will use the MTD from a previous Phase I study at the recommended dose
      for the combination regimen from the Phase I trial, Doxil 25mg/m2 IV Q 4 weeks and
      temsirolimus 25mg IV Q week.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This proposal aims to capitalize on the consensus recommendations of the NCI panel, the known
      antitumor activity of doxorubicin in HCC, and the as yet unpublished results of a recently
      completed Phase I clinical trial (WU HRPO# 07-0447, NCT00703170) combining pegylated
      liposomal doxorubicin (Doxil®) and temsirolimus (Torisel®) in patients with advanced solid
      tumors. In this Phase I study, twenty-two patients were enrolled and treated. The MTD and
      recommended Phase II dose for the combination regimen from this trial is is Doxil 25mg/m2 IV
      Q 4 weeks and temsirolimus 25mg IV Q week. During the conduct of this study two patients
      experienced confirmed partial responses (PR). One patient had heavily pretreated metastatic
      breast cancer and remained on the study for 6 months. The second patient with a PR had HCC
      that was previously treated with sorafenib. She remained on the study regimen for 14 months
      and tolerated this treatment well. Based on the tolerability of the drug combination and the
      observed anti-tumor activity in HCC, the current Phase II study in HCC is proposed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Doxil Shortage
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether the progression free survival (PFS) rate in patients with advanced HCC using this combination regimen of pegylated liposomal doxorubicin and temsirolimus exceeds 5 months in the majority of treated patients, justifying the further development of this therapeutic regimen in this patient population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity and tolerability for this combination regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To further characterize the toxicity profile and tolerability for this combination regimen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate, objective response rate, and overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the disease control rate (DCR), objective response rate (ORR), and overall survival (OS) of this combination regimen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mTOR inhibition</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether S6 kinase is inhibited in peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) as an indication of adequate mTOR inhibitor exposure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacogenomics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>To measure Poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase-1 (PARP-1) activity in PBMCs from the patients as an indication of adequate doxorubicin exposure54.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Polymoprhism assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>To assess whether common polymorphisms in ABCB1 and CYP2B6 are associated with any changes in treatment response or survival55.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Temsirolimus and Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Temsirolimus 25mg andPegylated liposomal doxorubicin 25mg/m2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Temsirolimus 25mg and Pegylated liposomal doxorubicin 25mg/m2</intervention_name>
    <description>Temsirolimus 25mg IV on days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of each 28 day cycle
Pegylated liposomal doxorubicin 25mg/m2 IV on day 1 of each 28 day cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Temsirolimus and Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(Torisel®)</other_name>
    <other_name>(Doxil®)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologic Diagnosis: Patients must have a histologically or cytologically proven
             hepatocellular cancer (HCC) that is not amenable to treatment via resection or liver
             transplantation. In the absence of a tissue diagnosis, nodules on CT with a
             characteristic appearance of HCC plus Alpha Fetoprotein (AFP) &gt; 400ng/ml will be
             considered diagnostic of HCC.

          -  Measurable Disease: Patients must have measurable disease.

        Measurable lesions are defined as those that can be accurately measured in at least one
        dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as ≥20 mm with conventional techniques (PET,
        CT, MRI, x-ray) or as ≥10 mm with spiral CT scan. All tumor measurements must be recorded
        in millimeters (or decimal fractions of centimeters).

        A positive bone scan, osteoblastic metastases, and pleural or peritoneal effusions are not
        considered measurable. Patients with only these lesions are not eligible for entry to the
        study.

          -  Prior Therapy: Patients may or may not have received prior systemic therapy in the
             metastatic setting. No prior treatment with an mTOR inhibitor or with doxorubicin is
             permitted. Participants must have recovered from the acute toxic effects of all prior
             chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or radiotherapy prior to entering this study. No
             chemotherapy or radiotherapy may be given within 4 weeks prior to the start of
             protocol treatment.

          -  Age: Patients must be ≥18 years old. Because no dosing or toxicity data are currently
             available on the use of temsirolimus in combination with pegylated liposomal
             doxorubicin in patients &lt;18 years of age, children are excluded from this study.

          -  Performance Status: ECOG 0-2 at study entry.

          -  Life Expectancy: Patients must have a life expectancy of greater than 12 weeks.

        Required Laboratory Values:

          -  absolute neutrophil count ≥1,500/mm3

          -  platelets ≥100,000/mm3

          -  hemoglobin ≥9.0 g/dL

          -  total bilirubin ≤1.5 x ULN

          -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) ≤1.5 x ULN (≤2.5 x ULN for patients with liver metastases)

          -  alkaline phosphatase ≤2.5 x ULN

          -  creatinine ≤1.5 x ULN OR

          -  creatinine clearance ≥60 mL/min/1.732 for patients with creatinine levels above 2.0
             mg/dl

          -  serum cholesterol ≤350 mg/dL /9.0 mmol/L (fasting)

          -  triglycerides ≤400 mg/dL (fasting)*

          -  albumin ≥3.0 mg/dL

               -  Patients with triglyceride levels &gt;400 mg/dL can be started on lipid lowering
                  agents and reevaluated within 1 week. If levels go to ≤400 mg/dL, they can be
                  considered for the trial and continue the lipid lowering agents.

               -  Child-Pugh (CP) A or B liver dysfunction are eligible unless the bilirubin is
                  &gt;1.5 x ULN. If non-contraindicated, hepatic impairment (bilirubin &gt;1-1.5 x ULN or
                  AST &gt;ULN but bilirubin ≤ULN) is present patients can be treated at a lower dose
                  (15 mg/week) of temsirolimus.

          -  Concomitant Medications: Temsirolimus is primarily metabolized by CYP3A4. Patients
             cannot be receiving enzyme-inducing antiepileptic drugs (EIAEDs; e.g., phenytoin,
             carbamazepine, phenobarbital) nor any other CYP3A4 inducer such as rifampin or St.
             John's wort, as these may decrease temsirolimus levels. A partial list of agents which
             interact with cytochrome P450 (CYP3A) is found in Appendix B. Use of agents that
             potently inhibit CYP3A (and hence may raise temsirolimus levels), such as
             ketoconazole, is discouraged, but not specifically prohibited. Temsirolimus can
             inhibit CYP2D6, and may decrease metabolism (and increase drug levels) of drugs that
             are substrates for CYP2D6, such as codeine. The appropriateness of use of such agents
             is left to physician discretion. A list of drugs that may have potential interactions
             with CYP2D6 is found in Appendix A. If there is any doubt about eligibility based on
             concomitant medication, the Principal Investigator should be contacted. All
             concomitant medications must be recorded.

          -  Known Allergies: Patients with known hypersensitivity reactions to macrolide
             antibiotics (such as erythromycin, clarithromycin, and azithromycin) are not eligible
             for this trial.

          -  Cardiac Function: Patients must have a normal left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF
             ≥50%) by MUGA scan.

          -  Sexually Active Patients: For all sexually active patients, the use of adequate
             contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control) will be required prior to
             study entry and for the duration of study participation. Non-pregnant status will be
             determined in all women of childbearing potential. Pregnant and nursing women are not
             eligible.

          -  HIV-Positive Patients: Patients receiving anti-retroviral therapy (HAART) for HIV
             infection are excluded from the study because of possible pharmacokinetic
             interactions. Appropriate studies will be undertaken in patients receiving HAART
             therapy, when indicated.

          -  Neurologic Status: Patients must not have active CNS disease.

          -  Recovery from Intercurrent Illness: Patients must have recovered from uncontrolled
             intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active infection,
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris or cardiac arrhythmia.

          -  Informed Consent: Patients must have signed a Washington University Human Research
             Protection Office (HRPO) approved informed consent. The patient should not have any
             serious medical or psychiatric illness that would prevent either the giving of
             informed consent or the receipt of treatment.

          -  Inclusion of Women and Minorities: Entry to this study is open to both men and women
             and to all racial and ethnic subgroups.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>A. Craig Lockhart, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 2, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 2, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

