<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01283009</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>574</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01283009</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Extended Steroid in CAP(e)</brief_title>
  <acronym>ESCAPe</acronym>
  <official_title>CSP #574 - Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Methylprednisolone in Hospitalized Veterans With Severe Community-Acquired Pneumonia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the study is to determine whether providing early treatment with a glucocorticoid
      drug, called methylprednisolone, will improve survival in critically ill patients with severe
      community-acquired pneumonia (CAP). Pneumonia develops when bacteria and other agents invade
      the lungs. The body's immune system creates a response to produce inflammation to kill the
      bacteria. A moderate amount of inflammation is beneficial. But, in patients sick enough to be
      admitted to the ICU, inflammation is frequently out of control. When the body cannot regulate
      inflammation vital organs (brain, heart, lung, kidney, liver) may be damaged, contributing to
      death or residual organ damage for those who survive. Glucocorticoids help reduce
      inflammation. Recent studies have shown that when the body is unable to produce sufficient
      amounts of glucocorticoids, inflammation can get out of control. Under these circumstances,
      glucocorticoids given in small doses may help aid the body's ability to reduce inflammation
      and improve recovery. In a small preliminary trial, glucocorticoid treatment, in addition to
      standard antibiotic treatment, sped up recovery from pneumonia. It also decreased the length
      of hospital stay, and increased survival. This Cooperative Studies Program study will be the
      first large-scale, prospective, randomized clinical trial evaluating whether or not this
      treatment improves recovery.

      In this study, at each site, patients with severe CAP will be assigned to one of two
      treatment groups. One group will receive methylprednisolone and the other will receive a
      placebo (an inert substance that will look like the drug). The investigators have chosen a
      total duration of treatment of 20 days (7 days full dose followed by slow reduction over 13
      days) to prevent relapse of inflammation and allow the body to recover its own ability to
      produce glucocorticoid. All patients will also receive standardized management of CAP in
      accordance with current practice guidelines. The study will take into consideration when
      assigning the treatment each participating site, and whether or not the patient requires
      mechanical ventilation at the time of assignment. Patients will be followed clinically for
      180 days. The primary outcome is all cause 60-day mortality. Secondary outcomes are (1)
      in-hospital morbidity-mortality, including ventilator-free days, multiorgan dysfunction
      syndrome (MODS)-free days, duration of ICU and hospital stay, and hospital discharge; and (2)
      posthospital discharge morbidity-mortality, including cardiovascular complications,
      functional and general health status in the first 180 days, rehospitalization, and mortality
      at 1 year. Serial blood samples will also be collected and stored for future translational
      research relating longitudinal inflammation markers to clinical outcomes.

      This study will advance knowledge on the relationship between inflammation and long-term
      outcome in severe CAP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      VA Cooperative Study #574 is designed to prospectively evaluate the efficacy of prolonged
      glucocorticoid (methylprednisolone) treatment on short- (in hospital) and long-term (after
      hospital discharge), morbidity and mortality in Veteran patients admitted to the ICU
      (including intermediate care unit) with severe community-acquired pneumonia (CAP).

      CAP is the sixth most common cause of death (acute mortality) in the United States and the
      leading cause of community-acquired infection requiring intensive care unit (ICU) admission.
      Despite significant advancements in medical care, there has been little change in crude
      mortality from respiratory tract infection for more than 5 decades (1950-2000). In the United
      States alone, over 1.3 million people were admitted to the hospital in 2002 with severe CAP
      (262 per 10,000 population) with an estimated inpatient cost of approximately $4.4 billion.
      In addition, severe CAP patients surviving hospitalization experience a significant increase
      in long-term morbidity (cardiovascular complications, impaired functional status, and
      recurrent hospitalizations) and a sizable mortality up to 1 year (up to 25%) that is
      independent of patient's chronic health condition.

      Dysregulated systemic inflammation, characterized by persistent elevation in circulating
      inflammatory cytokine levels over time, is the central pathogenetic process contributing to
      short- and long-term morbidity and mortality in patients with severe CAP. Even when patients
      survive ICU and hospital admission, elevation in inflammatory cytokine lasts for greater than
      3 weeks, and interleukin (IL)-6 levels at hospital discharge predict subsequent mortality.
      Endogenous and exogenous glucocorticoids are the most important physiologic inhibitors of
      inflammation. In a meta-analysis of four, small, published studies that included a total of
      198 patients with severe CAP, prolonged glucocorticoid treatment was associated with a
      significant reduction in short-term mortality (RR = 0.40, 95%CI 0.18-0.89; p = 0.03; I2 12%).
      This Cooperative Studies Program study will be the first large-scale, prospective, randomized
      clinical trial evaluating the efficacy of prolonged methylprednisolone in the treatment of
      severe CAP.

      In this study, at each site, patients with severe CAP will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to
      receive methylprednisolone or placebo in a double-blind fashion. The investigators have
      chosen a total duration of treatment of 20 days (7 days full dose followed by slow reduction
      over 13 days) to forestall relapse of systemic inflammation and allow recovery of the
      suppressed hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis. All patients will also receive
      standardized management of CAP in accordance with current practice guidelines. Randomization
      will be stratified separately within each participating site by whether or not the patient
      requires mechanical ventilation at the time of randomization. Patients will be followed
      clinically for 180 days. The primary outcome is all cause 60-day mortality. Secondary
      outcomes are (1) in-hospital morbidity-mortality, including ventilator-free days, multiorgan
      dysfunction syndrome (MODS)-free days, duration of ICU and hospital stay, and hospital
      discharge; and (2) posthospital discharge morbidity-mortality, including cardiovascular
      complications, functional and general health status in the first 180 days, rehospitalization,
      and mortality at 1 year. Serial blood samples will also be collected and stored for future
      translational research relating longitudinal inflammation markers to clinical outcomes.

      Based on published studies and VA Decision Support System, the investigators estimate the all
      cause 60-day mortality in severe CAP patients admitted to ICU is 28%. The investigators
      hypothesize that prolonged methylprednisolone treatment will reduce the 60-day mortality from
      28% to 21% (a 25% relative reduction). A total of 1406 patients (703 per group) will be
      required to give 85% power to detect this hypothesized improvement, using a two-sided 5%
      significance level test. Adjusting for 1% attrition, the target sample size is 1420. Assuming
      5 years of accrual and an intake rate of 8 patients per year per VAMC, the investigators will
      need 36 participating VAMCs.

      Treatment of severe CAP is of particular importance to the VA health care system because of
      the large patient population and because a single episode of severe CAP is associated with
      significant short- and long-term morbidity and mortality. In fiscal year 2006, 17,890
      patients were admitted to the VA hospital system with a diagnosis of CAP. Of these, 3727
      (21%) required ICU admission during their hospital stay. For ICU-admitted patients, mortality
      rates in the hospital at 60, 90, 180, and 365 days were 26%, 34%, 37%, 44%, and 51%,
      respectively. They had on average a hospital stay of 17.7 days with hospital costs of
      $49,936, and 48% of them were readmitted within 12 months of hospital discharge. This study
      will investigate the effects of an off-patent, inexpensive treatment that, based on strong
      experimental and translational evidence and the encouraging findings of preliminary trials,
      has the potential of significantly decreasing mortality and morbidity. Equally important,
      this study will advance knowledge on the relationship between inflammation and long-term
      outcome in severe CAP. Given that methylprednisolone is off-patent, there is little incentive
      for the pharmaceutical industry to fund this study. The VA system with its Cooperative
      Studies Program is uniquely suited to conduct the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 9, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>60-day</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is all-cause mortality at 60 days, defined by whether the patient has died by the end of study day 60.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">586</enrollment>
  <condition>Community Acquired Respiratory Disease Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Methylprednisolone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Methylprednisolone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Inactive substance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Inactive substance</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylprednisolone</intervention_name>
    <description>Methylprednisolone will be given in a double-blind fashion for 20 full days. The treatment course includes a bolus dose on the day of randomization, 7 days of full dose (40 mg/day), 7 days of half dose (20 mg/day), and 6 days of tapering doses (12 mg/day and 4 mg/day).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Methylprednisolone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Inactive substance</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Medrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient's origin. Patients are classified as having CAP if they are admitted directly
             from outside the hospital, including private residence, nursing home, rehabilitation
             center, other long-term care facility (health care-associated pneumonia-HCAP).

          -  Clinical diagnosis of CAP.

          -  Have radiographically confirmed pneumonia (new or progressive pulmonary infiltrate(s)
             on chest radiograph or chest computed tomography scan consistent with bacterial
             pneumonia) AND have acute illness ( &lt;=7 days' duration) with at least three of the
             following clinical signs or symptoms consistent with a lower respiratory tract
             infection:

        New or increased cough Purulent sputum or change in sputum character Auscultatory findings
        consistent with pneumonia (e.g., rales, egophony, findings of consolidation) Dyspnea,
        tachypnea, or hypoxemia (O2 saturation &lt;90% on room air or PaO2 &lt;60 mmHg) Fever &gt;= 38 C
        oral (&gt;=38.5 C rectally or tympanically) or hypothermia (&lt;=36 C) White blood cell count
        greater than 10,000 cells/mm3 or less than 4,000 cells/mm3 Greater than 15% immature
        neutrophils (bands) irrespective of WBC count

          -  Diagnosis of severe CAP. Pneumonia of sufficient severity to require admission to the
             ICU (including intermediate care unit) and meeting &gt;=1 major or &gt;= 3 minor modified
             Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA)/American

        Thoracic Society (ATS) criteria.:

          -  1 Major Criteria

               1. Use of invasive or noninvasive mechanical ventilation

               2. Vasopressors for shock despite adequate fluid resuscitation

               3. Arterial pH &lt; 7.30 -OR &gt;=3 Minor Criteria

               1. New onset of confusion or disorientation

               2. Hypothermia (core temperature &lt;=36 C)

               3. Respiratory rate &gt;=30 breaths/min

               4. Hypotension requiring aggressive fluid resuscitation

               5. Uremia (BUN &gt;=20 mg/dL)

               6. PaO2: FiO2 ratio &lt;=250 or SaO2:FiO2 ratio &lt;=250

               7. Leukopenia (WBC count &lt; 4000 cells/mm3)

               8. Platelet count &lt; 100,000 cells/mm3 or &gt; 400,000 cells/mm3

               9. Multilobar infiltrates

                  Exclusion Criteria:

                  - Patient's age 17 years or younger.

                  - Vasopressor-dependent shock requiring moderate-to-high dose vasopressor (i.e.,
                  norepinephrine &gt;=0.3 mcg/Kg/min) treatment for greater than 2 hours in patient
                  that is adequately fluid-resuscitated (at least 4 liters of crystalloids) WITH
                  central venous pressure (CVP) equal to or greater than 8 mm Hg for nonventilated
                  patients and equal to or greater than 12 mm Hg for ventilated patients. (See
                  explanation below)*

                  - Major gastrointestinal bleeding requiring transfusion of 5 units or more of
                  packed red blood cells within 3 months of current hospitalization.

                  - Any condition requiring 20 mg of prednisone equivalent/day for greater than 14
                  days, over the last 3 months.

                  - COPD with acute exacerbation requiring glucocorticoid treatment at hospital
                  admission. Patients with short-term glucocorticoid use (e.g., methylprednisolone
                  up to 300 mg within 5 days of randomization) will not be excluded.

                  - Patients enrolled in another experimental (interventional) protocol.

                  - Pregnancy, confirmed by urine or serum test.

                  - Presence of postobstructive pneumonia or cystic fibrosis.

                  - Clinical history consistent with aspiration of gastric content (i.e., loss of
                  consciousness or seizure).

                  - Active tuberculosis or fungal infection.

                  - Moribund patient (i.e., not expected to live more than 24 h) or with recent
                  (within 7 days) cardiopulmonary arrest, or with (known or suspected) irreversible
                  cessation of all brain function, or comfort measure status.

                  - Presence of preexisting medical condition that is irreversible and expected to
                  be fatal within 3 months.

                    -  Patients with severe immunosuppression (i.e., HIV with CD4 &lt;200),
                       neutropenia (less than 1000 neutrophils) not related to pneumonia, acute
                       burn injury, or receiving immunosuppressive or cytotoxic therapy for any
                       reason.

                    -  Chronic severe cognitive impairment caused by dementia or central nervous
                       system pathologies (tumor, cerebro-vascular accident, infections, or head
                       injuries) as defined by the site investigator by obtaining medical history
                       and reviewing medical record.

                    -  The physician doesn't feel the patient is a viable candidate for the study
                       (e.g., presence of hypersensitivity or previous severe adverse reaction to
                       cosyntropin or any glucocorticoid, history of adrenal insufficiency or
                       chronic systemic steroid use placing the patient at risk for relative
                       adrenal insufficiency).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gianfranco Umberto Meduri, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Memphis VA Medical Center, Memphis, TN</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Phoenix VA Health Care System Carl T. Hayden VA Medical Center, Phoenix, AZ</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85012</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Loma Linda Healthcare System, Loma Linda, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loma Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92357</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Long Beach Healthcare System, Long Beach, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Long Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90822</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Palo Alto Health Care System, Palo Alto, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304-1290</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA San Diego Healthcare System, San Diego, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92161</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Greater Los Angeles Healthcare System, West Los Angeles, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bay Pines VA Healthcare System, Pay Pines, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bay Pines</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33744</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Florida/South Georgia Veterans Health System, Gainesville, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32608</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami VA Healthcare System, Miami, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33125</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta VA Medical and Rehab Center, Decatur</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richard L. Roudebush VA Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202-2884</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Robley Rex VA Medical Center, Louisville, KY</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis VA Health Care System, Minneapolis, MN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Omaha VA Nebraska-Western Iowa Health Care System, Omaha, NE</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68105-1873</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Sierra Nevada Health Care System, Reno, NV</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reno</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Western New York Healthcare System, Buffalo, NY</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Syracuse VA Medical Center, Syracuse, NY</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asheville VA Medical Center, Asheville, NC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Asheville</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28805</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati VA Medical Center, Cincinnati, OH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45220</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Louis Stokes VA Medical Center, Cleveland, OH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oklahoma City VA Medical Center, Oklahoma City, OK</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System University Drive Division, Pittsburgh, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wm. Jennings Bryan Dorn VA Medical Center, Columbia SC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memphis VA Medical Center, Memphis, TN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michael E. DeBakey VA Medical Center, Houston, TX</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Texas Health Care System, San Antonio, TX</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Salt Lake City Health Care System, Salt Lake City, UT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84148</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Salem VA Medical Center, Salem, VA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salem</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>24153</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clement J. Zablocki VA Medical Center, Milwaukee, WI</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53295-1000</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Caribbean Healthcare System, San Juan, PR</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Juan</city>
        <zip>00921</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Puerto Rico</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 25, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pneumoniae</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiration Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

