<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01286142</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NV25182</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01286142</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oseltamivir Infant Influenza Safety Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Observational Safety Study in Children &lt;= 24 Months of Age Receiving Oseltamivir for the Treatment or Prophylaxis of Influenza Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hoffmann-La Roche</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In June 2009, the World Health Organization (WHO) declared a global pandemic of influenza A
      (H1N1). Although little is known about the pandemic influenza strain in children, during
      previous pandemics and influenza seasons children less than one year of age were shown to be
      at higher risk of influenza complications than older children. In light of the 2009 H1N1
      pandemic situation, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA), European Medicines Agency
      (EMA), and Health Canada issued emergency authorizations for oseltamivir to be used to treat
      and prevent influenza in infants under 1 year of age. It is anticipated that oseltamivir use
      in infants will dramatically increase due to the new authorizations for use in this
      population and high prevalence of H1N1 influenza circulating in the population. Ongoing
      safety surveillance is critical and this study will provide further data for evaluating the
      risk/benefit ratio of prescribing oseltamivir to this population in the current milieu of
      both seasonal and pandemic influenza viruses circulating in the population. The study will
      also provide useful information on the dose and duration of treatment used in clinical
      practice and their relationship to adverse events.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, observational, multicenter short-term safety study of the use of
      oseltamivir (prophylaxis or treatment) in children 24 months of age or younger. An internal
      comparator group of children diagnosed with influenza and not treated with antiviral
      medications will be enrolled. The study includes a 30-day follow-up period and will be
      conducted in multiple sites in multiple countries within the European Union. The study will
      cover two consecutive influenza seasons: 01 October 2009 - 31 May 2010 and 01 October 2010 -
      31 May 2011. Data collection may be interrupted in the interim period between influenza
      seasons (June 1, 2010 - September 30, 2010), depending on whether the influenza season
      follows the expected cycle.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 7 post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Information on the number of subjects with AEs will be collected at 7 days post-baseline. AEs include influenza symptoms and associated complications solicited from parent/legal guardian; secondary complications of influenza reported by physician, including otitis media and bacterial infections; and any other non-serious and serious AEs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day 30 post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Information on the number of subjects with AEs will be collected at 30 days post-baseline. AEs include influenza symptoms and associated complications solicited from parent/legal guardian; secondary complications of influenza reported by physician, including otitis media and bacterial infections; and any other non-serious and serious AEs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects treated with oseltamivir</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30 post baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Data on dosage and duration of treatment with oseltamivir in real-world practice are collected. The aim is to examine the relationship of adverse events to the regimen of oseltamivir.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with drug-resistant virus</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30 post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Data on oseltamivir resistance are collected (as reported only)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">900</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza, Human</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Influenza treatment with oseltamivir</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients 24 months of age and younger initially presenting with confirmed or presumed influenza A or B infection treated with oseltamivir.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Influenza prophylaxis with oseltamivir</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients 24 months of age and younger prescribed oseltamivir for influenza prophylaxis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Influenza patients with no antiviral treatment</arm_group_label>
    <description>A comparator group of patients 24 months of age and younger presenting with confirmed or presumed influenza A or B and not treated with any influenza antiviral.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will be conducted in multiple sites in multiple countries within the European
        Union. Initially, five countries (United Kingdom, Austria, Finland, Poland, Germany) are
        selected for inclusion, but additional countries in Europe, are likely to be added. It is
        estimated that 3-12 sites per country will be enrolled, with a target of at least 900
        patients. If additional countries are added, the number of sites/patients recruited per
        country will be adjusted accordingly.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  24 months of age or younger at time of enrollment

          -  Diagnosis of influenza A or B (suspected* or confirmed by viral testing) either
             treated with oseltamivir or with no antivirals OR prescribed oseltamivir for
             post-exposure influenza prophylaxis

          -  Parent/legal guardian willing to provide informed consent and be contacted by
             telephone as part of follow-up

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded if treated with an influenza antiviral other than
             oseltamivir, including amantadine, rimantadine, or zanamivir.

               -  Suspected influenza is defined as an acute febrile illness characterized by the
                  presence of fever and 1 or more of the following symptoms: cough, coryza/nasal
                  congestion or sore throat.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Barbara Rath, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Charite University Berlin, Department of Pediatrics (Div. of Pneumonology and Immunology)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charite University Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Interim Guidance for Clinicians on the Prevention and Treatment of Novel Influenza A (H1N1) Influenza Virus Infection in Infants and Children. 13 May 2009. Available at http://cdc.gov/h1n1flu/childrentreatment.htm. Accessed 03 Aug 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>European Medicines Agency (EMA), Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use. CHMP ASSESSMENT REPORT on Novel Influenza (H1N1) outbreak Tamiflu (oseltamivir) Relenza (zanamivir) [EMEA/CHMP/287662/2009]. 07 May 2009. Available at http://www.emea.europa.eu/humandocs/PDFs/EPAR/tamiflu/28766209en.pdf. Accessed 28 July 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Food and Drug Administration (FDA). Emergency Use Authorization Letter - Tamiflu. 14 July 2009. Available at http://www.cdc.gov/h1n1flu/eua/pdf/fda_letter_tamiflu.pdf. Accessed 03 Aug 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. 11 Jun 2009. Available at: http://www.who.int/mediacentre/news/statements/2009/h1n1_pandemic_phase6_20090611/en/index.html. Accessed 03 Aug 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Neurologic complications associated with novel influenza A (H1N1) virus infection in children - Dallas, Texas, May 2009. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2009 Jul 24;58(28):773-8.</citation>
    <PMID>19629027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tamura D, Miura T, Kikuchi Y. Oseltamivir phosphate in infants under 1 year of age with influenza infection. Pediatr Int. 2005 Aug;47(4):484.</citation>
    <PMID>16091087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okamoto S, Kamiya I, Kishida K, Shimakawa T, Fukui T, Morimoto T. Experience with oseltamivir for infants younger than 1 year old in Japan. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005 Jun;24(6):575-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15933579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 24, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 27, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 13, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 13, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 17, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Barbara Rath</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator, Pediatric Infectious Diseases &amp; Vaccines</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prospective, Observational Safety Study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oseltamivir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

