<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02661256</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02661256</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Nasal Continuous Positive Airway Pressure on The Pharyngeal Swallow in Neonates</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Nasal Continuous Positive Airway Pressure on The Pharyngeal Swallow in Neonates</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Winthrop University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Winthrop University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Oral feeding of neonates while on nasal continuous positive airway pressure (NCPAP) is a
      common practice in many neonatal intensive care units (NICU) all over the country. However
      the safety of such practice has never been established. The Investigators hypothesize that
      mechanoreceptors, which should perceive sensory input from the liquid bolus, may be altered
      by the reception of pressurized airflow provided by the NCPAP, hence increase risk of
      aspiration. In this study, changes in the pharyngeal phase of swallowing were identified
      using video fluoroscopic swallow studies (VFSS) for infants while on NCPAP as compared to off
      NCPAP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Preterm infants with underdeveloped lungs and term infants with cardio-respiratory illness
      frequently need to be placed on ventilatory assistance. Nasal Continuous Positive Airway
      Pressure (NCPAP) has been proven to be an effective mode of noninvasive ventilation in
      neonates, as it delivers positive pressure to the airway throughout the respiratory cycle.
      NCPAP works by improving the breathing pattern in neonates; it increases the mean airway
      pressure, stents the upper airway, decreases proximal airway resistance, reduces
      physiological dead space, optimizes lung recruitment and improves diaphragmatic function.
      While many infants in the Neonatal Intensive Care Units (NICUs) require NCPAP, many of their
      other medical and developmental needs such as initiating oral feedings need to be addressed.
      Oral feeding of neonates while on NCPAP is a common practice in many NICUs, however the
      effect of such practice on neonatal swallowing mechanism has never been investigated.

      Swallowing is a complex sensorimotor function that allows infant to safely and effectively
      ingest liquid nutrition. The ability of an infant to successfully feed is dependent on the
      precise interconnection of anatomy, physiology and neurology pathways. Afferent sequences
      play an integral role in the infant swallowing mechanism as sensory feedback is required
      during all phases of swallowing to allow appropriate positioning of anatomic structures, as
      well as to modulate the strength, velocity, and timing of muscle contractions. Sensory
      information is received from various types of sensory receptors distributed throughout the
      oral cavity, pharynx, larynx and esophagus. Localized areas of the infant's anatomy are known
      to have particular types of sensory receptors that are excited by specific stimuli which
      elicit appropriate motor movements.

      One of the most densely populated sensory receptors are the mechanoreceptors which are
      sensitive to touch and pressure to help decipher the shape, texture, size and temperature of
      the bolus about to be swallowed. The mechanoreceptors are also sensitive to the pressure and
      movement of air flow during breathing.

      The sensations perceived by these receptors are responsible for sending afferent sensory
      information to the medullary region of the brainstem where they are processed by the central
      pattern generators (CPGs). CPGs are composed of dedicated networks of interneurons that are
      responsible to sequence and activate different motor neurons at specified intensities to
      generate motor patterns. Both the swallowing CPG and the respiratory CPG are housed within
      the medulla. The close proximity of these neurons allows for precise swallow and breathing
      coordination. A close interrelationship between the swallowing and respiratory processes is
      further evident as they encompass shared anatomic structures and muscular components within
      the pharynx, and act as physiologically and biomechanically reciprocal events.

      This close interrelationship between swallowing and breathing has led to some controversy and
      difference in opinion among neonatologists on the decision to start oral feedings while on
      NCPAP. Although there is no research directly related to the effect of NCPAP on swallowing
      process in neonates, NCPAP has been reported to induce dilatation of the laryngeal opening in
      preterm infants and inhibit the swallow reflex in adults.

      For preterm infants, some neonatologists advocate initiation of oral feeds at 34 weeks
      gestational age, even if they require NCPAP; others strictly wait for NCPAP to be
      discontinued before oral feeding is established, fearing that infants may have difficulty
      coordinating breathing and swallowing acts, resulting in airway compromise. For term infants,
      many propose that oral feedings can be established once physiologic stability is
      demonstrated, either with or without NCPAP. Such controversies exist due to lack of evidence
      on the effect(s) of NCPAP on swallowing safety in human neonates.

      To our knowledge no studies have been completed on human infants to evaluate the effect of
      NCPAP on the pharyngeal swallowing mechanism. Previous studies utilizing neonatal lambs,
      revealed that the application of NCPAP had no deleterious effect on cardiopulmonary safety,
      feeding efficiency and on nutritive swallowing- breathing coordination.

      This study was designed with the aim to effectively assess the effects of NCPAP on the
      pharyngeal swallow mechanism in human neonates. The investigators hypothesize that the
      presence of NCPAP will lead to alterations in the sensorimotor sequence of the pharyngeal
      swallowing mechanism, increasing the risk for airway compromise and aspiration. The
      mechanoreceptors, which perceive sensory input from the liquid bolus, may be altered by the
      reception of continuous stream of airflow, provided by the NCPAP.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharyngeal Phase Dysphagia</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt;5 seconds post swallow trigger</time_frame>
    <description>presence of atypical or disordered movements during the pharyngeal phase of swallowing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tracheal Aspiration</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt;5 seconds post swallow trigger</time_frame>
    <description>the occurrence of barium below the level of the true vocal cords</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laryngeal Penetration, Deep</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt;2 seconds post swallow trigger</time_frame>
    <description>the occurrence of barium underneath the epiglottis, in the laryngeal vestibule to the level of the vocal folds</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Silent Aspiration</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt;5 seconds post swallow trigger</time_frame>
    <description>occurrence of a cough in the presence of aspiration (present/absent)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nasopharyngeal Reflux</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt;2 seconds post swallow trigger</time_frame>
    <description>the occurrence of barium detected in the nasopharynx, posterior or superior to the velum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharyngeal residue</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt;5 seconds post swallow trigger</time_frame>
    <description>the presence of residual barium coating the pharyngeal walls, pooling in the vallecula or pyriform sinuses post swallow (absent/mild/severe).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Deglutition Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Distress Syndrome In Premature Infants</condition>
  <condition>Respiratory Aspiration</condition>
  <condition>Newborn, Premature</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>on NCPAP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Once consented, each participant underwent a video fluoroscopic swallow study (VFSS) while NCPAP was administered via a RAM cannula® (intervention). With the NCPAP turned on each participant was fed room temperature thin liquid barium (Varibar® Thin Liquid Barium Sulfate for Suspension) from a standard bottle (60ml Similac® Volu-Feeder® with an attached Similac® Infant Nipple and Ring (standard flow), a total of 20 swallows were recorded. These swallows were termed &quot;on NCPAP&quot; swallows. The swallows were assessed in real time for any swallowing dysfunction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Off NCPAP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Immediately following the &quot;on NCPAP&quot; condition, an additional 20 swallows were recorded under VFSS with the NCPAP turned off (intervention). These swallows were termed &quot;off NCPAP&quot; swallows.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NCPAP</intervention_name>
    <description>Does NCPAP induce dysphagia in neonates? Each baby will be evaluated for dysphagia (using fluoroscopy) while on NCPAP and off NCPAP.</description>
    <arm_group_label>on NCPAP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Off NCPAP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Varibar® Thin Liquid Barium Sulfate for Suspension</intervention_name>
    <description>Liquid barium is used as a contrast material to allow visualization of swallowed boluses under fluoroscopy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>on NCPAP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Off NCPAP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants in neonatal ICU requiring NCPAP and tolerating at least 50% of their total
             required intake by mouth from a bottle, as determined by their medical team.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants with other comorbidity such as upper airway anomalies, brain injury
             neuromuscular disease, life threatening congenital disease. Any symptomatic
             intercurrent acute disease e.g. infectious disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>34 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Weeks</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nazeeh Hanna, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Winthrop University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 22, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Winthrop University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nazeeh Hanna, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Division of Neonatalogy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pharyngeal swallow</keyword>
  <keyword>airway compromise</keyword>
  <keyword>NICU</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deglutition Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>January 25, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>February 22, 2018</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

