<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02661490</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NOR-204</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1162-4913</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02661490</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Immunogenicity of Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 Bivalent Virus-Like Particle Vaccine in an Elderly Population</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Randomized, Double-blind, Safety and Immunogenicity Trial of Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 Bivalent Virus-Like Particle Vaccine in Healthy Elderly Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to further develop a formulation and dose regimen of the
      norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent virus-like particle (VLP) vaccine that is immunogenic and safe
      in an elderly population aged 60 years and above.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The vaccine being tested in this study is called norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent virus-like
      particle (VLP) vaccine adjuvanted with aluminum hydroxide (Formulation A) or adjuvanted with
      monophosphoryl lipid A (MPL) and aluminum hydroxide ( Formulation B). Two norovirus vaccine
      formulations are being tested to select for further development the formulation that will
      generate an optimal specific antibody response that may provide protection against norovirus
      and issafe in a population aged 60 years and above. This study will look at side effects and
      the level of antibodies to norovirus formed in people who will be injected with different
      formulations of the norovirus vaccine candidate.

      The study will enroll approximately 325 patients. Participants will be randomly assigned (by
      chance) to one of five treatment groups.

        -  Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine (Formulation A) 1-dose, participants ≥ 60
           years

        -  Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine (Formulation A) 2-dose, participants ≥ 60
           years

        -  Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine (Formulation B) 1-dose, participants ≥ 60
           years

        -  Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine (Formulation B) 2-dose, participants ≥ 60
           years

        -  Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine (Formulation A) 1-dose, participants 18 to 49
           years All participants in the age of 60 years and older will be administered either NoV
           vaccine (Formulation A or B) or placebo on Day 1 and NoV vaccine (Formulation A or B) on
           Day 29 of the study. In order to keep the treatment arms undisclosed to the patient and
           the doctor, those randomized to the one dose groups will receive a dose of placebo (this
           is a saline solution that has no active ingredient) on Day 1 followed by the NoV vaccine
           on Day 29. Those randomized to 2 doses with receive the NoV vaccine on Day 1 and Day 29.
           In case of an urgent medical need a participant can be unblinded.

      Adults aged 18 to 49 will receive placebo on Day 1 followed by NoV vaccine Formulation A on
      Day 29.

      Participants will be asked to record any reactions/ symptoms that may be related or not to
      the vaccine in a diary card for 28 days after each vaccination.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted in the United States of America. The overall time
      to participate in this study is up to 393 days. Participants will make multiple visits to the
      clinic including a final follow-up visit on Day 393.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 29, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 28, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a 4-Fold Rise or Greater in Serum Anti-Norovirus Antibody Titers for Both GI.1 VLP and GII.4 VLP (HBGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 57</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a 4-fold rise or greater in serum anti-norovirus antibody titers for both GI.1 VLP and GII.4 VLP as measured by histoblood group antigen (HBGA) binding assay.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Solicited Local Adverse Events (AEs) at Injection Site</measure>
    <time_frame>7 after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited local AEs at the injection site are defined as: pain, erythema, induration, and swelling that occurred within 7 days after each vaccination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Solicited Systemic Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited systemic AEs are defined as: headache, fatigue, myalgia, arthralgia, vomiting, and diarrhea that occurred within 7 days after each vaccination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Elevated Daily Oral Temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Oral body temperature measurement is to be performed using the thermometer provided by the site for 7 days after each vaccination. The highest body temperature observed each day will be recorded on the Diary Card also provided by the site. An elevated temperature is ≥ 38 degrees C (fever).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Unsolicited Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Unsolicited AEs are any AEs that are not solicited local or systemic AEs, as defined by this study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 up to Day 393</time_frame>
    <description>A serious adverse event (SAE) is any untoward medical occurrence that at any dose results in death, is life-threatening, requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in persistent or significant disability / incapacity, is a congenital anomaly / birth defect or is medically important due to other reasons than the above mentioned criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a 4-Fold Rise or Greater in Serum Anti-Norovirus Antibody Titers for Both GI.1 VLP and GII.4 VLP (HBGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a 4-fold rise or greater in serum anti-norovirus antibody titers for both GI.1 VLP and GII.4 VLP as measured by HBGA binding assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a 4-Fold Rise or Greater in Serum Anti-Norovirus Antibody Titers for GI.1 VLP (HBGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a 4-fold rise or greater in serum anti-norovirus antibody titers for GI.1 VLP as measured by HBGA binding assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a 4-Fold Rise or Greater in Serum Anti-Norovirus Antibody Titers for GII.4 VLP (HBGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a 4-fold rise or greater in serum anti-norovirus antibody titers for GII.4 VLP as measured by HBGA binding assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric Mean Titer (GMT) of GI.1 VLP Antibody Titers (HBGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>GMT of anti-norovirus GI.1 VLP antibody titers as measured by HBGA binding assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean titer (GMT) of GII.4 VLP Antibody Titers (HBGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>GMT of anti-norovirus GII.4 VLP antibody titers as measured by HBGA binding assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric Mean Fold Rise (GMFR) of GI.1 VLP Antibody Titers (HBGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>GMFR of anti-norovirus GI.1 VLP antibody titers as measured by HBGA binding assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric Mean Fold Rise (GMFR) of GII.4 VLP Antibody Titers (HBGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>GMFR of anti-norovirus GII.4 VLP antibody titers as measured by HBGA binding assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a 4-Fold Rise or Greater in Serum Anti-Norovirus Antibody Titers for Both GI.1 VLP and GII.4 VLP (Pan-Ig ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a 4-fold rise or greater in serum anti-norovirus antibody titers for both GI.1 VLP and GII.4 VLP as measured by pan immunoglobulin (Pan-Ig) enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a 4-Fold Rise or Greater in Serum Anti-Norovirus Antibody Titers for GI.1 VLP (Pan-Ig ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a 4-fold rise or greater in serum anti-norovirus antibody titers for GI.1 VLP as measured by Pan-Ig ELISA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a 4-Fold Rise or Greater in Serum Anti-Norovirus Antibody Titers for GII.4 VLP (Pan-Ig ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a 4-fold rise or greater in serum anti-norovirus antibody titers for GII.4 VLP as measured by Pan-Ig ELISA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric Mean Titer (GMT) of GI.1 VLP Antibody Titers (Pan-Ig ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>GMT of anti-norovirus GI.1 VLP antibody titers as measured by Pan-Ig ELISA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric Mean Titer (GMT) of GII.4 VLP Antibody Titers (Pan-Ig ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>GMT of anti-norovirus GII.4 VLP antibody titers as measured by Pan-Ig ELISA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric Mean Fold Rise (GMFR) of GI.1 VLP Antibody Titers (Pan-Ig ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>GMFR of anti-norovirus GI.1 VLP antibody titers as measured by Pan-Ig ELISA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric Mean Fold Rise (GMFR) of GII.4 VLP Antibody Titers (Pan-Ig ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 8, 29, 36, 57, 211 and 393</time_frame>
    <description>GMFR of anti-norovirus GII.4 VLP antibody titers as measured by Pan-Ig ELISA.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Adverse Events of Special Interest (AESI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to Day 393</time_frame>
    <description>AESIs are AEs that are not solicited local or systemic AEs and are predefined in the protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Any Adverse Event (AE) Leading to Withdrawal from the Study</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to Day 393</time_frame>
    <description>Withdrawal due to an AE will occur if the participant experiences an AE that requires early termination because continued participation imposes an unacceptable risk to the participant's health or the participant is unwilling to continue because of the AE.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">320</enrollment>
  <condition>Norovirus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: NoV Vaccine Formulation A _1-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants ≥ 60 years of age, 1-dose regimen: norovirus bivalent placebo-matching vaccine, intramuscularly (IM), on Day 1, followed by norovirus (NoV) GI.1/GII.4 bivalent virus-like particle (VLP) vaccine Formulation A, IM, on Day 29.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: NoV Vaccine Formulation A _2-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants ≥ 60 years of age, 2-dose regimen: norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine Formulation A, IM, on Days 1 and 29.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: NoV Vaccine Formulation B_1-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants ≥ 60 years of age, 1-dose regimen: norovirus bivalent placebo-matching vaccine, IM on Day 1, followed by norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine Formulation B, IM, on Day 29.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4: NoV Vaccine Formulation B_2-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants ≥ 60 years of age, 2-dose regimen: Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine Formulation B, IM, on Days 1 and 29.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 5: NoV Vaccine Formulation A_1-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants 18 to 49 years of age, 1-dose regimen: norovirus bivalent placebo-matching vaccine, IM, on Day 1, followed by norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine Formulation A, IM, on Day 29.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 Bivalent VLP Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine adjuvanted with aluminum hydroxide, without MPL for IM injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: NoV Vaccine Formulation A _1-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: NoV Vaccine Formulation A _2-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 5: NoV Vaccine Formulation A_1-Dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.9% sodium chloride (saline)</intervention_name>
    <description>norovirus bivalent placebo-matching vaccine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: NoV Vaccine Formulation A _1-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: NoV Vaccine Formulation B_1-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 5: NoV Vaccine Formulation A_1-Dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 Bivalent VLP Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Norovirus GI.1/GII.4 bivalent VLP vaccine adjuvanted with MPL and aluminum hydroxide for IM injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: NoV Vaccine Formulation B_1-Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 4: NoV Vaccine Formulation B_2-Dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Is aged 18 to 49 years, or 60 years and older at the time of enrollment;

          2. Participants who are in good health, or in stable health status with no exclusionary
             medical or neuropsychiatric conditions at the time of entry into the trial as
             determined by medical history, physical examination (including vital signs) and
             clinical judgment of the Investigator;

          3. Participant signs and dates a written, Informed Consent Form (ICF) and any required
             privacy authorization prior to the initiation of any trial procedures, after the
             nature of the trial has been explained according to local regulatory requirements;

          4. Participants who can comply with trial procedures and are available for the duration
             of follow-up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has a known hypersensitivity or allergy to any of the Norovirus (NoV) GI.1/GII.4
             Bivalent virus-like particle (VLP) Vaccine components;

          2. Has a clinically significant active infection (as assessed by the Investigator) or
             body temperature ≥38°C/100.4°F within 3 days of the intended date of vaccination;

          3. Participants with the presence of significant acute or chronic, uncontrolled medical
             or neuropsychiatric illness. Uncontrolled was defined as:

             Requiring institution of new medical or surgical treatment within 3 months prior to
             immunization, or Requiring a change in medication dosage in the 3 months prior to
             immunization due to uncontrolled symptoms or drug toxicity (elective dosage
             adjustments in stable participants were acceptable), or Hospitalization or an event
             fulfilling the definition of a serious adverse event within 3 months prior
             immunization.

          4. Has any unstable medical or neuropsychiatric condition, which in the Investigator's
             opinion poses a risk of unusual magnitude for the participant's age group of
             hospitalization, death, or an event meeting the definition of a serious adverse event
             within 2 months of immunization. The intent of this criterion is to recognize and
             allow for the frequent existence of significant health concerns in this population;
             but exclude those participants who are experiencing an acute decline in health status;

          5. Has any medical or neuropsychiatric condition, which in the Investigator's opinion,
             rendered the participant incompetent to provide informed consent or unable to provide
             valid safety observations and reports;

          6. Has behavioral or cognitive impairment or psychiatric disease that, in the opinion of
             the Investigator, may interfere with the participant's ability to participate in the
             trial;

          7. Participants with any history of progressive or severe neurologic disorder, history of
             seizure, or history of neuro-inflammatory disease (e.g.Guillain-Barre syndrome);

          8. Participants with history or any illness that, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             might interfere with the results of the trial or pose additional risk to the
             participants due to participation in the trial;

          9. Has known or suspected autoimmune disease;

         10. Has known or suspected impairment/alteration of immune function, including:

             Chronic use of oral steroids (Equivalent to 20 mg/day prednisone ≥ 12 weeks/≥ 2 mg/kg
             body weight/day prednisone ≥ 2 weeks) within 60 days prior to Day 1 (use of inhaled,
             intranasal, or topical corticosteroids is allowed).

             Receipt of parenteral steroids (Equivalent to 20 mg/day prednisone ≥ 12 weeks/≥ 2
             mg/kg body weight/day prednisone ≥ 2 weeks) within 60 days prior to Day 1.

             Receipt of immunosuppressive therapy within 3 months prior to Day 1. Receipt of
             immunostimulants within 60 days prior to Day 1. Receipt of parenteral, epidural or
             intra-articular immunoglobulin preparation, blood products, and/or plasma derivatives
             within 3 months prior to Day 1 or planned during the full length of the trial.

             Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection or HIV-related disease. Genetic
             immunodeficiency.

         11. Has abnormalities of splenic or thymic function;

         12. Has any significant disorder of coagulation or treatment with anticoagulant therapy
             that would increase the risk of intramuscular (IM) injection. Persons receiving
             prophylactic antiplatelet medication such as low dose of acetylsalicylic acid are
             eligible;

         13. Has any serious chronic or progressive disease according to judgment of the
             Investigator: cancer (malignancy other than resolved/excised skin lesion), insulin
             dependent Type I diabetes (Type II diabetes is accepted), cardiac, renal or hepatic
             disease;

         14. Has body mass index (BMI) greater than or equal to 35 kg/m^2 (= weight in kg/[height
             in meters^2]);

         15. Is participating in any clinical trial with another investigational product 30 days
             prior to first trial visit or intent to participate in another clinical trial at any
             time during the conduct of this trial;

         16. Participants who received any other vaccines within 14 days (for inactivated vaccines)
             or 28 days (for live vaccines) prior to enrollment in this trial or who are planning
             to receive any vaccine within 28 days of investigational vaccine administration;

         17. Participants involved in trial conduct or their first degree relatives;

         18. Has history of substance or alcohol abuse within the past 2 years;

         19. Females who are pregnant or breastfeeding;

         20. If female of childbearing potential, sexually active with a male partner who has not
             been sterilized, and has not used any of the &quot;acceptable contraceptive methods&quot; for at
             least 2 months prior to trial entry:

             Of childbearing potential is defined as status post onset of menarche and not meeting
             any of the following conditions: menopausal for at least 2 years, status after
             bilateral tubal ligation for at least 1 year, status after bilateral oophorectomy, or
             status after hysterectomy.

             Acceptable birth control methods are defined as one or more of the following: i.
             Hormonal contraceptive (such as oral, injection, transdermal patch, implant, cervical
             ring); ii. Barrier (condom with spermicide or diaphragm with spermicide) each and
             every time during intercourse; iii. Intrauterine device (IUD); iv. Monogamous
             relationship with vasectomized partner. Partner must have been vasectomized for at
             least six months prior to the participants' trial entry.

         21. If female of childbearing potential and sexually active, refusal to use an &quot;acceptable
             contraceptive method&quot; from Day 1 and throughout the duration of the trial. In
             addition, they must be advised not to donate ova during this period;

         22. Females with any positive or indeterminate pregnancy test.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director Clinical Science</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Simon Williamson Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fountain Hills Family Practice, P.C.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fountain Hills</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85268</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southwest Family Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Littleton</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80127</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami Research Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johnson County Clin-Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lenexa</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Louis University, School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regional Clinical Research Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Endwell</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13760</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Childrens Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229-3039</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Group Health Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Norovirus</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aluminum Hydroxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

