<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02666079</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LPM-007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02666079</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The LightPathTM Breast Cancer Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-centre Clinical Study to Evaluate the LightPathTM Imaging System in Wide Local Excision (WLE) for Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lightpoint Medical Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Commission</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lightpoint Medical Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, single arm, multi-centre study to evaluate the intra-operative
      use of the LightPath™ Imaging System for the assessment of tumour margin status compared to
      hospital standard of care histopathology in wide local excision (WLE) for breast cancer

      The intraoperative 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose (18F-FDG) LightPath™ Images will be used to inform
      the surgeons about detectable residual cancer, in an attempt to achieve better guided cancer
      surgery and complete tumour excision with clear WLE resection margins.

      Study sites will use the local criteria considered standard of care to guide decisions to act
      on positive margins.

      In the LightPathTM arm the resection margin status of the WLE specimen, cavity shavings (if
      any) and the metastatic status of axillary (sentinel) lymph nodes as measured with the
      LightPath™ Imaging System will be compared with histopathology results.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Female subjects with a diagnosis of invasive breast cancer scheduled to have wide local
      excision (WLE) +/- sentinel lymph node biopsy (SLNB) or axillary lymph node dissection (ALND)
      will be screened and receive 18F-FDG plus LightPath™ Image. Subjects will have standard of
      care WLE. Extra cavity shaving due to positive 18F-FDG LightPath™ Images is at the discretion
      of the surgeon.

      Subjects will receive an intravenous injection of up to 5 MBq/kg, to a maximum 300
      MegaBecquerel (MBq) of 18F-FDG prior to surgery.

      Following resection, the WLE specimen will be examined using the LightPath™ Imaging System.
      If the surgeons detect a positive signal they may perform cavity shavings of the resection
      cavity area corresponding to the positive signal area (up to a maximum thickness of 10mm).

      Axillary SLNB will be performed according to local practice. At sites where 99mTc is used: In
      the 18F-FDG + LightPath™ a higher dose of up to 150 MBq technetium-99m (99mTc) nanocolloid is
      necessary to avoid 18F-FDG masking the signal from 99mTc. Blue dye will be used according to
      local practice at sites where it is considered standard of care.

      Sentinel lymph nodes (SLNs) will be examined using the LightPath™ Imaging System. Where
      clinically indicated, ALND will be performed as per standard of care. At the time this
      protocol was finalised, LightPath™ data involved lymph nodes sufficient to support
      recommendations were not available. For this reason, LightPath™ Image results will not be
      used to direct ALND.

      All LightPath™ Images will be performed between 60 and 180 minutes post injection of 18F-FDG.

      The WLE specimen, cavity shavings (where performed) and SLNs (where performed) will then
      undergo standard of care histopathological analysis. Lymph nodes will also be examined
      according to standard of care histopathological analysis. The results of the
      histopathological analysis will then be correlated with the LightPath™ Images.

      All staff in the operating room will wear badge dosimeters. Staff handling surgical specimens
      in theatre will also wear ring dosimeters. Histopathology analyses should be delayed to allow
      for radioactive decay of tissue samples to suitably low levels.

      Subjects will be evaluated at screening and enrolment into the study. Data will be collected
      until the decision by the study site's MDT to recommend re-excision or mastectomy because of
      a positive margin on histopathological analysis (approx. 1-6 weeks post surgery)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic performance of the LightPathTM Imaging System</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The diagnostic performance of tumour margin assessment with the LightPathTM Imaging System compared to hospital histopathology.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The recommendation by the study site's multidisciplinary team (MDT) to re-operate at the index location (breast) within 1 to 6 weeks post-initial surgery according to local practice.</measure>
    <time_frame>1-6 weeks post initial surgery</time_frame>
    <description>MDT recommendation for the subject to undergo re-excision or mastectomy because of a positive margin on histopathological analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of re-operation at the index location</measure>
    <time_frame>1 to 6 weeks post initial surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The number of subjects undergoing re-operation at the index location because of a positive margin on histopathological analysis, compared to published data on re-operation rates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of tissue excised</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Weight (g) of all fresh pieces of tissue removed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiation dosimetry</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Dosimetry readings will be summarised by staff member and procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety - adverse events (related to breast surgery)</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Any untoward medical occurrence, unintended disease or injury, or untoward clinical signs (including abnormal laboratory findings) in subjects, users or other persons, whether r not related to the device</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Agreement between LightPathTM Image for lymph nodes status and histology</measure>
    <time_frame>Initial surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of lymph nodes that agree metastatic status</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarkers ER/PR/HER2 status</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening</time_frame>
    <description>ER/PR/HER2 will each be defined as positive or negative in accordance with local practice</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Wide local excision (WLE) for breast cancer with intra-operative use of the LightPath™ Imaging System.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LightPath™ Imaging System.</intervention_name>
    <description>Intra-operative use of the LightPath™ Imaging System.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who have signed an informed consent form prior to any study related activity

          -  Subjects who are able to give voluntary, written informed consent to participate in
             this study.

          -  Subjects who are able to understand this study and are willing to complete all the
             study assessments

          -  Female participants ≥18 years of age with a diagnosis of invasive breast cancer

          -  Subjects who have disease in one quadrant of the breast, not including the nipple

          -  Subjects scheduled for WLE for breast cancer +/- SLNB or ALND.

          -  Females of childbearing age must have a negative pregnancy test (by Beta human
             chorionic gonadotropin (HCG) qualitative analysis), or must have had a history of a
             surgical sterilisation, or must give history of no menses in the past twelve months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with pure DCIS or with pleomorphic LCIS

          -  Subjects who have had surgery in the ipsilateral breast in the past 12 months

          -  Subjects who have had radiotherapy in the ipsilateral breast

          -  Subjects who have had neoadjuvant systemic therapy

          -  Subjects who have had systemic chemotherapy in the past two years

          -  Subjects with a non-palpable lesion scheduled to have radio guided occult lesion
             localisation (ROLL)

          -  Subjects who have known hypersensitivity to 18F-FDG

          -  Subjects who are pregnant or lactating

          -  Subjects who have an existing medical condition that would compromise their
             participation in the study

          -  Subjects who have participated in a clinical study in the last 2 months

          -  Subjects with a current or active history of other known cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Qamar B Akbar</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Senior Clinical Research Associate</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Qamar B Akbar</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0) 1494 917 697</phone>
    <email>qamar.akbar@lightpointmedical.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Liverpool Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <zip>L7 8XP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sherald Barnes</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)1517064894</phone>
      <email>Sherald.Barnes@rlbuht.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Holcombe, MD FRCS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiff Breast Centre, LLandough Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Llandough</city>
        <zip>CF64 2XX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zoe Davies</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0)2920715710</phone>
      <email>Zoe.davies7@wales.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sumit Goyal, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.lightpointmedical.com/</url>
    <description>Company website with description of the technology and Conformité Européenne (CE) marked medical device</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.isrctn.com/ISRCTN17778965</url>
    <description>ISRCTN17778965</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Wide local excision (WLE) for breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

