<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02665104</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DE RKEB/IKEB:4364/2015</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>094579/2015/OTIG</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02665104</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Middle Cerebral Artery Velocity and Oxygen Saturation of the Brain During Carotid Endarterectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of Blood Flow Velocity in the MCA and Oxygen Saturation of the Brain During Carotid Endarterectomy in Local Anesthesia in Patients With and Without Neurological Symptoms Using Transcranial Doppler (TCD) and INVOS Monitor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Debrecen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Debrecen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary endpoint of our study is to determine whether neurological symptoms (aphasia,
      paresis, loss of consciousness, numbness) occur after clamping the internal carotid artery,
      and if so, changes showed by transcranial Doppler or INVOS monitor is more sensitive
      regarding the symptoms? Secondary endpoint: the degree of change in the measured parameters
      after the internal carotid artery is clamped, and if there is any difference between the
      operated and non-operated sides?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Investigation of blood flow velocity in the middle cerebral artery and oxygen saturation of
      the brain bilaterally during carotid endarterectomy carried out in local anesthesia in
      patients with and without neurological symptoms using transcranial Doppler (TCD) and INVOS
      monitor.

      Zoltán Gyöngyösi Study protocol

      The primary endpoint of our study is to determine whether neurological symptoms (aphasia,
      paresis, loss of consciousness, numbness) occur after clamping the internal carotid artery,
      and if so, changes showed by transcranial Doppler or INVOS monitor is more sensitive
      regarding the symptoms? Secondary endpoint: the degree of change in the measured parameters
      after the internal carotid artery is clamped, and if there is any difference between the
      operated and non-operated sides?

      Patients and Methods

      Outpatient examination, preparation and anesthesia of the patients:

        -  ECG test

        -  Echocardiography, if it is necessary due to the cardial status of the patient.

        -  Indication of surgical intervention provided by the cerebrovascular outpatient clinic,
           with attached carotid ultrasound and angiography results.

      Surgical anesthesia:

        -  Superficial and deep cervical block with 3.75% ropivacaine (50ml ropivacaine 3.75%)
           (incase of allergy bupivacaine should be used)

        -  Securing venous catheter, infusion of Lactated-Ringer or Voluven solution.

        -  In case of pain topical administration of Lidocaine by the surgeon, intravenous
           administration of 25-50ug Fentanyl or 1 vial of Algopyrin.

      Intraoperative measurements:

        -  Bilateral transcranial Doppler measurements of the blood flow velocity within the middle
           cerebral arteries: 1. before local anesthesia, 2. after the onset of local anesthetic,
           but before skin incision, 3. intraoperatively before clamping the internal carotid
           artery, 4. one minute after clamping the internal carotid artery, 5. five minutes after
           clamping the internal carotid artery, 6. fifteen minutes after clamping the internal
           carotid artery, 7. directly after the restoration of blood flow in the internal carotid
           artery, 8. postoperatively, 4-6 hours after the intervention.

        -  Recording mean arterial pressure with each TCD measurement.

        -  Recording cerebral saturation (INVOS) with each TCD measurement.

        -  Recording any anti-hypertensive therapy in the postoperative phase.

        -  Recording heart rate.

        -  Recording arterial oxygen saturation.

        -  Recording the patients' neurological status with each TCD measurement and continuous
           neurological monitoring while the internal carotid artery is clamped.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>to determine the changes in MCA flow velocity in patient with intraoperative neurological symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>15 month</time_frame>
    <description>(aphasia, paresis, loss of consciousness, numbness) occur after clamping the internal carotid artery, and if so, to determine the changes in MCA flow velocity in patient with intraoperative neurological symptoms
Recording mean arterial flow velocity with each TCD measurement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>to determine the changes in cerebral O2 saturation in patient with intraoperative neurological symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>15 month</time_frame>
    <description>Recording cerebral saturation (INVOS) with each measurement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the degree of change in the measured parameters during clamp and declamp after the internal carotid artery is clamped, if there is any difference between the operated and non-operated sides?</measure>
    <time_frame>15 month</time_frame>
    <description>Recording mean arterial pressure with each TCD measurement. Recording cerebral saturation (INVOS) with each measurement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Oxygen Saturation,MCA Velocity,Intraoperative Neurological Symptoms During Carotid Endarterectomy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients without neurological symptoms</arm_group_label>
    <description>carotid endarterectomy patients who dont'have any neurological symptoms after carotid clamping</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients with neurological symptoms</arm_group_label>
    <description>carotid endarterectomy patients who have new neurological symptoms after carotid clamping</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>transcranial Doppler (TCD) and INVOS monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>Bilateral transcranial Doppler measurements of the blood flow velocity within the middle cerebral arteries: 1. before local anesthesia, 2. after the onset of local anesthetic, but before skin incision, 3. intraoperatively before clamping the internal carotid artery, 4. one minute after clamping the internal carotid artery, 5. five minutes after clamping the internal carotid artery, 6. fifteen minutes after clamping the internal carotid artery, 7. directly after the restoration of blood flow in the internal carotid artery, 8. postoperatively, 4-6 hours after the intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>patients without neurological symptoms</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>patients with neurological symptoms</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        100 patients awaiting carotid artery endarterectomy carried out in regional anesthesia.

          -  Age: patients over 18 years.

          -  Gender: both female and male patients are included in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  100 patients awaiting carotid artery endarterectomy carried out in regional
             anesthesia.

          -  Age: patients over 18 years.

          -  Gender: both female and male patients are included in the study.

          -  Medical equipment: venous catheter, arterial catheter for invasive blood pressure
             monitoring.

          -  Bilateral continuous measurement of the middle cerebral arteries with Transcranial
             Doppler.

          -  Bilateral continuous measurement of the cerebral saturation with INVOS monitor.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy to ropivacaine, bupivacaine.

          -  Patients who does not consent to the awake surgery or does not sign the informed
             consent of the study.

          -  If the patient is either psychologically or neurologically unsuitable for the awake
             surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Béla Fülesdi, MD,PhD,DSci</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hungary University of Debrecen Debrecen, Hungary, 4032</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zoltán Mr Gyöngyösi, Md</last_name>
    <phone>+3630/2883970</phone>
    <email>zozman77@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Erzsébet Igbonu-nagy, nurse</last_name>
    <phone>+3620/3991551</phone>
    <email>nagyboske@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Debrecen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Debrecen</city>
        <state>Hajdú-Bihar</state>
        <zip>4032</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Béla Fülesdi, MD PhD DSci</last_name>
      <phone>00 36 52 255 347</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Zoltán Gyöngyösi, md</last_name>
      <phone>00 36 52 255 347</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Debrecen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Debrecen</city>
        <zip>4032</zip>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hungary</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Williams IM, Mead G, Picton AJ, Farrell A, Mortimer AJ, McCollum CN. The influence of contralateral carotid stenosis and occlusion on cerebral oxygen saturation during carotid artery surgery. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 1995 Aug;10(2):198-206.</citation>
    <PMID>7655972</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pennekamp CW, Immink RV, den Ruijter HM, Kappelle LJ, Bots ML, Buhre WF, Moll FL, de Borst GJ. Near-infrared spectroscopy to indicate selective shunt use during carotid endarterectomy. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2013 Oct;46(4):397-403. doi: 10.1016/j.ejvs.2013.07.007. Epub 2013 Aug 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23973277</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Debrecen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tamas Vegh, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>assistant professor anesthesiologist and intensive care specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cerebral oxygen saturation</keyword>
  <keyword>TCD</keyword>
  <keyword>NIRS</keyword>
  <keyword>Carotid endarterectomy</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

