<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02666781</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-9507</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02666781</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Postoperative Rostral Fluid Shift and Obstructive Sleep Apnea</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Contribution of Rostral Shift of Fluid to Postoperative Worsening of Obstructive Sleep Apnea Severity in Surgical Patients - A Prospective Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Society of Anesthesia and Sleep Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) are more likely to experience postoperative
      complications and impact significantly on healthcare resources. In the surgical population,
      the type and volume of IV fluid administration may contribute to the worsening of
      postoperative sleep apnea but the pathophysiological mechanisms have not been elucidated.
      Recent research from general population suggests that intravenous (IV) fluid administration
      worsens the severity of OSA by shifting of fluid from the legs to the neck thus increasing
      neck size and causing airway collapse. In this novel study, our objective is to examine the
      contribution of IV fluid administration and rostral fluid shift from the legs to the neck
      thereby leading to worsening of sleep apnea following surgery. In this prospective
      observational cohort study, 25 consecutive adult patients, requiring at least 2 days hospital
      stay, will be recruited. Following informed consent, patients will undergo portable home
      sleep study to determine the preoperative severity of sleep-disordered breathing. On the day
      of surgery, leg, neck and total body fluid volumes will be recorded, and patients will
      undergo general anesthetic. The results of this study will be used to design future clinical
      trials evaluating methods to decrease postoperative OSA worsening, as well as decreasing
      OSA-related postoperative complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a common sleep-related breathing disorder, associated with
      increased morbidity and mortality. It is an independent risk-factor for post-operative
      cardio-respiratory complications and increased perioperative utilization of health care
      resources. In non-surgical patients, rostral fluid shift from the lower limbs to the neck has
      been identified as a pathophysiologic mechanism to explain OSA severity based on gender,
      increasing age, and in fluid-overload states. In this novel study, our objective is to
      examine the contribution of fluid shift from the lower limbs to the neck thereby leading to
      worsening of sleep apnea following surgery.

      Objectives of the study

        -  Measure the change in the leg, neck and total fluid volume from preoperative baseline to
           the second postoperative day.

        -  Assess the impact of the change in neck fluid volume on neck circumference and
           postoperative AHI.

      Similar to the patients with heart failure, renal failure and older men, we hypothesize the
      rostral shift of fluid from the lower limbs to the neck occurs in the postoperative period
      contributing to the postoperative worsening of OSA. In this study, we will perform serial
      measurements of segmental and total body water shifts occurring after surgery, at various
      time-points over two postoperative days. We will monitor indices such as the Apnea Hypopnea
      index (AHI) and oxygen desaturation index (ODI) to examine changes in the severity of OSA.
      Internal validity of our study will be made more robust by use of well-validated methods such
      as BIA for fluid measurements and portable PSG for OSA severity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Leg, neck and total body fluid volume on postoperative nights 1 and 2</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Compartmental Fluids will be measured using an bioelectrical impedance device (BIA)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neck Circumference on Postoperative Nights 1 and 2</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Neck circumference (in cm) will be assessed with a measuring tape and reported for correlation with other data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apnea Hypopnea Index (AHI) on Postoperative Night 1</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>AHI will be measured as an indicator for the severity of Obstructive Sleep Apnea using an ApneaLink plus device.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pilot Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Postoperative surgical Patients with or without Obstructive Sleep Apnea</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ApneaLink Plus, BIA Device</intervention_name>
    <description>The study is only observational. No interventions will be performed. ApneaLink Plus will be used to diagnose Obstructive Sleep Apnea in potential candidates and grade its severity on Postoperative night 2 in participants. A BIA Device will be used to detect segmental fluid shifts. A 3-D accelerometer will be used to detect head and neck position.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pilot Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Surgical patients attending the preoperative assessment clinic in Toronto Western Hospital
        (UHN) who will be undergoing elective non-cardiac surgery, requiring general anesthesia,
        lasting for 1-2 hours or more and requiring same day admission for a minimum of 2 days
        postoperatively.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status I to IV

          -  Undergoing elective non-cardiac surgery, requiring general anesthesia, lasting for 1-2
             hours or more and requiring same day admission for a minimum of 2 days
             postoperatively.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing cardiac, intracranial surgery, procedures involving the neck such
             as cervical spine surgery, or carotid endarterectomy.

          -  Patients requiring epidural or spinal anesthesia for their surgery, as neuraxial
             blockade may impact fluid shifts from legs to neck and may confound our results.

          -  Prior history of vascular surgery in the lower limbs such as varicose vein surgery,
             vascular by-pass surgery or evidence of venous efficiency.

          -  Fluid overload states such as history of congestive heart failure, or renal failure
             will be excluded.

          -  Patients with metal implants in lower limbs or spine, due to possible interference
             with the leg impedance signals.

          -  Patients requiring urgent sleep physician referral (within four weeks) due to serious
             medical conditions or safety critical-occupations according to the 2011 Canadian
             Thoracic Society (CTS) guidelines e.g. unstable ischemic heart disease, recent
             cerebrovascular disease, congestive heart failure, obstructive/restrictive lung
             disease, pulmonary hypertension, hypercapnia respiratory failure.

          -  Pregnant or lactating patients, as the physiological mechanisms governing
             postoperative fluid shifts are different in this patient population.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD,FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Anesthesia, Toronto Western Hospital- UHN, University of Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mandeep Singh, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <phone>+1 (416) 790-0808</phone>
    <email>mandeep.singh@uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Arvind Tuteja, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>+1 (416) 603-5800</phone>
    <phone_ext>3959</phone_ext>
    <email>Arvind.Tuteja@uhnresearch.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Western Hospital- UHN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sazzadul Islam, Mac, CRA</last_name>
      <phone>416 603 5800</phone>
      <phone_ext>2246</phone_ext>
      <email>sazzadul.islam@uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stopbang.ca</url>
    <description>Official Website for &quot;STOP-Bang&quot; Screening Questionnaire for Diagnosis of Obstructive Sleep Apnea</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Durán J, Esnaola S, Rubio R, Iztueta A. Obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea and related clinical features in a population-based sample of subjects aged 30 to 70 yr. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2001 Mar;163(3 Pt 1):685-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11254524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mutter TC, Chateau D, Moffatt M, Ramsey C, Roos LL, Kryger M. A matched cohort study of postoperative outcomes in obstructive sleep apnea: could preoperative diagnosis and treatment prevent complications? Anesthesiology. 2014 Oct;121(4):707-18. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000407.</citation>
    <PMID>25247853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chung F, Yegneswaran B, Liao P, Chung SA, Vairavanathan S, Islam S, Khajehdehi A, Shapiro CM. STOP questionnaire: a tool to screen patients for obstructive sleep apnea. Anesthesiology. 2008 May;108(5):812-21. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31816d83e4.</citation>
    <PMID>18431116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng SS, Chan TO, To KW, Ngai J, Tung A, Ko FW, Hui DS. Validation of a portable recording device (ApneaLink) for identifying patients with suspected obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome. Intern Med J. 2009 Nov;39(11):757-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1445-5994.2008.01827.x. Epub 2008 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19220528</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>OSA, Surgery, Postoperative, Rostral Fluid Shift</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

