<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02666846</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FM52</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02666846</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assess the Efficacy and Safety in Volunteers of DCF100, TIB200 and SPR300 vs. Placebo and Control(s) in a UV Pain Model</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised, Double Blind, Cross Over Clinical Study in Healthy Human Volunteers to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of Three Different Topical Analgesics (DCF100, TIB200 And SPR300) Versus Placebo and Active Control(s) in a Model of UV-Induced Inflammatory Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Futura Medical Developments Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Parexel</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Futura Medical Developments Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomised, double blind, cross over clinical study in healthy human volunteers
      (including pharmacokinetic [PK] sampling and laser Doppler assessment of local blood flow in
      a subset of up to 6 subjects per cohort of 20) to assess the efficacy and safety of three
      different topical analgesics (DCF100, TIB200 and SPR300) versus placebo and active control(s)
      in a model of UV-induced inflammatory pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomised, double blind, cross over clinical study in healthy human volunteers,
      including pharmacokinetic (PK) sampling and laser Doppler assessment of local blood flow in a
      subset of up to 6 subjects per cohort, to assess the efficacy and safety of three different
      topical analgesics (DCF100, TIB200 and SPR300) versus placebo and active control(s) in a
      model of UV-induced inflammatory pain. The study will consist of 3 cohorts of subjects (n=20
      subjects per cohort). Subjects of each cohort will receive test and reference products (no
      reference product for Cohort 3) of one investigational medicinal product (IMP) and a placebo.

      Test Products:

      Cohort 1: Ibuprofen, TIB200 gel (10%, w/w) Cohort 2: Diclofenac, DCF100 gel (2% or 4%, w/w)
      Cohort 3: Methyl-salicylate and Menthol, SPR300 gel (15%:7%, w/w; ratio of Methylsalicylate
      to Menthol)

      Reference Products:

      Cohort 1: Ibuprofen, Nurofen Max Strength gel (10%, w/w), Ibuprofen, Nurofen, oral tablet
      (400 mg) Cohort 2: Voltaren Emulgel (2%), Voltarol oral tablet (50 mg)

      Placebo:

      All Cohorts:Test product matching vehicle gel.

      Pharmacodynamic tests and PK blood draws will be performed at: pre-dose, 1, 2, 4, and 6 hours
      post dose for all treatment cohorts and treatment days (PK blood sampling in up to 6 subjects
      per cohort only).

      Safety will be evaluated by the incidence of local and systemic treatment-emergent adverse
      events (TEAEs) reported after each treatment. Safety assessments will also include vital
      signs, 12-Lead Electrocardiograms (ECGs), laboratory tests and a physical examination at
      Screening and the Follow-up visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heat Pain Tolerance Test</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes before to 6 hours post administration</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the pharmacodynamic effect by Heat Pain Tolerance Test (HPTT) of three topical analgesics, DCF100, TIB200, and SPR300 versus topical placebo and active topical reference products in a model of UV-induced inflammatory pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensity of the UVB-induced erythema</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes before to 6 hours post administration</time_frame>
    <description>Intensity of the Ultra Violet B radiation (UVB)-induced erythema (determined by assessment of skin blood flow by laser Doppler imaging [flux units], up to 6 subjects per cohort)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes before to 6 hours post administration</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax), time corresponding to occurrence of Cmax (tmax) (up to 6 subjects per cohort only) laser Doppler imaging [flux units], up to 6 subjects per cohort)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Plasma Concentration versus Time Curve</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes before to 6 hours post administration</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the concentration vs. time curve from time zero to 6 hours (AUC0-6h) (up to 6 subjects per cohort only) laser Doppler imaging [flux units], up to 6 subjects per cohort)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Estimated study duration for each subject will be approximately 6 weeks; 4 week (28 days) Screening period, a 4 to 7 day treatment period and up to a 2 week (7 to 9 days) Follow-up period.</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory assessments - clinical chemistry and haematology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical exams</measure>
    <time_frame>Estimated study duration for each subject will be approximately 6 weeks; 4 week (28 days) Screening period, a 4 to 7 day treatment period and up to a 2 week (7 to 9 days) Follow-up period.</time_frame>
    <description>Physical examinations - including assessments of the application site. examination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Estimated study duration for each subject will be approximately 6 weeks; 4 week (28 days) Screening period, a 4 to 7 day treatment period and up to a 2 week (7 to 9 days) Follow-up period.</time_frame>
    <description>Local and systemic Adverse Events (AEs).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital Signs and Electrocardiograms (ECGs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Estimated study duration for each subject will be approximately 6 weeks; 4 week (28 days) Screening period, a 4 to 7 day treatment period and up to a 2 week (7 to 9 days) Follow-up period.</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs and ECGs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>11</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: TIB200 gel 10%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 1: Ibuprofen, TIB200 gel (10%, w/w)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Nurofen gel 10%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 1: Ibuprofen, Nurofen Max Strength gel (10%, w/w)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Nurofen tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 1: Ibuprofen, Nurofen oral tablets (2 x 400 mg)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: TIB200 Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 1: TIB200 matching placebo gel</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: DCF100 gel 2%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 2: Diclofenac, DCF100 gel (2% w/w)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: DCF100 gel 4%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 2: Diclofenac, DCF100 gel (4% w/w)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Voltaren gel 2%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 2: Diclofenac, Voltaren Emulgel (2%)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Voltarol oral tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 2: Diclofenac, Voltarol oral tablet (50 mg)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: DCF100 Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 2: DCF100 matching placebo gel</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: SPR300 gel (15%:7%)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 3: Methyl-salicylate / Menthol, SPR300 gel (15%:7%, w/w; ratio of Methylsalicylate / Menthol)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: SPR300 Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 3: SPR300 matching placebo gel</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibuprofen</intervention_name>
    <description>Single topical dose per 1.76 cm2 test site of: 22 microliters (μL) (20 ± l mg)* of TIB200 Gel (ibuprofen 10% w/w) (Test Gel) or 22 μL (20 ± l mg)* of matching placebo TIB200 Gel (placebo gel) or 22 μL (20 ± l mg)* of Nurofen Maximum Strength Gel (ibuprofen 10% w/w) (reference gel).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: TIB200 gel 10%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Nurofen gel 10%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Nurofen tablets</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nurofen Max Strength gel (10%, w/w)</other_name>
    <other_name>Ibuprofen, Nurofen, oral tablets (2 x 200 mg)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diclofenac</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects were randomised to receive 22 uL (20 ± l mg) DCF100 Gel (diclofenac 2% w/w) / DCF100 Gel (diclofenac 4% w/w) / Matching Placebo DCF100 Gel / Voltarol® 12 Hour Emulgel® P 2.32% Gel. The gels were administered topically on two test sites on the lower back of the subject, each 1.76 cm2 in size. The two test sites were UVB irradiated on the previous day, between 22 and 26 hours (24 ± 2 hours) before dosing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: DCF100 gel 2%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: DCF100 gel 4%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Voltaren gel 2%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Voltarol oral tablet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Voltaren Emulgel (2.32%, w/w)</other_name>
    <other_name>Voltarol 50 mg, oral tablet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methyl-salicylate / Menthol</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects were randomised to receive 22 uL (20 ± l mg) SPR300 Gel / Matching Placebo SPR300 Gel. The gels were administered topically on two test sites on the lower back of the subject, each 1.76cm2 in size. The two test sites were UVB irradiated on the previous day, between 22 and 26 hours (24 ± 2 hours) before dosing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: SPR300 gel (15%:7%)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SPR300</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo gels were administered topically on two test sites on the lower back of the subject, each 1.76 cm2 in size. The two test sites were UVB irradiated on the previous day, between 22 and 26 hours (24 ± 2 hours) before dosing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: TIB200 Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: DCF100 Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: SPR300 Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TIB200 Placebo, DCF100 Placebo and SPR300 Placebo gels</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Were able to provide written informed consent.

          2. Male between 18 and 65 years old, inclusive, at the time of screening.

          3. Good general health as ascertained by detailed medical history and physical
             examination.

          4. Body mass index (BMI) ≥18 and ≤29 kg/m2 (BMI = weight/height2), at the time of
             screening.

          5. No clinically relevant abnormalities in 12-lead ECG as per PI's judgement, e.g.,
             absence of cardiac rhythm disorder, in particular bradycardia (&lt;40 beats per minute),
             conduction abnormalities such as atrioventricular block, absence of active ischemia
             (such as unstable angina pectoris) or recent myocardial infarction, no QTcF interval
             &gt;450 milliseconds, no QRS complex ≥120 milliseconds, at Screening.

          6. No clinically relevant abnormalities in results of laboratory tests as per PI's
             judgement; in particular, no significant liver impairment defined as aspartate
             aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) 1.5x upper limit of normal
             (ULN); no significant kidney impairment defined as serum creatinine 2x ULN; abnormal
             thyroid function as defined by thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) and total thyroxin
             (T4) (TSH within range 0.27 to 4.2 mIU/L, total T4 within range 59 to 154 nmol/L).

          7. Had a skin type II or III (Fitz Patrick classification).

          8. Non-smokers or ex-smokers for at least 6 months prior to the Screening Visit, as
             confirmed by a urine cotinine test.

          9. Subjects were able to communicate well with the PI/designee. -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of hypersensitivity to the IMP or any of the excipients or to medicinal
             products with similar chemical structures.

          2. Presence of any clinically relevant acute or chronic disease which could interfere
             with the subject safety during the study, expose the subject to undue risk, limit the
             biological sampling (e.g., blood collection), interfere with the absorption of the IMP
             (e.g., active dermatological conditions at the application sites, or ulcers, irritable
             bowel syndrome) or interfere with the study objectives.

          3. Skin type I, IV, V or VI (Fitzpatrick Classification).

          4. History of chronic pain symptoms (&gt;6 months) or ongoing pain.

          5. Any condition that required regular concomitant medication including herbal products,
             or predicted need of any concomitant medication from Screening Visit until the end of
             the study.

          6. Intake of any medication including over the counter (OTC) medication (in particular
             any pain killers), herbal and dietary supplements such as St John's Wort, vitamins and
             minerals that could affect the outcome of the study, within 48 hours before the first
             administration of the investigational product and for the duration of the study.

          7. Use of photosensitising medication, such as phenothiazines, tetracyclines, quinolones,
             sulphonamides, nalidixic acid, non-steroidal anti-inflammatories, furosemides,
             hydrochlorothiazides, fibrate, phytotherapeutic drugs (herbal supplements),
             phenothiazines, quinidines, psoralens and amiodarone within 4 weeks before the first
             UVB irradiation and for the duration of the study.

          8. Any skin disease, acute or chronic (e.g., psoriasis vulgaris, neurodermatitis) or auto
             immune diseases associated with increased light sensitisation.

          9. Any active dermatological conditions, local pigmentary disorders, body art (e.g.,
             tattoos), or excessive hair growth at the lower back that might interfere with the
             study assessments or absorption of the IMP.

         10. History of skin cancer (i.e., melanoma, squamous cell carcinoma or basal cell
             carcinoma).

         11. History of conditions that increase risk for melanoma (e.g., dysplastic nevus [&gt;5
             nevi], xeroderma pigmentosum, Fanconi anaemia, Bloom's syndrome, Werner syndrome,
             Cockayne syndrome, trichothiodystrophy, or familial mole melanoma syndrome).

         12. History of bleeding disorders, peptic ulceration or gastro intestinal bleeding, heart
             burn, cardiovascular disease, myocardial infarction or stroke.

         13. Inability to give reproducible HPPT ratings on naïve skin at screening, (defined as
             HPTT test re-test difference ≥1.0 °C)

         14. Heat pain perception threshold &lt;40°C or &gt;51°C on naïve skin at Screening.

         15. Supine systolic blood pressure (SBP) &lt;90 mmHg or &gt;140 mmHg, or supine diastolic blood
             pressure (DBP) &lt;50 mmHg or &gt;90 mmHg after 5 minutes supine, at the Screening Visit.

         16. Positive test results for HBsAg, HCVAb or HIV-1 and/or -2 antibodies at Screening.

         17. Excessive use of caffeine-containing beverages exceeding 500 mg caffeine/day (5 cups
             of coffee) and the inability to refrain from the use of caffeine-containing beverages
             during confinement in the Clinical Unit.

         18. Excessive alcohol consumption (regular alcohol intake ≥21 units per week). Use of
             alcohol 48 hours before any study visit, as confirmed by urine alcohol testing at
             Screening, Day -2, and with any additional tests at the discretion of the PI.

         19. History in the last year or presence of drug addiction (positive urine drug screen) at
             Screening and Day -2.

         20. Presence or history of alcohol abuse in the last year, as confirmed by subject's
             general practitioner (GP).

         21. Blood donation within 8 weeks before the first IMP administration.

         22. Participation in another study with an experimental drug within 3 months before the
             first dosing day.

         23. Any psychological, emotional problems, any disorder or resultant therapy that was
             likely to invalidate informed consent, or limited the ability of the subject to comply
             with the protocol requirements.

         24. Unlikely to comply with the protocol requirements, instructions and study-related
             restrictions; e.g., uncooperative attitude, inability to return for Follow-up visits
             and improbability of completing the clinical study.

         25. Planned surgery, dental procedure, or hospitalisation from the Screening Visit until
             the end of the study.

         26. Inability to give written informed consent or to comply fully with the protocol.

         27. Subjects who, in the opinion of the PI, were considered unsuitable for any other
             reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Annelize Koch, MBChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>PAREXEL Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PAREXEL EPCU Northwick Park</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harrow</city>
        <state>Middlesex</state>
        <zip>HA1 3UJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>UVB Pain Model</keyword>
  <keyword>PK</keyword>
  <keyword>Topical</keyword>
  <keyword>NSAIDs</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ibuprofen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diclofenac</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Salicylates</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyl salicylate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Menthol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

