<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02669251</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>160060</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>16-C-0060</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02669251</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AZD9668, an Oral Neutrophil Elastase Inhibitor, in Bronchiolitis Obliterans Syndrome After Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b/2 Study of AZD9668, an Oral Neutrophil Elastase Inhibitor, in Bronchiolitis Obliterans Syndrome After Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Bronchiolitis obliterans syndrome (BOS) is a complication people can experience after
      hematopoietic stem cell transplant. It usually affects people with chronic graft versus host
      disease (cGVHD). This occurs when donor stem cells attack the cells of the person who
      received them. BOS reduces airflow and oxygen levels in the body. It may be caused by
      neutrophil elastase in the body. Researchers believe the new drug AZD9668 may help.

      Objectives:

      To test the safety of AZD9668 and see what dose best inhibits neutrophil elastase in people
      with BOS after a stem cell transplant. To study how well the best dose improves lung function
      in those people.

      Eligibility:

      Adults 18 and older who have had a hematopoietic stem cell transplant and have cGVHD and BOS.

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with a medical history, physical exam, and blood and urine
      tests. They will have lung function and heart function tests. They will have computed
      tomography scans of the chest.

      Study part 1: Participants will take the starting dose of the study drug by mouth twice a day
      for 14 days. This is 1 cycle. They will get different doses, for up to 4 cycles.

      Study part 2: Participants will take the study drug twice a day by mouth at the dose set in
      part 1, for up to 12 months.

      Participants will keep medicine diaries.

      Participants will have several study visits. These may include:

      Repeats of the screening tests.

      Bronchoscopy with bronchoalveolar lavage.

      Sputum samples taken.

      6-minute walking test.

      cGVHD assessment and answer questions.

      Participants will be contacted after the study for up to 24 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Chronic graft-versus-host disease (cGVHD) is the leading cause of non-relapse morbidity
           and mortality in persons after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (SCT).

        -  Bronchiolitis obliterans syndrome (BOS) is a complication of cGVHD associated with a
           high morbidity and mortality, and treatment options are limited.

        -  Neutrophil elastase (NE) is a protease released by neutrophils in the setting of
           inflammation, and has been implicated in the pathogenesis of BOS.

        -  AZD9668 is a potent and selective inhibitor of NE that has demonstrated evidence of
           target inhibition and a good safety profile in patients with inflammatory lung diseases,
           but has not been evaluated in BOS.

      Objectives:

      Phase 1b:

      To determine the optimal biologic dose (OBD) based on maximal NE inhibition measured in
      blood, and to determine the safety of AZD9668 in patients with BOS after SCT

      Phase 2:

      To determine the clinical efficacy of AZD9668 at the OBD in patients with BOS after SCT,
      based on the proportion of patients with stable or improved forced expiratory volume in 1
      second (FEV1) on pulmonary function testing

      Eligibility:

      Inclusion criteria:

        -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years

        -  BOS after SCT and moderate to severe cGVHD as defined by the NIH consensus criteria

        -  Within 2 years from the time of diagnosis (Phase 2 only)

        -  Karnofsky performance status greater than or equal to 60%

        -  If on systemic cGVHD therapy, must be receiving stable or tapering doses in the
           preceding 4 weeks

        -  Patients will be required to have received prior treatment with azithromycin for at
           least 3 months prior to enrollment, unless there is evidence of progression or
           unsatisfactory response while on azithromycin prior to 3 months of treatment, as deemed
           by the treating or referring physician.

        -  Patients who are on azithromycin, an antibiotic used in the treatment of BOS, will need
           to discontinue for at least 2 weeks prior to enrollment

      Exclusion criteria:

        -  FEV1 &lt; 30% (based on absolute percent predicted using USA-ITS-NIH equation) on pulmonary
           function testing

        -  Prior use of neutrophil elastase inhibitors

        -  Progressive malignancy

        -  Uncontrolled infection or any major organ dysfunction as defined by the protocol

      Design:

      Phase 1b:

        -  This is a Phase 1b trial to determine the OBD and safety of AZD9668 in patients with BOS
           after SCT.

        -  This trial will use an intra-patient dose escalation schedule. The starting dose will be
           60mg twice daily for 2 weeks, and the dose will be increased by 60mg with each
           escalation every 2 weeks until a maximum dose of 240mg twice daily is reached for a
           total treatment period of 8 weeks. After completion of the dose escalation phase,
           patients will have the option to continue the dose at which maximal NE inhibition and
           safety are demonstrated for up to 6 additional months.

        -  The co-primary endpoint of OBD will be defined as the dose level at which the maximal NE
           inhibition occurs, and at which no more than 1/3 of patients experience a DLT. NE
           activity will be measured in the blood at baseline and with each dose escalation, and
           will be compared between dose levels to determine the OBD.

        -  The co-primary endpoint of safety will be determined by monitoring adverse events and
           dose limiting toxicities (DLT) as defined by the protocol. Further dose escalation will
           cease in a patient who experiences a DLT. In addition, no subsequent patients will be
           treated at or beyond the dose in which 1/3 of patients have experienced a DLT.

        -  A total of 10 patients will be enrolled in the Phase 1b trial.

      Phase 2:

        -  This is a Phase 2 trial to determine the efficacy of AZD9668 at the OBD in patients with
           BOS after SCT, as measured by stabilization or improvement of FEV1 (based on absolute
           percent predicted) after 6 months of treatment.

        -  Patients will receive AZD9668 at the OBD determined in the Phase 1b trial, and pulmonary
           function testing with measurement of FEV1 will be performed to determine the primary
           endpoint.

        -  Response assessments will occur every 3 months with primary efficacy endpoint evaluated
           at 6 months. Patients with stable or responding disease will have the option to continue
           therapy for another 6 months.

        -  As an early stopping rule for futility, if 0-2 of the first 8 patients enrolled have
           responded, then no further patients will be accrued. While up to10 patients may be
           required for the Phase 1b portion of the trial and 20 patients may be needed for
           evaluation in phase II, in order to allow for a small number of inevaluable patients,
           the accrual ceiling will be set at 34 patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 29, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimal biologic dose (OBD) based on maximal NE inhibition measured in sputum</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after study drug initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Dose-finding.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the clinical efficacy of AZD9668 at the OBD in patients with BOS after SCT</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>determine the safety of AZD9668</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after study drug initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Safety.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1b and 2: Pharmacokinetics of blood and sputum</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1b: Baseline, first day of each cycle at dose escalation. Phase 2: Baseline, C1D1, C3D1, C6D1.</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacokinetics of study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1B: Correlation of NE activity in blood with sputum measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1B: Correlation of NE activity in blood with sputum measurements</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy/drug effect on laboratory values.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1B and 2: Determine the impact on lung inflammatorymarkers based on levels in blood, sputum and BAL fluid</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1b: Baseline, 8 wees. Phase 2: Baseline, 3 months and 6 months (end of treatment).</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy/drug effect on laboratory values.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: Efficacy testing via NIH Lung Symptom Score, 6 minutewalk test, survival, FEV1 slope measured from baseline, and otherPFT measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, C1D1, D4D1, C7D1, c10D1, Off treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1B and 2: Determine effect on patient-reported outcomes viaLee cGVHD Symptom Scale, HAP, FACT-BMT</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1B: C1D1, D1 of continuation phase, D1 of Cycle 11+, Off treatment. Phase 2: Baseline, D1 of C7-12, Off treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of patient-reported outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: Determine effect on markers of target inhibition insputum and blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months (end of treatment) or off study.</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy/drug effect on laboratory values.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Graft vs Host Disease</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Graft-Versus-Host-Disease</condition>
  <condition>Bronchiolitis Obliterans Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase Ib dose escalation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MTD po bid on days 1-28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AZD9668</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase 1b Cycle= 14 days: Each dose level will increase by 60mg PO BID, up to a maximum of 240mg PO BID
Phase 2 Cycle=28 days: MTD PO BID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients must have undergone hematopoietic stem cell transplantation and have moderate
             to severe chronic GVHD as defined by the NIH consensus criteria.

          -  Patients must have BOS as defined by the NIH consensus criteria (2014 updated
             criteria). To meet the criteria for BOS, all of the following must be present, in
             addition to at least one distinctive manifestation of cGVHD:

               -  FEV1/vital capacity &lt;0.7 or the fifth percentile of predicted

               -  FEV1 &lt;75% of predicted with greater than or equal to 10% decline over less than 2
                  years. FEV1 should not correct to &gt;75% with albuterol, and the absolute decline
                  for the corrected values should still remain at greater than or equal to 10% from
                  pre-translplant

               -  Absence of infection in the respiratory tract

               -  One of the 2 supporting features of BOS:

                    1. Evidence of air trapping by expiratory CT or small airway thickening or
                       bronchiectasis by high-resolution CT, or

                    2. Evidence of air trapping by PFTs: residual volume &gt;120% predicted or
                       residual volume/total lung capacity elevated outside the 90% confidence
                       interval.

        If a patient carries the diagnosis of cGVHD by virtue of organ involvement elsewhere, then
        only the first 3 criteria above are necessary.

          -  For the Phase 1b study, patients may have had the diagnosis of BOS for any period of
             time. For the Phase 2 study, patients must be within 2 years from the time of
             diagnosis. Patients may be at any time interval after SCT as long as the criteria for
             chronic GVHD and BOS are met.

          -  If patients are taking systemic therapy for cGVHD at the time of enrollment, they must
             be receiving stable or tapering doses within the previous 4 weeks. Patients are not
             required to have completed a course of steroids prior to enrollment.

          -  Age greater than or equal to18 years.

          -  Karnofsky greater than or equal to 60%

          -  Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  leukocytes greater than or equal to 3,000/mcL

               -  absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1,000/mcL

               -  platelets greater than or equal to 50,000/mcL

               -  total bilirubin less than or equal to 3 X institutional upper limit of normal,
                  unless there is a known history of Gilbert s disease

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) less than or equal to 2 X institutional upper limit of normal

               -  -serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 mg/dL or creatinine clearance greater
                  than or equal to 60 mL/min as estimated by the Cockcroft-Gault equation

          -  Patients will be required to have received prior treatment with azithromycin for at
             least 3 months prior to enrollment, unless there is evidence of progression or
             unsatisfactory response while on azithromycin prior to 3 months of treatment, as
             deemed by the treating or referring physician. Patients who are on azithromycin will
             need to discontinue for at least 2 weeks prior to enrollment

          -  Agree to adhere to methods of contraception and other fertility control measures:

        The effects of AZD9668 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason, women of
        child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or
        barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of
        study therapy. Contraception should be used up until 1 week of discontinuing study
        medication. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she is
        participating in this study, or if a man s partner becomes pregnant or suspects she is
        pregnant while he is participating in this study, she or he should inform their treating
        physician immediately.

        -Ability of subject to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
        document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  FEV1 &lt;30% (based on absolute percent predicted using USA-ITS-NIH equation) on
             pulmonary function testing

          -  Patients with clinically relevant abnormal ECG findings, including abnormal QTc&gt;500 ms
             on screening ECG (Note: If a patient has a QTc interval &gt;500 ms on screening ECG, the
             screening ECG may be repeated twice [at least 24 hours apart] for a total of 3 ECGs).

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Recurrent or progressive malignancy requiring anticancer treatment

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, acute kidney injury, or psychiatric illness/social situations within the
             previous 4 weeks that would limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because the teratogenic effects of AZD9668
             are unknown. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse events in
             nursing infants secondary to treatment of the mother with AZD9668, breastfeeding
             should be discontinued if the mother is treated with this agent.

          -  Prior use of neutrophil elastase inhibitors
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Z Pavletic, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven Z Pavletic, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6174</phone>
    <email>sp326h@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2016-C-0060.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 7, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Optimal Biologic Dose</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Graft-Versus-Host Disease (cGVHD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory Lung Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>FEV1</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchiolitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchiolitis Obliterans</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Proteinase Inhibitory Proteins, Secretory</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

