<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02666508</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-0620</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02666508</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Toothpaste to Reduce Plaque and Inflammation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial of Plaque Identifying Toothpaste on Reduction of Plaque and Inflammation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Illinois at Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Florida Atlantic University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Illinois at Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dental plaque causes caries and periodontal disease and data are sparse about toothpaste and
      plaque removal. Inflammation, caused by dental plaque, is a risk factor for cardiovascular
      disease. (CVD) The availability of (Plaque HD (TM), a plaque identifying toothpaste with
      targetol technology (TM)), afforded the unique opportunity to test whether there were
      statistically significant and clinically important reductions in plaque and inflammation in a
      randomized trial of apparently healthy individuals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Board of the University of Illinois and
      the trial was posted on ClinicalTrials.gov. We screened all potentially eligible subjects
      from the Medical District of the University of Illinois which includes the Colleges of
      Dentistry, Medicine, Public Health and Pharmacy.

      All willing and eligible subjects signed informed consent forms and were instructed to
      refrain from brushing or flossing teeth, using any oral hygiene aids (such as mouthwash or
      chewing gum) the evening prior to and the morning of the data collection appointment. All
      subjects were be asked to complete the following procedures:

        1. Rinse for 10 seconds with 25 mL of phosphate buffer

        2. Rinse for 1 minute with 5.0 mL of 1240-ppm fluorescein in phosphate buffer

        3. Rinse 3 times (for 10 seconds) with 25mL of phosphate buffer

        4. Be positioned on a tripod chin rest 15 inches in front of the camera, retraction placed
           and intraoral images captured under UV LED light imaging.

        5. Provide a blood sample for hs-CRP.

        6. Use a 30 day supply of their assigned toothpaste and were instructed to follow the same
           brushing protocol for the entire month as well as a brushing diary to assist in
           recording daily participation.

      The identical procedures were repeated at the 30 day follow up visit.. In addition, the
      Plaque HD group was instructed to brush in front of a mirror for 1 minute and to concentrate
      on removing all visible dye. The placebo group was asked to brush their teeth for 1 minute in
      front of a mirror, using the provided manual toothbrush.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in oral plaque</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>mean plaque score</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>30 day</time_frame>
    <description>hs-CRP serum level</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Plaque</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plaque identifying toothpaste</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 30 day supply of daily syringes containing a plaque identifying toothpaste with targetol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-plaque identifying toothpaste</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 30 day supply of daily syringes containing an identical non plaque identifying toothpaste without targetol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plaque identifying toothpaste</intervention_name>
    <description>Plaque identifying toothpaste with targetol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Plaque identifying toothpaste</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-plaque identifying toothpaste</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-plaque identifying toothpaste without targetol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-plaque identifying toothpaste</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The inclusion criteria were as follows:

          -  Apparently healthy men and women age 19-45 with no history of CVD

          -  All 12 anterior teeth present (canine to canine in both upper and lower arches)

          -  English speaking

          -  Ability to commit to two 30 minute appointments These appointment must be 1 month
             apart)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  • Student, faculty or staff with a clinical role at the University of Illinois College
             of Dentistry

          -  Individuals taking aspirin, other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or statins.

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing

          -  Women taking birth control pills or using any hormone released birth control device

          -  Women on hormone replacement therapy

          -  Individuals who have taken antibiotics within two weeks of data collection appointment

          -  Individuals experiencing xerostomia

          -  Individuals who have experienced an illness, infection or tissue injury within two
             weeks of data collection appointment

          -  Individuals with arthritis, lupus or other chronic inflammatory conditions or
             syndromes

          -  Individuals with allergies to dyes or over the counter products

          -  Individuals who have missing anterior teeth, fixed or removable appliances or visible
             decay or staining in the anterior region (canine to canine in both upper and lower
             arches)

          -  Individuals whom have had a dental prophylaxis within 30 days of the data collection
             visit

          -  Individuals who have had a new restoration placed (anywhere in the oral cavity) within
             30 days of the data collection visit
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kimberly Fasula, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Illinois at Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kimberly Fasula, MS</last_name>
    <phone>312-996-5513</phone>
    <email>kfasul1@uic.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UIC Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maryann Holtcamp, RN, APN</last_name>
      <phone>312-996-2937</phone>
      <email>mholt@uic.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kimberly Fasula, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/cardiovascular_diseases/en/</url>
    <description>The World Health Organization. Cardiovascular Diseases (CVDs)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/General/Heart-and-Stroke-Association-Statistics_UCM_319064_SubHomePage.jsp.</url>
    <description>American Heart Association. Heart and Stroke Statistics.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.adha.org/research-center</url>
    <description>American Dental Hygienist's Association. Research center.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cdc.gov/HeartDisease/facts.htm</url>
    <description>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Heart Disease Facts. www.cdc.gov/HeartDisease/facts.htm.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sciencedirect.com.proxy.cc.uic.edu/science/article/pii/S0003996911003876</url>
    <description>Relationship between serum antibody titres to porphyromonas gingivalis and hs-CRP levels as inflammatory markers of periodontitis.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://labtestsonline.org/understanding/analytes/hscrp/tab/test</url>
    <description>Hs-CRP: The test | high-sensitivity C-reactive protein; hs-CRP test: High-sensitivity C-reactive protein | lab tests online.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nlm.nih.gov/hsrinfo/grantsites.html</url>
    <description>HSRIC: Grants, funding and fellowships.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim YH, Lee SY. Identification of non-streptococcal organisms from human dental plaque grown on the Streptococcus-selective medium mitis-salivarius agar. Arch Oral Biol. 2015 Feb;60(2):267-71. doi: 10.1016/j.archoralbio.2014.11.002. Epub 2014 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>25463904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Oliveira C, Watt R, Hamer M. Toothbrushing, inflammation, and risk of cardiovascular disease: results from Scottish Health Survey. BMJ. 2010 May 27;340:c2451. doi: 10.1136/bmj.c2451.</citation>
    <PMID>20508025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kholy KE, Genco RJ, Van Dyke TE. Oral infections and cardiovascular disease. Trends Endocrinol Metab. 2015 Jun;26(6):315-21. doi: 10.1016/j.tem.2015.03.001. Epub 2015 Apr 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25892452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mbawalla HS, Masalu JR, Astrøm AN. Socio-demographic and behavioural correlates of oral hygiene status and oral health related quality of life, the Limpopo-Arusha school health project (LASH): a cross-sectional study. BMC Pediatr. 2010 Nov 30;10:87. doi: 10.1186/1471-2431-10-87.</citation>
    <PMID>21118499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gundala R, Chava VK. Effect of lifestyle, education and socioeconomic status on periodontal health. Contemp Clin Dent. 2010 Jan;1(1):23-6. doi: 10.4103/0976-237X.62516.</citation>
    <PMID>22114373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Anezi SA, Harradine NW. Quantifying plaque during orthodontic treatment:. Angle Orthod. 2012 Jul;82(4):748-53. doi: 10.2319/050111-312.1. Epub 2011 Nov 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22044115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter K, Landini G, Walmsley AD. Automated quantification of dental plaque accumulation using digital imaging. J Dent. 2004 Nov;32(8):623-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15476956</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Short VL, Ivory-Walls T, Smith L, Loustalot F. The Mississippi Delta Cardiovascular Health Examination Survey: Study Design and Methods. Epidemiol Res Int. 2014 Jan 1;2014(Article 499 861461):861461.</citation>
    <PMID>25844257</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mozaffarian D, Benjamin EJ, Go AS, Arnett DK, Blaha MJ, Cushman M, de Ferranti S, Després JP, Fullerton HJ, Howard VJ, Huffman MD, Judd SE, Kissela BM, Lackland DT, Lichtman JH, Lisabeth LD, Liu S, Mackey RH, Matchar DB, McGuire DK, Mohler ER 3rd, Moy CS, Muntner P, Mussolino ME, Nasir K, Neumar RW, Nichol G, Palaniappan L, Pandey DK, Reeves MJ, Rodriguez CJ, Sorlie PD, Stein J, Towfighi A, Turan TN, Virani SS, Willey JZ, Woo D, Yeh RW, Turner MB; American Heart Association Statistics Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Heart disease and stroke statistics--2015 update: a report from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2015 Jan 27;131(4):e29-322. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000152. Epub 2014 Dec 17. Erratum in: Circulation. 2016 Feb 23;133(8):e417. Circulation. 2015 Jun 16;131(24):e535.</citation>
    <PMID>25520374</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson KM, Odell PM, Wilson PW, Kannel WB. Cardiovascular disease risk profiles. Am Heart J. 1991 Jan;121(1 Pt 2):293-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1985385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loos BG, Craandijk J, Hoek FJ, Wertheim-van Dillen PM, van der Velden U. Elevation of systemic markers related to cardiovascular diseases in the peripheral blood of periodontitis patients. J Periodontol. 2000 Oct;71(10):1528-34.</citation>
    <PMID>11063384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Danesh J, Wheeler JG, Hirschfield GM, Eda S, Eiriksdottir G, Rumley A, Lowe GD, Pepys MB, Gudnason V. C-reactive protein and other circulating markers of inflammation in the prediction of coronary heart disease. N Engl J Med. 2004 Apr 1;350(14):1387-97.</citation>
    <PMID>15070788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramamoorthy RD, Nallasamy V, Reddy R, Esther N, Maruthappan Y. A review of C-reactive protein: A diagnostic indicator in periodontal medicine. J Pharm Bioallied Sci. 2012 Aug;4(Suppl 2):S422-6. doi: 10.4103/0975-7406.100318.</citation>
    <PMID>23066303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>D'Aiuto F, Parkar M, Andreou G, Suvan J, Brett PM, Ready D, Tonetti MS. Periodontitis and systemic inflammation: control of the local infection is associated with a reduction in serum inflammatory markers. J Dent Res. 2004 Feb;83(2):156-60.</citation>
    <PMID>14742655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noack B, Genco RJ, Trevisan M, Grossi S, Zambon JJ, De Nardin E. Periodontal infections contribute to elevated systemic C-reactive protein level. J Periodontol. 2001 Sep;72(9):1221-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11577954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ridker PM, Hennekens CH, Buring JE, Rifai N. C-reactive protein and other markers of inflammation in the prediction of cardiovascular disease in women. N Engl J Med. 2000 Mar 23;342(12):836-43.</citation>
    <PMID>10733371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ridker PM, Cushman M, Stampfer MJ, Tracy RP, Hennekens CH. Inflammation, aspirin, and the risk of cardiovascular disease in apparently healthy men. N Engl J Med. 1997 Apr 3;336(14):973-9. Erratum in: N Engl J Med 1997 Jul 31;337(5):356.</citation>
    <PMID>9077376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pepys MB, Hirschfield GM. C-reactive protein: a critical update. J Clin Invest. 2003 Jun;111(12):1805-12. Review. Erratum in: J Clin Invest. 2003 Jul;112(2):299.</citation>
    <PMID>12813013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Dyke TE, van Winkelhoff AJ. Infection and inflammatory mechanisms. J Clin Periodontol. 2013 Apr;40 Suppl 14:S1-7. doi: 10.1111/jcpe.12088. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23627321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim HC, Yang DM, Lee CM, Jin W, Nam DH, Song JY, Kim JY. Acute appendicitis: relationships between CT-determined severities and serum white blood cell counts and C-reactive protein levels. Br J Radiol. 2011 Dec;84(1008):1115-20. doi: 10.1259/bjr/47699219. Epub 2010 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21123307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pejcic A, Kesic LJ, Milasin J. C-reactive protein as a systemic marker of inflammation in periodontitis. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2011 Mar;30(3):407-14. doi: 10.1007/s10096-010-1101-1. Epub 2010 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>21057970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cusumano CA. Periodontal disease associated with an increased CRP in chronic hemodialysis patients. Rev Nefrol Dial Trans. 2013; 33:188-195.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loos BG. Systemic markers of inflammation in periodontitis. J Periodontol. 2005 Nov;76(11 Suppl):2106-15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16277583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tonetti MS. Periodontitis and risk for atherosclerosis: an update on intervention trials. J Clin Periodontol. 2009 Jul;36 Suppl 10:15-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2009.01417.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19432627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Persson GR, Persson RE. Cardiovascular disease and periodontitis: an update on the associations and risk. J Clin Periodontol. 2008 Sep;35(8 Suppl):362-79. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2008.01281.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18724863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goyal L, Bey A, Gupta ND, Sharma VK. Comparative evaluation of serum C-reactive protein levels in chronic and aggressive periodontitis patients and association with periodontal disease severity. Contemp Clin Dent. 2014 Oct;5(4):484-8. doi: 10.4103/0976-237X.142816.</citation>
    <PMID>25395764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar KR, Ranganath V, Naik R, Banu S, Nichani AS. Assessment of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein and lipid levels in healthy adults and patients with coronary artery disease, with and without periodontitis--a cross-sectional study. J Periodontal Res. 2014 Dec;49(6):836-44. doi: 10.1111/jre.12172. Epub 2014 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24620793</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anitha G, Nagaraj M, Jayashree A. Comparative evaluation of levels of C-reactive protein and PMN in periodontitis patients related to cardiovascular disease. J Indian Soc Periodontol. 2013 May;17(3):330-2. doi: 10.4103/0972-124X.115657.</citation>
    <PMID>24049333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zijnge V, van Leeuwen MB, Degener JE, Abbas F, Thurnheer T, Gmür R, Harmsen HJ. Oral biofilm architecture on natural teeth. PLoS One. 2010 Feb 24;5(2):e9321. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0009321.</citation>
    <PMID>20195365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen T, Yu WH, Izard J, Baranova OV, Lakshmanan A, Dewhirst FE. The Human Oral Microbiome Database: a web accessible resource for investigating oral microbe taxonomic and genomic information. Database (Oxford). 2010 Jul 6;2010:baq013. doi: 10.1093/database/baq013.</citation>
    <PMID>20624719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bokhari SA, Khan AA, Butt AK, Azhar M, Hanif M, Izhar M, Tatakis DN. Non-surgical periodontal therapy reduces coronary heart disease risk markers: a randomized controlled trial. J Clin Periodontol. 2012 Nov;39(11):1065-74. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2012.01942.x. Epub 2012 Sep 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22966824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kajikawa M, Nakashima A, Maruhashi T, Iwamoto Y, Iwamoto A, Matsumoto T, Hidaka T, Kihara Y, Chayama K, Goto C, Taguchi A, Noma K, Higashi Y. Poor oral health, that is, decreased frequency of tooth brushing, is associated with endothelial dysfunction. Circ J. 2014;78(4):950-4. Epub 2014 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24500034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mani A, Vadvadgi V, Anarthe R, Saini R, Mani S. A clinical study on Dental Air Force Cleaning System on adult chronic periodontits and its assessment to C-reactive protein levels. Int J Exp Dent Sci. 2012; 1:14-18.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harnacke D, Winterfeld T, Erhardt J, Schlueter N, Ganss C, Margraf-Stiksrud J, Deinzer R. What is the best predictor for oral cleanliness after brushing? Results from an observational cohort study. J Periodontol. 2015 Jan;86(1):101-7. doi: 10.1902/jop.2014.140152.</citation>
    <PMID>25186778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stevens K, Belavsky B, Evans CA, Viana MG, Wu C. Evaluation of plaque removal efficacy of a novel dye-containing toothpaste: a clinical trial. Int J Dentistry Oral Sci. 2016; 3(1):185-189</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Illinois at Chicago</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kim Fasula</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Clinic Operations &amp; Clinical Instructor, College of Dentistry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>plaque identifying toothpaste</keyword>
  <keyword>plaque score</keyword>
  <keyword>C-reactive protein</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 13, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>April 21, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>May 11, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>December 22, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

