<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02662673</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-817</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02662673</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Focal Treatments of Localized Prostate Cancers With High Intensity Focused Ultrasound Using the Focal One® Device</brief_title>
  <acronym>IDITOP-3</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Focal Treatments of Localized Prostate Cancers With High Intensity Focused Ultrasound Using the Focal One® Device</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospices Civils de Lyon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospices Civils de Lyon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Focal treatment of localized prostate cancer aims to destroy the cancerous foci without
      damaging surrounding tissues to avoid the side effects of radical treatments. This is why
      focal treatment is positioned as an alternative to radical surgery as well as an alternative
      to active surveillance.

      This study is a feasibility study. It aims at treating the index tumor (the most aggressive
      one) which determines the vital prognosis of patient, while preserving the maximum
      surrounding prostatic tissue to preserve quality of life. The expected result is the total
      destruction of aggressive tumor areas by focal or multifocal treatment strategy using the
      Focal One® device (EDAP-TMS, Vaulx-en-Velin, France). The tumor destruction is validated by
      the negative biopsy rate between 6 and 12 months post-treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 13, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 23, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Negative Biopsy Rate in the treated area</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 6 to 12 months after treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of positive biopsy rate in the untreated areas</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 6 to 12 months after treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 and 24 months after treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) level evolution after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prostate Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 2 years(s)</time_frame>
    <description>International Prostate Symptoms Score (IPSS) questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continence</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 2 years(s)</time_frame>
    <description>International Continence Society (ICS) questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Erectile Function</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 2 years(s)</time_frame>
    <description>International Index Erectile Function (IIEF-5) questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 2 years(s)</time_frame>
    <description>European Organization for Research and Treatment Quality of Life Questionnaire C30 (EORTC QLQ-C30) questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Localized Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Localized prostate cancer, Focal treatment.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Focal High Intensity Focused Ultrasound (HIFU) treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Focal High Intensity Focused Ultrasound (HIFU) treatment for localized prostate cancer (maximum two foci). HIFU treatment is using high energy ultrasound focused at the focal point to achieve precise tissue destruction. This mini-invasive therapy is using an endo-rectal approach to deliver the treatment, using a probe composed of a combined imaging and treatment transducer. The treatment is monitored by real-time ultrasound. The treatment planning is performed by the urologist, contouring the area to be treated (MRI target + security margins around the tumor) and the treatment phase is automatically performed by the robotic device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Localized prostate cancer, Focal treatment.</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 50 and 80 years (inclusive) with a life expectancy of more than 5 years.

          -  PSA ≤ 10 ng / mL.

          -  Initial diagnosis of localized prostate cancer (stage T1 or T2).

          -  Diagnosis confirmed by a multiparametric MRI and subsequent systematic and targeted
             prostate biopsies (at least 12 sextant biopsies and two biopsies per MRI target).

          -  Identification of a primary cancer site (index tumor) possibly associated with a
             second independent tumor (accessory tumor), provided that these tumors are separated
             by a sextant or the median line.

          -  Maximum two cancer foci, each one fulfilling the following conditions

          -  Gleason score of 6 AND biopsy invasion length ≥5 mm,

          -  OR Gleason score of 6 AND corresponding focal lesion on MRI with a PIRADS (Prostate
             Imaging Reporting and Data System) score ≥4/5 and a diameter ≥5 mm,

          -  OR Gleason score of 7 (3+4) whatever the biopsy invasion length or the MRI results may
             be.

          -  Patient with normal anal and rectal anatomy.

          -  Patient with a condition corresponding to an ASA (American Society of
             Anesthesiologists) classification 1 or 2.

          -  Patient for which treatment by focal HIFU (without performing an associated TURP) has
             been validated in Multidisciplinary meeting.

          -  Accepting patient monitoring constraints defined in the context of the study.

          -  Patient affiliated to health insurance or beneficiary a similar plan.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with ASA (American Society of Anesthesiologists) score 3.

          -  Patient clinical stage T3.

          -  Metastatic or distant (CT and/or MRI) lymph node.

          -  Patient with more than two cancer foci.

          -  Patients already treated for his prostate cancer (hormone therapy, radiotherapy,
             surgery).

          -  Patient having a distance between the rectal mucosa and the prostatic capsule over 8
             mm.

          -  History of inflammatory bowel disease, rectal or urinary tract fistula.

          -  History of pelvic radiotherapy.

          -  History of bladder cancer.

          -  History of sclerosis of the bladder neck or urethral stricture.

          -  Patient with an implant located at least 1 cm of the treatment zone (stent, catheter).

          -  Hemorrhagic risk patient.

          -  Urogenital infection in progress.

          -  Latex allergy.

          -  Allergy to sulfur hexafluoride or any of the other components of SonoVue®.

          -  Patients with recent acute coronary syndrome or unstable ischemic heart disease:
             myocardial infarction phase formation or evolution, typical angina at rest within last
             7 days, significant worsening of cardiac symptoms within last 7 days, recent
             intervention on the coronary arteries or other factors suggesting clinical instability
             (eg recent ECG changes, changes in clinical or laboratory parameters), acute heart
             failure, heart failure stage III or IV, or severe rhythm disorders (contra-indications
             to the use of SonoVue®).

          -  Patient with a right to left shunt, severe pulmonary hypertension (pulmonary artery
             pressure&gt; 90 mm Hg), uncontrolled systemic hypertension.

          -  Patient with respiratory distress syndrome.

          -  Patient with severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.

          -  Patient with acute endocarditis, prosthetic valve holder, acute systemic inflammation
             and / or sepsis, hyper coagulation status and / or recent thromboembolism.

          -  Patient on life support or suffering from unstable neurological diseases.

          -  Contra-indication for MRI (pacemakers, metal prosthesis, etc ...).

          -  Patient participating or having participated in another clinical study within the last
             30 days.

          -  Patient deprived of liberty following a judicial or administrative decision.

          -  Patient under guardianship or curatorship.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospices Civils de Lyon - Hôpital Edouard Herriot</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69003</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 25, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIFU</keyword>
  <keyword>Prostate Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Focal</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Index study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

