<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01876758</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>#6599</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01876758</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cognitive Training for Memory Deficits Associated With Electroconvulsive Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cognitive Training for Memory Deficits Associated With Electroconvulsive Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York State Psychiatric Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) remains the most effective treatment for people with
      severe depression, patients may experience a significant degree of persistent and/or
      permanent memory problems following ECT. Many patients report the memory problems are the
      most disturbing and serious side effect of ECT, and that such effects impact their quality of
      life following treatment and their willingness to consent to further ECT needed to complete a
      treatment course or to maintain remission. New developments in the field of cognitive
      remediation have demonstrated the benefits of cognitive training to improve memory
      performance in various conditions, such as epilepsy. However, these strategies have never
      been applied to help patients regain memory after ECT. The investigators have designed and
      piloted a novel cognitive program specifically targeted to the cognitive effects of ECT,
      based upon a program tailored to people with seizure disorders, a group with memory problems
      very similar to people who undergo ECT. This Memory Training for ECT (Mem-ECT) is designed to
      help cognitive functions that may be compromised following ECT remain relatively preserved.
      In addition, the intervention attempts to help ECT patients quickly regain their general
      memory skills immediately following ECT. Recent results from our preliminary group of
      patients who underwent ECT and memory training at New York Presbyterian shows no overall
      decline in memory function following ECT. On the basis of these promising findings, the
      investigators propose a more rigorous and larger study to confirm whether this novel memory
      training program can help alleviate memory problems associated with ECT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose to enroll 60 patients scheduled to undergo ECT over the course of 3
      years. They will be randomly assigned to one of three research conditions (a) participants in
      Mem-ECT condition will receive memory training before and after their ECT course, (b)
      participants in the active control condition will work on commercially available puzzle games
      at the same times prior and after ECT to determine if the developed memory training program
      is more effective than mere mental stimulation, (c) participants in the &quot;treatment as usual&quot;
      will not work on the memory training or the puzzle games but just undergo the study
      evaluations. Participants will be evaluated a few days before ECT, within 2 weeks following
      ECT, and once again 2 months later. The evaluation will consist of interviews, mental skill
      testing, and measuring brain waves using an electroencephalograph (EEG) before ECT and 2
      months after ECT (no EEG right after ECT). It is our hope that developing a safe and
      effective strategy to minimize the adverse memory side effects of ECT will make ECT a better
      and more easily tolerated treatment for patients with severe depression who need this
      therapeutic option.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia University Autobiographical Memory Interview-Short Form (AMI-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after the last ECT session</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Goldberg Remote Memory Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after the last ECT session</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression-24 item</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after the last ECT session</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Mini-Mental State examination</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after the last ECT session</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Memory Deficits</condition>
  <condition>Electroconvulsive Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Intervention: Memory Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Memory training before and after ECT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparable general mental stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Puzzle games before and after ECT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No memory training or puzzle games, just the study evaluations</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Intervention: Memory Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Paper-and-pencil and computerized exercises pre- and post-ECT which may be helpful in recovering episodic memories and allow for the retention of learned strategies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Intervention: Memory Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Comparable general mental stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Active control will work on commercially available puzzle games at the same time prior and after ECT to determine if the developed memory training program is more effective than mere mental stimulation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Comparable general mental stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Major Depressive Disorder

          -  Inpatient at NYSPI or Presbyterian Hospital

          -  Scheduled to undergo right-unilateral electroconvulsive therapy in the next two weeks

          -  We do not require participants to be psychiatrically stable in terms of their
             symptoms. They only need to demonstrate capacity to consent and be willing to sit
             through 3 training sessions prior to ECT and 5 sessions post ECT

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Significant auditory/visual impairment that would interfere with study procedures

          -  Lack of aptitude in English that may interfere with the administration of the tests

          -  Changes in the type of antidepressant during the course of ECT or 2 weeks post ECT

          -  Chart diagnosis of any other medical or neuropsychiatric illnesses known to impair
             brain function (e.g. mental retardation, traumatic brain injury, schizophrenia)

          -  History of ECT in past 2 months

          -  Mental status examination score below 40/57

          -  Current substance abuse (e.g. marijuana or crack), excluding nicotine and caffeine.

          -  Too agitated to sit through the required tests or training
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joan Prudic, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jimmy Choi, PsyD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York State Psychiatric Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Choi J, Lisanby SH, Medalia A, Prudic J. A conceptual introduction to cognitive remediation for memory deficits associated with right unilateral electroconvulsive therapy. J ECT. 2011 Dec;27(4):286-91. doi: 10.1097/YCT.0b013e31821d3ab3.</citation>
    <PMID>22080239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 3, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 13, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ECT</keyword>
  <keyword>Memory Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Remediation</keyword>
  <keyword>Electroconvulsive Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Resistant Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Geriatric Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Memory Loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Training</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Memory Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

