<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01875861</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SDP 08-375</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01875861</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Monitoring and Management for Metabolic Side Effects of Antipsychotics</brief_title>
  <acronym>AMMP</acronym>
  <official_title>Monitoring and Management for Metabolic Effects of Antipsychotics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test an approach for implementing guideline recommendations
      for assessing and managing metabolic side effects (including weight gain, diabetes, elevated
      lipids) in patients prescribed antipsychotic medications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Treatment of psychotic disorders consists primarily of antipsychotic medications, which are
      associated with metabolic side effects such as overweight/obesity, diabetes, and
      dyslipidemia. Expert consensus and evidence-based recommendations have been developed for
      assessment and management of these conditions; however, research studies show deficits and
      delays in metabolic monitoring for patients prescribed antipsychotics. This purpose of this
      study is to test a quality improvement intervention to enhance implementation of
      recommendations for assessing and managing metabolic side effects in patients prescribed
      antipsychotic medications.

      Study Objectives are:

        -  Objective 1: To test the effect of an Evidence-Based Quality Improvement/Facilitation
           (EBQI/F) intervention as an augmentation to a national implementation initiative on
           rates of monitoring for metabolic side effects of antipsychotics in sites likely to
           encounter greater challenges to implementation.

        -  Objective 2: To test the effect of the EBQI/F intervention as an augmentation to the
           national implementation initiative on management of metabolic side effects of
           antipsychotics in sites likely to encounter greater challenges to implementation.

        -  Objective 3: To assess the direct costs of the EBQI/F intervention, and explore
           potential variations in costs of the EBQI/F intervention in sites with lower versus
           higher organizational challenges.

      Methods This study employs a cluster randomized design with eligible study sites including VA
      Medical Centers with 300 patients receiving a new antipsychotic prescription in the first six
      months of FY08. Twelve sites have been recruited and matched according to level of
      organizational readiness-to-change. Randomization to intervention or control group was
      conducted within each of the six site-pairs. Study participants include VA employees involved
      in the monitoring and management of patients treated with antipsychotics at participating
      sites. The intervention involves researchers partnering with clinical stakeholders, offering
      tailoring in local implementation strategies to address barriers to metabolic side-effect
      monitoring and management. External facilitation to support, problem-solve and refine
      implementation will be provided for a six-month implementation phase. The effectiveness of
      the EBQI/F intervention combined with the ongoing national quality improvement initiative at
      six sites (intervention sites) will be compared to six matched comparison sites exposed to
      the national quality improvement initiative alone (control sites).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in site-level rates of weight monitoring at baseline (within 30 days of a new antipsychotic prescription)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in monitoring rates will be measured monthly through 6-month pre-implementation, implementation, and sustainability phases</time_frame>
    <description>For each monthly observation: The proportion of patients at each site due for weight monitoring at baseline who have weight recorded in the electronic health record.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in site-level rates of weight monitoring at follow-up (from 31-120 days after a new antipsychotic prescription)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in monitoring rates will be measured monthly through 6-month pre-implementation, implementation, and sustainability phases</time_frame>
    <description>For each monthly observation: The proportion of patients at each site due for weight monitoring at follow-up who have weight recorded in the electronic health record.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in site-level rates of management for obesity or weight gain within 30 days after a recording of BMI of 30 or greater, or 5% gain in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in weight management rates will be measured monthly through 6-month pre-implementation, implementation, and sustainability phases</time_frame>
    <description>For each monthly observation: The proportion of patients at each site with elevated BMI or weight gain that have guideline-recommended weight management (e.g., counseling about diet or exercise, referral to weight management program) initiated within 30 days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">103</enrollment>
  <condition>Mental Health</condition>
  <condition>Psychotic Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Evidence-Based Quality Improvement plus external facilitation to promote uptake of QI tools and improvement strategies available as part of a national initiative (the MIAMI Project) to disseminate recommendations, QI tools, and improvement strategies relevant to metabolic monitoring and management.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>&quot;Usual care,&quot; in the context of the MIAMI Project.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evidence-Based Quality Improvement Plus Facilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention involves researchers partnering with clinical stakeholders, offering tailoring in local implementation strategies to address barriers to metabolic side-effect monitoring and management. External facilitation to support, problem-solve and refine implementation will be provided for a six-month implementation phase.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EBQI/F</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Providers involved in antipsychotic management or management of metabolic side effects
        and related conditions

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard R. Owen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Central Arkansas Veterans Healthcare System Eugene J. Towbin Healthcare Center, Little Rock, AR</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Arkansas Veterans Healthcare System Eugene J. Towbin Healthcare Center, Little Rock, AR</name>
      <address>
        <city>No. Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72114-1706</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Helfrich CD, Blevins D, Smith JL, Kelly PA, Hogan TP, Hagedorn H, Dubbert PM, Sales AE. Predicting implementation from organizational readiness for change: a study protocol. Implement Sci. 2011 Jul 22;6:76. doi: 10.1186/1748-5908-6-76.</citation>
    <PMID>21777479</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Owen RR, Drummond KL, Viverito KM, Marchant K, Pope SK, Smith JL, Landes RD. Monitoring and managing metabolic effects of antipsychotics: a cluster randomized trial of an intervention combining evidence-based quality improvement and external facilitation. Implement Sci. 2013 Oct 8;8:120. doi: 10.1186/1748-5908-8-120.</citation>
    <PMID>24103648</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fortney JC, Owen RR. Increasing treatment engagement for persons with serious mental illness using personal health records. Am J Psychiatry. 2014 Mar;171(3):259-61. doi: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2013.13121701.</citation>
    <PMID>24585327</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cohen AN, Hamilton AB, Ritchie MJ, Mittman BS, Kirchner JE, Wyatt GE, Fortney JC, Hellemann G, Liu H, Curran GM, Whelan F, Eccles AM, Parker LE, McNagny K, Hutchinson CS, Teague AB, Reist C, Young AS. Improving care quality through hybrid implementation/effectiveness studies: Best practices in design, methods, and measures. [Abstract]. Implementation Science. 2015 Aug 20; 10(Suppl 1):A29.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 12, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 23, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 23, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 24, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Antipsychotic Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolic Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality Improvement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antipsychotic Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 14, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>January 10, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>January 16, 2018</submitted>
    <submission_canceled>Unknown</submission_canceled>
    <submitted>March 13, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

