<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01872702</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BAKMAL1305</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01872702</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeted Chemo-elimination (TCE) of Malaria</brief_title>
  <acronym>TME</acronym>
  <official_title>Targeted Chemo-elimination (TCE) to Eradicate Malaria in Areas of Suspected or Proven Artemisinin Resistance in Southeast Asia and South Asia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mahidol Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Centre for Parasitology, Entomology and Malaria Control, Cambodia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Family Health International, Cambodia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oxford University Clinical Research Unit, Vietnam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Malaria Control Program, Vietnam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Myanmar Oxford Clinical Research Unit</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Malaria Control Program, Myanmar</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lao-Oxford-Mahosot Hospital Wellcome Trust Research Unit (LOMWRU), Laos</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shoklo Malaria Research Unit</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall aim of this study is two fold:

        1. to pilot targeted chemo-elimination of plasmodium falciparum malaria in known areas of
           artemisinin resistance in South East Asia.

        2. to understand the micro-epidemiology of malaria in these areas; chiefly, the prevalence
           and importance to on-going transmission of sub-clinical p.f malaria infections.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The spread of artemisinin resistance in Plasmodium falciparum, which compromises the
      therapeutic efficacy of artemisinin combination treatments (ACTs), is the greatest threat to
      current global initiatives to control and eliminate malaria and is considered the highest
      priority of the WHO Global Malaria Programme. If not eliminated, resistant parasites could
      spread across Asia to Africa, as happened with resistance to other antimalarials in the past.

      Conventional descriptions of the epidemiology of malaria in low transmission settings suggest
      that malaria prevalences are low (&lt;10%) and heterogeneous. Most or all infections are thought
      to be symptomatic so the focus of malaria control activities is on the identification and
      treatment of symptomatic individuals. We and others have shown recently that artemisinin
      resistant P. falciparum is prevalent in Western Cambodia, and that it is now also found along
      the Thailand-Myanmar border and Vietnam. We have recently developed highly sensitive
      quantitative PCR (uPCR) methods for parasite detection using &gt;1mL of blood which are 5,000
      times more sensitive than conventional microscopy, and 100 times more sensitive than
      currently used PCR.

      We have studied villages along the Thai-Myanmar border which are typical for the region and
      are classified by conventional epidemiological techniques as low-transmission (5-20% malaria
      prevalence). Our studies suggest that the majority of the population is infected. In Pailin,
      Western Cambodia, in areas where the National Malaria Control Programme and WHO believe that
      malaria has been all but eliminated, we have also found very high rates (&gt;80%) of
      sub-microscopic parasitaemia in patients with fever or history of fever who are RDT negative.
      Thus, there is a lot more asymptomatic malaria in low transmission settings than previously
      thought, suggesting that control and elimination activities need to be rethought.

      Highly sensitive quantitative PCR (uPCR) requires a venous blood sample, a laboratory which
      can perform vacuum DNA extraction, and on average four weeks for processing. A rapid highly
      sensitive diagnostic test which can be performed at the point of care would be a
      technological breakthrough. Screening with highly sensitive RDTs and treating of asymptomatic
      carriers will have a range of public health applications. Such tests are becoming available
      in 2017 and will be evaluated side by side with uPCR.

      This study is designed to conduct and evaluate the efficacy of pilot implementation of
      targeted chemo-elimination in selected areas with the goal of eliminating malaria in these
      regions. This differs from mass drug administration (MDA); it is a strategy used to identify
      specific areas where mass treatment is necessary, in this case to eliminate all malaria
      parasites. Elimination will be targeted at communities with significant levels of subclinical
      infection and transmission which will be identifiable in the future by comparing rates of
      positivity by RDT or microscopy from new population samples against our qPCR data, which
      shows the true falciparum prevalence.

      The study will assess the feasibility, safety and acceptability of this strategy and its
      impact on the transmission of malaria and the progression of artemisinin resistance. In
      addition it will evaluate the contribution of low parasitaemia carriage to transmission of
      artemisinin resistant malaria. These pilot studies are a necessary prelude to future scale up
      and policy implementation.

      Dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (DP) is a highly efficacious and inexpensive ACT which is well
      tolerated by all age groups when used to treat uncomplicated multi-drug resistant falciparum
      malaria in South East Asia. Monthly DP treatments have proved highly effective and well
      tolerated. When used as part of a MDA strategy, the addition of a gametocytocidal drug
      contributes towards the goal of malaria elimination by adding a strong transmission blocking
      activity to the regimen. Primaquine (PQ), the only currently licensed 8-aminoquinoline, is
      relatively safe and very effective when used at a dose of 0.25 mg base/kg, and does not
      require G6PD screening. Thus, we propose to evaluate the potential of this strategy to
      eliminatie malaria focally in areas where artemisinin resistance in P. falciparum is
      prevalent using DP plus PQ.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of falciparum malaria measured by qPCR (quantitative real time polymerase chain reaction), 12 months after the first administration of treatment with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and primaquine. (1017-13 and 23-15)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage falls in asymptomatic malaria prevalence in the intervention villages vs control villages, as determined by highly sensitive qPCR, 12 months after the first administration of treatment with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and primaquine.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of falciparum malaria measured by qPCR (quantitative real time polymerase chain reaction), 12 months after the first administration of targeted malaria elimination (1015-13)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage falls in asymptomatic malaria prevalence in the intervention villages vs control villages, as determined by highly sensitive qPCR, 12 months after the first administration of treatment with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of falciparum malaria measured by qPCR (quantitative real time polymerase chain reaction), 4 months after the first administration of target malaria-elimination (23-15)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage falls in asymptomatic malaria prevalence in the intervention villages vs control villages, as determined by highly sensitive qPCR, 4 months after the first administration of treatment with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and primaquine.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and acceptability of targeted malaria elimination (1017-13 and 1015-13)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and acceptability of targeted malaria elimination, evaluated by questionnaires filled out by participants or care givers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on gametocyte carriage by targeted malaria elimination (1017-13 and 1015-13)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Effect on gametocyte carriage by targeted malaria elimination, measured by the proportions of gametocyte carriers over the 12 month period</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize parasite carriage using highly sensitive techniques in four geographically separate sites where resistance to artemisinin has been documented (1017-13 and 1015-13)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Characterize parasite carriage using by molecular analysis of parasite genotypes, markers of resistance and parasite population genetic structure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of targeted Chemo-elimination of malaria measured by number of peaople participate (1017-13)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost estimates of targeted Chemo-elimination of malaria by sampling strategy (1017-13)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>incidence of clinical malaria in the villages over the first 12 months (1015-13)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of Artemisinin resistance - P.falciparum infections (23-15)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity of novel RDTs (HS RDT)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>(Laos site only)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity of novel RDTs (HS RDT)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>(Laos site only)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">8000</enrollment>
  <condition>Plasmodium Falciparum Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>malaria elimination using DP and low-dose primaquine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two villages randomly allocated to intervention (chemo-elimination) at each of the 4 sites (population approximately 500 people in each village). In these villages the entire population will be invited to receive three, monthly rounds of treatment with dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine and primaqunine to kill malaria parasites. The micro-epidemiology of malaria will be studied and prevalence and patterns of transmission used for comparison. NB, in Cambodia there will be no intervention villages and all four villages will be used to study the micro-epidemiology of malaria transmission in the absence of malaria elimination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control villages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two villages randomly allocated to control (no chemo-elimination) at each of the 4 sites (population approximately 500 people in each village). In these villages only the micro-epidemiology of malaria will be studied and prevalence and patterns of transmission used for comparison. NB, in Cambodia there will be no intervention villages and all four villages will be used to study the micro-epidemiology of malaria transmission in the absence of malaria elimination.
From June 2013 to June 2014 Cambodia site conducted surveys with no medical intervention (treatment arm). In July 2015 Cambodia implemented the TCE protocol with two intervention and two control villages. Primaquine is not used in the TCE treatment regimen in Cambodia. Both studies were approved under OxTREC reference no. 1017-13 and 1015-13.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>malaria elimination using DP and low-dose primaquine</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment of all persons resident in the intervention villages including those who do not have malaria parasites as detected by rapid diagnostic test. This is to interrupt p.f malaria transmission by removing the reservoir of all potentially infectious people from the area.</description>
    <arm_group_label>malaria elimination using DP and low-dose primaquine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Three monthly rounds of:</other_name>
    <other_name>Dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine</other_name>
    <other_name>Low-dose primaquine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        OxTREC reference: 1017-13

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥6 months, male or female,

          -  Written informed consent (by parent/guardian in case of children)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women will not receive primaquine (urine pregnancy tests will be performed on
             women of appropriate age groups before drug administration at each TCE round)

          -  History of allergy or known contraindication to artemisinins, piperaquine or PQ

          -  Those who are, in the opinion of the study clinician, ill at the time of drug
             administration

        OxTREC reference: 1015-13

        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Age ≥6 months, male or female,

          -  Written informed consent (by legally acceptable representative in case of children)

          -  Healthy at the time of the survey or drug administration

          -  Not pregnant

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Significant non-compliance with study requirements

          -  Loss to follow up

          -  Suspected severe adverse events

          -  Severe illness

        OxTREC reference: 23-15

        Part 1. qPCR survey for identification of potential TMT villages;

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Males and females 18 and above

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Presence of any acute severe illness at the time of survey

        Exclusion criteria:

        • Pregnant women in their first trimester

        Part 2. TMT villages will be given directly observed therapy (DOT) with DP for 3 days and
        PQ (0.25 mg/kg) will be given on day 1

        Inclusion criteria for TMT

          -  Age ≥one year, male and female,

          -  Willing to provide consent for those 18 years and above. For children 10-18 years old,
             parents/guardians must provide consent, and the children must provide assent. For
             children below 10 years old, the parents/guardians must provide consent.

        Exclusion criteria for TMT

          -  History of allergy or known contraindication to artemisinins, piperaquine or PQ.

          -  Refusal of treatment.

          -  Pregnant women in their 1st trimester.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas J White, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pailin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pailin</city>
        <zip>372</zip>
        <country>Cambodia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Savannakhet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Savannakhet</city>
        <country>Lao People's Democratic Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mahidol Oxford Clincal Research Unit, Myanmar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rangoon</city>
        <country>Myanmar</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shoklo Malaria Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mae Sot</city>
        <state>Tak</state>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford University Clinical Research Unit - Vietnam</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ho Chi Minh city</city>
        <zip>Ward 1, District 5</zip>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cambodia</country>
    <country>Lao People's Democratic Republic</country>
    <country>Myanmar</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.tropmedres.ac</url>
    <description>The Mahidol Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>(2011) Global Plan for Artemisinin Resistance Containment. Geneva: World Health Organisation.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dondorp AM, Nosten F, Yi P, Das D, Phyo AP, Tarning J, Lwin KM, Ariey F, Hanpithakpong W, Lee SJ, Ringwald P, Silamut K, Imwong M, Chotivanich K, Lim P, Herdman T, An SS, Yeung S, Singhasivanon P, Day NP, Lindegardh N, Socheat D, White NJ. Artemisinin resistance in Plasmodium falciparum malaria. N Engl J Med. 2009 Jul 30;361(5):455-67. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0808859. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2009 Oct 22;361(17):1714.</citation>
    <PMID>19641202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phyo AP, Nkhoma S, Stepniewska K, Ashley EA, Nair S, McGready R, ler Moo C, Al-Saai S, Dondorp AM, Lwin KM, Singhasivanon P, Day NP, White NJ, Anderson TJ, Nosten F. Emergence of artemisinin-resistant malaria on the western border of Thailand: a longitudinal study. Lancet. 2012 May 26;379(9830):1960-6. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60484-X. Epub 2012 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22484134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hien TT, Thuy-Nhien NT, Phu NH, Boni MF, Thanh NV, Nha-Ca NT, Thai le H, Thai CQ, Toi PV, Thuan PD, Long le T, Dong le T, Merson L, Dolecek C, Stepniewska K, Ringwald P, White NJ, Farrar J, Wolbers M. In vivo susceptibility of Plasmodium falciparum to artesunate in Binh Phuoc Province, Vietnam. Malar J. 2012 Oct 26;11:355. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-11-355.</citation>
    <PMID>23101492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amaratunga C, Sreng S, Suon S, Phelps ES, Stepniewska K, Lim P, Zhou C, Mao S, Anderson JM, Lindegardh N, Jiang H, Song J, Su XZ, White NJ, Dondorp AM, Anderson TJ, Fay MP, Mu J, Duong S, Fairhurst RM. Artemisinin-resistant Plasmodium falciparum in Pursat province, western Cambodia: a parasite clearance rate study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2012 Nov;12(11):851-8. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(12)70181-0. Epub 2012 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22940027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tran TH, Dolecek C, Pham PM, Nguyen TD, Nguyen TT, Le HT, Dong TH, Tran TT, Stepniewska K, White NJ, Farrar J. Dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine against multidrug-resistant Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Vietnam: randomised clinical trial. Lancet. 2004 Jan 3;363(9402):18-22.</citation>
    <PMID>14723988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smithuis F, Kyaw MK, Phe O, Aye KZ, Htet L, Barends M, Lindegardh N, Singtoroj T, Ashley E, Lwin S, Stepniewska K, White NJ. Efficacy and effectiveness of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine versus artesunate-mefloquine in falciparum malaria: an open-label randomised comparison. Lancet. 2006 Jun 24;367(9528):2075-85. Erratum in: Lancet. 2017 Apr 29;389(10080):1698.</citation>
    <PMID>16798391</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashley EA, Krudsood S, Phaiphun L, Srivilairit S, McGready R, Leowattana W, Hutagalung R, Wilairatana P, Brockman A, Looareesuwan S, Nosten F, White NJ. Randomized, controlled dose-optimization studies of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated multidrug-resistant falciparum malaria in Thailand. J Infect Dis. 2004 Nov 15;190(10):1773-82. Epub 2004 Oct 18. Erratum in: J Infect Dis. 2005 Apr 1;191(7):1204.</citation>
    <PMID>15499533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashley EA, McGready R, Hutagalung R, Phaiphun L, Slight T, Proux S, Thwai KL, Barends M, Looareesuwan S, White NJ, Nosten F. A randomized, controlled study of a simple, once-daily regimen of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated, multidrug-resistant falciparum malaria. Clin Infect Dis. 2005 Aug 15;41(4):425-32. Epub 2005 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>16028147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>White NJ, Qiao LG, Qi G, Luzzatto L. Rationale for recommending a lower dose of primaquine as a Plasmodium falciparum gametocytocide in populations where G6PD deficiency is common. Malar J. 2012 Dec 14;11:418. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-11-418. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23237606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myint HY, Ashley EA, Day NP, Nosten F, White NJ. Efficacy and safety of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2007 Sep;101(9):858-66. Epub 2007 Jul 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17659311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malaria elimination</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Epidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>South East Asia</keyword>
  <keyword>Artemisinin resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Dihydroartemisinin piperaquine</keyword>
  <keyword>Primaquine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Primaquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Piperaquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dihydroartemisinin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

