<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01878370</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>075-2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01878370</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Audit and Feedback for Primary Care: a Cluster-randomized Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimizing Audit and Feedback for Primary Care - Testing Scalable Approaches to Providing Feedback Reports, a Cluster-randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In a previous study, the investigators delivered graphs to family physicians that outlined
      the proportion of patients with a history of diabetes or heart disease achieving
      evidence-based quality targets derived from guideline recommendations. A qualitative
      evaluation found that participating family physicians did not act upon the feedback for two
      main reasons. First, they felt that targets recommended in guidelines often did not apply for
      particular patients. Second, they complained that had difficulty using the feedback reports
      that only provided aggregate level data for clinical action. In this cluster-randomized
      trial, the investigators test two approaches to conducting audit and feedback that aims to
      address these issues. The investigators hypothesize that feedback identifying a small number
      of patients at high-risk for cardiovascular events requiring action will more effectively
      lead to changes in clinical behavior than feedback identifying all patients not reaching
      optimal care targets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For the last two years, all physicians contributing data to the Electronic Medical Record
      Administrative data Linked Database (EMRALD) have received two feedback reports. The first
      focused on diabetes and the second on patients with heart disease. The reports provide
      aggregate information regarding the proportion of the family physician's patients meeting
      quality targets, but no patient-specific information. Currently the feedback is sent to
      physicians by courier from the EMRALD team every six months.

      The intervention arms in this trial are as follows:

        -  Arm 1 - Standard, aggregate-level feedback reports focusing on the proportion of
           patients with hypertension and/or diabetes and/or ischemic heart disease meeting targets
           sent via courier every six months and available on a password protected website. Family
           physicians in this arm will also have access through this website to patient-level data
           to identify patients not achieving optimal quality of care targets.

        -  Arm 2 - Aggregate-level feedback reports focusing on the proportion of patients with
           hypertension and/or diabetes and/or ischemic heart disease meeting criteria for
           high-risk sent via courier every six months and available on a password protected
           website. Family physicians in this arm will also have access through this website to a
           list of chart numbers identifying those patients at highest risk.

      Both arms will have the opportunity to receive continuing medical education credits by
      completing worksheets that prompt them to reflect upon the data. Family physicians in Arm 1
      are asked to complete a worksheet that follows continuous quality improvement principles,
      including setting an aim statement, engagement with team members in the clinic, testing
      change concepts at first on a small scale, and then scaling up in a effort to spread best
      practices. Family physicians in Arm 2 are asked to complete a worksheet that also includes
      goal setting and action planning, but focuses on reducing the number of patients with
      high-risk criteria and offers some suggested practice-based approaches.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>composite quality score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of best-practice quality indicators that a patient is achieving divided by the number for which they are eligible.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>composite high risk score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of high risk indicators a patient meets divided by the number for which they are eligible.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with perfect composite quality score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>perfect composite quality score is equal to one hundred percent</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with perfect composite high risk score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>perfect composite high risk score is zero</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cholesterol (LDL)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Each metric within the composite scores</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>For Hypertension (HTN):
Blood Pressure (BP) tested in 15 months (M) BP meeting target BP test in 4 M if &gt;target Weight (WT) measured in 15 M Lipids measures in 15 M
For Diabetes:
HbA1c tested in 6 M HbA1c &lt; 7 BP &lt;130/80 Angiotensin agent (ACE/ARB) if also HTN WT measured within 15 M Lipids in 15 M LDL &lt;2 Statin if &gt;50yrs Albumin-creatinine ratio in 15 M
For Heart disease:
BP in 15 M BP meeting target Anti-platelet (or Anti-coagulant) WT within 15 M Lipids measured within 15 M LDL &lt;2 Statin
For Diabetes High Risk:
no HbA1c 15 M HbA1c &gt;9 no BP in 15 M BP &gt;160/100 no ACE/ARB if also HTN no WT within 24 M no lipids measured within 36 M LDL &gt;4
For Heart disease high risk:
no BP in 24 M BP &gt;160/100 no anti-platelet (anti-coagulant) no WT within 24 M no lipids measured within 36 M LDL &gt;4
For Hypertension high risk:
no BP in 24 M BP &gt;160/100 no WT within 24 M no lipids in 36 M</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">177</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Ischemic Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High risk</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Feedback reports focusing on the identification and management of patients who appear to have poorly managed diseases and who may require recall into clinic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Best Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Feedback reports focusing on the achievement of optimal care targets for patients with chronic disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High risk</intervention_name>
    <description>Aggregate-level feedback reports focusing on the proportion of patients with hypertension and/or diabetes and/or ischemic heart disease meeting criteria for high-risk sent via courier every six months and available on a password protected website. Family physicians in this arm will also have access through this website to a list of chart numbers identifying those patients at highest risk.
Family physicians in Arm 2 are asked to complete a worksheet that also includes goal setting and action planning, but focuses on reducing the number of patients with high-risk criteria and offers some suggested practice-based approaches.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High risk</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Best Practice</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard, aggregate-level feedback reports focusing on the proportion of patients with hypertension and/or diabetes and/or ischemic heart disease meeting targets sent via courier every six months and available on a password protected website. Family physicians in this arm will also have access through this website to patient-level data to identify patients not achieving optimal quality of care targets.
Family physicians in Arm 1 are asked to complete a worksheet that follows continuous quality improvement principles, including setting an aim statement, engagement with team members in the clinic, testing change concepts at first on a small scale, and then scaling up in a effort to spread best practices.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Best Practice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Family physicians belonging to and sharing data with the Electronic Medical Record
             Administrative Linked Database in Ontario

          -  Patients rostered to these family physicians with diabetes or hypertension or ischemic
             heart disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Family physicians without at least two years of Electronic Medical Record data in
             EMRALD

          -  Family physicians without at least 100 rostered, active patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Tu, MD MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 14, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 21, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 21, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

