<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01873131</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2010-P-001538</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01873131</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Trial of Pulsed-dye Laser Versus Timolol Topical Solution Versus Observation on the Growth of Hemangioma in Newborn</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preventing Growth of Hemangioma Tumors in Newborn: A Prospective Randomized Clinical Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out if pulsed dye laser treatment or timolol maleate
      0.5% gel can help infants who have a hemangioma. The investigators also want to find out if
      pulsed dye laser treatment and timolol maleate 0.5% gel are safe to use without causing too
      many side effects.

      Hemangioma is a common type of birthmark. These birthmarks happen when many new blood vessels
      grow in a specific area on the skin. Blood vessels are tiny tubes that carry blood through
      the body. No one knows what causes blood vessels to group together. Most birthmarks don't
      hurt at all and they usually aren't a sign of any kind of illness. Lots of newborns have
      these birthmarks on their bodies, like between the eyebrows. These birthmarks usually
      disappear within the first few months to years of life. These birthmarks tend to disappear
      spontaneously. Most hemangiomas are not treated unless the hemangioma threatens the child's
      health, which occurs in about 1 in 3 children with hemagiomas.

      Pulsed dye laser is widely used in children, and is approved by the U.S. Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA) for treating hemangioma.

      The FDA has approved timolol maleate to treat glaucoma in adults, but the FDA has not
      approved timolol maleate to treat hemangiomas in children. About 7 infants with hemangiomas
      have received timolol maleate. The results so far show that timolol maleate may be helpful
      and safe in treating hemangiomas in infants.

      An important question being tested in this study is whether pulsed-dye laser or timolol
      maleate can prevent hemangioma from growing when used very early after birth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hemangiomas affect 5-10% of all children born in the United States and up to 20% of premature
      infants, with a higher incidence in girls. Most infantile hemangiomas (IHs) appear within a
      few weeks of birth, grow rapidly for months to years and eventually involute. &quot;Benign
      neglect&quot; (no treatment) is therefore recommended by most pediatricians. However, about 1/3 of
      cases (2-3% of all children born in the US) eventually require medical or surgical
      interventions for hemangiomas due to blocked vision, problems with breathing, feeding, pain,
      ulceration, infection, profuse bleeding or disfigurement. None of the interventions are
      benign. Occasionally, hemangiomas may be fatal.

      The broad objective of this study is to prevent injury and disfigurement of millions of
      children per year by developing a very safe, effective, and non-invasive treatment that
      inhibits the growth of cutaneous hemangiomas in newborns. Historically, pulsed dye laser has
      been known to bea very effective and safe treatment for hemangiomas; however, this treatment
      modality has not been studied for the treatment of very early hemangiomas. Recently, systemic
      beta-blockade with propanolol has also shown remarkable results in treating threatening
      hemangiomas. However, systemic propanolol is not benign and requires inpatient monitoring for
      cardiac side effects. Topical beta-blocker has been demonstrated in a case report to prevent
      the growth of infantile eyelid hemangioma. We propose a prospective, single blinded,
      randomized study of pulsed dye laser (PDL) and topical beta-blocker solution (timolol maleate
      ophthalmic gel forming solution) in the treatment of very early hemangiomas. Specifically the
      efficacy, side effects and outcome of PDL and timolol will be compared with no treatment, the
      present standard of care for early stage hemangiomas. The extent to which early laser
      treatment or topical timolol treatment prevents tumor growth and the need for future medical
      or surgical treatments will be determined. Infants will be recruited from the pediatric and
      neonatal practices at Massachusetts General Hospital, and randomized to receive either: (1) a
      series of weekly to semi-weekly laser treatments, (2) twice daily topical application of
      timolol ophthalmic gel-forming solution for six weeks, or (3) no treatment. Hemangiomas will
      be assessed clinically and with digital photography for serial repeated measures of
      hemangioma size at each study visit. A panel of blinded evaluators will also provide
      assessment from photographs. Response, side effects and need for additional treatments will
      be recorded for up to 2 years after PDL and topical timolol treatment. This clinical trial
      fills a large gap in evidence-based medical therapy for IHs. If indeed early laser treatment
      of hemangiomas with PDL or topical timolol, both relatively harmless treatments, can
      eliminate the potential for complications by treating hemangiomas prior to the growth phase,
      then this trial would present an attractive solution for the problem of when and how to
      treat.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of lesions that are completely clear or with minimum residual signs</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measurement will be the proportion of lesions that are completely clear or with minimum residual signs (defined as faint macular erythema with no palpable component). Three independent assessors (blinded to patient allocation) will be asked to evaluate photographs at each study visit compared to baseline using a 100-mm visual analog scale (VAS). Improvement in lesion size, thickness and color relative to baseline will be assessed by three independent observers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of parents who consider their children to have a cosmetically acceptable outcome, functional improvement, need for additional treatment and any adverse reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of parents who consider their children to have a cosmetically acceptable outcome, functional improvement, need for additional treatment and any adverse reactions arising from PDL treatment or timolol treatment or occurring as a natural progression of the hemangioma including hyper- or hypo- pigmentation, ulceration, atrophy and hypertrophic scarring, pain associated with ulceration, infection, bleeding, and requirement for intra-lesional or systemic steroids or any other additional treatment will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemangioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Topical Timolol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After verification of eligibility criteria and obtaining informed consent of parent/guardian, infants randomized to the timolol arm will receive twice daily topical application of a physician-specified amount of timolol maleate 0.5% ophthalmic solution (hereby referred to as topical timolol) for up to six months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>After verification of eligibility criteria and obtaining informed consent of parent/guardian, infants randomized to the observation arm will be followed at study visits according to protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pulsed Dye Laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After verification of eligibility criteria and obtaining informed consent of parent/guardian, infants randomized to the pulsed dye laser arm will receive a series of six weekly to semi-weekly laser treatments treatments for up to 6 treatments with potential for reduced number of treatments if the hemangioma completely resolves. A 595-nm pulsed-dye laser (PDL, V-beam Perfecta, Candela Corp, Wayland, MA) with a dynamic cooling device (DCD) will be utilized for all treatments. This device is cleared by the FDA for clinical treatment of vascular lesions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>topical timolol maleate</intervention_name>
    <description>Timolol maleate 0.5% ophthalmic solution will be used. The dose will be 1 drop per square centimeter of hemangioma, rubbed into the area by the parent/guardian twice daily. The intent is to cover the entire lesion without excess of medication. Therefore, the dose can be lowered from 1 drop/cm2 at the discretion of the investigators, but not increased. This dose should not have significant systemic side effects given that the normal systemic intravenous dose for propanolol is 2mg/kg/day and there would be much less systemic absorption if the solution is applied topically. It is well established that the stratum corneum greatly slows the transport of timolol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Topical Timolol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>timolol</other_name>
    <other_name>beta blocker</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pulsed dye laser</intervention_name>
    <description>A 595-nm PDL (V-beam Perfecta, Candela Corp, Wayland, MA, USA) with a dynamic cooling device (DCD) will be utilized for all treatments. This device is cleared by the FDA for clinical treatment of vascular lesions. Protective eyewear for patient and all participants in the treatment room will be provided. A spot size of 7 or 10 mm will be used with an average fluence (energy delivered per unit area, in J/cm2) of 9 J/cm2 (range 8-10.0 J/cm2). Fluence will vary according to patient and hemangioma characteristics, including age, skin type, location, lesion thickness and response to treatment. A 30-50 ms cryogen spray cooling (CSC) duration will precede the laser pulse duration of 0.4 ms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pulsed Dye Laser</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PDL</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects aged less than 3 months, male or female.

          2. Infant with one or more superficial hemangiomas in the preproliferative phase or very
             early proliferative growth phase.

          3. Absence or minimal appearance of the lesion at birth

          4. More pronounced appearance within 1 month of birth.

          5. Willingness of parent/guardian to participate in the study

          6. Willingness of parent/guardian to receive EXPERIMENTAL treatment

          7. Informed consent agreement signed by the parent/guardian

          8. Willingness of parent/guardian to follow the treatment schedule and post treatment
             care requirements

          9. Willingness of parent/guardian to not use topical or systemic (oral) TREATMENT
             medications of the hemangioma other than those prescribed by the investigators during
             the study period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Infants already on other treatment prior to PDL or timolol treatments (including
             topical, systemic steroids or other agents)

          2. Any infant who, in the opinion of his or her pediatrician or the investigators, has a
             major medical problem (such as cardiac pathology or airway obstruction) that makes
             participation in the study difficult

          3. Infants with hemangiomas that threaten vital functions (e.g. obstructing the airway or
             impairing hearing or vision)

          4. Scarring or infection of the area to be treated

          5. Subjects who are immunocompromised

          6. Subject whose parent/guardian is unable to comply with treatment, home care or
             follow-up visits

          7. Patients with asthma or a history of asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or
             cardiovascular disease, including sinus bradycardia, second or third degree
             atrioventricular block, overt cardiac failure, and cardiogenic shock; hypersensitivity
             to any component of timolol; and in those patients receiving systemic administration
             of beta-blockers or ace inhibitors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>3 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>R. Rox Anderson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Thanh Nga T Tran, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>617 724-4937</phone>
    <email>ttran2@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yakir Levin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617 724-4937</phone>
    <email>YLEVIN2@PARTNERS.ORG</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thanh Nga T Tran, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-4937</phone>
      <email>ttran2@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ray H Jalian, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617 724-4937</phone>
      <email>hjalian@partners.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>R. Rox Anderson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thanh Nga T Tran, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kelly Stankiewicz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ray H Jalian, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard Rox Anderson, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Wellman Center for Photomedicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hemangioma</keyword>
  <keyword>infantile hemangioma</keyword>
  <keyword>pulsed dye laser</keyword>
  <keyword>PDL</keyword>
  <keyword>topical beta blocker</keyword>
  <keyword>timolol maleate</keyword>
  <keyword>timolol</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemangioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ophthalmic Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Timolol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adrenergic beta-Antagonists</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Maleic acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

