<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01871337</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UI_MS_HMO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01871337</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercises for Urinary Incontinence(UI) of Women With Multiple Sclerosis (MS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>UI-MS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Clinical Trial for the Efficacy of Paula Method ( Circular Muscle Exercise) in Women With Multiple Sclerosis Who Suffer From Urinary Incontinence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine whether the Paula method is an effective treatment for UI and the
      correlating LUTD symptoms. We assume that the Paula method, a simple, non-aerobic exercise
      method that significantly decreased urinary incontinence in women with MIX in two randomized
      controlled trials, would also be effective in Multiple Sclerosis (MS) patients with UI. The
      secondary aim is to evaluate the effectiveness in terms of MS general physical functioning,
      quality of life and sexual function and to detect adherence and continuity six months post
      intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The patient will be examined by the neurologist at the MS clinic, at the Hadassah University
      Medical Center. Patients who meet the inclusion criteria will receive an explanation, and
      will sign informed consent. She will be asked to complete the baseline questionnaires. Than
      the patient will be assigned to an exercise group. After 12 weeks the patient will be asked
      to complete post intervention questionnaire. Apart from the weekly lesson, women will be
      asked to exercise at home for 15 minutes a day. After six months she will be invited again
      for a neurological examination and filling an additional questionnaire.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary Incontinence ,measured by The ICIQ-SF Short Form questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>quality of life, sexual function and mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire for Urinary Incontinence Diagnosis (QUID); The Incontinence Quality of Life Questionnaire (I -QOL); The Pelvic Organ Prolapse/ Urinary Incontinence Sexual Questionnaire (PISQ-12); Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS);Demographic data questionnaire, General health and Paula Method Evaluation; Long term (6 months after the end of the intervention) questionnaire;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Urinary Incontinence;</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paula method</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the Paula method, a circular muscle exercise, invented in Israel by Paula Garbourg.The method is based on the principle that all sphincters in the body are synchronized, with the movement of one affecting the other.One can rehabilitate damaged muscles by contracting and relaxing specific &quot;circular&quot; muscles in other parts of the body.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paula method</intervention_name>
    <description>The Paula method will be taught to the participants by several registered Paula instructors. Subjects allocated to this intervention will receive one 45-minute group session per week for 12 weeks (with up to 30 minutes for personal questions regarding the exercises). This length of time is crucial because it has been demonstrated that it take three months for women to adequately learn the exercises in order for them to practice independently at home. Participants will be encouraged to practice daily for 15 minutes and report their at- home training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paula method</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Circular muscle exercises</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        women ≥18 years old; who have complained of urine leakage in the past four weeks; MS
        diagnosed with an Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS)≤7.5; literate in Hebrew and/or
        English; suffering from UI at least in the 4 last weeks prior to recruitment

        Exclusion Criteria:

        pregnant or breastfeeding women, those within 12 weeks of delivery; 6 weeks of abortion;
        six months of pelvic surgery; symptomatic urinary tract infection (UTI); more than grade 2
        genital prolapse, permanent catheterization for urination; women taking medications for UI
        less then 3 months and women who exercise on regular basis in Paula method.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adi Vaknin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91120</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 20, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 20, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 22, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>urinary incontinence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Incontinence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enuresis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

