<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01871545</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 12-0214</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01871545</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Liver Cancer With Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of HCC Response to Systemic Therapy With Quantitative MRI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) has recently increased in the United States.
      Although imaging plays a major role in HCC screening and staging, the possibility of
      predicting HCC tumor grade, aggressiveness, angiogenesis and hypoxia with imaging are unmet
      needs. In addition, new antiangiogenic drugs now available to treat advanced HCC necessitate
      the use of new imaging criteria beyond size. The investigators would like to develop and
      validate non-invasive magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) methods based on advanced
      diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI), MR Elastography, BOLD (blood oxygen level dependent) MRI
      and perfusion-weighted imaging (PWI, using gadolinium contrast) to be used as non-invasive
      markers of major histopathologic features of HCC, and to predict and assess early response of
      HCC to systemic therapy. The investigators also would like to develop quality control tools
      to improve the quality and decrease variability of quantitative MRI metrics. These techniques
      combined could represent non-invasive correlates of histologic findings in HCC, could enable
      individualized therapy, and provide prognosis in patients with HCC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) has recently increased in the US mostly due
      to an increase in chronic hepatitis C infection. Angiogenesis is critical for the growth and
      metastatic progression of HCC. With the development of new antiangiogenic drugs such as
      sorafenib, imaging methods to predict and assess therapeutic response beyond changes in size
      become critical. However, validated imaging methods to predict and assess early HCC response
      to targeted agents are lacking.

      In this study, the investigators would like to develop quantitative MRI methods interrogating
      different features of HCC tumor biology and pathology, including tumor cellularity, grade,
      angiogenesis and hypoxia. The investigators propose a multiparametric approach combining
      advanced DWI (IVIM: intravoxel incoherent motion diffusion measuring perfusion fraction and
      true diffusion coefficient), DCE-MRI (dynamic contrast-enhanced MRI, which measures arterial
      and portal flow, mean transit time, blood volume and distribution volume), and BOLD MRI using
      oxygen or carbogen challenge. This protocol will be performed in patients with HCC undergoing
      hepatic resection. Routine and advanced histopathologic methods will be performed (tumor
      grade, CK19 expression, presence of microvascular invasion, VEGF expression, microvessel
      density, HIF 1-alpha expression). MRI metrics will be correlated with histopathologic
      metrics.

      The first portion of the proposal involves the development of a QC algorithm assessing MR
      data quality and test-retest. The investigators will propose solutions to improve data
      acquisition and processing. The last 2 years of the study will be dedicated to a prospective
      randomized study comparing Yttrium 90 radioembolization to sorafenib, assessing the role of
      baseline MRI metrics and early changes (at 2 weeks) in these metrics as markers of tumor
      response and time to progression in patients with unresectable HCC.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor diffusion</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>measured with diffusion-weighted imaging sequence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perfusion/flow</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>measured with dynamic contrast-enhanced imaging using gadolinium contrast</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>measured with T2* and T1-weighted imaging</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stiffness</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>measured with magnetic resonance elastography</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">141</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>HCC</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>dynamic contrast-enhanced MRI measuring arterial and portal flow</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Magnetic Resonance Imaging is a radiation free non invasive technique using magnetic radiofrequency waves to image the body. In this study, the research team would like to investigate the possibility of providing functional information on aggressiveness, vascularity and oxygen uptake in liver cancer tumors.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Study group

          -  Patients diagnosed with HCC, who will undergo resection or transplantation within 6
             months, as part of routine clinical care and patients diagnosed with unresectable HCC

          -  18 years of age and older

          -  Patient is able to give informed consent for this study

        Control group

          -  Healthy volunteers 18 years of age and older

          -  Subject is able to give informed consent for this study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age less than 18 years

          -  Unable or unwilling to give informed consent

          -  Contra-indications to MRI:

               1. Electrical implants such as cardiac pacemakers or perfusion pumps

               2. Ferromagnetic implants such as aneurysm clips, surgical clips, prostheses,
                  artificial hearts, valves with steel parts, metal fragments, shrapnel, tattoos
                  near the eye, or steel implants

               3. Ferromagnetic objects such as jewelry or metal clips in clothing

               4. Pregnant subjects

               5. Pre-existing medical conditions including a likelihood of developing seizures or
                  claustrophobic reactions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bachir Taouli, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Courtney Mahr, MPH, CHES</last_name>
    <phone>212-824-8475</phone>
    <email>Courtney.Mahr@mountsinai.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bachir Taouli, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-824-8475</phone>
      <email>bachir.taouli@mountsinai.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nikki Charles</last_name>
      <phone>212-824-8475</phone>
      <email>nikki.charles@mountsinai.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bachir Taouli, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bachir Taouli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Radiology and Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hepatocellular carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>HCC</keyword>
  <keyword>liver cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>liver disease</keyword>
  <keyword>magnetic resonance imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

