<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01873885</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PB1046-PT-CL-0002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01873885</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Exploratory Study That Will Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Hemodynamic Response to a Single 30 Minute Intravenous Infusion of Vasomera™ (PB1046) in Adult Subjects With Stage 1 or 2 Essential Hypertension</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Exploratory Study That Will Assess the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Hemodynamic Response to a Single 30 Minute Intravenous Infusion of Vasomera™ (PB1046) in Adult Subjects With Stage 1 or 2 Essential Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PhaseBio Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PhaseBio Pharmaceuticals Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is an exploratory Phase 1 randomized, double-blind (Investigator and study subject
      and 2-D echo endpoint assessor), placebo-controlled single IV infusion dose escalation study
      that will enroll up to approximately 32 subjects with stage 1 or 2 essential hypertension.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be conducted in two parts.

      Part 1: For the initial evaluation of safety, pharmacokinetic exposure and pharmacodynamic
      response, subjects will be tapered off antihypertensive background therapy.The initial
      starting dose will be a sub-therapeutic dose. Dose escalation will continue with a maximum of
      a doubling of the previous dose until either 1) a maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is identified
      or 2) modeling of the pharmacokinetic (PK) data indicate that maximum exposure (Cmax) at the
      next planned dose level would exceed a maximum drug concentration (Cmax) which was the
      maximum observed drug concentration following a single subcutaneous administration in Study
      PB1046-PT-CL-0001.

      Part 2: The dose group which is capable of providing a Cmax exposure which is capable of
      eliciting a clinically relevant hemodynamic response, will be expanded to enroll an
      additional 12 subjects (6 active and 6 placebo).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Days -45 to 28: Vital signs (Days -45, -14, -1, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 14 and 28), ECGs (Days -45, -1, 0, 1 and 2), Safety Labs (Days -45, -1, 1, 7 and 28), and Telemetry (Days -1, 0 and 1)</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of single ascending doses of Vasomera administered as a 30 minute intravenous (IV) infusion to subjects with stage 1 or stage 2 essential hypertension.
Incidence and severity of adverse events (AEs) and their relationship to Vasomera (including AEs of interest, i.e., incidence and severity of gastrointestinal effects, and infusion site reactions)
Changes in vital signs, ECGs, safety laboratory parameters, heart rhythm via telemetry monitor from baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 0, 1, 2, 3, and 4</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the pharmacokinetic profile of single ascending doses of Vasomera administered as a 30 minute intravenous (IV) infusion to subjects with stage 1 or stage 2 essential hypertension.
Elimination Half-life (t½)
Area under the concentration curve from time 0 to infinity (AUC0-inf)
Area under the curve to the final sample
Time to maximum concentration (Tmax)
Maximum serum concentration (Cmax)
Elimination rate constant (Lambda-z)
Clearance (CL)
Distribution (Vz)
Compartmental modeling - If the graphical presentations of the individual subject serum concentrations vs. time suggest that a compartmental model may be consistent with the data, then an appropriate compartmental model will be fit to the data.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic Parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Days -14, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 14 and 28</time_frame>
    <description>Compare changes in hemodynamic parameters as measured by serial systolic and diastolic blood pressure (BP) measurements and echocardiography compared to placebo.
Change from baseline in systolic and diastolic BP and heart rate (HR).
Change from baseline in two-dimensional echocardiography parameters which may include:
BP and HR
Left ventricular (LV) internal diameter in diastole and in systole, wall thickness in diastole, outflow tract diameter in mid-systole, volumes in end-diastole and end-systole, and outflow tract flow-time velocity integral
Ascending aorta peak flow velocity
Transmitral flow velocity pattern
Doppler tissue imaging of tricuspid, septal and mitral annulus
Left atrial volume
Derivation of: LV Ejection Fraction, LV Stroke Volume and Index, LV Cardiac Output and Index, Ejection Time, Systemic Vascular Resistance, Mitral E and A velocities, LV and index, Myocardial tissue velocities S' and e'.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 0, 14 and 28</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate if subjects elicit an immune response to study drug and if that response cross reacts with related endogenous compounds following a single 30 minute IV infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Essential Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 1 - Single 30 minute infusion Vasomera (PB1046) at 0.01 mg/kg diluted in 0.9% Sodium Chloride or Placebo (0.9% Sodium Chloride)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 2 - Single 30 minute infusion Vasomera (PB1046) at 0.005mg/kg in 0.9% Sodium Chloride or Placebo (0.9% Sodium Chloride)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 3 - Single 30 minute infusion Vasomera (PB1046) at 0.02mg/kg 0.9% Sodium Chloride or Placebo (0.9% Sodium Chloride)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Single IV (Intravenous) Infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>0.9% Sodium Chloride - 30 minute IV infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Experimental: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Single IV Infusion Vasomera (PB1046) or Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Willing and able to sign a written informed consent and follow all study related
             procedures.

          -  Males or females age 18 - 80 years of age inclusive.

          -  Male and female subjects of childbearing potential must be willing and able to
             practice effective contraception during the study, and be willing and able to continue
             contraception for 1 month (30 days) after their last dose of study drug.

          -  BMI ≥ 20 but ≤ 40 kg/m2

          -  Diagnosed with essential hypertension and are currently taking one or more
             antihypertensive medications to control their blood pressure and, who in the opinion
             of the investigator, could be safely withdrawn from antihypertensive therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known allergy to the study drug or any of its components, or who have previously
             received Vasomera (PB1046).

          -  Inadequate &quot;imaging window&quot; by echocardiography as determined by screening
             echocardiography (core assessment), or cardiac abnormalities that may confound
             echocardiography readings (i.e., mitral regurgitation, &quot;floppy-valve&quot; syndrome) for
             evaluation of secondary study endpoints.

          -  Seated systolic blood pressure &lt;120 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure &lt; 80 mmHg
             (confirmed in triplicate) at randomization (Day -1) or prior to the first dose of
             study drug (V3 Day 0) will exclude the subject from participation.

          -  Evidence of sustained elevation in systolic blood pressure &gt;169 mmHg or diastolic
             blood pressure &gt;109 mmHg prior to dosing (Day 0) during the washout period which in
             the opinion of the investigator would place the subject at risk for continued study
             participation (i.e., can not be safely withdrawn from antihypertensive therapy).

          -  Clinically significant changes in health status or concomitant prescription
             medications within 2 weeks prior to dosing (V3 Day 0) that could place the subject at
             risk for dosing with study drug or confound the primary or secondary outcome measures
             as assessed by the Investigator.

          -  Unstable/underlying cardiovascular disease defined as: a. Congestive heart failure
             (NYHA class III-IV), stroke, transient ischemic attack, unstable angina pectoris, or
             myocardial infarction within the 6 months prior to screening (V1) b. Mean triplicate
             12-lead ECG demonstrating a QT interval (corrected using Fridericia's formula (QTcF))
             &gt;450 msec in males and &gt;470 msec in females at Screening, (V1) or a history or
             evidence of long QT syndrome. c. Sustained heart rate &gt;100 beats per minute (BPM) (at
             rest) at screening (V1), prior to randomization (V3 Day -1), or prior to dosing (V3
             Day 0). d. Any episode of atrial fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia (defined as ten
             (10) or more beats with heart rate greater than 130 beats per minute), ventricular
             fibrillation, firing of an implantable cardiac defibrillator (ICD) for documented
             ventricular ectopy, or other clinically significant documented arrhythmias within 3
             months prior to administration of study drug (V3 Day 0).

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes defined as a Hemoglobin A1c &gt; 10.0%. Note: only applicable for
             subjects with a known or suspected history of diabetes.

          -  Clinically significant renal and/or hepatic dysfunction at Screening (V1) or at
             baseline (V3 Day -1).

          -  Pregnant or lactating females.

          -  Known history of or active drug or alcohol abuse within the 12 months prior to
             screening (V1) and/or positive drug screen (for illicit drugs) or detection of alcohol
             at baseline.

          -  Positive for Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) antibodies, hepatitis B surface
             antigen (HBsAg) or hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibodies.

          -  Participation in any other study and have received any other investigational drug or
             device within 30 days prior to the Screening visit or are taking part in a non-drug
             study which in the opinion of the Investigator would interfere with the outcome of the
             study.

          -  Major surgery, donated or lost &gt; or = 1 unit of blood (approximately 500 mL) within 30
             days prior to Screening (V1) or display evidence of volume depletion (i.e., postural
             hypotension) prior to randomization (V3 Day -1) or dosing (V3 Day 0).

          -  Other medical or psychiatric condition which in the opinion of the Investigator would
             place the subject at increased risk, would preclude obtaining voluntary consent, or
             would confound the results of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William B. Smith, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New Orleans Center for Clinical Research- Knoxville</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New Orleans Center for Clinical Research - Knoxville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37920</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 10, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 10, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PB1046, VIP, Essential Hypertension, Vasomera</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

