<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00453219</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00024918</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00453219</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>FHA: Characterization of Metabolic Status, Brain Circuitry, and Stress-Reactivity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Functional Hypothalamic Amenorrhea: Characterization of Metabolic Status, Brain Circuitry, and Stress-reactivity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Functional Hypothalamic Amenorrhea (FHA), the spontaneous cessation of the menstrual cycle
      for at least 6 months after menstrual cyclicity has been established, is a common and
      reversible form of anovulation not due to discernible organic causes. Whereas animal studies
      suggest an interaction of metabolic and psychosocial stress in the genesis of FHA, the
      distinct central mechanisms in humans are not clear. On a behavioral level, FHA appears to
      depend on a complex interplay between individual stress susceptibility, stressful life
      events, and enduring metabolic challenge due to inappropriate attitudes towards eating and
      body image. We will use a comparison group of ovulatory, eumenorrheic women (EW) and a
      contrast group of lean women with polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS). Although women with FHA
      and PCOS present with anovulation, each condition differs markedly in pathobiology (and
      health burden). Contrasting women with FHA to those with PCOS will afford an opportunity to
      understand more about the interaction between metabolism, stress, and reproduction and to
      determine the extent to which differences between FHA and EW are attributable to reproductive
      compromise (anovulation) per se versus specific to the pathogenesis of FHA or PCOS. We have
      used this approach to great advantage in the past to show that hypercortisolemia was confined
      to FHA and not PCOS (Berga 1997) and that dysfunctional (unrealistic) attitudes and decreased
      coping skills were reported more often in FHA than in PCOS and more in PCOS than EW. Further,
      this approach of comparing 3 groups will allow us to improve therapeutic approaches for two
      principle causes of anovulatory infertility in women. To accomplish this, we will study women
      with FHA, PCOS, and normal ovulatory women. The study will take place over 2 months and women
      will make 4-5 outpatient visits to the Clinical Integration Network Center and will have one
      overnight stay for frequent blood sampling.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    prior to participant recruitment, PI left Emory, study stopped
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Anovulation</condition>
  <condition>FHA</condition>
  <condition>Eumenorrhea</condition>
  <condition>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women ages 18-35 years with regular ovulatory menstrual cycles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women ages 18-35 years with irregular or absent menstrual periods due to functional hypothalamic amenorrhea (FHA) also called stress-induced anovulation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women ages 18-35 years with irregular or absent menstrual periods due to polycystic ovary syndrome(PCOS).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Screening evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>A detailed history will be taken and a physical examination performed along with a blood sample to verify ovulatory status in women with regular cycles and determine cause of anovulation in women with irregular or absent menstrual cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meal Response</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators are interested in how nutrition and metabolism can influence reproduction and they will look at how the body senses hunger and how it responses to food. Blood samples will be collected and questionnaires given to assess responses and feeling about hunger and food.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Collection</intervention_name>
    <description>A blood sample will be collected and used to check for genetic markers of stress vulnerability.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Functional MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>research participants will have an functional MRI scan of their brain while reviewing word lists associated with body image and emotions. This procedure will last about 1 hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endocrine Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>research participants will have a 30 hour inpatient hospital admission with every 15 minute blood sampling for 24 hours. Hormone measures of stress, reproduction, and appetite will be obtained.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples will be collected, processed, and stored for the evaluation of genetic markers
      assocaited with stress vulnerability. Serum and plasma specimens will be collected and stored
      for the evaluation of factors associated with the regulation of reproduction.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women ages 18-35
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria for participation are a gynecological age (age since menarche) &gt; 5
             and &lt; 25 years, and chronological age &gt; 18 years, within 90-110% of ideal body weight
             as determined by the 1983 Metropolitan height and weight table for women, and exercise
             &lt; 10 h/wk and run &lt; 10 mi/wk, day-awake/night-asleep schedule.

          -  Women in the FHA and PCOS groups have to fulfill the diagnostic criteria of FHA or
             PCOS and to have all other causes of amenorrhea and anovulation excluded.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion criteria are smoking, medications, including psychotropic or illicit drugs,
             medical, neurological, or ophthalmologic disease except acuity problems, a weight loss
             or gain of &gt; 10 lb within a year preceding or since the onset of amenorrhea, a major
             Axis I disorder other than depression, parturition in the last 12 months and/or
             lactating in the last 6 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah L Berga, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berga SL, Marcus MD, Loucks TL, Hlastala S, Ringham R, Krohn MA. Recovery of ovarian activity in women with functional hypothalamic amenorrhea who were treated with cognitive behavior therapy. Fertil Steril. 2003 Oct;80(4):976-81.</citation>
    <PMID>14556820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marcus MD, Loucks TL, Berga SL. Psychological correlates of functional hypothalamic amenorrhea. Fertil Steril. 2001 Aug;76(2):310-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11476778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berga SL, Loucks TL. Use of cognitive behavior therapy for functional hypothalamic amenorrhea. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2006 Dec;1092:114-29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17308138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 26, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 28, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 29, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 29, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 30, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anovulation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

