<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00451841</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-12073</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00451841</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exhaled Breath Condensate pH in Patients With Cough Caused by Gastroesophageal Reflux</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exhaled Breath Condensate pH in Patients With Cough Caused by Gastroesophageal Reflux</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cough is the most common complaint for which patients seek medical attention in the United
      States, accounting for approximately 1 billion dollars in health care expenses annually.
      Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) is the sole cause of chronic cough in up to 20-40% of
      all cases. The majority of these patients with GERD-induced cough have no classic &quot;heartburn&quot;
      symptoms, so this important cause of cough can thus be difficult to detect.

      Our hypothesis is that changes in exhaled breath condensate (EBC) pH can be used as a
      sensitive and non-invasive marker to identify subjects with cough caused by acid reflux.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) is the sole cause of chronic cough in up to 20-40% of
      all cases, and majority of these patients with GERD-induced cough have no classic &quot;heartburn&quot;
      symptoms. This important cause of cough can thus be difficult to detect. Non-invasive
      radiologic tests for GERD such as barium swallow is imperfectly sensitive in subjects with
      GERD-induced cough. The 24 hour pH probe, which continuously monitors esophageal pH and can
      correlate cough events with reflux events, is considered to be the gold standard test.
      However, this test is expensive, invasive, and not universally available.

      The goal of the current study is to compare simultaneous measurements of esophageal pH with
      exhaled breath condensate pH after cough episodes, in patients with symptomatic cough. The
      cause of cough will be determined by a standard protocol, which includes 24 hour pH probe
      studies, and assessment for asthma, upper airway causes and sinus disease, and medication
      effects. All subjects will undergo 24 hour pH monitoring. During this monitoring period, they
      press an event button on the pH recording device to indicate a cough episode. After six such
      events, they will immediately perform an EBC collection, and EBC pH will subsequently be
      analyzed. Differences between pH changes in the group with cough cause by GERD will be
      compared to pH measurements in the group with cough but no GERD, to determine the sensitivity
      and specificity of pH changes for discriminating between the two groups, and optimal
      threshold values for pH changes in EBC.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    IRB approval not renewed/approval lapsed. Prior status: insufficient enrollment; study
    suspended pending analysis
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>March 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity of esophageal PH changes</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the sensitivity of esophageal PH changes between the group with GERD and the group without GERD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Cough</condition>
  <condition>Gastroesophageal Reflux</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Chronic cough caused by GERD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Chronic cough without GERD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RTube Exhaled Breath Condensate Collection System</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects breath through the device to collect exhaled breath condensate</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      frozen sputum supernatant and exhaled breath condensate fixed sputum cell preparations
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult patients evaluated for cough in the Lung and Allergy Center of Umass Memorial Medical
        Center
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age &gt; 18 years old

          -  able to speak and read English

          -  chronic cough

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cigarette smoking within the past 6 months, or greater than 10 pack year history of
             prior smoking

          -  Any self-reported or clinically diagnosed form of active lung disease, including
             asthma and emphysema

          -  Symptoms of persistent rhinitis within the past three months

          -  Dysphagia

          -  Symptoms of acute viral upper respiratory tract infection or sinusitis within one
             month of entry into the study

          -  Pregnancy - based on self report

          -  Abnormal chest radiograph
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Krinzman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMass Memorial Medical Center, University Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niimi A, Nguyen LT, Usmani O, Mann B, Chung KF. Reduced pH and chloride levels in exhaled breath condensate of patients with chronic cough. Thorax. 2004 Jul;59(7):608-12.</citation>
    <PMID>15223872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hunt J. Exhaled breath condensate pH: reflecting acidification of the airway at all levels. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2006 Feb 15;173(4):366-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16467175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horváth I, Hunt J, Barnes PJ, Alving K, Antczak A, Baraldi E, Becher G, van Beurden WJ, Corradi M, Dekhuijzen R, Dweik RA, Dwyer T, Effros R, Erzurum S, Gaston B, Gessner C, Greening A, Ho LP, Hohlfeld J, Jöbsis Q, Laskowski D, Loukides S, Marlin D, Montuschi P, Olin AC, Redington AE, Reinhold P, van Rensen EL, Rubinstein I, Silkoff P, Toren K, Vass G, Vogelberg C, Wirtz H; ATS/ERS Task Force on Exhaled Breath Condensate. Exhaled breath condensate: methodological recommendations and unresolved questions. Eur Respir J. 2005 Sep;26(3):523-48.</citation>
    <PMID>16135737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cough</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastroesophageal reflux</keyword>
  <keyword>Exhaled breath condensate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroesophageal Reflux</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cough</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

