<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00458731</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2009-00184</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2009-00184</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MDACC 2005-0910</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000538277</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MDACC 2005-0910</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>7534</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA062461</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00458731</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bevacizumab and Cediranib Maleate in Treating Patients With Metastatic or Unresectable Solid Tumor, Lymphoma, Intracranial Glioblastoma, Gliosarcoma or Anaplastic Astrocytoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Clinical Trial Evaluating the Toxicity, Pharmacokinetics and Biological Effect of Intravenous Bevacizumab (Avastin TM) in Combination With Escalating Doses of Oral AZD2171 for Patients With Advanced Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial is studying the side effects and best dose of bevacizumab and cediranib
      maleate in treating patients with metastatic or unresectable solid tumor, lymphoma,
      intracranial glioblastoma, gliosarcoma or anaplastic astrocytoma. Monoclonal antibodies, such
      as bevacizumab, can block cancer growth in different ways. Some block the ability of cancer
      cells to grow and spread. Others find cancer cells and help kill them or carry cancer-killing
      substances to them. Cediranib maleate may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of
      the enzymes needed for cell growth. Bevacizumab and cediranib maleate may also stop the
      growth of cancer cells by blocking blood flow to the cancer. Giving bevacizumab together with
      cediranib maleate may kill more cancer cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the safety and toxicity profile of intravenous bevacizumab (avastin)
      administered in combination with oral AZD2171 (cediranib maleate) for patients with advanced
      malignancies.

      II. To determine the pharmacokinetic profile of oral AZD2171 in combination with bevacizumab
      (avastin) administered to patients with advanced malignancies.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the serum concentrations of Nitric Oxide (NO) and Nitric oxide synthase (NOS)
      among patients treated with this regimen and to correlate with VEGF expression.

      II. To determine changes in the tumor vasculature detected by DCE-MRI among patients treated
      with this combination of VEGF receptor blocking agents.

      III. To evaluate the potential predictive role of angiogenesis molecular endpoints in
      malignant effusion samples.

      IV. To assess in a descriptive fashion the efficacy of the studied regimen.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study.

      Patients receive bevacizumab IV over 30-90 minutes on days 1 and 15 and oral cediranib
      maleate once daily on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 28 days in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of bevacizumab and cediranib maleate until
      the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that
      at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity.

      Blood samples are acquired at baseline, on day 2, and after 2 courses of treatment for
      pharmacokinetic studies. Samples are analyzed by TUNEL, immunofluorescence staining,
      laser-scanning cytometry, flow cytometry, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay, and
      immunohistochemistry to assess apoptosis in tumor and endothelial cells, microvessel density
      mean vessel volume, nitric oxide concentration, and signal transduction pathways (i.e., ERK
      ½, P38 mitogen-activated protein kinase, protein kinase B, circulating endothelial and
      progenitor cells, basic fibroblast growth factor, vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)
      receptor phosphorylation, VEGF, and hypoxia inducible factor-1α). Some patients also undergo
      tissue biopsy at baseline and after 2 courses of treatment for characterization of vascular
      and angiogenesis markers. Some patients also undergo DCE-MRI at baseline, once between days
      22-24, and after every 2 courses of treatment to assess blood perfusion.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed for 6 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2007</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and toxicity profile of combination bevacizumab and cediranib maleate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The descriptions and grading scales found in the revised NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 will be utilized for AE reporting.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic profile of oral cediranib maleate in combination with bevacizumab</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, and 24 hours after cediranib maleate treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">57</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Grade III Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</condition>
  <condition>Adult Nasal Type Extranodal NK/T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Angioimmunoblastic T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Grade III Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Nasal Type Extranodal NK/T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Cutaneous B-cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Extranodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma of Mucosa-associated Lymphoid Tissue</condition>
  <condition>Hepatosplenic T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Intraocular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Nodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Noncutaneous Extranodal Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Progressive Hairy Cell Leukemia, Initial Treatment</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Small Cleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult T-cell Leukemia/Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Childhood Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Childhood Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Childhood Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Childhood Small Noncleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mycosis Fungoides/Sezary Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent/Refractory Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Hairy Cell Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Small Intestine Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Splenic Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Small Cleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult T-cell Leukemia/Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Childhood Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Childhood Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Childhood Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Childhood Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Childhood Small Noncleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Mycosis Fungoides/Sezary Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Mycosis Fungoides/Sezary Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>T-cell Large Granular Lymphocyte Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Childhood Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <condition>Waldenström Macroglobulinemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cediranib maleate and bevacizumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive bevacizumab IV over 30-90 minutes on days 1 and 15 and oral cediranib maleate once daily on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of bevacizumab and cediranib maleate until the MTD is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cediranib maleate and bevacizumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-VEGF humanized monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>anti-VEGF monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>Avastin</other_name>
    <other_name>rhuMAb VEGF</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cediranib maleate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cediranib maleate and bevacizumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AZD2171</other_name>
    <other_name>Recentin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histological confirmation of Solid Tumor or Lymphoma that is
             metastatic or unresectable; if assessing a single target lesion, histological
             confirmation of that particular lesion MUST be carried out

          -  Patients may have received an unlimited number of prior therapies; however, At least 4
             weeks MUST have passed since the last chemotherapy to day 1 of registration (6 weeks
             for regimens containing nitrosoureas or Mitomycin C)

          -  ECOG performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 2.0 mg/dL (does NOT apply to patients with Gilbert's Syndrome)

          -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) =&lt; 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal (Patients with liver
             involvement will be allowed =&lt; 5.0 X institutional upper normal limit)

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Patients MUST have recovered from all treatment related toxicities to Grade 1 NCI CTC
             (v 4.0) in severity

          -  Patients must be willing and able to review, understand, and provide written consent
             before starting therapy

          -  Patients with stable brain metastasis (stable disease on one MRI assessment at least 4
             weeks after completion of whole brain radiation, no evidence of progression on MRI
             assessment 4 weeks after stereotactic radiosurgery or complete surgical excision) will
             also be allowed to participate in this trial

          -  Patients with histologically proven intracranial glioblastoma, gliosarcoma or
             anaplastic astrocytoma will be eligible; patients must have shown unequivocal
             radiographic evidence for tumor progression by MRI scan; scan should be performed
             within 14 days prior to registration and on a steroid dose that has been stable for at
             least 5 days; if the steroid dose is increased between the date of imaging and
             registration, a new baseline MRI is required

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with squamous non-small cell lung carcinoma

          -  Serious or non-healing wound, ulcer or bone fracture

          -  History of abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation or intra-abdominal abscess
             within 28 days of day 1 of registration

          -  Invasive procedures defined as follows:

               -  Major surgical procedure, open biopsy or significant traumatic injury within 28
                  days prior to Day 1 registration

               -  Anticipation of need for major surgical procedures during the course of the study

               -  Core biopsy within 7 days prior to day 1 of therapy

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients with bleeding diathesis (clinical bleeding, prothrombin time &gt;= 1.5 X upper
             institutional normal value, INR &gt;= 1.5, activated partial thromboplastin time aPTT &gt;=
             1.5 X upper institutional normal value), active gastric or duodenal ulcer

          -  Uncontrolled systemic vascular hypertension (Systolic blood pressure &gt; 140 mmHg,
             Diastolic Blood Pressure &gt; 90 mmHg)

          -  Urine protein should be screened by dipstick or urine analysis; for proteinuria &gt; 1+
             or urine protein:creatinine ratio &gt; 1.0, 24-hour urine protein should be obtained and
             the level should be &lt; 1000 mg for patient enrollment

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection requiring parenteral antibiotics on Day 1

          -  Patients with clinically significant cardiovascular disease:

               -  History of CVA within 6 months

               -  Myocardial Infarction or unstable angina within 6 months

               -  New York Heart Association Grade II or greater congestive heart failure, serious
                  cardiac arrhythmia requiring medication, unstable angina pectoris

               -  Clinically significant peripheral vascular disease

               -  QTc prolongation &gt; 500msec or other significant ECG abnormality noted within 14
                  days of registration

               -  Conditions requiring concurrent use of drugs or biologics with proarrythmic
                  potential; these drugs are prohibited during studies with AZD2171 (refer to
                  appendix V for a listing of these agents)

          -  Patients with history of hemoptysis

          -  Patients with tumor mass abutting a major vessel

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because AZD-2171 is an angiogenesis
             inhibiting agent with potential teratogenic or abortifacient effects; because of the
             potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the
             mother with AZD-2171, breastfeeding should be discontinued if the mother is treated
             with AZD-2171; these potential risks may also apply to other agents used in this
             study; women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use contraception prior
             to study entry and for the duration of study participation; should a woman become
             pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study, she should
             inform her treating physician immediately
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Hong</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 11, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 19, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell, Marginal Zone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Immunoblastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plasmablastic Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycosis Fungoides</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sezary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia-Lymphoma, Adult T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Anaplastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell, Peripheral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Hairy Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Extranodal NK-T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoblastic Lymphadenopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intraocular Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Large Granular Lymphocytic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cediranib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Maleic acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

