<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00459446</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>070128</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>07-H-0128</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00459446</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imaging of Totally Blocked Arteries</brief_title>
  <official_title>Gadofosveset Imaging of Chronic Total Peripheral Artery Occlusion (CTO)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test how well a new contrast agent (dye) used in magnetic resonance imaging
      (MRI) can help visualize totally blocked arteries that normally supply blood to the neck,
      arms or legs. Currently used agents work well in visualizing normal or partly blocked
      arteries (arteries that have some blood flowing through them), but only poorly in totally
      blocked arteries. This study will see if a contrast agent called gadofosveset can better
      brighten images of completely blocked arteries. Gadofosveset is approved in Europe for use in
      MRI scans, but is still considered experimental in the United States.

      People 18 years of age or older with known or suspected total blockage of an artery to the
      neck, arm or leg may be eligible for this study.

      Participants undergo MRI scanning with gadofosveset contrast dye. MRI uses a magnetic field
      and radio waves to produce images of body tissues and organs. For this procedure, the subject
      lies on a table that can slide in and out of the tubular scanner, wearing earplugs to muffle
      loud noises that occur during the scanning process. The procedure lasts about 1.5 to 2 hours,
      during which the subject may be asked to hold his or her breath several times for as long as
      5 to 20 seconds. During the procedure, gadofosveset is injected and several kinds of MRI
      pictures are taken to understand better how the new agent works. Subjects may be asked to
      undergo a second scan using conventional MRI contrast dye
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Repairing totally occluded peripheral arteries remains challenging because they are not
      visualized using available imaging technologies. Contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance
      angiography (CE-MRA), X-ray computed tomography angiography (CTA), and invasive radiocontrast
      digital subtraction angiography (DSA) all rely on blood flow within arteries that are not
      totally occluded. Where the arterial lumen is totally occluded, contrast does not enter and
      the artery remains invisible. As a result, physicians have difficulty identifying a pathway
      or trajectory for catheter devices in order to improve blood flow using angioplasty.

      Gadofosveset, an albumin-binding MRI contrast agent that is commercially available outside
      the United States, may accumulate in the walls of occluded arteries through a mechanism that
      is not known.

      The goal of this protocol is to determine whether gadofosveset has value in planning catheter
      trajectories in totally occluded peripheral arteries. We propose to study the gadofosveset
      contrast enhancement patterns in occluded peripheral artery segments in up to 20 patients
      with known occluded iliac, femoral, and shoulder arteries being considered for catheter-based
      treatment.

      This research may have value in planning and conducting minimally invasive treatments using
      conventional X-ray guidance and possibly in the future using investigational real-time MRI
      guidance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 5, 2007</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 25, 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Conspicuity of occluded arteries after contrast exposure.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>20</enrollment>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Intermittent Claudication</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Total Aterial Occlusion</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MS-325 Injection (Gadofosveset Trisodium)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects with known cardiovascular disease will be eligible for participation in this
        protocol. The subject is eligible under the following conditions:

          -  Subject's age is greater than 18 years of age.

          -  Known occlusion of iliac, femoral, or brachiocephalic arteries.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects with absolute contraindications to MRI scanning will be excluded. These
        contraindications include subjects with the following devices:

          -  Implanted cardiac pacemaker or defibrillator.

          -  Central nervous system aneurysm clips.

          -  Implanted neural stimulator.

          -  Cochlear implant.

          -  Ocular foreign body (e.g. metal shavings).

          -  Insulin pump.

          -  Metal shrapnel or bullet.

        When subjects can provide evidence that their implanted device is labeled compatible with
        MRI, exceptions to the above exclusions can be made and recorded in the note.

        Furthermore, certain subject groups will be excluded because of the administration of MRI
        contrast agents. The weight limit is related to availability of investigational contrast
        agents. Because of recent concerns about Nephrogenic Systemic Fibrosis/Nephrogenic
        Fibrosing Dermopathy after gadobenate exposure in patients with end-stage renal disease,
        renal excretory function will be determined and patients with severe renal excretory
        dysfunction are excluded from this research protocol.

          -  Pregnant women (subjects who are uncertain as to whether they are pregnant will be
             required to have a quantitative serum pregnancy test within 72 hours) or lactating
             women.

          -  Subjects who have experienced an allergic reaction to gadolinium-based contrast
             agents.

          -  Subjects with hemoglobinopathies.

          -  Weight greater than 120 kg.

          -  Subjects with renal disease (eGFR less than 30 ml/min/1.73m(2), or receiving renal
             replacement therapy).

        The creatinine clearance will be estimated in all subjects as an estimated glomerular
        filtration rate (eGFR) using the abbreviated MDRD Formula.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooki A, Narra V, Brown J. Gadofosveset (EPIX/Schering). Curr Opin Investig Drugs. 2004 Sep;5(9):967-76. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15503653</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goyen M, Edelman M, Perreault P, O'Riordan E, Bertoni H, Taylor J, Siragusa D, Sharafuddin M, Mohler ER 3rd, Breger R, Yucel EK, Shamsi K, Weisskoff RM. MR angiography of aortoiliac occlusive disease: a phase III study of the safety and effectiveness of the blood-pool contrast agent MS-325. Radiology. 2005 Sep;236(3):825-33. Epub 2005 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>16020554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bluemke DA, Stillman AE, Bis KG, Grist TM, Baum RA, D'Agostino R, Malden ES, Pierro JA, Yucel EK. Carotid MR angiography: phase II study of safety and efficacy for MS-325. Radiology. 2001 Apr;219(1):114-22.</citation>
    <PMID>11274545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 25, 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 11, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 12, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>NHLBI</name_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Gadolinium Contrast</keyword>
  <keyword>Gadofosveset</keyword>
  <keyword>Atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Total Arterial Occlusions</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Blocked Arteries</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral Artery Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>PAD</keyword>
  <keyword>Intermittent Claudication</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Total Arterial Occlusion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intermittent Claudication</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

