<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00450021</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>070118</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>07-M-0118</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00450021</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imaging of Cannabinoid Receptors Using New Radioactive Tracer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Imaging of Cannabinoid CB(1) Receptors Using [11C] MePPEP</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health, Eli Lilly &amp; Co.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test a new radioactive tracer, [(11)C]MePPEP, for use in positron emission
      tomography (PET) imaging. The tracer is used to visualize cannabinoid receptors, proteins in
      the brain that mediate a variety of natural chemicals. These receptors may be important in
      behavioral diseases such as addiction, obesity and psychiatric diseases.

      Healthy normal volunteers between 18 and 65 years of age may be eligible for this study.

      Ten participants undergo whole body PET imaging to determine where the [(11)C]MePPEP tracer
      is distributed in the body in order to calculate radiation exposure from the tracer. Another
      10 subjects undergo brain imaging with [(11)C]MePPEP to measure cannabinoid receptors in the
      brain.

      All participants are evaluated with a medical history and physical examination, blood and
      urine tests and an electrocardiogram (ECG) before scanning. They then have a PET scan. For
      this procedure, a catheter (plastic tube) is placed in a vein in the arm through which the
      tracer is injected. A special mask is fitted to the head and attached to the bed to help keep
      the head in place during the scan. Subjects undergoing brain imaging also have a catheter
      placed in an artery in the wrist from which blood samples are collected during the procedure.
      The scan lasts about 2 to 2.5 hours.

      Subjects undergoing brain imaging also have magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) within 1 year of
      the PET scan. For MRI, the subject lies on a bed that moves into the tubular scanner, wearing
      earplugs to protect the ears from loud noises that occur during the scan. The procedure takes
      about 1 hour.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BRAIN IMAGING:

      OBJECTIVE:

      The central cannabinoid receptor, CB(1) is one of the most abundant neuromodulatory receptors
      in the brain. It is found on glutamatergic, dopaminergic and GABA-ergic synaptic terminals
      and belongs to the G-protein coupled receptor family. The CB(1) is a target for drug therapy,
      including the use of an antagonist as an appetite suppressant. The central cannabinoid
      receptor CB(1) has never been visualized in humans. In collaboration with Eli Lilly, we
      developed a promising PET ligand for the CB(1) receptor: [(11)C]MePPEP. This study is known
      by Eli Lilly as H6O-MC-GCEB.

      STUDY POPULATION:

      In the current protocol, we wish to evaluate [(11)C]MePPEP in approximately 15 healthy
      subjects.

      DESIGN:

      Brain imaging studies will consist of subject evaluation followed by PET and MRI scans.

      OUTCOME MEASURES:

      We intend to determine the kinetics of brain uptake and washout, clearance in the plasma, and
      the distribution volume of [(11)C]MePPEP calculated with compartmental modeling. Distribution
      volume is proportional to the density of receptors and is equal to the ratio at equilibrium
      of uptake in brain to the concentration of parent radiotracer in plasma.

      WHOLE BODY DOSIMETRY:

      OBJECTIVE:

      Should the brain imaging studies prove to be successful, we will continue with whole body
      dosimetry studies. Preliminary dosimetry studies with [(11)C]MePPEP have been performed in
      nonhuman primates; however, these need to be continued in humans before further investigation
      of this novel tracer can continue. This study is known by Eli Lilly as H6O-MC-GCEC.

      STUDY POPULATION:

      In the current protocol, we wish to evaluate [(11)C]MePPEP in approximately 10 additional
      healthy subjects.

      DESIGN:

      The whole body dosimetry studies will consist of subject evaluation followed by a PET scan.

      OUTCOME MEASURES:

      We intend to determine the whole body distribution of activity and thereby calculate
      radiation exposure to organs of the body.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 19, 2007</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 6, 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of novel PET tracer for DB! in Brain imaging.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and radiation dosimetry of PET tracer [11C] MePPEP; Distribution and variance of CB1 receptors in the brain of healthy controls</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>25</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[(11)C] MePPEP</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        All subjects must be healthy and aged 18-65 years, with history/physical exam, ECG, and
        laboratory tests within one year of the PET scan. The volunteer must sign an informed
        consent form.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Current psychiatric illness, substance abuse including marijuana use, or severe
             systemic disease based on history and physical exam.

          2. Laboratory tests with clinically significant abnormalities or positive urine
             toxicology screen.

          3. Prior participation in other research protocols in the last year such that radiation
             exposure would exceed the annual limits.

          4. Pregnancy and breast feeding.

          5. Claustrophobia.

          6. Presence of ferromagnetic metal in the body or heart pacemaker.

          7. Positive HIV test.

          8. Employee of the investigative site or an immediate family member of an employee of the
             investigative site. Immediate family member is defined as a spouse, parent, child, or
             sibling, whether biological or legally adopted.

          9. Employee of Eli Lilly and Company.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carson RE, Huang SC, Green MV. Weighted integration method for local cerebral blood flow measurements with positron emission tomography. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 1986 Apr;6(2):245-58.</citation>
    <PMID>3485644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 6, 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 20, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 21, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Robert B. Innis, M.D./National Institute of Mental Health</name_title>
    <organization>National Institutes of Health</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PET</keyword>
  <keyword>CB1 Receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Cannabinoid</keyword>
  <keyword>[11C] MePPEP</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

