<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00450788</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999907120</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>07-C-N120</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00450788</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Esophageal Cancer in Northeastern Iran</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Golestan Cohort Study of Esophageal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      -Esophageal cancer is the most common cancer in Iran s Golestan Province. Nutritional
      deficiencies, ethnicity and environmental exposures might contribute to the development of
      this disease.

      Objectives:

      -To better understand the cause of esophageal cancer in Golestan Province and to reduce its
      occurrence there.

      Eligibility:

      -Adults from the Gonbad, Aq-Qala and Kalaleh districts of eastern Golestan Province in Iran.

      Design:

        -  The study is a collaboration between NIH, the Digestive Disease Research Center of
           Teheran University of Medical Sciences, and the International Agency for Research on
           Cancer.

        -  Participants complete a lifestyle questionnaire and food frequency questionnaire.

        -  Samples of participants blood, urine, hair and toenail clippings are obtained.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Esophageal cancer is the sixth most common cause of cancer death worldwide, killing over
      380,000 people each year. Over 80% of esophageal cancers occur in developing countries, where
      the great majority of cases are squamous cell carcinomas. Esophageal cancer is characterized
      by striking geographic variation in incidence. One remarkable high-risk area, called the
      Central Asian Esophageal Cancer Belt, stretches from the Caspian Sea across Central Asia to
      northern China and includes focal areas with recorded incidence rates greater than
      100/10s/year in both genders. For the past 20 years, D CEG investigators have studied
      esophageal and gastric cancer in one of these extremely high-risk areas, Linxian, China, at
      the eastern end of the Belt. While these studies have discovered new risk factors for
      esophageal cancer in this region, they have produced an incomplete explanation of the
      etiology of this disease. Now we have the opportunity to perform similar studies in another
      of these extremely high-risk areas, Golestan Province, Iran, at the other end of the
      high-risk Belt. The people of Golestan, in northeastern Iran, are geographically, culturally
      and ethnically quite different from the people of Linxian, and they appear to be similar only
      in their extraordinarily high rates of esophageal cancer. Performing similar studies in these
      two exceptional populations will give us a better chance to identify important new modifiable
      risk factors for esophageal cancer in both places.

      Our cohort study is a collaboration between the Digestive Disease Research Center of Tehran
      University of Medical Sciences (DDRC), the International Agency for Research on Cancer
      (IARC), and DCEG. The study has recruited 50,000 adults in three administrative districts of
      eastern Golestan Province. Baseline assessments included lifestyle questionnaire, a
      semi-quantitative food frequency questionnaire, and collection of blood, hair, nails and
      urine. Follow up will includes active surveillance by a study team, aided by a comprehensive
      health network in the rural areas, a GI referral clinic in the largest town, and a provincial
      cancer registry. The main hypotheses include dietary hypotheses (low consumption of fruits
      and vegetables, high consumption of hot tea), exposure to potential carcinogens (tobacco,
      PAHs from non-tobacco sources), novel exposures (opium, animal contact), and genetic
      susceptibility. Some cross sectional and a few total mortality analyses have been completed.
      Annual follow-up is ongoing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 15, 2007</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer Incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>Continuous</time_frame>
    <description>The main hypotheses include dietary hypotheses (low consumption of fruits and vegetables, high consumption of hot tea), exposure to potential carcinogens (tobacco, PAHs from nontobacco sources), novel exposures (opium, animal contact), and genetic susceptibility.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Continuous</time_frame>
    <description>Some cross sectional and a few total mortality analyses have been completed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50000</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>GI Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study has recruited 50,000 adults in three administrative districts of eastern Golestan
        Province. Baseline assessments included lifestyle questionnaire, a semi-quantitative food
        frequency questionnaire, and collection of blood, hair, nails and urine. Follow up will
        includes active surveillance by a study team, aided by a comprehensive health network in
        the rural areas, a GI referral clinic in the largest town, and a provincial cancer
        registry.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  Ages 40 to 75

               -  Patients with esophogeal cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christian Abnet, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Digestive Disease Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tehran</city>
        <zip>14117-1313</zip>
        <country>Iran, Islamic Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Iran, Islamic Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pourshams A, Khademi H, Malekshah AF, Islami F, Nouraei M, Sadjadi AR, Jafari E, Rakhshani N, Salahi R, Semnani S, Kamangar F, Abnet CC, Ponder B, Day N, Dawsey SM, Boffetta P, Malekzadeh R. Cohort Profile: The Golestan Cohort Study--a prospective study of oesophageal cancer in northern Iran. Int J Epidemiol. 2010 Feb;39(1):52-9. doi: 10.1093/ije/dyp161. Epub 2009 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19332502</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malekshah AF, Kimiagar M, Saadatian-Elahi M, Pourshams A, Nouraie M, Goglani G, Hoshiarrad A, Sadatsafavi M, Golestan B, Yoonesi A, Rakhshani N, Fahimi S, Nasrollahzadeh D, Salahi R, Ghafarpour A, Semnani S, Steghens JP, Abnet CC, Kamangar F, Dawsey SM, Brennan P, Boffetta P, Malekzadeh R. Validity and reliability of a new food frequency questionnaire compared to 24 h recalls and biochemical measurements: pilot phase of Golestan cohort study of esophageal cancer. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2006 Aug;60(8):971-7. Epub 2006 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>16465196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pourshams A, Saadatian-Elahi M, Nouraie M, Malekshah AF, Rakhshani N, Salahi R, Yoonessi A, Semnani S, Islami F, Sotoudeh M, Fahimi S, Sadjadi AR, Nasrollahzadeh D, Aghcheli K, Kamangar F, Abnet CC, Saidi F, Sewram V, Strickland PT, Dawsey SM, Brennan P, Boffetta P, Malekzadeh R. Golestan cohort study of oesophageal cancer: feasibility and first results. Br J Cancer. 2005 Jan 17;92(1):176-81.</citation>
    <PMID>15597107</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 26, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 22, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Etiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Carcinogens</keyword>
  <keyword>Esophageal Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

