<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02471326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>150140</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>15-I-0140</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02471326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRC01) in People With Chronic HIV Infection Undergoing Analytical Treatment Interruption</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Exploratory, Open-Label Study of VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRC01) in Subjects With Chronic HIV Infection Undergoing Analytical Treatment Interruption</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - A combination of daily drugs (called cART) can keep human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) very
      low for a long time. But cART can lose effectiveness and cause permanent side effects. If
      treatment stops, HIV levels go up again. Researchers want to see if a new product can control
      HIV levels when a person is off cART.

      Objective:

      - To see if the new product VRC01 is safe and can control the HIV level in the blood when a
      person is not taking cART.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults ages 18-65 with HIV who are willing to interrupt their treatment for at least 24
      weeks.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with:

        -  Physical exam

        -  Medical history

        -  Heart tests

        -  Blood and urine tests.

        -  Their HIV drugs may be switched. They will keep taking them until a few days after Visit
           1.

        -  Visit 1: Repeat screening procedures.

        -  Participants will also have genetic testing and leukapheresis. For this, blood will be
           removed through a needle in one arm and circulated through a machine that removes white
           blood cells. The rest of the blood is returned through a needle in the other arm.

        -  They will get the first study drug dose through a thin tube in an arm vein for about 1
           hour.

        -  For 24 weeks, participants will have 16 visits. They will have blood drawn every visit.
           At some visits they will repeat the screening procedures and get another VRC01 dose.
           They may have another leukapheresis.

        -  Four weeks after the last dose, participants will restart their cART. For 20 weeks, they
           will have monthly visits to repeat the screening procedures and discuss new symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent advances in antibody cloning technologies have led to the discovery of a number of
      highly potent, HIV-specific, broadly neutralizing monoclonal antibodies from B cells of
      HIV-infected individuals. It has been shown that certain broadly neutralizing HIV-specific
      antibodies can prevent acquisition of the virus, suppress viral replication, delay and/or
      prevent plasma viral rebound following treatment interruption in Simian Immunodeficiency
      virus (SIV)-infected animals and block cell-to-cell transmission of laboratory-adapted HIV in
      vitro. However, it is unclear what in vivo effects these antibodies might have on plasma
      viral rebound in HIV-infected individuals following discontinuation of combination
      antiretroviral therapy (cART).

      In this regard, it has been shown that virtually all infected individuals who initiated cART
      during the chronic phase of infection experience plasma viral rebound upon cessation of
      therapy. Current research on the treatment of HIV-infected individuals has been heavily
      focused on developing strategies aimed at achieving sustained virologic remission in the
      absence of cART. Thus, it is of great interest to investigate whether a potent HIV-specific
      monoclonal antibody, such as VRC01, can prevent plasma viral rebound in infected individuals
      upon discontinuation of cART. We propose to examine the effect of VRC01 on plasma viral
      rebound in HIV-infected individuals following analytical treatment interruption (ATI).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 13, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 7, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 7, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Grade 3 or Higher Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>From the start of the initial infusion until up to 48 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint was the number of grade 3 or higher adverse events, including serious adverse events, that were possibly related to VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjects Who Met Criteria to Restart Antiretroviral Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 3 post initial infusion until up to 28 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary endpoint was the number of subjects who met protocol defined virologic (sustained HIV RNA &gt;1000 copies/mL by Abbott HIV RTPCR at 2 consecutive visits), immunologic (a confirmed &gt;30% decline in CD4 cell count or an absolute CD4 cell count &lt; 350 cells/mm3), or clinical criteria (HIV-related symptoms) to discontinue VRC01 infusions and restart Antiretroviral Therapy (ART).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV Positive Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRC01) given in HIV-infected Adults (age 18-65 years) on cART with suppressed viremia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRC01)</intervention_name>
    <description>A potent HIV-specific monoclonal antibody</description>
    <arm_group_label>HIV Positive Subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

               1. Age 18-65 years old.

               2. HIV-1 infection and clinically stable.

               3. In general good health and with an identified primary health care provider for
                  medical management of HIV infection and willing to maintain a relationship with a
                  primary health care provider for medical management of HIV infection while
                  participating in the study.

               4. CD4+ cell count &gt;450 cells/mm^3 at screening.

               5. Documentation of continuous cART treatment with suppression of plasma viral level
                  below the limit of detection for greater than or equal to 3 years. Subjects with
                  blips (i.e., detectable viral levels on cART) prior to screening may be included
                  provided they satisfy the following criteria:

                    1. The blips are &lt;400 copies/mL, and

                    2. Succeeding viral levels return to levels below the limit of detection on
                       subsequent testing.

               6. Willingness to undergo ATI.

               7. Laboratory values within pre-defined limits at screening:

                    1. Absolute neutrophil count &gt;1,000/mm^3.

                    2. Hemoglobin levels &gt;10.0 g/dL for men and &gt;9.0 g/dL for women.

                    3. Platelet count &gt;100,000/mm^3.

                    4. Prothrombin time (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &lt;1.5 upper limit
                       of normal (ULN).

                    5. Estimated or a measured creatinine clearance rate of greater than or equal
                       to 50 mL/min as determined by the NIH Clinical Center laboratory.

                    6. AST and ALT levels of &lt;2.5 x ULN.

               8. Willingness to have samples stored for future research.

        Reproductive Risks

        Contraception: The effects of VRC01 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this
        reason, men and women of childbearing potential must agree to use adequate pregnancy
        prevention per the investigator. This includes highly reliable established lifestyle of
        complete abstinence of potentially reproductive sexual activity, or use of BOTH a long term
        hormonal or barrier (e.g. implant, depot injection, IUD in female participant or female
        partner of participant) method of contraception that is fully effective prior to dosing,
        COMBINED WITH a barrier method (male or female condom) for all potentially reproductive
        sexual activity. Pregnancy prevention must be maintained as effective and practiced
        continuously for the duration of study participation. Females of childbearing-age must have
        a negative pregnancy test result prior to receiving VRC01. During the course of the study,
        if a female participant, or the partner of a male participant suspects or in fact becomes
        pregnant, the effected participant should inform the study staff immediately, as well as
        the woman's primary care physician. Subjects must use safe sex practices during the trial,
        and particularly during the ATI phase, when risk of transmission of HIV may be increased.

          -  EXCLUSION CRITERIA

               1. Chronic hepatitis B, as evidenced by a positive test for hepatitis B surface
                  antigen (HBsAg), or chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection, as evidenced by a
                  positive test for HCV RNA. Subjects with a positive test for HCV antibody and a
                  negative test for HCV RNA are eligible.

               2. Documented virologic failure to &gt;1 cART regimen.

               3. HIV immunotherapy or vaccine(s) received within 1 year prior to screening.

               4. Any licensed or experimental non-HIV vaccination (e.g., hepatitis B, influenza,
                  pneumococcal polysaccharide) received within 2 weeks prior to study enrollment.

               5. Receipt of other investigational study agent within 28 days of enrollment.

               6. Any active malignancy that may require systemic chemotherapy or radiation
                  therapy.

               7. Systemic immunosuppressive medications received within 3 months prior to
                  enrollment (Not excluded: corticosteroid nasal spray or inhaler; topical
                  corticosteroids for mild, uncomplicated dermatitis; or oral/parenteral
                  corticosteroids administered for non-chronic conditions not expected to recur
                  [length of therapy less than or equal to 10 days, with completion in greater than
                  or equal to 30 days prior to enrollment]).

               8. History or other clinical evidence of:

                    1. Significant or unstable cardiac disease (e.g., angina, congestive heart
                       failure, recent myocardial infarction).

                    2. Severe illness, malignancy, immunodeficiency other than HIV, or any other
                       condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would make the subject
                       unsuitable for the study.

               9. Active drug or alcohol use or any other pattern of behavior that, in the opinion
                  of the investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

              10. Breast-feeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael C Sneller, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2015-I-0140.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou T, Georgiev I, Wu X, Yang ZY, Dai K, Finzi A, Kwon YD, Scheid JF, Shi W, Xu L, Yang Y, Zhu J, Nussenzweig MC, Sodroski J, Shapiro L, Nabel GJ, Mascola JR, Kwong PD. Structural basis for broad and potent neutralization of HIV-1 by antibody VRC01. Science. 2010 Aug 13;329(5993):811-7. doi: 10.1126/science.1192819. Epub 2010 Jul 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20616231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shingai M, Nishimura Y, Klein F, Mouquet H, Donau OK, Plishka R, Buckler-White A, Seaman M, Piatak M Jr, Lifson JD, Dimitrov DS, Nussenzweig MC, Martin MA. Antibody-mediated immunotherapy of macaques chronically infected with SHIV suppresses viraemia. Nature. 2013 Nov 14;503(7475):277-80. doi: 10.1038/nature12746. Epub 2013 Oct 30.</citation>
    <PMID>24172896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chun TW, Murray D, Justement JS, Blazkova J, Hallahan CW, Fankuchen O, Gittens K, Benko E, Kovacs C, Moir S, Fauci AS. Broadly neutralizing antibodies suppress HIV in the persistent viral reservoir. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2014 Sep 9;111(36):13151-6. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1414148111. Epub 2014 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>25157148</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>May 12, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>October 2, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">October 31, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV Neutralizing Antibodies</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>NIH Biomedical Translational Research Information System</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>HIV Positive Subjects</title>
          <description>Drug: VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1), 40 mg/kg in 100 mL Normal Saline; VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1) is a potent HIV-specific monoclonal antibody which was given at Baseline, Week 2, and then every 4 weeks for up to a total of 8 doses</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="10"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="9"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>HIV Positive Subjects</title>
          <description>Drug: VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1), 40 mg/kg in 100 mL Normal Saline; VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1) is a potent HIV-specific monoclonal antibody which was given at Baseline, Week 2, and then every 4 weeks for up to a total of 8 doses</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="10"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Ethnicity (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>More than one race</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Grade 3 or Higher Adverse Events</title>
        <description>The primary endpoint was the number of grade 3 or higher adverse events, including serious adverse events, that were possibly related to VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1).</description>
        <time_frame>From the start of the initial infusion until up to 48 weeks.</time_frame>
        <population>The analyses included all subjects who received at least one infusion of VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1).</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>HIV Positive Subjects</title>
            <description>Drug: VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1), 40 mg/kg in 100 mL Normal Saline; VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1) is a potent HIV-specific monoclonal antibody which was given at Baseline, Week 2, and then every 4 weeks for up to a total of 8 doses</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Grade 3 or Higher Adverse Events</title>
          <description>The primary endpoint was the number of grade 3 or higher adverse events, including serious adverse events, that were possibly related to VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1).</description>
          <population>The analyses included all subjects who received at least one infusion of VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1).</population>
          <units>Events</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Subjects Who Met Criteria to Restart Antiretroviral Therapy</title>
        <description>The secondary endpoint was the number of subjects who met protocol defined virologic (sustained HIV RNA &gt;1000 copies/mL by Abbott HIV RTPCR at 2 consecutive visits), immunologic (a confirmed &gt;30% decline in CD4 cell count or an absolute CD4 cell count &lt; 350 cells/mm3), or clinical criteria (HIV-related symptoms) to discontinue VRC01 infusions and restart Antiretroviral Therapy (ART).</description>
        <time_frame>From Day 3 post initial infusion until up to 28 weeks.</time_frame>
        <population>The analyses included all subjects who received at least one infusion of VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1).</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>HIV Positive Subjects</title>
            <description>Drug: VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1), 40 mg/kg in 100 mL Normal Saline; VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1) is a potent HIV-specific monoclonal antibody which was given at Baseline, Week 2, and then every 4 weeks for up to a total of 8 doses</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Subjects Who Met Criteria to Restart Antiretroviral Therapy</title>
          <description>The secondary endpoint was the number of subjects who met protocol defined virologic (sustained HIV RNA &gt;1000 copies/mL by Abbott HIV RTPCR at 2 consecutive visits), immunologic (a confirmed &gt;30% decline in CD4 cell count or an absolute CD4 cell count &lt; 350 cells/mm3), or clinical criteria (HIV-related symptoms) to discontinue VRC01 infusions and restart Antiretroviral Therapy (ART).</description>
          <population>The analyses included all subjects who received at least one infusion of VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1).</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>up to 48 Weeks</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>HIV Positive Subjects</title>
          <description>Drug: VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1), 40 mg/kg in 100 mL Normal Saline; VRC-HIVMAB060-00-AB (VRCO1) is a potent HIV-specific monoclonal antibody which was given at Baseline, Week 2, and then every 4 weeks for up to a total of 8 doses</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA (20.00)</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vomiting</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA (20.00)</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="10" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Chest pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Influenza like illness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Localised oedema</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhoea infectious</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Herpes simplex</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nasopharyngitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Tinea versicolour</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Investigations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Alanine aminotransferase increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Aspartate aminotransferase increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Blood bicarbonate decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Blood calcium decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Blood glucose increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Blood phosphorus decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Blood sodium decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neutrophil count decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperglycaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Psychiatric disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Insomnia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Reproductive system and breast disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gynaecomastia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cough</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Oropharyngeal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rhinorrhoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sinus congestion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rash</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Sneller, Michael</name_or_title>
      <organization>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases</organization>
      <phone>+1 301 496 0491</phone>
      <email>MSNELLER@niaid.nih.gov</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

