<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02476903</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015Salvo</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02476903</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Viscosupplementation in the Hip Following Hip Arthroscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Viscosupplementation in the Hip Following Hip Arthroscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rothman Institute Orthopaedics</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sean McMillan, DO</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rothman Institute Orthopaedics</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hip arthroscopy is a rapidly evolving procedure that has seen an exponential increase in the
      number of cases performed yearly. With hip arthroscopy still in its infancy in relation to
      knee and shoulder arthroscopy, there are still many questions yet to be answered. Axioms that
      were once thought to be true regarding indications and treatment for hip arthroscopy are
      continually being revised. As with the knee and shoulder before it, the hip is now graduating
      into treatment avenues that were otherwise thought to only be possible through an open
      surgical procedure.

      Viscosupplementation in patients post arthroscopy with known articular cartilage injury has
      been shown to be efficacious. The pathophysiology of hyaline degradation during the arthritic
      process within the knee has been studied, and with this understanding has grown the
      widespread usage of viscosupplementation. While questions still exist regarding the
      effectiveness of viscosupplementation in non-weightbearing joints, it appears the benefits
      seen in the weight bearing joints, such as the knee, are apparent
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Using Visual Analog Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using Visual Analog Scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Monovisc</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Preoperative inclusion criteria will be made via x-ray and MRI evaluation. These criteria
        shall include: 2 mm or greater joint space preservation of the hip on radiographs, absence
        of acetabular subcortical bone cysts, Tonnis Score less than 2 on radiographs, and patient
        age greater than 18.4 Intra-operative evaluation of the cartilage will be performed by the
        surgeon on both the acetabular and femoral head sides. Patients shall be included if the
        osteochondral defect meets Outerbridge Classification criteria of stage II or greater.
        Furthermore the lesion shall be greater than 1cm in size (and thus not amenable to other
        procedures such as microfracture). Subjects must be willing to sign the IRB-approved
        informed consent and be older than 18 years old.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        All patients 55 years of age and older. All patients with previous hip surgery on a
        concomitant side. Patients who present a history of radiculopathy or regional pain
        syndrome. Patients with a worker's compensation claim or pending litigation claim. Patients
        with Outerbridge Grade IV changes on either acetabular or femoral articular cartilage.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 19, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 19, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

