<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02474862</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01NR014540-01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02474862</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Expectations - A Program for Pregnant Women Experiencing Depressive Symptoms</brief_title>
  <acronym>HE</acronym>
  <official_title>RCT of a Tailored Walking Program to Reduce Stress Among Pregnant Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Butler Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Women and Infants Hospital of Rhode Island</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Butler Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomized control trial (RCT) evaluating a Prenatal Walking Program (PWP) in
      comparison to a Postpartum Prep Program (PPP) comparison group for pregnant women
      experiencing depressive symptoms. In addition to assessing changes in depressive symptoms,
      the investigators will examine other key maternal outcomes (maternal functioning, pain,
      anxiety, stress, fatigue), as well as infant outcomes including birth record data (gestation,
      weight, Apgar scores, etc) and careful, in-person assessment of infant neurobiological
      functioning at 30 days postpartum.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Depressive symptoms are prevalent among pregnant women, and they are consistently linked with
      adverse outcomes for both women and infants, including higher rates of spontaneous abortion,
      preeclampsia, operative delivery, and postpartum depression. Additional risks to offspring
      include pre-term delivery, neonatal growth retardation, low birth weight, and delayed
      developmental milestones. In spite of these risks, the vast majority of affected women do not
      pursue any type of mental health treatment. Many women are reluctant to use antidepressants -
      or anything that could potentially harm the baby - prenatally. Because pregnant women have
      unique concerns regarding treatment acceptability, a critical need exists to develop
      interventions that are not only efficacious in reducing depressive symptoms, but are also
      viewed as acceptable by pregnant women.

      Increased physical activity has numerous advantages as a strategy for improving mood during
      pregnancy, and prior research has shown that physical activity interventions can be effective
      in treating depressive symptoms in the general population. Physical activity interventions
      are also inexpensive, safe, and associated with a variety of positive health outcomes.

      In spite of its potential as an acceptable and efficacious strategy for improving prenatal
      mood, few studies have evaluated physical activity as an intervention for pregnant women with
      depressive symptoms. Existing exercise programs that have been tested for reducing depressive
      symptoms in the general population are not likely to be appropriate or feasible for pregnant
      women. In light of this important gap, the investigators interdisciplinary team developed a
      gentle, 10-week, pedometer walking intervention tailored for pregnant women, the Prenatal
      Walking Program (PWP) and preliminarily evaluated PWP in an open trial, finding the
      intervention to be safe, feasible, and acceptable.

      The current RCT will now evaluate PWP in comparison to a health education control comparison
      group tailored for perinatal women, called the Postpartum Prep Program (PPP). In addition to
      assessing changes in depressive symptoms, the investigators will examine other key maternal
      outcomes (maternal functioning, pain, anxiety, stress, fatigue), as well as infant outcomes
      including birth record data and in-person assessment of infant neurobiological functioning.
      Further, the investigators will examine evidence for potential behavioral, psychological, and
      biological mechanisms of action that mediate a possible treatment effect. Up to 152 pregnant
      women reporting elevated depressive symptoms during the current pregnancy will be enrolled
      and randomized into one of two groups, PWP or PPP, and will participate in blinded follow-up
      evaluations at multiple time-points throughout pregnancy and postpartum.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression symptom severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in depression severity at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>The Quick Inventory of Depression Symptoms (QIDS) is the primary outcome measure and will be used to assess depression symptom severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity level</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in physical activity level at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>Objective measurement using accelerometry and self-report</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in anxiety level at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>State Anxiety Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in perceived stress at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived Stress Scale -10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health status</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in health status at week 10</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in physical functioing at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS)- Short Form v1.0 - Phys. Function 10a</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in pain at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS)- Pain Short Form v1.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in fatigue at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS)- Short Form v1.0 - Fatigue 8a Participant Version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy discomfort</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in pregnancy at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>Maternal Physical Discomfort Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in quality of life at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire - Short Form</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attachment to fetus/infant</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in attachment to the fetus at week 10</time_frame>
    <description>Maternal Antenatal Attachment Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>30-days postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be based on a composite of measures relating to labor &amp; delivery outcomes (e.g. gestational age) and infant neurobehavioral functioning (i.e., the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit Network Neurobehavioral Scale; NNNS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">152</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prenatal Walking Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Prenatal Walking Program (PWP) is a gentle walking intervention tailored for pregnant women. The PWP intervention consists of 3 components: 1) biweekly session with a study interventionist; 2) the use of activity monitors to increase motivation and self-monitoring; 3) incentives to promote intervention adherence.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Postpartum Prep Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the Postpartum Prep Program control condition (PPP) participants will attend individually education sessions matched in number and duration to the sessions in PWP. PPP involves providing health information particularly relevant to expectant mothers, including both maternal and newborn wellbeing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prenatal Walking Program</intervention_name>
    <description>PWP is a gentle walking intervention tailored for pregnant women.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prenatal Walking Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Postpartum Prep Program</intervention_name>
    <description>PPP participants will attend individually education sessions matched in number and duration to the sessions in PWP. PPP involves providing health information particularly relevant to expectant mothers, including both maternal and newborn well being.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Postpartum Prep Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. women aged 18 or over

          2. 12-27 weeks gestation with a healthy singleton pregnancy

          3. English-speaking

          4. cleared by prenatal provider for moderate intensity exercise

          5. experiencing moderate depressive symptom elevations at time of enrollment (QIDS-C;
             8-20); (6) physically inactive or low-active at time of enrollment (mean &lt; 90
             minutes/week of moderate intensity exercise, over the last 3 months).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. recently started pharmacologic or psychosocial treatment for depressive symptoms
             within the past 4 weeks, or recently changed dose or treatment regimen in the past 4
             weeks

          2. current/recent acute suicidal symptoms

          3. current substance use disorder

          4. psychotic symptoms or cognitive impairment

          5. current eating disorder

          6. current or lifetime bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, or schizoaffective disorder.

               -  Finally, while the following will not exclude participants from enrollment in the
                  study, women meeting these two criteria will be excluded from participating in
                  the blood draw component examining inflammatory markers:

          7. current significant physical or neurological illness, ie., acute or chronic
             infectious, inflammatory or immune disorders

          8. regular use of aspirin or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cynthia Battle, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Butler Hospitl/Brown Unversity</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rita Rossi, MA</last_name>
    <phone>401-455-6303</phone>
    <email>rrossi@butler.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Brie Scott, BA</last_name>
    <phone>401-455-6303</phone>
    <email>bscott@butler.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Butler Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02906</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cynthia Battle, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>401-455-6371</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 18, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Butler Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cynthia Battle</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor (Research)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

