<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02471287</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>150128</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>15-EI-0128</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02471287</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetics of Inherited Eye Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Genetics of Inherited Eye Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Research has identified some of the genes involved in inherited eye diseases. But for many of
      these diseases, the genes are not yet known. Researchers want to try to find these genes.
      They also hope to learn more about how symptoms differ in people with similar gene changes.

      Objective:

      To learn more about genes involved in eye diseases.

      Eligibility:

      People who have a known or suspected inherited eye disease, and their relatives.

      Design:

        -  All participants will have a medical history, physical exam, and eye exam. They may have
           blood taken.

        -  Participants with an eye disease may have eye cell samples taken using a swab or biopsy
           procedure.

        -  Participants may have a skin biopsy. A (Omega)-inch piece of skin will be removed.

        -  Participants may have blood drawn and the red blood cells removed. The remaining serum
           will be made into an eye drop solution for the participant.

        -  Participants may provide samples of tears, urine, saliva, stool, hair, or inner cheek
           cells.

        -  Participants may have a retina test. They may also have a test that uses light to
           measure retina thickness.

        -  Participants may have an eye movement test. Electrodes will be placed on the skin next
           to both eyes.

        -  Participants may have a fluorescein angiography. A dye will be given through an
           intravenous line in the arm. A camera will take pictures of the dye as it flows through
           the eyes blood vessels.

        -  Participants may have microperimetry. They will sit at a computer screen and press a
           button when they see a light.

        -  Participants may have an eye movement test. They will wear contact lenses or goggles and
           watch a series of spots on a computer screen.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVE:

      Molecular genetics and genomics are revolutionizing the delivery of medicine in general and
      ophthalmology in particular. New treatment and prevention strategies rely on a detailed
      understanding of the genetics and molecular pathogenesis of vision-threatening disease. In
      addition, in order to determine whether an intervention is therapeutic, we must first have
      some understanding of what the best clinical outcome variables are for measuring a treatment
      effect. Because our ultimate goal is to develop disease-specific protocols for specific
      inherited conditions, establishing this protocol will help us establish an initial critical
      mass of patients and of knowledge to write such protocols; as such, this protocol will be
      hypothesis generating. A secondary aim of this protocol is to provide a mechanism for
      obtaining research samples from subjects that may be used for laboratory investigations; in
      this case, the basic research may be both hypothesis generating and/or hypothesis testing.
      Lastly, the Ophthalmic Genetics Branch, as a leader in the field and a sponsor of a clinical
      training program, should have the ability to serve as a tertiary referral center for the
      nation in the area of undiagnosed genetic eye diseases.

      STUDY POPULATION:

      One thousand (1000) individuals with inherited eye diseases and their relatives will be
      enrolled.

      DESIGN:

      This is a combined evaluation/treatment protocol and a genetic repository study. In general,
      participants will undergo a complete, age-appropriate, baseline examination and provide a
      blood sample. Some participants may undergo more specialized ophthalmic and/or systemic
      testing, if felt clinically indicated by the investigator. In some cases, collection of
      readily available body fluids (e.g., urine, saliva) and/or a punch skin biopsy may also be
      performed for diagnostic and/or research purposes.

      OUTCOME MEASURES:

      Given the breadth of ages and disease processes covered under this protocol, we will not
      systematically obtain any single outcome variable beyond visual acuity on research subjects.
      However, detailed, disease-specific findings will be collected through the NEI electronic
      medical record. Findings from systemic testing and from outside exams may be tabulated in a
      separate, secure database in the laboratory of the Principal Investigator (PI).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 12, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Since this is an evaluation and treatment and repository protocol, there are no formal outcomes to be measured; however all patients in the NEI clinic have visual acuity measured at every visit, so this can be used as a measure of adverse exper...</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Genetic Eye Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Participants will be eligible if they:

          1. Have a known or suspected inherited eye disease OR are an unaffected (usually first
             degree) relative of a participant with a known or suspected inherited eye disease.

          2. Have the ability to cooperate with an age-appropriate eye exam.

          3. Have the ability to understand and sign an informed consent or have a parent/legal
             guardian to do so if they are minor children.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Participants will not be eligible if:

          1. They are unwilling or unable to be followed as clinically indicated.

          2. They have a clear, non-genetic disease etiology (unless they are an unaffected
             relative).

          3. Their participation would not contribute to the NEI research mission, at the
             discretion of the PI.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wadih Zein, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Eye Institute (NEI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniel W Claus, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-9058</phone>
    <email>daniel.claus@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2015-EI-0128.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 13, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ocular Genetic Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>GENETIC DISEASE</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Eye Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

