<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02474966</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3403/23.10.14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02474966</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Deep TMS on the Permeability of the BBB in Patients With Glioblastoma Multiforme: a Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Deep Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation on the Permeability of the Blood-brain Barrier in Patients With Glioblastoma Multiforme: a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Roma La Sapienza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Roma La Sapienza</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The blood-brain barrier (BBB) is a specialized interface allowing a unique environment for
      neuro-glia networks. BBB dysfunction is common in brain disorders. The Transcranial Magnetic
      Stimulation (TMS) is a non-invasive method of stimulating cortical motor neurons with the use
      of rapidly changing electromagnetic fields generated by a coil placed over the scalp. The
      objective of this study is to evaluate the safety and effects of the deep TMS (dTMS) on
      barrier integrity in patients with malignant glial tumors. BBB permeability will be
      quantified using dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (DCE-MRI). Permeability
      change will be compared between two DCE-MRI scans performed immediately after &quot;real&quot; and
      &quot;sham&quot; rTMS, randomly assigned within one week of each other.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The blood-brain barrier (BBB) is a specialized interface allowing a unique environment for
      neuro-glia networks. BBB dysfunction is common in brain disorders. However, the mechanisms
      underlying BBB opening are poorly understood. The investigators suggest a novel mechanism
      modulating BBB integrity and therapeutic implications in patients with glioblastoma
      multiforme. The Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) is a noninvasive method of
      stimulating cortical motor neurons through the scalp and skull capable of inducing electrical
      currents and depolarizing neurons in focal brain areas with the use of rapidly changing
      electromagnetic fields generated by a coil placed over the scalp. The objective of this study
      is to evaluate the safety and effects of the deep TMS (dTMS) on barrier integrity in 20
      patients with malignant glial tumors (glioblastoma multiforme). BBB permeability will be
      quantified using dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (DCE-MRI). Permeability
      change will be compared between two DCE-MRI scans performed immediately after &quot;real&quot; and
      &quot;sham&quot; dTMS, randomly assigned within one week of each other.

      Design of study: Randomized double-blind crossover study. Patients will present on two
      consecutive days in order to receive dTMS followed by DCE-MRI. Subjects will be randomized
      into two groups: the first group will be treated before with real-dTMS (the first day) and
      after with sham-dTMS (the second day); the second group will be treated before with sham-dTMS
      (the first day) and after with real-dTMS (the second day). At the end of each session of dTMS
      the patients will undergo by MRI exams.

      Enrolled patients: twenty patients with glioblastoma multiforme treated with craniotomy and
      gross tumor resection or maximal debulking at least a year prior to the study and treated
      with standard post-operative radiotherapy and adjuvant chemotherapy.

      dTMS will be delivered at 1 Hz, on the anterior periphery of the resected tumor bed using the
      Hesed-coil (H-coil) (Brainsway Ltd., Jerusalem, Israel). Sham stimulation will be delivered
      with a sham coil placed in the same helmet able to produce similar sounds and scalp
      sensations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in blood-brain barrier permeability</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <description>The efficacy of the deep Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (dTMS) in modulating blood-brain barrier permeability in patients with glioblastoma multiforme through the measurement of the average value of the slope-value distribution function (CDF) evidenced with dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety of the deep Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (dTMS) applied in patients with glioblastoma multiforme</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme of Brain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Real-Sham dTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will be treated before with real deep Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (dTMS) (the first day) and after with sham dTMS (the second day)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham-Real dTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will be treated before with sham deep Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (dTMS) (the first day) and after with real dTMS (the second day)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deep Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (dTMS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will present on two consecutive days in order to receive dTMS followed by dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging (DCE-MRI). Subjects will be randomized into two groups: the first group will be treated before with real-dTMS (the first day) and after with sham-dTMS (the second day); the second group will be treated before with sham-dTMS (the first day) and after with realTMS (the second day). At the end of each session of dTMS the patients will undergo by MRI exams.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Real-Sham dTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham-Real dTMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histological diagnosis of glioblastoma multiforme (WHO grade IV)

          -  Craniotomy with resection of the tumor at least one year prior to the study

          -  Treatment with steroids or chemotherapy stable for at least four weeks prior to study
             enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of epilepsy

          -  Presence of cardiac pacemaker

          -  Presence of neurostimulators

          -  Presence of surgical clips or medical pumps

          -  Allergy to contrast medium for Magnetic Resonance Imaging

          -  History of head injuries

          -  Alcoholism or drugs abuse

          -  State of pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Severe psychiatric disorders
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maurizio Inghilleri, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University &quot;Sapienza&quot; of Rome</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abbott NJ, Patabendige AA, Dolman DE, Yusof SR, Begley DJ. Structure and function of the blood-brain barrier. Neurobiol Dis. 2010 Jan;37(1):13-25. doi: 10.1016/j.nbd.2009.07.030. Epub 2009 Aug 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19664713</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bolwig TG, Hertz MM, Paulson OB, Spotoft H, Rafaelsen OJ. The permeability of the blood-brain barrier during electrically induced seizures in man. Eur J Clin Invest. 1977 Apr;7(2):87-93.</citation>
    <PMID>404164</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Côté J, Bovenzi V, Savard M, Dubuc C, Fortier A, Neugebauer W, Tremblay L, Müller-Esterl W, Tsanaclis AM, Lepage M, Fortin D, Gobeil F Jr. Induction of selective blood-tumor barrier permeability and macromolecular transport by a biostable kinin B1 receptor agonist in a glioma rat model. PLoS One. 2012;7(5):e37485. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0037485. Epub 2012 May 21. Erratum in: PLoS One. 2012;7(6): doi/10.1371/annotation/6b95427c-645d-4f1b-a648-ceb215129583.</citation>
    <PMID>22629405</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hirschberg H, Uzal FA, Chighvinadze D, Zhang MJ, Peng Q, Madsen SJ. Disruption of the blood-brain barrier following ALA-mediated photodynamic therapy. Lasers Surg Med. 2008 Oct;40(8):535-42. doi: 10.1002/lsm.20670.</citation>
    <PMID>18798293</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pardridge WM. The blood-brain barrier: bottleneck in brain drug development. NeuroRx. 2005 Jan;2(1):3-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15717053</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Prager O, Chassidim Y, Klein C, Levi H, Shelef I, Friedman A. Dynamic in vivo imaging of cerebral blood flow and blood-brain barrier permeability. Neuroimage. 2010 Jan 1;49(1):337-44. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2009.08.009. Epub 2009 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19682584</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rossi S, Hallett M, Rossini PM, Pascual-Leone A; Safety of TMS Consensus Group. Safety, ethical considerations, and application guidelines for the use of transcranial magnetic stimulation in clinical practice and research. Clin Neurophysiol. 2009 Dec;120(12):2008-39. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2009.08.016. Epub 2009 Oct 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19833552</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Roth Y, Zangen A, Hallett M. A coil design for transcranial magnetic stimulation of deep brain regions. J Clin Neurophysiol. 2002 Aug;19(4):361-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12436090</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wassermann EM, Zimmermann T. Transcranial magnetic brain stimulation: therapeutic promises and scientific gaps. Pharmacol Ther. 2012 Jan;133(1):98-107. doi: 10.1016/j.pharmthera.2011.09.003. Epub 2011 Sep 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21924290</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zangen A, Roth Y, Voller B, Hallett M. Transcranial magnetic stimulation of deep brain regions: evidence for efficacy of the H-coil. Clin Neurophysiol. 2005 Apr;116(4):775-9. Epub 2004 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>15792886</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zimmermann R, Schmitt H, Rotter A, Sperling W, Kornhuber J, Lewczuk P. Transient increase of plasma concentrations of amyloid β peptides after electroconvulsive therapy. Brain Stimul. 2012 Jan;5(1):25-9. doi: 10.1016/j.brs.2011.01.007. Epub 2011 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22037136</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sharp CD, Hines I, Houghton J, Warren A, Jackson TH 4th, Jawahar A, Nanda A, Elrod JW, Long A, Chi A, Minagar A, Alexander JS. Glutamate causes a loss in human cerebral endothelial barrier integrity through activation of NMDA receptor. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2003 Dec;285(6):H2592-8. Epub 2003 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>12893641</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mottaghy FM, Gangitano M, Horkan C, Chen Y, Pascual-Leone A, Schlaug G. Repetitive TMS temporarily alters brain diffusion. Neurology. 2003 May 13;60(9):1539-41.</citation>
    <PMID>12743250</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chassidim Y, Veksler R, Lublinsky S, Pell GS, Friedman A, Shelef I. Quantitative imaging assessment of blood-brain barrier permeability in humans. Fluids Barriers CNS. 2013 Feb 7;10(1):9. doi: 10.1186/2045-8118-10-9.</citation>
    <PMID>23388348</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Baker GJ, Yadav VN, Motsch S, Koschmann C, Calinescu AA, Mineharu Y, Camelo-Piragua SI, Orringer D, Bannykh S, Nichols WS, deCarvalho AC, Mikkelsen T, Castro MG, Lowenstein PR. Mechanisms of glioma formation: iterative perivascular glioma growth and invasion leads to tumor progression, VEGF-independent vascularization, and resistance to antiangiogenic therapy. Neoplasia. 2014 Jul;16(7):543-61. doi: 10.1016/j.neo.2014.06.003.</citation>
    <PMID>25117977</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 18, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 17, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 17, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 18, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Roma La Sapienza</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maurizio Inghilleri</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

