<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02473237</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C 22-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02473237</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy in Walked Distance of Indacaterol vs Tiotropium in Women With COPD Secondary to Biomass (EMERALD)</brief_title>
  <acronym>EMERAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Acute Effects on Walked Distance froM basEline and Post Dose of indacateRol vs Tiotropium in Women With modeRAte to Severe COPD Secondary to Biomass Exposure: Open Label Crossover Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Respiratory Diseases, Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Respiratory Diseases, Mexico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) secondary to biomass exposure constitutes a
      chronic respiratory condition frequently excluded from large clinical trials. Biomass
      exposure COPD have some histopathologic, clinical, radiological and functional differences
      with tobacco smoke COPD. However, until now, there are no evidence in this patients about the
      clinical response to bronchodilators routinely used in tobacco smoke COPD.

      Primary objective: To compare changes in walked meters from baseline on six minute walking
      test (6MWT) to 23:45 hours after one dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium in patients with
      moderate to severe COPD secondary to biomass exposure.

      Secondary objectives: To compare changes in pulmonary function (inspiratory capacity, Forced
      Expiratory Volume in first second (FEV1) milliliters, FEV1 &quot;through&quot;) from baseline (-10
      minutes) to 23:45 hours after one dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium in patients with moderate
      to severe COPD secondary to biomass exposure.

      This will be an open label study, double blinded, cross over and conducted at specialized
      respiratory care center (National Institute of Respiratory Diseases), to compare the acute
      effects of ultra long acting bronchodilators used in tobacco smoke exposure COPD. Unicentric
      study.

      Ethics Committee approbation: C 22-12
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Until now, COPD secondary to biomass exposure is treated in similar way that COPD
      due to tobacco smoke. Unfortunately none of the clinical trial included patient with biomass
      exposure in their multicenter studies. COPD due to biomass exposure is very common in Mexico
      and in other sub-developed countries, and represent a high economy burden similar as the
      tobacco exposure. In Mexico, in a reference center of COPD (National Institute of Respiratory
      Disease) thirty percent of women who attended with COPD has only the antecedent to cook with
      biomass. These patients have a predominant airway component, rather than emphysema. These
      patients have chronic bronchitis as a main clinical picture and in consequence, more
      exacerbations. Additionally, they present more symptoms such as dyspnea, and as COPD
      secondary to tobacco exposure, the functional and inspiratory capacity are reduced. There are
      previous studies that described the acute effects of long acting bronchodilators like
      salmeterol on functional and inspiratory capacity. However, they were done in patients with
      COPD secondary to tobacco smoke and there are not studies done in patients with COPD
      secondary to biomass exposition. Indacaterol a novel long-acting bronchodilator provide 24 h
      bronchodilation on once-daily dosing with a fast onset of action. Assuming the conditions of
      patients with COPD secondary to biomass exposure (women, rural or suburban origin, etc.) it
      is necessary strategies that enhance the adherence. There is information about better
      adherence with the least frequency of a drug. Tiotropium provide 24 h bronchodilation on
      once-daily dosing with a slow onset of action, it was selected because it is widely used in
      the treatment of COPD and is the only drug of the therapeutic class (long acting
      antimuscarinic bronchodilator) available in the market.

      Until now there is no international nor national reported experience with any bronchodilators
      in COPD secondary to biomass.

      This will be the first clinical trial in the world that attempts to evaluate the acute
      effects (fast onset action) of those two long acting bronchodilators, in women with COPD
      secondary to biomass exposure. Besides, the results will help to highlight the need in the
      rest of the world to include these patients in the different multicenter studies.

      Primary objective:

      To compare changes in walked meters from baseline six minute walking test (6MWT) to 23:45
      hours after one dose of Indacaterol (150µg) vs Tiotropium (18µg) in patients with moderate to
      severe COPD secondary to biomass exposure.

      Secondary efficacy Objectives are:

        1. To compare changes in Inspiratory Capacity (IC) from baseline (-10 minutes) to 30, 60,
           240 minutes and 23:45 hours post dose of Indacaterol (150 µg) vs Tiotropium (18µg) in
           patients with with biomass smoke COPD.

        2. To compare changes in FEV1 from baseline (-10 minutes) to 30, 60, 240 min and 23:45
           hours post dose of Indacaterol (150 µg) vs Tiotropium (18µg) in patients with biomass
           smoke COPD.

        3. To compare the 'trough' FEV1 (mean of values at 23 h 10 min and 23 h 45 min post-dose)
           after one dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium in patients with COPD secondary to biomass
           exposure.

        4. To compare changes in dyspnea perception by using the Borg scale from baseline (-10
           minutes) to 30, 60, 240 min and 23:45 hours post dose of Indacaterol (150 µg) vs
           Tiotropium (18 µg) in patients with COPD secondary to biomass exposure.

        5. To compare the frequency of adverse events presented during the study, between
           indacaterol vs tiotropium arm.

      Methodology:

      This will be an open label study conducted at specialized respiratory care center (National
      Institute of Respiratory Diseases, Mexico) to compare the 24 hours response to two long
      acting bronchodilators (Indacaterol vs Tiotropium), after one inhaled dose.

      The primary endpoint will be changes in walked meters (6MWT) from baseline to 30, 60, 120 and
      240 minutes post dose of Indacaterol (150 µg) vs Tiotropium (18µg) in patients with moderate
      to severe COPD secondary to biomass exposure.

      The key secondary endpoint will be the 'trough' FEV1 in milliliters (mean of values at 23 h
      10 min and 23 h 45 min) post dose of Indacaterol (150 µg) vs Tiotropium (18 µg) in patients
      with moderate to severe COPD secondary to biomass exposure.

      The &quot;trough&quot; FEV1 value which was based on the mean of two measurements taken 23 h 10 min and
      23 h 45 min following the previous day's morning dose.

      Other secondary endpoints will be:

        -  FEV1 (in milliliters) and Inspiratory Capacity (IC in milliliters) will be measured frpm
           baseline (-10 min) to 30, 60, 90, 120 and 240 minutes post bronchodilators.

        -  Dyspnea perception will be measured by the 10 points Borg scale, from baseline to 30,
           60, 120 and 240 minutes post bronchodilators.

      In all patients spirometry will be performed serially over 24 h postdose. The design implies
      a crossover treatment in order to avoid variability between subjects and guarantee the
      outcome measures.

      There will be 40 intervention patients with 40 controls (crossover design). The study
      comprised a pre-screening visit, a 7-day screening period, and one day, 1-week treatment
      periods. At the baseline visit, eligible patients were randomized equally to one of two
      treatment sequences (A or B) to receive either indacaterol 150 µg once-daily or Tiotropium 18
      µg once-daily, followed by the other bronchodilator (Tiotropium or Indacaterol) each of them
      via a single-dose dry powder inhaler (SDDPI). Each treatment period was separated by a
      washout period of 7 days.

      Number of centers &amp; patients: 1 center with 40 patients, sequentially exposed to the two
      option treatment and will be their own control. It was decided making a self control design
      with crossover treatment in order to avoid variability between subjects and guarantee the
      outcome measures.

      Sample size justification:

      The sample size was calculated considering a power of 80% and a alpha value of 0.05 and two
      tails. Taking the minimal clinical significance value for 6 minutes walking test of 54 meters
      and standard deviation of 95 meters (BODE study). Because of the design of the study the
      investigators expected minimal patient withdrawn (less than 10%).

      Population:

      It is known that COPD secondary to biomass exposure patients commonly have a frequent
      exacerbation phenotype compared with patients with COPD secondary to tobacco smoke, and the
      investigators also expect that this phenotype would have the major benefit of the therapy.
      That´s why there will be included COPD patients in groups B, C or D, according to GOLD update
      2011.

      Pharmacovigilance requirements:

      All the Adverse Events (AE) would be reported following the procedure for Serious Adverse
      Events (SAEs) Report. In order to guarantee the safety of the patient, any AE occurring after
      patients began with the treatment of indacaterol.

      All the recurrence, complications or progression of the original AE must be reported as
      follow up of the original event, no matter when it was presented. This report should be
      submitted during the first 24 hours after the treating physician receive the notification.
      Any AE that is not considered to be related to the previous reported AE, should be informed
      as a new event.

      All SAEs shall be collected and registered in Serious Adverse Event Report Form.

      Outcome measurements:

      Primary:

      Walked meters on six minute walking test.

      Secondary:

      inspiratory capacity and post bronchodilator measures changes from basal measures .

        1. Changes from baseline in pulmonary function and inspiratory capacity.

        2. Changes from baseline in the total score of the Borg scale for dyspnea measure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>changes in walked meters on six minute walking test (6MWT) from baseline to 23:45 hours after one dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium in patients with moderate to severe COPD secondary to biomass exposure.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 30, 60, 240 and 23:45 hours post dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes in Inspiratory Capacity (IC) from baseline (-10 minutes) to 30, 60, 240 minutes and 23:45 hours post dose of Indacaterol (150 µg) vs Tiotropium (18µg) in patients with with biomass smoke COPD.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 30, 60, 240 and 23:45 hours post dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the 'trough' FEV1 (mean of values at 23 h 10 min and 23 h 45 min post-dose) after one dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium in patients with COPD secondary to biomass exposure.</measure>
    <time_frame>23:10 and 23:45 hours post dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes in dyspnea perception by using the Borg scale from baseline (-10 minutes) to 30, 60, 240 min and 23:45 hours post dose of Indacaterol (150 µg) vs Tiotropium (18 µg) in patients with COPD secondary to biomass exposure.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 30, 60, 240 and 23:45 hours post dose of indacaterol vs tiotropium</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the frequency of adverse events presented during the study, between indacaterol vs tiotropium arm</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>non serious adverse events; serious adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>COPD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>indacaterol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Indacaterol 150 mcgr, one inhaled capsule, dose once time on visit one, with dry powder inhaler device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tiotropium</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tiotropium 18 mcgr, 1 inhaled capsule, dose once time a Day, with dry powder inhaler device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>indacaterol</intervention_name>
    <description>Indacaterol, one inhales capsule, 150 mcgr, by dry powder dispositive</description>
    <arm_group_label>indacaterol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Onbrize</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tiotropium</intervention_name>
    <description>Tiotropium 18 mcgr, one inhaled capsule, by dry powder inhaler handihaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tiotropium</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Spiriva</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Mexican patients at the COPD outpatient clinic

          2. Age: &gt;50

          3. Female (female eligibility criteria are: Women in no fertile age who are non pregnant
             and committed to use effective contraception).

          4. FEV1 less than 80% of predicted and risk of exacerbation (GOLD update 2011) B, C or D

          5. Women with COPD diagnostic with biomass exposition (defined with an Hours/years index
             &gt;200 hr/y).

          6. Be Able to assist at the different visits during the study.

          7. Be Able to performed the spirometry

          8. Patients without contraindications to perform the six-minute walk test.

          9. Informed consent signed.

         10. No history of exacerbations in the last 6 weeks previous to the inclusion.

         11. With amenorrhea history more than a year duration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or breastfeeding women

          2. Use of Methotrexate, gold salts, troleandomycin, cyclosporine, immunosuppressants,

          3. History of uncontrolled renal disease, liver disease, uncontrolled cardiovascular
             disease, metabolic disease, neurologic disease, hematologic disease, oncologic
             disease, or autoimmune disease.

          4. Any alteration in normal values of the following Laboratory test: liver test, PIE,
             Biochemistry tests.

          5. History of asthma, bronchiectases, tuberculosis, recent respiratory tract infection,
             were hospitalized for a COPD exacerbation (6 weeks prior to visit 1), any significant
             pulmonary disease o cardiovascular abnormality

          6. Patients that is under suspicion of having cancer.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alejandra Ramírez-Venegas, M.Cs.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto Nacional de Enfermedades Respiratorias, &quot;Ismael Cosío Villegas&quot;</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto Nacional de Enfermedades Respiratorias, &quot;Ismael Cosío Villegas&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico, City</city>
        <zip>14080</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pérez-Padilla R, Regalado J, Vedal S, Paré P, Chapela R, Sansores R, Selman M. Exposure to biomass smoke and chronic airway disease in Mexican women. A case-control study. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1996 Sep;154(3 Pt 1):701-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8810608</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bruce N, Perez-Padilla R, Albalak R. Indoor air pollution in developing countries: a major environmental and public health challenge. Bull World Health Organ. 2000;78(9):1078-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11019457</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Torres-Duque C, Maldonado D, Pérez-Padilla R, Ezzati M, Viegi G; Forum of International Respiratory Studies (FIRS) Task Force on Health Effects of Biomass Exposure. Biomass fuels and respiratory diseases: a review of the evidence. Proc Am Thorac Soc. 2008 Jul 15;5(5):577-90. doi: 10.1513/pats.200707-100RP. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18625750</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Regalado J, Pérez-Padilla R, Sansores R, Páramo Ramirez JI, Brauer M, Paré P, Vedal S. The effect of biomass burning on respiratory symptoms and lung function in rural Mexican women. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2006 Oct 15;174(8):901-5. Epub 2006 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>16799080</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Caballero A, Torres-Duque CA, Jaramillo C, Bolívar F, Sanabria F, Osorio P, Orduz C, Guevara DP, Maldonado D. Prevalence of COPD in five Colombian cities situated at low, medium, and high altitude (PREPOCOL study). Chest. 2008 Feb;133(2):343-9. Epub 2007 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>17951621</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ramírez-Venegas A, Sansores RH, Pérez-Padilla R, Regalado J, Velázquez A, Sánchez C, Mayar ME. Survival of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease due to biomass smoke and tobacco. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2006 Feb 15;173(4):393-7. Epub 2005 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>16322646</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aaron SD, Vandemheen KL, Fergusson D, Maltais F, Bourbeau J, Goldstein R, Balter M, O'Donnell D, McIvor A, Sharma S, Bishop G, Anthony J, Cowie R, Field S, Hirsch A, Hernandez P, Rivington R, Road J, Hoffstein V, Hodder R, Marciniuk D, McCormack D, Fox G, Cox G, Prins HB, Ford G, Bleskie D, Doucette S, Mayers I, Chapman K, Zamel N, FitzGerald M; Canadian Thoracic Society/Canadian Respiratory Clinical Research Consortium. Tiotropium in combination with placebo, salmeterol, or fluticasone-salmeterol for treatment of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a randomized trial. Ann Intern Med. 2007 Apr 17;146(8):545-55. Epub 2007 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17310045</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 16, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 16, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Institute of Respiratory Diseases, Mexico</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alejandra Ramirez Venegas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>COPD</keyword>
  <keyword>biomass</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tiotropium Bromide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

