<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02471690</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MDCO-ORI-15-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02471690</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Safety,Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of a New Formulation of Oritavancin in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Single Center Cohort Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of a New Formulation of a Single 1200MG IV Dose of Oritavancin in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Medicines Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Medicines Company</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The protocol describes a double-blind study to evaluate the Pharmacokinetics and safety of a
      new formulation of oritavancin by adjusting infusion time, concentration and
      reconstitution/administration solutions, of a single 1200 mg intravenous (IV) infusion of
      oritavancin
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Oritavancin has been approved in the United States for the treatment of adult patients with
      acute bacterial skin and skin structure infections (ABSSSIs) caused or suspected to be caused
      by susceptible isolates of designated Gram-positive microorganisms. This is a Phase I, single
      center, double-blind, study evaluating the PK and safety of a new formulation of oritavancin
      by adjusting infusion time, concentration and reconstitution/administration solutions, of a
      single 1200 mg intravenous (IV) infusion of oritavancin in healthy adult subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety &amp; Tolerability: AEs/SAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>From Consent up to 14 days following termination of the study drug infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>A composite measure of the number and types of AE/SAEs encountered and relationship to time of dosing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety &amp; Tolerability: clinical safety laboratory results</measure>
    <time_frame>From Consent up to 14 days following termination of the study drug infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>A composite measure of multiple laboratory results assessing the clinical significance of any changes from baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety &amp; Tolerability: vital sign measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>From Consent up to 14 days following termination of the study drug infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>A composite of multiple vital sign measurements, assessing the clinical significance of any changes from baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety &amp; Tolerability: ECGs</measure>
    <time_frame>From Consent up to 14 days following termination of the study drug infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>A composite of multiple ECG measurements, assessing the clinical significance of any changes from baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety &amp; Tolerability: physical examination findings</measure>
    <time_frame>From Consent up to 14 days following termination of the study drug infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>A composite of multiple physical examination findings, assessing the clinical significance of any changes from baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters: Cmax and area under the plasma concentration-time curve</measure>
    <time_frame>From pre-dose until 168 hours from last dose</time_frame>
    <description>maximum measured plasma concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters: AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>From pre-dose until 168 hours from last dose</time_frame>
    <description>AUC from time zero to the time of the last measurable concentration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters: t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>From pre-dose until 168 hours from last dose</time_frame>
    <description>elimination half life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters: volume of distribution [Vz] and CL]</measure>
    <time_frame>From pre-dose to 168 hours from last dose</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of distribution</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters: tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>From pre-dose to 168 hours from last dose</time_frame>
    <description>Time to Cmax</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oritavancin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>IV -Single Dose - 1200 mg Oritavancin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>250 mL Dextrose 5% in Water</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oritavancin</intervention_name>
    <description>IV - Single dose 1200 mg Oritavancin</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oritavancin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Orbactiv</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dextrose</intervention_name>
    <description>D5W 5% in Water</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Able to provide written informed consent before initiation of any study related
             procedures.

          2. Healthy male or female between the ages of 18 and 65 years, inclusive.

          3. Body mass index (BMI) &lt; 45 kg/m2.

          4. Subject is in good health based on medical history and physical examination findings
             and has no clinically meaningful safety laboratory abnormalities (CBC, blood
             chemistry, and urinalysis) or 12 lead ECG results, as assessed by the PI.

          5. Vital signs (BP, pulse and temperature) measured at screening/baseline must be within
             the following ranges: SBP ≥90 to ≤150 mm Hg, DBP ≥45 to ≤90 mm Hg; Heart Rate ≥ 40 to
             ≤90 bpm (taken after resting in a supine position for at least 5 minutes).

          6. Willing to avoid all medications (other than the study drug and
             acetaminophen/paracetamol for minor aches/pains) during the study. This includes
             prescription and non-prescription medications, vitamins, herbal supplements, and
             nutriceuticals.

          7. Non-smoker and is willing to abstain from alcohol/illegal drug use for the duration of
             the study.

          8. If the female subject is surgically sterile, postmenopausal, or, if of childbearing
             potential, agrees to use at least 2 highly-effective methods of birth control (e.g.
             prescription oral contraceptives, contraceptive injections, contraceptive patch,
             intrauterine device, barrier methods, abstinence) or male partner sterilization alone
             for the duration of the study until 60 days after study drug administration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has any condition, including findings in the medical history or in pre-study
             assessments that constitutes a risk or a contraindication for the participation in the
             study or completing the study.

          2. Female subjects of childbearing potential that have a positive test result for human
             chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) at screening.

          3. Female subjects who are nursing.

          4. Positive urine test for alcohol and/or for drugs of abuse at screening.

          5. Has a history or presence of alcohol/drug abuse within 2 years. Alcohol abuse is
             defined as regularly consuming &gt;3 units/day (21 units per week for men), &gt;2 units/day
             (14 units/week) for women. 1 unit of alcohol is defined as a can of 4% beer (330 mL),
             approximately 190 mL of 6-7% beer (malt liquor), a glass of 40% spirits (30 mL), or a
             glass of wine (100 mL).

          6. History of hypersensitivity to drugs with a similar chemical structure (i.e.
             glycopeptide antibiotics) to oritavancin or any of its excipients.

          7. Blood or plasma donation within the past 2 months.

          8. Subjects who participated in other clinical research studies involving the evaluation
             of other investigational drugs or devices within 30 days or 5 half-lives, whichever is
             longer, prior to screening and/or unwilling to allow at least two months before
             participation in another drug trial following the current trial.

          9. Treatment with any prescription or OTC drugs, within 2 weeks or 5 half-lives,
             whichever is longer, or herbal nutritional supplements within 2 weeks of screening,
             with the exception of acetaminophen/paracetamol for minor aches/pains. Subjects will
             not be allowed to receive medications for the duration of the study (except the above
             mentioned acetaminophen/paracetamol). Birth control or other hormone replacement is
             also permitted as long as it has been taken at a stable dose for at least three months
             before the screening visit and remains stable for the duration of the study.

         10. Males who are unwilling to practice abstinence or use an acceptable method of birth
             control during the entire study period (i.e. condom with spermicide).

         11. Subjects that have any surgical or medical condition that could interfere with the
             administration of the study drug.

         12. Subjects that have known active hepatitis B or C, or human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV) infection or has known immune deficiency disease at screening.

         13. Subjects that have any condition that would confound or interfere with the assessment
             of safety.

         14. Subjects that have poor IV access as determined by the investigator.

         15. Prior exposure to Oritavancin alone or in combination with another product.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Spaulding Clinical</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Bend</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Volunteers</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oritavancin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

