<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02473731</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KTN3379-CL-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02473731</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Window of Opportunity Study of KTN3379 in Surgically Resectable Head and Neck Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Window of Opportunity Study of KTN3379 in Surgically Resectable Head and Neck Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celldex Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celldex Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the activity and safety of KTN3379 in head and neck
      cancer patients and to explore downstream molecular pathways to identify tumor response and
      resistance mechanisms by evaluating various biomarkers before and after treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label study in patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck
      (SCCHN) scheduled for surgery. Two cohorts of SCCHN patients, HPV negative and HPV positive,
      will be treated with KTN3379 to evaluate effects on ErbB3 phosphorylation and other
      biomarkers in tumor tissue. The KTN3379 treatment duration is within the expected window of
      time that elapses from initial patient evaluation by a surgeon to performance of surgery.
      Paired preoperative and postoperative tumor specimen analyses allow evaluation of
      proliferation, ErbB3 related biomarkers, pErbB3 modulation and pharmacodynamic changes in
      downstream molecular pathways.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 10, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 22, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pErbB3 levels in tumor tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in pErbB3 levels</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events (AEs), serious adverse events (SAEs), laboratory evaluations, radiological assessments, vital signs, electrocardiograms (ECGs), and physical examinations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ki67 proliferative index in tumor tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Ki67 proliferative index in tumor tissue before and after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in tumor measurements (RECIST 1.1 measurements)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>RECIST 1.1 measurements before and after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (Peak plasma concentrations of KTN3379 Trough plasma concentrations of KTN3379)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Peak plasma concentrations of KTN3379 Trough plasma concentrations of KTN3379</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti drug antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of anti KTN3379 antibodies in blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment with KTN3379 in HPV positive head and neck cancer patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment with KTN3379 in HPV negative head and neck cancer patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>KTN3379</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed primary, untreated SCCHN including variants.
             Patients must be candidates for surgical resection. Primary tumors of oral cavity,
             oropharynx, hypopharnyx or larynx are included.

          2. Written informed consent and any locally required authorization (e.g., HIPAA in the
             USA) obtained from the patient/legal representative prior to performing any
             protocol-related procedures, including screening evaluations.

          3. Females of childbearing potential who are sexually active with a nonsterilized male
             partner must use 2 methods of effective contraception from screening, and must agree
             to continue using such precautions for 60 days after the final dose of KTN3379.
             Females of childbearing potential are defined as those who are not surgically sterile
             (i.e., bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy, or complete hysterectomy) or
             those who are postmenopausal (defined as 12 months with no menses without an
             alternative medical cause)

          4. Nonsterilized males who are sexually active with a female partner of child-bearing
             potential must, with their partner, use 2 acceptable methods of effective
             contraception from Day 1 through 60 days after receipt of the final dose of KTN3379.

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) status of 0 or 1

          6. Adequate bone and marrow function as defined below:

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 10 g/dL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1500/mm3

               -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 ×ULN

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × ULN except for cases of documented or suspected Gilbert's
                  disease, in which bilirubin must be ≤ 5 × ULN

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 g/dL

               -  Normal PT or INR and aPTT

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any concurrent chemotherapy, radiotherapy, immunotherapy, biologic or hormonal therapy
             for cancer treatment.

          2. Immunosuppressive or systemic steroids medication within 7 days before the first dose
             of KTN3379 (inhaled and topical corticosteroids are permitted).

          3. Another invasive malignancy within 2 years prior to enrollment except for localized
             prostate cancer, cervical carcinoma in situ, non-melanomatous carcinoma of the skin,
             or ductal carcinoma in situ of the breast that has/have been surgically cured

          4. Major surgical procedure within 30 days prior to Day 1 or incomplete recovery from any
             prior surgery

          5. Pregnancy or lactation

          6. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension,
             uncontrolled or idiopathic hypotension, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia
             including atrial fibrillation, significant cardiac conduction abnormalities including
             prolongation of QTc interval or BBB, active peptic ulcer disease or gastritis, or
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements or compromise the ability of the patient to give written informed consent

          7. Patients with a left ventricular cardiac ejection fraction &lt; 50% as assessed by an
             echocardiogram or MUGA scan

          8. Patients with prior primary treatment for head and neck cancer (e.g. chemoradiation or
             radiation alone).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 16, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 17, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CDX3379</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

