<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01737515</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AbdoWaistHip</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01737515</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation of Waist Circumference and Waist/Hip Ratio as a Predictive Risk Factor for Morbidity and Mortality After Colorectal Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of Waist Circumference and Waist/Hip Ratio as a Predictive Risk Factor for Morbidity and Mortality After Colorectal Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cliniques universitaires Saint-Luc- Université Catholique de Louvain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cliniques universitaires Saint-Luc- Université Catholique de Louvain</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite advances in surgical technique, preoperative patient evaluation and post-operative
      care, elective colorectal surgery carries a risk of mortality of approximately 2% and a
      morbidity rate ranging from 20-40%. Risk prediction is important for two reasons: it informs
      decision-making in individual cases before surgery (part of informed consent) and allows the
      comparison of actual outcome with predicted outcome. A number of scoring systems for
      assessing risk of death after surgery have been developed. They vary from simple scores based
      on a few variables to highly complex mathematical models requiring detailed data input.
      Recently, the Association Française de Chirurgie conducted a multicentre study to develop and
      validate a 4-item predictive score of mortality after colorectal resection which has good
      predictive value and is simple to use.

      Although many surgeons associate obesity with adverse outcomes, recent large, well-designed
      studies have been unable to show that obesity (defined as Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt;30) is an
      independent risk factor for major morbidity or mortality after general abdominal surgery.
      Recently abdominal obesity (waist measurement &gt;102cm in men and &gt;88cm in women) has been
      shown to have better correlation with cardiovascular disease than BMI and is strongly
      associated with a clustering of risk factors for cardiovascular disease and diabetes (insulin
      resistance, hyperglycaemia, hypertension, dyslipidaemia and abdominal obesity) known as the
      metabolic syndrome. Waist circumference and waist/hip ratio are measures of abdominal obesity
      that correlate with the amount of intra-abdominal rather than subcutaneous or general body
      fat and may be a better measure of the risk of intra-operative complications and
      post-operative morbidity following abdominal surgery than BMI.

      The study will be prospective and multicentred, with 28 participating units in Belgium,
      France, Switzerland and Sweden. The coordinating centre will be UCL St Luc. The study will
      start on 1st September 2008 and will aim to include a minimum of 1000 patients. Consecutive
      patients undergoing elective colorectal resectional surgery for cancer or diverticulitis will
      be included. In addition to normal preoperative assessment, waist and hip circumference will
      be measured before surgery and specific data will be collected on intra and post-operative
      complications and mortality. Data will be recorded using an encrypted, anonymous database
      using variables carefully selected to assess short and long term outcomes. The study will be
      the first of its kind to investigate abdominal obesity as a predictive risk factor for
      colorectal surgery and will also be one of the biggest prospective studies of morbidity after
      colorectal surgery.

      The aims of the study are a) to assess if waist measurement or waist/hip ratio is a better
      predictive risk factor for complications or mortality after colorectal surgery than BMI, and
      b) if this measurement adds accuracy to the AFC score in risk prediction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity after colorectal surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days postoperatively</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality after colorectal surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days postoperatively</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1415</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Main group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Consecutive patients undergoing colorectal surgery for benign or malignant colorectal disease without any diversion from the standard of care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abdominal waist and hip circumference</intervention_name>
    <description>Abdominal waist and hip circumferences are measured clinically with a ruler as part of the standard pre-operative physical examination</description>
    <arm_group_label>Main group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients for whom elective colorectal resectional surgery (open and laparoscopic) is
        indicated.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  colorectal cancer

          -  diverticulitis

          -  colonic volvulus

          -  colorectal polyp

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 years

          -  Inability to give informed consent

          -  Emergency surgery

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Comorbidity resulting in altered abdominal circumference measurement:

        ascites secondary to chronic liver disease peritoneal carcinomatosis intestinal obstruction
        abdominal mass lesions &gt;20cm diameter on CT scan. pre-existing abdominal stoma incisional
        hernia

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease: it is recognised that this group of patients carries a
             well-recognised increased risk of a number of adverse outcomes (e.g. venous
             thrombo-embolism) and elevated inflammatory parameters therefore it is proposed to
             exclude this group from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alex H Kartheuser, MD, PhD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Colorectal Surgery Unit, Cliniques universitaires Saint-Luc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 27, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 29, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 27, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 27, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 29, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

