<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01739114</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00034524</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01739114</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Lung Aeration at Birth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sustained Inflations to Achieve Lung Aeration at Birth - a Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine if respiratory support at birth guided by RFM decreases BPD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite recent advances in perinatal-neonatal care, there is an increasing trend of
      bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) among survivors of prematurity1. Most infants developing BPD
      are born prematurely, and 75% of affected babies weigh less than 1000g at birth2. The risk of
      developing BPD increases with decreasing birth weight with reported incidence as high as 85%
      in neonates weighing between 500g and 699g, but only 5% in infants with birth weights over
      1500g2. Alberta has the highest rate (10%) of delivering premature infants in Canada. In
      Edmonton approximately 200 premature infants &lt;1250 g birth weight are born annually and up to
      50% will develop BPD. This puts a heavy burden on health resources since these infants
      require frequent hospital re-admission in the first two years after birth and, even as
      adolescents have persistent respiratory symptoms.

      Hypothesis Preterm infants &lt;33 weeks gestation requiring breathing support at birth, the
      delivery of SIs (SI group) before mask ventilation compared to standard mask ventilation
      (IPPV group) will reduce the incidence of BPD.

      Aim To determine if respiratory support at birth with initial sustained inflation compared to
      IPPV decreases BPD.

      Study population Entry criteria Infants &lt;33 weeks gestation born in the Royal Alexandra
      Hospital who require respiratory support for resuscitation in the delivery room.

      Exclusion criteria Infants will be excluded if they have a congenital abnormality or
      condition that might have an adverse effect on breathing or ventilation, e.g. congenital
      pulmonary or airway anomalies, congenital diaphragmatic hernia, or congenital heart disease
      requiring intervention in neonatal period. Infants will also be excluded if their parents
      refuse to give consent to this study.

      Description of interventions &quot;SI group&quot; Infants randomized into the &quot;SI group&quot; will receive
      two initial sustained inflations before PPV or CPAP.

      &quot;IPPV group&quot; Infants randomized into the &quot;IPPV group&quot; will receive mask IPPV with an initial
      PIP of 20 cmH2O and PEEP of 5 cm H2O, and a ventilation rate of 40-60 inflations/min until
      spontaneously breathing, at which time CPAP will be provided.

      &quot;Failed SI or IPPV&quot; Babies who fail to improve or remain apneic, bradycardic or hypoxemic
      despite two SIs and/or 30 seconds of effective IPPV require an alternative airway. Unit
      policy also dictates elective intubation and instillation of surfactant if, despite CPAP, a
      preterm infant continues to have increased work of breathing or requires a sustained
      inspiratory oxygen concentration over 40%.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in bronchopulmonary dysplasia</measure>
    <time_frame>36 weeks corrected gestational age</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in bronchopulmonary dysplasia as defined by need for oxygen or respiratory support at 36 weeks corrected gestational age.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neonatal death &lt; 28 days</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt; 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Neonatal death &lt; 28 days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death before discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>before discharge from the NICU</time_frame>
    <description>Death before discharge</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">186</enrollment>
  <condition>Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;SI group&quot;</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants randomized into the &quot;SI group&quot; will receive two initial sustained inflations with a PIP of 20 cm H2O.
After the two initial SIs infants will receive PEEP of 5 cm H2O and then CPAP if breathing spontaneously or, if found to have apnea or laboured breathing, mask IPPV with a PIP of 20 cm H2O and PEEP of 5 cm H2O at a rate of 40 to 60 bpm until spontaneously breathing, at which time CPAP will be provided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IPPV group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants randomized into the &quot;IPPV group&quot; will receive mask IPPV with an initial PIP of 20 cmH2O and PEEP of 5 cm H2O, and a ventilation rate of 40-60 inflations/min until spontaneously breathing, at which time CPAP will be provided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>&quot;IPPV group&quot;</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants randomized into the &quot;IPPV group&quot; will receive mask IPPV with an initial PIP of 20 cmH2O and PEEP of 5 cm H2O, and a ventilation rate of 40-60 inflations/min until spontaneously breathing, at which time CPAP will be provided.</description>
    <arm_group_label>IPPV group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SI group</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants randomized into the &quot;SI group&quot; will receive two initial sustained inflations with a PIP of 20 cmH2O. After the two initial SIs infants will receive PEEP of 5 cm H2O and then CPAP if breathing spontaneously or, if found to have apnea or laboured breathing, mask IPPV with a PIP of 20 cmH2O and PEEP of 5 cmH2O at a rate of 40 to 60 bpm until spontaneously breathing, at which time CPAP will be provided</description>
    <arm_group_label>&quot;SI group&quot;</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants &lt;33 weeks gestation born in the Royal Alexandra Hospital who require
             respiratory support for resuscitation in the delivery room.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants will be excluded if they have a congenital abnormality or condition that might
             have an adverse effect on breathing or ventilation, e.g. congenital pulmonary or
             airway anomalies, congenital diaphragmatic hernia, or congenital heart disease
             requiring intervention in neonatal period. Infants will also be excluded if their
             parents refuse to give consent to this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Minutes</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Georg Schmolzer, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Alexandra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T5K3V9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah PS, Sankaran K, Aziz K, Allen AC, Seshia M, Ohlsson A, Lee SK; Canadian Neonatal Network. Outcomes of preterm infants &lt;29 weeks gestation over 10-year period in Canada: a cause for concern? J Perinatol. 2012 Feb;32(2):132-8. doi: 10.1038/jp.2011.68. Epub 2011 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21593814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baraldi E, Filippone M. Chronic lung disease after premature birth. N Engl J Med. 2007 Nov 8;357(19):1946-55. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17989387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kattwinkel J, Perlman JM, Aziz K, Colby C, Fairchild K, Gallagher J, Hazinski MF, Halamek LP, Kumar P, Little G, McGowan JE, Nightengale B, Ramirez MM, Ringer S, Simon WM, Weiner GM, Wyckoff M, Zaichkin J. Part 15: neonatal resuscitation: 2010 American Heart Association Guidelines for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care. Circulation. 2010 Nov 2;122(18 Suppl 3):S909-19. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.971119. Review. Erratum in: Circulation. 2011 Oct 11;124(15):e406.</citation>
    <PMID>20956231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmölzer GM, Te Pas AB, Davis PG, Morley CJ. Reducing lung injury during neonatal resuscitation of preterm infants. J Pediatr. 2008 Dec;153(6):741-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2008.08.016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19014815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jobe AH. The New BPD. NeoReviews. 2006 Oct 1;7(10):e531-45.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boon AW, Milner AD, Hopkin IE. Lung expansion, tidal exchange, and formation of the functional residual capacity during resuscitation of asphyxiated neonates. J Pediatr. 1979 Dec;95(6):1031-6.</citation>
    <PMID>387935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vyas H, Milner AD, Hopkin IE, Boon AW. Physiologic responses to prolonged and slow-rise inflation in the resuscitation of the asphyxiated newborn infant. J Pediatr. 1981 Oct;99(4):635-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7277110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindner W, Vossbeck S, Hummler H, Pohlandt F. Delivery room management of extremely low birth weight infants: spontaneous breathing or intubation? Pediatrics. 1999 May;103(5 Pt 1):961-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10224173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lista G, Fontana P, Castoldi F, Cavigioli F, Dani C. Does sustained lung inflation at birth improve outcome of preterm infants at risk for respiratory distress syndrome? Neonatology. 2011;99(1):45-50. doi: 10.1159/000298312. Epub 2010 Jul 9.</citation>
    <PMID>20616570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>te Pas AB, Walther FJ. A randomized, controlled trial of delivery-room respiratory management in very preterm infants. Pediatrics. 2007 Aug;120(2):322-9. Erratum in: Pediatrics. 2007 Oct;120(4):936.</citation>
    <PMID>17671058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>te Pas AB, Siew M, Wallace MJ, Kitchen MJ, Fouras A, Lewis RA, Yagi N, Uesugi K, Donath S, Davis PG, Morley CJ, Hooper SB. Effect of sustained inflation length on establishing functional residual capacity at birth in ventilated premature rabbits. Pediatr Res. 2009 Sep;66(3):295-300. doi: 10.1203/PDR.0b013e3181b1bca4.</citation>
    <PMID>19542905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siew ML, Te Pas AB, Wallace MJ, Kitchen MJ, Lewis RA, Fouras A, Morley CJ, Davis PG, Yagi N, Uesugi K, Hooper SB. Positive end-expiratory pressure enhances development of a functional residual capacity in preterm rabbits ventilated from birth. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2009 May;106(5):1487-93. doi: 10.1152/japplphysiol.91591.2008. Epub 2009 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>19325025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmölzer GM, Morley CJ, Wong C, Dawson JA, Kamlin CO, Donath SM, Hooper SB, Davis PG. Respiratory function monitor guidance of mask ventilation in the delivery room: a feasibility study. J Pediatr. 2012 Mar;160(3):377-381.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2011.09.017. Epub 2011 Nov 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22056350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dawson JA, Schmölzer GM, Kamlin CO, Te Pas AB, O'Donnell CP, Donath SM, Davis PG, Morley CJ. Oxygenation with T-piece versus self-inflating bag for ventilation of extremely preterm infants at birth: a randomized controlled trial. J Pediatr. 2011 Jun;158(6):912-918.e1-2. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2010.12.003. Epub 2011 Jan 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21238983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dawson JA, Kamlin CO, Vento M, Wong C, Cole TJ, Donath SM, Davis PG, Morley CJ. Defining the reference range for oxygen saturation for infants after birth. Pediatrics. 2010 Jun;125(6):e1340-7. doi: 10.1542/peds.2009-1510. Epub 2010 May 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20439604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rabi Y, Singhal N, Nettel-Aguirre A. Room-air versus oxygen administration for resuscitation of preterm infants: the ROAR study. Pediatrics. 2011 Aug;128(2):e374-81. doi: 10.1542/peds.2010-3130. Epub 2011 Jul 11. Erratum in: Pediatrics. 2011 Dec;128(6):1212.</citation>
    <PMID>21746729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>SUPPORT Study Group of the Eunice Kennedy Shriver NICHD Neonatal Research Network, Finer NN, Carlo WA, Walsh MC, Rich W, Gantz MG, Laptook AR, Yoder BA, Faix RG, Das A, Poole WK, Donovan EF, Newman NS, Ambalavanan N, Frantz ID 3rd, Buchter S, Sánchez PJ, Kennedy KA, Laroia N, Poindexter BB, Cotten CM, Van Meurs KP, Duara S, Narendran V, Sood BG, O'Shea TM, Bell EF, Bhandari V, Watterberg KL, Higgins RD. Early CPAP versus surfactant in extremely preterm infants. N Engl J Med. 2010 May 27;362(21):1970-9. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0911783. Epub 2010 May 16. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2010 Jun 10;362(23):2235.</citation>
    <PMID>20472939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morley CJ, Davis PG, Doyle LW, Brion LP, Hascoet JM, Carlin JB; COIN Trial Investigators. Nasal CPAP or intubation at birth for very preterm infants. N Engl J Med. 2008 Feb 14;358(7):700-8. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa072788. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2008 Apr 3;358(14):1529.</citation>
    <PMID>18272893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 27, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Georg Schmolzer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Neonatologist, Postdoctoral Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lung aeration</keyword>
  <keyword>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Positive Pressure Respiration</keyword>
  <keyword>Sustained Inflation</keyword>
  <keyword>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

