<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01737528</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TVTR-2012-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01737528</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>STS/ACC Transcatheter Valve Therapy Registry (TVT Registry)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TVTR</acronym>
  <official_title>Society of Thoracic Surgeons and American College of Cardiology Transcatheter Valve Therapy Registry (STS/ACC TVT Registry).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Society of Thoracic Surgeons</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American College of Cardiology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Society of Thoracic Surgeons</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The TVT Registry™ is a benchmarking tool developed to track patient safety and real-world
      outcomes related to the transcatheter aortic valve replacement (TAVR) procedure. Created by
      The Society of Thoracic Surgeons (STS) and the American College of Cardiology (ACC), the TVT
      Registry is designed to monitor the safety and efficacy of this new procedure for the
      treatment of aortic stenosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose of the Registry

      The TVT Registry was designed to support a national surveillance system to assess the
      characteristics, treatments, and outcomes of patients receiving transcutaneous valve
      therapies. Patient-level data are submitted by participating hospitals to The Society of
      Thoracic Surgeons (STS) and American College of Cardiology Foundation's (ACCF) joint TVT
      Registry. The purposes of the TVT Registry include: (i) collecting pertinent and standardized
      data elements from participating hospitals, health care providers and others that measure and
      assess the quality of care for patients receiving TVT; (ii) providing confidential periodic
      reports to participating hospitals, health care providers and others, to evaluate and improve
      the quality of care in these areas; and (iii) permitting and fostering appropriate research
      based upon the data collected by means of the TVT Registry.

      The secondary aim of the TVT Registry is to serve as a scalable data infrastructure for post
      market studies.

      Background and Significance

      Transcatheter valve therapies are now emerging into clinical practice from the research phase
      in the United States. The first of several approaches to replacing the aortic valve without
      open-chest surgery has now become a reality. Other valve and delivery systems are expected to
      be approved in the upcoming years. An Expert Consensus Document on Transcatheter Valve
      Therapy has outlined the initial technology, targeted patient population, and the
      multidisciplinary heart team and specialized facilities needed. The document also proposes
      the establishment of a national registry of patients with valvular heart disease that can
      collect and analyze data as these new valve treatment options become available. Surveillance
      of device performance, monitoring of long-term outcomes, and performance of comparative
      effectiveness research are some of the proposed uses of the registry.

      Transcatheter valve therapies have emerged because of unmet patient needs. Furthermore, TVT
      has developed at a time when degenerative heart valve diseases of both the mitral and aortic
      valves are increasing in frequency as the population ages. With the introduction of the first
      TAVR commercial product, the targeted patient group is the &quot;inoperable&quot; patient who cannot
      receive the traditional therapy of surgical aortic valve replacement (SAVR). It is expected
      that TAVR will subsequently be extended to patients who have high risk with SAVR. The marked
      reduction of mortality by TAVR in the inoperable patients and the similar mortality of TAVR
      versus SAVR in the high risk patients provide patients with a new therapy with benefits but
      also with a different risk profile. Patients and their families will need to make informed
      decisions regarding the likelihood of having a mortality benefit, of improving their
      functional class and quality of life, of suffering a complication, and of choosing between
      different care options and therapeutic approaches.

      For these patients there are unique issues such as the prioritization of the health related
      quality of life versus the quantity of life, the desire to preserve independence and avoid
      becoming a burden to families, and the need to clearly understand what about their current
      condition is reversible versus irreversible and linked to other conditions and aging. These
      issues become further highlighted when considering the considerable costs and other treatment
      burdens of the TVT technologies versus the disabling symptoms and recurrent hospitalizations
      caused by untreated severe valvular heart disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>30 Days</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major adverse cardiac and cerebrovascular events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 day</time_frame>
    <description>increase in the 30-day risk of adverse events among patients receiving TAVR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who are alive with at least moderate functional improvement (defined as at least 10 point improvement in Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ) from baseline) at 1 year after receiving TAVR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Valve Academic Research Consortium (VARC) efficacy endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>30 day</time_frame>
    <description>30-day endpoints including mortality, stroke, stroke or transient ischemic attack (TIA), major vascular complications, valve related dysfunction requiring re-intervention, incident renal replacement therapy, life-threatening bleeding, and high-degree aortic valve (AV) block requiring permanent pacemaker implantation</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16000</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Valve Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAVR Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Will include all patients 18 years or over who undergo Transcatheter Aortic Valve Replacement (TAVR) for severe aortic stenosis. The sample size will include all patients entered into the Registry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcatheter Aortic Valve Replacement</intervention_name>
    <description>Minimal invasive implantation of a biological prothesis in Aortic Position</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAVR Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Transcatheter Aortic Valve Replacement must be furnished in a hospital with the appropriate
        infrastructre that includes, but is not limited to On site heart valve surgery program
        Cardiac catheterization lab or hybrid operating room with a fixed radiographic imaging
        system with flat panel fluoroscopy, offering quality imaging Non-invasive imaging such as
        echocardiography, vascular ultrasound, computed tomography and magnetic resonance
        Sufficient space, in a sterile environment, to accomodate necessary equipment for cases
        with and without complications Post-procedure intensive care facility with personnel
        experienced in managing patients who have undergone open-heart valve procedures Appropriate
        volume requirements
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  Primary indication is symptomatic primary severe aortic stenosis predicted to benefit
             from relief of valvular stenosis

          -  Aortic valve area less than 0.8 centimeters squared

          -  Mean aortic valve gradient greater than or equal to 40 mmHG

          -  Peak aortic jet velocity greater than or equal to 4.0 m per second

          -  Valve sheath access site is femoral, axillary, transapical, transaortic, subclavian or
             subaxillary

          -  Patient is judged by the local heart team to be inoperable for Aortic Valve
             Replacement due to severe chest wall deformities or radiation effects, severe
             peripheral or aortic vascular disease, or severe systemic disease prohibiting the safe
             conduct of Cardiopulmonary Bypass (CPB)

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Aortic valve annulus size is less than 18 mm or greater than 25 mm

          -  Active infectious endocarditis

          -  Valve in prosthetic valve procedure

          -  Patients considered by the heart team to be unlikely to receive meaningful or durable
             clinical benefit from the procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John D Carroll, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>American College of Cardiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fred H Edwards, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Society of Thoracic Surgeons</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kathleen Hewitt</last_name>
    <phone>(202) 375-6336</phone>
    <email>khewitt@acc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tina Kourtis</last_name>
    <phone>(312) 202-5879</phone>
    <email>tkourtis@sts.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>American College of Cardiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington, D.C.</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathleen Hewitt</last_name>
      <phone>202-375-6336</phone>
      <email>khewitt@acc.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncdr.com/TVT/Home/Default.aspx</url>
    <description>Link to homepage for STS/ACC TVT Registry</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 14, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 26, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 29, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>severe symptomatic native aortic valve stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>inoperable or high risk for open aortic valve replacement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

