<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03019458</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MINGO-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03019458</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MINGO Supplemental Trial in X-linked Dystonia-Parkinsonism Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>MINGO</acronym>
  <official_title>MINGO Supplemental Trial in X-linked Dystonia Parkinsonism Patients: A Prospective Randomized, Open-labeled, Parallel Group Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunshine Care Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jose R. Reyes Memorial Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunshine Care Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To see whether MINGO, a food supplement, will be able to lessen the drastic weight loss seen
      among X-linked Dystonia Parkinsonism patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      X-linked dystonia parkinsonism (XDP, formerly known as DYT3) occurs primarily in Filipino
      males and is characterized by neurodegenerative dystonia and parkinsonism. It is currently
      recognized to have wide phenotypic variability relating to age of onset, location of disease
      onset and rate of severity/disease progression. Most patients begin with focal dystonia that
      generalizes with the development of parkinsonism later in disease course. XDP patients suffer
      from severe nutritional loss due to symptoms such as dysphagia, loss of appetite, and
      consistently high metabolic requirements brought about by their movement disorder.
      Approximately 79% of patients with XDP have experienced rapid weight loss since the onset of
      their disease. It is the aim of the researchers to assess the clinical usefulness of adding a
      nutritional supplement to the daily dietary needs of these patients.

      MINGO is a supplement consisting of local ingredients such as moringa, rice and mung beans,
      which can be added to any type of edible paste, food, and liquid. Mingo has gained popularity
      as an emergency food in disaster relief operations due to the ease of its preparation, its
      high nutritional value and relatively low price. For the last two years, it has also been
      used as an agent for nutritional build up in malnourished populations of children. This study
      will provide valuable information on whether patients with XDP can increase their weight by
      consuming MINGO, which will lead to improvements in the patients' medical care and wellbeing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 26, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 8, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in Body Mass Index (BMI in kg/m2) from baseline using a bathroom weighing scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>after baseline BMI, we will measure BMI every 2 weeks for 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will first take a baseline BMI in kg/m2 for both control and interventional group, then subsequent measures every two weeks for 3 month duration of he trial. The goal of the investigators is to compare the net change in BMI in a 3 month period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>all cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months (study close out)</time_frame>
    <description>number of deaths in both arms at the end of the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of hospitalizations secondary to infectious causes</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months (study close out)</time_frame>
    <description>number of hospitalizations secondary to infections in both arms at the end of the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mid Upper Arm Circumference (MUAC) in cm using a tailor's tape measure from baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>After baseline measurements, the investigators will measure the MUAC evey month for 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>It has been reported that the Mid Upper Arm Circumference is a good predictor for BMI. It will serve as an indirect measurement to the subjects' BMI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>X-Linked Dystonia Parkinsonism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MINGO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MINGO is a supplement consisting of local ingredients such as moringa, rice and mung beans, which can be added to any type of edible paste, food, and liquid. The experimental group is required to take 6 sachets per day for 12 weeks in addition to their regular diet. They are required to keep a daily food diary</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group is required to eat their normal diet. They are also required to keep a daily food diary.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MINGO</intervention_name>
    <description>6 20oz sachets will be taken daily by intervention group</description>
    <arm_group_label>MINGO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is above the age of 18

          -  Positive Diagnosis of XDP by movement disorder specialist/fellow

          -  Subject with a yes response to a &quot;supportive home environment&quot; in the patient's most
             recent &quot;doctors monthly report&quot;

          -  Subject are easily accessible to passable roads and pubic transportation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who have extreme movements that prevent staff from performing BMI or MUAC
             measurements

          -  Subjects who have abnormal metabolic labs prior to the start of the study

          -  Subjects who are taking pharmacological or medicinal supplements that may effect
             weight

          -  Subjects who have been hospitalized within the last 2 weeks from the start of the
             trial

          -  Subjects who have a Nasogastric tube or G-tube

          -  Subjects with a history of other diseases that my effect weight (eg:
             hypo/hyperthyroidism)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Criscely L Go, MD,FPNA,DPBP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jose R. Reyes Memorial Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Health Centrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roxas City</city>
        <state>Capiz</state>
        <zip>5800</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Philippines</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 26, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 26, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prospective randomized trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parkinsonian Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonia Musculorum Deformans</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Genetic Diseases, X-Linked</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>December 7, 2017</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

