<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01063192</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>T2209</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01063192</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Randomized Study of Induction Chemotherapy Followed by Concurrent Chemo-radiotherapy in Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Health Research Institutes, Taiwan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Health Research Institutes, Taiwan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary end point is to evaluate the time to progression after gemcitabine alone versus
      Gemcitabine-based combination induction chemotherapy followed by concurrent chemoradiotherapy
      in locally advanced pancreatic cancer.

      The secondary end points are to evaluate the disease control rate, overall survival time,
      toxicity profile and compliance after induction chemotherapy and concurrent chemoradiotherapy
      as well as the disease control rate after inductional chemotherapy alone in locally advanced
      pancreatic cancer. Translational research including pharmacogenomic study and biomarker study
      will also be done concomitantly.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients should be randomized to two study arms stratified by resectability status
      (borderline resectable and unresectable) after enrollment. Eligible patients will be randomly
      assigned on a 1:1 basis to either of two study groups, using a central randomization
      procedure with stratification according to NCCN criteria of resectability.

      After randomization, induction chemotherapy (ICT) will be administered for 3 cycles ( 3
      months). Patients who have radiological evidence of distant dissemination will be shifted to
      salvage chemotherapy. Patients who have responsive, stable disease as well as those with
      localized progressive disease after ICT will receive concurrent chemoradiotherapy (CCRT) 3-4
      weeks after the last dose of ICT. Surgical evaluation will be performed 4-6 weeks after the
      completion of CCRT. Patients who have respectable disease will undergo surgical resection.
      Postoperative adjuvant chemotherapy for 3 cycles ( 3 months) will be given for those who are
      considered to have curative resection. Patients who still have unresectable disease or
      non-curative resection will receive systemic chemotherapy till disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      For Arm 1, ICT with gemcitabine ( fixed rate of 10mg/m2/min, 1000mg/m2 on day 1,8,15 every 28
      days/cycle) will be administered on a 3-week-on-one-week-off weekly basis. For Arm 2, ICT
      with GOFL ( 800mg/m2 gemcitabine at a fixed rate of 10mg/m2/min followed by a 2-hour
      oxaliplatin 85mg/m2 and then a 48-hour 3000mg/m2 5-FU and 150 mg/m2 leucovorin on day 1 and
      15 every 28 days/cycle) will be given biweekly.

      After three 3 cycles of ICT, patients without distant metastasis will be given CCRT with
      gemcitabine 400mg/m2 2 hrs before RT on day1,8,15,22,29,36. Radiation will be given 180cGy
      per day, 5 days a week for 28 fractions to totally 5040cGy.

      If complete surgical resection is feasible, optimal surgery will be performed 4-6 weeks after
      CCRT. If complete surgical resection is impossible, biopsy with or without bypass surgery may
      be performed. Patients who have curative surgical resection will receive additional 6 cycles
      ( 6 months) of adjuvant chemotherapy ( Arm1, gemcitabine alone; Arm 2, GOFL) within 4 weeks
      after surgery and then followed up until tumor progression. Patients who are not feasible for
      curative resection, will receive continued chemotherapy (Arm1, gemcitabine alone; Arm2, GOFL)
      3-4 weeks after CCRT complete. The regimen will continue till disease progression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Enrolling by invitation</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary end point is to evaluate the time to progression after gemcitabine alone versus Gemcitabine-based combination induction chemotherapy followed by concurrent chemoradiotherapy in locally advanced pancreatic cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary end points are to evaluate the disease control rate, overall survival time, toxicity profile and compliance after induction chemotherapy and concurrent chemoradiotherapy .</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">73</enrollment>
  <condition>Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 1: Gemcitabine alone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GOFL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm 2: GOFL (Gem 800mg/m2 80min, Oxa 85mg/m2 2hr, 5FU 3000mg/m2, LV 150mg/m2 iv 48hr)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Arm 1: Gemcitabine alone on D1,8,15 every 28 days for 3 cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine, Oxaliplatin, 5-Fluorouracil, Leucovorin (GOFL)</intervention_name>
    <description>Arm 2: GOFL on D1, 15 every 28 days for 3 cycles(Gem 800mg/m2 80min, Oxa 85mg/m2 2hr, 5FU 3000mg/m2, LV 150mg/m2 iv 48hr)</description>
    <arm_group_label>GOFL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the
             exocrine pancreas.

          2. Patients must have locally advanced pancreatic cancer (LAPC).

          3. Patients must have LAPC evaluated by radiologist and/or surgeon according to either
             abdominal CT or MRI, or intra-operative findings.

          4. Patients must have measurable disease.

          5. Age &gt;20 years.

          6. ECOG performance scale of 0-2.

          7. Patients must have normal organ and marrow function.

          8. Patients who present with jaundice, temporary or permanent internal / external
             drainage before enrollment will be allowed.

          9. The effects of study agents on the developing human fetus at the recommended
             therapeutic dose are unknown. Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to
             use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence)
             prior to study entry and for the duration of study participation.

         10. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with distant metastases are not eligible.

          2. Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents.

          3. Patients who have had prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy are not eligible.

          4. History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to study agents used in the study.

          5. Patients who have above grade II peripheral neuropathy.

          6. Patients who had non-curable second primary malignancy.

          7. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including.

          8. Pregnant women are excluded from this study because the study agents has the potential
             for teratogenic or abortifacient effects.

          9. Those who are immuno-compromised or receiving immuno-suppressive therapy are excluded
             from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pin-Wen Lin, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yen-Shen Shen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chiun Hsu, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Taiwan University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>National Health Research Instiutes, Taiwan</name_title>
    <organization>National Institute of Cancer Research</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Locally Advanced Pancreatic Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

