<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01062945</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-25442</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P50DA018197</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DPMC</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01062945</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Doxazosin on the Cardiovascular and Subjective Effects of Cocaine</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Doxazosin on the Cardiovascular and Subjective Effects of Cocaine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to asses the potential interactions between intravenous cocaine
      and doxazosin in cocaine dependent volunteers who are not seeking treatment. The study will
      evaluate the effects of doxazosin on the cardiovascular and subjective effects of cocaine in
      a human laboratory study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective: The primary objective is to determine the safety of treatment with
      doxazosin in cocaine-dependent volunteers by examining hemodynamic and subjective effects of
      administration of ascending doses of cocaine (0, 20mg, and 40mg) and a placebo dose during
      treatment with doxazosin.

      Secondary Objectives: To evaluate the effect of doxazosin on the pharmacokinetics of
      intravenously administered cocaine; To determine effects of treatment with doxazosin, as
      compared to placebo, on subjective effects produced by administration of cocaine or placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effects of treatment with doxazosin on cardiovascular effects after administration of ascending doses of cocaine (0, 20mg, and 40mg) and a placebo dose.</measure>
    <description>Blood pressure (resting and orthostatic) will be assessed daily prior to dosing. Heart rate, EKG, and blood pressure will be recorded throughout and after experimental sessions using an automatic monitoring system. Participants will be monitored for stability on days 11 and 12 and discharged from the hospital on day 13.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effects of treatment with doxazosin, as compared to placebo, on subjective measures produced by administration of cocaine or placebo.</measure>
    <description>Visual-analogue scale ratings of &quot;any cocaine effect&quot;, &quot;high&quot;, &quot;good effects&quot;, &quot;bad effects&quot;, &quot;like cocaine&quot;, &quot;desire cocaine&quot;, &quot;depressed&quot;, &quot;anxious&quot;, &quot;stimulated&quot;, and &quot;if you had access to cocaine right now, how likely would you be to use it?&quot; will be collected at -15 min, 5 min, 10 min, 15 min, 20 min, 30 min, and 45 min after cocaine dosing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Cocaine Addiction</condition>
  <condition>Cocaine Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Cocaine Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Substance Abuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Doxazosin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching administration of a placebo pill.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doxazosin</intervention_name>
    <description>The dose of doxazosin needed to alter the effects of cocaine is unknown and preclinical animal studies have not been conducted. Because of this, initially we will study the effects of a low dose of doxazosin (4 mg daily) compared to placebo daily. Because this class of medication needs to be titrated upward due to the potential for hypotension, treatment will begin at 1 mg and increased by 1 mg increments every three days until 4 mg is reached on day 12.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Doxazosin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cardura</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be English-speaking volunteers who are not seeking treatment at the time of the study.

          -  Be between 18-55 years of age.

          -  Meet DSM-IV TR criteria for cocaine dependence; participants may or may not meet
             criteria for nicotine dependence. Nicotine dependence is allowed but not required
             because most cocaine users smoke cigarettes.

          -  Have a self-reported history of using cocaine by the smoked or IV route.

          -  Have vital signs as follows: supine blood pressure &gt; 100/65 mm Hg, a seated blood
             pressure of &gt; 90/60 mm Hg and &lt; 150/90 mm Hg, and an orthostatic change &lt; 20 mm Hg
             systolic or &lt;10 mm Hg diastolic on standing. Resting pulse must be &lt; 90 bpm.

          -  Have hematology and chemistry laboratory tests that are within normal (+/- 10%) limits
             with the following exceptions: a) liver function tests (total bilirubin, ALT, AST, and
             alkaline phosphatase) &lt; 3 x the upper limit of normal, and b) kidney function tests
             (creatinine and BUN) within normal limits.

          -  Have a baseline EKG that demonstrates clinically normal sinus rhythm, clinically
             normal conduction, and no clinically significant arrhythmias.

          -  Have a medical history and brief physical examination demonstrating no clinically
             significant contraindications for study participation, in the judgment of the
             admitting physician and the principal investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Meet DSM-IV TR criteria for dependence on drugs other than cocaine or nicotine.

          -  Have any history or evidence suggestive of seizure disorder or brain injury.

          -  Have any previous medically adverse reaction to cocaine, including loss of
             consciousness, chest pain, or epileptic seizure.

          -  Have neurological or psychiatric disorders, such as: psychosis, bipolar illness or
             major depression as assessed by MINI; organic brain disease or dementia assessed by
             clinical interview; history of any psychiatric disorder which would require ongoing
             treatment or which would make study compliance difficult; history of suicide attempts
             within the past year and/or current suicidal ideation/plan.

          -  Have evidence of clinically significant heart disease or hypertension, as determined
             by the PI.

          -  Have evidence of untreated or unstable medical illness including: neuroendocrine,
             autoimmune, renal, hepatic, or active infectious disease.

          -  Have symptomatic HIV or are taking antiretroviral medication.

          -  Be pregnant or nursing. Other females must either be unable to conceive (i.e.,
             surgically sterilized, sterile, or post-menopausal) or be using a reliable form of
             contraception (e.g., abstinence, birth control pills, intrauterine device, condoms, or
             spermicide). All females must provide negative pregnancy urine tests before study
             entry, upon hospital admission, and at the end of study participation.

          -  Have asthma or currently use theophylline or other sympathomimetics.

          -  Have any other illness, condition, or use of psychotropic medications, which in the
             opinion of the PI and/or the admitting physician would preclude safe and/or successful
             completion of the study.

        Criteria for Discontinuation Following Initiation:

        Participants will be discharged if they have a positive breath test indicating use of
        alcohol or a urine test indicating illicit use of drugs while in the MED-VAMC, if they do
        not comply with study procedures, or if they do not tolerate the study drugs.

        Subject Selection Criteria Rationale for Route of Administration:

        Participants are required to have used cocaine by the IV or smoked route to avoid exposing
        participants to drugs by routes of administration that produce more intensive interoceptive
        effects than usually used by the participants. Prior experience with smoked cocaine is
        allowed (rather than restricting the population to those with experience with IV cocaine)
        because smoked cocaine reaches brain sites of action as rapidly as does intravenously
        administered cocaine and smoked cocaine produces effects that are comparable to IV cocaine.
        Speed of administration (and rate of delivery to brain) of stimulant drugs likely impacts
        subjective and cardiovascular effects, so smoked and intravenously administered cocaine
        produce similar subjective effects.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Newton, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michael Debakey VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 27, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thomas Newton</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cocaine</keyword>
  <keyword>Doxazosin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cocaine-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Doxazosin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

