<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00557648</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R21MH065369</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21MH065369</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00557648</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Effectiveness of Early Cognitive Behavioral Therapy With or Without Parental Involvement in Treating Anxious Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Interventions for Anxious Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the effectiveness of school-based cognitive behavioral therapy with
      or without parental involvement in treating anxious children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anxiety disorders are among the most common disorders in children. Although anxiety is a
      normal part of growing up, the worrying experienced by children with anxiety disorders can
      persist to the point that day-to-day functioning becomes difficult. Physical symptoms of
      anxiety disorders include a constant sense of worry or stress, headache, nausea, sweating,
      shaking, and inability to concentrate. Early identification of anxiety disorders is important
      to prevent progression of the disorder into a chronic issue. Cognitive behavioral therapy
      (CBT), which focuses on behavioral and thinking modifications, has been shown to be the most
      effective treatment for anxiety disorders. This study will evaluate the effectiveness of
      school-based CBT with or without parental involvement in treating anxious children who meet
      DSM-IV criteria or have features of separation anxiety disorder, generalized anxiety
      disorder, and social phobia.

      Participants in this single blind study will be randomly assigned by school to one of three
      treatment groups: CBT for children only, CBT for children plus parent training, and
      no-treatment control. Each child and parent participant will first undergo an interview,
      lasting between 1 and 1.5 hours, about the child's symptoms. Additionally, parents will
      complete rating scales about their children's symptoms and their own symptoms. The
      participants receiving CBT will then attend 9 weekly group sessions held in the school
      buildings after school. In the parental involvement group, parents will attend 9 weekly group
      parent-training sessions held at the same time as the children's CBT group sessions. During
      the children's CBT sessions, participants will learn techniques to identify feelings of
      worry, relax, modify negative thoughts, break down difficult situations into smaller
      achievable steps, reward themselves for trying hard, and maintain treatment gains. For the
      parent training group, early sessions will focus on normalizing anxiety during childhood,
      learning about anxiety, and identifying when their children are feeling anxious. The middle
      sessions will teach parents the same anxiety management skills being taught to their children
      and ways to help their children to apply the steps at home. The latter sessions will instruct
      parents on ways to encourage their children's behaviors in anxiety-provoking situations.
      After completing the 9-week program, participants will attend 2 follow-up booster sessions at
      Months 1 and 3 post-treatment. Follow-up assessments will occur at Months 3 and 6 and at
      Years 1, 2, 3, and 4 post-treatment. The assessments will include repeat interviews and
      rating scales. At the end of the 6-month follow-up assessment, participants in the
      no-treatment control group will have the opportunity to participate in the CBT group
      treatments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite Clinician Severity Rating (CSR) on the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule (ADIS) for DSM-IV for primary anxiety diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at Month 6 and Years 1, 2, 3, and 4 post-treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multidimensional Anxiety Scale for Children, Scale for Child Anxiety Related Emotional Disorders, Clinical Global Impressions-Improvement Scale, Family Adaptability and Cohesion Evaluation Scale II, and Behavior Assessment System for Children</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at Months 3 and 6 and Years 1, 2, 3, and 4 post-treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">61</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CBT for children only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CBT for children with parental involvement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention control group: families free to seek treatment on their own</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group CBT for children</intervention_name>
    <description>CBT for children consists of 9 weekly group CBT sessions. All sessions occur in the school building during after-school hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group CBT for children plus parent training</intervention_name>
    <description>CBT involving children and parents consists of 9 weekly group CBT sessions for the children and 9 weekly concurrent group parent training sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Total Anxiety T-score of greater than 57 on Multidimensional Anxiety Scale for
             Children and/or teacher nomination as one of the most anxious children in the
             classroom

          -  Meets DSM-IV criteria for separation anxiety disorder, generalized anxiety disorder,
             and/or social phobia, or features (one or more, but not all criteria) of one of these
             disorders with an associated composite CSR of 2 to 6 on ADIS

          -  Both parent and child speak English fluently

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current diagnosis of the following on ADIS: obsessive-compulsive disorder,
             posttraumatic stress disorder, attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder, conduct
             disorder, schizophrenia, pervasive developmental disorder, major depression, or
             substance abuse

          -  Current suicidal or homicidal intent or plan

          -  Diagnosis of mental retardation (IQ less than 71) on the Kaufman Brief Intelligence
             Test (KBIT)

          -  Currently receiving psychotropic medication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gail A. Bernstein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Division of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University of Minnesota Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Divisions of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University of Minnesota Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55454</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bernstein GA, Layne AE, Egan EA, Tennison DM. School-based interventions for anxious children. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2005 Nov;44(11):1118-27.</citation>
    <PMID>16239860</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bernstein GA, Layne AE, Egan EA, Nelson LP. Maternal phobic anxiety and child anxiety. J Anxiety Disord. 2005;19(6):658-72.</citation>
    <PMID>15927779</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Layne AE, Bernstein GA, March JS. Teacher awareness of anxiety symptoms in children. Child Psychiatry Hum Dev. 2006 Summer;36(4):383-92.</citation>
    <PMID>16736381</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Victor AM, Bernat DH, Bernstein GA, Layne AE. Effects of parent and family characteristics on treatment outcome of anxious children. J Anxiety Disord. 2007;21(6):835-48. Epub 2006 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>17161582</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bernstein GA, Bernat DH, Davis AA, Layne AE. Symptom presentation and classroom functioning in a nonclinical sample of children with social phobia. Depress Anxiety. 2008;25(9):752-60.</citation>
    <PMID>17557318</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bernstein GA, Bernat DH, Victor AM, Layne AE. School-based interventions for anxious children: 3-, 6-, and 12-month follow-ups. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2008 Sep;47(9):1039-47. doi: 10.1097/CHI.ob013e31817eecco.</citation>
    <PMID>18665000</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Layne AE, Bernat DH, Victor AM, Bernstein GA. Generalized anxiety disorder in a nonclinical sample of children: symptom presentation and predictors of impairment. J Anxiety Disord. 2009 Mar;23(2):283-9. doi: 10.1016/j.janxdis.2008.08.003. Epub 2008 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>18815006</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 14, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>School-Based Interventions</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

