<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00682669</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R21AT002938</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00682669</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Asthma and Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction (MBSR)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Asthma and Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction (MBSR)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Asthma is one of the four most common chronic disorders in adults, affecting 14 million
      adults in the United States and costing an estimated 7.9 billion dollars in medical care and
      5.3 billion dollars in lost work or school. About 40% of asthmatics report using some form of
      complementary and alternative medicine approach to help reduce their asthma symptoms, but
      there is little evidence for their effectiveness. Mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR)
      is a group based program shown to reduce medical symptoms and improve quality of life for
      patients with many different chronic diseases. The goals of the proposed randomized
      controlled trial are to collect preliminary data on the effect of MBSR on quality of life,
      symptoms, and lung function in mild and moderate-severity asthmatics and to refine
      recruitment and data collection procedures for a future, larger clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Asthma is a chronic respiratory disease that affects 7% or 14 million adults in the United
      States. It is one of the four most common chronic disorders in adults, costing an estimated
      7.9 billion dollars in medical care and 5.3 billion dollars in lost work or school.
      Approximately 40% of asthmatics report using some form of complementary and alternative
      medicine (CAM) approach to help alleviate their asthma symptoms, but there is little evidence
      for their effectiveness. Breathing and relaxation techniques, including yoga appear most
      promising. Mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) is a group-based program developed at
      the University of Massachusetts Medical School (UMMS) that focuses on the cultivation of
      mindfulness through formal meditation practices and the integration of mindfulness into
      everyday life as a coping resource to deal with physical symptoms, chronic medical
      conditions, and difficult emotional situations. MBSR has been shown to be an effective
      adjunctive intervention in reducing medical symptoms for a broad range of stress-related
      disorders and chronic diseases, reducing psychological distress anxiety and depression, and
      improving quality of life. A small preliminary study conducted by our research team found
      improvements in measures of quality of life, locus of control, stress, and anxiety
      immediately following the completion of the MBSR program.

      The overall goal of the proposed two year exploratory study is to conduct a randomized
      controlled trial (RCT) to test and optimize recruitment and data collection procedures and to
      collect preliminary data on the effect of MBSR on behavioral and psychological aspects of
      asthma and lung function to support justification for a larger clinical trial should the
      results of this study be promising. Eighty-two adults ages 21 and older with a
      physician-documented diagnosis of asthma classified as either mild or moderate documented
      will be recruited for seventy participants at final follow-up. Participants will be randomly
      assigned to one of two conditions stratified by asthma severity: (1) MBSR, or (2) Healthy
      Living Course (HLC) attention control condition. Participant assessments will occur at study
      entry (baseline) and at 10-week, 6- and 12-month follow-up. The primary aim of the project is
      to evaluate the efficacy of the MBSR program in improving quality of life and lung function
      as assessed by change from baseline to two-week average morning peak expiratory flow (PEF)
      compared to HLC participants. Secondary aims are to evaluate the effect of the MBSR program
      on reducing asthma rescue medication use, frequency of asthma exacerbations (prednisone
      therapy), asthma symptoms, healthcare utilization, number of days of work or school missed,
      peak expiratory flow (PEF) variation, and psychological distress, and in improving asthma
      control, asthma-related internal locus of control, and lung function as assessed by
      spirometry (FEV1).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life and lung function.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 week, 6- and 12-month post baseline</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduce asthma symptoms, exacerbations and health care utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>10-week, 6- and 12-month post baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">83</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MBSR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) program consisting of an 8-week, 9-session intervention based on systematic and intensive training in mindfulness meditation and mindful hatha yoga and their application to every day life.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HLC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A Healthy Living Course (HLC) consisting of an 8-week program of lectures and discussion on health-related topics.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MBSR</intervention_name>
    <description>A mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) program consisting of an 8-week, 9-session intervention based on systematic and intensive training in mindfulness meditation and mindful hatha yoga and their application to every day life.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MBSR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HLC</intervention_name>
    <description>An 8-week program consisting of lectures and discussion of health-related topics.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HLC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  documented diagnosis of asthma from their physician

          -  meet criteria for mild persistent or moderate persistent asthma

          -  able to read and understand English

          -  able to complete informed consent process and study data collection procedures

          -  21 or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  current smoker

          -  other lung diseases besides asthma

          -  cancer, except non-melanoma skin cancer

          -  currently receiving treatment for symptomatic cardiovascular disease

          -  on psychotropic medications in the prior 6 months

          -  psychiatric hospitalization in the last 2 years

          -  has taken the MBSR program in the past

          -  currently practicing meditation or yoga on a regular basis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lori Pbert, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Massachusetts Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 18, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 18, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lori Pbert</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Mindfulness-based stress reduction</keyword>
  <keyword>Peak expiratory flow rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Spirometry</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

