<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00687583</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1000010579</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00687583</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Head Movement Effect on Different Tracheal Tubes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Head Movement on the Position of Different Tracheal Tubes Determined Radiologically</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hospital for Sick Children</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hospital for Sick Children</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A breathing tube, which is used to secure the airway and allow ventilation of the lungs
      during general anaesthesia, is inserted into the windpipe either through the nose or mouth.
      In children, different formulas exist to determine the appropriate size of the tube according
      to age, and how far it should be advanced into the airway. Head movement can alter the
      position of the breathing tube, making it go in or come out too far. Different types of
      breathing tubes may also differ in their change of position with head movement. The aim of
      this study is to assess the accuracy of the formulae commonly used in our institution for
      depth of breathing tube placement, and to measure the degree of tube displacement on head
      movement with different types of tubes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An endotracheal tube, which is used to secure the airway and allow ventilation of the lungs
      during general anesthesia, is inserted into the trachea either through the nose or mouth. In
      children, different formulae exist to determine the approximate size of the tube according to
      age, and how far it should be advanced into the airway. Once a tracheal tube is inserted, its
      position is routinely checked to make sure both lungs are ventilated. To prevent
      displacement, the tube is taped to the lip, chin or at the nose. However, head movement could
      cause alteration of the tube position, and risk selective endobronchial intubation or
      inadvertent extubation. Knowledge of how the different tracheal tubes move with head position
      can help determine the best tube selection to reduce the risk of accidental tube advancement
      or removal, in cases where certain head positions are required for surgical access.

      The aim of this study is to assess the accuracy of the formulae commonly used in our
      institution for depth of breathing tube placement, and to measure the degree of tube
      displacement on head movement with different types of tube. Testing the formulae will enable
      us to be more aware of how frequently inaccurate tube placement may occur. Knowledge of how
      the different breathing tubes move with head position can help determine the best tube
      selection to reduce the risk of the tube going in too far or coming out accidentally, for
      cases were certain head positions are required for surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Research question deemed not of enough clinical importance to proceed.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Head Movements</condition>
  <condition>Intubation, Intratracheal</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Fifty children undergoing any procedure in the Image Guided Therapy (IGT) department
        requiring tracheal intubation and chest X-ray, will be recruited and will be evenly
        distributed in three different age groups (0 to 6 months, 6 to 24 months, 24 months to 6
        years).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children undergoing any procedure in the Image Guided Therapy (IGT) department
             requiring tracheal intubation and chest x-ray

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Premature neonates

          -  Patients with cranio-facial anomalies

          -  Cervical spine/upper thoracic anomalies

          -  Laryngomalacia/tracheomalacia

          -  Chronic hypoxemia (i.e. cardiac conditions with right to left shunts)

          -  Patients requiring positions other than supine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cengiz Karsli, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto Canada</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Hospital for Sick Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hospital for Sick Children</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cengiz Karsli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff Anesthesiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pediatrics</keyword>
  <keyword>anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>head movements</keyword>
  <keyword>endotracheal tube</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

