<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00688948</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDHA-RS/2007-035</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>JBGMS01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00688948</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Alfuzosin for Voiding Dysfunction in Multiple Sclerosis (MS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study Looking At The Use Of Alfuzosin In The Treatment Of Bladder Dysfunction In Patients With Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nova Scotia Health Authority</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nova Scotia Health Authority</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple Sclerosis is often associated with severe functional deficits resulting in a range
      of progressive impairments. Approximately 80% of patients have bladder symptoms at the time
      of diagnosis and up to 97% will have bladder symptoms during the course of the disease. To
      date, the vast majority of treatment has been centered on the use of medications to control
      &quot;bladder spasms&quot; and the use of catheters to help patients empty the bladder. There have been
      very few studies looking at medications like Alfuzosin that may help in controlling bladder
      symptoms in Multiple Sclerosis. Alfuzosin has been shown to significantly improve voiding
      symptoms and bladder emptying in patients with prostatic enlargement. There have been no
      controlled studies yet to determine whether this treatment helps patients with Multiple
      Sclerosis. The purpose of this study is to determine if Alfuzosin improves bladder symptoms
      and quality of life in patients with Multiple Sclerosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVE The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the use of Alfuzosin in the
      treatment of bladder dysfunction in patients with Multiple Sclerosis (MS).

      STUDY POPULATION Twenty (20) participants aged 18 years of age who have been diagnosed with
      Multiple Sclerosis and lower urinary tract symptoms will be treated with Alfuzosin.

      DESIGN This is a single institution, non-randomized, non-blinded pilot study of the use of
      Alfuzosin in the treatment of bladder dysfunction in MS patients. After the initial screening
      visit patients will be given 10 mg of Alfuzosin to be taken daily once daily.

      STUDY INSTRUMENTS The primary end points of this study are a reduction in the ICIQ
      questionnaires and improvement in uroflow, post-void residual (PVR) and voiding diaries. All
      patients will have a detailed history and physical examination at the beginning of the study
      and at 12 weeks follow-up. Women will have a pregnancy test at the beginning of the study.
      Participants will be given the ICIQ questionnaires, uroflow and PVR at the screening visit
      and at week 6 and 12. In addition, these patients will be asked to maintain a three day
      voiding diary prior to week 2 and week 12. Assessments for safety (blood pressure and heart
      rate) will be collected at baseline and at the last visit. Blood tests will be performed to
      check for liver, kidney and prostate problems at the baseline visit. Adverse events will be
      recorded at all visits and when spontaneously reported by the study participants.

      DURATION OF STUDY The study will be 12 weeks in duration.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of funding
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary efficacy measures will be the ICIQ-LUTSqol questionnaire, the IPSS questionnaire, uroflow/PVR and the voiding diaries.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Bladder Dysfunction</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alfuzosin</intervention_name>
    <description>Alfuzosin 10 mg once daily po for 12 weeks</description>
    <other_name>Xatral</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Participant should be eighteen years of age or older.

          2. Participant should have LUTS secondary to Multiple Sclerosis as defined below.

          3. Participant should have frequency ≥ 8/day and/or incontinence and/or nocturia ≥
             2/night and/or urgency and/or urinary retention.

          4. Participant should be able to understand, speak and read English.

          5. Participant 's urine culture should not show any evidence of urinary tract infection.

          6. Participant should be willing to take part in the study and sign the consent form.

          7. Female participants consents to use a medically acceptable method of birth control
             throughout the entire study period and for four weeks after the study is completed.
             Medically acceptable methods of contraception that may be used by the study
             participants and/or their partner includes abstinence, birth control pills or patches,
             diaphragm with spermicide, IUD, condom and vaginal spermicide, surgical sterilization,
             vasectomy, progestin implants or injections.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participant with known hypersensitivity to Alfuzosin.

          2. Participant with history of postural hypotension and/or syncope.

          3. Participant has used another alpha blocker within the last 30 days.

          4. Participant has active urethral stricture disease.

          5. Participant has a history of prostate cancer within the preceding five years.

          6. Participant has hepatic dysfunction.

          7. Participant has renal dysfunction.

          8. Participant has unstable angina pectoris.

          9. Participant has a positive pregnancy test at the time of screening.

         10. Participant has a history of serious social, mental or medical conditions that would
             stop patient from taking part in the study.

         11. Participant has a history of alcohol or drug abuse within the last five years.

         12. Participant who is currently being treated for chronic bacterial prostatitis or
             painful bladder syndrome/interstitial cystitis.

         13. Participant has a significant medical problem which the investigator considers a
             serious risk for the patient to be part of the study.

         14. Use of any investigational drug or device within the last 6 months.

         15. Participant who is unwilling or unable to abide by the requirements of study.

         16. Participant has a bladder infection proven by urine culture.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jerzy B Gajewski, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>QEII Health Science Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>QE II Health Science Centre, Halifax Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3H 3A7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 30, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 3, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Jerzy B Gajewski MD</name_title>
    <organization>Capital District Health Authority</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pilot clinical trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alfuzosin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

