<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00686621</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P05113</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00686621</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single Patient Treatment of Posaconazole in Invasive Fungal Infections (Study P05113)(COMPLETED)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Single Patient Emergency Treatment Use of Posaconazole in Invasive Fungal Infections</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to provide posaconazole compassionate treatment to patients with
      invasive fungal infections: 1) which are resistant to standard antifungal therapies; 2) for
      which there are no effective therapies; 3) with a prior history of serious, severe, or
      life-threatening toxicities while receiving standard antifungal therapies, or 4) with
      pre-existing organ dysfunction which precludes the use of standard antifungal therapies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      NCT00686621 was voluntarily registered even though it is a single patient use study, also
      known as compassionate exemption study; therefore results will not be disclosed for this
      study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical efficacy and safety of use</measure>
    <time_frame>Clinical outcome and adverse events measured every 3 months until the drug is marketed in the country.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Mycoses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Posaconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Posaconazole oral suspension 400 mg twice daily with meal or nutritional supplement. Alternatively, if meal or nutritional supplement is not tolerated, posaconazole should be administered at a dose of 200 mg four times a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SCH 056592</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        General Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults (age &gt;=18 years) of either gender and of any race.

          -  Children (age &gt;= 2 to 17 years) of either gender and of any race, who are not eligible
             for enrollment under any current clinical trial. Compassionate use will be permitted
             only under the direct supervision of qualified experts in pediatric infectious
             diseases with the written approval of the Schering Plough medical director (local
             country operations or headquarters project director).

          -  Subject or his/her legally authorized representative has given signed, written
             informed consent,

          -  Ability to take study medication orally by swallowing or via an enteral feeding tube.

          -  Subject is not considered eligible for any other clinical research program with
             posaconazole.

        Safety Related Inclusion Criteria

          -  Male or a female patient who meets any one of the following criteria:

               -  postmenopausal, surgically sterilized, or documented to have primary ovarian
                  failure due to prior cytotoxic chemotherapy or radiation therapy; abstinent from
                  sexual intercourse or practicing effective birth control. Effective birth control
                  methods must continue for at least 30 days after discontinuation of treatment
                  with posaconazole.

          -  Known to be non pregnant by history or (preferably) by negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test prior to the first dose of posaconazole for all females of childbearing
             potential.

          -  Not breast feeding or if lactating, willing to discontinue breast feeding during
             treatment.

        Invasive Fungal Infection Inclusion Criteria

          -  Each patient must have:

               -  A documented invasive fungal infection who have failed a reasonable trial of
                  other licensed antifungal agents, either due to progression or lack of
                  improvement of the infection, or

               -  Serious, severe or life-threatening toxicities related to current or prior
                  antifungal therapy, or

               -  An invasive fungal infection for which there are currently no effective
                  therapies.

          -  Patients with debilitating but not immediately life threatening fungal diseases, where
             significant morbidity may result in disability and where prior antifungal therapy has
             been unsuccessful (eg, chronic mucocutaneous candidiasis, recurrent oropharyngeal or
             esophageal candidiasis with dehydration and malnutrition, or cutaneous
             phaeohyphomycosis and mycetoma).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are pregnant or who will continue to breast-feed infants.

          -  History of serious or severe hypersensitivity or idiosyncratic reactions to azole
             antifungals.

          -  Patients who require ongoing treatment with any prohibited medication (see Core
             Clinical Data Sheet and list of Prohibited Medications) and for whom an appropriate
             washout period has not elapsed.

          -  Patients who are in a situation or have any condition requiring the use of prohibited
             drugs or unstable medical conditions where the risk of therapy would exceed any
             potential benefit i.e., hematological disorder such as unstable cardiac disorder
             (including acute myocardial infarction or unstable myocardial ischemia/angina within
             30 days, ventricular arrhythmia within 30 days, uncontrolled atrial fibrillation, or
             atrial fibrillation/flutter with symptomatic bradycardia [sick sinus syndrome], or
             unstable congestive heart failure) or impairment expected to be unstable or
             progressive during the course of this study (e.g., recurrent or uncontrolled seizure
             disorders, demyelinating syndromes, or progressive peripheral neuropathy).

          -  Patients receiving vinca alkaloids or anthracyclines within 24 hours of study
             enrollment or requiring therapy with vinca alkaloids or anthracyclines within the next
             30 days for treatment of uncontrolled (pre-existing) malignancy or requiring ongoing
             therapy with vinca alkaloids or anthracyclines, where the risk of toxicity from these
             medicinal products is considered to be significant.

          -  Any condition requiring the use of prohibited drugs (please consult current product
             labeling).

          -  Hepatic function tests: alanine amino transferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase
             (AST) &gt;10 times upper limit of normal, or evidence of severe hepatic dysfunction based
             on other clinical assessment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Maertens J, Cornely OA, Ullmann AJ, Heinz WJ, Krishna G, Patino H, Caceres M, Kartsonis N, Waskin H, Robertson MN. Phase 1B study of the pharmacokinetics and safety of posaconazole intravenous solution in patients at risk for invasive fungal disease. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2014 Jul;58(7):3610-7. doi: 10.1128/AAC.02686-13. Epub 2014 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24733463</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 30, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mycoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Invasive Fungal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Posaconazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>http://www.merck.com/clinical-trials/pdf/Merck%20Procedure%20on%20Clinical%20Trial%20Data%20Access%20Final_Updated%20July_9_2014.pdf
http://engagezone.msd.com/ds_documentation.php</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

