<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02630823</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201601062</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02630823</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MK-3475 Immunotherapy in Endometrial Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunotherapy With MK-3475 in Surgically Resectable Endometrial Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Due to the high expression of PD-L1 in endometrial cancers as well as in ovarian cancers
      which are molecularly similar to uterine serous cancers, using pembrolizumab should be
      beneficial in this patient population. Since the investigators are able to get a
      pre-treatment research- related endometrial biopsy as well as the surgical specimen post two
      cycles of pembrolizumab, the investigators will be able to evaluate the mechanism of action
      of this drug on the endometrial cancer tumor environment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as measured by treatment related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days following last dose of MK-3475 (approximately 56 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>-The descriptions and grading scales found in the revised NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 will be utilized for all adverse event reporting</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years following completion of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first.
Progressive Disease (PD): At least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study (this includes the baseline sum if that is the smallest on study). In addition to the relative increase of 20%, the sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm. (Note: the appearance of one or more new lesions is also considered progressions).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasms, Endometrial</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: MK-3475</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo endometrial biopsy followed by 2 doses of MK-3475 3 weeks apart. 3-4 weeks after the second dose of MK-3475, the standard of care surgical resection will take place, followed by standard of care adjuvant therapy. Tissue and blood will be collected at the time of surgical resection for immune analysis. For patients whose pathology confirms high-risk features and advanced stage, MK-3475 will be given every 3 weeks starting 4 -6 weeks after completion of adjuvant therapy for a maximum of 4 doses post-surgery.
MK-3475 will be given intravenously at a dose of 200 mg over the course of 30 minutes.
The standard of care chemotherapy will consist of 6 cycles of paclitaxel and carboplatin AUC 5 every 3 weeks for 6 cycles.
The decision to administer radiation therapy will be per the treating physician. If the patient does not receive radiation therapy, then the patient will start MK-3475 every 3 weeks x 4 doses after the completion of chemotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3475</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: MK-3475</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pembrolizumab</other_name>
    <other_name>Keytruda</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical resection (standard of care)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: MK-3475</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel (standard of care)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: MK-3475</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Taxol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin (standard of care)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: MK-3475</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paraplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation (standard of care)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: MK-3475</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endometrial biopsy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: MK-3475</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peripheral blood draw</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: MK-3475</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of FIGO grade 3 endometrioid cancer, serous, clear cell, or mixed high grade
             endometrial cancer with confirmation on research-related endometrial biopsy.

          -  Radiographically confirmed endometrial adenocarcinoma of stages III-IV requiring
             adjuvant therapy. If stage III disease is suspected, there should be multiple pelvic
             and/or lymph nodes involved.

          -  Measurable disease defined as lesions that can be accurately measured in at least one
             dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as &gt;10 mm with CT scan, as &gt;20 mm by chest
             x-ray, or &gt;10 mm with calipers by clinical exam by RECIST 1.1.

          -  Treatment plan must include primary site biopsy followed by resection of the primary
             tumor site and any metastatic sites at time of surgery.

          -  At least 18 years of age.

          -  GOG performance status ≤ 2

          -  Normal bone marrow and organ function as defined below:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500/mcl

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/mcl

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x IULN OR direct bilirubin ≤ IULN for patients with total
                  bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x IULN

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x IULN (or ≤ 5 x IULN for patients with liver
                  metastases)

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x IULN OR creatinine clearance by Cockcroft-Gault ≥ 60
                  mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels &gt; 1.5 x IULN

               -  INR or PT ≤ 1.5 x IULN unless patient is receiving anticoagulant therapy as long
                  as INR or PTT is within therapeutic range of intended use of anticoagulants

               -  aPTT ≤ 1.5 x IULN unless patient is receiving anticoagulant therapy as long as
                  INR or PTT is within therapeutic range of intended use of anticoagulants

          -  Sexually active women of childbearing potential must agree to contraceptive methods as
             described by the protocol prior to study entry, for the duration of pre-operative
             study participation and until definitive hysterectomy/bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy.
             Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this
             study, she must inform her treating physician immediately.

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign an IRB approved written informed consent
             document (or that of legally authorized representative, if applicable).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  FIGO grade 1 or 2 endometrioid cancer.

          -  Radiographic imaging demonstrating uterine cancer that is probably stage I or II.

          -  Prior treatment for endometrial cancer.

          -  Prior treatment with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-PD-L2 agent.

          -  Prior anti-cancer monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to first dose of
             MK-3475 or has not recovered (i.e., to ≤ grade 1 or baseline) from adverse events due
             to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          -  Prior chemotherapy, targeted small molecule therapy, or radiation therapy within 2
             weeks prior to the first dose of MK-3475 or has not recovered (i.e., to ≤ grade 1 or
             baseline) from adverse events due to a previously administered agent. Note, subjects
             with ≤ grade 2 neuropathy are an exception to this criterion and may qualify for the
             study. Note, if a subject received major surgery, she must have recovered adequately
             from the toxicity and/or complications from the intervention prior to starting
             therapy.

          -  Received a live vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of MK-3475. Examples of
             live vaccines include, but are not limited to, the following: measles, mumps, rubella,
             varicella/zoster (chicken pox), yellow fever, rabies, Bacillus Calmette-Guérin (BCG),
             and typhoid vaccine. Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection are generally killed
             virus vaccines and are allowed; however, intranasal influenza vaccines (e.g. FluMist)
             are live attenuated vaccines and are not allowed.

          -  A history of other malignancy ≤ 5 years previous with the exception of basal cell or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin which were treated with local resection only.

          -  Known active central nervous system metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis.
             Subjects with previously treated brain metastases may participate provided they are
             stable (without evidence of progression by imaging for at least 4 weeks prior to the
             first dose of MK-3475 and any neurologic symptoms have returned to baseline), have no
             evidence of new or enlarging brain metastases, and are not using steroids for at least
             7 days prior to trial treatment. This exception does not include carcinomatous
             meningitis which is excluded regardless of clinical stability.

          -  Diagnosis of immunodeficiency or is receiving chronic systemic steroid therapy in
             dosing exceeding 10 mg daily of prednisone or equivalent) or any other form of
             immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of MK-3475.

          -  Currently receiving any other investigational agents or has participated in a study of
             an investigational agent or using an investigational device within 4 weeks of the
             first dose of MK-3475.

          -  A history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or
             biologic composition to MK-3475 or other agents used in the study.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection requiring systemic therapy, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, immunosuppression, autoimmune conditions,
             underlying pulmonary disease, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  Has an active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2
             years (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids, or
             immunosuppressive drugs). Replacement therapy (e.g., thyroxine, insulin, or
             physiologic corticosteroid replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency,
             etc.) is not considered a form of systemic treatment.

          -  Has a history of (non-infectious) pneumonitis that required steroids or current
             pneumonitis.

          -  Pregnant and/or breastfeeding. Patient must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy
             test within 72 hours of study entry.

          -  Known history of hepatitis B (defined as hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg] reactive)
             or known active hepatitis C virus (defined as HCV RNA [qualitative] is detected).

          -  Known history of HIV (HIV 1/2 antibodies).

          -  Known history of active TB.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Premal Thaker, M.D., MSc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Premal Thaker, M.D., MSc.</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-1740</phone>
    <email>thakerp@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Premal Thaker, M.D., MSc.</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-1740</phone>
      <email>thakerp@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Premal Thaker, M.D., MSc.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katherine Fuh, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea Hagemann, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ian Hagemann, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>L. Stewart Massad, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carolyn McCourt, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David G Mutch, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen T Oh, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Russell Pachynski, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew A Powell, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lindsay Kuroki, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 10, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

