<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02635815</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>699</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02635815</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risk Factors for Variceal Bleeding in Egyptian Patients With Non-Cirrhotic Portal Hypertension</brief_title>
  <official_title>Risk Factors for Variceal Bleeding in Egyptian Patients With Non-Cirrhotic Portal Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ain Shams University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background &amp; Aims: Non-cirrhotic portal hypertension (NCPH) represents a relatively
      infrequent group of conditions. This work aimed at determining causes of NCPH and evaluating
      the role of some clinical, laboratory, imaging and endoscopic parameters in prediction of
      variceal bleeding in an Egyptian cohort with NCPH.

      Methods: Sixty patients with non-cirrhotic portal hypertension and oesophageal varices were
      included. All underwent complete clinical evaluation, laboratory investigations, Color
      Doppler ultrasonography, platelet count/spleen diameter (mm) ratio and upper gastrointestinal
      endoscopy. Patients were classified into two groups according to variceal bleeding: (1) Group
      I: twenty six patients with history of bleeding or had an attack of bleeding during one year
      follow-up; and (2) Group II: thirty four patients without bleeding.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All of the included patients underwent: (1) A complete clinical evaluation; (2) Laboratory
      investigations: CBC, liver profile, viral markers (HBs Ag, HB core Ab, HCV Ab) using the
      ELISA technique; (3) Thrombophilia workup to clarify the underlying etiology of vascular
      liver disease. It was done only for patients with Budd-Chiari syndrome and extrahepatic
      portal vein thrombosis: anticardiolipin antibodies, lupus anticoagulant, antinuclear
      antibodies, protein C, S, antithrombin III, factor V Leiden G1691A mutation, prothrombin gene
      G20210A mutation, methylene tetrahydrofolate reductase C677T mutation by PCR, Janus tyrosine
      kinase-2 (JAK II) V617F mutation by PCR (to exclude myeloproliferative disorders) and flow
      cytometry for CD55 and CD59 (to exclude paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria); (4) Abdominal
      ultrasonography: for liver size, echogenicity, spleen size, portal vein diameter and ascites;
      (5) Color Doppler ultrasonographic study: was done in the morning after an overnight fasting
      using a color Doppler unit with a 3.5 MHz convex probe for confirmation of portal vein (PV)
      patency and diameter, mean PV flow velocity (mean PVV) (cm/sec), PV direction of flow,
      splenic vein patency and diameter, presence of portosystemic collaterals and patency of
      hepatic veins; (6) Platelet count/spleen diameter ratio: calculated as: platelet count/
      maximum spleen bipolar diameter by ultrasound in mm; (7) Ultrasonography guided liver biopsy:
      for diagnosis of NCPH and exclusion of cirrhotic portal hypertension; and (8) Upper
      gastrointestinal endoscopy using the Pentax video endoscope EG 3440. Oesophageal varices were
      classified according to their size into small, medium or large [8]. Prophylaxis with band
      ligation was done to patients with large or medium sized risky varices who were eligible for
      starting anticoagulation. The diagnosis of variceal bleeding was confirmed if an actively
      bleeding varix or a varix with adherent clot or white nipple was seen. Red color signs were
      classified into Cherry Red Spots &quot;CRS&quot;, Red Wale Markings &quot;RWM&quot; and Hematocystic Spots &quot;HCS&quot;.
      Gastric varices were classified into either gastro-esophageal varices (GEV) or isolated
      gastric varices (IGV). Portal hypertensive gastropathy (PHG) was classified into either mild
      or severe.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The presence or absence of variceal bleeding within one year of follow up.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Portal Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group I</arm_group_label>
    <description>twenty six patients with history of bleeding or had an attack of bleeding during one year follow-up. All underwent upper gastrointestinal endoscopy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group II</arm_group_label>
    <description>thirty four patients without bleeding. All underwent upper gastrointestinal endoscopy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Upper gastrointestinal endoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Upper gastrointestinal endoscopy using the Pentax video endoscope EG 3440</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Egyptian patients with non-cirrhotic portal hypertension (NCPH) with oesophageal varices,
        presenting with or without variceal bleeding
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Egyptian patients with non-cirrhotic portal hypertension (NCPH) with oesophageal
             varices

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with concomitant infection with viral hepatitis, cirrhotic portal
             hypertension, hepatocellular carcinoma as well as those with other sources of bleeding
             such as erosions or ulcers were excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Reda Elwakil, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sara Abdelhakam</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Portal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

