<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02636010</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GEM-PEMBRESID</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02636010</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) in MM Patients With Residual Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II, Multicenter, Open Label, Clinical Trial of the Anti-PD1 Monoclonal Antibody Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) as Consolidation Therapy in Multiple Myeloma Patients With Residual Disease After Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PETHEMA Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Adknoma Health Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PETHEMA Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a national, multicenter, open label single-arm, non-comparative study that will
      determine the efficacy, safety and the changes in selected pharmacodynamics markers of
      MK-3475 monotherapy administered as consolidation therapy in MM patients who have achieved a
      response with a previous treatment but who still display some residual disease.

      For this purpose, 20 MM patients, who have received any treatment of limited duration either
      at diagnosis or at first relapse, and that have achieved a good response (≥VGPR) but with
      persistent residual disease (that is patients in VGPR, non-stringent CR, or MRD+ sCR), will
      be treated with MK-3475 monotherapy administered iv at a dose of 200 mg every three weeks for
      1 year, with a potential expansion of 1 additional year of treatment in case of clinical
      benefit and patient agreement. Efficacy, safety and pharmacodynamic parameters will be
      evaluated to understand the role of this monoclonal antibody in this setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multiple Myeloma (MM) is a B cell malignancy characterized by the presence of bone marrow
      infiltration by clonal plasma cells that generally secrete a monoclonal component in the
      serum or urine. It is the second most frequent hematological malignancy, after non-Hodgkin
      lymphomas, and accounts approximately for a 10% of all hematological tumors and 1% of all
      cancers. Treatment of MM has remained substantially unchanged for some time (reviewed in with
      alkylating agents such as melphalan in combination with steroids being the gold standard for
      more than 25 years. Later on, in the 1970 decade, other drugs such as carmustine or
      vincristine where combined with melphalan, cyclophosphamide or steroids giving rise to the
      chemotherapeutic regimens; and ten years later high doses of melphalan with autologous stem
      cell transplantation (ASCT) where introduced into the clinical practice. All these treatment
      schemes resulted in an overall survival of around 30 months until 1994 with a slight
      improvement in the subsequent five years, probably due to the introduction of ASCT and better
      measures of supportive care. Finally, in the first decade of this century, some new drugs
      with novel mechanisms of action and clear antimyeloma activity have been discovered and
      approved. In this regard, several studies have demonstrated the activity of the proteasome
      inhibitor bortezomib and the immunomodulatory agents thalidomide and lenalidomide in
      relapsed/refractory MM patients. The emergence of these drugs has resulted in a clear
      improvement in the outcome of these patients in the last years, with an increase in median
      overall survival of up to five years.

      Nevertheless, despite this clear progress, most patients (if not all) eventually relapse and
      the outcome of MM patients once they become refractory or ineligible to receive bortezomib or
      an IMID is quite poor with a survival inferior to one year.Therefore novel therapeutic
      options are still necessary for these relapsed or refractory patients. In this regard,
      several drugs that target specific mechanisms of the tumoral cells are currently being
      explored in the preclinical and clinical setting.(10) Some examples of the most promising of
      these targeted agents are second-generation proteasome inhibitors or immunomodulatory agents,
      deacetylase inhibitors (DACi), the kinesin spindle protein inhibitor filanesib and several
      monoclonal antibodies.

      Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) Programmed cell death 1 (PD-1) axis function and mechanism of action
      of MK-3475 The programmed cell death 1 (PD-1) receptor-ligand interaction is a major pathway
      hijacked by tumors to suppress immune control. The normal function of PD-1, expressed on the
      cell surface of activated T cells under healthy conditions, is to down-modulate unwanted or
      excessive immune responses, including autoimmune reactions.

      PD-1 and family members are type I transmembrane glycoproteins containing an Ig Variable-type
      (V-type) domain responsible for ligand binding and a cytoplasmic tail responsible for the
      binding of signaling molecules. The cytoplasmic tail of PD-1 contains two tyrosine-based
      signaling motifs, an immunoreceptor tyrosine-based inhibition motif (ITIM) and an
      immunoreceptor tyrosine-based switch motif (ITSM). Following T-cell stimulation, PD-1
      recruits the tyrosine phosphatases, SHP-1 and SHP-2, to the ITSM motif within its cytoplasmic
      tail, leading to the dephosphorylation of effector molecules such as CD3ζ, PKCθ, and ZAP70,
      which are involved in the CD3 T-cell signaling cascade.

      PD-1 (encoded by the gene Pdcd1) is an immunoglobulin (Ig) superfamily member related to CD28
      and CTLA-4 which has been shown to negatively regulate antigen receptor signaling upon
      engagement of its ligands (PD-L1 and/or PD-L2).The mechanism by which PD-1 down modulates
      T-cell responses is similar to, but distinct from, that of CTLA-4, as both molecules regulate
      an overlapping set of signaling proteins. PD-1 was shown to be expressed on activated
      lymphocytes including peripheral CD4+ and CD8+ T cells, B cells, T regs, and natural killer
      cells. Expression has also been shown during thymic development on CD4-CD8- (double negative)
      T cells, as well as subsets of macrophages and dendritic cells.(20) The ligands for PD-1
      (PD-L1 and PD-L2) are constitutively expressed or can be induced in a variety of cell types
      including non-hematopoietic tissues and in various tumors. Both ligands are type 1
      transmembrane receptors containing both IgV- and IgC-like domains in the extracelular region
      and contain short cytoplasmic regions with no known signaling motifs. Binding of either PD-L1
      or PD-L2 to PD-1 inhibits T-cell activation triggered through the T-cell receptor. PD-L1 is
      expressed at low levels on various non-hematopoietic tissues, most notably on vascular
      endothelium; whereas PD-L2 is only detectably-expressed on antigen-presenting cells found in
      lymphoid tissue or chronic inflammatory environments. PD-L2 is thought to control immune
      T-cell activation in lymphoid organs, whereas PDL1 serves to dampen unwarranted T-cell
      function in peripheral tissues.Although healthy organs express little (if any) PD-L1, a
      variety of cancers were demonstrated to express abundant levels of this T-cell inhibitor.
      High expression of PD-L1 on tumor cells (and to a lesser extent of PD-L2) has been found to
      correlate with poor prognosis and survival in various cancer types, including RCC, pancreatic
      carcinoma, HCC, and ovarian carcinoma. Furthermore, PD-1 has been suggested to regulate
      tumor-specific T-cell expansion in patients with melanoma. The observed correlation of
      clinical prognosis with PD-L1 expression in multiple cancers suggests that the PD-1/PD-L1
      pathway plays a critical role in tumor immune evasion and should be considered as an
      attractive target for therapeutic intervention.

      MK-3475 (previously known as SCH 900475) is a potent and highly selective humanized
      monoclonal antibody (mAb) of the IgG4/kappa isotype designed to directly block the
      interaction between PD-1 and its ligands, PD-L1 and PD-L2. This blockade enhances functional
      activity of the target lymphocytes to facilitate tumor regression and ultimately immune
      rejection.

        -  Clinical experience with MK-3475 Several clinical trials are being conducted in advanced
           melanoma, non-small cell lung cancer, head and neck cancer, urothelial tract cancer,
           triple negative breast cancer, gastric cancer, and hematologic malignancies (including
           smoldering multiple myeloma). A phase I trial in combination with lenalidomide and
           dexamethasone is now enrolling MM patients. .

        -  Rationale for using anti-PD1 MoAb as consolidation in MM PD-L1 is expressed on most MM
           plasma cells, and PD-L1 overexpression enhanced MM invasiveness and rendered tumor cells
           less susceptible to cytotoxic T-lymphocytes (CTLs). This effect was alleviated by
           anti-PD-L1 antibody treatment, demonstrating the importance of the PD-1/PD-L1 pathway in
           this process. In addition, a recent report demonstrated increased levels of PD-L1 on MM
           cells together with enhanced PD-1 expression on T cells with an &quot;exhausted&quot; phenotype.
           The immunosuppressive effects of myeloma are overcome by PD-L1 blockade.(32) A Phase 1
           clinical trial conducted in advanced hematologic malignancies using CT-011, showed
           clinical responses in 6 of 17 patients including stable disease in MM patients.

      Moreover, a recent experiment performed by our group showed that MM patients in serological
      complete remission but with residual disease have clear overexpression of the molecules in
      this pathway both in tumor cells and also T-lymphocytes. And that was very clear when
      compared with MM patients in immunophenotypic CR (that is without residual cells in the bone
      marrow by flow cytometry). This could be suggesting that this pathway may be responsible, at
      least partially, of the inability to eradicate the tumor cells in these patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of Pembrolizumab as measured by overall response rate manteinance</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety will be evaluated by assessing toxicity related to pembrolizumab</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy as measured by minimal residual disease rate after two years of maintenance treatment with pembrolizumab</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3475 Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MK-3475 at a dose of 200 mg every three weeks for 1 year with a potential expansion of 1 additional year of treatment in case of clinical benefit and patient agreement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MK-3475 Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MK-3475</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  Performance status (ECOG) ≤ 2.

          -  Patient is, in the Investigator's opinion, willing and able to comply with the
             protocol requirements.

          -  Patient has given voluntary written informed consent before performance of any
             study-related procedure not part of normal medical care, with the understanding that
             consent may be withdrawn by the patient at any time without prejudice to their future
             medical care.

          -  Patients previously diagnosed with MM according to the IMWG Criteria (Blood 2011) who
             are in good response (≥VGPR) but with persistent residual disease after the end of any
             therapy administered for a limited duration of time either at 1st or 2nd line of
             therapy.

        Persistent disease is defined by either the presence of an M-Component by electrophoresis,
        positive immunofixation, abnormal FLC ratio or identification of pathological plasma cells
        by flow cytometry.

          -  At least 2 months for any non-transplant therapy or 3 months after ASCT, must relapse
             from the last dose of the previous treatment before being eligible to be included in
             the trial.

          -  Response must be confirmed to be stable between the end of the previous therapy and
             the initiation of the trial (see the time that must elapse in the previous criteria).

        Stable is defined as: No change in response according to the IMWG Criteria between these
        determinations; No evidence of increase or decrease (&gt; 25%) in M-component, provided the
        variation is &gt; 0.5 mg/dl; No evidence of increase or decrease (&gt; 25%) of the involved FLC,
        provided the ratio is abnormal and the absolute change is &gt; 10 mg/dL; No evidence of
        increase or decrease (&gt; 50%) of the percentage of pathological plasma cells by flow
        cytometry in the bone marrow provided the variation is &gt; 0.5%; No positivization or
        negativization of the electrophoresis or IFE between these determinations.

        In case of doubt, another determination separated at least 1 month after the last one is
        required to confirm the stability of the response, and this must be discussed with the DMC,
        prior to be eligible.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2, anti-CD137, or anti-Cytotoxic
             T-lymphocyte-associated antigen-4 (CTLA-4) antibody (including ipilimumab or other
             antibody or drug specifically targeting T cell co-stimulation).

          -  Known hypersensitivity to pembrolizumab or any of its excipients.

          -  Non-adequate hematological or biochemical parameters as specified below:

        Hemoglobin &lt; 8.0 g/dl. Platelets count &lt; 75 x109/L without previous platelet transfusions
        in the last 7 days.

        Neutrophils (ANC) &lt;1 × 109/L without growth factor support (defined as no growth factor
        administration for at least 14 days prior to observation).

        Aspartate transaminase (AST): &gt; 2.5 x the upper limit range. Alanine transaminase (ALT): &gt;
        2.5 x the upper limit range. Total bilirubin: &gt; 2 x the upper limit range. Creatinine
        clearance: &lt; 30 mL/min (measured or calculated with the Cockcroft and Gault formula).

          -  Absence of recovery from any significant non-hematological toxicity derived from
             previous treatments. The presence of alopecia and NCI CTCAE grade &lt; 2 symptomatic
             peripheral neuropathy is allowed.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women or expecting to conceive or father children within the
             projected duration of the trial, starting with the pre-screening or screening visit
             through 120 days after the last dose of trial treatment. Female subjects of
             childbearing potential should have a negative urine or serum pregnancy prior to study
             registration and re-tested within 72 hours prior to receiving the first dose of study
             medication.

          -  Men and women of reproductive potential who are not using effective contraceptive
             methods (double barrier method, intrauterine device, oral contraception). Male
             subjects should agree to use an adequate method of contraception starting with the
             first dose of study therapy through 120 days after the last dose of study therapy

          -  Previous history of any other malignancy in the last 5 years (except basal cell
             carcinoma, skin epithelioma or carcinoma in situ of any site).

          -  More than 2 prior lines of therapy for MM.

          -  Previous allogeneic stem cell transplantation.

          -  Other relevant diseases or adverse clinical conditions:

        Congestive heart failure or angina pectoris, myocardial infarction within 12 months before
        inclusion in the study.

        Uncontrolled arterial hypertension or cardiac arrhythmias (i.e. requiring a change in
        medication within the last 3 months or a hospital admission within the past 6 months).

        History of significant neurological or psychiatric disorders. Active infection. Significant
        non-neoplastic liver disease (e.g., cirrhosis, active chronic hepatitis).

        Uncontrolled endocrine diseases (e.g. diabetes mellitus, hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism)
        (i.e. requiring relevant changes in medication within the last month, or hospital admission
        within the last 3 months).

        Active autoimmune disease or a documented history of autoimmune disease, or a syndrome that
        requires systemic steroids or immunosuppressive agents. Subjects with vitiligo or resolved
        childhood asthma/atopy would be an exception to this rule. Subjects that require
        intermittent use of bronchodilators or local steroid injections would not be excluded from
        the study. Subjects with hypothyroidism stable on hormone replacement or Sjogren's syndrome
        will not be excluded from the trial.

          -  Patient is known to be HIV positive, Hepatitis B surface antigen-positive, has active
             hepatitis C infection or has active tuberculosis.

          -  Limitation of the patient's ability to comply with the treatment or follow-up
             protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Germans Trias i Pujol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Badalona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital 12 de octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>MAdrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Ramón y Cajal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Morales Messeguer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murcia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario Morales Messeguer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murcia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Universitaria de Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hoapital Clinico Universitario Salamanca</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salamanca</city>
        <zip>37007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Virgen del Rocio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Doctor Peset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clinico de Zaragoza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zaragoza</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 16, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

