<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02637453</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ShanghaiXinhua-Af</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02637453</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Additional Linear Ablation Beyond Pulmonary Vein Isolation for Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Additional Linear Ablation Perpendicular to the Pulmonary Vein Isolation Line Reduces the Recurrence Rate of Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation (ALA-PAF)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pulmonary vein(PV) isolation has become the cornerstone of radiofrequency ablation for AF.
      However, recent reports have clearly shown that the longer the follow-up period, the lower
      the success rate with a single ablation procedure. In 5-year follow-up, the mean success rate
      was only about 45%. The purpose of the study to investigate whether the linear ablation
      perpendicular to the PV ostium on the basis of circumferential pulmonary vein isolation, can
      reduce recurrence rate of AF. All patients will be followed up for 12 months. And fourteen
      days Holter will be performed at the end of follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence rate of atrial fibrillation(Af) in 12-month follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of the observed time that a patient is in AF</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after ablation procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of the observed time that a patient is in AF, when the fourteen days Holter is performed at the end of follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of pulmonary vein stenosis, cardiac tamponade, phrenic nerve and embolism</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of life quality (SF-36 questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major cardiovascular events: heart failure, stroke, hospitalization and cardiovascular death</measure>
    <time_frame>monthly up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">390</enrollment>
  <condition>Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPVI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Only circumferential pulmonary vein isolation(CPVI) was performed for these patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPVI+ALA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Besides circumferential pulmonary vein isolation(CPVI), additional linear ablation(ALA) perpendicular to the pulmonary vein ostium was performed for these patients, ie. CPVI+ALA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPVI</intervention_name>
    <description>patients with circumferential pulmonary vein isolation （CPVI）</description>
    <arm_group_label>CPVI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPVI+ALA</intervention_name>
    <description>patients with circumferential pulmonary vein isolation（CPVI）and additional linear ablation perpendicular to the PV ostium （ALA）</description>
    <arm_group_label>CPVI+ALA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. With a history of paroxysmal Af(PAF) and PAF record within 6 months prior to ablation,
             confirming at least one of the following findings:

             AF lasting for ≥30 s recorded in Holter or 12-lead ECG

          2. No response to more than one antiarrhythmic drug, or unwilling to receive long-term
             drug treatment.

          3. Can provide informed consent form expressing willingness to participate in the study
             and comply with follow-up tests and evaluation procedures.

          4. Aged 18-80 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. With acute diseases, such as acute phase after myocardial infarction (within 3
             months), within 3 months after acute heart failure or new cerebral infarction;

          2. In the list of heart transplantation;

          3. Expected survival less than 1 year;

          4. With other hemorrhagic diseases and anticoagulant therapy is not allowed;

          5. Thrombosis in left atrium;

          6. Heart failure, New York Heart Association(NYHA) III/IV or eject fraction(EF)&lt;40%;

          7. Patients with uncontrolled cancer;

          8. Significant hepatic or renal impairment (and/or alanine transaminase(ALT) or Aspartate
             transaminase(AST) &gt;2 times upper limit of normal, creatinine clearance rate(CCr)&lt;50%);

          9. Previous catheter radiofrequency ablation for AF or cardiac surgery;

         10. Pregnant and lactating women, women who plan to become pregnant, or women of child
             bearing age not using reliable contraceptive measures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yi-Gang Li, MD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiaotong University School of Medicne</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yi-Gang Li, MD.</last_name>
    <phone>13761318166</phone>
    <email>drliyigang@outlook.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jian Sun, MD.</last_name>
    <phone>15801816064</phone>
    <email>ep-sunjian@vip.163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200092</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yi-Gang Li, MD.</last_name>
      <phone>13761318166</phone>
      <email>drliyigang@outlook.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jian Sun, MD.</last_name>
      <phone>15801816064</phone>
      <email>ep-sunjian@vip.163.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yi-Gang Li, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steinberg BA, Beckley PD, Deering TF, Clark CL, Amin AN, Bauer KA, Cryer B, Mansour M, Scheiman JM, Zenati MA, Newby LK, Peacock WF, Bhatt DL; Society of Cardiovascular Patient Care. Evaluation and management of the atrial fibrillation patient: a report from the Society of Cardiovascular Patient Care. Crit Pathw Cardiol. 2013 Sep;12(3):107-15. doi: 10.1097/HPC.0b013e31829834ed.</citation>
    <PMID>23892939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weerasooriya R, Khairy P, Litalien J, Macle L, Hocini M, Sacher F, Lellouche N, Knecht S, Wright M, Nault I, Miyazaki S, Scavee C, Clementy J, Haissaguerre M, Jais P. Catheter ablation for atrial fibrillation: are results maintained at 5 years of follow-up? J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Jan 11;57(2):160-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.05.061.</citation>
    <PMID>21211687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calkins H, Kuck KH, Cappato R, Brugada J, Camm AJ, Chen SA, Crijns HJ, Damiano RJ Jr, Davies DW, DiMarco J, Edgerton J, Ellenbogen K, Ezekowitz MD, Haines DE, Haissaguerre M, Hindricks G, Iesaka Y, Jackman W, Jalife J, Jais P, Kalman J, Keane D, Kim YH, Kirchhof P, Klein G, Kottkamp H, Kumagai K, Lindsay BD, Mansour M, Marchlinski FE, McCarthy PM, Mont JL, Morady F, Nademanee K, Nakagawa H, Natale A, Nattel S, Packer DL, Pappone C, Prystowsky E, Raviele A, Reddy V, Ruskin JN, Shemin RJ, Tsao HM, Wilber D; Heart Rhythm Society Task Force on Catheter and Surgical Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation. 2012 HRS/EHRA/ECAS expert consensus statement on catheter and surgical ablation of atrial fibrillation: recommendations for patient selection, procedural techniques, patient management and follow-up, definitions, endpoints, and research trial design: a report of the Heart Rhythm Society (HRS) Task Force on Catheter and Surgical Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation. Developed in partnership with the European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA), a registered branch of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Cardiac Arrhythmia Society (ECAS); and in collaboration with the American College of Cardiology (ACC), American Heart Association (AHA), the Asia Pacific Heart Rhythm Society (APHRS), and the Society of Thoracic Surgeons (STS). Endorsed by the governing bodies of the American College of Cardiology Foundation, the American Heart Association, the European Cardiac Arrhythmia Society, the European Heart Rhythm Association, the Society of Thoracic Surgeons, the Asia Pacific Heart Rhythm Society, and the Heart Rhythm Society. Heart Rhythm. 2012 Apr;9(4):632-696.e21. doi: 10.1016/j.hrthm.2011.12.016. Epub 2012 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>22386883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noheria A, Kumar A, Wylie JV Jr, Josephson ME. Catheter ablation vs antiarrhythmic drug therapy for atrial fibrillation: a systematic review. Arch Intern Med. 2008 Mar 24;168(6):581-6. doi: 10.1001/archinte.168.6.581. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18362249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Haïssaguerre M, Jaïs P, Shah DC, Takahashi A, Hocini M, Quiniou G, Garrigue S, Le Mouroux A, Le Métayer P, Clémenty J. Spontaneous initiation of atrial fibrillation by ectopic beats originating in the pulmonary veins. N Engl J Med. 1998 Sep 3;339(10):659-66.</citation>
    <PMID>9725923</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zhang S. Atrial fibrillation in mainland China: epidemiology and current management. Heart. 2009 Jul;95(13):1052-5. doi: 10.1136/hrt.2008.146589. Epub 2009 Mar 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19318342</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cheema A, Vasamreddy CR, Dalal D, Marine JE, Dong J, Henrikson CA, Spragg D, Cheng A, Nazarian S, Sinha S, Halperin H, Berger R, Calkins H. Long-term single procedure efficacy of catheter ablation of atrial fibrillation. J Interv Card Electrophysiol. 2006 Apr;15(3):145-55. Epub 2006 Aug 5.</citation>
    <PMID>17019636</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ouyang F, Tilz R, Chun J, Schmidt B, Wissner E, Zerm T, Neven K, Köktürk B, Konstantinidou M, Metzner A, Fuernkranz A, Kuck KH. Long-term results of catheter ablation in paroxysmal atrial fibrillation: lessons from a 5-year follow-up. Circulation. 2010 Dec 7;122(23):2368-77. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.946806. Epub 2010 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21098450</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Calò L, Rebecchi M, Sciarra L, De Luca L, Fagagnini A, Zuccaro LM, Pitrone P, Dottori S, Porfirio M, de Ruvo E, Lioy E. Catheter ablation of right atrial ganglionated plexi in patients with vagal paroxysmal atrial fibrillation. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2012 Feb;5(1):22-31. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.111.964262. Epub 2011 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22147839</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Katritsis DG, Pokushalov E, Romanov A, Giazitzoglou E, Siontis GC, Po SS, Camm AJ, Ioannidis JP. Autonomic denervation added to pulmonary vein isolation for paroxysmal atrial fibrillation: a randomized clinical trial. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Dec 17;62(24):2318-25. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.06.053. Epub 2013 Aug 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23973694</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stabile G, Bertaglia E, Senatore G, De Simone A, Zoppo F, Donnici G, Turco P, Pascotto P, Fazzari M, Vitale DF. Catheter ablation treatment in patients with drug-refractory atrial fibrillation: a prospective, multi-centre, randomized, controlled study (Catheter Ablation For The Cure Of Atrial Fibrillation Study). Eur Heart J. 2006 Jan;27(2):216-21. Epub 2005 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>16214831</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wilber DJ, Pappone C, Neuzil P, De Paola A, Marchlinski F, Natale A, Macle L, Daoud EG, Calkins H, Hall B, Reddy V, Augello G, Reynolds MR, Vinekar C, Liu CY, Berry SM, Berry DA; ThermoCool AF Trial Investigators. Comparison of antiarrhythmic drug therapy and radiofrequency catheter ablation in patients with paroxysmal atrial fibrillation: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2010 Jan 27;303(4):333-40. doi: 10.1001/jama.2009.2029.</citation>
    <PMID>20103757</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Reddy VY, Dukkipati SR, Neuzil P, Natale A, Albenque JP, Kautzner J, Shah D, Michaud G, Wharton M, Harari D, Mahapatra S, Lambert H, Mansour M. Randomized, Controlled Trial of the Safety and Effectiveness of a Contact Force-Sensing Irrigated Catheter for Ablation of Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation: Results of the TactiCath Contact Force Ablation Catheter Study for Atrial Fibrillation (TOCCASTAR) Study. Circulation. 2015 Sep 8;132(10):907-15. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.114.014092. Epub 2015 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26260733</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 22, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 17, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 17, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 22, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yi-Gang Li</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation;Additional Linear Ablation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

