<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02632981</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-10-14-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02632981</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IL-32 Levels in Patients With Chronic Periodontitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>IL-32 Levels in Gingival Crevicular Fluid and Saliva of Patients With Chronic Periodontitis After Periodontal Treatment.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bulent Ecevit University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bulent Ecevit University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Interleukin-32 (IL-32) is a recently described cytokine that is a strong inducer of
      pro-inflammatory cytokines such as tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α. A previous report have
      reported that Porphyromonas gingivalis-derived LPS significantly up-regulated IL-32
      expression compared with the unstimulated cells in monocytes (THP-1 cells). They suggested
      that IL-32 may contribute to the pathogenesis of periodontal disease. In the present study
      the investigators hypothesized that IL-32 levels may increase in the gingival crevicular
      fluid (GCF) and saliva of patients with chronic periodontitis compared with healthy controls
      and these levels may decrease together with treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study was to investigate IL-32 levels in the GCF and saliva of patients
      with chronic periodontitis and to evaluate changes after nonsurgical periodontal therapy.

      Twenty-seven CP and 27 periodontally healthy controls were enrolled in this study.
      Periodontitis patients received nonsurgical periodontal treatment. GCF and saliva sampling
      and clinical periodontal parameters were assessed before and a month after treatment. IL-32,
      IL-10 and TNF-α levels in GCF and saliva were measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay.

      Unstimulated salivary samples were collected using standard techniques. About 2 mL whole
      saliva was collected in disposable tubes and centrifuged immediately to remove cell debris
      (10,000 g x 10 minutes). The supernatants (50µL each) were stored at -40C until analyzed. GCF
      samples were collected from a mesio-buccal and disto-palatal site on each tooth. In the CP
      group, the samples were obtained from patients at areas with ≥5 mm CAL, ≥6 mm PD and ≥30%
      bone loss. In the healthy group, GCF samples were collected from teeth exhibiting PD&lt;3 mm
      without CAL and BOP. The area was isolated with cotton rolls, saliva contamination
      elimination was ensured, and it was slightly air dried. GCF was sampled with paper strips.
      Paper strips were placed into the crevice until mild resistance was felt (intracrevicular
      method) and left in the position for 30 seconds. Strips contaminated with blood or saliva
      were discarded. Each sampled strip was placed into a 400µl eppendorf centrifuge tube and
      stored at -40C until analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical parameters (IL-32, IL-10 and THF-alpha)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in levels of IL-32 after periodontal treatment determined by ELISA. The changes in levels of IL-32 were analyzed to determine diagnostic and prognostic potential as a biomarker of periodontitis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probing pocket depth</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in probing pocket depth after periodontal treatment.Probing pocket depth was measured for determining severity of disease and clinic outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probing pocket depth and clinical attachment level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in clinical attachment level after periodontal treatment. The probing depth and the distance from the gingival margin to the cemento-enamel junction are used to measurement of clinical attachment level. Clinical attachment level was measured for determining severity of disease and clinic outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gingival index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in gingival index after periodontal treatment. Gingival index was recorded for classifying and evaluating (coronally) gingival inflammation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plaque index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in plaque index after periodontal treatment. Plaque index was recorded for determining and classifying oral hygiene status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding on probing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in bleeding on probing after periodontal treatment. Bleeding on probing was recorded for classifying and evaluating (apically) gingival inflammation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Periodontitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chronic periodontitis patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>gingival crevicular fluid and saliva collecion were taken before and after nonsurgical periodontal treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>periodontally healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>gingival crevicular fluid and saliva collection were taken at baseline after oral hygiene instructions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nonsurgical periodontal treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Scaling and root planning under local anaesthesia, in a total of four clinical visits Oral hygiene instructions including the modified Bass technique, regular toothpaste, and an appropriate interdental cleaning device with dental floss and interdental brush.</description>
    <arm_group_label>chronic periodontitis patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>chronic periodontitis patients</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gingival crevicular fluid and saliva collection</intervention_name>
    <description>GCF collection with filter paper (Periopaper) using the intracrevicular method. Patients' mouths were rinsed with distilled water, and unstimulated salivary samples were collected by patients expectorating into disposable tubes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>periodontally healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>periodontally healthy controls</other_name>
    <other_name>chronic periodontitis patients</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all subjects in the study were possess of at least 20 teeth excluding third molars.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  agressive periodontitis,

          -  periapical pathologies,

          -  excessive forces including mechanical forces caused by orthodontic forces and occlusal
             forces;

          -  presence of systemic diseases;

          -  administration of non-steroidal and anti-inflammatory drugs or antibiotic therapies
             within the previous 6 months;

          -  need for antibiotic prophylaxis for dental treatment and having received non-surgical
             periodontal treatment within the past 6 months or surgical periodontal treatment
             within the past 12 months;

          -  allergy or sensitivity to any drug,

          -  pregnancy,

          -  lactation, and

          -  current and former use of tobacco.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 16, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 16, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 16, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bulent Ecevit University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Figen ÖNGÖZ DEDE</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Bülent Ecevit University Faculty of Dentistry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Interleukin-32</keyword>
  <keyword>periodontitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Periodontitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Periodontitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

