<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02639026</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCC 23915</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02639026</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial Of Hypofractionated Radiotherapy In Combination With MEDI4736 And Tremelimumab For Patients With Metastatic Melanoma And Lung, Breast And Pancreatic Cancers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Trial Of Hypofractionated Radiotherapy In Combination With MEDI4736 And Tremelimumab For Patients With Metastatic Melanoma And Lung, Breast And Pancreatic Cancers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of this study is to determine how best to combine hypofractionated
      radiotherapy, MEDI4736, and tremelimumab and to determine how safe and tolerable
      hypofractionated radiotherapy, MEDI4736, and tremelimumab are when given together in subjects
      with metastatic, melanoma, non small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), breast cancer, and pancreatic
      cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Non Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive 20 mg/kg MEDI4736 and 1 mg/kg tremelimumab in combination every 4 weeks for 4 doses, followed by 10 mg/kg MEDI4736 monotherapy every 2 weeks for 18 doses. The total duration of therapy is 12 months. Cohort 1 tests 8 Gy x 3 fractions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive 20 mg/kg MEDI4736 and 1 mg/kg tremelimumab in combination every 4 weeks for 4 doses, followed by 10 mg/kg MEDI4736 monotherapy every 2 weeks for 18 doses. The total duration of therapy is 12 months. Cohort 2 tests 17 Gy x 1 fraction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>two schedules of radiotherapy (8 Gy x 3 fractions and 17 Gy x 1 fraction)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MEDI4736</intervention_name>
    <description>20 mg/kg MEDI4736 every 4 weeks for 4 doses, followed by 10 mg/kg MEDI4736 monotherapy every 2 weeks for 18 doses</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tremelimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>1 mg/kg every 4 weeks for 4 doses</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically or cytologically confirmed metastatic melanoma,metastatic
             non-small cell lung cancer, metastatic breast cancer, or metastatic pancreatic
             adenocarcinoma relapsed or refractory to therapy as outlined below or patients with
             these malignancies who have declined, are or have become unable to tolerate (e.g.
             progressive chemotherapy-associated peripheral neuropathy), or were not eligible for
             standard therapy: Metastatic melanoma patients at any line of therapy, Metastatic
             non-small cell lung cancer patients who have relapsed or are refractory to at least
             one line of systemic anti-cancer therapy for metastatic disease, including cytotoxic
             chemotherapy or targeted therapy, Metastatic breast cancer patients who have relapsed
             or are refractory to at least one line of systemic anti-cancer therapy for metastatic
             disease, such as cytotoxic chemotherapy, hormonal therapy, or targeted therapy,
             Metastatic pancreatic adenocarcinoma who have relapsed or are refractory to at least
             one line of systemic anti-cancer therapy for metastatic disease, such as cytotoxic
             chemotherapy or targeted therapy

          -  At least two measurable lesions (including the index lesion) according to RECIST
             guidelines v1.1

          -  An index lesion measuring between 1cm - 7cm that is amenable to hypofractionated
             radiation therapy at the discretion of the treating radiation oncologist

             o Index lesions in the pancreas are excluded in the second cohort

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years

          -  Signed, written informed consent

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-1

          -  Adequate hematological function documented within 3 weeks prior to initial treatment
             based on: White blood cell ≥ 2,500 cells/ul without growth factor support, Absolute
             neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500 cells/ul without growth factor support, Hemoglobin ≥ 9
             g/dL, Platelet count ≥ 100,000 platelets/ul, Adequate hepatic and renal function
             documented within 3 weeks prior to initial treatment based on: Aspartate
             aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 x upper limit of
             normal (ULN). For subjects with liver metastasis, ALT and AST ≤ 5 x ULN, Total
             bilirubin ≤1.5 x ULN except in patients with documented Gilbert's syndrome or liver
             metastasis, who must have a baseline total bilirubin ≤ 3.0 mg/dl, Serum creatinine ≤
             2.0 mg/dL

          -  Full recovery from the acute effects of prior cancer treatments, defined as effects
             having resolved to NCI CTCAE v4.03 Grade 0 or 1 with the exception of alopecia and
             certain laboratory values as listed above. Subjects with irreversible toxicity that is
             not reasonably expected to be exacerbated by MEDI4736 and tremelimumab may be included
             (eg, hearing loss, neuropathy) upon approval of the PI.

          -  For patients with central nervous system (CNS) metastases, metastases must be
             asymptomatic at the time of Day 1 of the study and meet the following criteria:

          -  At least 28 days without progression of CNS metastases as evidenced by magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) after last day of treatment with
             radiation to the CNS metastases

          -  At least 14 days since last dose of corticosteroids

          -  Must not have leptomeningeal disease or cord compression

          -  Females of childbearing potential who are sexually active with a nonsterilized male
             partner must use highly effective method of contraception from the time of screening,
             and must agree to continue using such precautions for 180 days after the final dose of
             MEDI4736 and tremelimumab. Cessation of contraception after this point should be
             discussed with a responsible physician. Periodic abstinence, the rhythm method, and
             the withdrawal method are not acceptable methods of contraception. They must also
             refrain from egg cell donation for 180 days after the final dose of MEDI4736 and
             tremelimumab: Females of childbearing potential are defined as those who are not
             surgically sterile (ie, bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy, or complete
             hysterectomy) or those who are not post-menopausal (defined as 12 months with no
             menses with postmenopausal gonadotropin levels, luteinizing hormone [LH] and
             follicle-stimulating [FSH], or postmenopausal estradiol levels within the
             postmenopausal range according to local guidelines without an alternative medical
             cause), A highly effective method of contraception is defined as one that results in a
             low failure rate (i.e., less than 1% per year) when used consistently and correctly.
             The acceptable methods of contraception include barrier methods (male condom plus
             spermicide, Copper T intrauterine device, Levonorgesterel-releasing intrauterine
             system) or hormonal methods (implants, hormone shot or injection, combined pill,
             minipill, patch), Nonsterilized males who are sexually active with a female partner of
             childbearing potential must use a highly effective method of contraception (as
             outlined above) from Day 1 through 90 days after receipt of the final dose of MEDI4736
             and tremelimumab. In addition, they must refrain from sperm donation for 90 days after
             the final dose of investigational product.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Concurrent enrollment in another clinical study, unless in a follow-up period or the
             study is an observational or non-interventional study

          -  Prior treatment with anti-CTLA4, anti-PD-1, or anti-PD-L1 (approved or investigational
             agent)

          -  Concurrent treatment with any anticancer agent, including chemotherapy, immunotherapy,
             or biologic therapy. In breast cancer patients, concurrent use of hormonal therapy
             (but not trastuzumab) is acceptable provided hormonal therapy was initiated more than
             30 days prior to treatment on this study.

          -  Treatment with any other investigational agent within 3 weeks prior to the first dose
             of DURVALUMAB (MEDI4736) and tremelimumab

          -  Any unresolved toxicity NCI CTCAE Grade ≥2 from previous anticancer therapy with the
             exception of alopecia, vitiligo, and the laboratory values defined in the inclusion
             criteria

               -  Patients with Grade ≥2 neuropathy will be evaluated on a case-by-case basis after
                  consultation with the Study Physician.

               -  Patients with irreversible toxicity not reasonably expected to be exacerbated by
                  treatment with durvalumab may be included only after consultation with the Study
                  Physician

          -  Major surgical procedure (as defined by the investigator) within 28 days prior to the
             first dose of DURVALUMAB (MEDI4736) and tremelimumab or still recovering from prior
             surgery Note: Local surgery of isolated lesions for palliative intent is acceptable

          -  Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 14 days before the first
             dose of DURVALUMAB (MEDI4736) and tremelimumab with the exceptions of intranasal and
             inhaled corticosteroids, systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses not to exceed
             10 mg/day of prednisone or equivalent, or steroids used transiently to control
             contrast agent allergies for radiographic studies.

          -  History of allogenic organ transplantation.

          -  Active or prior documented autoimmune or inflammatory disorders (including
             inflammatory bowel disease [e.g., colitis or Crohn's disease], diverticulitis [with
             the exception of diverticulosis], systemic lupus erythematosus, Sarcoidosis syndrome,
             or Wegener syndrome [granulomatosis with polyangiitis, Graves' disease, rheumatoid
             arthritis, hypophysitis, uveitis, etc]). The following are exceptions to this
             criterion:

               -  Patients with vitiligo or alopecia

               -  Patients with hypothyroidism (e.g., following Hashimoto syndrome) stable on
                  hormone replacement

               -  Any chronic skin condition that does not require systemic therapy

               -  Patients without active disease in the last 5 years may be included but only
                  after consultation with the study physician

               -  Patients with celiac disease controlled by diet alone.

          -  History of sensitivity or allergy to monoclonal antibodies or immunoglobulin GActive
             infection including tuberculosis (clinical evaluation that includes clinical history,
             physical examination and radiographic findings, and TB testing in line with local
             practice), hepatitis B (known positive HBV surface antigen (HBsAg) result), hepatitis
             C, or human immunodeficiency virus (positive HIV 1/2 antibodies). Patients with a past
             or resolved HBV infection (defined as the presence of hepatitis B core antibody
             [anti-HBc] and absence of HBsAg) are eligible. Patients positive for hepatitis C (HCV)
             antibody are eligible only if polymerase chain reaction is negative for HCV RNA

          -  Receipt of a live, attenuated vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of
             DURVALUMAB (MEDI4736) and tremelimumab Note: Patients, if enrolled, should not receive
             live vaccine whilst receiving IP and up to 30 days after the last dose of IP.

          -  Clinical contraindication to stereotactic body radiotherapy as determined by the
             investigator (e.g., active systemic sclerosis, active inflammatory bowel disease if
             bowel is within radiation field.)

          -  Prior radiotherapy that precludes the proposed treatment with hypofractionated
             radiotherapy

          -  Females who are pregnant, lactating, or intend to become pregnant during the
             participation of the study

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness, including but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, interstitial lung disease, serious chronic
             gastrointestinal conditions associated with diarrhea, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirement, substantially increase
             risk of incurring AEs or compromise the ability of the patient to give written
             informed consent

          -  Other active invasive malignancy. History of non-invasive malignancies such as
             cervical carcinoma in situ, non-melanomatous carcinoma of the skin, or ductal
             carcinoma in situ of the breast is allowed, as is history of other invasive malignancy
             that is in remission after treatment with curative intent.

          -  Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with
             evaluation of the investigational product or interpretation of subject safety or study
             results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark H. O'Hara, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark H. O'Hara, MD</last_name>
    <phone>855-216-0098</phone>
    <email>PennCancerTrials@emergingmed.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark H O'Hara, MD</last_name>
      <phone>855-216-0098</phone>
      <email>PennCancerTrials@emergingmed.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tremelimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

