<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02637011</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01GY1340</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02637011</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Surviving ARDS: The Influence of Quality of Care and Individual Patient Characteristics on Quality of Life</brief_title>
  <acronym>DACAPO</acronym>
  <official_title>Influence of Quality of Care and Individual Patient Characteristics on Quality of Life/ Return to Work in Survivors of the Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS): Prospective, Observational, Multi-centre Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Regensburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Regensburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Regensburg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the DACAPO study (&quot;Surviving ARDS: the influence of quality of care and
      individual patient characteristics on quality of life&quot;) is to investigate the role of quality
      of care and individual patient characteristics on quality of life and return to work in
      survivors of ARDS (acute respiratory distress syndrome). It is hypothesized that higher
      quality of care is associated with better health-related quality of life and a higher rate of
      return to work among survivors.

      A prospective, observational, multi-centre patient cohort study is performed in Germany,
      using hospitals from the &quot;ARDS Network Germany&quot; as the main recruiting centres. It is
      envisaged to recruit 2400 patients into the DACAPO study and to analyze a study population of
      1500 survivors. They will be followed up until 12 months after discharge from hospital.
      Quality of care will be assessed as process quality, structural quality and volume at the
      institutional level. The main outcomes (health related quality of life and return to work)
      will be gathered by self-report questionnaires. Further data assessment includes general
      medical and ARDS-related characteristics of patients as well as sociodemographic and
      psycho-social parameters. Multilevel hierarchical modelling will be performed to analyse the
      effects of quality of care and individual patient characteristics on outcomes, taking the
      cluster structure of the data into account.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design Patients will be included in the study at the beginning of ICU stay in a participating
      hospital (t0) and survivors will be followed over a period of 12 months after discharge from
      ICU. If patients have been treated before in a referring hospital, a retrospective assessment
      of their health status during their stay in this hospital and during inter-hospital transport
      will be performed. Four follow-up measurements (at discharge from ICU as well as 3, 6 and 12
      months after discharge) will be performed on individual patient level.

      Sample &amp; Recruitment Hospitals of the &quot;ARDS Network Germany&quot; and other hospitals which
      provide care for patients with ARDS were invited to participate in the study.

      It is envisaged to screen 2600 patients for the presence of ARDS and to include 2400 patients
      as members of the source population. An in-hospital mortality rate of 30% is assumed;
      therefore, we expect to analyze a study population of 1500 patients at t1 (discharge from
      ICU). For each follow-up-assessment (t2-t4: 3 months, 6 months, 12 months after discharge),
      loss-to-follow-up rates due to death, withdrawal of consent or other reasons are estimated to
      be about 10%, resulting in slightly more than 1000 patients at 12-months-follow-up.

      Measurements The main predictor is quality of care provided in the ICUs of the participating
      hospitals. The following main indicators were chosen: qualification of physicians,
      implementation of routine daily multiprofessional ward rounds with documentation of daily
      therapy goals, number of ventilated patients per, and membership of the hospital in the &quot;ARDS
      Network Germany&quot;. All quality indicators will be assessed by questionnaire at the
      institutional level.

      Main outcome measures of the DACAPO study are HRQoL and return to work among survivors of
      ARDS (see study outcomes).

      Moderating variables are gender, socio-economic status, prevalent and incident
      psychopathological symptoms (PHQ-D, PTSS-14) and the availability of social support (F-SozU
      K-14).

      Additional variables comprise general medical ICU parameters (e.g. comorbidity, prognostic
      scores (SAPS (Simplified Acute Physiology Score) II, SAPS III ) and an organ dysfunction
      score (SOFA (Sequential Organ Failure Assessment score)) and parameters relating to ARDS
      (e.g. cause and severity) and its treatment (e.g. ventilation parameters, use of supportive
      care measures, critical events (hypoglycaemia, hypoxia)) as well as socio-demographic and
      psycho-social characteristics.

      Additionally, costs will be assessed as direct costs in terms of treatment costs at the ICU.

      Data Sources and Data Collection Patients's general medical characteristics and medical data
      relating to ARDS and its treatment will be assessed during ICU stay and gathered through
      electronic case report forms (eCRFs). Data on the direct costs of treating patients with ARDS
      in the ICU will be gathered from hospital records. A 12-months mortality follow-up will be
      performed. Local municipal population registries will be contacted to obtain data on
      mortality at the patient level.

      At baseline, caregivers will provide proxy report of patients' socio-demographic data, at
      follow-ups (discharge from ICU, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months), patients themselves will
      complete self-report questionnaires on socio-demographic and psycho-social characteristics as
      well as on the main outcome measures.

      Data on indicators of quality of care will be assessed through questionnaires administered to
      the directors of the hospitals/ICUs.

      Data Management The open source software OpenClinica, version 3.1, will be used for
      electronic data collection and data management. eCRFs will be used for data entry. A
      continuous assessment of data quality will be performed by exporting data sets to statistical
      packages to run further error and plausibility checks. Data from paper-pencil-questionnaires
      completed by patients will be entered into the database twice in order to ensure high data
      quality.

      Statistical Analysis A linear multilevel regression model will be fitted both for the
      physical and the mental component summary score of the SF-12. A non-parametric multilevel
      regression model will be used for the outcome &quot;return to work&quot;. The modelling procedure will
      be applied to each of the operationalizations of the predictor &quot;quality of care&quot;.

      All analyses will be carried out using SAS 9.4 software and STATA version 12 software.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life, measured by the Short-Form 12-item Health-Survey (SF-12)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months, 6 months, 12 months after discharge from the ICU</time_frame>
    <description>change from baseline (discharge from the ICU) to 3 months, 6 months and 12 months, respectively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>return to work</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months, 6 months, 12 months after discharge from the ICU</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment by questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS)</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study participants will be selected of patients with ARDS treated at intensive care units
        of the participating hospitals. Participating hospitals are members of the ARDS Network
        Germany or other hospitals which agreed to take part in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ARDS according to the criteria of the Berlin-Definition:

             i) Acute onset within one week, ii) bilateral pulmonary infiltrates (chest imaging),
             iii) respiratory failure not fully explained by cardiac failure or fluid overload.

          -  informed consent provided by the patient or the legal guardian

          -  18 years old or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  no ARDS

          -  no informed consent provided by the patient or the legal guardian

          -  younger than 18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Bein, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Regensburg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Thomas Bein, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>++49-941-944-0</phone>
    <email>thomas.bein@ukr.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christian Apfelbacher, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>++49-941-944-0</phone>
    <email>christian.apfelbacher@ukr.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin Charite</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steffen Weber-Carstens, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>++49-30-450651055</phone>
      <email>steffen.weber-carstens@charite.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anton Goldmann, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>++49-30-4500</phone>
      <email>anton.goldmann@charite.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin Göttingen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Göttingen</city>
        <zip>37075</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lars-Olav Harnisch, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49551/39-13328</phone>
      <email>lars-olav.harnisch@med.uni-goettingen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michael Quintel, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49551/39-13328</phone>
      <email>mquintel@med.uni-goettingen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinik für Intensivmedizin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefan Kluge, Prof.Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>49-(0)40-7410-57010</phone>
      <email>s.kluge@uke.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dacapo-ards.de</url>
    <description>Website of the study</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 15, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 22, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 19, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 19, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 22, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Regensburg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Dr. Thomas Bein M.A.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute respiratory distress syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>intensive care medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>critical illness</keyword>
  <keyword>long-term outcomes</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>return to work</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

