<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02683811</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASLCN2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02683811</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of the Updated Version of the School-based Program Diario Della Salute (DDS-2)</brief_title>
  <acronym>DDS-2</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomised Controlled Study for Evaluating the Effectiveness of the Updated Version of Diario Della Salute, a School-based Program for Prevention of Unhealthy and Risky Behaviours and Promotion of Well-being in Italian Pre-adolescents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Sanitaria Locale CN2 Alba-Bra</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eclectica Sas di Beccaria Franca, Ermacora Antonella e C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Turin, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Eastern Piedmont</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Sanitaria Locale CN2 Alba-Bra</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the short- and long-term effects on psychological wellbeing and
      health-related behaviours of the updated version of a universal school-based program called
      Diario della Salute (DDS-2) in Italian students aged 11-13 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The updated version of Diario della Salute (DDS-2) is a universal school-based intervention
      aimed at promoting psychological and emotional well-being and preventing unhealthy and risky
      behaviours (cigarettes smoking, alcohol abuse, unhealthy eating habits, physical inactivity)
      in preadolescence. The program is composed by 5 highly standardized interactive units
      delivered by previously trained teachers during school hours on emotional and social issues
      related to developmental tasks in adolescence. The kit includes: 1) a teacher's manual, 2) a
      booklet for each participating student, 3) a booklet for parents of each participating
      student. The objective is to promote and reinforce adolescents' emotional and social skills
      as factors contributing to adolescent well-being and health.

      A randomised controlled trial with two parallel groups is performed, with 1:1 allocation
      ratio, in two different Regions of Italy (Piedmont and Veneto). Schools are randomly assigned
      to one of the two groups (DDS-2 intervention vs. no intervention) and are used as the unit of
      allocation. Individual participants (i.e. students) are the unit of analysis. Schools are
      matched by number of students and average socioeconomic status. Eligible schools are
      identified from the list of all schools having students from 11 to 13 located in study sites.
      A number of eligible schools accounting for the requested number of students in the target
      grades is invited to participate in the study. If a school does not respond to the invitation
      or declines to participate, the school recruitment process is repeated, and another eligible
      school is invited to participate. The process continues until achievement of the sample size.
      No incentive is offered to students, families and schools for participating in the study.

      A paper-and-pencil self-report anonymous questionnaire developed by the research group is
      used to determine whether the interventions have changed the outcomes. The questionnaire will
      be administered in classes by the researchers at baseline, at the end of the intervention and
      one-year after the end of the intervention (at equal intervals both in the intervention and
      in the control group). The questionnaire consists of the following sections: 1) demographics,
      2) emotional and social skills, 3) psychological wellbeing, 4) school experience, 5)
      unhealthy and risky behaviours, 6) prosocial and aggressive behaviours. Questionnaires are
      linked through an anonymous self-generated code.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological well-being (Brief Psychological Wellbeing Inventory)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>Four scales (3 items per scale) from Brief Psychological Wellbeing Inventory (PWB, Ryff &amp; Keyes, 1995 - Italian version by Cicognani, Zani, 1999) assessing different areas of perceived wellbeing such as autonomy, environmental mastery, positive relations with others, self-acceptance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychosomatic disorders (Health Behaviors in School-aged Children - Symptom checklist)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>8 items from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviors in School-aged Children - Symptom checklist (Haugland et al., 2001; Raves-Sieberer et al., 2009) assessing the frequency of perceived psychological and somatic disorders</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health status (Health Behaviors in School-aged Children Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>1 item from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviors in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing the general perceived health status.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Verbal and physical aggression (Verbal and Physical Aggression Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>20 items from Verbal and Physical Aggression Scale (Caprara &amp; Pastorelli, 1988) assessing the frequency of aggressive behaviors</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prosocial behaviours (Prosocial Behaviours Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>15 item from Prosocial Behaviours Scale (Caprara &amp; Pastorelli, 1988) assessing the frequency of prosocial behaviours</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>School success (Health Behavior Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>1 item from the Health Behavior Questionnaire (Jessor et al., 1992 - Italian version by Bonino et al., 2003) assessing the school performance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cigarette smoking (HBSC Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>3 items from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviours in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing cigarette smoking behavior</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of cigarette smoking (HBSC Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>1 item from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviours in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing the number of smoked cigarettes in the last month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol use (HBSC Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>3 items from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviours in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing the use of alcohol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drunkenness (HBSC Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>3 items from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviours in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing the frequency of drunkenness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating habits (HBSC Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>16 items from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviours in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing the frequency of use of healthy and unhealthy food</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating style (HBSC Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>2 items from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviours in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing the frequency of healthy and unhealthy eating habits per week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity (HBSC Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>4 items from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviours in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing the frequency of physical activity per week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical inactivity (HBSC Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>6 items from the Italian version of HBSC (Health Behaviours in School-aged Children) Questionnaire assessing the frequency of sedentary behaviours per day</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Emotional skills (Self- Efficacy Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>27 items from the Italian version of Self- Efficacy Scale (Bandura, 1997 - Italian version by Caprara et al., 2001) assessing the perceived individual emotional skills</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with school (School Situation Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>4 scales (5 items per scale) from the School Situation Questionnaire (Santinello &amp; Bertarelli, 2002) assessing the quality of relationship with schoolmates and teachers, self-esteem at school, attitude towards learning</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Social skills (Self- Efficacy Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after intervention completion</time_frame>
    <description>13 27 items from the Italian version of Self- Efficacy Scale (Bandura, 1997 - Italian version by Caprara et al., 2001) assessing the perceived individual social skills</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3600</enrollment>
  <condition>Adolescent Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Health Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Mental Health Wellness 1</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Diario della Salute (DDS-2), a school-based program aimed to promote psychological well-being and to prevent cigarette smoking, alcohol abuse, unhealthy eating habits, physical inactivity in preadolescents aged 11-13 years. The program is composed by 5 highly standardised interactive units led by previously trained teachers during school hours (15 hours total). Units focus on emotional and social issues related to adolescent developmental tasks. The goal is to promote the adolescent emotional and social skills.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention aimed at preventing cigarette smoking, alcohol abuse, unhealthy eating habits, physical inactivity and promoting emotional and social well-being is administered at school by teachers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diario della Salute (DDS-2)</intervention_name>
    <description>The updated version of Diario della Salute program (DDS-2) includes: 1) teachers' manual, 2) a booklet for teens telling the story of four same-age students (e.g. experimenting with risky behaviours, conflicting feelings and thoughts, need for independence and control, etc.), 3) a booklet for parents telling the experience of a mum and a dad with teenage children (e.g. problems in the relationship with teenage children, family conflicts, parental control and supervision, family communication, etc.).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Percorsi di promozione del benessere tra i pre-adolescenti</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. public/government schools,

          2. at least two classes attended by students aged 11-13,

          3. not participating in other school-based programs with similar objectives targeted to
             the classes of interest,

          4. providing consensus to study participation. In participating schools, all classes of
             students aged between 11 and 13 years are eligible to be enrolled in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. private schools,

          2. less than two classes attended by students aged 11-13,

          3. involved in other school-based programs with similar objectives targeted to the
             classes of interest. In participating schools, students whose parents opt out from the
             study are excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>13 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura Marinaro</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ASL CN2</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASL AL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Casale Monferrato</city>
        <state>AL</state>
        <zip>15033</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Sanitaria Locale CN2 Alba-Bra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alba</city>
        <state>Cuneo</state>
        <zip>12051</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASL CN1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cuneo</city>
        <zip>12100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASL TO1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <zip>10128</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regione Veneto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Venezia</city>
        <zip>30123</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.diariodellasalute.it/</url>
    <description>project web site</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 27, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 27, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Sanitaria Locale CN2 Alba-Bra</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Laura Marinaro</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr Laura Marinaro</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adolescence</keyword>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>wellbeing</keyword>
  <keyword>evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>effectiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>school-based program</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>Study Protocol</doc_type>
      <doc_url>http://www.diariodellasalute.it</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>Study protocol (Italian version) can be requested by contacting the project manager (lmarinaro@aslcn2.it)</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>program materials and tools</doc_type>
      <doc_url>http://www.diariodellasalute.it</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>The Italian version of program materials and tools (teachers' manual, students' booklet and parents' booklet) can be freely accessed and downloaded from project web site.</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

