<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02687685</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Acta 313 05-09-2015</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02687685</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial of Immediate Skin to Skin Contact at Birth Early vs. Immediate (CPPITLH)</brief_title>
  <acronym>CPPITLH</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Clinical Trial of Immediate Skin to Skin Contact (SSC) at Birth, Early vs. Immediate, on the Duration of Exclusive Human Lactation in Full-term Newborns Treated at the Universidad de La Sabana Clinic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad de la Sabana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad de la Sabana</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      SUMMARY: Human lactation is a simple, cost-effective strategy contributing to infant and
      maternal mortality control. Skin to skin contact (SSC), is an immediate postpartum period
      strategy that has proven to benefit the initiation and continuation of human lactation and
      decreased hospitalization during the first week of life. This study aims to determine the
      effect of the initiation of SSC at birth (immediate vs. early) in healthy, full term newborns
      treated at Universidad de La Sabana Clinic, on the duration of exclusive human lactation.

      Research question: What is the effect of immediate SSC at birth (immediate vs. early) on the
      duration of exclusive human lactation in full-term newborns treated at the Universidad de La
      Sabana Clinic?

      Methodology: A random blind clinical trial was performed in which full-term healthy newborns
      that are attended at the Universidad de La Sabana Clinic are included. The blind participants
      will be those persons measuring the results and analysing the data. The sample size is
      calculated for a type I error of 5%, a two tailed type II error of 20%, therefore estimating
      percentage losses of 30%; 150 infants were included per group. Randomization will be
      performed using permuted, size 6 blocks. Descriptive analysis will be conducted using central
      tendency and dispersion measurements. A bivariate analysis will be performed to determine
      which variables are associated with exclusive human lactation at 6 months. For continuous
      variables, the Student t- test will be used for independent samples or the Wilcoxon rank sum
      test, in case the assumptions of normality for the t-tests are not fulfilled. The assumption
      of normality will be evaluated with the Shapiro Wilk and Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Categorical
      variables in contingency tables will be constructed, assessing independence between variables
      with the Chi-square test or Fisher's exact test when the assumption of the number of cases is
      not met by the cells in the contingency tables, times two. It will be calculated as a
      measurement of the effect of relative risk (RR) with confidence intervals; the adjusted
      measurements will be calculated using a multivaried regression Poisson model, variables with
      significant results will be used in the bivariate analysis and those with biological
      plausibility used for the adjustment. The analysis will be carried out for a two-tailed type
      I error level of 5%. The Stata 11 program will be used for the data analysis. An interim
      analysis will be performed upon submission of half of the expected events (106), setting
      limits for early termination of the trial according to the method proposed by Pampallona and
      Tsiatis (1994).

      Intervention: There will be 2 SSC randomization groups, early vs. immediate. After completing
      the neonatal adaptation process and according to the group assignment, it will proceed to
      leave the newborn with the mother in accommodation. Prior to discharge, the IBFAT scale will
      be applied. Monitoring will initially be performed with a face valuation between 3 and 10
      days of life, then monthly telephone calls for 6 months to verify the status of human
      lactation.

      Results: To determine whether early versus immediate SSC has an impact on the duration of
      exclusive human lactation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Exclusive human lactation</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Exclusive human lactation for 3 or more months. Exclusive human lactation is defined as: the time in months of human lactation as the only food source without having received other liquids or solid foods (except drugs and / or vitamins)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Human lactation capacity in the newborn</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 24 hours of life</time_frame>
    <description>Human lactation capacity in the newborn within the first 24 hours of life by IBFAT Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal satisfaction with breastfeeding</measure>
    <time_frame>First 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Maternal satisfaction with breastfeeding in the first 24 hours according to the IBFAT Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evolution of birth weight</measure>
    <time_frame>First week of life</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of birth weight in the first week of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The need for hospitalization in the neonatal care unit</measure>
    <time_frame>First week of life</time_frame>
    <description>The need for hospitalization in the neonatal care unit in the first week of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Feeding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Skin to skin contact immediate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>At birth, the baby will be placed and dried on the breast of his mother where thermoregulation manoeuvres will be applied and once the cord clamping procedure has taken place; the baby will be left in SSC with the mother where the immediate neonatal adaptation interventions will take place. Mother and baby will be left in SSC for at least one hour or until the baby has completed its first lactation properly. Once completed, the baby will be taken to the heat lamp to perform and complete all the newborn mediate adaptation interventions. If the mother expresses the desire to continue in SSC, it will be allowed again after these interventions. During immediate SSC, mother and baby receive continuous monitoring by the health staff</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>skin to skin contact early</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>At birth, the baby will be dried and placed on the abdomen and chest of his mother where thermoregulation manoeuvres are applied once there is an indication that the cord clamp procedure has been completed. At this time the baby will go to the radiant heat lamp in order to complete all newborn adaptation interventions. Once stable, the mother and the baby who has 60 minutes of life, will proceed with the initiation of SSC for at least one hour or until the baby has completed the first lactation adequately; SSC will be allowed to continue if the mother expresses a desire to do so. During SSC the mother and baby will receive monitoring by health personnel</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Skin to skin contact immediate</intervention_name>
    <description>Immediate SSC (intervention group) At birth, the baby will be dried and placed at the mother's breast where thermoregulation maneuvers will be applied and, once cord clamping has taken place, the baby will be left in SSC with the mother where the immediate neonatal adaptation interventions will take place. Mother and baby will be left in SSC for at least 1 h or until the baby has completed its first lactation properly. Once completed, the baby will be taken to the heat lamp to perform and complete all the newborn mediate adaptation interventions. If the mother expresses the desire to continue in SSC, this will be allowed again after these interventions. During immediate SSC, mother and baby will receive continuous monitoring by the health staff.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Skin to skin contact immediate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>skin to skin contact early</intervention_name>
    <description>Early SSC group (control group) At birth, the baby will be dried and placed on the abdomen and chest of their mother where thermoregulation maneuvers are applied once cord clamping has been completed. At this time, the baby will placed under the radiant heat lamp in order to complete all newborn adaptation interventions. Once stable, the mother and the baby will proceed with the initiation of SSC for at least 1 h or until the baby has completed the first lactation adequately; SSC will be allowed to continue if the mother expresses a desire to do so. During SSC, the mother and baby will receive monitoring by health personnel. All adaptation interventions, mediate and immediate, in the newborn will take place under the radiant heat lamp during the first postnatal hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>skin to skin contact early</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants of mothers who express before the birth, their desire to breastfeed their
             newborn baby.

          -  Infants born between 7:00 am and 5:00 pm Monday through Friday in the USC.

          -  Full-term newborns defined by obstetric method and confirmed by paediatric method
             (Ballard), between 37 and 42 weeks of gestation, with appropriate weight for
             gestational age (between 10th and 90th percentiles for gestational age).

          -  Vaginal birth.

          -  Do not require basic or advanced neonatal resuscitation manoeuvres.

          -  Healthy and stable cardiorespiratory at birth.

          -  Have been permitted to room with the mother.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Mothers and newborns that present absolute or relative contraindications for human
             lactation.

          -  Multiple births and pregnancies.

          -  Mothers with postpartum complications that limit the onset of human lactation.

          -  Major congenital malformations that prevent human lactation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Minutes</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Oscar Gamboa, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>573112018714</phone>
    <email>oagambaog@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sergio Agudelo, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5718615555</phone>
    <phone_ext>23307</phone_ext>
    <email>sergioap@clinicaunisabana.edu.co</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 16, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad de la Sabana</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Oscar Andrés Gamboa Garay</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>School of Medicine Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Skin to Skin Contact</keyword>
  <keyword>Infant, Newborn</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>the committee required each month informations about adverse events and informs of recruitment each six months</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

