<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02689726</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PC10VAC05</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>016462</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02689726</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of GTL001 Vaccine Adjuvanted With Imiquimod Cream in HPV 16- and/or HPV 18-Infected Women Aged 25 to 65 Years, With Normal Cytology, ASCUS, or LSIL</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of GTL001 Vaccine Adjuvanted With Imiquimod Cream in HPV 16- and/or HPV 18-Infected Women Aged 25 to 65 Years, With Normal Cytology, ASCUS, or LSIL</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genticel</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PPD</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Genticel</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Phase 1, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of
      GTL001 Vaccine Adjuvanted With Imiquimod Cream in HPV 16- and/or HPV 18-Infected Women Aged
      25 to 65 Years, With Normal Cytology, ASCUS, or LSIL.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an outpatient, open-label study. After a screening period of up to 4 weeks, all
      eligible subjects will receive 2 doses, 6 weeks apart, of GTL001 Powder reconstituted with
      water for injection. GTL001 will be adjuvanted with Aldara, 5% imiquimod cream, applied to
      the injection site 15 minutes and 24 hours after each vaccination. The follow-up period is 12
      weeks from the first injection. The duration of the study is defined for each subject as the
      date that signed, written informed consent is provided through the last follow-up visit.
      Total duration of subject participation is approximately 16 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of efficacy in European Phase 2 study
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of local and systemic reactions recorded on diary cards as a measure of safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>14-day period following an injection</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the tolerability, with respect to vaccine-specific local and systemic reactions, of GTL001 adjuvanted with imiquimod in women in 2 age cohorts: 25 to 50 years, inclusive, and 51 to 65 years, inclusive. The diary cards will include local abd systemic reactions to the adjuvant, medications taken with start and stop dates, and other unsolicited symptoms/complaints, including start and stop dates.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of anti-CyaA serum as a measure of cellular and humoral Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by enzyme-linked immunoabsorbent assay (ELISA) at weeks 0,2,6,8, and 12 (Visits 1,2,3,4, and 5, respectively) To assess the cellular and humoral immunogenicity of GTL001 adjuvanted with imiquimod in the 2 age cohorts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with anti-CyaA serum antibody response as a measure of cellular and humoral immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured at weeks 2,6,8, and 12 (Visits 2,3,4, and 5, respectively) To assess the cellular and humoral immunogenicity of GTL001 adjuvanted with imiquimod in the 2 age cohorts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific responses to HPV 16 and HPV 18 E7 Ag stimulation as a measure of cellular and humoral Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured at weeks 0,2,6,8, and 12 (Visits 1,2,3,4, and 5, respectively) To assess the cellular and humoral immunogenicity of GTL001 adjuvanted with imiquimod in the 2 age cohorts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with positive specific response to HPV 16 and/or HPV 18 E7 stimulation as a measure of cellular and humoral Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the cellular and humoral immunogenicity of GTL001 adjuvanted with imiquimod in the 2 age cohorts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>HPV 16- and/or HPV 18-Infected Women With Normal Cytology, ASCUS, or LSIL</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GTL001 + Aldara, 5% imiquimod cream</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 doses, 6 weeks apart, GTL001 will be adjuvanted with Aldara, 5% imiquimod cream, applied to the injection site 15 minutes and 24 hours after each vaccination</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GTL001+</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>GTL001 + Aldara, 5% imiquimod cream</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aldara</intervention_name>
    <description>5% imiquimod cream</description>
    <arm_group_label>GTL001 + Aldara, 5% imiquimod cream</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Females between the ages of 25 and 65 years, inclusive, at the time of screening.

          2. Subject is in generally good health based on medical history and on clinically
             acceptable results, in the judgment of the investigator, on the following assessments:
             physical examination, vital signs, clinical chemistry, and hematology.

          3. Cervical HPV 16 and/or 18 infection confirmed by cobas® HPV Test (Roche Molecular
             Systems, Inc) real-time polymerase chain reaction (RT PCR) assay at screening.

          4. Cervical cytological evaluation with a normal, ASCUS, or LSIL result.

          5. Subjects of childbearing potential must use effective contraception at the time of
             GTL001 injection and for at least 12 months after the first vaccination. Effective
             methods of birth control include those that result in a low failure rate (ie, less
             than 1% per year) when used consistently and correctly, such as implants, injectable,
             combined oral contraceptives, desogestrel only pill, levonorgestrel-releasing
             intrauterine system, intrauterine devices, vasectomized partner, and true sexual
             abstinence. Subjects not of childbearing potential include those who are surgically
             sterile or postmenopausal (no menses for the previous 12 months).

          6. Subject is capable of understanding the written informed consent, provides signed and
             witnessed written informed consent, and agrees to comply with protocol requirements.

          7. In the opinion of the investigator, the subject is able to comply with the protocol
             and has a high probability of completing the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current or history of untreated high-grade cervical lesion (either CIN2 or CIN3).

          2. Current or history of cervical, vulvar, or vaginal cancer.

          3. Prior exposure to HPV prophylactic vaccine, regardless of number of doses received, or
             participation in another HPV vaccination clinical trial.

          4. Current acute or chronic disease, other than HPV 16/18 infection, which would be
             expected to interfere with the protocol-defined evaluations.

          5. Clinically significant gynecological abnormalities that could interfere with study
             procedures (eg, prolapse, severe vaginal atrophy, myoma, hysterectomy) in the judgment
             of the investigator.

          6. Malignancy, or treatment for malignancy, within the previous 2 years, with the
             exception of basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin.

          7. Clinically important abnormalities in the physical examination or laboratory tests
             during the screening period (ie, hemoglobin level &lt;9.5 g/dL, white blood cells &lt;2500
             cells/mm3, aspartate aminotransferase and/or alanine aminotransferase ≥1.5 × the upper
             limit of normal [ULN], creatinine ≥1.25 × ULN, alkaline phosphatase ≥2 × ULN, and
             total bilirubin &gt;ULN).

          8. Administration of any live viral vaccine within 3 months or any inactivated (nonlive)
             vaccine within 2 weeks prior to screening.

          9. Primary or secondary systemic immunosuppression (defined as prolonged [≥7 days] use of
             corticosteroids that is ≥20 mg/day of prednisone equivalent or any other
             immunosuppressive drug).

         10. History of severe allergy requiring hospital care or history of severe asthma
             requiring oral or parenteral drug management in the last year.

         11. Known hypersensitivity to imiquimod.

         12. History of a severe reaction to any drug or vaccination.

         13. Medical condition with clinical and/or biological consequences judged by the
             investigator to be incompatible with ID vaccination.

         14. History of, or positive test results at screening for, human immunodeficiency virus,
             hepatitis B virus surface Ag, or hepatitis C virus.

         15. Current episode of symptomatic vaginal or genital infection.

         16. Current episode or history of genital herpes.

         17. Subject is pregnant or lactating/breastfeeding.

         18. Use of any investigational drug within 30 days before screening or current
             participation in another clinical trial.

         19. History of recent (within 1 year) alcohol/drug abuse.

         20. Employee or family member of the investigator or study site personnel.

         21. Enrollment goals have been reached in the subject's age cohort
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Louisville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Research Associates, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Raleigh</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Research Advantage, Inc./ Columbus Obstetricians and Gynecology, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Planned Parenthood Southeastern Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 24, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Imiquimod</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

