<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02689375</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PM13/10904</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02689375</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective, Open Label, Pilot Study of Patient OutcoMes Following Successful TriAl of High Frequency SpInal CorD Stimulation at 10kHz (HF10™) Leading to Permanent Implant Compared to Trial Failure and Standard CarE for the TreatmeNt of Persistent Low BACK Pain of Neuropathic Origin</brief_title>
  <acronym>Maiden Back</acronym>
  <official_title>Rospective, Open Label, Pilot Study of Patient OutcoMes Following Successful TriAl of High Frequency SpInal CorD Stimulation at 10kHz (HF10™) Leading to Permanent Implant Compared to Trial Failure and Standard CarE for the TreatmeNt of Persistent Low BACK Pain of Neuropathic Origin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      25 participants with back pain and no previous spinal surgery will be enrolled from a single
      NHS site in England.

      Participants will have already discussed spinal cord stimulation (SCS) pain management with
      their consultant before being invited to participate. Participants will attend for 10 visits
      over a period of 66 months. At visit one, study suitability screening and informed consent
      will be conducted. Suitable participants will be booked to have SCS trial leads implanted and
      an external programmable High Frequency battery trial box as a day case (Visit 2).
      Participants will be contacted over the next 21 days to assess how the trial is progressing
      and to book a follow up appointment in clinic to remove the trial leads (Visit 3) where a
      treatment decision will be made. If a participant is determined as having had a successful
      trial they will be listed and implanted with a full HF10 SCS implant (Visit 4). The
      participants who proceed to a full HF10 SCS implant will be reviewed in the Clinic at 6, 12,
      24, 36, 48 and 60 months post procedure. Their participation in this study will be no longer
      than 66 months. A successful trial is defined as a reduction in pain by 30% on a Visual
      Analogue Scale. Participants who do not obtain 30% reduction in 21 days is classed as a
      failed trial and once the leads are removed will be reviewed in clinic by the investigator
      for an alternative treatment plan (Visit 4). If a participant is determined a failed trial of
      HF10, they will remain in the study with their consent for the full follow up schedule. The
      follow-up for the failed trial cohort can be conducted via telephone to reduce the burden on
      this trial group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>50% reduction in patient reported Visual analogue scale for pain</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months compared to baseline</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>50% reduction in patient reported numerical rating score for pain</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months compared to baseline</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Palliative Care</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients to receive spinal cord stimulator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Senza Spinal Cord Stimulation system</intervention_name>
    <description>Suitable participants will be booked to have spinal cord stimulator trial leads implanted and an external programmable High Frequency battery trial box as a day case</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients to receive spinal cord stimulator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        I. Patient is 18 years of age or older and has given written informed consent. II. Has
        persistent chronic predominant low back pain of neuropathic origin, with or with out
        radiculopathy, for a minimum of 6 months III. Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) back pain score
        of at least 50 mm at baseline IV. Confirmation of pain from neuropathic origin by SLANSS
        score (≥12) AND PainDETECT score( ≥19) V. Total daily dose of opioids equivalent to ≤200mg
        of Morphine VI. No previous open spinal surgery (percutaneous procedures such as
        nucleoplasty are not considered as open surgical procedures) VII. Failed conservative
        therapies such as physiotherapy, chiropractor, hydrotherapy, TENS.

        VIII. MRI within the previous 18 months (as per standard care) IX. In the investigators
        opinion the patient is a suitable candidate for HF10

        Exclusion Criteria:

        I. Patient has mechanical spine instability based on flexion/extension testing of lumbar
        spine (documented in the last 6 months) II. Patient is pregnant, or pregnancy is suspected
        or planned within the first six months of the study timeframe.

        III. Patient has a cardiac pacemaker, automatic defibrillator, or any other implanted
        device, which will make the trial impossible. IV. Allergy to device components or drugs to
        be used in the intended procedure. V. Medical co-morbidities that preclude surgical
        intervention. VI. Patient is incapable of understanding or responding to the study
        questionnaires VII. Patient is incapable of understanding or operating the patient
        programmer handset.

        VIII. History of previous open spinal surgery (not percutaneous procedures) IX. Patient is
        morbidly obese (BMI ≥ 40). X. Patient is simultaneously participating in another device or
        drug study within the last 30 days.

        XI. Patient has a spinal fracture, tumour or infection. XII. Clinical evidence of cauda
        equina syndrome. XIII. Progressive neurologic deficit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>G Baranidharan, MBBS</last_name>
    <email>g.baranidharan@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>R&amp;I Administrator</last_name>
    <phone>0113 392 0152</phone>
    <email>leedsth-tr.lthtresearch@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <state>West Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>LS9 7TF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>R&amp;I Administrator</last_name>
      <phone>0113 392 0152</phone>
      <email>leedsth-tr.lthtresearch@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>G Baranidharan, MBBS, ATLS, FRCA, FCARCSI</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

