<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02684786</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-000928</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02684786</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Stellate Ganglion Block and / or Reserpine in Group 2 Pulmonary Hypertension</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Stellate Ganglion Block and / or Reserpine in Group 2 Pulmonary Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pulmonary hypertension Group 2 (PH 2) associated with left-sided heart disease is relatively
      common, is associated with a poor prognosis, and unfortunately there are no proven medical
      treatments beyond attempts at correcting the left sided heart disease. Many PH 2 patients
      have evidence of active constriction of blood vessels from increased nerve traffic. Use of
      agents or procedures which produce a reversible chemical blockage of this nerve traffic have
      not been systematically tested in PH 2. The investigators will test whether acute
      interruption of sympathetic nervous system tone, which local anesthetic block of the stellate
      ganglion in the neck, will improve PH2, and also test whether the high blood pressure drug
      reserpine, which blocks sympathetic nerve activity, will do so during a one month trial
      period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background. Pulmonary hypertension Group 2 (PH 2) associated with left-sided heart disease is
      relatively common, is associated with a poor prognosis, and unfortunately there are no proven
      medical treatments beyond attempts at correcting the left sided heart disease. Many PH 2
      patients have evidence of vasoconstriction and increased sympathetic nervous system activity.
      Use of agents or procedures which produce a reversible chemical sympathectomy have not been
      systematically tested in PH 2.

      Methods. Two groups will be eligible for participation: Group 1 (n=10): Patients with PH 2
      previously documented by echocardiography (echo), 6 minute walk test, biomarkers, and right
      heart catheterization (RHC) will receive reserpine, 0.05 mg per day for two weeks, then, 0.1
      mg per day for an additional two weeks. After one month, patients will be reassessed for New
      York Heart Association (NYHA) class and drug side effects, echocardiography, 6 minute walk
      assessment, and brain natriuretic peptide (BNP). Group 2 patients (n=10) will have clinically
      suspected PH 2 and be scheduled to undergo clinically indicated RHC. If during RHC PH 2 is
      confirmed, after assessment of nitric oxide responsiveness, their baseline hemodynamics will
      be re-established over 10 minutes, and a left stellate ganglion block with lidocaine will be
      performed, and immediate hemodynamic responsiveness assessed. Four hours post-procedure, a
      side effect questionnaire will be obtained. Group 2 patients who complete RHC will then begin
      reserpine treatment in the same manner as Group I patients.

      Hypothesis and Impact. PH 2 is the most common type of pulmonary hypertension. The current
      diagnostic and therapeutic strategy aims to treat the left sided heart disease in attempt to
      normalize pulmonary artery pressure. The place of selective pulmonary vasodilators is
      undefined. The investigator's approach addresses inhibition of adverse pulmonary
      vasoconstriction mediated by the sympathetic nervous system in PH 2.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events of interest are for stellate ganglion block: pulmonary edema, bradycardia requiring treatment, hypotension requiring treatment, arrhythmia, pneumothorax, hoarseness, dysphagia, globus, left upper extremity weakness. For reserpine, heart failure hospitalization, syncope, all cause hospitalization, bradycardia requiring treatment, hypotension requiring treatment, new arrhythmia, edema requiring an increase in diuretics, depression, lethargy, nasal stuffiness, dizziness, orthostatic hypotension, falls, nightmares, sexual dysfunction, anxiety, dyspepsia.
Adverse events classed as serious:
Life threatening serious adverse events including acute coronary syndrome with active ischemia, fatal arrhythmias, myocardial infarction, acute kidney injury, cardiogenic shock, stroke, pulmonary embolization, arterial and/or venous thrombosis, systemic embolization, severe hypotension, respiratory failure and death
Prolonged hospitalization or rehospitalization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with successful stellate ganglion block</measure>
    <time_frame>One hour</time_frame>
    <description>Stellate block: frequency of the occurrence of ptosis and conjunctival flushing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of stellate ganglion block on heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>One hour</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate before and after stellate ganglion block</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 6 minute walk distance from one month of reserpine therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>One month</time_frame>
    <description>Six minute walk distance, meters, baseline compared to one month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in brain natriuretic peptide (BNP) from one month of reserpine therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>One month</time_frame>
    <description>BNP, pg/ml, baseline compared to one month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Doppler derived mean pulmonary artery pressure from one month of reserpine therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>One month</time_frame>
    <description>Mean pulmonary artery pressure estimate, mm Hg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in blood pressure from one month of reserpine therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>One month</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure, mm Hg, baseline versus one month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Minnesota Living with heart failure questionnaire from one month of reserpine therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>One month</time_frame>
    <description>Minnesota Living with heart failure questionnaire aggregate score, baseline versus one month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic effect of stellate ganglion block</measure>
    <time_frame>One hour</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure, mm Hg, before and after stellate ganglion block</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic effect of stellate ganglion block</measure>
    <time_frame>One hour</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary artery pressure, mm Hg, before and after stellate ganglion block</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic effect of stellate ganglion block</measure>
    <time_frame>One hour</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary capillary wedge pressure, mm Hg, before and after stellate ganglion block</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic effect of stellate ganglion block</measure>
    <time_frame>One hour</time_frame>
    <description>right atrial pressure, mm Hg, before and after stellate ganglion block</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic effect of stellate ganglion block</measure>
    <time_frame>One hour</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiac output, liters per minute, before and after stellate ganglion block</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in heart rate from one month of reserpine therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>One month</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate, baseline versus one month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Artery Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prior right heart catheterization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with qualifying hemodynamics from prior right heart catheterization will receive open label reserpine, 0.05 mg by mouth daily for two weeks, then 0.10 mg by mouth daily for two weeks, and then have repeat non-invasive assessments of status.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Scheduled for right heart catheterization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with suspected group 2 pulmonary hypertension by clinical and non-invasive assessments and are scheduled to undergo clinically indicated right heart catheterization will have pulmonary artery pressures measured. If qualifying severity of group 2 pulmonary hypertension is present, after clinically indicated assessment of inhaled nitric oxide, their baseline hemodynamics will be allowed to re-equilibrate over 10 minutes, and then ultrasound guided left stellate ganglion block with lidocaine will be performed, and hemodynamics reassessed 10 minutes afterward</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>reserpine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with qualifying hemodynamics from prior right heart catheterization will receive open label reserpine, 0.05 mg by mouth daily for two weeks, then 0.10 mg by mouth daily for two weeks, and then have repeat non-invasive assessments of status</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prior right heart catheterization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stellate ganglion block</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with suspected group 2 pulmonary hypertension by clinical and non-invasive assessments and are scheduled to undergo clinically indicated right heart catheterization will have pulmonary artery pressures measured. If qualifying severity of group 2 pulmonary hypertension is present, after clinically indicated assessment of inhaled nitric oxide, their baseline hemodynamics will be allowed to re-equilibrate over 10 minutes, and then ultrasound guided left stellate ganglion block with lidocaine will be performed, and hemodynamics reassessed 10 minutes afterward</description>
    <arm_group_label>Scheduled for right heart catheterization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lidocaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with suspected group 2 pulmonary hypertension by clinical and non-invasive assessments and are scheduled to undergo clinically indicated right heart catheterization will have pulmonary artery pressures measured. If qualifying severity of group 2 pulmonary hypertension is present, after clinically indicated assessment of inhaled nitric oxide, their baseline hemodynamics will be allowed to re-equilibrate over 10 minutes, and then ultrasound guided left stellate ganglion block with lidocaine will be performed, and hemodynamics reassessed 10 minutes afterward</description>
    <arm_group_label>Scheduled for right heart catheterization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Prior right heart catheterization, with mean pulmonary artery pressure &gt; 25 mm Hg,
             pulmonary capillary wedge pressure &gt; 15 mm Hg, and diastolic pressure gradient
             (pulmonary artery diastolic pressure - mean pulmonary capillary wedge pressure) ≥ 7 mm
             Hg OR clinically suspected group 2 pulmonary hypertension from non-invasive testing
             with planned right heart catheterization (RHC).

          -  On stable diuretic therapy

          -  Able to attend end-study visit 4 weeks after study entry

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Anticipated surgery to correct heart lesion responsible for pulmonary hypertension

          -  Need for heparinization for right heart catheterization (not standard practice, but
             sometimes utilized)

          -  History of depression, or treatment with tricyclic anti-depressant, serotonin uptake
             inhibitor, monamine oxidase inhibitor

          -  Severe renal or hepatic impairment, creatinine clearance &lt; 30 ml/minute or renal
             replacement therapy or post-kidney transplant, abnormal liver function with elevated
             enzymes&gt; 1.5 times the upper limit of normal or prior liver transplant.

          -  Systolic blood pressure &lt;100 mm Hg

          -  Heart rate &lt; 60 beats per minute

          -  Inability to independently complete telephone follow-up at two weeks, and clinic
             end-study visit at 4 weeks.

          -  Pulmonary edema

          -  Infiltrative cardiomyopathy - amyloidosis

          -  Symptomatic orthostatic hypotension

          -  Women of childbearing age who have not had surgical sterilization and are not using
             oral contraceptives, or who's spouse has not had surgical sterilization will be
             excluded due to the length of the trial and the possibility that they could become
             pregnant after entry.

          -  Uncontrolled heartburn

          -  Prior surgery to the left neck, for example, carotid endarterectomy, or other surgery
             which would increase the risk of stellate ganglion block

          -  Known sensitivity, allergy, or contraindication to lidocaine, any local anesthetic, or
             reserpine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Blackshear, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joseph Blackshear, MD</last_name>
    <phone>904-953-2000</phone>
    <phone_ext>7279</phone_ext>
    <email>blackshear.joseph@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Charles Burger, MD</last_name>
    <phone>904-953-2000</phone>
    <phone_ext>2282</phone_ext>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joseph L. Blackshear</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Consultant, Department of Cardiovascular Diseases</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Reserpine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nitric Oxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

