<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02683213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EFFECTS2012</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-006130-16</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02683213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Fluoxetine - a Trial in Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>EFFECTS</acronym>
  <official_title>Establishing the Effect(s) and Safety of Fluoxetine Initiated in the Acute Phase of Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Swedish Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swedish Heart Lung Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stroke-Riksförbundet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Konung Gustaf V:s och Drottning Victorias Frimurarestiftelse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hjärnfonden (The Swedish Brain foundation)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Svenska Läkaresällskapet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karolinska Institutet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate whether routine administration of fluoxetine 20mg
      once daily in the 6 months initiated during the acute stroke improves the patient's
      functional outcome.

      EFFECTS is an investigator lead Sweden-based, multicenter, parallel group, double blind
      placebo controlled trial with broad entry criteria and follow up at 6 and 12 months.

      The anticipated numbers of participants is 1,500 in Sweden. As of 31 August 2017, EFFECTS has
      recruited 810 participants at 35 centers. Last patient in is anticipated July 2019, with the
      last follow-up one year later.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stroke is a serious, life-threatening medical condition that happens when the blood supply to
      a part of the brain is cut off, usually due to a blood clot (ischemic) or hemorrhage.
      Symptoms vary according to how much of the brain is affected and where in the brain the
      stroke occurs but includes paralysis, muscle weakness and speech problems.

      A stroke can also have an impact on the sufferers emotions and can lead to anxiety,
      depression and personality changes. Fluoxetine (otherwise known as Prozac) has been used for
      many years to treat depression. However, there is evidence to suggest that it may also have
      other effects of the brain and enhance brain plasticity (the reorganisation of neural
      pathways in the brain) in a number of different ways.

      One small study, for example, has shown that, if taken soon after a stroke, fluoxetine might
      improve the recovery of arm strength and lead to greater restoration of movement of the
      limbs.

      Adult participants (at least 18 years old) who have had a stroke (either ischemic or
      hemorrhagic) within the last 2-15 days and still have some residual problems caused by the
      stroke e.g. weakness, or problems with their speech (speech impairment).

      Participants are randomly allocated into one of two groups. Those in group 1 are given
      fluoxetine capsules for 6 months. Those in group 2 are given a placebo capsules for 6 months.

      The participants are contacted after one week of starting their treatment, and then again
      after one month, to check on their well-being and that they are still taking their allocated
      caplets. Each participant is asked about any side effects and how much training they have had
      with e.g. a physiotherapist, occupational- or speech-therapist.

      The research team contacts each participant at 3 months to check whether they are still
      taking the capsules, ask about bad side effects, and about how they are feeling (mood). If
      all is well, the participant is given enough medication to cover the rest of the study
      period.

      The participant is asked to stop the study medication after 6 months and repeat assessments
      that they did before they started the study at the local hospital. They are also asked to
      fill in questionnaires together with their next of kin or carer. These questionnaires are
      sent to the trial main centre. If needed, they can also be filled in with the help of a trial
      nurse over the telephone.

      The participants are contacted again one month after they have stopped the medication to see
      how they have progressed.

      At 12 months after recruitment, participants are asked to complete the same questionnaires
      again about how well they have recovered from their stroke and what problems they now have
      after the stroke e.g. weakness in limbs, memory problems, problems with speech, low mood.
      These questionnaires can again be completed on paper or by telephone. The researchers then
      collect data on long-term recovery through national statistics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 20, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status, measured with the modified Rankin scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The simple modified Rankin scale questionnaire delivered by postal questionnaire, or via interview over the telephone or face to face to determine the modified Rankin scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be determined by following patients up for 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Survival will be analysed with the Cox proportional hazards model adjusting for the factors included in the minimisation algorithm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status, measured with the modified Rankin scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The simple modified Rankin scale questionnaire delivered by postal questionnaire, or via interview over the telephone or face to face to determine the modified Rankin scale. The study will also investigate if the benefits of Fluoxetine remains at 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health status measured with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Health status will be measured with the Stroke Impact Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm, hand, leg and foot strength assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.
The 8 domains in the Stroke Impact Scale will be used for secondary outcome measures 5 to 13.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hand function assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mobility assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Communication and understanding assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory and thinking assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mood and emotions assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily activities assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participation in work, leisure and social activities assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall rating of recovery assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Stroke Impact Scale will provide an overall assessment of patient outcome as well as allowing us to assess the effect of treatment on specific outcomes of importance to the patients. The Stroke Impact Scale was developed with input from both patients and caregivers and includes 8 domains (strength, hand function, ADL/IADL, mobility, communication, emotion, memory and thinking, participation) from across the full impairment-participation continuum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events/outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will specifically ask for adverse events at each follow-up time (1 week, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months), see the outcome 16-24 below. The definition of the SAE is defined according to Good Clinical Practice. We will not register known side effects of fluoxetine, which are listed in the drug's Summary of Product Characteristics. We will not register known problems following stroke, such as pneumonia, deep vein thrombosis etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression using the Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Depression using the Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) and patients scoring high have a diagnosis of depression confirmed based on the DSM-IV criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a recurrent stroke including ischaemic and hemorrhagic strokes</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with a recurrent stroke including ischaemic and hemorrhagic strokes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with an acute coronary syndromes</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with an acute coronary syndromes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with an Epileptic seizures</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with an epileptic seizures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with an episodes of Hyponatraemia</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with an episodes of hyponatraemia (&lt;125 mmol/l)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with an upper gastrointestinal bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with an upper gastrointestinal bleeding</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with other major bleeds</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with an other major bleeds includes lower GI, extracranial, intracranial but extracerebral</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with poorly controlled diabetes</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with an poorly controlled diabetes including hyperglycaemia (&gt;22 mmol/l) and hypoglycaemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with falls resulting in injury</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with falls resulting in injury</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with new fractures</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with new fractures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue measured with the vitality subscale of the Health Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue will be measured with the vitality subscale of the Health Questionnaire, equivalent to SF 36.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognition assessed with the Stroke Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cognition—the Stroke Impact Scale, which incorporates an assessment of memory and thinking, is used in conjunction with with the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life measured with the five-level Euroqol 5D (EQ5D-5 L)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Health-related quality of life measured with the five-level Euroqol 5D (EQ5D-5 L).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness and cost-utility assessed by measuring costs, survival and health related quality of life (EQ5D)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Direct and indirect costs will be estimated at 3-month, 6- month and 1 year. Effects will be measured using survival and EuroQoL 5 Dimensions (EQ5D) scale, which will be estimated into a utility score. The effectiveness measure that will be used for comparison purposes, the quality adjusted life years (QALYs), will be estimated by multiplying the relevant time parameter of the comparison with the estimated utility scores.
A societal perspective will be adapted for the analysis, and comparison of costs and effects (QALYs) will be conducted for the period of the clinical trial, as well as by adopting a lifetime perspective, where costs and QALYs will be extrapolated beyond the duration of the trial over the expected lifetime of patients. Standard statistical regressions will be used in order to calculate the expected lifetime costs and QALYs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fluoxetine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One capsule Fluoxetine 20mg once daily for 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One matching capsule placebo once daily for 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluoxetine</intervention_name>
    <description>Fluoxetine 20mg once daily for 6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fluoxetine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed consent can only be obtained from a patient who according to the trial
             investigator is mentally capable of decision-making and who, after having received
             information and got answers to their questions, wants to participate in the trial.

          -  Brain imaging is compatible with intra cerebral hemorrhage or ischemic stroke.

          -  Randomization can be performed between 2 and 15 days after stroke onset and by the
             research group at the patient's local/emergency hospital.

          -  Persisting focal neurological deficit is present at the time of randomization severe
             enough to warrant treatment from the physicians and the patient's and relative's
             perspective.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subarachnoidal hemorrhage except where secondary to a primary intracerebral
             hemorrhage.

          -  Unlikely to be available for follow up for the next 12 months e.g. no fixed home
             address.

          -  Unable to speak Swedish and no close family member available to help with follow up
             forms.

          -  Other life threatening illness (e.g. advanced cancer) that will make 12-month survival
             unlikely.

          -  History of epileptic seizures.

          -  History of allergy or contraindications to fluoxetine including: Hepatic impairment
             (S-ASAT/ALAT &gt; 3 upper normal limit) and renal impairment (S-Creatinine levels &gt; 180
             micromol/L).

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding, women of childbearing age not taking contraception. Minimum
             contraception is an oral contraceptive. An HCG-test is to be made prior randomization
             and after the end of trial medication.

          -  Previous drug overdose or attempted suicide.

          -  Already enrolled into a CTIMP.

          -  Current or recent (within the last month) depression requiring treatment with an SSRI
             antidepressant.

        Current use of medications which have serious interactions with fluoxetine Use of any
        mono-amino-oxidase inhibitor (MAOI) during the last 5 weeks. Co-administration of
        Fluoxetine and a mono-amino-oxidase inhibitor (MAOI) may result in life threatening
        interactions. Therefore, patients on MAOI are ineligible for the EFFECTS trial. Also, any
        patient in need of treatment with a MAOI must stop their trial treatment for at least 5
        weeks before commencing the MAOI, or to be treated as in-patients by a psychiatrist.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Erik Lundström, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Erik Lundström, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+46 707 677 411</phone>
    <email>erik.lundstrom@ki.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eva Isaksson, RN</last_name>
    <phone>+46 70 340 48 92</phone>
    <email>eva.isaksson@ds.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska Institutet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>171 76</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eva Isaksson, RN</last_name>
      <phone>+46 70 340 48 92</phone>
      <email>eva.isaksson@ds.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nina Greilert, RN</last_name>
      <phone>+46 70-566 02 43</phone>
      <email>nina.greilert@ds.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.effects.se</url>
    <description>The EFFECTS study home page, for investigators, layman and participants in the study. Currently only available in Swedish.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mead G, Hackett ML, Lundström E, Murray V, Hankey GJ, Dennis M. The FOCUS, AFFINITY and EFFECTS trials studying the effect(s) of fluoxetine in patients with a recent stroke: a study protocol for three multicentre randomised controlled trials. Trials. 2015 Aug 20;16:369. doi: 10.1186/s13063-015-0864-1.</citation>
    <PMID>26289352</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mead GE, Hsieh CF, Lee R, Kutlubaev MA, Claxton A, Hankey GJ, Hackett ML. Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) for stroke recovery. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Nov 14;11:CD009286. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD009286.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23152272</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 16, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Erik Lundström, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD, Senior Consultant in Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fluoxetine</keyword>
  <keyword>outcome</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>plasticity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluoxetine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Three trial investigator teams have collaboratively developed a core protocol for Fluoxetine after stroke. Minor variations have been tailored to the national setting in the UK (FOCUS), Australia and New Zealand (AFFINITY) and Sweden (EFFECTS). Each trial is run and funded independently and will report its own results. A prospectively planned individual patient data meta-analysis of all three trials will subsequently provide the most precise estimate of the overall effect of fluoxetine after stroke and establish whether any effects differ between trials and subgroups of patients.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

