<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02684097</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 15-1497</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02684097</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study of Tralokinumab in Subjects With Moderate to Severe Alopecia Areata</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Placebo-controlled Single Center Pilot Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Tralokinumab in Subjects With Moderate to Severe Alopecia Areata</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emma.Guttman</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess whether tralokinumab can be a helpful treatment for
      alopecia areata. This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled pilot study of a
      total of 30 subjects with moderate to severe alopecia areata involving 30-100% of the scalp.
      Expected is 50% of these subjects to have concomitant alopecia areata (AA) and atopic
      dermatitis (AD). Subjects with AA alone (15 subjects) will be randomized (2:1) to either
      receive tralokinumab or placebo via subcutaneous injection every 2 weeks for 24 weeks.
      Subjects with concomitant alopecia areata and atopic dermatitis (15 subjects) will be
      randomized separately in a 2:1 ratio to receive tralokinumab or placebo via subcutaneous
      injection every 2 weeks for 24 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess whether tralokinumab can be a helpful treatment for
      alopecia areata.

      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled pilot study of a total of 30 subjects
      with moderate to severe alopecia areata involving 30-100% of the scalp. The researchers
      expect 50% of these subjects to have concomitant alopecia areata (AA) and atopic dermatitis
      (AD).

      The researchers' experience in AD12-14, and past experience in psoriasis15, 16 showed that
      biomarker studies in skin tissues are critical to the understanding of key pathogenic
      pathways that are upregulated in each disease and how well they are suppressed with effective
      treatment. These mechanistic studies coupled with clinical trials are key in the disease to
      shed light on important disease mechanisms, and to explain which molecules are suppressed by
      each therapeutic target. Data shows that IL-13 is significantly upregulated in both AD and AA
      lesions compared to nonlesional skin. It is very important to associate the clinical
      responses with suppression of this cytokine and related molecules as well as other pathway
      cytokines in skin tissues. Both the whole genomic profiling and individual molecular and
      cellular markers are very important in order to understand how well anti-IL-13 will
      change/suppress AA-associated pathways and compare with those that will be suppressed in AD.

      Since this study is designed to gain basic knowledge rather than to yield information
      directly related to patient care, the results are not entered in the participants' medical
      records. If, at a later date, correlations of in-vitro tests and the patients' clinical
      situation suggest that the results do bear on the patients' health, an amended protocol will
      be submitted to the IRB so that results can be made available to the medical record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gene expression changes in Th2/IL-13, &quot;T22&quot;/IL-22, S100A7 and S100A8, Th1/IFN-gamma, and Th17/IL-17A jointly correlated</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in cellular, and molecular markers in skin biopsies after treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Alopecia Tool (SALT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change from Baseline in the Severity of Alopecia Tool (SALT) at Week 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SALT score (SALT50)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients achieving 50% or greater improvement in their SALT score (SALT50) at Week 24, compared to Baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alopecia Areata Symptom Impact Scale (AASIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change from baseline in the Alopecia Areata Symptom Impact Scale (AASIS) at Week 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alopecia Areata Quality of Life questionnaire (AA-QoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change from Baseline in the Alopecia Areata Quality of Life questionnaire (AA-QoL) at Week 24</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 40</time_frame>
    <description>To study the safety of tralokinumab in patients with moderate to severe alopecia areata and in patients with concomitant moderate to severe alopecia areata and atopic dermatitis</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Alopecia Areata</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tralokinumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tralokinumab subcutaneous injection every two weeks for 24 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Saline subcutaneous injection every two weeks for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tralokinumab</intervention_name>
    <description>All groups will receive study drug every two weeks for 24 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tralokinumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo given every two weeks for 24 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Saline subcutaneous injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, aged from 18 to 75 years, inclusively at the time of signing the
             informed consent document.

          -  Subject has provided written informed consent prior to any study specific procedures.

          -  Body weight of ≥40 and &lt;150 kg at enrollment.

          -  Subject has a history of alopecia areata for at least 3 months.

          -  Subject has extensive patchy alopecia areata (at least 30% scalp hair loss).

          -  No evidence of hair regrowth at Baseline.

          -  For WOCBP only: have a negative urine pregnancy test prior to administration of the
             IP.

          -  For inclusion in the voluntary pharmacogenetic research, subjects should fulfill the
             following criterion: Provision of a signed and dated written informed consent for the
             pharmacogenetic sample and analysis. If a subject declines to participate in the
             pharmacogenetic research, there will be no consequence or loss of benefit to the
             subject. The subject will not be excluded from the other aspects of the study
             described in the protocol, as long as they consent to participate in the study.

          -  Subject is judged to be in good general health as determined by the principal
             investigator based upon the results of medical history, laboratory profile, and
             physical examination performed at Screening.

          -  Subjects may be naïve to treatment or unresponsive to intralesional steroids or other
             treatments for alopecia areata.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of male or female pattern hair loss Ludwig stage III or Hamilton &gt; stage V.

          -  Subjects in whom the diagnosis of alopecia areata is in question.

          -  Any disorder, including but not limited to, cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, hepatic,
             renal, neurological, musculoskeletal, infectious, endocrine, metabolic,
             haematological, psychiatric, or major physical impairment that is not stable in the
             opinion of the Investigator and could:

               1. Affect the safety of the subject throughout the study

               2. Influence the findings of the studies or their interpretations

               3. Impede the subject's ability to complete the entire duration of study

          -  Known history of allergy or reaction to any component of the IP formulation.

          -  History of anaphylaxis following any biologic therapy.

          -  The following treatments within 4 weeks before the Baseline visit, or any condition
             that, in the opinion of the investigator, will likely require such treatment(s) at any
             time during the study:

               1. Systemic corticosteroids

               2. Immunosuppressive/immunomodulating drugs (eg, cyclosporine,
                  mycophenolate-mofetil, IFN-γ, Janus kinase (JAK) inhibitors, azathioprine or
                  methotrexate), Ultra-Violet (UV) B phototherapy; and/or Psoralen Ultra-Violet A
                  (PUVA) therapy.

          -  Treatment with topical corticosteroids, tacrolimus and/or pimecrolimus within 1 week
             before the Baseline visit.

          -  Subject has taken enzyme-modifying drugs that are moderate inhibitors/potent inducers
             of cytochrome P450 3A4 or potent inhibitors of cytochrome P450 2C19 enzymes (such as
             cimetidine, quinidine, erythromycin, ciprofloxacin, fluconazole, ketoconazole etc…)
             and strong inducers of CYP enzymes (such as rifampin etc…), in the previous 28 days
             before day 0.

          -  A helminth parasitic infection diagnosed within 6 months prior to the date informed
             consent or assent obtained that has not been treated with, or has failed to respond
             to, standard of care therapy.

          -  History of clinically significant infection, including acute upper or lower
             respiratory infections, requiring antibiotics or antiviral medication within 30 days
             prior to the date informed consent or assent is obtained or during the run-in period.

          -  Tuberculosis requiring treatment within the 12 months prior to enrolment (Visit 1).

          -  Any clinically significant abnormal findings in physical examination, vital signs,
             ECG, hematology, clinical chemistry, or urinalysis during the run-in period, which in
             the opinion of the Investigator, may put the subject at risk because of his/her
             participation in the study, or may influence the results of the study, or the
             subject's ability to complete entire duration of the study.

          -  History of chronic alcohol or drug abuse within 12 months of the enrolment visit, or a
             condition associated with poor compliance as judged by the Investigator.

          -  Positive hepatitis B surface antigen or hepatitis C virus antibody serology. Subjects
             with a history of hepatitis B vaccination without a history of hepatitis B are allowed
             to be enrolled.

          -  History of any known primary immunodeficiency disorder including a positive human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) test at enrolment, or the subject taking antiretroviral
             medications as determined by medical history and/or subject's verbal report.

          -  Current tobacco smoking (smoking must have stopped for ≥ 3 months prior to enrollment)
             or a history of tobacco smoking for ≥ 10 pack-years (one pack year = 20 cigarettes
             smoked per day for 1 year).

          -  History of cancer: - Subjects who have had basal cell carcinoma, localized squamous
             cell carcinoma of the skin or in situ carcinoma of the cervix are eligible provided
             that the subject is in remission and curative therapy was completed at least 12 months
             prior to the date informed consent was obtained Subjects who have had other
             malignancies are eligible provided that the subject is in remission and curative
             therapy was completed at least 5 years prior to the date informed consent was obtained

          -  Use of immunosuppressive medication (including but not limited to: methotrexate,
             troleandomycin, cyclosporine, azathioprine, systemic corticosteroids including regular
             treatment with OCS or intramuscular long-acting depot corticosteroids, or any
             experimental anti-inflammatory therapy) within 3 months prior to the date informed
             consent or assent is obtained.

          -  Clinically significant asthma exacerbation, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             including those requiring use of oral corticosteroids 30 days prior to the date of
             informed consent or during the screening/run-in period.

          -  Receipt of immunoglobulin or blood products within 30 days prior to the date informed
             consent or assent is obtained.

          -  Receipt of any marketed or investigational biologic agent within 4 months or 5
             half-lives prior to the enrolment visit, whichever is longer.

          -  Receipt of live attenuated vaccines 30 days prior to the date of randomization and
             during the study including the follow-up period Receipt of inactive/killed
             vaccinations (eg, inactive influenza) are allowed, provided they are not administered
             within 5 days before/after any study visit.

          -  Receipt of any investigational non-biologic agent within 30 days or 5 half lives prior
             to informed consent or assent being obtained, whichever is longer.

          -  Previous receipt of tralokinumab (CAT-354).

          -  Initiation of new allergen immunotherapy or change in existing immunotherapy is not
             allowed within 30 days prior to the date of informed consent. However allergen
             immunotherapy initiated prior to this period may be continued provided there is a span
             of at least 5 days between the immunotherapy and IP administration.

          -  Current use of oral or ophthalmic non-selective β-adrenergic antagonist (eg,
             propranolol).

          -  Current use of five- lipoxygenase inhibitors (eg, Zileuton) or roflumilast.

          -  Major surgery within 8 weeks prior to the enrolment visit, or planned in-subject
             surgery or hospitalization during the study period.

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) level ≥2.5 times
             the upper limit of normal (ULN) at enrolment

          -  Pregnant, currently breast-feeding, or lactating women.

          -  Previous randomization in the present study.

          -  Concurrent enrollment in another clinical study where the subject is receiving an IP.

          -  Involvement in the planning and/or conduct of the study (applies to both AstraZeneca
             staff and/or staff at the study site).

          -  Employees of the clinical study site or any other individuals directly involved with
             the planning or conduct of the study, or immediate family members of such individuals.

          -  Individuals who are legally institutionalized.

        For exclusion from the voluntary pharmacogenetic research:

          -  Previous allogeneic bone marrow transplant.

          -  Non-leukocyte depleted whole blood transfusion within 120 days of genetic sample
             collection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emma Guttman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ISMMS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emma Guttman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-241-3288</phone>
    <email>emma.guttman@mountsinai.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Giselle Singer, BS</last_name>
    <phone>212-241-3288</phone>
    <email>giselle.singer@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emma Guttman, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-3288</phone>
      <email>emma.guttman@mountsinai.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>John Nia, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-3288</phone>
      <email>John.Nia@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emma Guttman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alkhalifah A. Alopecia areata update. Dermatol Clin. 2013 Jan;31(1):93-108. doi: 10.1016/j.det.2012.08.010. Epub 2012 Oct 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23159179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Safavi KH, Muller SA, Suman VJ, Moshell AN, Melton LJ 3rd. Incidence of alopecia areata in Olmsted County, Minnesota, 1975 through 1989. Mayo Clin Proc. 1995 Jul;70(7):628-33.</citation>
    <PMID>7791384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang KP, Mullangi S, Guo Y, Qureshi AA. Autoimmune, atopic, and mental health comorbid conditions associated with alopecia areata in the United States. JAMA Dermatol. 2013 Jul;149(7):789-94. doi: 10.1001/jamadermatol.2013.3049. Erratum in: JAMA Dermatol. 2014 Jun;150(6):674.</citation>
    <PMID>23700152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Betz RC, Pforr J, Flaquer A, Redler S, Hanneken S, Eigelshoven S, Kortüm AK, Tüting T, Lambert J, De Weert J, Hillmer AM, Schmael C, Wienker TF, Kruse R, Lutz G, Blaumeiser B, Nöthen MM. Loss-of-function mutations in the filaggrin gene and alopecia areata: strong risk factor for a severe course of disease in patients comorbid for atopic disease. J Invest Dermatol. 2007 Nov;127(11):2539-43. Epub 2007 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>17581619</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olsen EA, Hordinsky MK, Price VH, Roberts JL, Shapiro J, Canfield D, Duvic M, King LE Jr, McMichael AJ, Randall VA, Turner ML, Sperling L, Whiting DA, Norris D; National Alopecia Areata Foundation. Alopecia areata investigational assessment guidelines--Part II. National Alopecia Areata Foundation. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2004 Sep;51(3):440-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15337988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Emma.Guttman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alopecia, Alopecia Totalis, Alopecia Universalis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alopecia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alopecia Areata</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

