<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00198250</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0308-07</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NINR/NIH R01 NR05261</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00198250</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Venlafaxine for Hot Flashes After Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Venlafaxine for Hot Flashes After Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate Venlafaxine as a treatment option for hot flashes in
      breast cancer survivors. The goals of this study are to assess the effectiveness and toxicity
      of venlafaxine hydrochloride and identify the psychological, behavioral, and physical
      outcomes associated with relief of hot flashes in women following treatment for breast
      cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hot flashes are the most severe and fourth most prevalent menopausal symptom reported by
      women with breast cancer. Hot flashes affect over 65% of this population, with 59% rating the
      symptom as severe and 44% reporting they are extremely distressed by the symptom. Despite the
      high prevalence, severity and distress associated with this symptom, the scientific basis for
      managing hot flashes in women with breast cancer is limited. This randomized, double-blind,
      placebo-controlled crossover trial examines the effectiveness and toxicity of sustained
      release venlafaxine hydrochloride (37.5 mg po qd) on hot flashes in women following treatment
      for breast cancer. Venlafaxine is a phenylethylamine derivative that potently inhibits the
      reuptake of neuronal serotonin and norepinephrine and weakly inhibits the reuptake of
      dopamine. A secondary aim of this project is to examine the impact of hot flashes on
      psychological, behavioral, and physical outcomes. This study is based on the Wickham Symptom
      Management Model which depicts interrelationships between symptoms, symptom management
      strategies, and symptom management outcomes. Participants (n = 80) who are at least one month
      post-completion of surgery, radiation, and/or chemotherapy and who have been on tamoxifen (if
      prescribed) for at least six weeks will complete a two-week baseline hot flash assessment and
      be randomized to one arm of the crossover trial. At the end of the first six-week arm,
      participants will crossover to the opposite study arm for an additional six weeks. Outcomes
      to be assessed include effectiveness of the intervention (hot flash frequency, severity,
      distress and magnitude), toxicity of the intervention (subjective preference, side effects),
      psychological outcomes (mood disturbance), behavioral outcomes (quality of life, interference
      with daily activities) and physical outcomes (fatigue and sleep disturbance). Hot flashes
      will be measured daily, using a subjective, prospective diary methodology, and weekly, using
      objective state-of-the art 24-hour physiological monitoring of sternal skin conductance.
      Other outcomes will be measured weekly. Compliance with the intervention/placebo will be
      assessed weekly using medication blister pack cards. Timing of outcome assessments is based
      on limitations of the physiological monitoring device and expected timing of treatment
      effects. Summary statistics (i.e., mean, slope, maximum response, range, proportion,
      achievable difference) will be used to effectively reduce the design to a 2 X 2 crossover and
      data will be analyzed accordingly (i.e., t-tests, linear regression, GEE, mixed model). Study
      findings will significantly contribute to the scientific basis of hot flash management in
      women following treatment for breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the effectiveness venlafaxine hydrochloride versus placebo in alleviating hot flash frequency, severity, distress, and magnitude in women following treatment for breast cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>completed</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify the psychological, behavioral, and physical outcomes associated with relief of hot flashes in women following treatment for breast cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>completed</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>venlafaxine</intervention_name>
    <description>Venlafaxine taper dose from 37.5mg for one week to 75 mg for 3 weeks</description>
    <other_name>Effexor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women at least 21 years of age

          -  willing and able to provide informed consent

          -  first time diagnosis of breast cancer

          -  no other history of cancer

          -  considered disease free at time of study enrollment

          -  at least four weeks post-completion of surgery, radiation, and/or chemotherapy for
             non-metastatic cancer

          -  experiencing daily hot flashes

          -  desirous of treatment for hot flashes, but not concurrently using any other hot flash
             treatments

          -  living within 60 miles of Indianapolis

          -  able to read, write and speak English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  current treatment with antidepressants for depression, neuropathic pain or hot flashes

          -  diagnosis of metastatic breast cancer (stage IV)

          -  treatment for hot flashes within the past four weeks, including (a) soy supplements;
             (b) botanicals, such as dong quai (Angelica sinensis), black cohosh, ginseng, gotu
             kola, licorice root, chaste tree, sage, or wild yam root; (c) vitamin E; or (d)
             prescription medications, such as clonidine hydrochloride or megestrol acetate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janet S Carpenter, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carpenter JS, Storniolo AM, Johns S, Monahan PO, Azzouz F, Elam JL, Johnson CS, Shelton RC. Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled crossover trials of venlafaxine for hot flashes after breast cancer. Oncologist. 2007 Jan;12(1):124-35.</citation>
    <PMID>17227907</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 15, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 15, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 14, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Janet S. Carpenter</name_title>
    <organization>Indiana University</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast cancer survivorship</keyword>
  <keyword>hot flashes</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hot Flashes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Venlafaxine Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

