<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03466177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S60932</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03466177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multimodal Retinal Imaging in the Detection and Follow-up of Alzheimer's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>RetAD</acronym>
  <official_title>Multimodal Retinal Imaging in the Detection and Follow-up of Alzheimer's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitaire Ziekenhuizen Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitaire Ziekenhuizen Leuven</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Because of a shared ontogenic origin, the retina displays similarities to the brain and
      spinal cord in terms of anatomy, functionality, response to insult, and immunology. Hence,
      the retina can be approached as an integral part of the central nervous system. The occurence
      of ocular manifestations in several neurodegenerative pathologies, such as Alzheimer's
      disease and Parkinson's disease, accentuates the strong relationship between eye and brain.
      Particularly retinal changes can present a substrate for cerebral changes in these disorders.
      Offering a 'window to the brain', the transparent eye enables non-invasive imaging of these
      changes in retinal structure and vasculature. In this project, the potential of retinal
      biomarkers for e.g. Alzheimer's will be explored with the aim to overcome some of the hurdles
      in the current management of these pathologies, mainly the lack of techniques for patient
      screening and early diagnosis. The aim of this clinical trial is to correlate the retinal
      biomarkers for Alzheimer's with neuro-imaging, and cognitive function. Integrating the
      results will yield non-invasive retinal biomarkers for clinical research, screening, and
      follow-up of disease progression in various neurodegenerative disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Alzheimer's disease (AD) is the most common neurodegenerative disorder and the leading cause
      of dementia worldwide. A growing number of people are surviving into their 80s-90s and the
      number of AD patients projected to nearly triple in the next three decades, affecting 80-90
      million people worldwide by 2040. As such, AD will become the third cause of death for older
      people, just behind cardiovascular disease and cancer. In contrast to the latter, AD cannot
      be prevented, slowed or cured. AD represents an enormous socio-economic burden and has become
      a trillion dollar disease. Despite decades of intensive research, diagnosis and treatment
      remain challenging for AD. A string of recent failures in clinical trials for AD drugs has
      pointed out that our understanding of the disease is still far from complete. More in detail,
      three major reasons underlying this treatment gap have been identified:

      i. The lack of techniques for patient screening and early diagnosis. ii. The incomplete
      understanding of the complex interplay of pathological processes that underlie AD.

      iii. The many hurdles between drug discovery and approval.

      With this study, the investigators propose a novel way to address these needs, by using the
      retina as a model organ to study the central nervous system (CNS). Many of the hallmark
      cerebral pathophysiological processes of AD have also been observed in the retina. Unlike the
      rest of the CNS, the retina can be visualized directly, with an imaging resolution up to 100x
      higher than PET and MRI scans. Using these high-resolution imaging tools such as Optical
      Coherence Tomography (OCT), studies have demonstrated microvascular changes and neuro-retinal
      thinning in AD patients. Pilot data show that retinal Aβ can be visualized non-invasively
      solely based on the intrinsic hyperspectral signature of aggregated amyloid deposits.
      Non-invasive retinal imaging (e.g., fundus photography, OCT, hyperspectral imaging (HSI)) -
      which are all available at affordable cost -, could therefore represent novel means for
      identifying patients at risk, for longitudinal follow-up of disease progression in AD
      patients, and for research in a quest for more effective treatments.

      This is an open-label longitudinal biomarker study without investigational medicinal product
      in subjects in different stages of the AD spectrum.

      The data that we will collect consist of amyloid imaging, MRI, blood, genetic, general health
      and cognitive data, as well as visual acuity, ocular biomicroscopy and funduscopy, fundus
      photographs, hyperspectral retinal images, Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT) retinal images
      and OCT angiography (OCT-A) retinal images. Subjects will be followed longitudinally. In the
      current study the investigators will primarily investigate the potential of non-invasive,
      multimodal retinal imaging for the early detection of Alzheimer's disease and for the
      evaluation of disease progression. This will be done in comparison with amyloid imaging and
      neuropsychological evaluations.

      The investigators will build a longitudinal database of ocular, systemic, neuro-psychiatric,
      MRI and PET imaging parameters of Aβ-positive and Aβ-negative patients with different stages
      of cognitive impairment. This database will be used to provide proof-of-concept that retinal
      biomarkers provide an early, accurate and non-invasive tool for AD detection and follow-up.
      All data will be collected in a database for statistical analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>2 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal biomarkers for AD: specificity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the diagnostic performance of selected ocular biomarkers for Alzheimer's disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal biomarkers for AD: sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the diagnostic performance of selected ocular biomarkers for Alzheimer's disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal biomarkers for AD: number needed to image</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the diagnostic performance of selected ocular biomarkers for Alzheimer's disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal biomarkers for AD: area under the curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the diagnostic performance of selected ocular biomarkers for Alzheimer's disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal biomarkers for AD: receiver operating characteristic (ROC)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the diagnostic performance of selected ocular biomarkers for Alzheimer's disease</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal biomarkers for AD: quantification of cerebral Aβ load by non-invasive retinal imaging against the cerebral Aβ load measured by cerebral imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To deliver a proof-of-concept for the use of retinal biomarkers to quantitatively measure cerebral Aβ load by comparing the results of cerebral imaging (Standard Uptake Value ratio (SUVr) on amyloid-PET) with the results of retinal hyperspectral imaging (area of retinal Aβ detected, in µm²)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retinal biomarkers for AD: disease progression by measuring the change from baseline at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To deliver a proof-of-concept for the use of retinal biomarkers to follow Alzheimer's disease progression by measuring the change from baseline at 2 years and to compare the results of the cerebral imaging and neuropsychiatric tests with the results from the selected retinal biomarkers for AD at different time points (t0, t 6 months, t 12 months, t 18 months, t 24 months)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimer Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ AD patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>amyloid positive Alzheimer's Disease patients
Venous blood sampling Hematology and chemistry
Genotyping: apolipoprotein E (apoE) polymorphism Cerebral imaging
Brain MRI MPRAGE volumetric MRI, en FLAIR and Gradient Echo sequence
18F-Flutemetamol PET CT
Neuropsychiatric testing Auditory Verbal Learning Test (AVLT) Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of Neuropsychological Status (RBANS) Raven's Progressive Matrices (RPM) Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD)
Ocular examination Visual acuity, biomicroscopy, funduscopy Fundus pictures, including hyperspectral imaging OCT + angio-OCT (Non-invasive, multimodal retinal imaging)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>amyloid positive Mild Cognitive Impairment patients
Venous blood sampling Hematology and chemistry
Genotyping: apoE polymorphism Cerebral imaging
Brain MRI MPRAGE volumetric MRI, en FLAIR and Gradient Echo sequence
18F-Flutemetamol PET CT
Neuropsychiatric testing Auditory Verbal Learning Test (AVLT) Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of Neuropsychological Status (RBANS) Raven's Progressive Matrices (RPM) Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD)
Ocular examination Visual acuity, biomicroscopy, funduscopy Fundus pictures, including hyperspectral imaging OCT + angio-OCT (Non-invasive, multimodal retinal imaging)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <description>amyloid positive cognitively intact volunteers
Venous blood sampling Hematology and chemistry
Genotyping: apoE polymorphism Cerebral imaging
Brain MRI MPRAGE volumetric MRI, en FLAIR and Gradient Echo sequence
18F-Flutemetamol PET CT
Neuropsychiatric testing Auditory Verbal Learning Test (AVLT) Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of Neuropsychological Status (RBANS) Raven's Progressive Matrices (RPM) Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD)
Ocular examination Visual acuity, biomicroscopy, funduscopy Fundus pictures, including hyperspectral imaging OCT + angio-OCT (Non-invasive, multimodal retinal imaging)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ab- cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <description>amyloid negative cognitively intact volunteers
Venous blood sampling Hematology and chemistry
Genotyping: apoE polymorphism Cerebral imaging
Brain MRI MPRAGE volumetric MRI, en FLAIR and Gradient Echo sequence
18F-Flutemetamol PET CT
Neuropsychiatric testing Auditory Verbal Learning Test (AVLT) Repeatable Battery for the Assessment of Neuropsychological Status (RBANS) Raven's Progressive Matrices (RPM) Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD)
Ocular examination Visual acuity, biomicroscopy, funduscopy Fundus pictures, including hyperspectral imaging OCT + angio-OCT (Non-invasive, multimodal retinal imaging)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-invasive, multimodal retinal imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Ocular exam including the application of different non-invasive ocular imaging techniques</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ AD patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab- cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cerebral imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>amyloid-PET and MRI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ AD patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab- cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neuropsychiatric testing</intervention_name>
    <description>neuropsychiatric test battery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ AD patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab- cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Venous blood sampling</intervention_name>
    <description>fasting laboratory tests and apoE genotyping</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ AD patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab+ cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ab- cognitively intact volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Venous blood samples for genotyping of the apoE polymorphism
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cfr. eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between ≥ 50 and ≤ 85 years of age.

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, the patient is in stable medical condition and
             willing and able to perform study procedures.

          -  Patient is fluent in written and verbal Dutch.

          -  Patient is capable of giving informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has a history or current evidence of a neurological disorder, which, in the
             opinion of the primary investigator, may contribute to the subject's cognitive
             impairment.

          -  Patient has a history of large-vessel stroke or evidence of a large-vessel infarction
             or other focal lesions on baseline MRI scan, which may contribute to the cause of the
             memory impairment in the opinion of the investigator. Vascular white matter lesions or
             other signs of microangiopathy will not be considered an exclusion.

          -  Patient has a history of malignancy ≤ 5 years prior to signing informed consent,
             except for patients who have undergone potentially curative therapy with no evidence
             of recurrence for 1 year, and who are deemed at low risk for recurrency by her/his
             treating physician.

          -  Patient is currently participating or has participated in a study with an
             investigational compound within 30 days of signing informed consent.

          -  Subject has any magnetizable metal prostheses, implants or foreign objects that could
             pose a hazard during MRI scans.

          -  Patient has a known history of ocular diseases other than the exception of cataract
             and/or wearing glasses/contact lenses.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ingeborg Stalmans, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UZ Leuven/KU Leuven</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sophie Lemmens, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+3216332387</phone>
    <email>sophie.1.lemmens@uzleuven.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <state>Vlaams Brabant</state>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ingeborg Stalmans, Phd</last_name>
      <phone>003216332372</phone>
      <email>ingborg.stalmans@uzleuven.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sien Boons, Optometrist</last_name>
      <phone>003216340391</phone>
      <email>sien.boons@uzleuven.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Mild cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Optical coherence tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperspectral imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Multimodal retinal imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

