<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03463772</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IVM/IVF-PCOS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03463772</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IVM Versus Standard IVF in Infertile Patients Diagnosed With PCOS</brief_title>
  <official_title>In Vitro Maturation Versus Standard in Vitro Fertilization in Infertile Patients Diagnosed With Polycystic Ovaries Syndrome: a Study Protocol for a Single-center Prospective, Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jie Qiao</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University Third Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A single center, prospective, open-label, non-inferiority randomized controlled clinical
      trials (1:1 treatment ratio) regarding pregnancy outcomes between IVM and standard IVF among
      infertility couples with PCOS in China.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A single center, randomized controlled clinical trial will enroll 820 couples with PCOS
      undergoing their first cycle of IVF. The participation in this study will be approximately 2
      years with a total of 7 visits from the cycle beginning, pregnancy to delivery. On day 2 or
      day 3 following the onset of menstrual bleeding, eligible patients will be allocated to two
      groups at a ratio of 1:1- IVM protocol, and standard IVF protocol. All participants will be
      randomized through stratified block randomization according to the study sites.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Eligible patients that have provided informed consent will be randomized to either IVM or standard IVF. Randomization and allocation of patients to study groups will be performed on the day 2 or 3 of the menstrual cycle. Randomization will be centrally controlled by administrative staff in the trial center, who are not involved in the treatment procedure. When there is an eligible participant to be enrolled into the study, nurses from the specific site will log in the trial center to get allocation of patients according to a computer-generated randomization list in a 1:1 ratio, with a variable block size of 2, 4 or 8 and stratified by center.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the proportion of ongoing pregnancy leading to live birth</measure>
    <time_frame>after 22 weeks of gestation</time_frame>
    <description>number of ongoing pregnancy leading to live birth resulting from the first oocyte retrieval cycle after the randomization ( 6 month) divided by the number of patients with oocyte retrieval</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>implantation</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days after embryo transfer</time_frame>
    <description>Number of gestational sacs observed per embryo transferred</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 weeks after embryo transfer</time_frame>
    <description>one or more observed gestational sac or definitive clinical signs of pregnancy under ultrasonography at 7 weeks after embryo transfer (including clinical documented ectopic pregnancy)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Miscarriage</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks of gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Spontaneous loss of an intra-uterine pregnancy prior to 28 completed weeks of gestational age</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preterm birth</measure>
    <time_frame>28-37 weeks of pregnancy</time_frame>
    <description>Birth of a fetus delieved after 28 and before 37 completed weeks of gestational age in participants confirmed ongoing pregnancy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Birth weight</measure>
    <time_frame>within 2 weeks after live birth</time_frame>
    <description>Including low birth weight (defined as weight &lt;2500 gm at birth), very low birth weight (defined as &lt; 1500 gm at birth), high birth weight (defined as &gt; 4000 gm at birth) and very high birth weight (defined as &gt; 4500 gm at birth).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Large for gestational age</measure>
    <time_frame>within 2 weeks after live birth</time_frame>
    <description>Birth weight &gt;90th centile for gestation, based on standardised ethnicity based charts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Small for gestational age</measure>
    <time_frame>within 2 weeks after live birth</time_frame>
    <description>Less than 10th centile for gestational age at delivery based on standardised ethnicity based charts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Congenital anomaly</measure>
    <time_frame>within 2 weeks after live birth</time_frame>
    <description>Any congenital anomaly will be included diagnosed by physical examinition, ultrasound or necessary testing (including CT, X-ray etc.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perinatal mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>within 2 weeks after live birth</time_frame>
    <description>Fetal or neonatal death occurring during late pregnancy (at 28 completed weeks of gestational age and later), during childbirth, or up to seven completed days after birth.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Moderate/severe ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome (OHSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of controlled ovarian hyperstimulation until the date of oocyte retrieval, assesses about 14-16 days.</time_frame>
    <description>exaggerated systemic response to ovarian stimulation characterized by a wide spectrum of clinical and laboratory manifestations. It is classified as mild, moderate, or severe according to the degree of abdominal distention, ovarian enlargement and respiratory hemodynamic, and metabolic complications. Diagosised by ultrasound, blood testing and physical examination according the Chinese Medical Guildline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>PCOS</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>standard IVF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>On the Day2/3 of the menstrual cycle, qualified participants will be randomized into either of two groups. Participants in group A will receive standard IVF procedure. Other standard assisted reproductive treatments are similar and parallel between two groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>In vitro maturation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>On the Day2/3 of the menstrual cycle, qualified participants will be randomized into either of two groups. Participants in group B will receive IVM procedure.Other standard assisted reproductive treatments are similar and parallel between two groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>standard IVF</intervention_name>
    <description>Ovarian stimulation will be performed by a standard protocol using gonadotrophin-releasing hormone antagonist (GnRH-ant) in association with recombinant FSH (rFSH) and human chorionic gonadotrophin (hCG).Oocyte retrieval is scheduled for 36 (±2) after hCG injection.The retrieved cumulus oocyte complexes (COC) will be inseminated using ICSI or conventional IVF according to the seman analysis. All embryos will be cultured to blastocyst stage and be vitrified.</description>
    <arm_group_label>standard IVF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>In vitro maturation</intervention_name>
    <description>Controlled ovarian stimulation protocol will not performed in this group patients. Transvaginal ultrasound scanning was examined on natural cycle to monitor the follicle size in group B participants. Oocyte retrieval was scheduled once the endometrium had reached at least 6 mm in thickness and there was no follicle larger than 10 mm. After oocyte retrieval, the COCs will be cultured for 28-32h in special IVM media in order to get the matured oocytes. All the metaphase II (MII) oocytes were inseminated by means of intracytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI). All embryos will be cultured to blastocyst stage and be vitrified.</description>
    <arm_group_label>In vitro maturation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Infertile couples scheduled for their first IVF cycle.

          2. Women diagonosed with polycystic ovarian syndrome.

          3. Voluntary participation and informed consent obtained.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Couple with contraindication for IVF or ICSI.

          2. Couples receiving donor sperm or donor eggs.

          3. Couples with indications or have plan to receive PGD and PGS.

          4. Sperm analysis diagnosed as azoospermia;

          5. Either male partner or female partner with an abnormal chromosome karyotype
             (chromosome polymorphisms was not included).

          6. Women who have undergone unilateral ovariectomy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>38 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jie Qiao</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University Third Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xiaoying Zheng</last_name>
    <phone>86-10-82265033</phone>
    <email>zheng_xiaoying@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rui Yang</last_name>
    <phone>86-10-82265080</phone>
    <email>yrjeff@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking University third Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100191</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University Third Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jie Qiao</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>President</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>in vitro maturation</keyword>
  <keyword>polycystic ovarian syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>oocyte</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

