<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03464396</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201611138</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5U01HL133700-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03464396</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prematurity-Related Ventilatory Control</brief_title>
  <acronym>PreVent</acronym>
  <official_title>Physiologic Biomarkers Predicting Ventilatory Instability and Hypoxemia in Pre Mature Infants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to improve our understanding of unstable breathing and
      heart blood flow patterns seen in premature infants. The investigator will use novel
      non-invasive measures to understand the determinants of these unstable breathing and heart
      flow patterns to potentially identify new therapies for their prevention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigator will look at results of breathing tests, non-invasive sound wave
      (ultrasound) test of the heart and blood vessel (Echocardiography), and a sample of blood to
      see if it is possible for early detection of breathing control and lung blood vessel
      dysfunction (pulmonary vascular disease) in infants that are at risk for exposure to long
      term low oxygen levels. A subset of infants will have a magnetic resonance Imaging study
      (MRI) between 37- 40 weeks gestational age (GA) or at the time of discharge, whichever comes
      first.

      Respiratory tests include:

        -  Bedside Physiology Study completed at 28, 32, 36, 40, and 52 weeks gestational age (GA)
           in conjunction with the respiratory tests. A 90-minute recording will be made using
           standard recording equipment that includes a conventional pulse oximeter, an EEG, an
           airflow sampling catheter near the nose, and respiratory inductance plethysmography
           (RIP) bands. Standard bedside monitoring will continue during the physiologic studies

        -  Carotid Body Function Test completed at 32, 36, 40 and 52 weeks GA. This test is to
           unmask respiratory instability in response to hyperoxia.

        -  Challenge Test completed at 36 weeks GA.

             1. Infants receiving nasal cannula flow with or without supplemental oxygen will
                undergo a Room Air Challenge Test.

             2. Infants on RA alone will undergo a Hypoxia Challenge test.

        -  Effects of Nasal Cannula Flow completed at 28, 32, 36, 40 and 52 week's GA. The flow
           will be increased through a nasal cannula. This test is to see how flow effects the
           breathing pattern.

      A subset of infants will have an MRI between 37-40 weeks GA or before discharge, whichever
      comes first. The MRI will allow the doctors to look and see if there is any injury present in
      the brain that can be linked to an abnormal breathing pattern called periodic breathing.

      A subset of infants will have an Echocardiogram (Echo) at 32, 36 and 52 weeks GA. The Echo is
      performed to assess cardiac structure and function. Echocardiography is performed routinely
      in premature newborns in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU). The echocardiogram will be
      performed at the infant bedside and will be coordinated with bedside nurse. The infant will
      remain on a cardio-respiratory monitor during the echocardiogram for approximately 15
      minutes.

      Infants that have an Echo will have a blood sample collected near the time of the Echo,
      3-blood samples total. The purpose of collecting the blood sample is to detect if the
      Fibroblast Growth Factor (FGF2) level is elevated and possibly be a biomarker of early
      pulmonary hypertension in pre term infants validated with the echo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory phenotype based on physiologic testing</measure>
    <time_frame>36 weeks post menstrual age</time_frame>
    <description>Categorization of subjects based on physiologic Challenge Tests into one of four respiratory phenotypes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">375</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Control in Premature Infants</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
    <description>Preterm infants Study Visits
Bedside Physiology Study at 28, 32, 36, 40, and 52 weeks GA.
Respiratory tests:
Carotid Body Function Test will be completed at 32, 36, 40 and 52 weeks GA
Room Air Challenge (RAC) or Hypoxia Challenge Test (HCT) will be completed at 36 weeks GA
Effects of nasal cannula flow be completed at 28, 32, 36, 40 and 52 weeks GA
Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI): Completed on a subset of infants between 37-40 weeks GA or before discharge, whichever comes first.
Echocardiogram (Echo): Completed at 32, 36 and 52 weeks GA
Blood sample: Obtained at 32, 36 and 52 weeks GA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bedside Physiology study</intervention_name>
    <description>A 90-minute recording in conjunction with the respiratory evaluations using standard recording equipment that includes a conventional pulse oximeter, an EEG, an airflow sampling catheter near the nose, and respiratory inductance plethysmography (RIP) bands. Standard clinical bedside monitoring will continue during the respiratory evaluations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carotid Body Function Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants without nasal cannula will have a nasal cannula placed in their nares. After a 15-minute baseline period and during quiet sleep, the infant will then be exposed to 30 seconds of 100% O2 by increasing FiO2. This test will be repeated 3 times, with at least 3 minutes between tests to allow for return of SpO2 to baseline values. If oxygen saturations increase to 99% for 15 seconds or the infant is apneic for greater than 5 seconds following initiation of 100% O2, the test will be stopped and FiO2 brought back to baseline. Infants in the NICU will be monitored continuously with heart rate, respiratory rate, and SpO2% for 12 hours after Carotid Body Function Test according to NICU standards. Infants discharge who return for Carotid Body Function Test at 40 and 52 weeks PMA will be monitored continuously for 1 hour after the test is finished.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Room Air Challenge</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants receiving nasal cannula high flow support 3 liters per minute (LPM) or less with or without supplemental O2 at 36 weeks PMA will be eligible. After a 15-minute quiet sleep period, infants' FiO2 will be weaned, in 0.20 decrements for 5 min intervals. Flow then decreased in 10 min intervals, initially in 1 LPM decrement until nasal cannula flow is 1LPM, and then decreased by 50% decrements to 0.125 LPM then off. If the infant is weaned to room air alone for 15 minutes, not meeting failure criteria, he/she has passed the RAC. Failure of the RAC is defined as occurring when SpO2% falls below 80%, even briefly, or remains less than 90% for 5 consecutive minutes any time during the test, bradycardia (HR &lt; 80 bpmx 10 sec) or persistent apnea despite stimulation. Infant is returned to the level of support provided before the RAC begun if meets any failure criteria.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypoxia Challenge Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Infant's breathing room air alone at 36 weeks PMA are eligible. A nasal cannula will be placed prior to a 15-minute period of quiet sleep. During the 15 minutes of quiet sleep, the infant is required to maintain a SpO2 of &gt; 92% in order to undergo the HCT. After the15-minute baseline recording, HCT will begin using FiO2 = 0.18 for 5 minutes. If infant does not meet failure criteria, infant will be given FiO2 0.15 for 10 minutes. Failure criteria is SpO2% &lt; 80% even briefly, or SpO2% 80% to 85% for 30 seconds, bradycardia (HR &lt; 80 bpmx 10 sec) or persistent apnea despite stimulation. If an infant meets criterion for failure, supplemental O2 with FiO2 100% will be started until SpO2% is sustained between 90% and 95%. At that time, the infant will be returned to RA.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HCT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Effects of Nasal Cannula Flow</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants will have a standard nasal catheter in place at time of testing (NeoTech Premature RAM Cannula). A 15-minute baseline recording of all physiologic study parameters prior to initiation. Tested in three groups of infants.
28 and 32 weeks PMA flow rates increased after a 15-minute baseline period to 3LPM, or by 1LPM to a max of 5LPM for duration of 15 minutes.
Infant's that fail the RAC or HCT at 36 weeks with periodic breathing will have high flow at 3LPM started for 2 minutes or until periodic breathing stops.
Breathing room air alone at 40 and 52 weeks PMA will have a high flow catheter inserted in their nares. If they have periodic breathing lasting longer than 1 minute during the 15-minute baseline period, flow at 3LPM will be started and maintained for 2 minutes or until periodic breathing stops.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>A non-sedating MRI scan will be performed on 3 subsets of infants at 37-40 weeks PMA, or when infant is within one week of discharge from the NICU. Standard images as well as research images will be obtained. The research images use the same MRI scanner and collection techniques as standard clinical imaging, but provide a more detailed examination of brain anatomy and injury. Collection of these sequences using our standard non-sedated acquisition practices for infants is well tolerated. Infants will be placed in scanner by registered nurse accompanied by radiology technician to assure infants' comfort during scan. Infant will remain on cardio-respiratory monitor during MRI via a pulse oximetry probe. It will take no longer than one hour to complete MRI scan including transportation to radiology unit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Echocardiogram</intervention_name>
    <description>An echocardiogram (referred to as an ultrasound of the heart on the consent form) will be performed to assess cardiac structure and function. Echocardiograms are performed routinely in premature newborns in the NICU. The Echocardiogram will be performed at the infant bedside and will be coordinated with bedside nurse. The infant will remain on a cardio-respiratory monitor during the echocardiogram for approximately 15 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Echo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Sample</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants that have echocardiograms will have a blood sample collected near the time the echocardiogram is obtained, 3-blood samples total. The blood sample will only be collected with parental permission on an opt-in or out-basis and collected only with routine clinical labs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infant study visits</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Buccal Swabs
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Infants admitted to the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit who are born between 24 0/7 to 28 7/8
        weeks GA
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All infants born between 24 0/7 and 28 6/7 weeks GA admitted to the Neonatal Intensive
             Care Unit at St. Louis Children's Hospital will be considered for enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants not likely to survive

          -  Infant with significant heart disease

          -  Infant with a significant congenital abnormalities of the central nervous system,
             nose, mouth lungs or ribs, or congenital diseases that affect lung growth

          -  Physician refusal

          -  Unlikely that the infant will be available for 52-week follow-up visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>7 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Kemp, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julie A Hoffmann, RN</last_name>
    <phone>314-273-1990</phone>
    <email>hoffmann_j@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Barbara Warner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>314-424-7115</phone>
    <email>warner_b@kids.wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie A Hoffmann, RN</last_name>
      <phone>314-273-1990</phone>
      <email>hoffmann_j@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laura Linneman, RN</last_name>
      <phone>314-454-1990</phone>
      <email>linneman_l@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Kemp, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coste F, Ferkol T, Hamvas A, Cleveland C, Linneman L, Hoffman J, Kemp J. Ventilatory control and supplemental oxygen in premature infants with apparent chronic lung disease. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2015 May;100(3):F233-7. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2014-307272. Epub 2015 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>25716677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carroll JL, Agarwal A. Development of ventilatory control in infants. Paediatr Respir Rev. 2010 Dec;11(4):199-207. doi: 10.1016/j.prrv.2010.06.002. Epub 2010 Jul 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21109177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Periodic breathing</keyword>
  <keyword>Apnea of prematurity</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Lung disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Prematurity</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypoxia</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Hypertension</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

