<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03464448</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00136966</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03464448</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mechanistic Studies of Teriflunomide in RRMS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mechanistic Studies of Teriflunomide in Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis: Regulatory B Lymphocytes as Central Mediators of the Therapeutic Effects of Teriflunomide in MS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to address the mechanism of action of teriflunomide in a phase IV open label
      trial with Teriflunomide in multiple sclerosis. Researchers will recruit 20 relapsing
      remitting multiple sclerosis patients (Group 1) start on treatment with teriflunomide
      (Aubagio). Patients will be enrolled from the Multiple Sclerosis Center at the University of
      Michigan Health System in Ann Arbor. Meanwhile, 10 healthy controls will be recruited, to
      establish a healthy baseline for B and T cells, which are affected by both MS and its
      treatment (Group 2). This Study will collect baseline pre-treatment blood samples
      periodically for up to 2 years. Blood biomarker changes will be correlated with clinical
      response to teriflunomide treatment intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multiple sclerosis is the most common autoimmune inflammatory and debilitating chronic
      demyelinating disease of the central nervous system mainly affecting young adults. There is a
      tremendous need to understand the mechanism of action of the treatment and how they might
      work in multiple sclerosis patients. Most recently, teriflunomide (AubagioTM) has been
      demonstrated to act as an immune modulatory therapy for patients with multiple sclerosis.
      Although one biochemical mechanism of action is understood to be related to inhibition of
      dihydroorotate dehydrogenase (DHODH) which affects synthesis of pyrimidine nucleotides, there
      have also been reports that the functions of regulatory T cells are promoted by these drugs
      independent of DHODH. Much accumulating evidence suggests that specialized subsets of B
      lymphocytes are important inducers of regulatory T cells, as well as having killer functions
      that may preferentially target TH1 and TH17 cells.

      This study aims to address the mechanism of action of teriflunomide in a phase IV open label
      trial with Teriflunomide in multiple sclerosis
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in frequency of regulatory and effector B cell subset</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Compare aubagio treatment to baseline and to healthy controls</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in frequency of CD4+ Th17, Th1, Th2, and Treg cells</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Compare aubagio treatment to baseline and to healthy controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in chemokine levels</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Compare aubagio treatment to baseline and to healthy controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cytokine levels</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Compare aubagio treatment to baseline and to healthy controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with RRMS who have been newly prescribed Teriflunomide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy Controls</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Teriflunomide</intervention_name>
    <description>AUBAGIO® (teriflunomide) is a prescription medicine used to treat relapsing forms of multiple sclerosis (MS), which inhibits pyrimidine de novo synthesis by blocking the enzyme dihydroorotate dehydrogenase.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aubagio</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood will be collected after 3, 6, 9, 12, 18 and 24 months of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A total of 20 multiple sclerosis (MS) patients and 10 healthy controls will be recruited to
        voluntarily donate blood for the study. Blood samples will be collected prior to starting
        teriflunomide treatment (baseline) and after 3, 6, 9, 12, 18 and 24 months of treatment
        (+/- 2 weeks).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with clinically-defined relapsing-remitting MS (RRMS) who &quot; are newly
             starting on teriflunomide (AubagioTM) at the time of enrollment &quot; have no evidence of
             relapse or corticosteroid treatment use within 2 months prior to enrollment

             OR

             Healthy controls who do not have a significant medical condition such as cancer,
             chronic infection, or autoimmune disease, have not taken steroids in the past 2
             months, and who are not on an immune suppressant medication.

          2. Ability to give informed consent

          3. Willing to have blood drawn as scheduled in the protocol

          4. Willing and able to complete all procedures and evaluations related to the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Medical or psychiatric conditions that may affect the patient's ability to give
             informed consent

          2. Has received an experimental drug within 30 days of enrollment

          3. Concomitant other disease modifying medications (such as Rebif, Betaseron, Avonex,
             Copaxone, Gilenya, Tecfidera, Alemtuzumab, methotrexate, azathioprine, mitoxantrone,
             cyclophosphamide, cyclosporine, natalizumab, rituxan, ocrelizumab, etc.) without the
             minimal washout period stated below:

             &quot; rebif, betaseron, avonex, copaxone within 1 month &quot; zinbryta, plegridy, gilenya,
             tecfidera within 2 months &quot; natalizumab within 3 months &quot;
             immunosuppressive/chemotherapeutic medications (e.g. azathioprine, methotrexate)
             within 6 months &quot; cyclophosphamide within 1 year &quot; rituximab, ofatumumab, ocrelizumab,
             cladribine within 1 year &quot; alemtuzumab at any time &quot; any mitoxantrone during previous
             2 years prior to randomization or evidence of cardiotoxicity following mitoxantrone or
             a cumulative life-time dose of more than 60 mg/m2 &quot; lymphoid irradiation, bone marrow
             transplantation or other immunosuppressive treatments with effects potentially lasting
             over 6 months, at any time

          4. Has any contraindication to high-dose immunotherapy, including pregnancy, trying to
             become pregnant, or breast feeding during the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yang Mao-Draayer, MD/PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yang Mao-Draayer, MD/PHD</last_name>
    <phone>734-763-3630</phone>
    <email>maodraay@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Caitlyn J Fisher, BA</last_name>
    <phone>734-764-8971</phone>
    <email>fishercj@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yang Mao-Draayer, MD/PHD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hauser SL, Oksenberg JR. The neurobiology of multiple sclerosis: genes, inflammation, and neurodegeneration. Neuron. 2006 Oct 5;52(1):61-76. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17015227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trapp BD, Nave KA. Multiple sclerosis: an immune or neurodegenerative disorder? Annu Rev Neurosci. 2008;31:247-69. doi: 10.1146/annurev.neuro.30.051606.094313. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18558855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bar-Or A, Pachner A, Menguy-Vacheron F, Kaplan J, Wiendl H. Teriflunomide and its mechanism of action in multiple sclerosis. Drugs. 2014 Apr;74(6):659-74. doi: 10.1007/s40265-014-0212-x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24740824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lundy SK, Wu Q, Wang Q, Dowling CA, Taitano SH, Mao G, Mao-Draayer Y. Dimethyl fumarate treatment of relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis influences B-cell subsets. Neurol Neuroimmunol Neuroinflamm. 2016 Mar 3;3(2):e211. doi: 10.1212/NXI.0000000000000211. eCollection 2016 Apr.</citation>
    <PMID>27006972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claussen MC, Korn T. Immune mechanisms of new therapeutic strategies in MS: teriflunomide. Clin Immunol. 2012 Jan;142(1):49-56. doi: 10.1016/j.clim.2011.02.011. Epub 2011 Mar 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21367665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baban B, Liu JY, Mozaffari MS. Aryl hydrocarbon receptor agonist, leflunomide, protects the ischemic-reperfused kidney: role of Tregs and stem cells. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 2012 Dec;303(11):R1136-46. doi: 10.1152/ajpregu.00315.2012. Epub 2012 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>23100028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korn T, Magnus T, Toyka K, Jung S. Modulation of effector cell functions in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis by leflunomide--mechanisms independent of pyrimidine depletion. J Leukoc Biol. 2004 Nov;76(5):950-60. Epub 2004 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>15328336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weigmann B, Jarman ER, Sudowe S, Bros M, Knop J, Reske-Kunz AB. Induction of regulatory T cells by leflunomide in a murine model of contact allergen sensitivity. J Invest Dermatol. 2006 Jul;126(7):1524-33. Epub 2006 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>16543898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter NA, Rosser EC, Mauri C. Interleukin-10 produced by B cells is crucial for the suppression of Th17/Th1 responses, induction of T regulatory type 1 cells and reduction of collagen-induced arthritis. Arthritis Res Ther. 2012 Feb 8;14(1):R32. doi: 10.1186/ar3736.</citation>
    <PMID>22315945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flores-Borja F, Bosma A, Ng D, Reddy V, Ehrenstein MR, Isenberg DA, Mauri C. CD19+CD24hiCD38hi B cells maintain regulatory T cells while limiting TH1 and TH17 differentiation. Sci Transl Med. 2013 Feb 20;5(173):173ra23. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3005407.</citation>
    <PMID>23427243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iwata Y, Matsushita T, Horikawa M, Dilillo DJ, Yanaba K, Venturi GM, Szabolcs PM, Bernstein SH, Magro CM, Williams AD, Hall RP, St Clair EW, Tedder TF. Characterization of a rare IL-10-competent B-cell subset in humans that parallels mouse regulatory B10 cells. Blood. 2011 Jan 13;117(2):530-41. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-07-294249. Epub 2010 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20962324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mann MK, Maresz K, Shriver LP, Tan Y, Dittel BN. B cell regulation of CD4+CD25+ T regulatory cells and IL-10 via B7 is essential for recovery from experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis. J Immunol. 2007 Mar 15;178(6):3447-56.</citation>
    <PMID>17339439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matsushita T, Horikawa M, Iwata Y, Tedder TF. Regulatory B cells (B10 cells) and regulatory T cells have independent roles in controlling experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis initiation and late-phase immunopathogenesis. J Immunol. 2010 Aug 15;185(4):2240-52. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.1001307. Epub 2010 Jul 12.</citation>
    <PMID>20624940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ray A, Basu S, Williams CB, Salzman NH, Dittel BN. A novel IL-10-independent regulatory role for B cells in suppressing autoimmunity by maintenance of regulatory T cells via GITR ligand. J Immunol. 2012 Apr 1;188(7):3188-98. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.1103354. Epub 2012 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22368274</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klinker MW, Lundy SK. Multiple mechanisms of immune suppression by B lymphocytes. Mol Med. 2012 Feb 10;18:123-37. doi: 10.2119/molmed.2011.00333. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22033729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cross AH, Stark JL, Lauber J, Ramsbottom MJ, Lyons JA. Rituximab reduces B cells and T cells in cerebrospinal fluid of multiple sclerosis patients. J Neuroimmunol. 2006 Nov;180(1-2):63-70. Epub 2006 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>16904756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yang Mao-Draayer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Teriflunomide</keyword>
  <keyword>B cell</keyword>
  <keyword>T cell</keyword>
  <keyword>cytokines</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis, Relapsing-Remitting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

