<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03463213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-148</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U54MD006882-06</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03463213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SHE Tribe: An Intervention to Improve Health Behavior Among Women in Underserved Communities</brief_title>
  <official_title>She's Healthy and Empowered (SHE Tribe): A Social Networked-based Peer-facilitated Intervention to Improve Health Behavior Among Women in Underserved Communities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Texas Health Science Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>YMCA of Metropolitan Fort Worth</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Texas Health Science Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      While healthy lifestyle behaviors have been identified as instrumental to preventing chronic
      disease, programs to successfully promote healthy behavior adoption in underserved
      communities have had limited sustainable success. SHE Tribe is a culturally tailored, social
      network intervention created through CBPR to overcome previously identified barriers and
      improve health behavior among women in underserved communities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The leading causes of death for women in the United States are heart disease, cancer, and
      stroke. Chronic diseases disproportionately affect underserved communities where race,
      poverty, education-level, healthcare access, and other social and environmental determinants
      intersect. African-American (AA) and Hispanic women are at particularly high risk for
      diabetes-related mortality 1 and are more likely than white women to be functionally impacted
      by chronic disease . Factors associated with increased disease risk include physical
      inactivity, poor nutrition, obesity, underutilization of health screenings, and high
      stress/allostatic load . While healthy lifestyle behaviors have been identified as
      instrumental to preventing chronic disease, programs to successfully promote healthy behavior
      adoption in underserved communities have had limited sustainable success, due in part to
      perceived relevance of program outcomes, lack of cultural tailoring, access to care, and lack
      of social support for health behavior change.

      The Texas Center for Health Disparities received National Institute of Minority Health and
      Health Disparities funding to address women's chronic health conditions through community
      outreach and research strategies from 2012-2017. A workgroup of community members, former
      research and program participants, and University of North Texas Health Science Center
      faculty and staff utilized a Community-Based Participatory Research (CBPR) process to design
      SHE Tribe (She's Healthy and Empowered), a social-network based initiative to support healthy
      behavior adoption among women in underserved communities. This effort was based on earlier
      findings that women in underserved neighborhoods were often resistant to participating in a
      &quot;disease-labeled&quot; intervention (e.g., obesity prevention) and expressed a desire to practice
      wellness-oriented behaviors that have been adapted for their social and cultural groups.
      These findings were consistent with the growing body of literature indicating that being
      &quot;healthy and strong&quot; is perceived as more desirable than engaging in a program where the
      explicit expectation is to lose weight. As part of the development process, the workgroup
      sought to develop a sustainable, evidence-based approach that would appeal to underserved
      communities that are disproportionately impacted by chronic disease.

      Components of SHE Tribe include evidence-based characteristics associated with the adoption
      and maintenance of health behaviors: a) incorporating social network to promote healthy
      activities, b) setting goals that are specific to the needs and interests of the individual ,
      c) self-monitoring of desired behaviors, d) motivational interviewing-based dialogue that
      promotes intrinsic motivation to change, e) choosing small units of change for the purpose of
      habit formation, and f) combining practice and reflection to promote integration with
      existing life patterns and beliefs. The advantage of SHE Tribe over previous models is its
      explicit use of social networks and reliance on a broader set of activities that are
      consistent with a healthy lifestyle rather than disease. SHE Tribe was initially pilot-tested
      with a small cohort of 5 peer facilitators. Based on their feedback, it was then enhanced to
      include telephone or tablet-based assessment and tailored feedback at the beginning
      (baseline) and end of each 5-session cycle. The current version is being pilot-tested as a
      community-initiated project, and as such includes only a basic set of assessment tools that
      are necessary to make the intervention work. The purpose of this 2-year exploratory
      submission is to examine the effects of SHE Tribe on key health outcomes such as health
      self-management, coping, diet, activity, and social network health norms.

      AIM 1. Determine whether SHE Tribe can be feasibly implemented with groups of women from
      communities at high risk for chronic health conditions. The research team will examine the
      characteristics of women recruited to SHE Tribe to determine whether the network-based
      recruitment is an effective method for reaching the underserved communities. This will
      include a review of audio-recorded sessions, session summary reports, and semi-structured
      interviews with participants and facilitators to understand the perceived value and adoption
      of different intervention components.

      AIM 2. Examine how health behaviors are adopted by individuals and diffused through social
      networks. At the individual level: Using validated measures, the research team determine
      which goals are selected and the relationship between goal selection, key health outcomes,
      and activation of health behavior self-management. At the interpersonal level: Using a social
      network analysis instrument which measures participants' perceptions of identified
      individuals in their networks, the research team will examine the diffusion of healthy
      lifestyle norms.

      The impact of this study will be the refinement of an intervention that supports
      sustainability and reach in underserved communities that are at high-risk for chronic
      diseases. The emphasis on a constellation of healthy behaviors and the use of peer
      facilitators will appeal to the cultural identities of women residing in underserved and/or
      high poverty communities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a feasibility study with a single group pre/post outcome design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Healthy Habits Tracking</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>This tool includes 42 items representing tracking and monitoring behaviors, such as weighing oneself, keeping a food diary, etc... Each is answered with a yes/no (0/1) response. Scores range from 0 to 42. The questionnaire is administered at baseline and again at 8 weeks. The desired outcome is an increase in the total score between baseline and 8 weeks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Support for Diet and Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>These 11 items are adapted from the Patient Assessment and Counseling for Exercise (PACE+ Women: Measurement Questionnaire). Scores range from 11 to 44, with higher scores indicating a greater social support for healthy lifestyle choices associated with diet and exercise.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coping with stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>These 10 questions include 5 subscales from the Brief COPE tool which measure use of emotional support, use of instrumental support, positive reframing, planning and religion. Each sub-scale score ranges from 0 to 4 with higher values reflecting better coping strategies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Appreciation Scale (BAS-2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a 10 item scale measuring body positivity. Scores are based on mean values of all items.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthy Lifestyle Activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>This tool includes 7 items that measure health-related efficacy, agency, and self-management. Each item is ranked on a scale of 1 to 10 with overall scores ranging from 7 to 70.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fruit and vegetable consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>This item is from the Patient Assessment and Counseling for Exercise (PACE+ Women: Measurement Questionnaire) and measures self-reported days of purposeful physical activity (30 minutes or more) during a typical week. Scores range from 0 to 7 with higher values reflecting more frequent physical activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity days</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>This item is from the Patient Assessment and Counseling for Exercise (PACE+ Women: Measurement Questionnaire) and measures self-reported daily consumption of fruit and vegetables servings.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Promotion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SHE Tribe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SHE Tribe is a social network-based peer-facilitated intervention to promote adoption of health behaviors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SHE Tribe</intervention_name>
    <description>Social network-based peer-facilitated intervention to promote adoption of health behavior</description>
    <arm_group_label>SHE Tribe</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  representative of underserved community (determined by race, ethnicity, socioeconomic
             status, and/or neighborhood)

          -  18 and older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Males

          -  Children
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Must self-represent as a female</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emily Spence-Almaguer, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNT Health Science Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily E Spence-Almaguer, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>817-735-2323</phone>
    <email>emily.spence-almaguer@unthsc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Katherine C Anguiano, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>817-735-2378</phone>
    <email>katherine.cantu@unthsc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.cdc.gov/women/lcod/2014/race-ethnicity/index.htm</url>
    <description>CDC Office for Women's Health Leading Causes of Death</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.icer-review.org</url>
    <description>Diabetes Prevention Programs: Effectiveness and Value</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://blog-cdn1.myfitnesspal.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/MyFitnessTribe_Ebook_interactive_FINAL.pdf</url>
    <description>The rise of fitness tribes</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sudano JJ, Baker DW. Explaining US racial/ethnic disparities in health declines and mortality in late middle age: the roles of socioeconomic status, health behaviors, and health insurance. Soc Sci Med. 2006 Feb;62(4):909-22. Epub 2005 Aug 2.</citation>
    <PMID>16055252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lantz PM, House JS, Lepkowski JM, Williams DR, Mero RP, Chen J. Socioeconomic factors, health behaviors, and mortality: results from a nationally representative prospective study of US adults. JAMA. 1998 Jun 3;279(21):1703-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9624022</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kington RS, Smith JP. Socioeconomic status and racial and ethnic differences in functional status associated with chronic diseases. Am J Public Health. 1997 May;87(5):805-10.</citation>
    <PMID>9184510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mosca L. Guidelines for prevention of cardiovascular disease in women: a summary of recommendations. Prev Cardiol. 2007 Fall;10 Suppl 4:19-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17917527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geronimus AT, Hicken M, Keene D, Bound J. &quot;Weathering&quot; and age patterns of allostatic load scores among blacks and whites in the United States. Am J Public Health. 2006 May;96(5):826-33. Epub 2005 Dec 27.</citation>
    <PMID>16380565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bauer UE, Briss PA, Goodman RA, Bowman BA. Prevention of chronic disease in the 21st century: elimination of the leading preventable causes of premature death and disability in the USA. Lancet. 2014 Jul 5;384(9937):45-52. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60648-6. Epub 2014 Jul 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24996589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nelson D, Harris A, Horner-Ibler B, Harris KS, Burns E. Hearing the Community: Evolution of a Nutrition and Physical Activity Program for African American Women to Improve Weight. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2016;27(2):560-7. doi: 10.1353/hpu.2016.0088.</citation>
    <PMID>27180695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bacon L, Aphramor L. Weight science: evaluating the evidence for a paradigm shift. Nutr J. 2011 Jan 24;10:9. doi: 10.1186/1475-2891-10-9. Review. Erratum in: Nutr J. 2011;10:69.</citation>
    <PMID>21261939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bacon L, Keim NL, Van Loan MD, Derricote M, Gale B, Kazaks A, Stern JS. Evaluating a 'non-diet' wellness intervention for improvement of metabolic fitness, psychological well-being and eating and activity behaviors. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 2002 Jun;26(6):854-65.</citation>
    <PMID>12037657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumanyika SK, Wadden TA, Shults J, Fassbender JE, Brown SD, Bowman MA, Brake V, West W, Frazier J, Whitt-Glover MC, Kallan MJ, Desnouee E, Wu X. Trial of family and friend support for weight loss in African American adults. Arch Intern Med. 2009 Oct 26;169(19):1795-804. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2009.337.</citation>
    <PMID>19858438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson JW, Konz EC, Frederich RC, Wood CL. Long-term weight-loss maintenance: a meta-analysis of US studies. Am J Clin Nutr. 2001 Nov;74(5):579-84.</citation>
    <PMID>11684524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fitzgibbon ML, Tussing-Humphreys LM, Porter JS, Martin IK, Odoms-Young A, Sharp LK. Weight loss and African-American women: a systematic review of the behavioural weight loss intervention literature. Obes Rev. 2012 Mar;13(3):193-213. doi: 10.1111/j.1467-789X.2011.00945.x. Epub 2011 Nov 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22074195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warsi A, Wang PS, LaValley MP, Avorn J, Solomon DH. Self-management education programs in chronic disease: a systematic review and methodological critique of the literature. Arch Intern Med. 2004 Aug 9-23;164(15):1641-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15302634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samuel-Hodge CD, Johnson CM, Braxton DF, Lackey M. Effectiveness of Diabetes Prevention Program translations among African Americans. Obes Rev. 2014 Oct;15 Suppl 4:107-24. doi: 10.1111/obr.12211. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25196409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brady TJ, Murphy L, O'Colmain BJ, Beauchesne D, Daniels B, Greenberg M, House M, Chervin D. A meta-analysis of health status, health behaviors, and healthcare utilization outcomes of the Chronic Disease Self-Management Program. Prev Chronic Dis. 2013;10:120112. doi: 10.5888/pcd10.120112.</citation>
    <PMID>23327828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yancey AK, Ortega AN, Kumanyika SK. Effective recruitment and retention of minority research participants. Annu Rev Public Health. 2006;27:1-28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16533107</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chin MH, Clarke AR, Nocon RS, Casey AA, Goddu AP, Keesecker NM, Cook SC. A roadmap and best practices for organizations to reduce racial and ethnic disparities in health care. J Gen Intern Med. 2012 Aug;27(8):992-1000. doi: 10.1007/s11606-012-2082-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22798211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hibbard JH, Greene J, Becker ER, Roblin D, Painter MW, Perez DJ, Burbank-Schmitt E, Tusler M. Racial/ethnic disparities and consumer activation in health. Health Aff (Millwood). 2008 Sep-Oct;27(5):1442-53. doi: 10.1377/hlthaff.27.5.1442.</citation>
    <PMID>18780935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green LW, Ottoson JM, García C, Hiatt RA. Diffusion theory and knowledge dissemination, utilization, and integration in public health. Annu Rev Public Health. 2009;30:151-74. doi: 10.1146/annurev.publhealth.031308.100049. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19705558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pearson ES. Goal setting as a health behavior change strategy in overweight and obese adults: a systematic literature review examining intervention components. Patient Educ Couns. 2012 Apr;87(1):32-42. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2011.07.018. Epub 2011 Aug 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21852063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubak S, Sandbaek A, Lauritzen T, Christensen B. Motivational interviewing: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Gen Pract. 2005 Apr;55(513):305-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15826439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burke LE, Wang J, Sevick MA. Self-monitoring in weight loss: a systematic review of the literature. J Am Diet Assoc. 2011 Jan;111(1):92-102. doi: 10.1016/j.jada.2010.10.008. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21185970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hill JO. Can a small-changes approach help address the obesity epidemic? A report of the Joint Task Force of the American Society for Nutrition, Institute of Food Technologists, and International Food Information Council. Am J Clin Nutr. 2009 Feb;89(2):477-84. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.2008.26566. Epub 2008 Dec 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19088151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodearmel SJ, Wyatt HR, Stroebele N, Smith SM, Ogden LG, Hill JO. Small changes in dietary sugar and physical activity as an approach to preventing excessive weight gain: the America on the Move family study. Pediatrics. 2007 Oct;120(4):e869-79.</citation>
    <PMID>17908743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harmon BE, Forthofer M, Bantum EO, Nigg CR. Perceived influence and college students' diet and physical activity behaviors: an examination of ego-centric social networks. BMC Public Health. 2016 Jun 6;16:473. doi: 10.1186/s12889-016-3166-y.</citation>
    <PMID>27267371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latkin CA, Knowlton AR. Social Network Assessments and Interventions for Health Behavior Change: A Critical Review. Behav Med. 2015;41(3):90-7. doi: 10.1080/08964289.2015.1034645. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26332926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Michie S, Abraham C, Whittington C, McAteer J, Gupta S. Effective techniques in healthy eating and physical activity interventions: a meta-regression. Health Psychol. 2009 Nov;28(6):690-701. doi: 10.1037/a0016136. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19916637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stevanovic D. Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire-short form for quality of life assessments in clinical practice: a psychometric study. J Psychiatr Ment Health Nurs. 2011 Oct;18(8):744-50. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2850.2011.01735.x. Epub 2011 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21896118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tylka TL, Wood-Barcalow NL. The Body Appreciation Scale-2: item refinement and psychometric evaluation. Body Image. 2015 Jan;12:53-67. doi: 10.1016/j.bodyim.2014.09.006. Epub 2014 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25462882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sallis JF, Grossman RM, Pinski RB, Patterson TL, Nader PR. The development of scales to measure social support for diet and exercise behaviors. Prev Med. 1987 Nov;16(6):825-36.</citation>
    <PMID>3432232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hibbard JH, Stockard J, Mahoney ER, Tusler M. Development of the Patient Activation Measure (PAM): conceptualizing and measuring activation in patients and consumers. Health Serv Res. 2004 Aug;39(4 Pt 1):1005-26.</citation>
    <PMID>15230939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greene J, Hibbard JH. Why does patient activation matter? An examination of the relationships between patient activation and health-related outcomes. J Gen Intern Med. 2012 May;27(5):520-6. doi: 10.1007/s11606-011-1931-2.</citation>
    <PMID>22127797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carver CS. You want to measure coping but your protocol's too long: consider the brief COPE. Int J Behav Med. 1997;4(1):92-100.</citation>
    <PMID>16250744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beaudreau SA, Spira AP, Stewart A, Kezirian EJ, Lui LY, Ensrud K, Redline S, Ancoli-Israel S, Stone KL; Study of Osteoporotic Fractures. Validation of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index and the Epworth Sleepiness Scale in older black and white women. Sleep Med. 2012 Jan;13(1):36-42. doi: 10.1016/j.sleep.2011.04.005. Epub 2011 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22033120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carlson JA, Sallis JF, Wagner N, Calfas KJ, Patrick K, Groesz LM, Norman GJ. Brief physical activity-related psychosocial measures: reliability and construct validity. J Phys Act Health. 2012 Nov;9(8):1178-86. Epub 2011 Dec 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22207589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miura S, Yamaguchi Y, Urata H, Himeshima Y, Otsuka N, Tomita S, Yamatsu K, Nishida S, Saku K. Efficacy of a multicomponent program (patient-centered assessment and counseling for exercise plus nutrition [PACE+ Japan]) for lifestyle modification in patients with essential hypertension. Hypertens Res. 2004 Nov;27(11):859-64.</citation>
    <PMID>15824468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calfas KJ, Sallis JF, Zabinski MF, Wilfley DE, Rupp J, Prochaska JJ, Thompson S, Pratt M, Patrick K. Preliminary evaluation of a multicomponent program for nutrition and physical activity change in primary care: PACE+ for adults. Prev Med. 2002 Feb;34(2):153-61.</citation>
    <PMID>11817910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of North Texas Health Science Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Emily Spence-Almaguer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Dean; Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>health behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic disease prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>healthy lifestyle</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

