<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03461770</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LUS IV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03461770</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure Decreased Lung Collapse During General Anesthesia Induction in Pediatric Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure Decreased Lung Collapse During General Anesthesia Induction in Pediatric Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Privado de Comunidad de Mar del Plata</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Privado de Comunidad de Mar del Plata</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Anesthesia-induced atelectasis is a well-known entity observed in approximately 68-100% of
      pediatric patients undergoing general anesthesia. Infants and young children are more
      susceptible to this lung collapse due to their small functional residual capacity. Thus,
      intrapulmonary shunting caused by those atelectasis are more likely to occur during general
      anesthesia in infants and younger children than in adults. This problem predisposes children
      to hypoxemic episodes that can persist in the early postoperative period. Beyond the negative
      impact of atelectasis on gas exchange, mechanical ventilation induces a local inflammatory
      response in atelectatic lungs, even in healthy patients undergoing general anesthesia.

      Therefore, the diagnosis, prevention and active treatment of anesthesia-induced atelectasis
      are mandatory, not only to avoid hypoxemic episodes and atelectasis-related post-operative
      pulmonary complications, but also to protect the lungs during mechanical ventilation.
      Nowadays, the diagnosis of anesthesia-induced atelectasis is easily and accurately
      accomplished by lung ultrasound (LUS). LUS is a simple and non-invasive tool useful to detect
      atelectasis in children, to assess lung aeration and for monitoring ventilator settings or
      strategies. Regarding to the prevention of atelectasis, it was demonstrated that the
      application of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) during the induction of general
      anesthesia decreases atelectasis formation in adult morbidly obese patients.

      The investogators hypothesized that the use of CPAP during general anesthesia induction in
      pediatric patients can prevent or decrease atelectasis formation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Compare lung aeration between two different strategies of induction to general anesthesia:
      breathing throughout a facial mask without CPAP and breathing with 5 cmH20 of CPAP in
      pediatric patients scheduled for surgery under general anesthesia, using ultrasound imaging
      and a four-point-aeration score to assess the lung aeration.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lung aeration during anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>intra-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Compare lung aeration between two different strategies of induction to general anesthesia: breathing throughout a facial mask without CPAP and breathing with 5 cmH20 of CPAP in pediatric patients scheduled for surgery under general anesthesia, using ultrasound imaging and a four-point-aeration score to assess the lung aeration (0 = normal lung, 1 = moderate aeration loss, 2 = severe aeration loss, 3 = complete aeration loss and consolidation).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral arterial oxygenation by pulse oximetry</measure>
    <time_frame>intra-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral capillary oxygen saturation (SpO2) by pulse oximetry will be recorded during anesthesia with the 'Air-Test'.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lung aeration after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>intra-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Lung aeration score immediately after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Atelectasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive anesthesia induction with Sevoflurane using a circular circuit without CPAP. Protective ventilation with 5 cmH20 of positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) will be initiated after induction. At the end of surgery, mechanical ventilation will stop allowing spontaneous ventilation. Patients will be extubated without CPAP. Lung ultrasound examinations will be performed at different times-points: before anesthesia induction, during surgery, at the end of surgery and before extubation, and after extubation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPAP group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive anesthesia induction using 5 cmH20 of CPAP until the moment of intubation. After induction patients will receive the same protective ventilation than the control group. A lung recruitment maneuver will be applied if these patients present atelectasis during surgery. At the end of surgery, patients will be extubated under the modality of CPAP with 5 cmH20. Lung ultrasound examinations will be performed at different times-points: before anesthesia induction, during surgery, at the end of surgery and before extubation, and after extubation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPAP</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive general anesthesia induction with CPAP at 5 cmH20 via face mask with a circular system. CPAP will use before extubation.The air-test will perform during anesthesia with transitory decreases inspired fraction of oxygen to 0.21 over a 5 min period. Recruitment maneuver will be perform if the air test is positive, ( SpO2 is ≤ 96%)</description>
    <arm_group_label>CPAP group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent by parents.

          -  Patients aged 6 months to 7 years old

          -  Scheduled for surgery under general anesthesia with tracheal intubation.

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists classification: physical status I-II

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute airway infection

          -  Cardiovascular or pulmonary disease

          -  Previous thoracic procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>7 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cecilia Acosta, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Privado de Comunidad</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cecilia Acosta, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+542234990074</phone>
    <email>ceciliamacosta@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gerardo Tusman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+542234990074</phone>
    <email>gtusman@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>atelectasis</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Atelectasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

