<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03462004</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIR 324</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03462004</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Live-Attenuated Human Parainfluenza Virus Type 3 Vectored Vaccine Candidate Expressing Ebolavirus Zaire Glycoprotein as the Sole Envelope Glycoprotein</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Evaluation of a Live-Attenuated Human Parainfluenza Virus Type 3 Vectored Vaccine Candidate Expressing Ebolavirus Zaire Glycoprotein as the Sole Envelope Glycoprotein</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety, infectivity, and immunogenicity of two
      doses of the HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine candidate when administered intranasally in healthy
      adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety, infectivity, and immunogenicity of two doses of the
      HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine candidate when administered intranasally in healthy adults.

      Participants will be enrolled sequentially in two cohorts. Participants in Cohort 1 will be
      randomly assigned to receive two doses of either 10^6.0 PFU/mL of HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ-GP vaccine
      or placebo. The first dose will be given on Day 0 and the second dose will be given 4-8 weeks
      later. Participants in Cohort 2 will be randomly assigned to receive two doses of either
      10^7.0 PFU/mL of HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ-GP vaccine or placebo on Days 0 and 28.

      Participants will be admitted to the inpatient unit 2 days prior to receiving their first
      dose of the vaccine or placebo. While in the inpatient unit, study procedures will include
      physical examinations, nasal washes, and blood collection. Participants will be discharged
      from the inpatient unit on Day 8 or thereafter once two consecutive rRT-PCR assay results are
      below the pre-determined threshold. An additional study visit will occur on Day 14.

      On Day 26 (+28), participants will be readmitted to the inpatient unit, and will receive
      their second dose of the vaccine or placebo on Day 28 (+28). Participants will undergo the
      same study procedures that occurred during the first inpatient stay, and will be discharged 7
      days after the second dose, or once the subject is without respiratory symptoms and rRT-PCR
      assay is below the pre-determined threshold (around Day 35). Additional study visits will
      occur on Days 42 ± 3, 56 ± 5, 84 ± 5, 112 ± 7, 180 ± 14, 270 ± 14, and 360 ± 30.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of vaccine-related solicited adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>Graded according to Division of AIDS (DAIDS) Table for Grading the Severity of Adult and Pediatric Adverse Events, Version 2.1, March 2017</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the curve of nasal virus shedding after each dose of vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Day 35</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by liquid titration of nasal secretions on LLC-MK2 monkey kidney cells</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of serum antibody to the EbovZ GP</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Day 360</time_frame>
    <description>As measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Ebola Virus Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive two doses of 10^6.0 PFU/mL of HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine on Days 0 and 28 (+28).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive two doses of placebo on Days 0 and 28 (+28).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive two doses of 10^7.0 PFU/mL of HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine on Days 0 and 28 (+28).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive two doses of placebo on Days 0 and 28 (+28).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered intranasally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: HPIV3/ΔHNF/EbovZ GP vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered intranasally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult males and non-pregnant females between 18 and 50 years of age inclusive

          -  General good health, without significant medical illness, physical examination
             findings, or significant laboratory abnormalities as determined by the investigator

          -  Agree to storage of blood specimens for future research

          -  Available for the duration of the trial

          -  Able to demonstrate understanding of key study concepts, study rationale, and study
             participation requirements by scoring greater than or equal to 70% on a written
             comprehension assessment in less than or equal to 3 attempts.

          -  Willingness to participate in the study as evidenced by signing the informed consent
             document

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential must agree to have used effective birth
             control methods beginning at least one month prior to vaccination, and continuing with
             'per label/fully effective use' for the chosen method for the duration of the study,
             from amongst these:

               -  pharmacologic/hormonal contraceptives, including oral, parenteral, subcutaneous,
                  and transcutaneous delivery;

               -  condoms with spermicide;

               -  diaphragm with spermicide;

               -  intrauterine device;

               -  absolute abstinence from heterosexual intercourse as a matter of normal preferred
                  lifestyle;

               -  or must be surgically sterile, or must be age 50 AND have had no menses at all
                  for at least one full year.

               -  All females must provide samples for urine and serum pregnancy testing prior to
                  enrollment (immediately prior to each vaccination), as well as a statement of
                  menstrual history and a summary of all potentially reproductive sexual activity
                  for the month prior to each vaccination, and at each study contact throughout the
                  study, and report if they may be pregnant immediately.

          -  Willingness to refrain from blood donation during the course of the study

          -  Willingness to refrain from receiving other vaccines or investigational products
             during the first 4 months of the study after enrollment

          -  Willingness to follow admission and isolation requirements for the indicated duration
             per protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy as determined by a positive human choriogonadotropin (ß-HCG) test or history
             of recent unprotected intercourse in a woman of reproductive capacity

          -  Currently breastfeeding

          -  Evidence of clinically significant neurological, cardiac, pulmonary, hepatic,
             rheumatological, autoimmune, or renal disease by history, physical examination, and/or
             laboratory studies

          -  History of intranasal pathology or evidence of structural abnormalities of the sinuses
             or nasal cavity upon examination

          -  Behavioral or cognitive impairment or psychiatric disease that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, affects the subject's ability to understand and cooperate with the study
             protocol

          -  Positive urine drug toxicology test indicating narcotic use or history of dependency

          -  Have medical, occupational, or family problems as a result of alcohol or illicit drug
             use during the past 12 months

          -  Other condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would jeopardize the safety
             or rights of a subject participating in the trial, or would render the subject unable
             to comply with the protocol.

          -  History of anaphylaxis

          -  Current diagnosis of asthma or reactive airway disease (within the past 2 years)

          -  Current history of allergic rhinitis requiring the use of medication in the 2 weeks
             before enrollment or the first 56 days of the study

          -  History of Bell's palsy

          -  Positive enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) and confirmatory test (e.g.,
             Western blot or HIV-1/HIV-2 differentiation assay) for human immunodeficiency virus-1
             (HIV-1)

          -  Positive ELISA and confirmatory test (e.g., polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for virus)
             for hepatitis C virus (HCV)

          -  Positive hepatitis B virus surface antigen (HBsAg) by ELISA test

          -  Known immunodeficiency syndrome or history suggestive of impaired immune function

          -  Use of corticosteroids (excluding topical preparations) or immunosuppressive drugs
             within 30 days prior to vaccination

          -  Receipt of a live vaccine within 4 weeks or a killed vaccine within 2 weeks prior to
             study vaccination

          -  History of asplenia.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) less than 18.5 or greater than 40

          -  Receipt of blood or blood-derived products (including immunoglobulin) within 6 months
             prior to study vaccination

          -  Current tobacco user unwilling to refrain from smoking, snuffing, vaping, or chewing
             for the duration of the inpatient study (subjects may use nicotine patches if needed)

          -  Travel to an Ebola-endemic region at the time when cases were present or planned
             travel to West or Central Africa during the study period

          -  Receipt of another investigational vaccine or drug within 30 days prior to study
             vaccination

          -  Previous receipt of an investigational Ebola or Marburg virus vaccine, a chimpanzee
             adenovirus, or human parainfluenza virus (HPIV)-vectored vaccine, or any other
             investigational vaccine likely to affect interpretation of the trial data

          -  Current or past (in the last 4 weeks) user of intranasal medications (including
             steroids, decongestants, or hormonal medications), or planning to use them within 28
             days of study vaccination

          -  Live or have close contact with vulnerable individuals, including infants, the
             elderly, or immunocompromised individuals (those with HIV/AIDS, malignancy, or
             transplant patients)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kawsar Talaat, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Immunization Research, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel Adkinson</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-7283</phone>
      <email>radkins5@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kawsar Talaat</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-9627</phone>
      <email>ktalaat@jhu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CIR Inpatient Unit, Johns Hopkins Bayview Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel Adkinson</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-7283</phone>
      <email>radkins5@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kawsar Talaat</last_name>
      <phone>410-502-9627</phone>
      <email>ktalaat@jhu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhagic Fever, Ebola</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paramyxoviridae Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Krestin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

