<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03465735</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-008129</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03465735</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vascular Boot Warming Program After Acute Deep Vein Thrombosis (DVT) ± Pulmonary Embolism (PE)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Safety of Vascular Boot Warming Program After Acute DVT±PE for Earlier Resolution of VTE and Prevention of Post Thrombotic Syndrome: A Pilot Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Researchers are studying whether a vascular boot warming program plus standard of care
      anticoagulation can be a safe and effective method to resolve Deep Vein Thrombosis (DVT)
      ±Pulmonary Embolism (PE) earlier and prevent development of post-thrombotic syndrome (PTS).
      Additionally, to learn whether a more detailed imaging of the affected lower extremities will
      provide a more accurate and reliable method to guide treatment for this condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants with diagnosis of acute lower extremity DVT (proximal and distal) and/or
      pulmonary embolism will be identified and approached for participation, when they are seen in
      the Thrombophilia Clinic or Mayo Hospital for management of the acute VTE. If they match the
      preset inclusion and exclusion criteria, they would then be consented during this visit and
      scheduled for baseline studies at a later date. Baseline tests include Venous
      plethysmorgraphy, Lower Extremity Ultrasound, and Medical history, will be conducted and if
      eligible, participant will then be randomized to vascular boot plus standard anti coagulation
      program or standard anti coagulation using a randomization program. Participants will be
      randomized into two groups and followed for 3 months. Standard of Care (SOC) Group (no
      vascular boot utilized): Patients will receive standard anticoagulation (determined at
      discretion of the treating provider), baseline studies, and follow up at the end of treatment
      (3months). Vascular Boot (VB) Group (includes vascular boot in addition to SOC): Patients
      will receive standard anticoagulation (determined at discretion of the treating provider),
      baseline studies and standardized vascular boot warming. All patients randomized to this
      group will wear the vascular boot for a minimum of 30 minutes per day for the first 10 days
      of participation. Patients in this group may initially be enrolled at either the
      thrombophilia clinic or the hospital.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in affected leg pain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Affected leg pain measured on a 0-10 scale. 0 indicating No pain and 10 indicating Worst Possible Pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute DVT of Lower Extremity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ultrasound of the leg with DVT and leg circumference measurement at 3 days, 10 days, and 3 months. Ultrasound data will include data on thrombus resolution, such as size and recanalization present.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vascular Boot Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>For each vascular boot session, the following data will be recorded:
Wearing the vascular boot during first 10 days of study for minimum of 30 minutes per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vascular Boot</intervention_name>
    <description>The Vascular Boot is one size fits all, insulated fleece padding, and cell foam to enhance and maintain lower limb warmth while maintaining no pressure points on the lower extremity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vascular Boot Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rooke Boot</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Anticoagulant therapy will be decided by physician and patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vascular Boot Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Heparin</other_name>
    <other_name>Enoxaparin (Lovenox)</other_name>
    <other_name>Dalteparin (Fragmin)</other_name>
    <other_name>Warfarin (Coumadin, Jantoven)</other_name>
    <other_name>Dabigatran (Pradaxa)</other_name>
    <other_name>Rivaroxaban (Xarelto)</other_name>
    <other_name>Apixaban (Eliquis)</other_name>
    <other_name>Edoxaban (Savaysa)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to tolerate wearing a vascular boot, if randomized to this group.

          -  Diagnosis of acute DVT±PE (within 24 - 48 hours) and received approximately 24 hours
             of anticoagulation prior to starting the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to tolerate wearing a vascular boot

          -  Unable to comply with keeping log of activity/ of wearing a vascular boot.

          -  Weight &gt; 300 pounds. (weight limit for the venous plethysmography chair)

          -  Previous history of DVT or PE.

          -  On anticoagulation for another purpose (example stroke prevention with atrial
             fibrillation).

          -  Patients who do not accept to participate in research studies.

          -  Pregnant women will not be allowed to participate

          -  Patients less than 18 yrs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Waldemar E Wysokinski, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heit JA. The epidemiology of venous thromboembolism in the community. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2008 Mar;28(3):370-2. doi: 10.1161/ATVBAHA.108.162545. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18296591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Venous thromboembolism in adult hospitalizations - United States, 2007-2009. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2012 Jun 8;61(22):401-4.</citation>
    <PMID>22672974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heit JA, Crusan DJ, Ashrani AA, Petterson TM, Bailey KR. Venous thromboembolism attack rates among recently hospitalized vs. community residents: a population-based cohort study. JAMA. 2015 in submission.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heit JA, Ashrani AA, Crusan DJ, Petterson TM, Bailey KR. Trends in venous thromboembolism incidence, 1981-2010: a population-based cohort study. JAMA. 2015, in submission.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kahn SR, Comerota AJ, Cushman M, Evans NS, Ginsberg JS, Goldenberg NA, Gupta DK, Prandoni P, Vedantham S, Walsh ME, Weitz JI; American Heart Association Council on Peripheral Vascular Disease, Council on Clinical Cardiology, and Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing. The postthrombotic syndrome: evidence-based prevention, diagnosis, and treatment strategies: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2014 Oct 28;130(18):1636-61. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000130. Epub 2014 Sep 22. Erratum in: Circulation. 2015 Feb 24;131(8):e359.</citation>
    <PMID>25246013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kahn SR, Shapiro S, Wells PS, Rodger MA, Kovacs MJ, Anderson DR, Tagalakis V, Houweling AH, Ducruet T, Holcroft C, Johri M, Solymoss S, Miron MJ, Yeo E, Smith R, Schulman S, Kassis J, Kearon C, Chagnon I, Wong T, Demers C, Hanmiah R, Kaatz S, Selby R, Rathbun S, Desmarais S, Opatrny L, Ortel TL, Ginsberg JS; SOX trial investigators. Compression stockings to prevent post-thrombotic syndrome: a randomised placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2014 Mar 8;383(9920):880-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61902-9. Epub 2013 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24315521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'shaughnessy AM, Fitzgerald DE. The patterns and distribution of residual abnormalities between the individual proximal venous segments after an acute deep vein thrombosis. J Vasc Surg. 2001 Feb;33(2):379-84.</citation>
    <PMID>11174793</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Killewich LA, Macko RF, Cox K, Franklin DR, Benjamin ME, Lilly MP, Flinn WR. Regression of proximal deep venous thrombosis is associated with fibrinolytic enhancement. J Vasc Surg. 1997 Nov;26(5):861-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9372826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Killewich LA, Bedford GR, Beach KW, Strandness DE Jr. Spontaneous lysis of deep venous thrombi: rate and outcome. J Vasc Surg. 1989 Jan;9(1):89-97.</citation>
    <PMID>2911146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Ramshorst B, van Bemmelen PS, Hoeneveld H, Faber JA, Eikelboom BC. Thrombus regression in deep venous thrombosis. Quantification of spontaneous thrombolysis with duplex scanning. Circulation. 1992 Aug;86(2):414-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1638710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caprini JA, Arcelus JI, Hoffman KN, Size G, Laubach M, Traverso CI, Coats R, Finke N, Reyna JJ. Venous duplex imaging follow-up of acute symptomatic deep vein thrombosis of the leg. J Vasc Surg. 1995 Mar;21(3):472-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7877229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meyer G, Vicaut E, Danays T, Agnelli G, Becattini C, Beyer-Westendorf J, Bluhmki E, Bouvaist H, Brenner B, Couturaud F, Dellas C, Empen K, Franca A, Galiè N, Geibel A, Goldhaber SZ, Jimenez D, Kozak M, Kupatt C, Kucher N, Lang IM, Lankeit M, Meneveau N, Pacouret G, Palazzini M, Petris A, Pruszczyk P, Rugolotto M, Salvi A, Schellong S, Sebbane M, Sobkowicz B, Stefanovic BS, Thiele H, Torbicki A, Verschuren F, Konstantinides SV; PEITHO Investigators. Fibrinolysis for patients with intermediate-risk pulmonary embolism. N Engl J Med. 2014 Apr 10;370(15):1402-11. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1302097.</citation>
    <PMID>24716681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piazza G, Hohlfelder B, Jaff MR, Ouriel K, Engelhardt TC, Sterling KM, Jones NJ, Gurley JC, Bhatheja R, Kennedy RJ, Goswami N, Natarajan K, Rundback J, Sadiq IR, Liu SK, Bhalla N, Raja ML, Weinstock BS, Cynamon J, Elmasri FF, Garcia MJ, Kumar M, Ayerdi J, Soukas P, Kuo W, Liu PY, Goldhaber SZ; SEATTLE II Investigators. A Prospective, Single-Arm, Multicenter Trial of Ultrasound-Facilitated, Catheter-Directed, Low-Dose Fibrinolysis for Acute Massive and Submassive Pulmonary Embolism: The SEATTLE II Study. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2015 Aug 24;8(10):1382-92. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2015.04.020.</citation>
    <PMID>26315743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ogawa T, Hoshino S, Midorikawa H, Sato K. Intermittent pneumatic compression of the foot and calf improves the outcome of catheter-directed thrombolysis using low-dose urokinase in patients with acute proximal venous thrombosis of the leg. J Vasc Surg. 2005 Nov;42(5):940-4.</citation>
    <PMID>16275451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy TP, Cutlip DE, Regensteiner JG, Mohler ER, Cohen DJ, Reynolds MR, Massaro JM, Lewis BA, Cerezo J, Oldenburg NC, Thum CC, Goldberg S, Jaff MR, Steffes MW, Comerota AJ, Ehrman J, Treat-Jacobson D, Walsh ME, Collins T, Badenhop DT, Bronas U, Hirsch AT; CLEVER Study Investigators. Supervised exercise versus primary stenting for claudication resulting from aortoiliac peripheral artery disease: six-month outcomes from the claudication: exercise versus endoluminal revascularization (CLEVER) study. Circulation. 2012 Jan 3;125(1):130-9. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.075770. Epub 2011 Nov 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22090168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Recek C. Calf pump activity influencing venous hemodynamics in the lower extremity. Int J Angiol. 2013 Mar;22(1):23-30. doi: 10.1055/s-0033-1334092. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24436580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Labropoulos N, Giannoukas AD, Nicolaides AN, Veller M, Leon M, Volteas N. The role of venous reflux and calf muscle pump function in nonthrombotic chronic venous insufficiency. Correlation with severity of signs and symptoms. Arch Surg. 1996 Apr;131(4):403-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8615726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kahn SR, Azoulay L, Hirsch A, Haber M, Strulovitch C, Shrier I. Acute effects of exercise in patients with previous deep venous thrombosis: impact of the postthrombotic syndrome. Chest. 2003 Feb;123(2):399-405.</citation>
    <PMID>12576357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shrier I, Kahn SR. Effect of physical activity after recent deep venous thrombosis: a cohort study. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2005 Apr;37(4):630-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15809562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Waldemar E. Wysokinski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deep</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary</keyword>
  <keyword>Venous</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular</keyword>
  <keyword>Post</keyword>
  <keyword>Vein</keyword>
  <keyword>Thrombosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Embolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Thromboembolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Thrombotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Postthrombotic Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

