<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03461315</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P17/121</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03461315</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparative Study Between Two Models of Home Care.</brief_title>
  <official_title>&quot;COMPARATIVE STUDY OF TWO MODELS OF PREVENTIVE HOME VISITS &quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Badalona Serveis Assistencials</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rosa Maria Sequera Requero</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sebastià J. Santaeugènia González</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Francisco José Tarazona Santabalbina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Badalona Serveis Assistencials</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Home care is the assistance provided at home to those who can not travel to their Health
      Center. There are multiple studies on models of home care and many discrepancies about the
      impact that preventive home visits can have. Hypothesis: home care is expected to be better
      if performed by a team dedicated exclusively to the home patient, than to the traditional
      model, where the patient is assisted by the team that cares for the rest of the community.

      Goals:

      Main: determine the difference in median cumulative days of hospital admission in 12 months.

      Secondaries:

        -  results in health

        -  in health experience in efficiency Methodology: Quasi-experimental study of two years
           duration. All the subjects included in the Home Care Program and that meet the inclusion
           and exclusion criteria are studied. The care team will provide the informed consent and
           information sheet to the patient and clinical scales at the beginning and end of the
           study. Researchers will be responsible for the collection of data that they will
           anonymize and guard. Statistical analysis: The analyzes will be calculated with the
           statistical package SPSS version 21 Expected results: hospital admissions (25%) and
           cumulative days by admission and patient by 65% are expected to improve in the model
           under study. Applicability and relevance: the trend towards a greater aging of the
           population makes it necessary to study models of care that allow us to detect which can
           be beneficial to the population and feasible in our current context.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our purpose will be to compare 2 models of home care corresponding to 2

      Primary Care Centers (EAP):

        -  Model integrated (EAP Gran Sol), traditional, continuity, made by the UBA with care of
           the home patient by the usual care team (family physician and nurse)

        -  Model functional (EAP Apenins), based on the internal reorganization of the EAP:
           equipment specific home care program composed of family physician and nurse, with
           dedication exclusively to Preventive home visits, with training aimed at excellence in
           the Management of fragile patients with pluripathology and palliative care.

      HYPOTHESIS. A care group dedicated exclusively to the ATDOM patient with what it entails in
      dedication of time and specific knowledge could get better results in health, optimize health
      resources and at the same time achieve greater satisfaction and quality of life to these
      patients. That is why our hypothesis will be that it is expected that the patient's global
      assistance attended from Primary Care in your home is better if it is performed by a Primary
      Care team trained for it with exclusive dedication to this type of patient, that, with the
      traditional model, where the patient that is attended at home is assisted by the clinical
      team that serves the rest of the community.

      OBJECTIVES Main objective The main objective will be the comparison of the two models of home
      care in Primary care previously described by the difference in the average number of days
      hospitalized for 12 months among the people served in an integrated model of home care and
      among those served in a functional model. 3.2 Secondary objectives We will analyze them under
      a triple vision AIM, triple goal, better health, better care, lower costs, -effectiveness,
      efficiency and experience in people's health-

        -  Results in health: comparison in mortality at 12 months and integral geriatric
           assessment.

        -  Results in experience in health care and quality of life:

      Comparison of both models in terms of self-perception in patients' health included in the
      preventive home care program, the patient's experience in attention to their health and
      overload of the caregiver.

      -Results in efficiency and resource utilization: comparison in professional assistance,
      consumption of intermediate resources, consumption of social products, quality in the
      prescription.

      METHODOLOGY OF THE STUDY.

        -  Design of the study. It is a quasi-experimental study of 2 population samples. The group
           of study is composed of the sample of subjects treated with the home care model
           exclusive and expert. The control group is made up of the subjects that are treated with
           the model of traditional home care. The study is expected to have a duration of 2 years
           that will be the time of follow-up of each participant, being able present the
           possibility of doing later substudies.

        -  Population under study. Justification of the choice of the comparator. The integrated
           model of home care that is implemented in EAP Gran Sol is compared with the proposed new
           functional model that includes a team of family doctor and nurse dedicated exclusively
           to patient care included in the home care program and who have received specific
           training. This intervention has been carried out in EAP Apenins since 2013.

      To the subjects of this obtained sample, a telephone call will be made inviting them to
      participate in the study, agreeing a visit by the doctor or nurse responsible for the patient
      and the subject of the project will be informed. In the agreed view, will give the informed
      consent and the information sheet to the patient. Once signed in informed consent by the
      subject or in case of patients with deterioration cognitive, by the caregiver, the
      self-administered scales EuroQOL and IEXPACto the patient, in the case of patients with
      cognitive impairment, at caregiver and the Zarit questionnaire to the main caregiver so that
      complete They will be given an envelope to enter the completed scales that will be delivered
      closed to the healthcare professional. Fragility will be measured with instrument of
      Gérontopole at that time. These scales will be redelivered the patient and the caregiver at
      the end of the study, after 2 years, with the same methodology.

      It is considered inevitable that professionals know how to measure themselves since they have
      their collaboration for the delivery of informed consent and information sheet to patient and
      the EuroQol, IEXPAC and Zarit scales and calculation of fragility index.

      There will be 2 training sessions for healthcare professionals on the project of the study
      and the use of the scales they will deliver. Losses of selection of the sample are considered
      to the subjects or main caregivers, in the case of subjects with cognitive impairment, who do
      not sign informed consent.

      Every 6 months the researchers will contact the subjects by telephone participants of the
      study (each of their Primary Care Center) and on that call will proceed to question about
      possible admission to private hospitals, stay in day centers or answer questions or provide
      information about the study. Study groups.

      They are the following:

      A control group of patients included in the Home Care program of the ABS Gran Sol where11
      healthcare teams work with 241 patients in total in the Home care program (date December
      2016) And a study group, of patients included in the Home Care program of ABS Apenins, the
      which have a healthcare team that works exclusively for home care with 113 patients (date
      December 2016) Study sample. Patients will be included who are in the Home care program and
      who comply with the Inclusion and exclusion criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Quasi-experimental study .</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>difference in the average of days hospitalized for 12 months among the people served in an integrated model of home care and among those served in a functional model.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">354</enrollment>
  <condition>Managed Care Program</condition>
  <condition>Home Care</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional Mode</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Traditional Model: Team That Cares for the Rest of the Community</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Model</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study Model:Team Dedicated Exclusively to the Home Patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Functional assistance model</intervention_name>
    <description>Preventive home visits carried out by a Team Dedicated Exclusively to the Home Patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Model</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -Patients of 65 or more years, with or without cognitive impairment, that during the period
        of recruitment are new or existing users in a home care program long duration of the
        centers participants.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  the patients who have a life expectancy of less than 1 month, considering that
             provides information for this study and may not be appropriate for the patient and the
             operating system relatives

          -  patients with Pfeiffer index mayor or equal to 5 without primary caregiver or with a
             partial caregiver, since we consider that with moderate cognitive impairment or severe
             will not be able to answer self-administered questionnaires.

          -  the patients included in the home care program for the performance of cures or
             treatments that 3 months (Transient home care Program).

          -  the patients who have been in the home care program for less than 1 month at the time
             of their recruitment, since we believe that there has not yet been time to carry out a
             comprehensive assessment of the patient.

          -  the patients included in the home care program who are not registered in Badalona
             because they are temporarily in the home of a family member.

          -  the patients included in the home care Program due to the existence of barriers
             architectures to go to the Primary Care Center.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carolina Burgos Diez</last_name>
    <phone>34 647681373</phone>
    <email>carolinaburgosdiez@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sebastià Santaeugènia González</last_name>
    <phone>34 633896522</phone>
    <email>sebastia.santaeugenia@gencat.cat</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Badalona Serveis Assistencials</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carolina Burgos Diez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Family physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>home care</keyword>
  <keyword>primary care</keyword>
  <keyword>preventive home visits</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

