<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03464253</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4372/25-2-2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03464253</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prediction of Post-dural Puncture Headache in Parturients Undergoing Elective Caesarean Section</brief_title>
  <official_title>Transcranial Doppler Role in Prediction of Post-dural Puncture Headache in Parturients Undergoing Elective Caesarean Section</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Zagazig University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Zagazig University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The parturients are at particular risk of post dural puncture headache (PDPH) because of
      their sex, young age, and the widespread application of spinal and epidural anesthesia. PDPH
      has a negative impact on quality of life, patient satisfaction, the postpartum experience
      with the mother's inability to bond with and care for her baby and it increases the economic
      burden associated with childbirth. Therefore, it is necessary to prevent or decrease its
      incidence and severity.

      TCD enables measurement of the blood flow velocity in intracranial arteries and its
      parameters are affected by both fluctuations in intracranial pressure and changes in cerebral
      vessel diameters. The possibility of equipment mobilization, the opportunity of repeated
      bedside technique together with the noninvasive nature, makes TCD measurements attractive in
      the attempt to estimate CBF and offers potential application to predict and follow patients
      with PDPH.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PDPH is described as severe &quot;searing and spreading like hot metal&quot; distributed over the
      occipital and frontal areas radiating to the neck and shoulders. 90% of headache will occur
      within three days of the procedure, and 66% within the first 48 hours. The PDPH rarely
      develops between 5 and 14 days after the technique however it may immediately occur after
      dural puncture but it is rare and should pay attention of the physician to alternative
      causes. The pain is increased by head movement, upright posture and relieved by lying down.
      It resolves either spontaneously within 7 days or within 48 h after effective treatment which
      is usually consists of fluid therapy, analgesics, sumatriptan and caffeine. Epidural blood
      patch remained the gold standard therapy but it is an invasive technique.

      The exact etiology of PDPH is unknown; there is two hypothesis attempts to explain the cause.
      First it's known that dural tear leads to cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) leak and decreased volume
      of CSF result in intracranial hypotension which cause on pain sensitive intracranial
      structures that become stretched when assuming upright position result in pain. Second,
      intracranial volume is constant and equal to the sum of intracranial blood, CSF, and brain
      matter. After loss of CSF a compensatory reflex vasodilatation occur in the same pain
      sensitive blood vessels and this result in pain.

      The association of common risk factors like female gender, particularly females during
      pregnancy, age groups of 20 - 40 years, a prior history of chronic headache, and a lower body
      mass index expose the patient to PDPH. The identification of factors that predict the
      likelihood of PDPH is important so that measures can be taken to minimize this painful
      complication resulting from spinal anesthesia.

      Transcranial Doppler ultrasound (TCD) is a portable, safe, noninvasive and real-time tool for
      assessing intracranial blood hemodynamics. The first description of the technique was by Rune
      Aaslid in early 20th century and it has gained increasing acceptance as an accurate
      diagnostic and therapeutic tool in both cerebrovascular disease and neurocritical care. TCD
      enables measurement of the blood flow velocity in intracranial arteries and several Studies
      have shown that its parameters are affected by both fluctuations in intracranial pressure and
      changes in cerebral vessel diameters. So, as PDPH may be resulted from significant changes in
      cerebral blood flow, it could be visualized by TCD.

      The possibility of equipment mobilization, the opportunity of repeated bedside technique
      together with the noninvasive nature, makes TCD measurements attractive in the attempt to
      estimate CBF and offers potential application to predict and follow patients with PDPH.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>5 Days</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>TCD is able to predict the occurrence of PDPH in female patients undergoing spinal anesthesia for elective Caesarean Section</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>The group of patients who developed PDPH will be identified and their pre puncture cerebral blood flow measurements by TCD will be compared with the corresponding measurements of PDPH free patients to correlate the pre-puncture measurements with the occurrence of PDPH.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>verify that lumber puncture in PDPH patients leads to significant changes in cerebral blood flow supporting the theory of cerebral vasodilatation in PDPH patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>The post-puncture TCD measurements will be compared to verify that lumber puncture and CSF leak leads to reflex vasodilatation in PDPH patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Postdural Puncture Headache</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Performance of the transcranial Doppler (TCD)</intervention_name>
    <description>Within 24 hour before the operation, TCD is performed using Siemens Acuson X300 machine with ultrasound frequency is 1 - 5 MHz probe to measure Mean Velocity and Pulsatility Index in the right middle cerebral artery.postoperatively, TCD study is performed twice at 24h and 48h after spinal anesthesia. For 5 days postoperatively, the Patients are assessed clinically for the occurrence of headache. Patients who developed PDPH will be identified and their pre and post puncture measurements will be compared with the corresponding measurements of PDPH free patients.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pregnant female undergoing Elective caesarean section under spinal anesthesia.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient acceptance.

          -  Pregnant female undergoing Elective caesarean section under spinal anesthesia.

          -  Age 18-40 years old.

          -  ASA I and ASA II.

          -  Accepted mental state of the patient.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient refusal.

          -  Contraindications to regional anesthesia as local infection, coagulopathy,….etc

          -  ASA Grade 3 and 4.

          -  Emergent caesarean section.

          -  Inadequate temporal window.

          -  Hypertensive disorders of the pregnancy.

          -  Atrial fibrillation.

          -  Significant fetal illness.

          -  History of allergy to local anesthetics.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shereen E Abd Ellatif, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care Department, faculty of medicine, Zagazig University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sherif MS Mowafy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care Department, faculty of medicine, Zagazig University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sherif MS Mowafy, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01003523374</phone>
    <phone_ext>002</phone_ext>
    <email>sherifmowafy2012@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shereen E Abd Ellatif, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01007948840</phone>
    <phone_ext>002</phone_ext>
    <email>shosh.again@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zagazig University Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zagazig</city>
        <state>Sharkia</state>
        <zip>44111</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shereen E Abd Ellatif, MD</last_name>
      <phone>01007948840</phone>
      <phone_ext>002</phone_ext>
      <email>shosh.again@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sherif MS Mowafy, MD</last_name>
      <phone>01003523374</phone>
      <phone_ext>002</phone_ext>
      <email>sherifmowafy2012@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohammed EL and El Shal SM. Efficacy of different size Quincke spinal needles in reduction of incidence of Post-Dural Puncture Headache (PDPH) in Caesarean Section (CS). Randomized controlled study. Egyptian Journal of Anaesthesia 33: 53-58, 2017</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah A, Bhatia PK, Tulsiani KL. Post dural puncture headache in caesarean section-a comparative study using 25G Quincke, 27G Quincke and 27G Whitacre needle. Indian J Anaesth 46(5):373-377, 2002</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bardon J, LE Ray C, Samama CM, Bonnet MP. Risk factors of post-dural puncture headache receiving a blood patch in obstetric patients. Minerva Anestesiol. 2016 Jun;82(6):641-8. Epub 2015 Jul 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26222393</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sachs A, Smiley R. Post-dural puncture headache: the worst common complication in obstetric anesthesia. Semin Perinatol. 2014 Oct;38(6):386-94. doi: 10.1053/j.semperi.2014.07.007. Epub 2014 Aug 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25146108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turnbull DK, Shepherd DB. Post-dural puncture headache: pathogenesis, prevention and treatment. Br J Anaesth. 2003 Nov;91(5):718-29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14570796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kracoff SL and Kotlovker V. Post Dural Puncture Headache—Review and Suggested New Treatment. Open Journal of Anesthesiology 6: 148-163, 2016</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Venturelli PM, Brunser AM, Gaete J, et al. Reliability of Hand-Held Transcranial Doppler with M-mode Ultrasound in Middle Cerebral Artery Measurement. Journal of Medical Ultrasound 25: 76-81, 2017</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vadhera RB, Babazade R, Suresh MS, Alvarado MC, Cruz AL, Belfort MA. Role of transcranial Doppler measurements in postpartum patients with post-dural puncture headache: a pilot study. Int J Obstet Anesth. 2017 Feb;29:90-91. doi: 10.1016/j.ijoa.2016.10.010. Epub 2016 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28012860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nowaczewska M, Książkiewicz B. Cerebral blood flow characteristics in patients with post-lumbar puncture headache. J Neurol. 2012 Apr;259(4):665-9. doi: 10.1007/s00415-011-6236-1. Epub 2011 Sep 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21935623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Zagazig University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sherif M. S. Mowafy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>lecturer of Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Post-Dural Puncture Headache</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>all IPD that underlie results in a publication</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

