<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03460847</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>29-316 ex 16/17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03460847</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fecal Microbiota Alterations in Steroid Refractory Active Colitis Ulcerosa</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can Fecal Microbiota Alterations Predict a Refractory Disease Course to Standard Steroid Therapy in Patients With Active Ulcerative Colitis?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Graz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Alterations in the intestinal microbiota have been associated to disease pathogenesis in
      ulcerative colitis. Refractory disease to standard medical therapy as corticosteroids often
      leads to an unfavourable course in patients suffering from this disorder. This study proposal
      aims at investigating changes in the intestinal microbiota that can predict a therapy
      refractory course of ulcerative colitis (UC) and may be used to identify high risk patients
      in an early phase of their disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Investigators suggest that certain alterations in the intestinal microbiota are at least
      in part responsible for the inability of some patients to response to steroid therapy and
      probably also for the failure to other immunosuppressive therapies. Certain pathobionts have
      the capability to stimulate the mucosal immune system, thereby leading to chronic
      inflammation. On the other hand, commensals are necessary for repair processes in the mucosa
      and are providing metabolites that are used as an energy source for the colonic epithelium.
      An increase in pathobionts in combination with a lack of certain commensals might therefore
      maintain colonic inflammation despite immunosuppressive therapy with systemic steroids in
      patients with UC.

      The investigators therefore plan to investigate the intestinal microbiota in UC patients
      before and 4 weeks after a systemic corticosteroid therapy and correlate potential
      alterations of the microbiota to the therapeutic response. Other factors like concomitant UC
      treatment, disease severity, disease extent and environmental factors will also be correlated
      to changes in the microbiota.

      In the subgroup of patients not responding to steroids and requiring a rescue therapy with
      infliximab or a calcineurin Inhibitor, the predictive value of microbiota alterations will
      also be investigated.

      If certain bacterial taxa can predict a steroid refractory and an unfavorable disease course,
      the results of this study will help in identifying possible microbiota based biomarkers for
      an individualized treatment approach in UC patients in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiota alterations</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>To assess if alterations of the fecal microbiota are associated with a failure to respond to steroid therapy within 28 days in patients with ulcerative colitis. The microbiota will be assessed by 16s RNA analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Colitis, Ulcerative</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Steroids</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with active colitis ulcerosa who need steroids because of their disease course. 1mg/kg bodyweight for one week, followed by a tapping periode.</description>
    <other_name>Aprednisolon, Prednisolut</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Stool samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients suffering from an active colitis ulcerosa and requiring steroids as therapy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Active ulcerative colitis with a Lichtiger score ≥4

          -  Patient scheduled for steroid therapy with systemic steroids (prednisolone or
             methylprednisolone) at standard dosing and patients who started steroid therapy not
             longer than 48 hours prior to the study inclusion.

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Established or suspected diagnosis of ulcerative colitis or indeterminate colitis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No follow up possible

          -  Bacterial intestinal infections (C. difficile, Salmonella, EHEC, Campylobacter,
             Shigella, Yersinia), parasitic or viral infection causing acute infectious diarrhea at
             baseline.

          -  Diagnosis of Crohn´s disease

          -  Planned initiation or discontinuation of probiotic therapy between baseline and follow
             up visit
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christoph Hoegenauer, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of Graz</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christoph Hoegenauer, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>0043385-000</phone>
    <email>christoph.hoegenauer@medunigraz.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andreas Blesl, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>0043385-000</phone>
    <email>andreas.blesl@medunigraz.at</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

