<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03464162</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>7597</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03464162</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>OnTrackNY With the Option of Social Network Meetings</brief_title>
  <official_title>OnTrackNY With the Option of Social Network Meetings</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lisa Dixon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York State Psychiatric Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Early intervention programs for psychosis help improve short-term treatment and recovery
      outcomes for individuals experiencing psychosis. OnTrackNY is a coordinated specialty care
      (CSC) program, developed to treat young adults within two years of experiencing a
      non-affective episode of psychosis. This project aims to expand the role of family engagement
      and support within the OnTrackNY model. Borrowing from the Needs Adapted and Open Dialogue
      models, the study team created a family therapy service that includes the client and members
      of his/her social network to navigate crises and assist in treatment planning. This service,
      Social Network Meetings, will be offered to individuals enrolled in the OnTrackNY@MHA program
      as an additional, voluntary, service option. The study proposes that the introduction of
      Social Network meetings may improve treatment and recovery outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project aims to expand the role of family engagement and support within the OnTrackNY
      model by offering a new service, Social Network Meetings. The study team will offer Social
      Network Meetings to individuals enrolled in the OnTrackNY@MHA program as an additional
      service option. This option will be completely voluntary and available for a 12 month period.
      Participant entrance into the study will be staggered with no more than approximately 5
      individuals in the Social Network group and no more than 5 individuals not in the Social
      Network group enrolled each month. Participants will choose which group they would like to be
      in, if any. Data will be collected for all participants, both those participating and not
      participating in the Social Network Meetings upon entering the study and then once every
      three months and at the end of their time in the study. For all participants, the study will
      end after 6 months of participation.

      Meetings may occur as often as 3 times a week when there is a crisis or more commonly would
      occur once every other week. These meetings will last between 60 and 90 minutes and will take
      place for however long the clients and their social networks would like within the project
      period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 11, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 20, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 20, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will choose if they want to receive Social Network Meetings or be in a group that does not receive Social Network Meetings. Entrance of clients into the study will be staggered with no more than approximately 5 individuals in the Social Network group and no more than 5 individuals not in the Social Network group enrolled each month. There will be a maximum of 15 participants (clients) in each group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in score on the Questionnaire about the Process of Recovery (QPR) from baseline to 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>We will measure scores at baseline, 3 months and 6 months to determine change between these assessment points</time_frame>
    <description>The QPR is a 15-item self-report survey which assesses individuals' perceptions of self and factors that are important to recovery. Items on the QPR are rated on a 5-point Likert scale and range from &quot;disagree strongly&quot; to &quot;agree strongly.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in score on the SCORE-15 Index of Family Functioning and Change (SCORE-15) from baseline to 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>We will measure scores at baseline, 3 months and 6 months to determine change between these assessment points</time_frame>
    <description>The SCORE-15 is a 15-item self-report survey which assesses perceptions about a family's level of intimacy and support for one another. It asks both clients and social network members to give impressions about the level of disclosure between family members, perceptions of trust, and how the family deals conflict and crisis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Satisfaction Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>We developed a brief 5-item survey that will ask clients and social network members about their satisfaction with the Social Network Meetings.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>First Episode Psychosis</condition>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Social Network Meetings Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will receive Social Network Meetings for a 6 month period. Meetings may occur as often as 3 times a week when there is a crisis or more commonly would occur once every other week. These meetings will last between 60 and 90 minutes and will take place for however long the clients and their social networks would like within the project period. Ideally, each client and his/her Social Network would participate in 4 meetings during the 6 month period. This group would continue to receive care as usual with the addition of these meetings.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Social Network Meetings Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will not receive the Social Network Meetings intervention. Clients in this arm will participate in the study for 6 months and receive care as usual during this time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Social Network Meetings</intervention_name>
    <description>Social Network Meetings are a type of family therapy that includes clients and members of their social network.The social network may include family members, friends or anyone else that clients believe can help them move toward recovery. The meetings will focus on improving communication within the social network.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Social Network Meetings Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Subject Population 1: OnTrackNY MHA Client- Social Network Meeting Group (ages 16-30)

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages 16-30

          -  Currently enrolled, clinically stable, English speaking clients in the OnTrackNY
             program at MHA Westchester determined my client roster for MHA Westchester program and
             clinical judgment

          -  Willingness to participate in Social Network meetings determined by self-report as
             asked by clinician

          -  Willingness to complete brief baseline and quarterly assessments determined by
             self-report as asked by clinician

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anyone who the OnTrackNY team determines is clinically unstable determined by
             clinician assessment

          -  Clients who are unwilling to participate in Social Network meetings determined by
             self-report

        Subject Population 2: OnTrackNY MHA Client- No Social Network Meeting Group (ages 16-30)

        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Ages 16-30

          -  Currently enrolled clients in the OnTrackNY program at MHA Westchester determined by
             MHA Westchester Client Roster for OnTrackNY

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anyone who the OnTrackNY team determines is clinically unstable determined by
             clinician assessment

        Subject Population 3: Social Network Member (ages 18+)

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be 18 years or older

          -  English speaking member of social network (i.e., biological or chosen family member/s)
             of a currently enrolled client in the OnTrackNY program at MHA Westchester who has
             agreed to participate in the study determined by client self-report

          -  Willingness to complete brief baseline and quarterly assessments determined by social
             network member self-report

          -  Willingness to participate in social network meetings determined by social network
             member self-report

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Family members who the client does not want involved in the social network meetings
             determined by client self-report
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa Dixon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-774-8420</phone>
    <email>Lisa.Dixon@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sacha Zilkha, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>646-774-8469</phone>
    <email>sacha.zilkha@nyspi.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kane JM, Robinson DG, Schooler NR, Mueser KT, Penn DL, Rosenheck RA, Addington J, Brunette MF, Correll CU, Estroff SE, Marcy P, Robinson J, Meyer-Kalos PS, Gottlieb JD, Glynn SM, Lynde DW, Pipes R, Kurian BT, Miller AL, Azrin ST, Goldstein AB, Severe JB, Lin H, Sint KJ, John M, Heinssen RK. Comprehensive Versus Usual Community Care for First-Episode Psychosis: 2-Year Outcomes From the NIMH RAISE Early Treatment Program. Am J Psychiatry. 2016 Apr 1;173(4):362-72. doi: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2015.15050632. Epub 2015 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>26481174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hamilton E, Carr A. Systematic Review of Self-Report Family Assessment Measures. Fam Process. 2016 Mar;55(1):16-30. doi: 10.1111/famp.12200. Epub 2015 Nov 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26582601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neil, S. T., Kilbride, M., Pitt, L., Nothard, S., Welford, M., Sellwood, W., &amp; Morrison, A. P. (2009). The Questionnaire about the Process of Recovery: A measurement tool developed in collaboration with service users. Psychosis: Psychological, Social and Integrative Approaches, 1(2), 145-155.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York State Psychiatric Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lisa Dixon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Social Network Meetings</keyword>
  <keyword>First Episode Psychosis</keyword>
  <keyword>OnTrackNY</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

