<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02425410</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AOM 10061</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02425410</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Analysis of Viral Infections' Exposition Preceding the Type 1 Diabetes (T1D) Diagnostic in Children of the Isis-Diab Cohort. Search for Explanations of of the Disease's Early Onset</brief_title>
  <acronym>ISIS-VIRUS</acronym>
  <official_title>Analysis of Viral Infections' Exposition Preceding the Type 1 Diabetes (T1D) Diagnostic in Children of the Isis-Diab Cohort. Search for Explanations of of the Disease's Early Onset</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre National de Génotypage</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate viral factors determining the early onset of T1D.
      Thanks to the quantification of viral exposures of T1D patients before the disease onset with
      questionnaires and environmental databases analyses, and through whole genome association
      studies of these patients, investigators could attempt to identify gene-virus interactions
      determining the age of T1D onset.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The &quot;hygiene hypothesis&quot;, which has been proposed to explain the observed increase of the
      incidence of T1D, relies on experimental evidence acquired in mouse models. However,
      epidemiological data are still lacking to validate this hypothesis in man. This is critical,
      because -in opposition with the hygiene hypothesis- there are many reasons to believe that,
      at contrary, certain virus can trigger the disease.

      Genetic predisposition to a severe infection form (particularly primary infection) was
      demonstrated for several infectious diseases (Casanova JL, Science 317:617-619, 2007;
      Casanova JL, EMBO J 26:915-922, 2007). It usually corresponds to deficiencies in genes
      involved in the host's immune response, the transmission of which being Mendelian. Genetic
      factors affect the ability of enteroviruses and other viruses to damage beta cells and to
      induce diabetes. Recently, Nejentsev et al have demonstrated a link between enteroviruses and
      diabetes genes: they have indeed identified 4 rare IFIH1 polymorphisms that reduce the T1D
      risk. However, this gene encodes an enzyme recognizing the DNA enterovirus, causing immunity
      activation; mutations inhibit gene activation. Except one study on HIV-1, there is to our
      knowledge no genome wide association studies (GWAS) in humans on the role of host's genetic
      polymorphisms in the risk of infection, clinical expression, duration of viral shedding, or
      response to therapy or to anti-viral vaccines.

      We relied on our cohort of T1D children (Isis-Diab) to investigate the possible relation
      between viral exposures, genetic polymorphisms, and subsequent T1D.

      The search for viral factors responsible for the increased T1D prevalence in youth children
      is difficult to implement. The absence or scarcity of infections is difficult to assess
      robustly at the individual level. The analysis of digestive, ENT or blood samples in the
      search for viruses themselves can only be done at T1D diagnosis and is therefore unlikely to
      be positive several years after the causal infection. It is not possible to reconstitute
      retrospectively viral events, which an individual has been exposed between birth and date of
      diabetes diagnosis. That is why our project proposes to use a proxy of viral infections
      crossed by a child, quantifying viral exposures to which he was submitted before the T1D
      diagnosis. We focused on early childhood's viral infections that may interfere with early
      forms of T1D. We combine 2 data sources:

        -  The geolocation of the child's address will locate places where he lives.
           Spatio-temporal data from Sentinel Network, collected since 1984, will provide access on
           the following viral exposures: seasonal influenza, viral diarrhea (mostly enteroviral),
           mumps, measles, chickenpox. If the defect of our approach is that it does not see real
           viral infections experienced by children, but only the level of exposure to which they
           were exposed according to their address, the advantage is an objective spatio-temporal
           description of virus epidemics around children, making it more or less likely infection
           of these. Only France has such Sentinel data.

        -  Vaccination (including MMR) and information on infectious past of children will be
           collected from data recorded in his book health. We will focus on the mother's pregnancy
           and the child between birth and 2 years of age.

      Environmental data from these 2 sources will be crossed with already available genetic data
      from GWAS to identify gene-virus associations potentially determining age of T1D onset. This
      &quot;high dimensionality&quot; analysis will be addressed with &quot;machine learning&quot; programs.

      If avoidable risks are identified, it would be possible to think to design clinical trials
      for prevention of the identified forms of T1D.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of viral events before T1D diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>From birth to 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delay between viral events and T1D diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>From birth to 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Age at T1D diagnosis as a quantitative trait</measure>
    <time_frame>From birth to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Insulin-Dependent</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Isis-Virus</arm_group_label>
    <description>T1D patients of the Isis-Diab cohort with genetic data (GWAS) and specific environmental data on viral events during childhood</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Collect of data on viral environment of T1D patients</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaires on viral events during mother's pregnancy and patient's childhood, health book copies, addresses' geolocation, quantification of viral exposures using Sentinel Network data</description>
    <arm_group_label>Isis-Virus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Collect of blood samples for DNA extraction and genetic characterization (GWAS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Collect of blood samples for DNA extraction and genetic characterization (GWAS) on Illumina platform (Centre National de Genotypage)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Isis-Virus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      whole blood (already collected for the Isis-Diab project)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients of the Isis-Diab cohort, i.e. T1D patients aged more than 6 months, already
        sampled for genetic analysis.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 diabetic patients included in the Isis-Diab cohort

          -  Patients with available genetic data (GWAS)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient refusal (or parents) to participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alain-Jacques Valleron, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierre Bougnères, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Inserm U986 / Pediatric endocrinology department of the Bicêtre Hospital (AP-HP)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sophie Le Fur, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 1 49 59 53 43</phone>
    <email>sophie.le-fur@inserm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laurence LECOMTE, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+ 33 1 71 19 64 94</phone>
    <email>laurence.lecomte@nck.aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inserm U986</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Kremlin Bicêtre</city>
        <zip>94276</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sophie Le Fur, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+ 33 1 49 59 53 43</phone>
      <email>sophie.le-fur@inserm.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laurence Lecomte, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+33 1 71 19 64 94</phone>
      <email>laurence.lecomte@nck.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.isis-diab.org</url>
    <description>public web-site of the Isis-Diab cohort</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes Mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin-Dependent</keyword>
  <keyword>Virus Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Genome-Wide Association Study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

