<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02429284</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PH-2013-008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02429284</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>U.S. CTEPH Registry</brief_title>
  <official_title>United States CTEPH Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>E Squared Trials and Registries, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The U.S. CTEPH Registry is a multicenter, observational, U.S.-based study of the clinical
      course and treatment of patients diagnosed with chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension
      (CTEPH), WHO Group IV Classification for Pulmonary Hypertension. The mission of the Registry
      will be to promote a greater understanding of the prevalence, pathophysiology, evaluation,
      and treatment of patients with CTEPH through shared information, education, and collaborative
      investigation among pulmonary hypertension (PH) centers of excellence throughout the U.S.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH) is a subset of pulmonary hypertension
      (PH) characterized by the obstruction of pulmonary arteries with fibrotic material and
      vascular remodeling that leads to increased pulmonary arterial pressure and right ventricular
      failure.

      A United States CTEPH Registry has been established under the guidance of a Steering
      Committee consisting of recognized physicians and scientists with expertise in CTEPH and
      related diseases. The mission of the Registry will be to promote a greater understanding of
      the prevalence, pathophysiology, evaluation, and treatment of patients with CTEPH through
      shared information, education, and collaborative investigation among PH centers of excellence
      throughout the U.S. The development of a national CTEPH registry will be an important element
      in the advancement of the understanding of CTEPH and improvement in the care of patients who
      suffer from this debilitating disease.

      All consecutive consenting patients recently diagnosed (&lt; 6 months) with CTEPH at
      participating study sites will be enrolled. At the time of study entry, data on prior history
      and evaluation will be obtained from patient interview and review of medical records.
      Patients will be followed biannually after enrollment until the conclusion of the study
      (minimum of 1 year follow-up for final patients enrolled).

      Much of the data gathered by the Registry will be presented as descriptive statistics. The
      Registry will seek the assistance of a biostatistician to develop a statistical plan for
      within patient and between patient cohort analyses.

      Approximately 750 patients with newly diagnosed (&lt; 6 months) CTEPH will be enrolled.

      TIME FRAME:

      Participants will be followed from the time of their enrollment until 1 year after the final
      patient is enrolled. Short term outcome measures and medical history will be collected during
      the initial visit, and clinical data will be collected from the initial clinic visits,
      hospital says, or procedures (if applicable). Patients will then be followed every 6 months
      after their enrollment for long term outcome measures on quality of life, functional status,
      and medical treatments.

      DATA ANALYSES:

      Demographics and Clinical Course:

      Demographics, risk factors, time to appropriate testing and diagnosis, PAH targeted
      medication use, functional status, and hemodynamics at the time of enrollment will be
      provided annually as aggregate data to all investigators.

      Evaluating Outcomes of PTE Surgery:

      Descriptive statistics of the peri-operative data collected will be provided as aggregate
      data to all investigators annually. Immediate post-operative and longitudinal follow-up of
      all patients undergoing PTE surgery will also be provided as aggregate data annually to all
      sites. Comparisons of hemodynamics, functional status, medication and supplemental oxygen use
      and healthcare utilization will be made between the pre-operative data and longitudinal
      post-operative data.

      Evaluating Predictors of Successful PTE:

      Using longitudinal data collected on post-operative PTE patients, a definition of &quot;successful
      PTE&quot; will be established based upon hemodynamics, functional status and QoL. Retrospective
      analysis of pre-, peri-, and post-operative data can then be analyzed to identify factors
      that predict a &quot;successful&quot; or &quot;unsuccessful&quot; PTE surgery.

      Evaluating Outcomes of Nonsurgical Therapy of CTEPH:

      Predominantly descriptive statistics will be used to describe why patients are not operative
      candidates and the nonsurgical therapies (medication, balloon pulmonary angioplasty) used for
      treatment. Changes in hemodynamics, functional status, QoL and healthcare utilization on
      therapy will be provided as aggregate data annually.

      Evolving Research Needs:

      To adapt to the evolving science and research needs of the CTEPH community, separate analysis
      plans will be developed for new objectives identified and minor changes in the eCRF may occur
      in response to new diagnostics and treatments, if approved by the Steering Committee. Ongoing
      assessment of enrollment and data captured will also be performed by the Steering Committee
      to be certain the goals of the Registry are being met.

      COMMITTEES:

      A Steering Committee, chaired by Dr. Kim Kerr, is comprised of thought leaders in the areas
      of cardiology, pulmonology, and cardiothoracic surgery with expertise in CTEPH. The committee
      will have the following responsibilities:

        -  Provide advice and guidance on the U.S. CTEPH Registry study design and protocol

        -  Provide advice and guidance on the variables to be captured by the eCRF

        -  Provide guidance on study sites selection

        -  Review data results and provide insights into interpretation of the data annually

        -  Provide input on the planning and organization of abstracts and manuscripts

        -  Review abstracts and papers for submission to scientific journals or conferences

        -  Present data at conferences

      An Adjudication Committee, consisting of physicians with expertise in the diagnosis of CTEPH,
      will review all patients felt by Investigators to be eligible for the Registry. The
      adjudication committee members must confirm the diagnosis of CTEPH before the subject can be
      enrolled in the Registry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>4 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe the patterns of evaluation of CTEPH Patients</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe the patters of risk factors and clinical presentation of CTEPH Patients</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcomes of medical and surgical therapy of CTEPH patients as assessed by hemodynamics, quality of life, and functional status</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years, at 6 month intervals</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">750</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension (CTEPH)</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients newly diagnosed with CTEPH</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients newly diagnosed with chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH), WHO Group IV Classification for Pulmonary Hypertension.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All consecutive consenting patients recently diagnosed (&lt; 6 months) with CTEPH at
        participating study sites will be enrolled. Patients must meet inclusion criteria and have
        the diagnosis of CTEPH confirmed by the Adjudication Committee (AC) to be enrolled. Adult
        and pediatric patients may be enrolled and prior medical therapy will not exclude patients
        from enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be a permanent resident of the United States

          -  Documentation of the following hemodynamic parameters by right heart catheterization

               -  Mean pulmonary arterial pressure (PAPm) ≥ 25 mm Hg at rest and,

               -  Pulmonary artery wedge pressure (PAWP) ≤ 15 mm Hg (or &gt; 15 mmHg if justified)

          -  Radiologic confirmation that chronic thromboembolic disease is the cause of the
             pulmonary hypertension by

               -  One or more mismatched perfusion defect(s) by lung ventilation/perfusion scan,
                  and

               -  Confirmation of chronic thromboembolic disease by evidence of bands/webs, vessel
                  narrowing or occlusion seen on CT pulmonary angiogram (CTA), conventional
                  angiography or MR angiography (MRA).

          -  Patients must be diagnosed with CTEPH within 6 months of being considered for study
             eligibility (signing of consent to participate). The date of diagnosis will be defined
             as when both hemodynamic criteria have been met and chronic thromboembolic disease is
             confirmed to be the cause of the pulmonary hypertension by an abnormal V/Q scan and
             the presence of chronic thromboembolic disease on CTA, MRA or pulmonary angiography.
             Hemodynamic and radiologic criteria can be met at separate time points; the most
             recently met criteria time point will be defined as the date of diagnosis.

          -  Prior to enrollment all subjects must have the diagnosis of CTEPH confirmed by the
             Adjudication Committee.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients unwilling or unable to provide written consent for participation in the
             study. Appropriate surrogate consent will be obtained for pediatric patients as
             defined by each investigational site's IRB.

          -  Patients with an underlying medical disorder with an anticipated life expectancy less
             than 2 years.

          -  Patients who do not meet inclusion criteria including:

               -  Have not had documentation of hemodynamic criteria by right heart catheterization
                  as outlined in the inclusion criteria

               -  Do not have radiologic confirmation of chronic thromboembolic disease as outlined
                  in the inclusion criteria

               -  Meet the criteria for inclusion into WHO Groups I, II, III, or V
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kim M Kerr, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kim M Kerr, MD</last_name>
    <phone>858-657-7140</phone>
    <email>kmkerr@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jeffrey R Terry, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>858-657-7141</phone>
    <email>jterry@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSD Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kim M Kerr, MD</last_name>
      <phone>858-657-7140</phone>
      <email>kmkerr@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jeffrey R Terry, MBA</last_name>
      <phone>858-657-7141</phone>
      <email>jterry@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kim M Kerr, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://usctephregistry.com</url>
    <description>The central website for the U.S. CTEPH Registry</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim NH, Delcroix M, Jenkins DP, Channick R, Dartevelle P, Jansa P, Lang I, Madani MM, Ogino H, Pengo V, Mayer E. Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Dec 24;62(25 Suppl):D92-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.10.024. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24355646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGoon MD, Benza RL, Escribano-Subias P, Jiang X, Miller DP, Peacock AJ, Pepke-Zaba J, Pulido T, Rich S, Rosenkranz S, Suissa S, Humbert M. Pulmonary arterial hypertension: epidemiology and registries. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Dec 24;62(25 Suppl):D51-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.10.023. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24355642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pepke-Zaba J, Delcroix M, Lang I, Mayer E, Jansa P, Ambroz D, Treacy C, D'Armini AM, Morsolini M, Snijder R, Bresser P, Torbicki A, Kristensen B, Lewczuk J, Simkova I, Barberà JA, de Perrot M, Hoeper MM, Gaine S, Speich R, Gomez-Sanchez MA, Kovacs G, Hamid AM, Jaïs X, Simonneau G. Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH): results from an international prospective registry. Circulation. 2011 Nov 1;124(18):1973-81. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.015008. Epub 2011 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21969018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 29, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kim Kerr</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension (CTEPH)</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Endarterectomy (PEA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Thromboendarterectomy (PTE)</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Balloon Pulmonary Angioplasty (BPA)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

