<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02424851</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>26866138-MMY2070</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-003947-31</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02424851</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimising Renal Outcome in Myeloma Renal Failure</brief_title>
  <acronym>OPTIMAL</acronym>
  <official_title>A Study of Thalidomide, Bendamustine and Dexamethasone (BTD) Versus Bortezomib, Bendamustine and Dexamethasone (BBD) in Patients With Renal Failure Defined as a GFR Below 30 Mls/Min</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Janssen-Cilag Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bloodwise</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Warwick</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the effectiveness of bortezomib versus thalidomide in
      reducing free light chains in the blood of myeloma patients. In addition participants will
      receive bendamustine (chemotherapy) and dexamethasone (steroids), which increase the
      effectiveness of both bortezomib and thalidomide. The trial will also study whether an
      earlier reduction of free light chains increases the chances of the kidneys recovering.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Renal impairment is a life threatening condition of myeloma. 20-25% of patients will present
      at diagnosis with renal dysfunction. Outcome is poor due to high early mortality, with 28% of
      newly diagnosed myeloma patients in myeloma trials with renal failure not surviving beyond
      100 days, compared with 10% overall.

      This study aims to establish:

        1. Whether proteosomal inhibition (bortezomib) or immunomodulatory (thalidomide) based
           therapy achieves threshold reduction of serum free light chains (sFLCs) in a significant
           majority of patients.

        2. Whether sFLC response to the first 2 cycles (early responder) predicts haematological
           and renal response to the next 2 cycles of therapy.

        3. An early time point for assessment of sFLC reduction as a biomarker for response.

      Participants will be stratified by age and chronic kidney disease (CKD) stage to receive
      either bortezomib, bendamustine and dexamethasone (BBD) or thalidomide, bendamustine and
      dexamethasone (BTD).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum free light chain response to treatment - defined as &gt;50% reduction from baseline in sFLC</measure>
    <time_frame>End of week 6 (after receiving two cycles of therapy)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal response to treatment using the International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) renal response criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>End of week 12 (after receiving 4 cycles of therapy)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Haematological and non-haematological toxicity in both treatment arms</measure>
    <time_frame>End of weeks 3, 6, 9, 12 (after receiving 4 cycles of therapy), 30 days after final treatment and 12 months after randomisation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month post end of treatment and 1 year post randomisation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of renal response, using the IMWG renal response criteria, at the end of the second and fourth cycles of therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>End of weeks 6 and 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life measured by the EQ-5D-3L Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>End of week 1 cycles 1-4 and at 1 and 12 month follow up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Kidney Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (BBD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bortezomib, Bendamustine and Dexamethasone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (BTD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Thalidomide, Bendamustine and Dexamethasone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>1.3 mg/m2 subcutaneously* days 1, 4, 8 and 11 of each cycle. Number of cycles: Four 21 day cycles (participants not suitable for ASCT (autologous stem cell transplant) will continue up to 6 cycles on the treatment regimen to which they were randomised).
*intravenous infusion available in case of patient intolerance to subcutaneous bortezomib</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (BBD)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg daily orally, preferably at night, days 1-21 of each cycle. Four 21 day cycles (participants not suitable for ASCT will continue up to 6 cycles on the treatment regimen to which they were randomised)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (BTD)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bendamustine</intervention_name>
    <description>60 mg/m2 i.v. days 1 and 8 of each cycle. Four 21 day cycles (participants not suitable for ASCT will continue up to 6 cycles on the treatment regimen to which they were randomised)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (BBD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (BTD)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>40mg orally days 1-2, 4-5, 8-9 and 11-12 of each cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (BBD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (BTD)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the
             trial.

          -  Patients attending NHS (National Health Service) Haemato-oncology centres.

          -  Patients with newly diagnosed symptomatic myeloma.

          -  Glomerular Filtration Rate (GFR) &lt;30 mls/min.

          -  Chronic kidney disease (CKD) staging is based on estimated or measured GFR. CKD stage
             4 (15-29 ml/min) and CKD stage 5 (&lt;15 ml/min) are eligible to enter the study. It is
             expected centres will consider use of fluid resuscitation and pulsed dose of steroid
             therapy in this group of patients to salvage renal function prior to trial screening.

          -  A number of patients with newly diagnosed myeloma and renal failure will have a
             pre-existing medical condition (hypertension, diabetes etc.) causing renal damage.
             Where there is a medical condition (e.g. hypertension, diabetes) which may cause renal
             damage, there must have been a further decline (≥15 mls/min GFR) between previous
             steady state and the study screening.

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential and male patients whose partner is a
             woman of childbearing potential must be prepared to use contraception in accordance
             with (and consent to) the Celgene-approved process for thalidomide and lenalidomide
             Risk Management and Pregnancy Prevention Programme.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test performed by a
             healthcare professional in accordance with the Celgene-approved process for
             thalidomide and lenalidomide Risk Management and Pregnancy Prevention.

          -  Free of prior malignancies for ≥ 2 years with exception of currently treated basal
             cell, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, localised prostate cancer or carcinoma
             &quot;in-situ&quot; of the cervix or breast.

          -  In the Investigator's opinion, is able and willing to comply with all trial
             requirements.

          -  Willing to allow his or her General Practitioner and consultant, if appropriate, to be
             notified of participation in the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female participant who is pregnant, lactating or planning pregnancy during the course
             of the trial or the female partner of a male participant planning a pregnancy during
             the course of the trial.

          -  Known allergy to investigational drugs.

          -  Any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             may either put the participants at risk because of participation in the trial, or may
             influence the result of the trial, or the participant's ability to participate in the
             trial.

          -  Any of the following laboratory abnormalities:

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1.0 x10^9/L

          -  Platelet count &lt;75 x 10^9/L

          -  Serum SGOT/AST or SGPT/ALT (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase/aspartate
             aminotransferase or serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase/alanine aminotransferase) &gt;3 x
             upper limit of normal.

          -  Use of any standard/experimental anti-myeloma drug therapy excluding dexamethasone 14
             days prior to trial entry.

          -  CKD stages &lt; 4.

          -  Intention to use a physical method of serum free light chain removal such as plasma
             exchange or high cut off dialysis.

          -  Grade 2 neuropathy or more (National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for
             Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v 4.0) will preclude use of thalidomide and bortezomib.

          -  Participants who have participated in another research trial involving an
             investigational product in the past 12 weeks.

          -  Contraindicated to receive either one of the study drugs, thalidomide, bortezomib,
             bendamustine based on the respective summary of product characteristics.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karthik Ramasamy</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Health Service, United Kingdom</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Optimal Trial Coordinator</last_name>
    <phone>01865 223353</phone>
    <email>optimal.trial@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Basingstoke &amp; North Hampshire Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basingstoke</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Noel Ryman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kent &amp; Canterbury Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Canterbury</city>
        <zip>CT1 3NG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jindrinska Lindsay</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Helier Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Epsom</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Simon Stern</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Liverpool Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nauman Butt</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Churchill Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <zip>OX3 7LE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karthik Ramasamy</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Alexandra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portsmouth</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helen Dignum</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helen Dignum</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Great Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Swindon</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Suspended</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cancerresearchuk.org/cancer-info/cancerstats/types/myeloma/uk-multiple-myeloma-statistics</url>
    <description>Cancer Research UK - Myeloma Statistics</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar SK, Rajkumar SV, Dispenzieri A, Lacy MQ, Hayman SR, Buadi FK, Zeldenrust SR, Dingli D, Russell SJ, Lust JA, Greipp PR, Kyle RA, Gertz MA. Improved survival in multiple myeloma and the impact of novel therapies. Blood. 2008 Mar 1;111(5):2516-20. Epub 2007 Nov 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17975015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner H, Gondos A, Pulte D. Expected long-term survival of patients diagnosed with multiple myeloma in 2006-2010. Haematologica. 2009 Feb;94(2):270-5. doi: 10.3324/haematol.13782. Epub 2009 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19144659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Landgren O, Kyle RA, Pfeiffer RM, Katzmann JA, Caporaso NE, Hayes RB, Dispenzieri A, Kumar S, Clark RJ, Baris D, Hoover R, Rajkumar SV. Monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS) consistently precedes multiple myeloma: a prospective study. Blood. 2009 May 28;113(22):5412-7. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-12-194241. Epub 2009 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>19179464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knudsen LM, Hippe E, Hjorth M, Holmberg E, Westin J. Renal function in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma--a demographic study of 1353 patients. The Nordic Myeloma Study Group. Eur J Haematol. 1994 Oct;53(4):207-12.</citation>
    <PMID>7957804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eleutherakis-Papaiakovou V, Bamias A, Gika D, Simeonidis A, Pouli A, Anagnostopoulos A, Michali E, Economopoulos T, Zervas K, Dimopoulos MA; Greek Myeloma Study Group. Renal failure in multiple myeloma: incidence, correlations, and prognostic significance. Leuk Lymphoma. 2007 Feb;48(2):337-41.</citation>
    <PMID>17325894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark AD, Shetty A, Soutar R. Renal failure and multiple myeloma: pathogenesis and treatment of renal failure and management of underlying myeloma. Blood Rev. 1999 Jun;13(2):79-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10414944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drayson M, Begum G, Basu S, Makkuni S, Dunn J, Barth N, Child JA. Effects of paraprotein heavy and light chain types and free light chain load on survival in myeloma: an analysis of patients receiving conventional-dose chemotherapy in Medical Research Council UK multiple myeloma trials. Blood. 2006 Sep 15;108(6):2013-9. Epub 2006 May 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16728700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan GJ, Davies FE, Gregory WM, Bell SE, Szubert AJ, Navarro Coy N, Cook G, Feyler S, Johnson PR, Rudin C, Drayson MT, Owen RG, Ross FM, Russell NH, Jackson GH, Child JA; National Cancer Research Institute Haematological Oncology Clinical Studies Group. Cyclophosphamide, thalidomide, and dexamethasone as induction therapy for newly diagnosed multiple myeloma patients destined for autologous stem-cell transplantation: MRC Myeloma IX randomized trial results. Haematologica. 2012 Mar;97(3):442-50. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2011.043372. Epub 2011 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22058209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Augustson BM, Begum G, Dunn JA, Barth NJ, Davies F, Morgan G, Behrens J, Smith A, Child JA, Drayson MT. Early mortality after diagnosis of multiple myeloma: analysis of patients entered onto the United kingdom Medical Research Council trials between 1980 and 2002--Medical Research Council Adult Leukaemia Working Party. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Dec 20;23(36):9219-26. Epub 2005 Nov 7.</citation>
    <PMID>16275935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Torra R, Bladé J, Cases A, López-Pedret J, Montserrat E, Rozman C, Revert L. Patients with multiple myeloma requiring long-term dialysis: presenting features, response to therapy, and outcome in a series of 20 cases. Br J Haematol. 1995 Dec;91(4):854-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8547129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kastritis E, Anagnostopoulos A, Roussou M, Gika D, Matsouka C, Barmparousi D, Grapsa I, Psimenou E, Bamias A, Dimopoulos MA. Reversibility of renal failure in newly diagnosed multiple myeloma patients treated with high dose dexamethasone-containing regimens and the impact of novel agents. Haematologica. 2007 Apr;92(4):546-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17488666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knudsen LM, Hjorth M, Hippe E. Renal failure in multiple myeloma: reversibility and impact on the prognosis. Nordic Myeloma Study Group. Eur J Haematol. 2000 Sep;65(3):175-81.</citation>
    <PMID>11007053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alexanian R, Barlogie B, Dixon D. Renal failure in multiple myeloma. Pathogenesis and prognostic implications. Arch Intern Med. 1990 Aug;150(8):1693-5.</citation>
    <PMID>2383164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gandhi V. Metabolism and mechanisms of action of bendamustine: rationales for combination therapies. Semin Oncol. 2002 Aug;29(4 Suppl 13):4-11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12170425</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaul L, Mandl-Weber S, Baumann P, Emmerich B, Schmidmaier R. Bendamustine induces G2 cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in myeloma cells: the role of ATM-Chk2-Cdc25A and ATM-p53-p21-pathways. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol. 2008 Feb;134(2):245-53. Epub 2007 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>17653574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pönisch W, Mitrou PS, Merkle K, Herold M, Assmann M, Wilhelm G, Dachselt K, Richter P, Schirmer V, Schulze A, Subert R, Harksel B, Grobe N, Stelzer E, Schulze M, Bittrich A, Freund M, Pasold R, Friedrich T, Helbig W, Niederwieser D; East German Study Group of Hematology and Oncology (OSHO). Treatment of bendamustine and prednisone in patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma results in superior complete response rate, prolonged time to treatment failure and improved quality of life compared to treatment with melphalan and prednisone--a randomized phase III study of the East German Study Group of Hematology and Oncology (OSHO). J Cancer Res Clin Oncol. 2006 Apr;132(4):205-12. Epub 2006 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>16402269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knop S, Straka C, Haen M, Schwedes R, Hebart H, Einsele H. The efficacy and toxicity of bendamustine in recurrent multiple myeloma after high-dose chemotherapy. Haematologica. 2005 Sep;90(9):1287-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16154860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haubitz M, Bohnenstengel F, Brunkhorst R, Schwab M, Hofmann U, Busse D. Cyclophosphamide pharmacokinetics and dose requirements in patients with renal insufficiency. Kidney Int. 2002 Apr;61(4):1495-501.</citation>
    <PMID>11918757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eriksson T, Höglund P, Turesson I, Waage A, Don BR, Vu J, Scheffler M, Kaysen GA. Pharmacokinetics of thalidomide in patients with impaired renal function and while on and off dialysis. J Pharm Pharmacol. 2003 Dec;55(12):1701-6.</citation>
    <PMID>14738599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tosi P, Zamagni E, Cellini C, Cangini D, Tacchetti P, Tura S, Baccarani M, Cavo M. Thalidomide alone or in combination with dexamethasone in patients with advanced, relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma and renal failure. Eur J Haematol. 2004 Aug;73(2):98-103.</citation>
    <PMID>15245508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan GJ, Davies FE, Gregory WM, Russell NH, Bell SE, Szubert AJ, Navarro Coy N, Cook G, Feyler S, Byrne JL, Roddie H, Rudin C, Drayson MT, Owen RG, Ross FM, Jackson GH, Child JA; NCRI Haematological Oncology Study Group. Cyclophosphamide, thalidomide, and dexamethasone (CTD) as initial therapy for patients with multiple myeloma unsuitable for autologous transplantation. Blood. 2011 Aug 4;118(5):1231-8. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-02-338665. Epub 2011 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>21652683</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramasamy K, Hazel B, Mahmood S, Corderoy S, Schey S. Bendamustine in combination with thalidomide and dexamethasone is an effective therapy for myeloma patients with end stage renal disease. Br J Haematol. 2011 Dec;155(5):632-4. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2141.2011.08754.x. Epub 2011 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21689088</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jagannath S, Barlogie B, Berenson JR, Singhal S, Alexanian R, Srkalovic G, Orlowski RZ, Richardson PG, Anderson J, Nix D, Esseltine DL, Anderson KC; SUMMIT/CREST Investigators. Bortezomib in recurrent and/or refractory multiple myeloma. Initial clinical experience in patients with impared renal function. Cancer. 2005 Mar 15;103(6):1195-200.</citation>
    <PMID>15690325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chanan-Khan AA, Kaufman JL, Mehta J, Richardson PG, Miller KC, Lonial S, Munshi NC, Schlossman R, Tariman J, Singhal S. Activity and safety of bortezomib in multiple myeloma patients with advanced renal failure: a multicenter retrospective study. Blood. 2007 Mar 15;109(6):2604-6. Epub 2006 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>17138816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>San Miguel JF, Schlag R, Khuageva NK, Dimopoulos MA, Shpilberg O, Kropff M, Spicka I, Petrucci MT, Palumbo A, Samoilova OS, Dmoszynska A, Abdulkadyrov KM, Schots R, Jiang B, Mateos MV, Anderson KC, Esseltine DL, Liu K, Cakana A, van de Velde H, Richardson PG; VISTA Trial Investigators. Bortezomib plus melphalan and prednisone for initial treatment of multiple myeloma. N Engl J Med. 2008 Aug 28;359(9):906-17. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0801479.</citation>
    <PMID>18753647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fenk R, Michael M, Zohren F, Graef T, Czibere A, Bruns I, Neumann F, Fenk B, Haas R, Kobbe G. Escalation therapy with bortezomib, dexamethasone and bendamustine for patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. Leuk Lymphoma. 2007 Dec;48(12):2345-51.</citation>
    <PMID>18067009</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 10, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 22, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 23, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karthik Ramasamy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic kidney disease</keyword>
  <keyword>renal failure</keyword>
  <keyword>bortezomib</keyword>
  <keyword>Velcade</keyword>
  <keyword>thalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>bendamustine</keyword>
  <keyword>dexamethasone</keyword>
  <keyword>serum free light chains</keyword>
  <keyword>proteosomal inhibition</keyword>
  <keyword>immunomodulatory</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bendamustine Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

