<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02422550</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-073</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02422550</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imaging Acquisition and Analysis Methods for Optimization of MRI Radiation Oncology Simulation and Response Assessment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Development and Evaluation of Imaging Acquisition and Analysis Methods for Optimization of MRI Radiation Oncology Simulation and Response Assessment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is currently one of the standard diagnostic imaging methods
      used to diagnose tumor stage before treatment in Radiology Oncology Department. It is also
      used to check responses to radiation after treatment. However, MRI isn't traditionally used
      in planning for radiation treatment or in checking treated tumor and tissue changes during
      radiation treatment. The goal is to find out the possible benefits of MRI imaging techniques
      in these settings of radiation treatment. Participating in this study would NOT change the
      current treatment plans, this will allow the investigators to use the MRI methods in research
      and future patient care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this protocol is to demonstrate proof of concept and feasibility of new MRI
      hardware, pulse sequences and data analysis software to plan radiotherapy treatment and to
      assess tumor response to radiotherapy (only FDA approved hardware are allowed in this study).
      Efforts to develop, modify and evaluate new or existing MR imaging techniques must be a
      continuous practice with the goal of enhancing the use of MRI during radiation therapy. The
      investigators therefore anticipate an ongoing need for such a protocol and believe the
      ability to perform such studies is critical to the translation of new imaging technologies
      from concept to routine clinical use. Under this protocol, modifications to the following
      items may be tested: pulse sequence programs, radiofrequency coils, reconstruction and
      processing software, other MR system hardware and analysis software. A brief description of
      each of these items is described below. The potential risks associated with modifying each of
      these items, and the measures that will be taken to minimize these risks are described in
      subsequent sections.

      Given that performing MRI examinations during radiation therapy is not the current standard
      of care, no changes to radiation treatment plans, radiotherapy delivery or treatment
      recommendations or guidelines will be done based on the findings for any participants entered
      on this protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 9, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>evaluate the feasibility of new MRI applications</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>MRI acquisition and analysis methods for radiotherapy planning or tumor response assessment during radiotherapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">212</enrollment>
  <condition>Radiation Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>participants undergoing radiation therapy &amp; normal volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants enrolled on this protocol may undergo multiple MRI examinations periodically over the course of their treatment and follow-up if they are participating in a development project related to tumor response assessment. Volunteers enrolled on this protocol may undergo multiple MRI examinations periodically for studies of reproducibility.</description>
    <arm_group_label>participants undergoing radiation therapy &amp; normal volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will be participants undergoing radiation therapy in the Department of
        Radiation Oncology, optional normal volunteers, or a combination thereof.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women age 18 or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anyone who would be normally excluded from undergoing an MRI examination as per
             Memorial Hospital for Cancer and Allied Diseases Screening Questionnaire

          -  Participants/volunteers with a pacemaker, aneurysm clip or any other condition that
             would warrant avoidance of a strong magnetic field

          -  Female participants/volunteers who are pregnant or nursing

          -  Participants/Volunteers who are unable to comply or complete the MRI exam due to
             claustrophobia or high levels of anxiety

          -  Participants/Volunteers from the vulnerable population, as defined by 45 CFR 46.

          -  Participants at higher risk due to age, frailty, or the emergent nature of their
             condition.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nancy Lee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nancy Lee, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-3341</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Simon Powell, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-6072</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nancy Lee, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3341</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Simon Powell, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-6072</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nancy Lee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://one.mskcc.org/sites/pub/Pages/default.aspx</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 14, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>15-073</keyword>
  <keyword>participants undergoing radiation therapy</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

