<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02426424</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SOR-0305-14-ctil</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02426424</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect Of Early C-PAP Treatment For Sleep Apnea On Rehabilitation Of Stroke Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect Of Early C-PAP Treatment For Sleep Apnea On Rehabilitation Of Stroke Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Soroka University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Soroka University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective randomized open label trial with control-to-treatment cross-over. The
      investigators wish to assess the effectiveness and safety of immediate detection and
      treatment for Sleep Apnea in Stroke patients. The investigators hypothesize that in patients
      with acute ischemic stroke a sleep apnea treatment by CPAP will result in a better
      neurological outcome and more successful rehabilitation.

      The study will enroll 140 subjects which will be randomized into one of two arms:

        -  Investigational - The sleep study will be performed during the index hospitalization
           with acute stroke. Following the diagnosis of sleep apnea, patients will be treated with
           C-PAP both during the hospital stay and after discharge.

        -  Control group -Will receive standard medical care. Patients will undergo sleep study at
           3 months following discharge and patients diagnosed with sleep apnea will be treated
           with C-PAP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients eligible to be enrolled in this study are patients admitted to the Department of
      Neurology due to acute ischemic stroke up to 72 hours from the start of the stroke symptoms.

      After receiving written informed consent from the patient, patients will be randomized into
      the intervention and control groups (1:1). The intervention group will be tested for sleep
      apnea and C-PAP treatment will be initiated during the initial hospitalization. The control
      group will receive standard medical care. Control group patients will undergo sleep study at
      3 months following discharge and patients diagnosed with sleep apnea will be treated with
      C-PAP.

      All subjects:

        -  At the baseline, physical examination MRS and NIHSS will be performed by the
           neurologist.

        -  Sleep testing at the baseline with mobile sleep lab device (Watch PAT)

        -  Four questionnaires will be administered for all patients: Epworth Sleepiness Scale
           (ESS), Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI), quality of life (SF36), depression scale
           (Beck).

        -  Blood sample will be taken for CRP, TNF-alpha, IL-6 and IL1 beta, VEGF, HBA1C, LDL and
           markers of endothelial dysfunction. These blood tests will be repeated at 3 and 6
           months.

        -  At discharge from the Neurology Department, 3 months and 6 months all patients will
           undergo NIHSS assessment.

        -  Patients will be referred to the Soroka stroke clinic with rehabilitation program.

        -  All patients will undergo 3 brain MRI scans, at baseline hospitalization, 3 and 6 months
           after.

      Intervention group:

        -  In the intervention group, the mobile sleep lab device (Watch PAT) will be used to
           identify patients with sleep apnea.

        -  Treatment phase: Patients with (apnea hypopnea index) AHI≥15 will receive an in-hospital
           treatment with CPAP and continue CPAP treatment following discharge. The CPAP parameters
           will be titrated during the hospital stay.

      Control group:

        -  Patients will receive standard medical care. At three months, patients will undergo home
           sleep test with Watch-PAT device.

        -  Patients with (apnea hypopnea index) AHI≥15 will receive CPAP treatment with titration
           at home.

      TRIAL PROCEDURES 1. Patients eligible to be enrolled in this study are patients admitted to
      the Neurology Department due to stroke up to 72 hours after the showing of stroke symptoms.

      2. At the baseline, physical examination, MRS and NIHSS will be performed by one of the
      Neurology Department doctors.

      3. After receiving written informed consent from the patient, patients will be divided into 2
      groups. Study group will have detection and treatment in 72 hours after stroke. Control group
      will have detection and treatment 3 months after stroke.

      STUDY AND CONTROL GROUP

        1. The patient will answer four questionnaires: Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS), Pittsburgh
           Sleep Quality Index (PSQI), &quot;quality of life&quot; (SF36) and &quot;depression scale&quot; (beck).

        2. Next, the mobile sleep lab device (Watch PAT) will be placed on the patient's finger
           which will provide the apnea-hypopnea Index (AHI) and respiratory disturbance index
           (RDI).

        3. Blood samples for circulating inflammatory biomarkers and endothelial dysfunction will
           be performed in the morning. Four tubes of peripheral venous blood will be drawn. Every
           study patient will be tested for the presence of pro-inflammatory state. Specifically,
           the investigators will measure the presence of high sensitive C Reactive Protein (CRP)
           and centrifuged sera will be tested (by ultra- sensitive ELISA), for levels of
           circulating TNF-alpha, IL-6 and IL1 beta. Sera will also be tested for vascular
           endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and markers of endothelial dysfunction; P-selectin.
           LDL, HBA1C.

        4. At discharge from the Neurology Department, the patient will undergo NIHSS assessment.

        5. Half of patients randomly chosen will be asked to join an &quot;early treatment&quot; group for 6
           months of C-PAP treatment. Patients from the other half will be asked for C-PAP
           treatment at 3 months (late intervention).

        6. All four questionnaires will be completed by all patients at the end of the follow up
           period.

        7. MRI scan will be done at three points: CVA admission, 3 and 6 months after.

        8. Six months after baseline hospitalization, patients from both groups will answer four
           questionnaires: Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS), Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI),
           &quot;quality of life&quot; (SF36) and &quot;depression scale&quot; (beck).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Failure to have funding to perform the trial
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>NIHSS change from the baseline to 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the NIHSS score from admission to three months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NIHSS change score from admission to discharge from the Neurology Department.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NIHSS score change from admission to 6 months following hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NIHSS score change from three to six months following hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevent recurrent strokes at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analyse the composite of cardiovascular events at 6 months (acute myocardial infarction, coronary revascularization, death or recurrent stroke)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate new MRI ischemic lesions between 3 MRI scans.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) at 3 and 6 months from the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change quality of life (SF36) at 3 and 6 months from the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change depression scale (Beck) at 3 and 6 months from the baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change number of severe adverse events (SAE) at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Investigatory 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The sleep study will be performed via Watchpat during the index hospitalization with acute stroke. Following the diagnosis of sleep apnea, patients will be treated with C-PAP both during the hospital stay and after discharge for three months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Investigatory 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The sleep study will be performed via Watchpat at home three months after hospitalization with acute stroke. Following the diagnosis of sleep apnea, patients will be treated with C-PAP for three months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Watchpat</intervention_name>
    <description>WatchPAT ™ is an FDA-approved portable diagnostic device that uses the most innovative technology to ensure the accurate screening, detection, and the follow-up treatment of sleep apnea.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigatory 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Investigatory 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPAP</intervention_name>
    <description>Continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) is a form of positive airway pressure ventilator, which applies mild air pressure on a continuous basis to keep the airways continuously open in a patient who is able to breathe spontaneously on his or her own.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigatory 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Investigatory 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients over the age of 18.

          2. Admitted to the Neurology Department due to acute ischemic stroke.

          3. Able to sign informed consent.

          4. Admission NIHSS 6-12.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Stroke symptom onset more than 72 hours prior to the enrollment

          2. Transient Ischemic Attack.

          3. Chronic pulmonary disease requiring home oxygen treatment.

          4. History of C-PAP treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 24, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Soroka University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gal Ifergane MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Neurology Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>c-PAP</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

