<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02428491</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A3L35</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1143-8177</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02428491</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT02821195</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Sanofi Pasteur's DTaP-IPV Hep B-PRP-T Combined Vaccine in Infants Who Previously Received Hepatitis B Vaccine</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity and Safety of Sanofi Pasteur's DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP-T Combined Vaccine Given as a Three-Dose Primary Series at 2, 3, and 4 Months of Age and Followed by a Booster Dose Given at 16 to 17 Months of Age in Vietnamese Infants Who Previously Received a Dose of Hepatitis B Vaccine at Birth or Within 1 Week After Birth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanofi Pasteur, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Hygiene and Epidemiology, Vietnam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to describe the immunogenicity and safety of Sanofi Pasteur's
      DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP-T fully liquid combined hexavalent vaccine (Hexaxim®) administered at 2,
      3, and 4 months of age and at 16 to 17 months of age in infants and toddlers who received a
      dose of Hep B vaccine at birth or within 1 week after birth.

      Primary Objective:

        -  To describe the safety profile after each and all doses of Sanofi-Pasteur's DTaP-IPV-Hep
           B-PRP-T combined vaccine in Vietnamese infants and toddlers

      Secondary Objective:

        -  To evaluate the immunogenicity of the study vaccine one month after the third dose
           primary series.

        -  To demonstrate the non-inferiority of the immune response to all antigens induced by the
           study vaccine in Vietnamese infants one month after the third dose in a 3 dose primary
           series with the immune response to all antigens induced by the same study vaccine
           outside Vietnam

        -  To describe the persistence of all antibodies before receipt of the booster vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants will receive a total of 5 doses of Hep B: One dose of Hep B monovalent vaccine
      given at birth or within 1 week after birth followed by 3 doses of the Sanofi Pasteur's
      hexavalent vaccine given at 2, 3, and 4 months of age (Primary Series) and then (at 16 to 17
      months of age [booster]) to comply with Vietnamese vaccination recommendations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Reporting Solicited Injection-site Reactions, Solicited Systemic Reactions, Unsolicited Systemic Reactions, and Serious Adverse Events Occurring Throughout the Trial</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 up to Day 90 post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited injection-site reactions: Tenderness, Erythema, and swelling. Solicited systemic reactions: Fever (temperature), Vomiting, Crying abnormal, Drowsiness, Appetite loss, and Irritability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with anti Pertussis toxoid and anti Filamentous Hemagglutinin antibody concentrations ≥ Lower Limit of Quantitation (LLOQ) and ≥ 4 x LLOQ at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 (pre-vaccination)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with ≥ 4-fold and ≥ 2-fold increase in anti-Pertussis toxoid and anti-Filamentous Hemagglutinin antibody concentrations (EU/mL) from pre-dose 1 to one month post-dose 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 21 post-dose 3</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with vaccine response for pertussis toxoid and Filamentous Hemagglutinin antigens</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 21 post-dose 3</time_frame>
    <description>Vaccine response defined as post-third dose anti-Pertussis toxoid and anti-Filamentous Hemagglutinin antibody concentrations ≥ 4 x LLOQ if pre-vaccination concentration is &lt;4 x LLOQ or ≥ pre-vaccination concentration if pre- vaccination concentrations ≥ 4 x LLOQ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with anti-Diphtheria antibody concentrations ≥ 0.01 and ≥ 0.1 IU/mL International Units (IU)/mL post-third dose vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 21 post-dose 3</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">354</enrollment>
  <condition>Diphtheria</condition>
  <condition>Tetanus</condition>
  <condition>Pertussis</condition>
  <condition>Poliomyelitis</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis B</condition>
  <condition>Haemophilus Influenzae Type b</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the primary series vaccinations at 2, 3, and 4 months of age and evaluated for safety and immunogenicity post vaccination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the primary series vaccinations at 2, 3, and 4 months of age and will be evaluated for safety only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP-T combined vaccine (Hexaxim™)</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL, Intramuscular</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group I</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hexaxim™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP-T combined vaccine (Hexaxim™)</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mL, Intramuscular</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hexaxim™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 61 to 91 days on the day of the first study visit

          -  Born at full term of pregnancy (≥ 37 weeks) and with a birth weight ≥2.5 kg

          -  Informed consent form has been signed and dated by the parent(s) or other legally
             acceptable representative (and by an independent witness if required by local
             regulations)

          -  Subject and parent/legally acceptable representative are able to attend all scheduled
             visits and to comply with all trial procedures

          -  Have received one dose of Hep B vaccine at birth or within 1 week after birth
             (documented according to the national recommendations).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in the 4 weeks preceding the first trial vaccination or planned
             participation during the present trial period in another clinical trial investigating
             a vaccine, drug, medical device, or medical procedure

          -  Receipt of any vaccine in the 4 weeks preceding the first trial vaccination or planned
             receipt of any other vaccine within the period from 8 days before to 8 days after each
             subsequent trial vaccination except for Bacille Calmette Guerin (BCG) vaccination (any
             administration of oral poliovirus vaccine (OPV) in the context of oral poliovirus
             vaccine-national immunization days (NIDs) does not fall within the scope of this
             exclusion criterion)

          -  Previous vaccination against diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis, poliomyelitis, hepatitis
             B (except the dose of Hep B vaccine given at birth or within 1 week after birth)
             diseases or Haemophilus influenzae type b infection with either the trial vaccine or
             another vaccine (any administration of OPV in the context of OPV-NIDs does not fall
             within the scope of this exclusion criterion)

          -  Past or current receipt of immune globulins, blood or blood-derived products or
             planned administration during the trial

          -  Known or suspected congenital or acquired immunodeficiency; or receipt of
             immunosuppressive therapy, such as anti-cancer chemotherapy or radiation therapy since
             birth; or long-term systemic corticosteroid therapy (prednisone or equivalent for more
             than 2 consecutive weeks since birth)

          -  History of diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis, poliomyelitis, hepatitis B, or Haemophilus
             influenzae type b infections (confirmed either clinically, serologically or
             microbiologically)

          -  Known personal or maternal history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), or hepatitis
             C seropositivity

          -  Known systemic hypersensitivity to any of the vaccine components, or history of a
             life-threatening reaction to the vaccine used in the trial or to a vaccine containing
             any of the same substances

          -  Known thrombocytopenia, as reported by the parent/legally acceptable representative

          -  Bleeding disorder, or receipt of anticoagulants in the 3 weeks preceding inclusion,
             contraindicating intramuscular vaccination

          -  History of seizures

          -  In an emergency setting, or hospitalized involuntarily

          -  Chronic illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, is at a stage where it might
             interfere with trial conduct or completion

          -  Moderate or severe acute illness/infection (according to investigator judgment) on the
             day of vaccination or febrile illness (temperature ≥38.0°C). A prospective subject
             should not be included in the study until the condition has resolved or the febrile
             event has subsided

          -  Identified as a natural or adopted child of the Investigator, relatives or employee
             with direct involvement in the proposed study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>61 Days</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>91 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sanofi Pasteur SA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Preventive Medicine Centre of Thai Binh Province</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thai Binh</city>
        <country>Vietnam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofipasteur.com</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sanofi.com</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 28, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diphtheria</keyword>
  <keyword>Tetanus</keyword>
  <keyword>Pertussis</keyword>
  <keyword>Poliomyelitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis B</keyword>
  <keyword>DTaP-IPV-Hep B-PRP-T Combined Vaccine (Hexaxim™)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Whooping Cough</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetanus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diphtheria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Poliomyelitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data (IPD) and supporting clinical documents are available for request at www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com. While making information available the company continue to protect the privacy of the participants in clinical trials and to remove commercially confidential information (CCI). Details on Data Sharing criteria and process for requesting access can be found at this web address: Clinicalstudydatarequest.com/Sanofi&quot;.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

