<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02426138</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014P002778</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02426138</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community Servings: Food as Medicine for Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Community Servings: Food as Medicine for Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Food insecurity, defined as difficulty accessing food owing to cost, affects 1 in 5 diabetes
      patients. To address this, the investigators are conducting a pilot randomized controlled
      trial of medically tailored meal delivery (MTM). The pilot study has two specific aims:

      Aim 1: To determine the effect of receiving MTM on dietary quality for food insecure diabetes
      patients with hyperglycemia Aim 2: To determine the feasibility and acceptability of the
      program as a medical intervention and refine the program as needed for testing in larger
      studies.

      This study is a crossover randomized controlled pilot trial, where approximately 50
      participants, 25 in each arm, will be randomized to receipt of 12 weeks of MTM, to begin
      immediately, or waitlist control. After 12 weeks, the groups will crossover, with the
      waitlist control group now receiving 12 weeks of MTM. At baseline, 12 weeks, and 24 weeks,
      the participants will complete assessments of their dietary quality (HEI score), psychosocial
      measures such as diabetes distress and food insecurity, along with measures of body mass
      index, blood pressure, hemoglobin A1c, and lipids.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      a. Historical background The Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) estimates that
      there are currently 29 million people with diabetes and 86 million people with pre-diabetes
      in the U.S. One in 10 Americans has diabetes now, and, if current trends continue, 1 in 3
      Americans will have diabetes by 2050. This chronic disease significantly impacts both quality
      of life and rapidly rising national healthcare costs. The estimated cost of diabetes in the
      U.S. in 2014 was $265 billion with $176 billion in direct medical costs and $89 billion is
      indirect medical costs (disability, work loss, premature mortality). Medical expenses for
      people with diabetes are 2.3 times higher than for people without diabetes.

      Food insecurity, defined as limited access to nutritious food due to cost, has been
      associated with increased prevalence of diabetes and worse diabetes control. Food insecurity
      may worsen diabetes by decreasing consumption of fresh fruits and vegetables and increasing
      consumption of inexpensive, calorie-dense food, and which in turn leads to greater Hemoglobin
      A1c, an indicator of hyperglycemia, over time.

      c. Rationale behind the proposed research, and potential benefits to participants and/or
      society

      Approximately 20% of diabetes patients report food insecurity, a number that increases to
      over 25% among those with the worst metabolic control.5 The prevalence of food insecurity is
      also 20% in the MGH Population we surveyed (data not yet published). Hyperglycemia is
      particularly responsive to dietary changes,8 yet few interventions have attempted to address
      food insecurity in diabetes care. Prior studies have examined the impact of the Supplemental
      Nutrition Assistance Program (SNAP, formerly the Food Stamp Program), but have not found
      important improvements in diabetes outcomes for participants9. This may be because
      neighborhood access to produce and other high quality food is low for many SNAP participants,
      or because making healthy food choices is difficult in resource-constrained environments.
      Additionally, recent sociological work has shown that expecting low-income women to cook
      healthy meals for their families induces a significant burden, and the burden of these
      expectations may drive less healthy food choices. Additionally, while significant time is
      needed for healthy food preparation, low-income patients often face limited leisure time, and
      multiple competing demands for both time and financial resources. Alternatively, direct
      provision of healthy foods was incidentally noted to improve diabetes outcomes in a prior
      randomized controlled trial, but this study was not conducted with the goal of addressing
      food insecurity.

      In this study, we propose to test whether home delivery of freshly prepared meals
      specifically tailored to the needs of diabetes patients improves their dietary quality. We
      hypothesize that the delivery of the meals will help them eat more healthily and improve the
      food security of participants. Secondary outcomes in this pilot study will be weight and
      metabolic control, along with psychological aspects of diabetes care.

      Aim 1: To evaluate the effectiveness of receiving Community Servings meals on dietary quality
      for food insecure diabetes patients with severe hyperglycemia (HbA1c &gt; 8.0%) H1. Primary
      outcome. Healthy Eating Index 2010 (HEI) score: We hypothesize that the CS group will
      demonstrate greater improvements in dietary quality, as assessed by HEI score, at 12 weeks,
      compared with usual care. The sample size of 50 provides 80% power to detect a 5 point
      difference between the CS and usual care groups, assuming an 11 point standard deviation and
      accounting for a 10% drop-out rate.

      H1b. Secondary exploratory outcomes. Medical outcomes: We hypothesize that compared with
      usual care, CS group participants will improve HbA1c, blood pressure, weight, and lipids from
      baseline at the end of the intervention.

      H1c. Behavioral and psychosocial outcomes: Because meal provision will reduce stress related
      to procuring healthy meals, and free up household resources that would otherwise be spent on
      food, we hypothesize that compared with usual care, the CS groups will have greater
      improvements from baseline in patient-reported outcomes of diabetes distress and material
      need security.

      Aim 2: To evaluate the feasibility of providing meals and patient experience with the CS
      program, particularly focusing on factors that determine acceptability, continuation, and
      scalability We will use a mixed methods approach using participant structured interviews and
      surveys to assess engagement and satisfaction with the program, and participant interviews or
      focus groups to compare responders and non-responders. We will also collect quantitative
      indicators of feasibility and implementation such as percent of meals delivered and consumed,
      enrollment and persistence with the program, and logistical issues in order to plan for a
      future full-scale intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Healthy Eating Index 2010 Score</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated using data from ASA24 24-hour dietary recall tool</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Insecurity ( defined as &gt; 2 affirmative responses on the 10-item USDA Food Security</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Survey Modules</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diabetes Distress calculated using Diabetes Distress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Blood Lipids (Triglycericedes, LDL Cholesterol, HDL Cholesterol, Total Cholesterol)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Systolic Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Diastolic Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Medication Adherence (Assessed using medication adherence rating scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost related medication underuse (Defined as &gt; 0 affirmative responses to 4-items on cost-related medication underuse from the medication expenditure panel survey)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Food and medication tradeoffs (Prevalence of food and medication trade-offs between groups, calculated from 3 items asking about tradeoffs)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depressive Symptoms (assessed using the PHQ-8 scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Cognitive Burden (Assessed using times on the Stroop Task)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported hypoglycemia (Prevalence between groups, using 2 self-report hypoglycemia items)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 12 weeks of medically tailored meal delivery, comprising approximately half of their weekly caloric intake and consisting of foods prepared under the supervision of a registered dietitian to be compatible with a diabetes diet. They will also receive usual diabetes care and a Choose MyPlate healthy eating brochure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care + Choose Myplate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive usual diabetes care and a Choose MyPlate healthy eating brochure for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medically Tailored Meal Delivery (MTM)</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive delivery of medically tailored meals for 12 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care + Choose MyPlate</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive usual diabetes care + a Choose MyPlate healthy eating brochure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care + Choose Myplate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Diagnosis of type 2 diabetes

               -  Age 18 years or older

               -  HbA1c level &gt;8.0%

               -  Report food insecurity as indicated by the 2-item USDA Food Security Survey
                  Module13

               -  Willing to commit to random assignment to either receive CS meals immediately or
                  as a waitlist control

               -  Stable health, with no severe medical comorbidities that might interfere with
                  their ability to participate in the intervention, such as severe psychiatric
                  illness or imminent hospitalization

               -  Be willing to keep a food diary

               -  Be willing to attend and complete a baseline, 12 week, and 24 week assessment at
                  MGH

               -  Be able to understand and communicate effectively in English

               -  Have a primary care physician within the MGH practice based research network

               -  Live in an area where Community Servings can deliver meals

               -  Ability to store and prepare Community Servings meals

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  • Must not be pregnant or planning pregnancy in the next year

               -  Currently enrolled in another diabetes study Food allergy that would prohibit
                  consumption of meals

               -  Receiving episodic treatments that may increase blood glucose levels (e.g.
                  prednisone)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Seth A Berkowitz, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Seth A Berkowitz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Instructor in Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

