<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03250312</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB #170804-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03250312</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of OMT on the Expression Patterns of Immune Cell Biomarkers</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Osteopathic Manipulations on the Expression Patterns of Immune Cell Biomarkers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>A.T. Still University of Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>A.T. Still University of Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study intends to understand the effects of osteopathic manipulative treatment (OMT) on
      the expression patterns of 60 immune cell biomarkers in the peripheral blood mononuclear
      cells (PBMC) of each participant, before and after intervention - OMT or seated control. This
      study will utilize participants with a history of low back pain (LBP), and will identify and
      validate those immune cell biomarkers that change in most participants after OMT, by using
      the novel protein subcellular localization (PSL) microarray technology. This study intends to
      uncover the important immune cells affected by OMT techniques, therefore to uncover the
      molecular mechanisms of OMT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be conducted over the course of one year. Forty men and women ages 20 to 55
      years with at least one or more episodes of LBP in the past two weeks will be randomly
      assigned into one of two groups - control or OMT groups. Twenty participants will be assigned
      to each group. The study will begin recruitment in September 2017. Participants will be
      recruited from the surrounding Kirksville area. Individuals who cannot tolerate OMT or have
      coagulation disorders will be excluded. Potential participants will be excluded from the
      study if they have had nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medication in the 48 hours prior to the
      study or if they have had corticosteroids in the 2 weeks prior to the study.

      Participants will be randomly assigned into two groups, control or OMT using a random number
      generator. Males and females will be randomized separately to ensure equal distribution into
      the two study groups. Demographics including sex, age, and body mass index (BMI) will be
      collected on all participants. All participants will receive two blood draws,with 8 ml each
      draw: first blood draw immediately prior to intervention and second blood draw following the
      intervention.

      The OMT treatment will begin with a brief physical examination to identify somatic
      dysfunction that the treating physician judges to be relevant to the individual participant's
      low back pain. OMT will be performed to improve the somatic dysfunctions that the treating
      physicians finds most relevant. The types of OMT techniques used will include muscle energy,
      articular, or high velocity-low amplitude (HVLA) as indicated by the physical findings and
      will be at the discretion of the treating physician. Additional techniques such as still,
      counter strain, facilitated positional release, balanced ligamentous tension, and cranial
      techniques may also be used at the discretion of the treating physician. The treatment will
      conclude with 2 minutes of pedal lymphatic pumping technique. The total treatment time will
      not to exceed 20 minutes.

      The control group will wait in another room for approximately 30 minutes. To encourage
      participation in the proposed study, participants who are assigned to the control group will
      have an opportunity to receive OMT after the second blood draw.

      The investigators shall determine the expression patterns of 60 immune cell biomarkers in
      human peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) of the study participants, and determine the
      ratio change of those 60 biomarkers, after the OMT treatment. The investigators shall compare
      the effects of OMT treatment on the ratio change of those 60 biomarkers, with those in the
      control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 15, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomly assigned into two groups, control or OMT using a random number generator. Males and females will be randomized separately to ensure equal distribution into the two study groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>The investigators who determine the expression profile of the 60 immune cell biomarkers would not know which group does each sample belong to</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effects of OMT on the amounts of immune cell biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>immediate after the 20 minutes OMT treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the ratio change of immune cell biomarkers in the PBMC cell of Low back pain patients after the OMT treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteopathic Manipulation</condition>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <condition>Biomarkers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The OMT group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be treated by the osteopathic manipulation techniques (OMT). The types of OMT techniques used will include muscle energy, articular, or high velocity-low amplitude (HVLA) as indicated by the physical findings and will be at the discretion of the treating physician. Additional techniques such as still, counter strain, facilitated positional release, balanced ligamentous tension, and cranial techniques may also be used at the discretion of the treating physician. The treatment will conclude with 2 minutes of pedal lymphatic pumping. The total treatment time will not to exceed 20 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will wait in another room for approximately 30 minutes.
To encourage participation in the proposed study, participants who are assigned to the control group will have an opportunity to receive OMT after the second blood draw</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The Osteopathic Manipulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The types of OMT techniques used will include muscle energy, articular, or high velocity-low amplitude (HVLA) as indicated by the physical findings and will be at the discretion of the treating physician. Additional techniques such as still, counter strain, facilitated positional release, balanced ligamentous tension, and cranial techniques may also be used at the discretion of the treating physician. The treatment will conclude with 2 minutes of pedal lymphatic pumping</description>
    <arm_group_label>The OMT group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  experienced at least one or more episodes of LBP in the past two weeks

          -  BMI (body mass index) &lt; 30 kg/m2

          -  be able to lie on my back for 30 minutes

          -  be able to tolerate OMT

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Have spinal manipulation in the 48 hours prior to the study date

          -  Have corticosteroids in the 2 weeks prior to the study date

          -  Have nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medication in the 48 hours prior to the study data

          -  Have spinal surgery in the lumbar or low thoracic spine

          -  Have congenital deformities of the lumbar spine such as spina bifida
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wayne Zhou, Ph. D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>A.T. Still University of Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>A. T. Still University of Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kirksville</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 11, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteopathic manipulation</keyword>
  <keyword>low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>immune cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

