<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03257904</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SynapseICU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03257904</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>iNtrAcranial PreSsurE in ICU Intensive Care (ICU) (SynapseICU)</brief_title>
  <acronym>SynapseICU</acronym>
  <official_title>International Prospective Observational StudY on iNtrAcranial PreSsurE in Intensive Care (ICU) (SynapseICU)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Milano Bicocca</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Society of Intensive Care Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Milano Bicocca</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intracranial pressure (ICP) monitoring is the most common neuromonitoring modality used in
      neurocritical care (NCCU) around the world. Uncertainties remain around intracranial pressure
      monitoring both in traumatic and non-traumatic brain injury, and variation in clinical
      practice of intracranial pressure monitoring exists between neurocritical care units.

      The objectives of the study will explore intracranial pressure monitoring variation in
      practice to prioritise uncertainties in the clinical management of critical care patients
      with acute brain injury and support further collaborative hypotheses-based prospective
      studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intracranial pressure (ICP) monitoring is the most common neuromonitoring modality used in
      neurocritical care (NCCU) around the world. Uncertainties remain around intracranial pressure
      monitoring both in traumatic and non-traumatic brain injury, and variation in clinical
      practice of intracranial pressure monitoring monitoring exists between neurocritical care
      units.

      The objectives of the study will explore intracranial pressure monitoring variation in
      practice to prioritise uncertainties in the clinical management of critical care patients
      with acute brain injury and support further collaborative hypotheses-based prospective
      studies.

      Sample Size: This international prospective observational study aims to recruit &gt;5000
      patients in coma after acute traumatic and non-traumatic brain damage admitted to &gt;200
      Intensive Care Units.

      Inclusion Criteria:

        -  Acute brain injury (ABI) admitted to ICU following:

             1. Hemorrhagic stroke, including intracerebral hematoma and subarachnoid haemorrhage,

             2. Traumatic brain injury (penetrating and non-penetrating).

        -  Age &gt;18 years old

        -  Motor score of the Glasgow Coma Scale on admission to ICU &lt;6

      Exclusion Criteria:

        -  Acute brain injury due to causes other than the one specified in the inclusion criteria.

        -  Age &lt;18 years old

        -  Motor score of the Glasgow Coma Scale on admission to ICU = 6

      Outcome measures:

      Glasgow Outcome Score-Extended at 6 months

      Endpoint:

      The primary endpoint of the study is the exploration of the effect size of the variation in
      clinical practice around intracranial pressure monitoring in acute brain injury patients.

      Screening and recruitment: 12 weeks at each centre.

      Follow-up: outcome measures will be collected at 6 months.

      Duration of study: 2 years.

      The SYNAPSE-ICU study is partly funded by ESICM (ESICM Trials Group Portfolio).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term outcome measures of neurological disability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Extended Glasgow Outcome Scale score
Long-term outcome measures of neurological disability
Mortality/Disability</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</condition>
  <condition>Intracerebral Hemorrhage</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intracranial pressure monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>measurement of intracranial pressure</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Haemorrhagic stroke, including intracerebral hematoma and subarachnoid haemorrhage,
        Traumatic brain injury
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute brain injury (ABI) admitted to ICU following

          -  Haemorrhagic stroke, including intracerebral hematoma and subarachnoid haemorrhage

          -  Traumatic brain injury (penetrating and non-penetrating)

          -  Age &gt;18 years old Motor score of the Glasgow Coma Scale on admission to ICU &lt; 6

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute brain injury due to causes other than the one specified in the inclusion
             criteria

          -  Age &lt; 18
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giuseppe Citerio</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Milano Bicocca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Giuseppe Citerio</last_name>
    <phone>+390392334316</phone>
    <email>gciterio@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lara Prisco</last_name>
    <phone>+44 7901 192056</phone>
    <email>priscolara@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASST-Monza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monza</city>
        <state>MB</state>
        <zip>20900</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giuseppe Citerio, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+390392334316</phone>
      <email>giuseppe.citerio@unimib.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stocchetti N, Carbonara M, Citerio G, Ercole A, Skrifvars MB, Smielewski P, Zoerle T, Menon DK. Severe traumatic brain injury: targeted management in the intensive care unit. Lancet Neurol. 2017 Jun;16(6):452-464. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(17)30118-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28504109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carney N, Totten AM, O'Reilly C, Ullman JS, Hawryluk GW, Bell MJ, Bratton SL, Chesnut R, Harris OA, Kissoon N, Rubiano AM, Shutter L, Tasker RC, Vavilala MS, Wilberger J, Wright DW, Ghajar J. Guidelines for the Management of Severe Traumatic Brain Injury, Fourth Edition. Neurosurgery. 2017 Jan 1;80(1):6-15. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0000000000001432.</citation>
    <PMID>27654000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cnossen MC, Scholten AC, Lingsma HF, Synnot A, Tavender E, Gantner D, Lecky F, Steyerberg EW, Polinder S. Adherence to Guidelines in Adult Patients with Traumatic Brain Injury: A Living Systematic Review. J Neurotrauma. 2016 Aug 25. doi: 10.1089/neu.2015.4121. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>26431625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Helbok R, Olson DM, Le Roux PD, Vespa P; Participants in the International Multidisciplinary Consensus Conference on Multimodality Monitoring. Intracranial pressure and cerebral perfusion pressure monitoring in non-TBI patients: special considerations. Neurocrit Care. 2014 Dec;21 Suppl 2:S85-94. doi: 10.1007/s12028-014-0040-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25208677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chesnut RM, Bleck TP, Citerio G, Classen J, Cooper DJ, Coplin WM, Diringer MN, Grände PO, Hemphill JC 3rd, Hutchinson PJ, Le Roux P, Mayer SA, Menon DK, Myburgh JA, Okonkwo DO, Robertson CS, Sahuquillo J, Stocchetti N, Sung G, Temkin N, Vespa PM, Videtta W, Yonas H. A Consensus-Based Interpretation of the Benchmark Evidence from South American Trials: Treatment of Intracranial Pressure Trial. J Neurotrauma. 2015 Nov 15;32(22):1722-4. doi: 10.1089/neu.2015.3976. Epub 2015 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26061135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hemphill JC 3rd, Greenberg SM, Anderson CS, Becker K, Bendok BR, Cushman M, Fung GL, Goldstein JN, Macdonald RL, Mitchell PH, Scott PA, Selim MH, Woo D; American Heart Association Stroke Council; Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing; Council on Clinical Cardiology. Guidelines for the Management of Spontaneous Intracerebral Hemorrhage: A Guideline for Healthcare Professionals From the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2015 Jul;46(7):2032-60. doi: 10.1161/STR.0000000000000069. Epub 2015 May 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26022637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chesnut R, Videtta W, Vespa P, Le Roux P; Participants in the International Multidisciplinary Consensus Conference on Multimodality Monitoring. Intracranial pressure monitoring: fundamental considerations and rationale for monitoring. Neurocrit Care. 2014 Dec;21 Suppl 2:S64-84. doi: 10.1007/s12028-014-0048-y. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25208680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Le Roux P, Menon DK, Citerio G, Vespa P, Bader MK, Brophy GM, Diringer MN, Stocchetti N, Videtta W, Armonda R, Badjatia N, Böesel J, Chesnut R, Chou S, Claassen J, Czosnyka M, De Georgia M, Figaji A, Fugate J, Helbok R, Horowitz D, Hutchinson P, Kumar M, McNett M, Miller C, Naidech A, Oddo M, Olson D, O'Phelan K, Provencio JJ, Puppo C, Riker R, Robertson C, Schmidt M, Taccone F; Neurocritical Care Society; European Society of Intensive Care Medicine. Consensus summary statement of the International Multidisciplinary Consensus Conference on Multimodality Monitoring in Neurocritical Care : a statement for healthcare professionals from the Neurocritical Care Society and the European Society of Intensive Care Medicine. Intensive Care Med. 2014 Sep;40(9):1189-209. doi: 10.1007/s00134-014-3369-6. Epub 2014 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25138226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stocchetti N, Maas AI. Traumatic intracranial hypertension. N Engl J Med. 2014 Sep 4;371(10):972. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1407775.</citation>
    <PMID>25184881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilson JT, Pettigrew LE, Teasdale GM. Structured interviews for the Glasgow Outcome Scale and the extended Glasgow Outcome Scale: guidelines for their use. J Neurotrauma. 1998 Aug;15(8):573-85.</citation>
    <PMID>9726257</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cossu G, Messerer M, Stocchetti N, Levivier M, Daniel RT, Oddo M. Intracranial pressure and outcome in critically ill patients with aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage: a systematic review. Minerva Anestesiol. 2016 Jun;82(6):684-96. Epub 2016 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27045637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Citerio G, Oddo M, Taccone FS. Recommendations for the use of multimodal monitoring in the neurointensive care unit. Curr Opin Crit Care. 2015 Apr;21(2):113-9. doi: 10.1097/MCC.0000000000000179. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25689123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stocchetti N, Le Roux P, Vespa P, Oddo M, Citerio G, Andrews PJ, Stevens RD, Sharshar T, Taccone FS, Vincent JL. Clinical review: neuromonitoring - an update. Crit Care. 2013 Jan 15;17(1):201. doi: 10.1186/cc11513. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23320763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Milano Bicocca</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Giuseppe Citerio, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>intracranial pressure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

