<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03250299</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ABTC 1601</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDI-CS-004</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB00131687</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03250299</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Microtubule-Targeted Agent BAL101553 and Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Newly Diagnosed Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study to Determine the Safety and Tolerability of the Oral Microtubule Destabilizer BAL101553 in Combination With Standard Radiation in Patients With MGMT Promoter Unmethylated Newly Diagnosed Glioblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Basilea Pharmaceutica</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of microtubule-targeted agent
      BAL101553 when given together with radiation therapy in treating patients with newly
      diagnosed glioblastoma. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as microtubule-targeted agent
      BAL101553, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the
      cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Radiation therapy
      uses high-energy x-rays to kill tumor cells and shrink tumors. Giving microtubule-targeted
      agent BAL101553 and radiation therapy may work better in treating patients with glioblastoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the maximum tolerated dose of microtubule-targeted agent BAL101553
      (BAL101553) in combination with standard radiation in patients with newly diagnosed MGMT
      promoter unmethylated glioblastoma (GBM).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To estimate safety and tolerability of the combination of BAL101553 in combination with
      standard radiation in patients with newly diagnosed MGMT promoter unmethylated GBM.

      II. To determine overall and progression-free survival. III. To assess the pharmacokinetics
      of BAL101553 and BAL27862. IV. To explore expression of biomarkers, including BubR1, stathmin
      and EB1 at baseline (exploratory biomarkers).

      OUTLINE: This is a dose escalation study of the microtubule-targeted agent BAL101553.

      Patients receive microtubule-targeted agent BAL101553 orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days
      1-42 and undergo concomitant standard radiation therapy 5 days per week for 6 weeks in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days, and then every 2
      months for 2 years and then every 6 months thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Dose Escalation study Starting dose, 8mg with 3 escalations 15,20, 25mg.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Dose limited Toxicities per dose level. ANC &lt; 500mm3; Platelets &lt; 25K; Febrile neutropenia; any event which prevents 80% administration of planned BAL101553 dose; &gt;/= gr 2 CNS ischemia; &gt;/= gr 2 neurological toxicities interfering with AODL not resolved within 2wks; gr 3/4 non-hematological, non-CNS toxicities with expections</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with Grade 3 and Grade 4 AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>CTC AE 4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>initial diagnosis to date of death - up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Median time of survival along with 95% confidence interval</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>initial diagnosis to date of progression - up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Median time of progression-free survival along with 95% confidence interval</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Plasma Concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours post dose on days 1 and 22</time_frame>
    <description>PK of microtubule-targeted agent BAL101553 and BAL27862</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of Maximum Plasma Concentraion</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours post dose on days 1 and 22</time_frame>
    <description>PK of microtubule-targeted agent BAL101553 and BAL27862</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-time Curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours post dose on days 1 and 22</time_frame>
    <description>PK of microtubule-targeted agent BAL101553 and BAL27862</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Half-life</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours post dose on days 1 and 22</time_frame>
    <description>PK of microtubule-targeted agent BAL101553 and BAL27862</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Clearance and Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours post dose on days 1 and 22</time_frame>
    <description>PK of microtubule-targeted agent BAL101553 and BAL27862</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>MGMT-Unmethylated Glioblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1 8mg - BAL101553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>8mg BAL101553 PO (7 days per week), combined with RT days 1-5 for 6 weeks followed by 4 week rest. Off treatment after 4 week rest.
Microtubule-targeted Agent BAL101553 Radiation Therapy Laboratory Biomarker Analysis Pharmacological Study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 2 15mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15mg BAL101553 PO(7 days per week), combined with RT days 1-5 for 6 weeks followed by 4 week rest. Off treatment after 4 week rest.
Microtubule-targeted Agent BAL101553 Radiation Therapy Laboratory Biomarker Analysis Pharmacological Study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 3 20mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20mg BAL101553 PO(7 days per week), combined with RT days 1-5 for 6 weeks followed by 4 week rest. Off treatment after 4 week rest.
Microtubule-targeted Agent BAL101553 Radiation Therapy Laboratory Biomarker Analysis Pharmacological Study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 4 25mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25mg BAL101553 (7 days per week), combined with RT days 1-5 for 6 weeks followed by 4 week rest. Off treatment after 4 week rest.
Microtubule-targeted Agent BAL101553 Radiation Therapy Laboratory Biomarker Analysis Pharmacological Study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microtubule-Targeted Agent BAL101553</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1 8mg - BAL101553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 2 15mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 3 20mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 4 25mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BAL101553, Microtubule-targeted Agent BAL101553</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1 8mg - BAL101553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 2 15mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 3 20mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 4 25mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cancer Radiotherapy, Irradiate, irradiated, irradiation, RADIATION, Radiation, radiation therapy, Radiation Therapy, Radiotherapeutics, radiotherapy, Radiotherapy, RT, Therapy, Radiation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1 8mg - BAL101553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 2 15mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 3 20mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 4 25mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1 8mg - BAL101553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 2 15mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 3 20mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 4 25mg - BAL10553</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically-proven GBM

          -  Patients must have recovered from the immediate post-operative period

          -  Patients must have tumor MGMT methylation status of unmethylated as determined by
             local pathologist using a Clinical Laboratory Improvement Act (CLIA)-approved
             diagnostic test; results of routinely-used methods for MGMT methylation testing (e.g.
             methylation-specific [MS]- polymerase chain reaction [PCR] or quantitative PCR) are
             acceptable

          -  Patients must be able to undergo magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain with
             gadolinium

          -  Patients must not have received prior radiation therapy (RT), chemotherapy,
             immunotherapy or therapy with a biologic agent (including immunotoxins,
             immunoconjugates, antisense, peptide receptor antagonists, interferons, interleukins,
             tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes, lymphokine-activated killer cells, or gene therapy),
             or hormonal therapy for their brain tumor; glucocorticoid therapy is allowed

          -  Patients must have a tumor tissue form indicating availability of archived tissue from
             initial resection at diagnosis of GBM, completed and signed by a pathologist

          -  Patients must have a Karnofsky performance status &gt;= 60% (i.e. the patient must be
             able to care for himself/herself with occasional help from others)

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN), unless the patient
             has known Gilbert's syndrome

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels &gt; ULN

          -  Activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT)/partial thromboplastin time (PTT) =&lt; 1.5
             x ULN

          -  Sodium &gt;= 130 mmol/L

          -  Patients must be able to provide written informed consent

          -  Patients must have baseline MRI performed within the 21 days prior to starting
             treatment

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 72
             hours prior to the first dose of BAL101553; women of childbearing potential must agree
             to use highly-effective contraceptive methods for the duration of study participation
             and for an additional 90 days after the last dose of study drug; highly-effective
             contraceptive methods include male or female sterilization (bilateral tubal occlusion
             or vasectomy); intrauterine device (IUD); combined (estrogen- and
             progesterone-containing) hormonal contraception (oral, vaginal ring or transdermal
             patch) with an ethinylestradiol dose of at least 30 ug, plus use of male condoms
             (preferably with spermicides), female condoms, a female diaphragm or a cervical cap;
             or total sexual abstinence; should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant
             while participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician
             immediately; male patients must agree not to donate sperm from the first dose of study
             drug until 90 days after the end of treatment; male patients, without a vasectomy and
             with a partner of childbearing potential, must agree to use condoms during the study
             and for at least 90 days after the end of treatment; the patient should be instructed
             that their female partner should use another form of contraception for the duration of
             the study and continue this use for at least 90 days after the last dose of study drug

          -  Patients must have no concurrent malignancy except curatively treated basal or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or carcinoma in situ of the cervix, breast, or
             bladder; patients with prior malignancies must be disease-free for &gt;= 5 years

          -  Patients must be maintained on a stable corticosteroid regimen (no increase for 5
             days) prior to the start of treatment

          -  Patients must be able to swallow whole capsules

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to BAL101553

          -  Patients on drugs that are strong inhibitors and/or inducers of CYP2C9, CYP2C19 or
             CYP3A4 (including enzyme-inducing anti-epileptic drugs [EIAEDs]), are not eligible for
             treatment under this protocol; patients taking non-EIAEDs are permitted to take part
             in the study; patients previously treated with any of the prohibited concomitant
             medications listed above may be enrolled if they have been off of the medication for
             &gt;= 10 days prior to the first dose of BAL101553

          -  Patients may not be on coumarin anti-coagulants (warfarin, etc.); heparin,
             low-molecular weight heparin (LMWH), or other antithrombotic medications are permitted

          -  Patients with gastrointestinal disease, or those who have had a procedure that is
             expected to interfere with the oral absorption or tolerance of BAL101553 (e.g.,
             functionally-relevant gastrointestinal obstruction, or frequent vomiting unresolved
             upon anti-emetic supportive care)

          -  Patients with peripheral neuropathy &gt;= Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
             (CTCAE) grade 2

          -  Patients with ataxia &gt;= CTCAE grade 2

          -  Patients with known acute or chronic hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection \

          -  Patients with systolic blood pressure (SBP) &gt;= 140 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure
             (DBP) &gt;= 90 mmHg at the screening visit are ineligible; patients with an initial
             clinic blood pressure (BP) &gt;= 140/90 mmHg may be included if SBP &lt; 140 mmHg and DBP &lt;
             90 mmHg is confirmed in two subsequent BP measurements on the same day

          -  Patients with blood pressure (BP) combination treatment with more than two
             antihypertensive medications are ineligible

          -  Significant cardiac disease or abnormality, including any one of the following:

               -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 50% at screening (assessed by
                  echocardiography, cardiac MRI or multigated acquisition [MUGA])

               -  Corrected QT Fridericia's correction formula (QTcF) &gt; 470 ms on screening
                  electrocardiogram (ECG), or a clinically-relevant ECG abnormality

               -  Congenital long QT syndrome

               -  History of sustained ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, or
                  torsades de pointes

               -  Presence of atrial fibrillation with tachyarrhythmia (ventricular response rate &gt;
                  100 beats per minute [bpm])

               -  Bradycardia (heart rate &lt; 50 bpm)

               -  Complete left bundle branch block.

               -  Bifascicular block (complete right bundle branch block and anterior or posterior
                  left hemiblock)

               -  Myocardial infarction, acute coronary syndrome (including unstable angina),
                  coronary revascularization procedures, or coronary arterial bypass grafting
                  within the 6 months prior to starting study drug

               -  Cardiac troponin (either troponin T or troponin I) &gt; ULN

               -  Congestive heart failure of New York Heart Association class III or IV

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing
             or active infection or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
             compliance with study requirements, are ineligible

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with BAL101553

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are ineligible
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthias Holdhoff, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UAB Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294-3410</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber/Harvard Cancer Center at Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henry Ford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest University Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Taussig Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abrams Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hillman Cancer Center at University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

