<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00109642</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050147</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-M-0147</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00109642</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Role of Norepinephrine in Emotional Processing</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigating the Role of Norepinephrine in Emotional Processing Through Alpha-2 Adrenergic Receptor Modulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the role of a brain chemical called norepinephrine in thinking,
      decision-making, and emotional processing. After norepinephrine is released from a brain
      cell, it binds to another brain cell's receptor. Some of the receptors it binds to are called
      alpha-2 adrenergic receptors. This study will use medicines called yohimbine and guanfacine
      to look at the function of norepinephrine in the brain when it binds to the alpha-2
      adrenergic receptors. Yohimbine increases norepinephrine's function and guanfacine decreases
      its function.

      Healthy volunteers between 20 and 50 years of age who do not have heart disease, high blood
      pressure, psychiatric illness, or other serious medical conditions and who are not allergic
      to lactose may be eligible for this study. Candidates are screened with a medical and
      psychiatric history, physical examination, neuropsychological testing, blood and urine tests
      and electrocardiogram. Women are screened with a urine pregnancy test.

      Participants are given a pill of yohimbine, guanfacine, or placebo and undergo the following
      tests and procedures:

        -  Blood pressure and heart rate measurements: Blood pressure and heart rate are measured
           before the medication is taken and several times after.

        -  Blood draws: Blood is drawn before the medicine is taken and 90 minutes after to measure
           levels of norepinephrine and the hormone cortisol.

        -  Neurocognitive testing: Participants do neurocognitive tasks on the computer for up to
           90 minutes. The tasks involve looking at pictures or words on a screen and responding
           according to instructions given.

        -  Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI): Patients may undergo neurocognitive testing MRIs. This
           test uses a strong magnetic field and radio waves to show changes in brain activity. The
           subject lies on a table that slides into a narrow cylinder (the MRI scanner). Images of
           the brain are obtained while the subject performs the computer tasks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An understanding of the role of specific neurotransmitters in the neurocognitive functions
      mediating emotional processing is essential for the understanding and treatment of mood and
      anxiety disorders. One such disorder, currently regarded as untreatable, is psychopathy.
      Psychopathy has been linked with noradrenergic and amygdala disturbances. However, an
      understanding of the functional significance of the noradrenergic system in humans remains in
      its infancy. The goal of this protocol is to use targeted noradrenergic manipulations
      (yohimbine and guanfacine) in conjunction with specific neurocognitive and neuroimaging
      paradigms to consider the role of norepinephrine in reward and punishment processing. In
      particular, we wish to evaluate the hypothesis that increased norepinephrine levels following
      the administration of yohimbine will lead to enhanced formation and processing of
      stimulus-reward and stimulus-punishment associations, while decreased norepinephrine levels
      following the administration of guanfacine will reduce the formation and processing of
      stimulus-reward and stimulus-punishment associations. In addition, we aim to examine the
      hypothesis that increased norepinephrine levels will lead to increased neural response in the
      amygdala during either the formation, or processing, of stimulus-reinforcement associations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 26, 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>216</enrollment>
  <condition>Psychopathy</condition>
  <condition>Mental Disorders</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Age: Participants will be males and females, 20-50 years of age.

        IQ: IQ, as measured by 4 subscales from the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale-Revised
        (WAIS-R), must be greater than 80.

        Medication status: No current use of any psychotropic medication or benzodiazepine.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Because factors such as psychiatric disease, or CNS disease, can influence functional brain
        activity, these factors are exclusionary:

          -  Psychiatric History: Participants will be assessed using DSM-IV criteria via
             standardized psychiatric interviews conducted by trained examiners (SCID). All
             participants will be free of any current or past major affective disorder, psychotic
             disorder, substance dependence, anorexia, somatoform disorder, or anxiety disorders
             with the exception of specific phobias.

          -  Severe acute and chronic medical illnesses (e.g. cardiac disease, diabetes, epilepsy).

          -  CNS disease: Known history of brain abnormalities (e.g., neoplasms, subarachnoid
             cysts), cerebrovascular disease, infectious disease (e.g., abscess), other central
             nervous system disease, or history of head trauma which resulted in a persistent
             neurologic deficit or loss of consciousness greater than 3 minutes.

          -  Currently on regular medication that would interfere with study results. This includes
             alpha and beta adrenergic medications, other anti-hypertensive medications,
             glucocorticoid and mineralocorticoid medications, and medications causing sedation or
             stimulation. For example, current use of tylenol or ibuprofen is permitted, while
             current use of benadryl or methylphenidate is not. Use of oral contraceptive pills is
             permitted.

          -  Currently breast feeding or pregnant (as documented by pregnancy testing at screening
             or at days of the challenge studies).

        Additional exclusion criteria for fMRI studies:

          -  Metal or electronic objects: Metal plates, certain types of dental braces, cardiac
             pacemakers, etc., that are sensitive to electromagnetic fields contraindicate MRI
             scans.

          -  Claustrophobia: participants will be questioned about potential discomfort in being in
             an enclosed space, such as an MRI scanner.

          -  Body weight - to reduce the likelihood of significant orthostasis from guanfacine,
             participants must weigh 60kg or greater. Those weighing less than 60 kg will be
             excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adolphs R. Neural systems for recognizing emotion. Curr Opin Neurobiol. 2002 Apr;12(2):169-77. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12015233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arnsten AF. Adrenergic targets for the treatment of cognitive deficits in schizophrenia. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2004 Jun;174(1):25-31. Epub 2003 Dec 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15205875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aron AR, Fletcher PC, Bullmore ET, Sahakian BJ, Robbins TW. Stop-signal inhibition disrupted by damage to right inferior frontal gyrus in humans. Nat Neurosci. 2003 Feb;6(2):115-6. Erratum in: Nat Neurosci. 2003 Dec;6(12):1329.</citation>
    <PMID>12536210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 8, 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Amygdala</keyword>
  <keyword>Orbitofrontal Cortex</keyword>
  <keyword>Yohimbine</keyword>
  <keyword>Emotion</keyword>
  <keyword>Guanfacine</keyword>
  <keyword>Norepinephrine</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Norepinephrine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

