<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00102258</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050077</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-CH-0077</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00102258</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of Nutrition and Hormones in Boys With Disordered Growth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Nutrients and Hormones: Effects in Boys With Disordered Growth - Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will determine whether adding more calories to the diet helps boys with growth
      problems grow better while being treated with Nutropin, a growth hormone that is used to help
      children grow taller. The Food and Drug Administration has approved Nutropin for use in
      children who are very short. This study will examine whether giving nutritional supplements
      in addition to Nutropin can help children grow better than with Nutropin alone.

      Boys between 7 and 10 years of age who are very short and below average in weight, but are
      otherwise healthy may be eligible for this study. Candidates must qualify for Nutropin
      treatments to boost their growth. Boys will be recruited for the study from the Nemours
      Children's Clinic in Jacksonville, FL, and from the National Institutes of Health in
      Bethesda, MD.

      Participants are randomly assigned to one of two treatment groups. One group is observed for
      6 months and then receives a Nutropin injection every day for 12 months. The second group
      drinks 8 ounces of a high-calorie beverage called Pediasure every day for 6 months and then
      receives Nutropin plus Pediasure every day for 12 months. In addition to treatment,
      participants undergo the following tests and procedures at the schedule indicated: Baseline,
      3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18 months

        -  Clinical examination

        -  Height measurement

        -  Body composition assessment: Skin-fold thickness calipers are used in four places on the
           body to estimate body fat

        -  Bioelectric impedance: A small amount of electrical current is used to calculate the
           percentage of body fat.

      Baseline, 6, 12, and 18 months

        -  Blood tests

        -  Bone age x-ray: x-ray of the left hand to measure growth potential

        -  DEXA (dual energy x-ray absorptiometry) scan: x-ray scan to measure body fat, muscle,
           and bone mineral content. The subject lies on a flat table during the scan.

      Baseline, 6, and 12 months

        -  Record of dietary intake: Parents are asked to write down everything the child eats and
           drinks for 3 days. Using this record, a dietitian calculates the daily caloric intake.

        -  Total energy expenditure: This test determines how much energy the child uses. For the
           test, the child drinks water labeled with harmless isotopes (heavy oxygen and heavy
           hydrogen). For the next 10 days he collects urine in plastic tubes at home. At the end
           of the 10 days, the parents bring the urine to the clinic for analysis to determine how
           fast the labeled water leaves the body. This information is used to calculate how much
           energy the child expends each day.

      Participants' weight is measured at 2 and 4 weeks, and then monthly for the remainder of the
      18-month study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We propose a pilot study to examine the role of nutrition and its interaction with growth
      hormone (GH) therapy in boys with very short stature who also have delayed bone age
      characteristic of constitutional delay of growth and maturation (CDGM). Recent studies have
      suggested that insufficient caloric intake may contribute to the pathophysiology of CDGM.
      This prompted us to consider whether nutritional intervention may benefit children with
      severe short stature who also have CDGM.

      To investigate this further, we would like to enroll a total of 20 boys (10-15 boys in
      Jacksonville, Florida and 5-10 boys at the NIH, Bethesda, Maryland), ages 7-10 years, who are
      otherwise healthy, but have significant short stature (height SDS less than -2.25 = the
      current FDA approved indication for the use of GH in idiopathic short stature), delayed bone
      age (greater than 12 months below chronologic age), and low BMI and weight-for-height (less
      than 25th percentile). Ten boys will be randomized to receive observation for 6 months,
      followed by GH therapy for 12 months. Ten boys will be randomized to receive daily liquid
      nutritional supplementation for 6 months, followed by combined GH therapy and nutritional
      supplementation for 12 months. For all subjects, weight gain will be monitored at 2 weeks, 4
      weeks, and then monthly. Height gain and body composition (using skin-fold thickness calipers
      and bioelectric impedance analysis) will be assessed every 3 months. Total energy
      expenditure, three-day dietary history, bone age, body composition/bone mineral density
      (using dual energy X-ray absorptiometry), and laboratory studies (IGF1, IGFBP3, pre-albumin,
      transferrin, ghrelin, fasting insulin, glucose, and lipid profile) will be obtained at
      baseline and then every 6 months.

      We hypothesize that nutritional supplementation alone can lead to small improvements in
      linear growth and lean body mass accrual, but when combined with GH therapy, can augment the
      anabolic actions of GH, thereby resulting in even greater improvements in linear growth
      velocity and lean body mass accrual than GH alone. If the data from this study confirm this
      trend, we would then like to proceed with a larger study, appropriately powered based on the
      results of this pilot.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 19, 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2, 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>20</enrollment>
  <condition>Short Stature</condition>
  <condition>Constitutional Delay of Growth and Development</condition>
  <condition>Dwarfism, Pituitary</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Growth Hormone Therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

        Age 7-10 years, genital Tanner 1, significant short stature (current height less than
        2.25SD below the mean for age), body mass index (BMI) less than 25th percentile for age,
        weight-for-height less than 25th percentile, bone age less than 10 years and with delay
        greater than 1 year below chronological age, minimum of 6 months of documented height
        measurements performed in the pediatric endocrinology clinic using a stadiometer to permit
        accurate calculation of baseline growth velocity at time of enrollment, otherwise normal
        physical exam, expressed desire for medical intervention to promote growth, and assessment
        by a pediatric endocrinologist that the boy qualifies for GH treatment according to current
        FDA guidelines for the use of GH in children with idiopathic short stature (i.e., children
        who are determined not to have growth hormone deficiency but have height less than -2.25SD
        below the mean for age).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        History of major/chronic illness, anosmia/hyposmia, any clinically significant
        abnormalities on biochemical testing. GH deficiency would be excluded prior to enrollment
        based on anthropometric and GH stimulation test data. Endocrinopathies (except stable
        thyroid replacement), skeletal dysplasias, participation in highly competitive endurance
        sports activities, diagnosis of ADHD with use of stimulant medication in the previous 3
        months will also be exclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nemours Children's Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leschek EW, Rose SR, Yanovski JA, Troendle JF, Quigley CA, Chipman JJ, Crowe BJ, Ross JL, Cassorla FG, Blum WF, Cutler GB Jr, Baron J; National Institute of Child Health and Human Development-Eli Lilly &amp; Co. Growth Hormone Collaborative Group. Effect of growth hormone treatment on adult height in peripubertal children with idiopathic short stature: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2004 Jul;89(7):3140-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15240584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2, 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 26, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Short Stature</keyword>
  <keyword>Constitutional Delay of Growth and Development</keyword>
  <keyword>Body Composition</keyword>
  <keyword>Energy Expenditure</keyword>
  <keyword>Dietary Supplements</keyword>
  <keyword>Constitutional Delay of Growth</keyword>
  <keyword>CDGM</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dwarfism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dwarfism, Pituitary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

