<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00101244</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2012-03193</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>C-2818</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA062487</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000404369</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00101244</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SB-715992 in Treating Patients With Metastatic or Unresectable Solid Tumors or Hodgkin's or Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation Study of SB-715992 Administered Days 1-3 of a 21-Day Cycle in Patients With Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial is studying the side effects and best dose of SB-715992 in treating
      patients with metastatic or unresectable solid tumors or Hodgkin's or non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.
      Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as SB-715992, work in different ways to stop the growth of
      cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety and tolerability of SB-715992 administered as a 1-hr intravenous
      infusion on days 1-3 of a 21-day cycle in patients with solid tumors.

      II. To determine the dose limiting toxicity (DLT) and maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of
      SB-715992 for this administration schedule.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To observe clinical response of SB-715992 given days 1-3, every 21-days. II. To
      characterize the pharmacokinetics (PK) of SB-715992 for this administration schedule.

      III. To explore drug metabolism, molecular and cellular predictors of efficacy (biomarkers)
      and toxicity and drug interaction potential.

      OUTLINE: This is an open-label, dose-escalation, multicenter study.

      Patients receive SB-715992 IV over 1 hour on days 1-3. Courses repeat every 21 days in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of SB-715992 until the maximum tolerated
      dose (MTD) is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2
      of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity. Up to 10 additional patients are treated at
      the MTD

      Patients are followed for 4 weeks.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 18-31 patients will be accrued for this study within 11-19
      months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Administratively Complete.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2004</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD), based on the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 21 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical response (complete response [CR], partial response [PR], and response duration) based on the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 years</time_frame>
    <description>Both point and confidence interval estimates of response rate will be calculated for all eligible patients (the intention to treat population), and for response-evaluable patients (the per-protocol population). Response duration will be calculated using the standard Kaplan-Meier estimator for a censored time-to-event endpoint.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma ispinesib concentration levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 24</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics will be computed, including both point and confidence interval estimates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre- and post-treatment intra-tumoral drug levels (from tumor-accessible, consenting patients only)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 3</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics will be computed, including both point and confidence interval estimates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cluster of differentiation (CD)34+ stem cell levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics will be computed, including both point and confidence interval estimates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">31</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Grade III Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</condition>
  <condition>Extranodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma of Mucosa-associated Lymphoid Tissue</condition>
  <condition>Nodal Marginal Zone B-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Small Cleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Grade III Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Splenic Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Diffuse Small Cleaved Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 1 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 2 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Marginal Zone Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <condition>Waldenström Macroglobulinemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ispinesib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive SB-715992 IV over 1 hour on days 1-3. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of SB-715992 until the MTD is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity. Up to 10 additional patients are treated at the MTD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ispinesib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ispinesib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CK0238273</other_name>
    <other_name>SB-715992</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ispinesib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ispinesib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed malignancy that is metastatic or
             unresectable and for which standard curative or palliative measures do not exist or
             are no longer effective; patients with solid hematologic malignancies (Hodgkin's and
             non-Hodgkin's lymphomas) may be included as long as a bone marrow has been performed
             within 6 weeks of enrollment

          -  Prior chemotherapy is allowed; patients may not have received chemotherapy for 4 weeks
             prior to the initiation of study treatment and must have full recovery from the acute
             effects of any prior chemotherapy; patients must not have had nitrosoureas or
             mitomycin C for 6 weeks prior to initiation of study treatment

          -  Prior radiation therapy is allowed; patients must have completed radiation at least 4
             weeks prior to initiation of study treatment; patients who have received prior
             radiation to 50% or more of their total marrow volume will be excluded

          -  Prior treatment with EGFR inhibitors is allowed; prior experimental therapies (non
             FDA-approved agents) and immunotherapies are allowed; patients may not have received
             these therapies for 4 weeks prior to the initiation of study treatment and must have a
             full recovery from the acute effects of these therapies

          -  ECOG performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Life expectancy of &gt; 12 weeks

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/uL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/uL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; normal institutional limits

          -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) =&lt; 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 X institutional upper limit of normal OR creatinine clearance
             (calculated) or measured clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine
             levels above institutional normal

          -  The effects of SB-715992 on the developing human fetus are unknown; for this reason
             and because mitotic inhibitors are known to be teratogenic, women of child-bearing
             potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method
             of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of study
             participation; should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to entering the study or those who have not
             recovered from acute AEs due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier

          -  Patients may not have received any other investigational agents within 28 days of
             study entry

          -  Patients may not receive any other anti-cancer therapy (cytotoxic, biologic,
             radiation, or hormonal other than for replacement) while on this study except for
             medications that are prescribed for supportive care but potentially may have
             anticancer effect (i.e. megestrol acetate, bisphosphonates); these medications must
             have been started 1 month prior to enrollment on study; in addition, men receiving
             treatment for prostate cancer will be maintained at castrate levels of testosterone by
             continuation of luteinizing- releasing hormone agonists

          -  Prohibited medications: SB-715992 is a moderate to significant in vitro inhibitor of
             CYP3A4; the following lists of medications/substances are moderate to significant
             inhibitors/inducers of CYP3A4 that, if administered concomitantly with SB-715992, may
             alter study drug exposure; the use of these medications/substances within 14 days (&gt;=
             6 months for amiodarone) prior to the administration of the first dose of SB-715992
             through discontinuation from the study is prohibited;

               -  Inhibitors of CYP3A4

                    -  Antibiotics: clarithromycin, erythromycin, troleandomycin

                    -  Antifungals: itraconazole, ketoconazole, fluconazole (doses &gt; 200 mg/day),
                       voriconazole

                    -  Antidepressants: nefazodone, fluovoxamine

                    -  Calcium channel blockers: verapamil, diltiazem

                    -  Bitter Orange

                    -  Miscellaneous: amiodarone*, grapefruit juice**; *use of amiodarone within 6
                       months prior to the administration of the first dose of SB-715992 is
                       prohibited; ** use of grapefruit juice within 7 days prior to administration
                       of the first dose of SB-715992 is prohibited

               -  Inducers of CYP3A4

                    -  Anticonvulsants: phenytoin, carbamazepine, phenobarbital

                    -  Antibiotics: rifampin, rifabutin, rifapentine

                    -  Miscellaneous: St. John's wort, modafinil, oxcarbazepine

          -  Patients with known, symptomatic or untreated brain metastases should be excluded from
             this clinical trial because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop
             progressive neurologic dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic
             and other adverse events

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because SB-715992 is a mitotic inhibitor
             with the potential for teratogenic or abortifacient effects; because there is an
             unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary to
             treatment of the mother with SB-715992, breastfeeding should be discontinued if the
             mother is treated with SB-715992

          -  Patients with immune deficiency are at increased risk of lethal infections when
             treated with marrow-suppressive therapy; therefore, HIV-positive patients receiving
             combination anti-retroviral therapy are excluded from the study because of possible
             pharmacokinetic interactions with SB-715992; appropriate studies will be undertaken in
             patients receiving combination anti-retroviral therapy when indicated

          -  Patients are ineligible for participation in the Drug Interaction study, or can be
             deemed to be ineligible to receive certain drug probes, if they have:

               -  Sensitivity to sulfa drugs or adverse reactions to sulfonylureas

               -  Concurrent antifungal medications, or within the past 4 weeks

               -  Diabetes or other glucose imbalance

               -  Acidosis

               -  Concurrent alcohol use (based on the discretion of treating physician)

               -  Concurrent phenytoin or diazepam treatment, or within the past 4 weeks

               -  Previous intolerance to benzodiazepam therapies

               -  A patient maybe excluded from all or a portion of the Drug Interaction study
                  based on the medical discretion of the investigator

               -  EVEN THOUGH PATIENTS MAY BE INELIGIBLE TO PARTICIPATE IN THE DRUG INTERACTION
                  STUDY, THEY CAN STILL PARTICIPATE IN THE PHASE I CLINICAL TRIAL
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia LoRusso</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 10, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 14, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell, Marginal Zone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Immunoblastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plasmablastic Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphomatoid Granulomatosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Extranodal NK-T-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

