<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00103467</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VAX005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00103467</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of an Anthrax Recombinant Protective Antigen Vaccine</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of an Anthrax Recombinant Protective Antigen Vaccine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VaxGen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VaxGen</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this phase 1 study is to evaluate the safety and immunogenicity of rPA102
      vaccine, using anthrax vaccine adsorbed (AVA) as a comparator.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2003</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and immunogenicity of 3 doses over 4 different dose ranges.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>100</enrollment>
  <condition>Prevention of Anthrax Infection</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rPA102 Vaccine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to understand the study and give written informed consent. A signed informed
             consent must be in place before the initiation of any study interventions.

          -  Healthy male or female aged 18 to 40 years old (inclusive) without significant
             physical or clinical laboratory abnormalities.

          -  Two intact upper arms with sufficient intramuscular (IM) tissue in the deltoid region
             for vaccine administration.

          -  For females, negative serum pregnancy test at screening and agreement to use adequate
             birth control during the first 3 months of the study.

          -  Willingness and ability to return for all follow-up visits and blood draws for the
             duration of the study.

          -  Willingness to complete the Volunteer Diary and to report concomitant medications and
             adverse events (AEs) to the study site monitors during the study period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior history of, or known exposure to any form of B. anthracis or any anthrax
             immunization.

          -  Member of the Armed Services (Active Duty or Reserve) since 1990, with history of
             previous anthrax vaccination.

          -  Employment in an industry involved in contact with ruminant animals, veterinary
             sciences, or other exposure to B. anthracis.

          -  Expected to be noncompliant with study visits or planning to move within 8 months.

          -  Body mass index of &gt;35 or &lt;19.

          -  Known allergy to aluminum hydroxide, formaldehyde, benzethonium chloride, latex,
             kanamycin, or any other aminoglycoside antibiotics (such as gentamycin).

          -  Pregnancy (positive urine pregnancy test within 24 hours prior to vaccination), or
             lactation.

          -  HIV positive (by history or screening ELISA).

          -  Hepatitis B or C positive (by history or screening HBsAg/anti-HCV ELISA).

          -  Active or past internal organ, hematologic malignancy, or metastatic cutaneous
             malignancy.

          -  History of, or current autoimmune disease, including but not limited to systemic lupus
             erythematosus, scleroderma, and polyarteritis.

          -  Immunodeficiency or unstable medical condition as determined by baseline medical
             history, physical exam, and laboratory assessment.

          -  Received, or plans to receive, licensed live vaccines within 30 days of study
             vaccination.

          -  Received, or plans to receive, licensed killed vaccines within 14 days of study
             vaccination.

          -  Received, or plans to receive, immunoglobulin or other blood products within 60 days
             of study vaccination.

          -  Received, or plans to receive, experimental drugs/vaccines within 30 days of study
             vaccination.

          -  Received, or plans to receive, systemic immunosuppresive therapy, radiation therapy,
             or high-dose inhaled steroids within 30 days of study vaccination.

          -  Use of systemic chemotherapy within 5 years prior to study.

          -  History of Guillain-Barre Syndrome.

          -  In addition to the conditions listed above, the following may qualify as a reason to
             exclude a volunteer from the study: fever along with moderate or serious illness
             within 3 days of vaccination or any condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would render vaccination unsafe or would interfere with the study
             evaluations. Pending resolution of these symptoms, a volunteer may be reconsidered for
             vaccination.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dept. of International Health - Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Louis University - SoLutions/SLUtest</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 8, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 8, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 9, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anthrax</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

