<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00100503</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050066</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-N-0066</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00100503</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain Reorganization Following Constraint-Induced Therapy in Children With Cerebral Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cortical Reorganization Following Pediatric Constraint-Induced Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine how therapy changes the way the brain controls movements in children
      with cerebral palsy. Normally, one side of the brain controls movements in the opposite side
      of the body. In cerebral palsy, however, this pattern may be different, with one side of the
      brain controlling movements on the same side of the body. This study will use magnetic
      resonance imaging (MRI) and transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) to study brain function
      in children with cerebral palsy before and after therapy.

      Children between 9 and 17 years of age with spastic hemiplegia type cerebral palsy will be
      recruited for this study from the National Rehabilitation Hospital and Georgetown University
      Center Medical Center in Washington, D.C., and the Sparks Center at UAB in Alabama. In
      addition, five healthy control children will be recruited from community groups, such as Cub
      Scouts, Brownies, and schools. Candidates are screened with a review of medical records and
      neurological and physical examinations.

      Healthy controls undergo MRI (described below) twice, 3 weeks apart. Children with cerebral
      palsy undergo the following tests and procedures:

        1. Rehabilitation evaluation at the NIH Clinical Center Rehabilitation Medicine Department.

        2. MRI: For this test, the child lies on a table that slides in and out of the MRI
           scanner-a metal cylinder surrounded by a strong magnetic field. He or she wears earplugs
           to muffle loud knocking sounds that occur during scanning. Images are obtained while the
           child performs simple finger tapping movements.

        3. Movement Testing:

             1. Finger tapping: The child taps buttons on a box hooked up to a computer

             2. Muscle reflex measurements: One method uses a small motor that makes the child's
                fingers move with sudden, small movements; a second method uses small shocks to the
                finger or wrist. The shocks feel like a buzz; most are gentle, but some might feel
                stronger.

        4. TMS: This procedure maps brain function. A wire coil is held on the scalp, and a brief
           electrical current is passed through the coil, creating a magnetic pulse that stimulates
           the brain. During the stimulation, the child may be asked to perform simple movements..
           The stimulation may cause a twitch in muscles of the face, arm, or leg, and the child
           may hear a click and feel a pulling sensation on the skin under the coil.

        5. Therapy: After these tests, children are randomly selected to receive either standard
           therapy (neurodevelopmental treatment) or constraint-induced therapy, as follows:

             1. Neurodevelopmental therapy uses principles of movement science to enhance the
                child's capacity to function. The child receives therapy a few times a week for 3
                weeks.

             2. Constraint-induced therapy uses a combination of motor learning method and
                constraint to teach the new motor skills in the child's affected hand. Children
                treated with this therapy must live near a special treatment center in Alabama for
                the 3 weeks of treatment. The child's good arm is constrained with a bivalve,
                removable cast. The cast is placed before therapy starts and remains in place
                except when the therapist removes it once a day to examine the good arm. With the
                cast on, children are encouraged to use their affected hand in new ways. The
                therapist then uses the motor learning method, building motor programs as a result
                of practice, to teach them new skills. Motor learning therapy is 6 hours a day.

        6. Post-treatment testing: After treatment, children undergo repeat rehabilitation
           assessment, MRI, TMS, and movement testing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: To determine the underlying brain reorganization that occurs in children with
      hemiplegic cerebral palsy before and after pediatric Constraint-Induced therapy.

      Background: A promising new therapy for adults with hemiparesis consequent to stroke, known
      as Constraint-Induced Movement (CI) therapy, has recently been modified for use in children
      with cerebral palsy. Children with cerebral palsy treated with CI therapy show significant
      gains in motor skills after receiving this intensive and extended treatment.

      There is evidence to suggest that, after an acute stroke in adults, the undamaged motor
      cortex exerts greater control over movements in the affected hand than is normally seen in
      neurologically intact subjects. While this might seem to be an advantage, combined functional
      magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) and transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) studies
      demonstrate that it is associated with poor motor recovery in adults after a stroke and
      impaired hand function in patients with cerebral palsy. Thus, anomalous motor control of the
      affected hand by the unaffected cortex may reflect a less efficient cortical reorganization
      process.

      There is controversy about how CI therapy produces an improvement in motor function.
      Conflicting evidence from fMRI and TMS studies in adult patients with stroke have shown that
      patients may have either an increase in ipsilateral motor cortical activation or an increase
      in activation in the damaged hemisphere. The answer to this controversy may be related to the
      presence of ipsilateral projections. Since ipsilateral projections are associated with worse
      functional outcome, determining the type of response to CI therapy may give insights into
      those patients who need more intense therapy.

      Subject Population: Children with hemiplegic subtype of cerebral palsy; age-matched children
      with no neurological abnormalities

      Design: We will assess motor cortex activation before and after CI therapy using fMRI and
      neurophysiologic tests including TMS and muscle reflex studies in children with hemiplegic
      cerebral palsy with and without evidence for ipsilateral projections.

      Outcome measures: Patients will be stratified by the presence of mirror movements. Primary
      outcome measure will be laterality index on cortical activation of the fMRI before and after
      CI therapy. Secondary outcome measures will be standardized measures of sensory and motor
      function. We will examine the relationship between the presence of anomalous ipsilateral
      motor control and cortical reorganization following CI therapy.

      Significance: Understanding this relationship is essential for planning large randomized
      controlled trials. Since anomalous ipsilateral cortical reorganization reflects an
      inefficient cortical reorganization process, treatment outcome of CI therapy may also be
      worse in this group. In this case, future studies may need to stratify children on study
      entry according to types of brain reorganization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 27, 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 30, 2006</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>50</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Children 9 to 17 years of age.

                  Cerebral palsy patients:

               2. Children previously diagnosed with spastic hemiplegia subtype of cerebral palsy

               3. Children with non-progressive cerebral lesions acquired pre-, peri- or
                  post-natally, before 1 year of age.

        Typically Developing subjects:

          1. Scores below 60 on Connor's attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) checklist.

          2. Normal neurological history and examination

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Any child who is pregnant

          2. Patients with Development Quotient (DQ) or Intelligence Quotient (IQ) below 50 on
             standardized tests

             Cerebral palsy patients:

          3. Children with subtypes of cerebral palsy that are not hemiplegia.

          4. Children with uncontrolled seizures within the last 6 months

          5. Children with progressive or neurodegenerative disorders; underlying known genetic or
             chromosomal disorders, familial or non-familial syndromes (without known chromosomal
             or genetic defect)

          6. Patients with cerebral lesions caused by sickle cell disease or by emboli associated
             with congenital cardiac lesions

          7. Patients incapable of voluntary movement or with severe cognitive deficits who cannot
             follow simple verbal commands

        Typically Developing Children:

          1. Children with chronic medical disorders or any neurological and /or psychiatric
             disorder including attention deficit hyperactivity disorder or learning disorder

          2. Children taking regular medications, including medications for allergies, hormonal
             oral contraceptives, or over-the-counter medications

          3. Children born before 36 weeks gestation as estimated by dates, ultrasound or other
             methods (if a discrepancy exists, then the ultrasound estimation will be taken as
             definitive)

        Exclusionary criteria for clinical MRI studies:

          1. Any child with metal objects in the body such as pacemakers, aneurysm clips (metal
             clips on the wall of a large artery), metallic prostheses, cochlear implants, or
             shrapnel fragments).

          2. Any child with permanent tattoos on the eyelids (ferromagnetic iron oxide-based)
             tattoo pigments can interact with the static magnetic field of an MRI imager.

        Exclusionary criteria for TMS:

        1. Children with hearing loss (greater than 15 dB at any individual frequency) in either
        ear (as evaluated in the Audiology Department, CC, NIH).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carr LJ, Harrison LM, Evans AL, Stephens JA. Patterns of central motor reorganization in hemiplegic cerebral palsy. Brain. 1993 Oct;116 ( Pt 5):1223-47.</citation>
    <PMID>8221056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 30, 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 31, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 31, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 3, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Forced Use</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemiplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>TMS</keyword>
  <keyword>Cerebral Palsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Spastic Hemiplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

