<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00105131</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050115</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-N-0115</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00105131</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Characterization of Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Genetic Characterization of Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will explore the risks and causes of Parkinson's disease, a chronic progressive
      nervous system disorder. Patients typically have tremors, muscle weakness and a shuffling
      gait.

      Patients with Parkinson's disease, their relatives and healthy volunteers may be eligible for
      this study. Candidates must be 18 years of age or older. Patients whose parkinsonism is due
      to a secondary cause, such as infection or injury, and healthy volunteers who have a first
      degree family member (parent, grandparent, child, sibling) with Parkinson's disease are
      excluded from enrollment.

      Participants are asked about possible symptoms they may have and about their general health.
      They provide a blood sample to obtain DNA for genetic analysis to look for genetic
      differences that might be related to risks for Parkinson's disease. White blood cells may be
      treated in the laboratory to grow a cell line, which provides a source of substances in the
      blood without having to draw samples repeatedly.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD) was noted to have a familial component as early as 1880. More
      recently, the discovery of several genetic factors influencing Parkinson's disease has
      emphasized the importance of heredity in PD.

      Objective: The goal of this protocol will be to contribute to the genetic understanding of
      Parkinson's disease. Clinical data will be collected in order to document the features of
      Parkinson's disease in affected individuals (phenotyping). Genetic characterization will be
      undertaken for the discovery of specific genes which cause or contribute to the risk for
      Parkinson's disease (genotyping).

      Design: The study design has two components. The first (aim 1) involves positional cloning
      for gene discovery in families with apparent Mendelian inheritance. The second (aim 2) will
      utilize an association study design, using genetic case-control methods for assessment of
      genetic risk factors. We will examine individuals affected by Parkinson's disease and their
      family members towards Specific Aim 1. Specific Aim 2 will involve evaluation of individuals
      with apparent sporadic Parkinson's disease, and also, healthy adult volunteers who will be
      recruited as control subjects.

      Outcome Measures:

      Primary Outcome Measures for Specific Aim 1 are:

        1. The identification of new genes causal for Parkinson's disease.

        2. The identification of new mutations in known genes.

      Primary Outcome Measures for Specific Aim 2 are:

        1. The discovery of gene variants which confer risk for Parkinson's disease.

        2. The validation of already reported polymorphisms as risk factors for PD.

      Secondary Outcome Measures (both Specific Aims 1 and 2): Genotype/phenotype correlations for
      specific genetic forms of Parkinson's disease. For example, we will assess if a particular
      age of onset, cardinal or secondary feature of PD or associated clinical course is associated
      with a given genotype.

      Future Direction: Because 1) the larger sample base the greater the likelihood of the
      discovery of genes of minor effect and 2) discoveries of genetic risk factors require
      validation in additional sample series, it is likely that renewal of this protocol will be
      sought after five years.

      Study Population: We aim to enroll a total of 2500 subjects over five years. These will
      include approximately 500 samples for the Mendelian studies (Specific Aim 1), and 2000 for
      association studies (Specific Aim 2). These estimates are based both on feasibility and on
      statistical power. Subjects will be evaluated at the NIH Clinical Center.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date>November 2005</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>2500</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <condition>PD</condition>
  <condition>Movement Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteer</condition>
  <condition>HV</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Individuals with Parkinson's disease OR

        Family members of an individual diagnosed with Parkinson's disease OR

        Healthy adult controls obtained through the NIH Clinical Research Volunteers Program (CVRP)
        or other healthy control volunteers who come forward.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Under the age of 18 years of age OR

        Individuals with Parkinsonism secondary to a specific cause such as toxin exposure, birth
        injury, head injury, or brain infection such as encephalitis.

        Healthy volunteers with a medical history or first degree family history of Parkinson's
        disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polymeropoulos MH, Lavedan C, Leroy E, Ide SE, Dehejia A, Dutra A, Pike B, Root H, Rubenstein J, Boyer R, Stenroos ES, Chandrasekharappa S, Athanassiadou A, Papapetropoulos T, Johnson WG, Lazzarini AM, Duvoisin RC, Di Iorio G, Golbe LI, Nussbaum RL. Mutation in the alpha-synuclein gene identified in families with Parkinson's disease. Science. 1997 Jun 27;276(5321):2045-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9197268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kitada T, Asakawa S, Hattori N, Matsumine H, Yamamura Y, Minoshima S, Yokochi M, Mizuno Y, Shimizu N. Mutations in the parkin gene cause autosomal recessive juvenile parkinsonism. Nature. 1998 Apr 9;392(6676):605-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9560156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonifati V, Rizzu P, van Baren MJ, Schaap O, Breedveld GJ, Krieger E, Dekker MC, Squitieri F, Ibanez P, Joosse M, van Dongen JW, Vanacore N, van Swieten JC, Brice A, Meco G, van Duijn CM, Oostra BA, Heutink P. Mutations in the DJ-1 gene associated with autosomal recessive early-onset parkinsonism. Science. 2003 Jan 10;299(5604):256-9. Epub 2002 Nov 21.</citation>
    <PMID>12446870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 7, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Movement Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Tremor</keyword>
  <keyword>Alpha-Synuclein</keyword>
  <keyword>Lewy Bodies</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>PD</keyword>
  <keyword>Movement Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Movement Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

