<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00105950</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EGF103009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00105950</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00214409</nct_alias>
    <nct_alias>NCT00278317</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Of Lapatinib In Patients With Relapsed Or Refractory Inflammatory Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study to Evaluate the Efficacy, Safety and Pharmacodynamics of Lapatinib in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Inflammatory Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was designed to determine how effective and safe a new investigational drug,
      lapatinib, is in treating patients with treatment refractory or relapsed inflammatory breast
      cancer. Tumor tissue collected pre-treatment and at Day 28 will be examined for biologic
      activity by IHC (immunohistochemistry). Treatment will consist of daily oral therapy with
      lapatinib. A patient may continue treatment as long as they are receiving benefit. Blood
      samples for hematology and chemistry panels, MUGA/ECHO (multigated
      acquisition/echocardiogram) exams and physical exams will be performed throughout the study
      to monitor safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This Phase II open label, multicenter study is designed to evaluate the efficacy, safety, and
      pharmacodynamic effects of oral lapatinib administered as a single agent therapy to patients
      with relapsed or refractory inflammatory breast cancer. Eligible patients must have a
      diagnosis of inflammatory breast cancer based on clinicopathologic criteria, tumor that is
      readily accessible for biopsy, and must have previously received treatment with an
      anthracycline and taxane-containing regimen (30 patients) plus trastuzumab (90 patients).
      Patients enrolled must have tumors that overexpress ErbB2, with or without co-expression of
      ErbB1. The primary objective for this study is to evaluate the objective response rate
      (defined as complete response plus partial response). Secondary objectives are to evaluate
      clinical benefit including quality of life parameters, progression-free survival, overall
      survival, time-to-response, response duration, safety and tolerability, pharmacodynamic
      effects on intracellular mediators that regulate tumor cell growth and survival, as well as
      effects on proteomic profile, and circulating levels of extracellular domains of ErbB1 and
      ErbB2 in peripheral blood.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response rate (complete response plus partial response)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 84</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical benefit (progression free survival, time to progression, response duration)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of clinical benefit, defined as CR or PR for at least 4 weeks, or SD for at least 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>week 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculation of progression-free survival, defined as the time between the first dose of investigational product and the first documented sign of disease progression or death.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculation of time-to-response, defined as the time between the first dose of investigational product and the first documented CR or PR.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculation of duration of response, defined as the time from initial documented CR or PR to the first documented sign of disease progression.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of changes in QoL and pain scale measurements collected on Day 1 and every 4 weeks while receiving study treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of adverse events (AEs), changes in laboratory values and echocardiogram (ECHO) or multiple gated acquisition scan (MUGA) results from pre-dose, during dosing and post-dose assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>week 84</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the effects of lapatinib on biomarkers that are involved in regulating tumor cell proliferation and survival (e.g., phosphorylated forms of Erk1/2 and Akt, STAT3, S6 Kinase, Bad, truncated ErbB2 and potentially other downstream mediators of</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>tumor cell growth and survival) by quantitative IHC and by direct and genome-wide methods (e.g., direct sequencing and DNA microarray) in tumor tissue collected prior to and following 28 days of lapatinib monotherapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examination of the effects of lapatinib therapy on the levels of circulating ErbB1 and ErbB2 ECD and the proteomic profile of peripheral blood. Investigation of the use of FDG-PET to predict early response to treatment with lapatinib.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms, Breast</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lapatinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm study of lapatinib with no comparator arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lapatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Tyrosine kinase inhibitor administered daily at 1500 mg/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lapatinib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Must have a life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          -  Has a left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) ≥ 50%, or ≥ lower limit of normal for
             the institution, based on ECHO or MUGA.

          -  Aspartate and alanine transaminase (AST or ALT) ≤ 3 times the upper limit of the
             reference range (patients with liver metastases may have AST and ALT ≤ 5 times the
             upper limit of the reference range and may be enrolled).

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ 3.0 mg/dL.

          -  Serum creatinine ≤ 2.0 mg/dL or calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) ≥ 30 mL/min

          -  Adequate bone marrow function. Hemoglobin ≥ 9 gm/dL. Absolute granulocyte count ≥
             1,500/mm³ (1.5 x 10^9/L). Platelets ≥ 75,000/mm³ (100 x 10^9/L).

          -  Recovered or stabilized sufficiently from side effects associated with previous
             chemotherapy, surgery or radiotherapy.

          -  Provided written informed consent.

          -  ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) performance status 0 to 2.

          -  Able to swallow and retain oral medication.

          -  Male or female, if female:

        A female is eligible to enter and participate in the study if she is of:

          1. Non-childbearing potential (i.e., women with functioning ovaries who have a current
             documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy, or women who are postmenopausal); or

          2. Childbearing potential (i.e., women with functioning ovaries and no documented
             impairment of oviductal or uterine function that would cause sterility. This category
             includes women with oligomenorrhoea (severe), women who are perimenopausal, and young
             women who have begun to menstruate), has a negative serum pregnancy test at screening,
             and agrees to one of the following where considered acceptable to the local IRB/IEC:
             Double-barrier contraception (condom with spermicidal jelly, foam suppository, or
             film; diaphragm with spermicide; or male condom and diaphragm).

        Abstinence from sexual intercourse from 2 weeks prior to administration of the
        investigational product, throughout the active study treatment period, and through the
        post-treatment follow-up visit (to occur 28 days after last dose of investigational
        product).

        Male partner who is sterile prior to the female subject's entry into the study and is the
        sole sexual partner for that female subject.

        Implants of levonorgestrel. Injectable progestogen. Any intrauterine device (IUD) with a
        documented failure rate of less than 1% per year.

        Oral contraceptives (either combined or progestogen only). Barrier methods including
        diaphragm or condom with a spermicide.

          -  At least 18 years of age.

          -  Has either measurable disease by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RESIST)
             or clinically evaluable skin disease. Measurable lesions may be in the field of prior
             adjuvant irradiation; however, there must be at least an 8 week period between the
             last radiation treatment and the baseline scan documenting disease status for the
             lesion to be measurable.

          -  Tumor that is accessible for biopsy.

          -  Tumor that overexpresses ErbB2 defined as 3+ by IHC or FISH +. The ErbB 2
             overexpression must be documented prior to dosing.

          -  Documented disease progression or relapse following treatment, which must have
             contained a taxane and anthracycline-containing regimen in the adjuvant or metastatic
             setting (30 patients) plus trastuzumab (90 patients)

          -  Histological diagnosis of breast carcinoma with a clinical diagnosis of IBC based on
             the presence of inflammatory changes in the involved breast, including diffuse
             erythema and edema (peau d'orange), with or without an underlying palpable mass
             involving the majority of the skin of the breast. Pathologic evidence of dermal
             lymphatic invasion should be noted but is not required for diagnosis.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Is clinically assessed to have inadequate venous access for protocol-related blood
             draws.

          -  Has a clinically significant electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormality.

          -  Has Class II to IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart Association (NYHA)
             functional classification system.

          -  Has physiological, familial, sociological, or geographical conditions that do not
             permit compliance with the protocol.

          -  Is currently receiving oral steroid treatment (inhaled steroids are permitted), or any
             other medication on the prohibited medications list

          -  Is currently receiving amiodarone or has received amiodarone in the 6 months prior to
             screening.

          -  Has received chemotherapy, immunotherapy, biologic therapy or hormonal therapy within
             the past 14 days, with the exception of mitomycin C within the past 6 weeks.

          -  Has received treatment with any investigational drug in the previous 4 weeks.

          -  Has a known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to drugs
             chemically related to the investigational product. These include other
             anilinoquinazolines, such as gefitinib [Iressa], erlotinib [Tarceva], or other
             chemically related compounds.

          -  Is considered medically unfit for the study by the investigator as a result of the
             medical interview, physical exam, or screening investigations.

          -  Has evidence of symptomatic or uncontrolled brain metastases or leptomeningeal
             disease. Patients with brain metastases treated by surgery and/or radiotherapy are
             eligible if neurologically stable and do not require steroids or anticonvulsants.

          -  Has malabsorption syndrome, a disease affecting gastrointestinal function, or
             resection of the stomach or small bowel.

          -  Is a pregnant or lactating female.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136-1002</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zion</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60099</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892-1201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bayonne</city>
        <zip>64100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon Cedex 08</city>
        <zip>69373</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille Cedex 09</city>
        <zip>13273</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris Cedex 20</city>
        <zip>75970</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris Cedex 5</city>
        <zip>75248</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-Herblain</city>
        <zip>44805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ramat Gan</city>
        <zip>52621</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zrifin</city>
        <zip>70300</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08036</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Girona</city>
        <zip>17007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sfax</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Tunisia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sfax</city>
        <zip>3029</zip>
        <country>Tunisia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tunis</city>
        <zip>1004</zip>
        <country>Tunisia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tunis</city>
        <zip>1007</zip>
        <country>Tunisia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SW3 6JJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Tunisia</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kaufman B, Trudeau M, Awada A, Blackwell K, Bachelot T, Salazar V, DeSilvio M, Westlund R, Zaks T, Spector N, Johnston S. Lapatinib monotherapy in patients with HER2-overexpressing relapsed or refractory inflammatory breast cancer: final results and survival of the expanded HER2+ cohort in EGF103009, a phase II study. Lancet Oncol. 2009 Jun;10(6):581-8. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(09)70087-7. Epub 2009 Apr 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19394894</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kaufman B, Wu Y, Amonkar MM, Sherrill B, Bachelot T, Salazar V, Viens P, Johnston S. Impact of lapatinib monotherapy on QOL and pain symptoms in patients with HER2+ relapsed or refractory inflammatory breast cancer. Curr Med Res Opin. 2010 May;26(5):1065-73. doi: 10.1185/03007991003680323.</citation>
    <PMID>20214527</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 21, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 24, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 24, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 28, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ErbB2 overexpressing</keyword>
  <keyword>ErbB1 expressing</keyword>
  <keyword>relapsed breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory inflammatory breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammatory Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lapatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>September 8, 2017</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

