<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00102583</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-EI-0002</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00102583</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cyclosporine Implant for Ocular Graft-Versus-Host Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Clinical Trial to Study the Safety of a Sustained-Release Subconjunctival Cyclosporine Implant for Ocular Graft-vs-Host Disease (GVHD1)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Graft-vs.-Host Disease (GVHD) is a major complication of allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation (SCT) commonly affecting the skin, liver, gastrointestinal tract, and eye.
      The most common clinical manifestations of ocular GVHD generally result from

      involvement of the lacrimal gland and the conjunctiva. Lacrimal gland involvement can lead to
      aqueous tear deficiency resulting in severe keratoconjunctivitis sicca (KCS) which can
      significantly increase the morbidity of patients with chronic GVHD.

      Systemic immunosuppressants such as cyclosporine (CsA) can be effective for treating ocular
      GVHD including lacrimal gland dysfunction. However, systemic immunosuppression is not
      generally prescribed for patients whose sole manifestation of GVHD is ocular complications as
      it may negate the overall graft-vs.-tumor effect and decrease patient survival. Topical CsA
      and corticosteroids are generally not effective for treating aqueous tear deficiency possible
      due to epithelial barriers preventing penetration of the drugs to the lacrimal gland. A
      sustained-release subconjunctival CsA implant was developed to bypass these epithelial
      barriers and significantly increase the CsA concentrations in the lacrimal gland to treat
      aqueous tear deficiency related to GVHD.

      The objective of this randomized pilot study is to investigate the safety and potential
      efficacy of a CsA implant in patients with lacrimal gland involvement and aqueous tear
      deficiency related to GVHD. Safety will be evaluated in terms of adverse events related to
      the implant. Efficacy will be evaluated by changes in Schirmer tear test (with anesthesia).
      Secondary efficacy evaluation will include changes in corneal and conjunctival staining
      grades, best-corrected visual acuity (BCVA), the Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI), changes
      in conjunctival GVHD grades, tear break-up time and meibomian gland dysfunction.

      Patients with active systemic GVHD with aqueous tear deficiency associated with lacrimal
      gland dysfunction following allogeneic hematopoietic SCT who are nine years of age or older
      are eligible for inclusion in this pilot study. The study will involve surgical placement of
      the CsA implant into the subconjunctival space adjacent to the lacrimal gland of one eye in
      each participant. Participants older than 12 years of age will be randomized to receive one
      of two implant release rates. All participants under the age of 12 will receive the smaller,
      lower dose implant. However, all participants under age 12 will not be randomized and will
      only be eligible to receive the smaller, lower dose implant.

      The implant will remain in place for up to two years and then be removed. IF the participant
      has clinical success, they will be given the option of allowing the implant to remain in
      place for an additional year. Clinical success is achieved if the participant meets any of
      the following measures in either eye assessed at the 1-year visit:

      Interval change from baseline characteristics

      Decrease in corneal staining by greater than or equal to 2

      Decrease in temporal or nasal conjunctival staining grades by greater than or equal to 2

      Decrease in total staining grade by greater than or equal to 2

      Decrease in OSDI calculated score by greater than or equal to 20%

      Increase in Schirmer tear test measurement by greater than or equal to 3 mm

      Meets mild-moderate KCS characteristics at 1 year

      Corneal staining grade less than or equal to 3

      Nasal or temporal conjunctival staining grades less than or equal to 3

      OSDI calculated score less than or equal to 15

      Schirmer tear test measurement greater than or equal to 5 mm

      For participants with implant duration of one year, safety evaluations will be conducted at
      baseline (pre-implantation) and monthly post-implantation for 13 months. Additional safety
      assessments will be done at 1 day, and at 1 and 2 weeks post-operatively for implant
      placement and removal procedures. Safety and efficacy evaluations will be conducted at
      baseline, at 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months post-implantation, and at 3 months following implant
      removal (15 months post-implantation). For participants with clinical success and who choose
      the implant to remain for another year, visits will be held as described above then conducted
      at 2-month intervals starting at month 14. Safety evaluations will be conducted every 2
      months until the end of the second year. Additional safety assessments will be done at 1 day,
      and at 1 and 2 weeks post-operatively for implant removal procedures. Safety and efficacy
      evaluations will be conducted at 16, 20, and 24 months post-implantation, and at 3 months
      following implant removal (27 months post-implantation).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this randomized pilot study is to investigate the safety and potential
      efficacy of a CsA implant in participants with lacrimal gland involvement and aqueous tear
      deficiency related to GVHD. Safety will be evaluated in terms of adverse events related to
      the implant. Efficacy will be evaluated by changes in Schirmer tear test (with anesthesia).
      Secondary efficacy evaluation will include changes in corneal and conjunctival staining
      grades, best-corrected visual acuity (BCVA), the Ocular Surface Diseases Index (OSDI),
      changes in conjunctival GVHD grades, tear break-up time and meibomian gland dysfunction.

      Participants with active systemic GVHD with aqueous tear deficiency associated with lacrimal
      gland dysfunction following allogeneic hematopoietic SCT who are nine years of age or older
      are eligible for inclusion in this pilot study. The study will involve surgical placement of
      the CsA implant into the subconjunctival space adjacent to the lacrimal gland of one eye in
      each participant. Participants older than 12 years of age will be randomized to receive one
      of two implant release rates. However, all participants under age 12 will not be randomized
      and will only be eligible to receive the smaller, lower dose implant. On each anniversary
      study visit a participant will be given the opportunity to retain the implant on an annual
      basis. This will be based upon the determination of clinical success (defined in the Study
      Design section below) combined with a participant's report of symptom improvement. The
      Implant will be removed if the Investigator believes the implant is harmful or if the
      participant requests the implant to be removed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 14, 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4</enrollment>
  <condition>Graft Vs Host Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Subconjunctival Cyclosporine Implant</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        To be eligible for the study each participant must satisfy all of the following inclusion
        criteria:

          -  Male or female greater than or equal to 9 years of age.

          -  Must be greater than or equal to 30 days post-hematopoietic stem cell transplantation
             (SCT) and have systemic GVHD diagnosed by the transplant physician.

          -  Must have lacrimal gland dysfunction from GVHD following SCT as defined by Schirmer
             tear test score (with anesthesia) of greater than or equal to 1 mm but less than or
             equal to 9 mm in both eyes.

          -  Must have open puncta and no puncta plug placement at the time of enrollment.

          -  If using topical corticosteroids, must be equal dose in both eyes of less than or
             equal to 4 drops per day.

          -  Topical lubrication using tear substitutes (includes eye drops, gels, and ointments)
             are permitted with equal dosing in both eyes.

          -  Must understand and sign informed consent or assent.

          -  Must be willing and able to comply with study evaluation and testing schedule.

          -  Females of childbearing potential and all males must agree to use an effective form of
             birth control for duration of the study.

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at
             baseline evaluation.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        To be eligible for the study, participants must not satisfy any of the following exclusion
        criteria.

          -  Use of a topical ophthalmic cyclosporine formulation less than or equal to 30 days
             prior to enrollment.

          -  Diagnosed with active ocular infection.

          -  History of recurrent herpes keratitis or active disease less than or equal to 6 months
             prior to enrollment.

          -  Aqueous tear deficiency or KCS related to previous irradiation, Stevens-Johnson
             syndrome, cicatricial pemphigoid, alkali burns, trachoma or Sjogren's syndrome.

          -  Seropositive for Hepatitis C (i.e. positive anti-HCV antibody) or seropositive for HIV
             with testing performed no earlier than 4 months before the date of stem cell
             transplantation.

          -  Diagnosis of active sarcoidosis.

          -  Use of a drug with anticholinergic activity within less than 4 times the half-life of
             the drug prior to enrollment (e.g., carbamazepine [Tegretol (R)] has a half-life of
             16-24 hours so must not be used within 4 days of enrollment).

          -  Use of an investigational drug for eye disease within 30 days of enrollment.

          -  Known allergy or hypersensitivity to cyclosporine, fluorescein, or lissamine green.

          -  Uncontrolled systemic disease or serious illness that could, in the investigator's
             opinion, interfere with the participant's ability to comply with study therapy,
             required follow-up testing, or interfere with interpretation of the study results.

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Serum creatinine greater than 2.5 mg/dL, absolute neutrophil count (ANC) less than
             750/MicroL Platelet count less than 25,000/MicroL, Partial Thromboplastin Time (PTT),
             or International Normal Ratio (INR) or Prothrombin Time (PT) exceeding the
             institutional upper limit of normal would require review by the Hematologist for
             surgical clearance. Hematologist review of the abnormal coagulation value and approval
             for surgery must be documented in the medical record prior to the surgical procedure.

          -  Participants that have received total body irradiation or direct eye/orbital radiation
             greater than 5000 cGy. (Potential participants will be assessed by a study clinician
             to determine that the cause of the dry eye symptoms is due to GVHD and not radiation.
             The clinician, in conjunction with the oncology staff as needed, will also assess the
             participant's clinical exam and medical history).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhushan V, Collins RH Jr. Chronic graft-vs-host disease. JAMA. 2003 Nov 19;290(19):2599-603. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14625337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ogawa Y, Okamoto S, Wakui M, Watanabe R, Yamada M, Yoshino M, Ono M, Yang HY, Mashima Y, Oguchi Y, Ikeda Y, Tsubota K. Dry eye after haematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Br J Ophthalmol. 1999 Oct;83(10):1125-30.</citation>
    <PMID>10502571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young NS, Barrett AJ. The treatment of severe acquired aplastic anemia. Blood. 1995 Jun 15;85(12):3367-77. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7780125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 15, 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Dry Eye</keyword>
  <keyword>Lacrimal Gland</keyword>
  <keyword>Tear Deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Keratitis Sicca</keyword>
  <keyword>GVHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Ocular GVHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Ocular Graft Vs Host Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

