<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01860300</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Sapienza Università di Roma</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-002430-36</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01860300</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Amoxicilline/Clavulanic Acid in Patients Affected by Tic Disorder Colonized by Group A Streptococcus</brief_title>
  <acronym>AntibioTICS</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicentre, Randomised, Double-blinded, Placebo-controlled Trial of Efficacy of Amoxicilline/Clavulanic Acid in Patients Affected by Tic Disorder Colonized by Group A Streptococcus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Roma La Sapienza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Roma La Sapienza</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is an extension of the European Multicentre Tics In Children Studies (EMTICS)
      COURSE study for which a separate study protocol exists; Aim of this clinical trial is to
      study the efficacy of treatment with antibiotics in reducing severity of tics and associated
      neuropsychiatric symptoms in patients with a tic disorder colonised by GAS.

      Primary Objective: Test the hypothesis that antibiotic treatment of GAS colonisation compared
      to placebo is associated with a larger reduction of tic and associated neuropsychiatric
      symptoms in the short-term (1 month) in patients with a tic disorder colonised by GAS.

      Secondary Objective: Test the hypothesis that antibiotic treatment of GAS colonisation is
      superior to placebo in the long-term (1 year) reduction of tic and associated
      neuropsychiatric symptoms in patients with a tic disorder colonized by GAS.

      Patients affected by a chronic tic disorder followed in the EMTICS- Longitudinal Course Study
      that show a positive culture for GAS at any microbiological examination during their
      follow-up will be considered eligible for the treatment trial.

      Patients showing GAS positivity will be invited to participate in the clinical trial.

      The patients enrolled will be randomly assigned to antibiotic or placebo in a 1:1 ratio.

      All participating patients will undergo a microbiological, serological and clinical
      assessment 1 month after the date of entering in the treatment trial (i.e. around 20 days
      after the end of treatment). Then, the patients will be followed with clinical, laboratory
      and microbiological assessments every four months for 1 year.

      Patients will be deblinded at the end of the treatment trial follow-up (1 year after the
      recruitment).

      Patients who will develop a true GAS infection or who otherwise need to be prescribed
      antibiotics for any clinical reason during the follow-up will be withdrawn from the study and
      immediately deblinded. Data of such patients would, however, remain part of the study
      analyses, following the intention-to-treat principle.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Following the few studies performed on this topic, children affected by tic disorder show a
      rate of Group A Streptococcus (GAS) colonization similar or slightly higher than that
      reported in the normal population.

      However, several studies have documented high rates of elevated anti-streptolysin O titers
      (ASOT) in children affected by tic disorders. One study reported a significantly higher ASOT
      in 150 children with tics compared to 150 healthy children, documenting a direct relationship
      between ASOT and tic severity. In this study, however, throat swab culture analyses on a
      subsample of patients failed to detect a predominant GAS serotype associated with tics. An
      American cohort of 81 patients with TS also exhibited higher ASOT than age-matched healthy
      volunteers and a mixed group of patients with autoimmune diseases. Increased ASOT,
      anti-deoxyribonuclease B (DNAse B), anti- streptococcal M12 and M19 titres were also observed
      in a smaller German sample of patients with TS. In a British cohort of 100 patients with TS
      (50% children), ASOT was raised in 64% of children and in 68% of adults with TS; this was
      significantly higher than in neurological disease and healthy control subjects. Two other
      reports from British and Italian cohorts confirmed these findings. However, a subsequent
      study failed to find a significant association with ASOT and anti-DNAse B titres using the
      same cross-sectional approach. More recently, a study on a large service-based cohort of TS
      patients confirmed the significant elevated rate of the high ASOT, but evidenced also that,
      on prospective analysis, ASOT were persistently elevated in 57% of patients with TS.
      Moreover, in tic patients the enhanced immune response is not limited to ASOT but it involves
      a broad range of GAS antigens.

      Taken together, these observations lead to hypothesize that TS patients colonized by GAS are
      not merely carriers and that this colonization may promote a sustained anti-streptococcal
      immune response contributing to the persistence of tic symptoms.

      If this hypothesis is true, the antibiotic treatment of GAS colonization in patients affected
      by a chronic tic disorder could modify their symptoms in term of severity and number of
      exacerbations.

      Up to now, only tic patients diagnosed as Pediatric Autoimmune Neuropsychiatric Disorders
      Associated with Streptococcal infection (PANDAS) underwent a controlled antibiotic treatment:
      two trials, aimed to study the efficacy of different preventive regimens on number of tic
      exacerbations, obtained however mixed results, mainly due to poor compliance.

      Investigators here designed a placebo-controlled trial with amoxicilline/clavulanic acid in
      tic patients showing GAS colonization. This drug is the first line therapy for streptococcal
      pharyngo-tonsillitis. Some previous studies have shown a superiority of amoxicillin versus
      penicillin in the treatment of GAS infections. A 10-day course of amoxicillin is considered
      sufficient and efficient in the treatment of GAS tonsillo-pharyngitis. Moreover, oral
      amoxicillin/clavulanic acid and oral clindamycin for 10 days achieved comparable rates of
      bacteriologic eradication at 12 days and 3 months. Furthermore, amoxicilline/clavulanic acid
      has been demonstrated to be efficacious in the treatment of GAS colonization. A few
      antibiotic regimens - evaluated prospectively in randomized, controlled trials- have
      demonstrated efficacy for termination of GAS carriage: among these, a regimen of 10 days of
      amoxicillin/ clavulanic acid was more effective than repeat penicillin in patients with
      treatment failure. Thus, the 10-days regimen of amoxicilline/clavulanic acid should be
      efficient in GAS eradication and, on the other hand, the shortness of the treatment should
      avert problems in patient's compliance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of tic disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
    <description>YGTSS scores</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of tic disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>YGTSS scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of associated neuropsychiatric symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>one month - one year</time_frame>
    <description>CYBOCS - PUTS - SCQ - SNAP-IV -SDQ</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Tic Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Antibiotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amoxicillin-Potassium Clavulanate Combination</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amoxicillin-Potassium Clavulanate Combination</intervention_name>
    <description>Amoxicillin-Potassium Clavulanate Combination will be prescribed at the dose of 25/3.6 mg/kg/day for 10 days, 2 times/day, as oral suspension.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Antibiotic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Augmentin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Tourette Syndrome or another chronic tic disorder according to DSM IV-TR
             criteria.

          -  Evidence of GAS colonization at any visit of EMTICS Longitudinal Course Study.

          -  Either no current psychotropic medication or on stable anti-tic medication for at
             least 2 months before the enrolment in the trial.

          -  Able (in the Investigators opinion) and willing to comply with all study requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children and/or parents are unable to understand and comply with protocol

          -  Any antibiotic treatment for any reason during the last month before enrolment in the
             trial.

          -  Clinical manifestations of pharyngitis or other streptococcal infections at moment of
             enrolment in the trial.

          -  Known or suspected hypersensitivity to penicillin or other β-lactam antibacterials, a
             history of amoxicillin-clavulanate-associated cholestatic jaundice or hepatic
             dysfunction.

          -  Known and/or suspected renal or hepatic impairment (due to the potential for
             drug-related toxicity in patients with such a condition).

          -  Scheduled elective surgery or other procedures requiring general anaesthesia during
             the study.

          -  Any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             may either put the participants at risk because of participation in the study, or may
             influence the result of the study, or the participant's ability to participate in the
             study.

          -  Participants who have participated in another research study involving an
             investigational product in the past 12 weeks
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francesco Cardona, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sapienza Università di Roma</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francesco Cardona, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+390644712288</phone>
    <email>francesco.cardona@uniroma1.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Pediatrics and Child Neuropsychiatry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00185</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Valeria Neri, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.emtics.eu</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about this study: www.emtics.eu</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bombaci M, Grifantini R, Mora M, Reguzzi V, Petracca R, Meoni E, Balloni S, Zingaretti C, Falugi F, Manetti AG, Margarit I, Musser JM, Cardona F, Orefici G, Grandi G, Bensi G. Protein array profiling of tic patient sera reveals a broad range and enhanced immune response against Group A Streptococcus antigens. PLoS One. 2009 Jul 22;4(7):e6332. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0006332.</citation>
    <PMID>19623252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardona F, Orefici G. Group A streptococcal infections and tic disorders in an Italian pediatric population. J Pediatr. 2001 Jan;138(1):71-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11148515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Church AJ, Dale RC, Lees AJ, Giovannoni G, Robertson MM. Tourette's syndrome: a cross sectional study to examine the PANDAS hypothesis. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2003 May;74(5):602-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12700302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Creti R, Cardona F, Pataracchia M, Hunolstein CV, Cundari G, Romano A, Orefici G. Characterisation of group A streptococcal (GAS) isolates from children with tic disorders. Indian J Med Res. 2004 May;119 Suppl:174-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15232189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Curtin-Wirt C, Casey JR, Murray PC, Cleary CT, Hoeger WJ, Marsocci SM, Murphy ML, Francis AB, Pichichero ME. Efficacy of penicillin vs. amoxicillin in children with group A beta hemolytic streptococcal tonsillopharyngitis. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 2003 Apr;42(3):219-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12739920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garvey MA, Perlmutter SJ, Allen AJ, Hamburger S, Lougee L, Leonard HL, Witowski ME, Dubbert B, Swedo SE. A pilot study of penicillin prophylaxis for neuropsychiatric exacerbations triggered by streptococcal infections. Biol Psychiatry. 1999 Jun 15;45(12):1564-71.</citation>
    <PMID>10376116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaplan EL, Johnson DR. Eradication of group A streptococci from the upper respiratory tract by amoxicillin with clavulanate after oral penicillin V treatment failure. J Pediatr. 1988 Aug;113(2):400-3.</citation>
    <PMID>3135377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loiselle CR, Wendlandt JT, Rohde CA, Singer HS. Antistreptococcal, neuronal, and nuclear antibodies in Tourette syndrome. Pediatr Neurol. 2003 Feb;28(2):119-25.</citation>
    <PMID>12699862</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahakit P, Vicente JG, Butt DI, Angeli G, Bansal S, Zambrano D. Oral clindamycin 300 mg BID compared with oral amoxicillin/clavulanic acid 1 g BID in the outpatient treatment of acute recurrent pharyngotonsillitis caused by group a beta-hemolytic streptococci: an international, multicenter, randomized, investigator-blinded, prospective trial in patients between the ages of 12 and 60 years. Clin Ther. 2006 Jan;28(1):99-109.</citation>
    <PMID>16490583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martino D, Church AJ, Defazio G, Dale RC, Quinn NP, Robertson MM, Livrea P, Orth M, Giovannoni G. Soluble adhesion molecules in Gilles de la Tourette's syndrome. J Neurol Sci. 2005 Jul 15;234(1-2):79-85. Erratum in: J Neurol Sci. 2006 Feb 15;241(1-2):111.</citation>
    <PMID>15941572</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martino D, Chiarotti F, Buttiglione M, Cardona F, Creti R, Nardocci N, Orefici G, Veneselli E, Rizzo R; Italian Tourette Syndrome Study Group. The relationship between group A streptococcal infections and Tourette syndrome: a study on a large service-based cohort. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2011 Oct;53(10):951-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-8749.2011.04018.x. Epub 2011 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21679362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morshed SA, Parveen S, Leckman JF, Mercadante MT, Bittencourt Kiss MH, Miguel EC, Arman A, Yazgan Y, Fujii T, Paul S, Peterson BS, Zhang H, King RA, Scahill L, Lombroso PJ. Antibodies against neural, nuclear, cytoskeletal, and streptococcal epitopes in children and adults with Tourette's syndrome, Sydenham's chorea, and autoimmune disorders. Biol Psychiatry. 2001 Oct 15;50(8):566-77. Erratum in: Biol Psychiatry 2001 Dec 15;50(12):following 1009.</citation>
    <PMID>11690591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Müller N, Kroll B, Schwarz MJ, Riedel M, Straube A, Lütticken R, Reinert RR, Reineke T, Kühnemund O. Increased titers of antibodies against streptococcal M12 and M19 proteins in patients with Tourette's syndrome. Psychiatry Res. 2001 Mar 25;101(2):187-93.</citation>
    <PMID>11286821</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rizzo R, Gulisano M, Pavone P, Fogliani F, Robertson MM. Increased antistreptococcal antibody titers and anti-basal ganglia antibodies in patients with Tourette syndrome: controlled cross-sectional study. J Child Neurol. 2006 Sep;21(9):747-53.</citation>
    <PMID>16970879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snider LA, Lougee L, Slattery M, Grant P, Swedo SE. Antibiotic prophylaxis with azithromycin or penicillin for childhood-onset neuropsychiatric disorders. Biol Psychiatry. 2005 Apr 1;57(7):788-92.</citation>
    <PMID>15820236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 19, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Roma La Sapienza</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Francesco Cardona</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tic Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Tourette Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tics</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amoxicillin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clavulanic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clavulanic Acids</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amoxicillin-Potassium Clavulanate Combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

