<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01865539</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MIRB00558</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01865539</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Foot Orthotics in Veterans With Chronic Lower Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Foot Orthotics in Veterans With Chronic Lower Back Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Canandaigua VA Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Foot Levelers, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York Chiropractic College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Canandaigua VA Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomized sham controlled trial evaluating the efficacy of the use of custom foot
      orthotics in veterans suffering from chronic lower back pain. The current study hypothesizes
      that those veterans with chronic lower back pain who receive the custom foot orthotics will
      show greater improvements in pain and disability associated with the chronic lower back pain
      than those who receive the sham orthotic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aim 1: Utilizing a gold standard sham controlled randomized trial design, we will
      evaluate the change in pain, back related disability and quality of life in Veterans with
      CLBP who utilize either a custom foot orthotic or a sham orthotic.

      As part of this aim the investigators will build on the teams strength of recruiting and
      enrolling Veteran's with CLBP into a randomized trial. The investigators will collect
      baseline pain and disability measures utilizing validated tools. Once the patients are
      enrolled, utilizing the &quot;gold standard&quot; placebo controlled design the investigators will
      randomize patients to receive either a custom foot orthotic or a sham orthotic. The Veterans
      will then be assessed at 5, 12 and 24-weeks post baseline to evaluate differences in pain and
      disability. Based on previous studies on the effectiveness of custom foot orthotics the
      investigators hypothesize that that Veteran's who receive the custom orthotic will experience
      less pain and disability as compared to those who receive the sham orthotics.

      Specific Aim 2: To evaluate baseline characteristics of Veterans with CLBP predictive of
      responsiveness to custom foot orthotics including age, BMI, psychosocial characteristics and
      arch classification.

      Focusing on the Veterans who receive the custom foot orthotic, the investigators next examine
      the important characteristics that may predict those Veterans who are most likely to benefit
      from wearing custom foot orthotics. Assessing potential confounders or facilitators of
      effectiveness of the custom foot orthotic will allow the investigators to best describe
      potential mechanisms of responsiveness. The investigators have chosen previously described
      confounders to responsiveness to treatment of CLBP, specifically age, body mass index and
      psychosocial characteristics. This methodology is particularly important in a sham controlled
      trial to assess if effectiveness or lack of thereof, is a factor of the intervention or from
      other confounding variables. The investigators have also chosen to evaluate the arch
      classification based on the measurement of the Veterans arch; again this allows for specific
      recommendations concerning use of this product. Based on previous studies on the
      effectiveness of custom foot orthotics in addition to previous studies evaluating CLBP the
      investigators hypothesize that those Veterans who are older, have a higher BMI and greater
      fear avoidance belief scores will show less responsiveness to the custom foot orthotics as
      compared to those younger Veterans who have a lower BMI and lower fear avoidance belief
      scores. In addition based on previous biomechanical literature, the investigators feel that
      those Veterans with a lower arch will show the greatest responsiveness to the custom foot
      orthotic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Difficulty with recruitment/funding
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 5, 12 and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Analog Scales (VAS): The VAS has become very popular in pain research and in the clinical assessment of pain. The test has shown test-retest reliability, intra-examiner reliability and inter-examiner reliability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Oswestry Disability Index (mODI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 5, 12 and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The back pain specific, self-rating scale evaluates the degree of functional impairment that a patient is experiencing in a number of activities of daily living. John O'Brien first developed it in 1976. Since that time, the original authors have created a revision, the ODI 2.0. The ODI has been found to have high reliability for test-retest and also for internal consistency. The ODI has been shown to reliably predict functional disability as tested by functional capacity evaluation and physical performance tests. There is no direct cost involved in the administration of this test and there are no adverse effects associated with the administration of this test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Reported Outcome Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Physical Function</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 5, 12 and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>As part of the National Institutes of Health Roadmap PROMIS was developed to address several shortcomings of the historically used patient reported outcome questionnaires. PROMIS attempts to acquire precise meaningful data in a short number of questions by the application of item response theory, and CAT 31. This has resulted in an electronic questionnaire of between 6 and 12 questions. PROMIS has varied instruments designed to look at a variety of chronic conditions, for the purposes of this study we will be utilizing the Physical Function instrument, which has been previously utilized in a variety of orthopedic patient populations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>RAND 36-Item Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline at 5, 12 and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The medical outcomes survey SF-36 was first developed for use in the longitudinal component of a medical outcomes study, a four-year observational study of health outcomes among patients with chronic medical and psychiatric conditions. The RAND 36-Item Health Survey consists of 36 items covering eight generic health concepts: physical functioning, role disability due to physical problems, bodily pain, general health perceptions vitality, social functioning, role disability due to emotional health problems and general mental health. Specific to this study the statistical analysis is based on bodily pain and physical functioning. These two measures have been previously utilized in other research on spinal pain syndromes and found to be reliable and valid.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Back Pain Lower Back Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Custom Foot Orthotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Custom foot orthotic</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Orthotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will be a sham orthotic that will be the same as the actual orthotic without the custom support pads.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Custom Foot Orthotic</intervention_name>
    <description>Custom foot orthotic with custom design pads</description>
    <arm_group_label>Custom Foot Orthotic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Foot Levelers Custom Foot Orthotic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Orthotic</intervention_name>
    <description>Leather insert without the custom design pads</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Orthotic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION:

        Ages 18-65 Lower back pain ≥ 3 months in duration Pain elicited upon deep palpation of the
        lumbar erector spinae musculature Primary complaint of CLBP from L1 to Sacroiliac joint
        inclusive. Ability/willingness to use orthotics in their shoes Numeric Pain Rating Scale
        (NRPS) of ≥ 3

          -  30 mm on the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)

          -  20% for the Modified Oswestry Disability Index (mODI)

        EXCLUSION:

        spinal surgery, spinal injections or injections in their feet within the past 6 months
        Inability to use orthotics in shoes Custom foot orthotics within the past 12 months
        Currently undergoing Chiropractic, Physical Therapy or Acupuncture treatment for their
        chronic lower back pain.

        evidence of cauda equina syndrome, spinal neoplasia or metastatic disease, destructive
        joint pathology such as rheumatoid arthritis bowel/bladder dysfunction (associated with the
        back pain) peripheral neuropathy or progressive lumbosacral radiculopathy, progressive
        myelopathy or neurogenic claudication.

        open workers compensation or no fault case.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul E Dougherty, DC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Canandaigua VA Medical Center/ New York Chiropractic College</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rochester Outpatient Clinic (ROPC) of the Canandaigua VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14620</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nycc.edu</url>
    <description>New York Chiropractic College</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.footlevelers.com/</url>
    <description>Foot Levelers Website</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sahar T, Cohen MJ, Uval-Ne'eman V, Kandel L, Odebiyi DO, Lev I, Brezis M, Lahad A. Insoles for prevention and treatment of back pain: a systematic review within the framework of the Cochrane Collaboration Back Review Group. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2009 Apr 20;34(9):924-33. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e31819f29be. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19359999</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 30, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 31, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Canandaigua VA Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul Dougherty, DC</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chiropractor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic lower back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Custom foot orthotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>February 7, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>March 27, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

