<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01863134</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2 P05C 023 27</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01863134</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Effects of Eptifibatide Administration in High Risk Patients Presenting With Non-ST Segment Elevation Acute Coronary Syndrome (NSTE-ACS) Requiring Urgent Coronary Artery Bypass Graft Surgery in Short- and Long-Term Follow-up</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Silesia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Silesia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. INTRODUCTION

           Through last couple of years the number of patients treated for acute coronary event
           without persistent ST segment elevation in ECG has been growing.

           This is probably an effect of improving diagnostics of myocardial infraction without
           persistent ST segment elevation in ECG, due to routine Troponin serum level evaluation
           and better primary prevention.

           This fact makes the search for the optimal treatment for patients with acute coronary
           event without persistent ST segment elevation in ECG, including both patients intended
           for pharmacological and invasive treatment percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) or
           coronary artery byppass grafting (CABG).

           Patients undergoing invasive treatment for acute coronary event, have higher risk rate,
           than those with stabile angina pectoris.

           The authors of this study want to evaluate, whether the proportional use of platelet GP
           IIb/IIIa receptor antagonist - eptifibatide in patients undergoing CABG results in
           improvement of short-, and long time results in those patients.

           Eptifibatide ( Integrilin) a cyclic heptapeptide antagonist of the GP IIb/IIIa integrin
           receptor, is an intravenous antagonist with rapid onset and short half-life.

        2. STUDY RATIONALE

      The notion acute coronary syndrome (ACS) includes several clinical situations, such a
      unstable coronary artery disease, non-Q wave myocardial infarction and Q wave myocardial
      infarction.

      On the basis of 12-lead ECG, patients with acute coronary syndrome (ACS) can be divided into
      two groups: with and without ST segment elevation.

      Another stratification factor in patients with ACS, especially these without ST elevation is
      evaluation of biochemical markers of myocardial necrosis, such as Troponins (TnI, TnT) and
      creatinine kinase isoenzymes (CK-MB). Serum concentrations of these markers allow to
      distinguish myocardial infarction (elevation of markers' concentration) from unstable
      coronary artery disease.

      All ACS have common etiopathogenesis which is plaque rupture, thrombus formation in the lumen
      of coronary artery.

      Platelets are the key factor in this process. Platelets by means of their collagen and von
      Willebrand factor glycoprotein receptors bind to damaged artery wall. Simultaneously many
      factors cause platelet activation, which leads to changes in their shape, release of
      intraplatelet components and activation of fibrinogen-binding glycoprotein receptors IIb/IIIa
      (GP IIb/IIIa). Activated form of GP IIb/IIIa binds to GP IIb/IIIa of another platelet by
      means of fibrinogen molecule. Fibrinogen molecules form stable bridges between platelets.
      This process is referred to as aggregation, and leads to clot formation, which is further
      stabilized by fibrine fibres.

      In this way the intravascular thrombus is formed, which after totally occluding the arterial
      lumen causes acute ischemia of the relevant region of myocardium and subsequently its
      infarction.

      The key role of GP IIa/IIIb in the process of platelet clot formation has important
      therapeutic consequences. By now several specific (direct) and non-specific (indirect)
      antagonists of GP IIb/IIIa have been developed.

      There are indirect antagonists as acetylsalicylic acid, ticlopidine and clopidogrel and
      direct antagonists as abciximab, tirofiban and eptifibatide Additionally also anticoagulants
      (heparin, LMWH - low molecular weight heparin) have antiplatelet properties by inhibiting
      thrombin production.

      Clinical studies performed all over the world have proven the efficacy and safety of three
      agents from the GP Iia/IIIb group: abciximab, tirofiban and eptifibatide.

      In several big clinical studies (EPIC, EPILOG, EPISTENT, ESPRIT, CAPTURE, PURSUIT,
      PRISM-PLUS, TACTICS-TIMI 18) the high efficacy of these drugs was showed in patients with ACS
      without ST segment elevation undergoing mainly percutaneous transluminal coronary angiography
      (PTCA) and stenting. The use of GP IIa/IIIb antagonists in this group of patients
      significantly reduces the death and myocardial infarction (MI) rate during early as well as
      late follow-up period. Moreover, last observations indicate, that the biggest benefit from
      such therapeutic strategy is observed in high risk patients; those with diabetes, high
      troponin levels and ECG changes.

      During last years, there is an increase in frequency of ACS without ST segment elevation.
      This is probably due to improved diagnostics of MI without ST elevation basing on routine
      troponin evaluation, but also thanks to better primary prevention.

      Therefore determining an optimal therapeutic strategy for patients with ACS without ST
      segment elevation remains a crucial issue.

      It concerns patients qualified to medical treatment as well as those qualified to invasive
      procedures (PTCA or CABG).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Adverse Cardiac and Cerebrovascular Events (MACCE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>MACCE was defined as combined death, nonfatal myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular event (stroke) and the need for re-hospitalization due to recurrent ischemia up to 12 months follow-up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Non ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eptifibatide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients were given a bolus of eptifibatide (Integrillin; 180µg/kg of body weight) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg orally daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg subcutaneous - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients were given placebo infusion (0,9% Natrium Chloride) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg orally daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg subcutaneous - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eptifibatide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Eptifibatide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>In the active treatment arm patients were additionally treated with eptifibatide (Integrillin; 180µg/kg of body weight) at an infusion rate 2 µg/kg/min</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must have a typical anginal pain lasting at least 20 min., but no longer than
             24h.

          -  ECG confirming ischaemia

          -  ST segment depression &gt;= 1,0 mm in at least 2 leads, or,

          -  negative T waves &gt;= 2,0 mm in at least 2 leads.

          -  Positive troponin I (TnI).

          -  Subjects must demonstrate their willingness to participate in the study and comply
             with its procedures by signing a written informed consent and/or parent or legal
             guardian must have signed a written informed consent.

          -  Subjects must be ≥ 21 year of age, of either sex and any race.

          -  Women of childbearing potential (includes women who are less than 1 year
             postmenopausal and women who become sexually active) must be using an acceptable
             method of birth control (e.g., hormonal contraceptive, medically prescribed IUD -
             intrauterine device, condom in combination with spermicide) or be surgically
             sterilized (e.g., hysterectomy or tubal ligation).

          -  Subjects must be free of any clinically significant disease that would interfere with
             study evaluations (see exclusion criteria).

          -  Subjects must understand and be able to adhere to the dosing and visit schedules, and
             agree to record concomitant medications and adverse events.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing.

          -  Subjects who have not observed the designated washout periods for any of the
             prohibited medications.

          -  Subjects who have used any investigational product within 30 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Subjects who have the following clinical conditions are excluded:

        Patients with:

          -  Angina lasting longer than 24h.

          -  ST segment elevation - Pardy wave

          -  age over 75 years

          -  history of revascularization procedure during last 6 months (PTCA, CABG)

          -  chronic heart failure (NYHA III or IV) during pre-hospitalization period

          -  history of bleeding from gastrointestinal tract or genitourinary system during last 30
             days

          -  history of intracranial lesions or stroke

          -  history of major surgery or trauma during last 6 weeks

          -  history of hemorrhagic diathesis

          -  thrombocytopenia &lt; 100 000/mm3

          -  anticoagulant therapy with INR&gt;2,0

          -  significant hepatic failure

          -  significant renal failure with serum creatinine&gt;2,0 mg%

          -  elevated blood pressure: SBP&gt;200mmHg and/or DBP&gt;110mmHg despite the antihypertensive
             treatment

          -  allergy to drugs or any therapeutic agent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miroslaw Wilczynski, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of Silesia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albert Einstein College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>First Department of Cardiac Surgery, Medical University of Silesia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Katowice</city>
        <state>Slaskie</state>
        <zip>40-635</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Cardiovascular Research and Development, American Heart of Poland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Katowice</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine and Clinical Pharmacology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Katowice</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>First Department of Cardiology, Medical University of Silesia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Katowice</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Division of Molecular Biology and Clinical Genetics, Jagiellonian University Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Krakow</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>May 30, 2013</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2013</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2013</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 19, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 19, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Silesia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Miroslaw Wilczynski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-ST Elevated Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Eptifibatide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Four clinical centers located within a radius of 50km of the reference center were selected for the study. From 2005 to 2010 a total of 140 patients presenting with NSTE-ACS not eligible for PCI were enrolled to the study. All CABG procedures were performed at 1st Department of Cardiac Surgery, Silesian Medical University in Katowice.</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Eptifibatide</title>
          <description>Patients were given a bolus of eptifibatide (Integrillin; 180µg/kg of body weight) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg PO daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg SC - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery).</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>Patients were given placebo infusion (0,9% Natrium Chloride) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg PO daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg SC - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery).</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="72"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="68"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="72"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="68"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Placebo/Control Group</title>
          <description>In the control group patients were given identical doses of acetylsalicylic acid and enoxaparin followed by a placebo infusion of saline in lieu of the GPIIb/IIIa inhibitor.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Eptifibatide</title>
          <description>In the treatment group patients were given a bolus of eptifibatide (Integrillin; 180µg/kg of body weight) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg PO daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg SC - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery). The minimal and maximal periods of eptifibatide infusion were established at 12 and 48 hours respectively.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="68"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="72"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="140"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="58"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="61"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="119"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="11"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="21"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="63.60" spread="8.32"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="62.47" spread="10.41"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="63.01" spread="9.39"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="40"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="49"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="51"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="100"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Poland</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="68"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="72"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="140"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Major Adverse Cardiac and Cerebrovascular Events (MACCE)</title>
        <description>MACCE was defined as combined death, nonfatal myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular event (stroke) and the need for re-hospitalization due to recurrent ischemia up to 12 months follow-up</description>
        <time_frame>Up to 12 month</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Patients were given placebo infusion (0,9% Natrium Chloride) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg PO daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg SC - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery).</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Eptifibatide</title>
            <description>Patients were given a bolus of eptifibatide (Integrillin; 180µg/kg of body weight) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg PO daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg SC - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Major Adverse Cardiac and Cerebrovascular Events (MACCE)</title>
          <description>MACCE was defined as combined death, nonfatal myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular event (stroke) and the need for re-hospitalization due to recurrent ischemia up to 12 months follow-up</description>
          <units>Percentage of study group</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="68"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="72"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="35.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="13.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
      <desc>Death up to 12 Months</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Eptifibatide</title>
          <description>Patients were given a bolus of eptifibatide (Integrillin; 180µg/kg of body weight) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg PO daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg SC - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery).</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>Patients were given placebo infusion (0,9% Natrium Chloride) and an intravenous infusion of 2 µg/kg/min followed by acetylsalicylic acid (150mg PO daily until the day of the procedure) and enoxaparin (1mg/kg SC - with the last dose 12 hours before surgery).</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="72"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="68"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Death up to 12 Months</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="72"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="7" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="68"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>1.4</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="72"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="68"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pulmonary infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="72"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="68"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Delirium</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="72"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="68"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Miroslaw Wilczynski</name_or_title>
      <organization>First Department of Cardiac Surgery, Medical University of Silesia, Katowice, Poland</organization>
      <phone>+48 32 20 24 025</phone>
      <email>miroslaw.wilczynski@cardiosurg.pl</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

