<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01866735</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00019937</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01866735</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Mobility for the Critically Injured Burn Patient</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early ICU Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy for the Critically Injured Burn Patient</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will demonstrate that Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy for burn patients with
      ARF reduces hospital stay through immediate improvement in functional capacity and functional
      performance. Our team comprises Burn Surgeons, Intensivists with expertise in Critical Care
      Trial design, Exercise Physiologists and Outpatient Functional Outcome Assessment Experts.
      The design was conceived through the US-Critical Illness and Injury Trials Group which
      allowed these investigators to bring varied expertise to the problems faced by critically ill
      Burn patients.

      Hypotheses:1) Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy (SRT) will shorten hospital stay in burn
      patients with ARF. 2) SRT will prevent loss in muscle size and loss of architecture during
      critical illness of severe burns. 3) SRT will improve objective functional measures and
      quality of life at 3, 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-enrollment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Burn injury requiring mechanical ventilation affects a high proportion of the
      25,000 patients admitted to US Burn Centers every year. Patients with a burn injury and acute
      respiratory failure (ARF) experience deconditioning, muscle weakness, joint contractures,
      dyspnea, depression, and reduced health-related quality of life. Delivery of rehabilitative
      therapy (physical therapy) within the Burn Intensive Care Unit (BICU) for burn patients
      requiring mechanical ventilation is not uniform in its content, timing, or the acceptance of
      its safety. Our published data indicate that Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy, initiated
      in the ICU, is feasible and safe for Medical ICU patients. Data have shown reductions in
      hospital stay, and improvements in functional outcomes. Mechanistically, it is understood
      that patients with burns and concomitant ARF exhibit acute alterations of metabolism, with
      the resultant loss of muscle strength. This study will demonstrate that Standardized
      Rehabilitation Therapy for burn patients with ARF reduces hospital stay through immediate
      improvement in functional capacity and functional performance. Our team comprises Burn
      Surgeons, Intensivists with expertise in Critical Care Trial design, Exercise Physiologists
      and Outpatient Functional Outcome Assessment Experts. The design was conceived through the
      US-Critical Illness and Injury Trials Group which allowed these investigators to bring varied
      expertise to the problems faced by critically ill Burn patients.

      Objective/Hypotheses: 1) Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy (SRT) will shorten hospital stay
      in burn patients with ARF. 2) SRT will prevent loss in muscle size and loss of architecture
      during critical illness of severe burns. 3) SRT will improve objective functional measures
      and quality of life at 3, 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-enrollment. Specific Aims: Aim 1: To
      determine whether standardized rehabilitation therapy for BICU patients requiring mechanical
      ventilation will decrease hospital length of stay. Aim 2: To determine by serial ultrasound
      and strength assessments whether standardized rehabilitation therapy decreases loss of biceps
      and quadriceps size, architecture and strength during critical illness of the severe burn
      patient. Aim 3: To determine whether standardized rehabilitation therapy will improve
      functional capacity and performance, and quality of life.

      Study Design: The investigators will conduct a two arm trial with stratified randomization in
      150 burn patients with concomitant ARF to compare SRT, initiated while on mechanical
      ventilation in the ICU and administered throughout the hospitalization, vs. Usual Care
      (control). Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy will consist of: passive range of motion,
      physical therapy, and progressive resistance exercise (strength training). Our unique
      approach will provide an experienced Mobility Team (7days/week) consisting of a critical care
      nurse, physical therapist, and nursing assistant to administer this protocol at 3 University
      Hospital sites. The proposed study is a natural extension of our prior work, is
      multidisciplinary, is supported by extensive preliminary studies, and is innovative in its
      application of strength training techniques and in-hospital strength assessments.

      Relevance: Burn patients with ARF suffer for months after hospital discharge with weakness
      and decreased quality of life. This study will provide the information to prioritize and
      budget for the rehabilitation needs of burn patients with ARF by demonstrating that
      Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy, initiated in the ICU, reduces hospital length of stay
      with immediate and sustained improvement in function and quality of life for burn patients
      with ARF. Given that military burn patients and civilian burn patients utilize similar
      resources and experience similar outcomes, the results of this study will be immediately
      transferable to the military burn patient with concomitant ARF resulting in improved
      outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Results from trial in another population lead investigators to determine study outcome may not
    reach statistical significance. Suspended for futility.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization through 36 months post-study enrollment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Status &amp; Health Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>ICU/Hospital Discharge, 3, 6 &amp; 12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Critically Injured Burn Patients</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy (SRT):
Participants randomized to the Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy arm will receive three types of interventions - Passive Range of Motion (PROM), Physical Therapy (PT) and Progressive Resistance Exercise (PRE). The SRT protocol will be administered by the BICU Mobility Team within 80 hours of ventilation and contains four levels of activity therapy. This Protocol will be delivered 7 days a week. Patients will be assessed daily and if appropriate will receive 3 separate sessions of activity each day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Standardized Rehabilitation Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 years or older

          -  Mechanically ventilated via an endotracheal tube or mask (via tracheostomy is
             acceptable if performed emergently due to burn injury)

          -  Burn injury requiring ICU admission

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to walk without assistance prior to burn injury (use of a cane or walkers
             not exclusions)

          -  Cognitive impairment prior to burn injury (non-verbal)

          -  Acute Stroke

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt;50

          -  Neuromuscular disease that could impair ventilator weaning (myasthenia gravis, ALS,
             Gillian-Barre)

          -  Hospitalization within 30 days prior to burn injury

          -  Re-admission to ICU/BICU within current hospitalization

          -  Expected hospitalization length of stay &lt; 3 days

          -  Hip fracture, unstable cervical spine or pathological fracture

          -  Mechanically ventilated &gt;80 hours prior to study enrollment

          -  Current hospitalization or transferring hospital stay &gt;7days prior to study enrollment

          -  DNR/DNI on admission

          -  Ineligible cancer treatment within the last 6 months

          -  Investigator judgment/determination that patient is unable to participate in
             intervention (SRT)

          -  Moribund

          -  Participation in treatment arm of another research study within the past 30 days/or at
             any time during the treatment phase of this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter E Morris, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kentucky</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Holmes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina, Chapel-Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest University Baptist Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 31, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Burns</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

