<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01866462</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ProCo Metformin</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01866462</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study of the Effect of MN-504 Cobiotic Formulation on the Efficacy and Tolerability of Metformin</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of the Effect of NM-504 Cobiotic Formulation on the Efficacy and Tolerability of Metformin in Patients With Metformin Intolerance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NuMe Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NuMe Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine if NM504 will prevent GI side effects that are
      associated with using metformin for the treatment of diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Only subjects with known intolerance to metformin will be recruited and enrolled in this
      study. When a participant qualifies, after signing the consent, they will be asked to
      complete a questionnaire about medical history which will be reviewed with the coordinator.
      Their height, weight, and blood pressure will be measured, and their medications will be
      reviewed. They will be taught how to measure their fasting blood glucose by a finger stick.
      They will be given metformin and asked to take a 500mg tablet twice day before breakfast and
      dinner starting the next day with breakfast. They will be given doses of NM504 or a placebo
      in a pouch to be mixed with 6 ounces of water before breakfast and dinner as a smoothie drink
      starting before breakfast the next day. Before consuming the first smoothie each day and
      before eating any food each day they will be asked to record their fasting finger stick blood
      glucose and complete the questionnaire about their bowel habits. The study takes place in
      two-week segments with a two week washout in between. They will receive metformin in both
      periods, but they will receive NM504 during one 2-week segment and a placebo smoothie during
      the other two-week segment. Five subjects will receive NM504 and 5 subjects will be assigned
      placebo during the initial 2 weeks. The treatment sequence will be randomly assigned. After
      the 2 week washout period the subjects will cross over to either placebo or NM504.

      Phone Visit 1: week 1 subjects will receive a call from the coordinator to see how they are
      tolerating the metformin and the smoothies. An increase in metformin dose to 500mg 3 times a
      day may or may not happen.

      Clinic Visit 2: week 2, Subjects will bring bottle of metformin and empty packages of
      smoothie powder to the visit along with logs of their daily fasting finger stick blood
      glucose and their daily bowel questionnaires. Their body weight weight will be measured.

      Clinic Visit 3: week 4, subjects will be asked about their metformin tolerance and body
      weight will be measured. They will be given metformin and asked to take a 500 mg pill twice a
      day before breakfast and dinner starting the next day before breakfast. Before consuming the
      first smoothie each day, and before eating any food each day, subjects will be asked to
      record a fasting finger stick blood glucose and complete the questionnaire about bowel
      habits.

      Phone Visit 2: week 5 subjects will be asked about their tolerance to metformin and the
      smoothies. They may or may not be asked to increase their 500mg dose of metformin from 2
      times a day to 3 times a day.

      Clinic Visit 4: week 6, Subjects will bring the bottle of metformin and the empty packages of
      the smoothie powder to the visit along with the logs of daily fasting finger stick blood
      glucose and daily bowel questionnaires. Their body weight will be measured at the end of the
      study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Metformin Tolerance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Fecal frequency, fecal consistency, fecal score and incidence of diarrhea will be assessed using the validated King's Stool Chart.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting Blood Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood glucose will be measured by finger stick daily.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GI Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Other possible GI symptoms such as sensations of bloating and flatulence will be measured with a questionnaire adapted from the validated Irritable Bowel Syndrome Global Improvement Scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GI Stool Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Stool will be collected at baseline, after the initial 2 week treatment, at the end of the washout period, and at the completion of the study. The complete stool GI function profile assessed by Genova Diagnostics will be performed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight Loss</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Body weight will be measured at each clinic visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin, NM504</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>metformin 500mg b.i.d. with NM504 b.i.d. for 1 week followed by metformin 500mg t.i.d. with NM504 b.i.d. for 1 week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>metformin 500mg b.i.d. with Placebo b.i.d. for 1 week followed by metformin 500mg t.i.d. with Placebo b.i.d. for 1 week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NM504</intervention_name>
    <description>NM504 is a medical food designed to shift the dysbiota reported in type 2 diabetes. The placebo is carboxymethylcellulose prepared to look, taste and mix like NM504.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin, NM504</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NM-504</other_name>
    <other_name>NM-504 cobiotic</other_name>
    <other_name>NM-504 cobiotic formula</other_name>
    <other_name>NM504 cobiotic</other_name>
    <other_name>NM504 cobiotic formula</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or a female with type 2 diabetes

          -  Known tolerance to metformin

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Body mass index that is not less than 20 kg/m2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not pregnant or breast feeding a baby.

          -  Not taking chronic medication that has not had a stable dose for 1 month or longer.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baton Rouge</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70808</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 30, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 31, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 24, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

