<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01297192</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>178-CL-069</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2008-007929-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01297192</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Study to Assess the Effect on Pharmacokinetics of Dosing Mirabegron (YM178) and Solifenacin Simultaneously</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, One-sequence, Two-arm Study to Evaluate the Effect of Steady State Concentrations of Mirabegron on the Pharmacokinetics of Solifenacin and to Evaluate the Effect of Steady State Concentrations of Solifenacin on the Pharmacokinetics of Mirabegron in Healthy Young Male and Female Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Astellas Pharma Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigates whether mirabegron (YM178) has an effect on the pharmacokinetics of
      solifenacin and whether solifenacin has an effect on the pharmacokinetics of mirabegron.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of pharmacokinetics of solifenacin through analysis of blood samples</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 - 9 and Days 23 - 39</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of pharmacokinetics of mirabegron through analysis of blood samples</measure>
    <time_frame>Time Frame: Days 1 - 6 and Days 16 - 21</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <condition>Pharmacokinetics of Mirabegron</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The effect of mirabegron on the pharmacokinetics of solifenacin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The effect of solifenacin on the pharmacokinetics of mirabegron</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>solifenacin succinate</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vesicare</other_name>
    <other_name>YM905</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mirabegron</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YM178</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male subject must agree to sexual abstinence and/or use a highly effective method of
             birth control from screening until 3 months after last dose of study medication

          -  Female subject must be of non-child bearing potential, i.e. post menopausal,
             surgically sterilized (e.g. tubal ligation), hysterectomy in medical history, or must
             practice an adequate non-hormonal contraceptive method to prevent pregnancies.
             Non-hormonal contraceptive methods are defined as:

               -  sexual abstinence from 1 month before admission until 3 months after discharge

               -  subject's sexual partner has been surgically sterilized (since at least 3 months
                  prior to the screening), or

               -  subject is under two (2) of the following contraceptive methods: I. diaphragm
                  with spermicide II. intrauterine device III. sexual partner is using condoms in
                  combination with a spermicidal cream

          -  Body Mass Index between 18.5 and 30.0 kg/m2, inclusive

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known or suspected hypersensitivity to mirabegron or any of the components of the
             formulation used

          -  Known or suspected hypersensitivity to solifenacin succinate or any of the components
             of the formulation used

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding within 6 months before screening assessment.

          -  Any of the liver function tests (i.e. ALT, AST and Alkaline phosphatase) above the
             upper limit of normal at repeated measures

          -  Any clinical significant history of or at risk for urinary retention, severe
             gastro-intestinal condition (including toxic megacolon), myasthenia gravis or
             narrow-angle glaucoma

          -  Any clinically significant history of asthma, eczema, any other clinically significant
             allergic condition or previous severe hypersensitivity to any drug (excluding
             non-active hay fever)

          -  Any clinically significant history of any other disease or disorder -
             gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, respiratory, renal, hepatic, neurological,
             dermatological, psychiatric or metabolic as judged by the medical investigator

          -  Any clinically significant abnormality following the investigator's review of the
             pre-study physical examination, ECG and clinical laboratory tests

          -  Abnormal pulse and/or blood pressure measurements at the pre-study visit as follows:
             pulse &lt;40 or &gt;90 bpm; mean systolic blood pressure &gt;140 mmHg; mean diastolic blood
             pressure &gt;90 mmHg (blood pressure measurements taken in triplicate after subject has
             been resting in supine position for 5 min; pulse will be measured automatically)

          -  A marked baseline prolongation of QT/QTc interval after repeated measurement of &gt;450
             ms, a history of unexplained syncope, cardiac arrest, unexplained cardiac arrhythmias
             or torsades de pointes, structural heart disease, or a family history of Long QT
             syndrome (LQTS)

          -  Use of any prescribed or OTC (over-the counter) drugs (including vitamins, oral
             contraceptives or hormone replacement therapy, natural and herbal remedies, e.g. St.
             John's wort) in the 2 weeks prior to admission to the Clinical Unit, except for
             paracetamol (up to 3 g/day)

          -  Regular use of any inducer of liver metabolism (e.g. barbiturates, rifampin) in the 3
             months prior to admission to the Clinical Unit

          -  Any use of drugs of abuse within 3 months prior to admission to the Clinical Unit

          -  History of smoking more than 10 cigarettes (or equivalent amount of tobacco) per day
             within 3 months prior to admission to the Clinical Unit

          -  History of drinking more than 21 units of alcohol per week (1 unit=270 cc of beer or
             40 cc of spirits or 1 glass of wine) (&gt;14 units of alcohol for female subjects) within
             3 months prior to admission to the Clinical Unit

          -  Donation of blood or blood products within 3 months prior to admission to the Clinical
             Unit

          -  Positive serology test for HBsAg, anti HAV (IgM), anti-HCV or anti-HIV 1+2

          -  Subject who, in the opinion of the investigator, is not likely to complete the trial
             for any reason

          -  Participation in any clinical study within 3 months or participation in more than 3
             clinical studies within 12 months, prior to the expected date of enrolment into the
             study, provided that the clinical study did not entail a biological compound with a
             long terminal half life

          -  Any clinical condition, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would not allow
             safe completion of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Use Central Contact</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Astellas Pharma Europe B.V.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.clinicaltrials.jp/user/ctrDetail_e.jsp?resultId=666</url>
    <description>Link to Results on JAPIC</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 15, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 29, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>YM178</keyword>
  <keyword>Mirabegron</keyword>
  <keyword>DDI</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase I</keyword>
  <keyword>Solifenacin</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics of mirabegron</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Solifenacin Succinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mirabegron</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

