<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01294345</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110093</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-HG-0093</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01294345</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Personalized Genomic Research</brief_title>
  <official_title>Personalized Genomic Research</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Congenital malformations, sometimes called birth defects, occur because of a difference in
      early human development. There are many different types of congenital malformations, and some
      of these can be caused by changes in genetic material. Researchers are interested in studying
      individuals with these congenital malformations to better understand the causes and the
      effects of certain congenital malformations.

      Objectives:

        -  To understand more about what causes congenital malformations that arise in early human
           development.

        -  To learn if genetic causes can be found to explain why a person has a congenital
           malformation.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals who have been diagnosed with a congenital malformation.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be seen at the National Institutes of Health for a series of visits
           over 3 to 4 days. Participants will be asked to provide copies of past medical records
           and test results for review, and will be asked questions about pregnancy/prenatal
           history, birth, newborn, medical, developmental, and family history.

        -  Parents or siblings of participants may also be asked to provide information for
           research purposes.

        -  Participants may have additional medical evaluations as part of this study, including
           any of the following tests:

        -  Physical examinations

        -  Other consultations as clinically indicated

        -  Blood samples for genetic testing

        -  Tissue biopsy for genetic testing

        -  Photographs of affected areas, such as front and side views of the face and other body
           parts that may be involved in a congenital malformation, like the hands and feet.

        -  Other tests as indicated by a specific malformation, such as organ ultrasounds.

        -  No additional invasive testing, testing requiring sedation, or testing involving
           radiation is planned for this protocol. These tests, if performed, would involve a
           separate consent....
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent advances in genomic techniques are making possible a new wave of genetic discovery. We
      hope to couple genomic techniques with more traditional methods involved in genetic discovery
      in order to investigate a broad range of conditions for which there is strong evidence that
      genetic factors are involved. To accomplish this, we plan to enroll approximately five
      families, in whom members have congenital malformations consistent with an error of early
      human development, in our research protocol each year. Patients will be referred from outside
      clinicians or may self-refer, and may be seen at the NIH Clinical Center or may send samples
      for testing. Some participants, for whom we already have DNA or tissue stored, may be
      reconsented for specific participation in this protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 10, 2011</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Genetics</condition>
  <condition>Genetic Disease</condition>
  <condition>Genetic Linkage</condition>
  <condition>Birth Defects</condition>
  <condition>Genetic Variation</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  For affected individuals (individuals who are related to a person who meets criteria
             (1) below may also be included in the research protocol), determination of clinical
             criteria for inclusion will be determined by prior medical record review before
             participation.

          -  Presence of a congenital malformation or related medical finding thought to be related
             to errors in early human development.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Anyone unwilling to provide informed consent (for themselves as adults, or on behalf
             of their children as minors, or on behalf of an adult who is unable to provide consent
             for themselves) or assent.

          -  Clear evidence for the presence of a condition for which diagnostic testing is already
             available.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maximilian Muenke, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul S Kruszka, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-9654</phone>
    <email>kruszkaps@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maximilian Muenke, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-8167</phone>
    <email>mamuenke@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2011-HG-0093.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bamford RN, Roessler E, Burdine RD, Saplakoğlu U, dela Cruz J, Splitt M, Goodship JA, Towbin J, Bowers P, Ferrero GB, Marino B, Schier AF, Shen MM, Muenke M, Casey B. Loss-of-function mutations in the EGF-CFC gene CFC1 are associated with human left-right laterality defects. Nat Genet. 2000 Nov;26(3):365-9. Erratum in: Nat Genet 2000 Dec;26(4):501.</citation>
    <PMID>11062482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beaty TH, Murray JC, Marazita ML, Munger RG, Ruczinski I, Hetmanski JB, Liang KY, Wu T, Murray T, Fallin MD, Redett RA, Raymond G, Schwender H, Jin SC, Cooper ME, Dunnwald M, Mansilla MA, Leslie E, Bullard S, Lidral AC, Moreno LM, Menezes R, Vieira AR, Petrin A, Wilcox AJ, Lie RT, Jabs EW, Wu-Chou YH, Chen PK, Wang H, Ye X, Huang S, Yeow V, Chong SS, Jee SH, Shi B, Christensen K, Melbye M, Doheny KF, Pugh EW, Ling H, Castilla EE, Czeizel AE, Ma L, Field LL, Brody L, Pangilinan F, Mills JL, Molloy AM, Kirke PN, Scott JM, Arcos-Burgos M, Scott AF. A genome-wide association study of cleft lip with and without cleft palate identifies risk variants near MAFB and ABCA4. Nat Genet. 2010 Jun;42(6):525-9. doi: 10.1038/ng.580. Epub 2010 May 2. Erratum in: Nat Genet. 2010 Aug;42(8):727. Scott, James M [corrected to Scott, John M].</citation>
    <PMID>20436469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown SA, Warburton D, Brown LY, Yu CY, Roeder ER, Stengel-Rutkowski S, Hennekam RC, Muenke M. Holoprosencephaly due to mutations in ZIC2, a homologue of Drosophila odd-paired. Nat Genet. 1998 Oct;20(2):180-3.</citation>
    <PMID>9771712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 4, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 10, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 11, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Birth Defects</keyword>
  <keyword>Genomics</keyword>
  <keyword>Congenital Malformations</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Genetic Diseases, Inborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

