<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01294475</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDC-NCIPC-5054</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01294475</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preventing Child Maltreatment Through A Cellular-Phone Technology-Based Parenting Program</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preventing Child Maltreatment Through A Cellular-Phone Technology-Based Parenting Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this project is to examine the effects of the use of cellular-phone technology in
      conjunction with a parenting program entitled &quot;Planned Activities Training (PAT)&quot; on
      participant enrollment, engagement, and motivation for the PAT intervention, as well as on
      parent and child outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current project will employ a 3-group experimental design with random assignment of
      parents to one of three groups: Planned Activities Training as usual (PAT); Cellular Phone
      Enhanced PAT (CPAT), or a no-intervention control group. Two cohorts of high-risk
      mother-child dyads (low education or mother adolescent at time of birth) will be recruited.
      In years 1 and 2, the first cohort of participants will be recruited in Kansas City, MO and
      South Bend, IN from an ongoing longitudinal descriptive study of child neglect, which has
      tracked risk and protective factors since the child's birth (n=180). During years 3 and 4, a
      second cohort of matched high risk mothers (operationally defined the same as for cohort 1)
      will be recruited from Head Start programs within the same two communities (n=180). Families
      in both cohorts will be enrolled when the first family child is between the ages of 4 and 6
      years.

      Participants assigned to the intervention groups will receive intervention services in the
      home setting and will be assessed prior to the intervention, as well as at 1-, 6-, and 12-
      month post-intervention time points. The control group participants will complete assessments
      at similar time points to the intervention groups. Several outcomes will be examined in order
      to measure intervention effects, including child maltreatment risk and occurrences, parent
      behaviors, and child behaviors. These outcomes will be collected utilizing a multi-method
      approach that will involve parent interview, parent-report and self-report measures,
      mother-child observation, and review of local CPS system records. For those parents
      participating in an intervention group, data will also be collected on maternal engagement,
      retention, fidelity, and dosage with regard to the intervention. Lastly, program and
      participant costs will be examined to determine the cost-effectiveness of including a
      technological component with this existing parenting program. It is expected that the
      knowledge generated through this study will aid in the improvement of parenting interventions
      targeting the prevention of child maltreatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Maltreatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">371</enrollment>
  <condition>Child Maltreatment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cell Phone Enhanced Parent Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cell phones will be provided to mothers participating in Planned Activities Training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Planned Activities Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Mothers will be provided a parenting intervention, Planned Activities Training (PAT). Some of the mothers will receive the PAT intervention enhanced with a cell phone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cell Phone Enhanced Parent Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion:

          -  Women between the ages of 15-18 at the time of their first child's birth OR between
             the ages of 22-35 years at the time of their first child's birth, with no formal
             education beyond high school or GED

          -  Mothers' oldest biological child should be between 4 and 6 years

          -  Families anticipate living in the 50 mile vicinity of Kansas City or South Bend for
             the next 18 months

          -  Primary caregiver should be functionally literate.

          -  Must speak English or Spanish fluently.

        Exclusion:

          -  Mother has a major medical illness that could interfere with her ability to
             participate in a 2-year project

          -  Mother currently lives in a treatment program or rehab center

          -  Mother has a serious mental illness

          -  Mother lives in a group home or correctional program.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judy Carta, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kansas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kansas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lawrence</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 10, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 11, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 9, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

