<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02431494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08291420Exp</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02431494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Preliminary Efficacy of Combination Therapy for the Treatment of Acne Vulgaris</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Preliminary Efficacy of Combination Blue Light Phototherapy and Microcurrent Therapy for the Treatment of Acne Vulgaris</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nova Southeastern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nova Southeastern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acne vulgaris is a multifactorial, highly prevalent dermatologic condition that results in
      visible lesions that can be quite disfiguring. Consequently, individuals with acne often
      suffer from a wide range of psychological manifestations. Although there is consensus that
      combination therapy is most effective in treating acne, researchers are constantly striving
      to develop new treatment. Microcurrent therapy (MCT) is a non-invasive modality that has
      successfully been used to promote wound healing and has been routinely used in aesthetics.
      Use of MCT alone or in combination with current successful treatment such as blue light
      phototherapy (BLP), may hold promise for acne treatment. The investigators propose to conduct
      a small randomized control trial to determine the safety and preliminary efficacy of a novel
      combination therapy to treat acne vulgaris. The investigators will recruit up to 60 males and
      females and randomly assign them to one of 3 arms: 1) BLP; 2) MCT; and combination therapy
      (BLP and MCT). The investigators will assess physiological parameters (number of acne
      lesions, amount of sebum produced, degree of acne severity) and psychosocial factors
      (dermatologic quality of life, social anxiety, depressive symptomatology, self-esteem).
      Participants will complete a baseline assessment prior to initiating treatment and a
      follow-up assessment at 4 weeks post termination of treatment. The investigators will conduct
      intermediary assessments at weeks 3 and 5 and 1 week post termination of the treatment. The
      investigators will use measures of central tendency to describe the sample and repeated
      measures analysis of variance to compute the main and interaction effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Overview: The goal of this study is to conduct a small randomized control trial (RCT) to test
      the safety and preliminary efficacy of a novel combination therapy to treat acne vulgaris.
      The investigators will also explore the effects of the treatments on psychosocial factors
      (Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI), social anxiety, depressive symptomatology, and
      self-esteem). The RCT will have 3 arms: 1) FDA approved treatment: blue light phototherapy
      (BLP); 2) Microcurrent therapy (MCT); and 3) combination therapy (BLP + MCT). The main
      outcomes will be: 1) number of acne lesions; 2) amount of sebum produced, 3) degree of acne
      severity; and 4) improvement in dermatologic quality of life. The specific aims of the study
      are:

      Aim 1: To explore the use of MCT to improve blood flow and lymphatic drainage and promote
      tissue repair in patients with acne vulgaris.

      Aim 2: To examine the safety and preliminary efficacy of enhancing traditional blue light
      therapy treatment with microcurrent therapy (BLP + MCT) to promote faster healing in patients
      with acne vulgaris.

      Aim 3: To determine if combination therapy is a more effective (fewer number of acne lesions,
      decreased amount of sebum produced, lesser degree of acne severity and greater improvement in
      dermatologic quality of life) for acne than either type of monotherapy.

      Aim 4: To explore the effects of the three modalities on psychosocial factors (social
      anxiety, depressive symptomatology, and self-esteem).

      The investigators will recruit up to 60 males and females and randomly assign them to one of
      3 treatment arms (blue light phototherapy (BLP); microcurrent therapy (MCT); and combination
      therapy (BLP and MCT). All participants will complete a baseline assessment prior to
      initiating treatment one follow-up assessment at 4 weeks post termination of treatment.
      During the treatment phase, the investigators will conduct intermediary assessments to track
      the progression of the treatment over time at weeks 3 and 5 as well as 1 week post the
      termination of the treatment (week 6). The investigators will conduct both physiological and
      psychosocial assessments; the content of the intermediary assessment will be much less than
      the other 3 assessments to reduce participant data. The most comprehensive assessments will
      be conducted at baseline and one follow-up points and will consist of all of the
      physiological and psychosocial factors as well as demographic factors that will be collected
      exclusively at the baseline assessment. At the intermediary assessments, the investigators
      will collect the number of acne lesions, amount of sebum produced and dermatologic quality of
      life. Psychosocial data will be collected via computer-assisted self-interviews (CASI).
      Physiological data will be entered into the computer program by research staff.

      Procedures for collecting psychosocial data: All assessments will be conducted using
      computer-assisted self-interviews (CASI). Participants will be assigned a unique study
      identification number (ID) that will be used to track data. Computer-assisted self-interviews
      are more effective than other tools for measuring sensitive and socially stigmatized
      behaviors. This mode of data collection eliminates interviewer bias, standardizes
      questionnaire administration, and reduces skip pattern errors. Using CASI, the participant
      responds to the questions using the computer keyboard or mouse. Selection of CASI for data
      collection decreases costs and error of entry, cleaning data, and publication lag, as well as
      enhances interviewer efficiency. The laptop computers the investigators use for data
      collection have been set up with two different log-in screens, one for participants and one
      for an administrator. The screen used by participants only contains the icon to access the
      CASI system. No other files appear or are available on this screen. The investigators access
      the CASI for participants by clicking the icon and filling in the assigned participant ID
      number (not participant name) completing all set up procedures. The investigator then
      provides a brief training on using the laptop and completing the CASI. As part of this
      training, the participant will complete a brief set of practice questions illustrative of the
      type of questions and the responses contained in the assessment. The investigator remains
      with the participant during the practice session to answer questions or to provide additional
      instructions. Participants will be encouraged to seek assistance, if needed, as they complete
      the interview. At this point, the interview starts and the participant completes the
      interview on their own. Once the participant completes the interview, he/she comes upon a
      screen instructing him/her to contact the investigators so that the file may be saved
      correctly.

      Procedures for collecting physiological data: The investigators will conduct visual
      inspection of the affected areas and systematically count the number of acne lesions present
      on the face. At baseline and the follow-up assessment the investigators will also take high
      quality digital photographs of the affected areas that will be used to compute the degree of
      acne severity. The photographs will be identified exclusively by study ID and will be kept in
      a password protected file in a secure NSU computer. The Sebumeter® SM 815 sebum meter will be
      used to estimate the amount of sebum produced. The investigators will bring the mat tape of
      the meter in contact with the affected areas. This instrument uses a non-invasive probe
      placed on the affected area and the instrument then calculates the amount of sebum produced.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Number of Acne Lesions over the course of 9 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1,3,5,6,9</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will conduct a systematic count of acne lesions (papules and pustules) present in all of the affected areas of the face.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Amount of Sebum Produced over the course of 9 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1,3,5,6,9</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use the Sebumeter® SM 815 manufactured by CK Electronic to estimate the amount of sebum. The measurement is based on grease spot photometry. The mat tape of the Sebumeter® SM 815 is brought into contact with facial skin. It becomes transparent in relation to the sebum on the surface of the measurement area. Then the tape is inserted into the aperture of the device and the transparency is measured by a photocell. The light transmission represents the sebum content.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Acne Severity over the course of 9 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 and 9</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use the acne counts and the digital photographs of the affected areas to compute the acne severity level following the procedures established by Hayashi et al. (2008). The investigators will not print the digital photographs. The investigators will visually inspect the digital photographs and assign a preliminary severity score to each half of the face using the following classification guide: 0-5 papules and/pustules for mild acne; 6-20 for moderate acne, 21-50 for severe acne; and more than 50 for very severe. The investigators will examine each half of the face separately. The most severe classification obtained for either side of the face will be the assigned severity score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Dermatologic Quality of Life over the course of 9 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1,3,5,6,9</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use the Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) developed by A. Y. Finlay and G. K. Khan (1992), one of the most widely used, dermatologic specific quality of life measures in the published literature to assess quality of life. The DLQI consists of 10 Likert type items; 9 of these items have 4 response categories scored from 0 to 3 with &quot;very much&quot; being &quot;3&quot; to &quot;not at all&quot; being &quot;0&quot;. Item 7 &quot;Over the last week, has participant's skin prevented participant from working or studying&quot; uses dichotomous responses; where &quot;yes&quot; is scored as a &quot;3&quot; and a &quot;no&quot; requires answering an additional sub-question, &quot;Over the past week how much has participant's skin been a problem at work or studying&quot;. Responses for this sub-question range from &quot;a lot&quot; coded a &quot;2&quot;, to &quot;not at all&quot; coded a &quot;0.&quot; The DLQI is calculated by summing the response to each question; the maximum score is &quot;30&quot; and the minimum score is &quot;0&quot;. The higher the score, the lower the dermatologic quality of life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Social Anxiety Score over the course of 9 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 and 9</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms of social anxiety will be assessed using the Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (Liebowitz, 1987), one of the most widely used scales to measure social anxiety. It consists of 24 items designed to assess fear and avoidance in different situations that are likely to produce social anxiety such as going to a party or speaking in public. For each situation, participants are first asked to state how fearful or anxious they feel in that situation using a Likert scale that ranges from &quot;none&quot; (0) to &quot;severe&quot; (3). Then they are asked to state how often they avoid that same situation using a Likert scale that ranges from &quot;never&quot; (0) to &quot;usually&quot; (3). Responses are summed to create an overall anxiety score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depressive Symptomatology Score over the course of 9 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 and 9</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will assess depressive symptomatology using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) (Zigmond and Snaith 1983), one of the most widely used screening tools to identify symptoms of depression, anxiety and emotional distress amongst patients being treated for a variety of clinical problems. It consists of 14 items, 7 of which assess generalized symptoms of anxiety and the remaining 7 assess depressive symptomatology. Although the specific wording of the item responses vary in accordance to the item, all responses are coded using a Likert format ranging from &quot;0&quot; to &quot;3&quot; where the most positive response is coded a &quot;0&quot; and the most negative response a &quot;3&quot;. The maximum score for each subscale is 21; higher scores are reflective of more symptoms of anxiety or depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Self-esteem Score over the course of 9 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 1 and 9</time_frame>
    <description>Self-esteem will be assessed using the Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale, one of the most widely-used self-esteem measures in social science research. It consists of ten items designed to assess respondent's self-satisfaction, self-respect and other general feelings about himself/herself. The response format is a four point Likert scale ranging from &quot;strongly agree&quot; to &quot;strongly disagree&quot;. For items 1, 2, 4, 6, 7: Strongly Agree=3, Agree=2, Disagree=1, and Strongly Disagree=0. For items 3, 5, 8, 9, 10: Strongly Agree=0, Agree=1, Disagree=2, and Strongly Disagree=3. The scale ranges from 0-30, higher scores indicating higher self-esteem.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Acne Vulgaris</condition>
  <condition>Acne</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BLP arm (Blue Light Phototherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm participants will receive 5 BLP sessions at 1 week intervals. The duration of each session will be approximately 20 minutes. At each session, the affected areas of the participant's face will be exposed to a light source using blue light phototherapy machine between 15 to 20 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MCT arm (Microcurrent Therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm participants will receive 5 MCT sessions 1 week intervals using MCT machine. The duration of each session will be approximately 45 minutes. The investigators will place one electrode in one of the regional areas of the lymph nodes or affected area (i.e. the forehead) and move the second electrode systematically from the affected area towards the stationary electrode. Once the entire affected area has been covered, the investigators will move the first electrode to another regional area of the lymph nodes or affected area and the process will be repeated. This will continue until all of the affected areas have been treated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combination of BLP and Microcurrent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm participants will receive 5 BLP and 5 MCT sessions at 1 week intervals. At each session, participants will receive MCT portion as described in above followed by BLP portion as described above. These visits will last approximately 65 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blue light phototherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Blue light phototherapy (BLU-U Blue Light Photodynamic Therapy Illuminator manufactured by DUSA Pharmaceutical Inc. Wilmington, MA) At each session, the affected areas of the participant's face will be exposed to a light source using blue light phototherapy machine between 15 to 20 minutes. The duration of each session will be approximately 20 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BLP arm (Blue Light Phototherapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microcurrent therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Microcurrent therapy (Micro Current Electro-Device w/gloves and carrying case, SKU:DSE-X1008 Classic Spa Collection) The investigators will place one electrode in one of the regional areas of the lymph nodes or affected area (i.e. the forehead) and move the second electrode systematically from the affected area towards the stationary electrode. Once the entire affected area has been covered, the investigators will move the first electrode to another regional area of the lymph nodes or affected area and the process will be repeated. This will continue until all of the affected areas have been treated. The duration of each session will be approximately 45 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MCT arm (Microcurrent Therapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combination of BLP and Microcurrent</intervention_name>
    <description>Same devices as described above. At each session, participants will receive MCT portion as described in above followed by BLP portion as described above. These visits will last approximately 65 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combination of BLP and Microcurrent</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have mild to moderate facial acne

          -  Have Fitzpatrick skin type II-V

          -  Be able to understand written and/or spoken English

          -  Be able to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have been treated with oral retinoids in the past 6 months

          -  Have been treated with oral antibiotic within the last 30 days

          -  Have received topical acne treatment (i.e. retinoids, antibiotics and anti-inﬂammatory
             agents or chemical peeling) within the last 30 days

          -  Pregnant or lactating

          -  Have history of photo-sensitive dermatitis

          -  Have previously received light therapy

          -  Taking oral contraceptive pills (OCP)

          -  Have pacemaker
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sergey Arutyunyan, M.S.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nova Southeastern University College of Osteopathic Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sergey Arutyunyan, M.S.</last_name>
    <phone>(305) 860-8710</phone>
    <email>sa1096@nova.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>M. Isabel Fernandez, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(305) 860-8710</phone>
    <email>mariafer@nova.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NSU COM Division of Dermatology, General, Cosmetic Dermatology and Cutaneous Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Lauderdale</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33328</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergey Arutyunyan, M.S.</last_name>
      <phone>305-860-8710</phone>
      <email>sa1096@nova.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>M. Isabel Fernandez, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>(305) 860-8710</phone>
      <email>mariafer@nova.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hollywood Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hollywood</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergey Arutyunyan, M.S.</last_name>
      <phone>305-860-8710</phone>
      <email>sa1096@nova.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>M. Isabel Fernandez, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>(305) 860-8710</phone>
      <email>mariafer@nova.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uhlenhake E, Yentzer BA, Feldman SR. Acne vulgaris and depression: a retrospective examination. J Cosmet Dermatol. 2010 Mar;9(1):59-63. doi: 10.1111/j.1473-2165.2010.00478.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20367674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gollnick H, Cunliffe W, Berson D, Dreno B, Finlay A, Leyden JJ, Shalita AR, Thiboutot D; Global Alliance to Improve Outcomes in Acne. Management of acne: a report from a Global Alliance to Improve Outcomes in Acne. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2003 Jul;49(1 Suppl):S1-37. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12833004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cunliffe WJ. The sebaceous gland and acne--40 years on. Dermatology. 1998;196(1):9-15.</citation>
    <PMID>9557218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gupta MA, Gupta AK. Depression and suicidal ideation in dermatology patients with acne, alopecia areata, atopic dermatitis and psoriasis. Br J Dermatol. 1998 Nov;139(5):846-50.</citation>
    <PMID>9892952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashkenazi H, Malik Z, Harth Y, Nitzan Y. Eradication of Propionibacterium acnes by its endogenic porphyrins after illumination with high intensity blue light. FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol. 2003 Jan 21;35(1):17-24.</citation>
    <PMID>12589953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheng N, Van Hoof H, Bockx E, Hoogmartens MJ, Mulier JC, De Dijcker FJ, Sansen WM, De Loecker W. The effects of electric currents on ATP generation, protein synthesis, and membrane transport of rat skin. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 1982 Nov-Dec;(171):264-72.</citation>
    <PMID>7140077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach S, Bilgrav K, Gottrup F, Jørgensen TE. The effect of electrical current on healing skin incision. An experimental study. Eur J Surg. 1991 Mar;157(3):171-4.</citation>
    <PMID>1678624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carley PJ, Wainapel SF. Electrotherapy for acceleration of wound healing: low intensity direct current. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1985 Jul;66(7):443-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3893385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acne Vulgaris</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

