<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02431728</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DuquesneU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02431728</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Melatonin Upon Post-Acute Withdrawal Among Males in a Residential Treatment Program</brief_title>
  <acronym>M-PAWS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Melatonin Upon Post-Acute Withdrawal Among Males in a Residential Treatment Program: A Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo, Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duquesne University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duquesne University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Individuals recovering from drug and/or alcohol addiction initially experience the symptoms
      of acute withdrawal before experiencing the symptoms of post-acute withdrawal (PAWS). PAWS
      include a wide array of emotional and psychological symptoms such as anxiety, sleep
      disturbances, depression, and stress. Previous studies have shown that melatonin therapy was
      beneficial to alleviate anxiety, depressive symptoms, and sleep disturbances. However, no
      randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled trials have been conducted in males who are
      experiencing PAWS. The purpose of this study is to investigate the effect of 5 mg melatonin
      given nightly for four weeks on weekly assessed, self-reported anxiety, depressive symptoms,
      insomnia, and stress in males with PAWS who reside in a residential treatment center.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approval was obtained from the Institutional Review Board at Duquesne University prior to the
      study implementation. The trial was a single-center, randomized, double-blind, matched
      placebo-controlled, parallel-group trial conducted in males 18 years of age and older who are
      in a residential treatment program for chemical dependency at the Salvation Army Harbor Light
      Center (865 West North Avenue, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 15233) in the United States of
      America. Convenience sampling was used to recruit individuals from July 2015 to December
      2015. A total sample of 70 participants were enrolled and block randomized with an allocation
      ratio of 1:1 for the interventions. Financial compensation of $5.00 U.S. was initiated at Day
      7 and continued at each follow-up (Day 14, Day 21 &amp; Day 28). Intention-to-treat and complete
      case analyses were conducted. No interim analysis was performed to assess efficacy.
      Participants completed study materials in a designated room at the center.

      Briefly, this study involved the completion of four validated surveys assessing self-reported
      perceived severity of anxiety (Generalized Anxiety Disorder Scale; GAD-7), depression
      (Personal Health Questionnaire Depression Scale; PHQ-8), stress (Perceived Stress Scale;
      PSS-14), sleep complaints and how is sleep affecting daily life (Pittsburgh Sleep Symptom
      Questionnaire - Insomnia; PSSQ-1) at five time points (Baseline, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, and
      Day 28). To address any adverse events relating to the interventions, the participant was
      encouraged to report any perceived adverse events to the investigator. To protect the
      anonymity and confidentiality of the participants, all paperwork were de-identified but
      contained their unique identification number.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of melatonin or placebo on the change in anxiety as measured by the Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD-7) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The GAD-7 assesses the perceived severity of anxiety through a 7-item scale that assesses anxiety as measured by a symptom checklist over the last two weeks. It employs a four point scale with the response options &quot;Not at all&quot; (0 pts), &quot;Several days&quot; (1 pt), &quot;More than half the days&quot; (2 pts), and &quot;Nearly every day (3 pts). Severity is based on the sum total where 15 - 21 is considered &quot;severe anxiety&quot;. The GAD-7 also asks a question about how difficult have these problems contributed to the activities of daily living, responses range from &quot;Not difficult at all&quot; to &quot;Extremely difficult.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of melatonin or placebo on the change in depressive symptoms as measured by the Personal Health Questionnaire Depression Scale (PHQ-8)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The PHQ-8 assesses the perceived degree of depression through an 8-item scale that assesses if the individual indicates symptoms over the last two weeks. It employs a four point scale with the response options &quot;Not at all&quot; (0 pts), &quot;Several days&quot; (1 pt), &quot;More than half the days&quot; (2 pts), and &quot;Nearly every day (3 pts). The higher the sum total the greater the degree of depression; for example, a score of ≥20 is considered severe major depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of melatonin or placebo on the change in sleep symptoms as measured by the Pittsburgh Sleep Symptom Questionnaire - Insomnia (PSSQ-1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>It is a 13-item scale with two subscales: Sleep complaints and How sleep is affecting daily life and assesses their experience during the past month. It employs a six point scale to assess for &quot;Sleep complaints&quot; with response options &quot;Never&quot; (0 pts), &quot;Do not know&quot; (1 pt), &quot;Rarely&quot; (2 pts), &quot;Sometimes&quot; (3 pts), &quot;Frequently&quot; (4 pts) and &quot;Always&quot; (5 pts). It employs a five point scale to assess for &quot;How sleep is affecting daily life,&quot; with the response options &quot;Not at all&quot; (0 pts), &quot;A little bit&quot; (1 pt), &quot;Moderately&quot; (2 pts), &quot;Quite a bit (3 pts), and &quot;Extremely&quot; (4 pts). If all criterion questions result in a &quot;Yes,&quot; then one can assign a diagnosis of insomnia disorder.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of melatonin or placebo on the change in stress as measured by the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS-14)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The PSS-14 assesses the perceived stress through a 14-item scale that asks about the thoughts and feelings of the individual during the past month. It employs a five point scale with the response options &quot;Never&quot; (0 pts), &quot;Almost Never&quot; (1 pt), &quot;Sometimes&quot; (2 pts), &quot;Fairly Often (3 pts), and &quot;Very Often&quot; (4 pts). In scoring the scale, scores are obtained by reversing the scores on items 4, 5, 6, 7, 9, 10, and 13 because these questions are positively stated items. The scores are summed with higher score indicating more perceived stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient health histories (social, medical, medication, preventive, and mental health)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Patient health histories were used to collect key information that may be used to further identify relevant data that have the potential be used to formulate other studies that the self-reported scales do not assess. Also, the histories were used to measure the effect of confounding and moderating factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of reported adverse effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Substance Withdrawal Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Melatonin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>capsule containing 5mg melatonin plus cellulose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matched Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>capsule containing cellulose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Melatonin</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg capsule p.o. at bedtime daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Melatonin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>N-acetyl-5-methoxytryptamine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matched Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg capsule p.o. at bedtime daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matched Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vegetable fiber</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males 18 years of age and older who are actively participating in therapy at a
             residential treatment program

          -  Willingness to participate in the 4-week study

          -  Willingness to provide self-reported demographic, social, medical, medication,
             preventive, and mental health histories

          -  Willingness to complete self-assessments of anxiety, depression, insomnia, and stress
             at designated time intervals

          -  Willingness to administer daily before bed a capsule containing either 5 mg melatonin
             plus vegetable fiber filler or only the vegetable fiber filler without melatonin
             (i.e., the matched placebo).

          -  English speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients already taking melatonin

          -  Adverse history with melatonin supplementation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vincent Giannetti, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duquesne University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Salvation Army Harbor Light Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 4, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 4, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Melatonin</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-acute withdrawal symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Insomnia</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Substance withdrawal syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance Withdrawal Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melatonin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All data were in aggregrate with no personal identification.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

