<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02430324</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>prot.1937/2009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02430324</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Multicenter Italian INCEPT (INfarto CErebrale Post-Traumatico) Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Post Traumatic Cerebral Infarction Increases Mortality and Morbidity in Patients With Moderate or Severe Head Trauma. The Multicenter Italian INCEPT (INfarto CErebrale Post-Traumatico) Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliera Spedali Civili di Brescia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliera Città della Salute e della Scienza di Torino</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fondazione Poliambulanza Istituto Ospedaliero</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>A.O. Ospedale Papa Giovanni XXIII</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliera San Gerardo di Monza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Policlinico San Matteo Pavia Fondazione IRCCS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliero, Universitaria Pisana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Università degli Studi di Brescia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Ospedaliera Spedali Civili di Brescia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Traumatic brain injury (TBI) is a leading cause of death and disability worldwide (Ghajar,
      2000). With an estimated annual incidence of up to 500 per 100,000 population and more than
      200 hospital admissions per 100,000 admissions in Europe each year, TBI is a major challenge
      to public health (Lingsma, 2010). Mortality and morbidity after TBI depend on several
      factors, either associated with patients characteristics, the cause of TBI, the neurological
      and general severity and secondary brain insults, the structural brain alterations as
      diagnosed at brain computed tomography (CT) (Rosenfeld, 2012).

      The prognostic value of brain CT characteristics is well documented, including the status of
      basal cisterns, midline shift, the presence and type of intracranial lesions, and traumatic
      subarachnoid hemorrhage (Maas, 2008). Postraumatic cerebral ischemia, which includes
      functionally impaired yet still viable tissue, so-called ischemic penumbra, and irreversible
      cerebral infarction (PTCI), is frequent in patients who die after moderate or severe head
      trauma (Stocchetti, 2014).

      Evidence of antemortem occurrence of PTCI is limited to three single-center retrospective
      studies, reporting a varying prevalence of 1.9%, 8% and 19.1% (Mirvis, 1990; Marino, 2006;
      Tawil, 2008). Increased intracranial pressure (ICP), blunt cerebral vascular injury, need for
      craniotomy and treatment with recombinant activated factor VII, have been demonstrated to be
      risk factors for PTCI. In one study, PTCI was an independent risk factor for poor outcome
      after moderate or severe head trauma with a two-fold increase in mortality and severe
      disability (Marino, 2006).

      PTCI can be an important diagnosis in patients with significant TBI for various reasons.
      First, it might influence long-term outcome. Second, as an outcome that is measurable, and
      relevant to survival and lifestyle, PTCI could be used as an outcome measure in randomized
      controlled trials. Third, diagnosis of PTCI could be used as a standard diagnostic reference
      to validate early surrogate indicators of cerebral ischemia.

      The investigators therefore planned a multi-center prospective study to investigate the
      impact of PTCI on disability at hospital discharge, and on 6-month morbidity and mortality in
      a population of moderate and severe adult TBI patients. The investigators also evaluated the
      role of intracranial hypertension, decreased cerebral perfusion pressure, hypotension and
      other secondary ischemic insults in determining the appearance of PTCI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxford Handicap Scale (OHS)</measure>
    <time_frame>patients will be evaluated at hospital discharge, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Oxford Handicap Scale evaluates the outcome as follow: 0 no symptoms, 1 minor symptoms, 2 minor handicap, 3 moderate handicap, 4 severe handicap, 5 death.
Favourable outcome: 0-3; unfavourable outcome: 4-5</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glasgow Outcome Scale (GOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>the GOS will be performed 6 months after the hospital admission</time_frame>
    <description>The Glasgow Outcome Scale evaluates the outcome as follow: 1 death, 2 vegetative state, 3 severe handicap, 4 moderate handicap, 5 good recovery.
Favourable outcome: 4-5; unfavourable outcome: 1-3</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital and ICU mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>at the discharge from ICU, an expected average of 3 weeks; and at the discharge from hospital, an expected average of 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome refers to the mortality during ICU stay and hospital stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>during ICU stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Days of ventilation, how long does it take to weaning from ventilation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of ICU and Hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>at the discharge from ICU, an expected average of 3 weeks; and at the discharge from hospital, an expected average of 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>How many days the patients whith cerebral infarction and without cerebral infarction have been in ICU, and how many days the patients were in hospital</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">143</enrollment>
  <condition>TBI (Traumatic Brain Injury)</condition>
  <condition>Stroke Acute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TBI, no cerebral infarction</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients with moderate or severe brain injury that do not develop posttraumatic cerebral infarction</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TBI, posttraumatic cerebral infarction</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients with moderate or severe brain injury that develops posttraumatic cerebral infarction</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>posttraumatic cerebral infarction</intervention_name>
    <description>the difference between groups refers to the developing of cerebral infarction after traumatic brain injury</description>
    <arm_group_label>TBI, posttraumatic cerebral infarction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients with moderate or severe brain injury, monitored with invasive intracranial
        pressure.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age &gt;15 years old,

          -  with moderate or severe head trauma (GCS &lt;14),

          -  admitted to ICU. Cases were classified as severe head injury (GCS score &lt; 9), or
             moderate head injury (GCS score from 9 to 13).

        All patients recruited were monitored by means of invasive intracranial pressure (ICP),
        invasive arterial pressure monitoring, peripheral oxygen saturation, in accordance with
        published international and local guidelines

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age &lt;16 years old,

          -  mild head trauma,

          -  absence of invasive ICP or invasive arterial pressure monitoring,

          -  dying patients,

          -  absence of brain stem reflexes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicola Latronico, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Brescia and AO Spedali Civili di Brescia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nazzareno Fagoni, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>AO Spedali Civili di Brescia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Spedali Civili di Brescia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brescia</city>
        <zip>25123</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghajar J. Traumatic brain injury. Lancet. 2000 Sep 9;356(9233):923-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11036909</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marino R, Gasparotti R, Pinelli L, Manzoni D, Gritti P, Mardighian D, Latronico N. Posttraumatic cerebral infarction in patients with moderate or severe head trauma. Neurology. 2006 Oct 10;67(7):1165-71.</citation>
    <PMID>17030747</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maas AI, Stocchetti N, Bullock R. Moderate and severe traumatic brain injury in adults. Lancet Neurol. 2008 Aug;7(8):728-41. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(08)70164-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18635021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirvis SE, Wolf AL, Numaguchi Y, Corradino G, Joslyn JN. Posttraumatic cerebral infarction diagnosed by CT: prevalence, origin, and outcome. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 1990 Mar-Apr;11(2):355-60.</citation>
    <PMID>2107719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tawil I, Stein DM, Mirvis SE, Scalea TM. Posttraumatic cerebral infarction: incidence, outcome, and risk factors. J Trauma. 2008 Apr;64(4):849-53. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e318160c08a.</citation>
    <PMID>18404047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenfeld JV, Maas AI, Bragge P, Morganti-Kossmann MC, Manley GT, Gruen RL. Early management of severe traumatic brain injury. Lancet. 2012 Sep 22;380(9847):1088-98. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60864-2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22998718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lingsma HF, Roozenbeek B, Steyerberg EW, Murray GD, Maas AI. Early prognosis in traumatic brain injury: from prophecies to predictions. Lancet Neurol. 2010 May;9(5):543-54. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(10)70065-X. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20398861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stocchetti N, Maas AI. Traumatic intracranial hypertension. N Engl J Med. 2014 May 29;370(22):2121-30. doi: 10.1056/NEJMra1208708. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24869722</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 27, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 30, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 30, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliera Spedali Civili di Brescia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Nazzareno Fagoni</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Nazzareno Fagoni, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

