<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02439515</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GR-2010-2312228-SF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02439515</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fall Prevention and Locomotion Recovery in Post-stroke Patients: A Multimodal Training</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fall Prevention and Locomotion Recovery in Post-stroke Patients: A Multimodal Training</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione Salvatore Maugeri</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Politecnico di Milano</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione Salvatore Maugeri</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study proposes a novel rehabilitative program for the recovery of locomotor abilities in
      post-acute stroke patients. The hypothesis is that a rehabilitative program which involves a
      biofeedback cycling training combining voluntary effort and Functional Electrical Stimulation
      (FES) of the leg muscles, and a biofeedback balance training is superior to usual care in
      improving walking abilities, disability, motor performance, and independence of post-acute
      stroke patients. The innovative approach is to investigate whether interventions which do not
      directly involve locomotor functions but movements similar in terms of kinematic patterns and
      neural commands (e.g. pedaling), or aimed at recovering an essential prerequisite for
      walking, such as postural control during upright stance, may improve and/or accelerate the
      recovery of walking abilities.

      A single-blind randomized controlled study is carried out. Participants are post-acute stroke
      patients experiencing a first stroke less than 6 months before recruitment, with an adult
      age, a low level of spasticity of the leg muscles (Modified Ashworth scale &lt;2), no
      limitations at hip, knee, and ankle joints, and able to sit up to 30 minutes. Subjects are
      randomized to one of two groups, one performing the novel rehabilitative program in addition
      to usual care (experimental group), and one performing usual care alone (control group).

      The experimental program consists of 15 sessions of FES-supported voluntary cycling training
      followed by 15 sessions of balance training. Both cycling and balance training are supported
      by a visual biofeedback in order to maximize patients' involvement in the exercise and are
      performed in addition to usual care.

      The control group is involved in standard physical therapy which includes stretching,
      muscular conditioning, exercises for trunk control, standing, and walking training, and upper
      limb rehabilitation.

      Both training programs last 6 weeks and patients are trained daily for about 90 minutes.
      Cycling and balance training last about 20 minutes; thus, patients in the experimental group
      perform only about 70 minutes of usual care.

      Participants are evaluated at baseline (T1), after the end of the cycling training or after 3
      weeks of usual care (post-treatment, T2), after the end of the whole intervention
      (post-treatment, T3), and about 6 months after the end of the intervention (follow-up, T4).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      More details on the experimental training program are here provided.

      The cycling training is performed on a motorized cycle-ergometer (MOTOmed, Reck GmbH)
      equipped with force sensors mounted at the base of the cranks (PowerForce system, Radlabor
      GmbH). The acquired force signals are displayed to the subjects who are asked to achieve a
      symmetrical involvement of the two legs. To deliver FES, a current-controlled 8-channel
      stimulator (RehaStim; Hasomed GmbH) is used and surface electrodes are applied in a bipolar
      configuration on the quadriceps, hamstrings, gastrocnemius lateralis, and tibialis anterior
      of both legs. Rectangular biphasic pulses with a pulse width of 400 μs and a stimulation
      frequency of 20 Hz are adopted. The stimulus intensity is set on each muscle the first day of
      training: for the paretic muscles values well tolerated by the subject and able to produce
      visibly good muscle contractions are identified, whereas for the healthy side lower values
      just above the sensory threshold are used. The stimulation timing is synchronized to the
      cycling movement according to physiological stereotyped activation patterns.

      The balance training is performed during upright stance using a balance board (Balance board
      basic™, NeuroCom® International, Inc.). Subjects are asked to keep still or move their center
      of pressure following a target displayed on a screen in front of them.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait Speed</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects are asked to walk three times at self-selected speed over the GaitRite mat using their walking aid (if any) or receiving the needed assistance. Spatial-temporal parameters are evaluated using the GaitRite software.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait speed</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;Day 0&quot;, &quot;3 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects are asked to walk three times at self-selected speed over the GaitRite mat using their walking aid (if any) or receiving the needed assistance. Spatial-temporal parameters are evaluated using the GaitRite software.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aerobic capacity/endurance during gait assessed by 6-minute walking test</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;Day 0&quot;, &quot;3 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects are asked to walk along a rectilinear corridor for 6 minutes. The distance covered is measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motor power of the paretic lower extremity assessed by Motricity Index</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;Day 0&quot;, &quot;3 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Italian version; Only leg-subscale of the paretic side</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trunk Control assessed by Trunk Control Test</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;Day 0&quot;, &quot;3 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Italian version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abilities during activities of daily life assessed by Functional Independence Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;Day 0&quot;, &quot;3 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Italian version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk of fall assessed by Fall Efficacy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;Day 0&quot;, &quot;3 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Italian version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Balance control assessed by Berg Balance Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;Day 0&quot;, &quot;3 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Italian version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's perception of the effect of the intervention assessed by Global Perceived Effect</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Italian version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pedaling performance assessed by Pedaling test</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;Day 0&quot;, &quot;3 weeks&quot;,&quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>A pedaling test is performed on the motorized cycle-ergometer to measure the force produced by the two sides during voluntary cycling as well as electromyography activations of the main lower limb muscles. Subjects are asked to pedal at four difference target pace (20 RPM, 30 RPM, 40 RPM, and 50 RPM), while the ergometer motor maintains a constant cadence of 10 RPM less than the target. A visual numerical cadence indicator and a metronome help the subjects to keep the constant cadence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Balance performance assessed by Balance test</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;3 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 weeks&quot;, &quot;6 months+6 weeks&quot;</time_frame>
    <description>Postural stability is evaluated using the commercial balance board exploited in the experimental intervention program (Balance board basic™, NeuroCom® International, Inc.). Pre-defined assessments are used to evaluate the postural sways during upright stance both with eyes open and closed; the limits of stability in all directions (forward, backward, right, and left); and the capability to shift the weight both left/right and forward/backward.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Biofeedback training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>It consists of 15 daily sessions of voluntary cycling training augmented by functional electrical stimulation (FES) followed by 15 daily sessions of balance training (multimodal biofeedback training). Both cycling and balance training are supported by a visual biofeedback and last about 20 minutes.
In addition to cycling or balance training, subjects perform standard physical therapy in order to reach 90 minutes of training per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>It consists of 30 daily sessions of standard physical therapy. Each session last about 90 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cycling</intervention_name>
    <description>Voluntary cycling augmented by electrical stimulation and biofeedback</description>
    <arm_group_label>Biofeedback training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MOTOmed, Reck GmbH</other_name>
    <other_name>PowerForce system, Radlabor GmbH</other_name>
    <other_name>RehaStim; Hasomed GmbH</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Balance</intervention_name>
    <description>Balance control exercises with visual biofeedback</description>
    <arm_group_label>Biofeedback training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Balance board basic™, NeuroCom® International, Inc.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard physical therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>It consists of stretching, muscular conditioning, exercises for trunk control, standing, and walking training, and upper limb rehabilitation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Biofeedback training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  post-acute stroke patients experiencing a first stroke (both ischemic or hemorrhagic)
             less than 6 months before recruitment

          -  low level of spasticity of the leg muscles (Modified Ashworth scale &lt;2)

          -  no limitations at hip, knee, and ankle joints

          -  able to sit up to 30 minutes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  neurological impairment (Mini mental scale &lt;24)

          -  presence of other neurological diseases

          -  spatial hemineglect

          -  cardiac pacemakers

          -  allergy to electrodes

          -  an inability to tolerate electrical stimulation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simona Ferrante, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Politecnico di Milano</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Simona Ferrante, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+390223999004</phone>
    <email>simona.ferrante@polimi.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Emilia Ambrosini, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+390223999509</phone>
    <email>emilia.ambrosini@polimi.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituti Clinici e Scientifici Maugeri</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lissone</city>
        <state>Monza Brianza</state>
        <zip>20851</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giorgio Ferriero, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+390394657259</phone>
      <email>giorgio.ferriero@icsmaugeri.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Emilia Ambrosini, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+390223999509</phone>
      <email>emilia.ambrosini@polimi.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ambrosini E, Ferrante S, Ferrigno G, Molteni F, Pedrocchi A. Cycling induced by electrical stimulation improves muscle activation and symmetry during pedaling in hemiparetic patients. IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng. 2012 May;20(3):320-30. doi: 10.1109/TNSRE.2012.2191574. Epub 2012 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22514205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferrante S, Ambrosini E, Ravelli P, Guanziroli E, Molteni F, Ferrigno G, Pedrocchi A. A biofeedback cycling training to improve locomotion: a case series study based on gait pattern classification of 153 chronic stroke patients. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2011 Aug 24;8:47. doi: 10.1186/1743-0003-8-47.</citation>
    <PMID>21861930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ambrosini E, Ferrante S, Pedrocchi A, Ferrigno G, Molteni F. Cycling induced by electrical stimulation improves motor recovery in postacute hemiparetic patients: a randomized controlled trial. Stroke. 2011 Apr;42(4):1068-73. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.110.599068. Epub 2011 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21372309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 24, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 8, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Politecnico di Milano</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Simona Ferrante</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>post-acute stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>functional electrical stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>biofeedback</keyword>
  <keyword>balance</keyword>
  <keyword>cycling</keyword>
  <keyword>rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>gait</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

