<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02433691</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-001411</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02433691</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Memory and Exercise Training Study in Older Adults With Subjective Memory Complaints</brief_title>
  <acronym>MET</acronym>
  <official_title>Simultaneous Aerobic Exercise and Memory Training in Older Adults With Subjective Memory Complaints</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>David Merrill, MD, PhD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study is a first step in a rapidly growing area of clinical research to create the
      most effective means to combat age-related losses in cognitive function through preventive
      lifestyle strategies such as physical exercise and memory training. This study will develop
      innovative simultaneous exercise and memory training programs in non-demented volunteers with
      subjective memory complaints (controls or MCI). Our primary goal is to assess the cognitive
      impact of 4-week memory training programs done twice weekly: 1. during simultaneous aerobic
      exercise (SIM-AR-MET), 2. sequentially after aerobic exercise (SEQ-AR-MET), or 3. without
      aerobic exercise (replaced with sequential stretching and toning) (SEQ-ST-MET). The
      investigators will also measure potential metabolic (e.g., glucose, lipid panel) and
      molecular (serum BDNF) mediators of observed cognitive changes in a subset of participants
      (those at the UCLA CTRC/IPCN site).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A total of 90 non-demented healthy older adult volunteers (age 60-75) with subjective memory
      complaints (controls or MCI) will be screened and enrolled into the study. The CTRC/IPCN site
      will enroll 30 subjects (10 in each group); the MPTF site will enroll 60 subjects (20 in each
      group). Baseline assessments will include neuropsychological testing of all study subjects.
      At UCLA CTRC/IPCN, baseline assessments will also include cardiorespiratory fitness, body
      composition, YMCA fitness tests, and blood-based markers of metabolism and plasticity. To
      control for total activity levels, all study subjects will wear continuous physical activity
      monitors (FitBit accelerometers) and keep exercise and cognitive activity logs during the
      entire study. All subjects (n = 90) will first complete a 1-week observational period to
      capture baseline activity levels. Subjects will then be randomized to one of three groups:
      SIM-AR-E&amp;MT, SEQ-AR-E&amp;MT, or SEQ-ST-MET (n = 30 per group). SIM-AR-MET and SEQ-AR-MET
      subjects will complete a 3-week exercise only 'ramp-up' period consisting of twice weekly
      1-hour sessions practicing stationary bicycling, improving cardiovascular fitness enough to
      complete the upcoming 4-weeks of MET sessions (described below), and practicing stretching
      and toning; SEQ-ST-MET subjects 3-week exercise only 'ramp-up' period will consist of an
      equal number of six stretching and toning sessions (no aerobic components). All 3 programs
      will then have two 2-hour sessions per week for 4 weeks. The SIM-AR-MET and SEQ-ST-MET
      subjects will do stretching/toning during the first hour; SEQ-AR-MET subjects will do aerobic
      cycling during the first hour. During the second half of the sessions, all 3 groups will
      first learn new memory training strategies while sedentary. SIM-AR-MET subjects will then
      practice the memory techniques while cycling while SEQ-AR-MET and SEQ-ST-MET subjects will
      practice the memory techniques while still sedentary. The three groups will have group
      specific exercise and memory training homework assignments, along with monitoring of activity
      and logging of cognitively enriching activities. The NP testing will be done again at the end
      of the 4 weeks of memory training classes for all study subjects. UCLA CTRC/IPCN subjects
      will have the additional testing done at baseline (e.g., blood-based markers, etc.).

      Consideration was given to having a purely observational 'wait-list' group, but in our
      experience with this population such groups have typically initiated greater levels of
      self-guided exercise and memory training in reaction to being put on a wait list.
      Alternatively, if no increase in activity or memory training is undertaken by wait list
      subjects, the investigators would not expect any differences in cognitive performance to be
      measurable within the brief 3 month total time frame of this initial study. The investigators
      also considered have a group do aerobic exercise immediately after memory training, but based
      on current literature, this combination seemed the least likely to impact memory
      synergistically. Thus, these two groups will be deferred for the pilot until later, larger
      studies can be done to confirm or refute these hypotheses. Similarly, while our primary aim
      assessing change in NP performance will be tested in all subjects, the pilot nature of the
      study prohibits testing of secondary aims in both sites. The academic medical center site
      will leverage the assistance of the UCLA CTRC/IPCN to accomplish preliminary testing of the
      secondary aims in 30 subjects, while the UCLA MPTF community site will test only the primary
      study aim of change in NP performance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of the MET interventions on cognition (comparing baseline vs. end-of-study NP testing)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in composite measure of memory related tasks including retention, attention, and mood.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in BDNF levels in response to the interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Increase of baseline measurement for BDNF levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical health measures</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in baseline in composite measurement of weight (loss), and increase in physical activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Memory Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequential Exercise and Memory Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aerobic exercise via stationary bicycling followed by memory training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Simultaneous Exercise &amp; Memory Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Simultaneous aerobic exercise via stationary bicycling while receiving memory training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching and Toning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Anerobic stretching and toning followed by memory training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>simultaneous aerobic exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>stationary bicycling at 65% of heart rate reserve for 30 minutes while receiving memory training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Simultaneous Exercise &amp; Memory Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sequential aerobic exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>stationary bicycling at 65% of heart rate reserve for 30 minutes followed by memory training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequential Exercise and Memory Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stretching and toning</intervention_name>
    <description>anaerobic stretching and toning followed by memory training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching and Toning</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  In good health

          -  Have memory problems or complaints

          -  Living independently

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of neurodegenerative disease or dementia

          -  Major psychiatric conditions

          -  Neurological disorders

          -  Active alcohol or substance abuse

          -  Head trauma or systemic diseases affecting brain function

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension or cardiovascular disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah McEwen, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCSD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Longevity Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Miller KJ, Siddarth P, Gaines JM, Parrish JM, Ercoli LM, Marx K, Ronch J, Pilgram B, Burke K, Barczak N, Babcock B, Small GW. The memory fitness program: cognitive effects of a healthy aging intervention. Am J Geriatr Psychiatry. 2012 Jun;20(6):514-23. doi: 10.1097/JGP.0b013e318227f821.</citation>
    <PMID>21765343</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barnes DE, Yaffe K, Satariano WA, Tager IB. A longitudinal study of cardiorespiratory fitness and cognitive function in healthy older adults. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2003 Apr;51(4):459-65.</citation>
    <PMID>12657064</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Erickson KI, Miller DL, Roecklein KA. The aging hippocampus: interactions between exercise, depression, and BDNF. Neuroscientist. 2012 Feb;18(1):82-97. doi: 10.1177/1073858410397054. Epub 2011 Apr 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21531985</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goodwin VA, Richards SH, Taylor RS, Taylor AH, Campbell JL. The effectiveness of exercise interventions for people with Parkinson's disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Mov Disord. 2008 Apr 15;23(5):631-40. doi: 10.1002/mds.21922. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18181210</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillman CH, Erickson KI, Kramer AF. Be smart, exercise your heart: exercise effects on brain and cognition. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2008 Jan;9(1):58-65. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18094706</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Petzinger GM, Fisher BE, McEwen S, Beeler JA, Walsh JP, Jakowec MW. Exercise-enhanced neuroplasticity targeting motor and cognitive circuitry in Parkinson's disease. Lancet Neurol. 2013 Jul;12(7):716-26. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(13)70123-6.</citation>
    <PMID>23769598</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barnes DE, Santos-Modesitt W, Poelke G, Kramer AF, Castro C, Middleton LE, Yaffe K. The Mental Activity and eXercise (MAX) trial: a randomized controlled trial to enhance cognitive function in older adults. JAMA Intern Med. 2013 May 13;173(9):797-804. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.189.</citation>
    <PMID>23545598</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Oswald WD, Rupprecht R, Gunzelmann T, Tritt K. The SIMA-project: effects of 1 year cognitive and psychomotor training on cognitive abilities of the elderly. Behav Brain Res. 1996 Jun;78(1):67-72.</citation>
    <PMID>8793039</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Berchtold NC, Castello N, Cotman CW. Exercise and time-dependent benefits to learning and memory. Neuroscience. 2010 May 19;167(3):588-97. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.02.050. Epub 2010 Feb 26.</citation>
    <PMID>20219647</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rasmussen P, Brassard P, Adser H, Pedersen MV, Leick L, Hart E, Secher NH, Pedersen BK, Pilegaard H. Evidence for a release of brain-derived neurotrophic factor from the brain during exercise. Exp Physiol. 2009 Oct;94(10):1062-9. doi: 10.1113/expphysiol.2009.048512. Epub 2009 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>19666694</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Merrill, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>(An)aerobic exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>memory training</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive benefits</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

