<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02430428</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VisuMax-2014-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02430428</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Correction of Myopia Wtih or Without Astigmatism Using the VisuMax™ Femtosecond Laser</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of the VisuMax™ Femtosecond Laser Lenticule Removal Procedure for the Correction of Myopia Wtih or Without Astigmatism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carl Zeiss Meditec, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Carl Zeiss Meditec, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this clinical trial is to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the Carl
      Zeiss Meditec VisuMax™ Femtosecond Laser lenticule removal procedure for the reduction or
      elimination of myopia from ≥ -1.00 D to ≤ -10.00 D with ≤ -3.00 D cylinder (myopia with or
      without astigmatism) and MRSE ≤ -11.50 D.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective multi-center clinical trial in which a maximum of 360 eyes of 360
      consecutive subjects will be enrolled and treated with the VisuMax™ Femtosecond Laser. The
      study will be conducted at up to 8 clinical sites.

      Subjects will be screened for eligibility, and informed consent will be obtained from those
      who meet screening criteria and are interested in participating in the study. Eligible
      subjects will be examined preoperatively to obtain a medical history and to establish a
      baseline ocular condition. Baseline and postoperative measurements will include manifest
      refraction, cycloplegic refraction, distance visual acuity (best corrected and uncorrected),
      slit-lamp examination, fundus examination, corneal topography, central corneal pachymetry,
      mesopic pupil measurement, wavefront analysis, mesopic contrast sensitivity, and intraocular
      pressure (IOP).

      Only eyes with astigmatism ≥ -0.75 D to ≤ -3.00 D targeted for the full distance manifest
      spherocylindrical refraction, or eye(s) with astigmatism &lt; -0.75 D targeted for the full
      distance manifest sphere-only refraction, will be enrolled into the study.

      Subjects must have astigmatism ≤ -3.00 D in the eye to be treated. Eyes with astigmatism ≥
      -0.75 D to ≤ -3.00 D will receive a spherocylindrical treatment. Eyes with astigmatism &lt;
      -0.75 D will receive a sphere-only treatment.

      Operative eyes with astigmatism ≥ -0.75 D to ≤ -3.00 D must be targeted for the full distance
      manifest spherocylindrical refraction. Operative eye(s) with astigmatism &lt; -0.75 D must be
      targeted for the full distance manifest sphere-only refraction.

      Monovision treatments and retreatments of the study eye will not be allowed during the course
      of the study. Bilateral investigational treatments will not be allowed during the study.

      Safety and effectiveness criteria from the American National Standard for Ophthalmics (ANSI
      Z80.11-2012) - Laser Systems for Corneal Reshaping will be utilized in the evaluation of the
      VisuMax Femtosecond Laser.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with MRSE within ± 1.00 D and ± 0.50 D</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Predictability: Decrease in manifest refraction spherical equivalent (MRSE) to within ± 1.00 D and ± 0.50 D of the intended refractive outcome at the point at which stability is first reached</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in UCVA following treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>The uncorrected visual acuity of 20/40 or better for eyes targeted for emmetropia at the postoperative interval at which stability has been established</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Preservation of Best-Spectacle Corrected Visual Acuity (BSCVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Preservation of Best-Spectacle Corrected Visual Acuity (BSCVA):
In eyes with preoperative BSCVA 20/20 or better, the percentage of eyes with BSCVA worse than 20/40 at the postoperative interval at which stability has been established
The percentage of eyes with BCVA loss ≥ 2 lines</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with induced MRCyl &gt; 2.00 D</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Induced manifest refractive astigmatism: The percentage of eyes treated for spherical myopia only with induced manifest refractive cylinder of &gt; 2.00 D at the postoperative interval at which stability has been established</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of Adverse Events: The rate of each type of adverse event will be summarized</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Contrast Sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Contrast Sensitivity: Mean of &quot;within-eye&quot; loss of contrast sensitivity from baseline to 12 months will be provided with the 1-sided 95% confidence interval for each spatial frequency. Percentage of eyes showing ≥ 0.3 log units loss at two or more spatial frequencies at the last available postoperative visit will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Symptoms: Will be considered as a secondary safety variable and will be evaluated via a subject questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <condition>Astigmatism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VisuMax lenticule removal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>VisuMax femtosecond laser sphere-only or spherocylindrical treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carl Zeiss Meditec VisuMax Femtosecond Laser</intervention_name>
    <description>VisuMax femtosecond laser sphere-only or spherocylindrical treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>VisuMax lenticule removal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male and female subjects age 22 years of age and older;

          2. Myopia from ≥ -1.00 D to ≤ -10.00 D with ≤ -3.00 D cylinder and MRSE ≤ -11.50 D in the
             eye to be treated;

          3. A stable refraction for the past year, as demonstrated by a change in MRSE of ≤ 0.50 D
             in the eye to be treated;

          4. A difference between cycloplegic and manifest refractions of &lt; 0.75 D spherical
             equivalent in the eye to be treated;

          5. UCVA worse than 20/40 in the eye to be treated;

          6. BSCVA at least 20/20 in the eye to be treated;

          7. Discontinue use of contact lenses for at least 2 weeks (for hard lenses) or 3 days
             (for soft lenses) prior to the preoperative examination, and through the day of
             surgery;

          8. All contact lens wearers must demonstrate a stable refraction (within ±0.5 D), as
             determined by MRSE, on two consecutive examinations at least 1 week apart, in the eye
             to be treated;

          9. Central corneal thickness of at least 500 microns in the eye to be treated;

         10. Willing and able to return for scheduled follow-up examinations;

         11. Able to provide written informed consent and follow study instructions in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Mesopic pupil diameter &gt;8.0 mm;

          2. Cylinder &gt; -3.00 D;

          3. Treatment depth is less than 250 microns from the corneal endothelium;

          4. Eye to be treated is targeted for monovision;

          5. Fellow eye has BSCVA worse than 20/40;

          6. Keratometry readings via Sim-K values less than 40.00 D;

          7. Abnormal corneal topographic findings, e.g. keratoconus, pellucid marginal
             degeneration in either eye;

          8. History of or current anterior segment pathology, including cataracts in the eye to be
             treated;

          9. Clinically significant dry eye syndrome unresolved by treatment in either eye;

         10. Residual, recurrent, active ocular or uncontrolled eyelid disease, corneal scars or
             other corneal abnormality such as recurrent corneal erosion or severe basement
             membrane disease in the eye to be treated;

         11. Ophthalmoscopic signs of progressive or unstable myopia or keratoconus (or keratoconus
             suspect) in either eye;

         12. Irregular or unstable (distorted/not clear) corneal mires on central keratometry
             images in either eye;

         13. History of ocular herpes zoster or herpes simplex keratitis;

         14. Deep orbits, strong blink, anxiety, pterygium, or any other finding suggesting
             difficulty in achieving or maintaining suction;

         15. Difficulty following directions or unable to fixate;

         16. Previous intraocular or corneal surgery of any kind in the eye to be treated,
             including any type of surgery for either refractive or therapeutic purposes;

         17. History of steroid-responsive rise in intraocular pressure, glaucoma, or preoperative
             IOP &gt; 21 mmHg in either eye;

         18. History of diabetes, diagnosed autoimmune disease, connective tissue disease or
             clinically significant atopic syndrome;

         19. Immunocompromised or requires chronic systemic corticosteroids or other
             immunosuppresive therapy that may affect wound healing;

         20. History of known sensitivity to planned study medications;

         21. Participating in any other ophthalmic drug or device clinical trial during the time of
             this clinical investigation;

         22. Pregnant, lactating, or of child-bearing potential and not practicing a medically
             approved method of birth control.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dishler Laser Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenwood Village</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Discover Vision Centers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leawood</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vance Thompson Vision</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sioux Falls</city>
        <state>South Dakota</state>
        <zip>57108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Slade and Baker Vision Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Davis Duehr Dean</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53715</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 30, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myopia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Astigmatism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

