<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00659646</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INN-TOP-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00659646</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Safety and Efficacy of an Antibiotic Sponge in Diabetic Patients With Moderately Infected Foot Ulcers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Open Label Study of the Safety and Efficacy of a Topical Gentamicin Collagen Sponge Combined With An Antibiotic Compared to Antibiotic Therapy Alone in Diabetic Patients With Moderately Infected Foot Ulcers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Innocoll</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Premier Research Group plc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Innocoll</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the gentamicin-collagen sponge when
      combined with standard daily wound care and an oral antibiotic (levofloxacin) is safe and
      effective in treating moderately infected skin ulcers compared to treatment only with
      standard daily wound care and an oral antibiotic (levofloxacin).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Infected skin ulcers with diabetes can be very debilitating because they are difficult to
      heal. Diabetic ulcers are responsible for frequent health care visits, and are a major
      predictor of amputation. Diabetic ulcers can be caused by a patient's inability to sense pain
      or warmth as well as peripheral vascular disease, which causes diminished blood flow to the
      foot. Early aggressive treatment is necessary to treat infection and ultimately prevent the
      need for amputation.

      Gentamicin is an antibiotic that is effective in treating certain kinds of infection.
      Collagen is a protein that is found in all mammals. The gentamicin-collagen sponge is a thin
      flat sponge made out of collagen that comes from cow tendons and containing gentamicin. When
      applied to an open ulcer, the collagen breaks down and the gentamicin is released into the
      ulcer, but very little is absorbed into the blood stream. The high levels of gentamicin in
      the open infected ulcer may help treat the infection.

      In this study, all subjects will be given the necessary supplies and taught how to take care
      their foot ulcer. All subjects will also receive oral an antibiotic (levofloxacin).
      Additionally, subjects who are randomly assigned to receive the gentamicin-collagen sponge
      will place a gentamicin-collagen sponge on their ulcer during daily wound care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The percent of patients with a clinical outcome of &quot;clinical cure&quot; in each treatment group at Visit 3</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7 of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percent of patients with a positive clinical response at each time point</measure>
    <time_frame>Every time point</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percent of patients with a &quot;clinical cure&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Every time point</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percent of patients with pathogen eradication</measure>
    <time_frame>Every timepoint</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute change in total wound surface area in each treatment group</measure>
    <time_frame>Every time point</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical cure</measure>
    <time_frame>Actual time assessed</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to positive clinical response</measure>
    <time_frame>Actual time assessed</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time on parenteral antimicrobial therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Actual time assessed</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Scale (VAS) for pain assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Every timepoint</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipsky wound score</measure>
    <time_frame>Every timepoint</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment emergent adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout study period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Foot Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gentamicin sponge applied into wound plus levofloxacin, 750 mg by mouth (po) or intravenous (IV) every 24 hours or, if ulcer culture results show resistance to levofloxacin, alternative antimicrobial therapy as determined by susceptibility testing</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Levofloxacin, 750 mg po or IV every 24 hours or, if ulcer culture results show resistance to levofloxacin, alternative antimicrobial therapy as determined by susceptibility testing</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gentamicin-collagen sponge and levofloxacin</intervention_name>
    <description>Topical Gentamicin Collagen Sponge: 10 × 10 cm in size And 750 mg tablet po every 24 hours or 750 mg IV administered by slow infusion over 90 minutes every 24 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Collatamp G</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levofloxacin only</intervention_name>
    <description>levofloxacin, 750 mg tablet po every 24 hours or 750 mg IV administered by slow infusion over 90 minutes every 24 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tavanic, Levaquin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Is a man or woman aged ≥ 18 and ≤ 80 years.

          -  Has diabetes mellitus, according to the American Diabetes Association criteria.

          -  Has a single infected skin ulcer below the knee, defined as &quot;moderate&quot; by the
             Infectious Disease Society of America (IDSA) Guidelines for whom, in the
             Investigator's opinion, intravenous (IV) or oral antimicrobial therapy is appropriate

          -  Has had an x ray of the infected area within the 2 days immediately preceding or at
             Visit 1 (Baseline/Randomization) to document the presence or absence of osteomyelitis.
             Patients with osteomyelitis must receive appropriate surgical intervention to remove
             all necrotic and infected bone and otherwise meet enrollment criteria before being
             enrolled in the study.

          -  Meets certain minimal laboratory criteria

          -  Has an ankle brachial index (ABI) &gt; or = 0.7 and ≤ 1.3. (Note: Patients with ABI &lt; 0.7
             or &gt; 1.3 may be included if they have either a transcutaneous oxygen pressure or a toe
             pressure &gt; or = 40 mm Hg on limb with ulcer.)

          -  If female, is nonpregnant (negative pregnancy test results at the
             Baseline/Randomization Visit) and nonlactating.

          -  If female, is either not of childbearing potential (defined as postmenopausal for ≥ 1
             year or surgically sterile [bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy or
             hysterectomy]) or practicing a medically acceptable methods of birth control and
             agrees to continue with the regimen throughout the study

          -  Willing to return to the study facility for the Final Study Visit.

          -  Must be able to fluently speak and understand English and be able to provide
             meaningful written informed consent for the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has a known history of hypersensitivity to gentamicin (or other systemic
             aminoglycosides) or levofloxacin or drugs in the same class, or any of the test
             article or reference product components.

          -  Has a known hypersensitivity to bovine collagen.

          -  Has any uncontrolled illnesses that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would
             interfere with interpreting the results of the study.

          -  Has a target ulcer with a wound size &gt; 10 × 10 cm.

          -  Has gangrenous tissue of the affected limb that cannot be removed with a single
             debridement.

          -  Has wound known to contain isolates resistant to levofloxacin.

          -  Has a wound associated with prosthetic material or device.

          -  Received any topical or systemic antimicrobial therapy within the 2 weeks prior to
             study entry (Visit 1 [Day 1]).

          -  If severely immunocompromised, may be excluded at the discretion of the Investigator.

          -  Has a history of alcohol or substance abuse in the past 12 months.

          -  Has serum creatinine &gt; 3 mg/dL, is undergoing dialysis (renal or peritoneal) or has a
             history of kidney transplant.

          -  Has a history of myasthenia gravis or other neurological condition where gentamicin
             use is contraindicated as determined by the Investigator.

          -  Has a history of epilepsy

          -  Has a history of tendon disorders related to fluoroquinolone administration
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Prior</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Innocoll</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karr Foot Kare PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lakeland</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33813</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lipsky BA, Kuss M, Edmonds M, Reyzelman A, Sigal F. Topical application of a gentamicin-collagen sponge combined with systemic antibiotic therapy for the treatment of diabetic foot infections of moderate severity: a randomized, controlled, multicenter clinical trial. J Am Podiatr Med Assoc. 2012 May-Jun;102(3):223-32. Erratum in: J Am Podiatr Med Assoc. 2012 Jul-Aug;102(4):323.</citation>
    <PMID>22659765</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 11, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 16, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 30, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>ulcers</keyword>
  <keyword>ulcerations</keyword>
  <keyword>infection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levofloxacin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ofloxacin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gentamicins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

