<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00654316</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TB006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00654316</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Safety and Immunogenicity of Bacille Calmette Guerin (BCG) Vaccine</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of the Safety and Immunogenicity of BCG (Bacille Calmette-Guerin) Vaccine Delivered Intradermally by a Needle Injection in Healthy Volunteers Who Have Previously Received BCG.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Tuberculosis (TB) kills about three million people annually. It is estimated that one third
      of the world's population are latently infected with Mycobacterium tuberculosis (M.tb).
      Multi-drug resistant strains of M.tb, and co-infection with M.tb and HIV present major new
      challenges. The currently available vaccine, M. bovis BCG, is largely ineffective at
      protecting against adult pulmonary disease in endemic areas and it is widely agreed that a
      new more effective tuberculosis vaccine is a major global public health priority1. However,
      it may be unethical and impractical to test and deploy a vaccine strategy that does not
      include BCG, as BCG does confer worthwhile protection against TB meningitis and leprosy. An
      immunisation strategy that includes BCG is also attractive because the populations in which
      this vaccine candidate will need to be tested will already have been immunised with BCG.

      M.tb is an intracellular organism. CD4+ Th1-type cellular responses are essential for
      protection and there is increasing evidence from animal and human studies that CD8+ T cells
      also play a protective role2. However, it has generally been difficult to induce strong
      cellular immune responses in humans using subunit vaccines. DNA vaccines induce both CD4+ and
      CD8+ T cells and thus offer a potential new approach to a TB vaccine. DNA vaccines encoding
      various antigens from M. tuberculosis have been evaluated in the murine model, and to date no
      DNA vaccine alone has been shown to be superior to BCG.

      A heterologous prime-boost immunisation strategy involves giving two different vaccines, each
      encoding the same antigen, several weeks apart. Such regimes are extremely effective at
      inducing a cellular immune response. Using a DNA- prime/MVA-boost immunisation strategy
      induces high levels of CD8+ T cells in animal models of malaria and HIV5, and high levels of
      both CD4+ and CD8+ T cells in animal models of TB. BCG immunisation alone induces only CD4+ T
      cells in mice. A prime-boost strategy using BCG as the prime and a recombinant MVA encoding
      an antigen from M.tb that is also present in BCG (antigen 85A: 'MVA85A') as the boost,
      induces much higher levels of CD4+ T cells than BCG or MVA85A alone. In addition, this regime
      generates specific CD8+ T cells that are undetectable following immunisation with BCG alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recombinant viruses as vaccines.

      Recombinant viruses used alone have for some years represented a promising vaccine delivery
      system, particularly for inducing cellular immune responses8. The recombinant virus encodes
      the immunising protein or peptide. Immunisation by a recombinant virus vaccine occurs when
      host cells take up and express the inoculated attenuated virus encoding a protective antigen.
      The expressed protein often has the native conformation, glycosylation, and other
      post-translational modifications that occur during natural infection. Recombinant viral
      vaccines may elicit both antibody and cytotoxic T-lymphocyte responses, which persist without
      further immunisations.

      Many viruses have been investigated as potential recombinant vaccines. The successful
      worldwide eradication of smallpox via vaccination with live vaccinia virus highlighted
      vaccinia as a candidate for recombinant use. The recognition in recent years that
      non-replicating strains of poxvirus such as MVA and avipox vectors can be more immunogenic
      than traditional replicating vaccinia strains has enhanced the attractiveness of this
      approach. MVA (modified vaccinia virus Ankara) is a strain of vaccinia virus which has been
      passaged more than 570 times though avian cells, is replication incompetent in human cell
      lines and has a good safety record. It has been administered to more than 120,000 vaccinees
      as part of the smallpox eradication programme, with no adverse effects, despite the
      deliberate vaccination of high risk groups. This safety in man is consistent with the
      avirulence of MVA in animal models. MVA has six major genomic deletions compared to the
      parental genome severely compromising its ability to replicate in mammalian cells. Viral
      replication is blocked late during infection of cells but importantly viral and recombinant
      protein synthesis is unimpaired even during this abortive infection. Replication-deficient
      recombinant MVA has been seen as an exceptionally safe viral vector. When tested in animal
      model studies recombinant MVAs have been shown to be avirulent, yet protectively immunogenic
      as vaccines against viral diseases and cancer. The most useful data on the safety and
      efficacy of various doses of a recombinant MVA vaccine comes from clinical trial data with a
      recombinant MVA expressing a number of CTL epitopes from Plasmodium falciparum
      pre-erythrocytic antigens fused to a complete pre-erythrocytic stage antigen, Thrombospondin
      Related Adhesion Protein (TRAP). These trials have given a total of 169 immunisations with
      this recombinant MVA, to 49 UK vaccinees 38 Gambian vaccines (20 of whom were children aged
      1-5). 6 doses of 1 x 10^7 pfu, 139 doses of 5 x 10^7 pfu, 6 doses of 1 x 10^8 pfu and 18
      doses of 2.5 x 10^8 pfu have been administered, all without serious adverse effects.

      Recombinant MVA encoding antigen 85A

      Secreted antigens from M. tuberculosis are released from actively metabolising bacteria, and
      are important targets in protective immunity. Antigen 85A is a major secreted antigen from M.
      tuberculosis which forms part of the antigen 85 complex (A, B and C). This complex
      constitutes a major portion of the secreted proteins of both M.tb and BCG. It is involved in
      fibronectin binding within the cell wall and has mycolyltransferase activity.

      MVA85A induces both a CD4+ and a CD8+ epitope when used to immunise mice. When mice are
      primed with BCG and then given MVA85A as a boost, the levels of CD4+ and CD8+ T cells induced
      are higher than with either BCG or MVA85A alone.

      We are evaluating the safety and immunogenicity of the following 3 groups:

        1. BCG alone

        2. MVA85A alone

        3. BCG prime-MVA85A boost

      BCG-BCG provides a control group for BCG-MVA85A. Many countries have a tradition of repeated
      BCG vaccination and the criteria for revaccination differ between countries.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The occurence and severity of local side-effects The occurence and severity of systemic side-effects</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The induction of T cell responses (as measured by an interferon-gamma Elispot assay). Other exploratory cellular immunology assays will be performed as such assays are developed.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>TB</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BCG delivered intradermally into the deltoid region in volunteers who have received BCG 10 - 20 years previously.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BCG</intervention_name>
    <description>intradermal injection of 0.1ml BCG over the deltoid muscle</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bacille Calmette-Guerin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adult aged 18-55 years.

          -  Normal medical history and physical examination.

          -  Normal urine dipstick, blood count, liver enzymes, and creatinine.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exposure to TB at any point. A positive ESAT6/CFP10 Elispot response (defined as
             greater than 5 spots/well above background and at least double the background
             response).

          -  Clinically significant history of skin disorder (eczema, psoriasis, etc.), allergy,
             immunodeficiency, cardiovascular disease, respiratory disease, endocrine disorder,
             liver disease, renal disease, gastrointestinal disease, neurological illness,
             psychiatric disorder, drug or alcohol abuse.

          -  Oral or systemic steroid medication or the use of immunosuppressive agents.

          -  Positive HIV antibody test, HCV antibody test or positive HBV serology except
             post-vaccination.

          -  Heaf test greater than Grade II

          -  Confirmed pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helen McShane</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Clinical Vaccinology and Tropical Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 7LJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>McShane H, Brookes R, Gilbert SC, Hill AV. Enhanced immunogenicity of CD4(+) t-cell responses and protective efficacy of a DNA-modified vaccinia virus Ankara prime-boost vaccination regimen for murine tuberculosis. Infect Immun. 2001 Feb;69(2):681-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11159955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McShane H, Behboudi S, Goonetilleke N, Brookes R, Hill AV. Protective immunity against Mycobacterium tuberculosis induced by dendritic cells pulsed with both CD8(+)- and CD4(+)-T-cell epitopes from antigen 85A. Infect Immun. 2002 Mar;70(3):1623-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11854254</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr Helen McShane</name_title>
    <organization>University of Oxford</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TB</keyword>
  <keyword>Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>MVA85A</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>BCG</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

