<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00659048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BY9010/M1-408</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00659048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation of Potential Additive Inhibitory Effects on HPA-Axis of Ciclesonide Nasal Spray When Administered Concomitantly With Orally Inhaled Beclomethasone Dipropionate (HFA-BDP) in Patients With Perennial Allergic Rhinitis (PAR) (BY9010/M1-408)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of Potential Additive Inhibitory Effects on HPA-Axis of Ciclesonide Nasal Spray When Administered Concomitantly With Orally Inhaled Beclomethasone Dipropionate (HFA-BDP) in Patients (18-60 Years) With Perennial Allergic Rhinitis (PAR)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AstraZeneca</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to demonstrate that there are no clinically relevant
      additive inhibitory effects on the HPA-axis when ciclesonide nasal spray is concomitantly
      administered with orally inhaled HFA-BDP. The secondary objectives are to evaluate safety and
      tolerability of the combined dosing regimen of orally inhaled HFA-BDP and ciclesonide nasal
      spray.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>24 h plasma cortisol profiles and urinary cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>53 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>24-hour urinary cortisol will be monitored at the following times</measure>
    <time_frame>53 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>53 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>53 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">106</enrollment>
  <condition>Rhinitis, Allergic, Perennial</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ciclesonide 200µg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ciclesonide</intervention_name>
    <description>Ciclesonide 200µg versus Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female, 18 - 60 years of age.

          2. General good health, and free of any concomitant conditions or treatment that could
             interfere with study conduct, influence the interpretation of study
             observations/results, or put the patient at increased risk during the trial.

          3. A history of PAR for a minimum of one year immediately preceding the Screening Visit.

          4. A demonstrated sensitivity to at least one allergen known to induce PAR through a
             standard prick or intradermal test. A positive test is defined as a wheal diameter at
             least 3 mm larger than the control wheal for the prick test, and 7 mm or greater than
             the control for the intradermal test. Documentation of a positive result within 12
             months prior to the Screening Visit is acceptable.

          5. Females of child-bearing potential are currently taking and will continue to use a
             medically reliable method of contraception for the entire study duration (e.g. oral,
             injectable, trans-cutaneous or implantable contraceptives or intrauterine devices or
             double-barrier protection). Women of childbearing potential, or less than 1 year
             postmenopausal, will require a negative plasma pregnancy test at the Screening Visit
             as well as at last on-treatment visit.

          6. Capable of understanding the requirements, risks, and benefits of study participation,
             and, as judged by the investigator, capable of giving informed consent and compliance
             with all study requirements (visits, record keeping, etc).

          7. Normal body weight as evidenced by a Body Mass Index (BMI) between ³ 18 and 31 kg/m²,
             and a body weight &gt; 45 kg.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy, nursing, or plans to become pregnant or donate gametes (ova or sperm) for
             in vitro fertilization during the study period or for 30 days following the study
             period.

          2. History or physical findings of nasal pathology, including nasal polyps (within the
             last 60 days) or other clinically significant respiratory tract malformations, recent
             nasal biopsy (within the last 60 days), nasal trauma, or surgery and atrophic rhinitis
             or rhinitis medicamentosa (within the last 60 days).

          3. Participation in any investigational drug trial within the 30 days preceding the
             Screening Visit (S0).

          4. A known hypersensitivity to any corticosteroid or any of the excipients in the
             formulations.

          5. History or current evidence of clinically relevant allergies or idiosyncrasy to drugs
             or food.

          6. History of alcohol or drug abuse within the preceding two years.

          7. History of a positive test for HIV, hepatitis B or hepatitis C.

          8. Use of any prohibited concomitant medications within the prescribed (per protocol)
             withdrawal periods prior to the Screening Visit (S0) and during entire study duration.

          9. Previous participation in an intranasal ciclesonide study.

         10. Non-vaccinated exposure to or active infection with, chickenpox or measles within the
             21 days preceding the Screening Visit (S0).

         11. Exposure to corticosteroids for any indication, chronic or intermittent (e.g.: asthma,
             contact dermatitis), during the past 2 months, or presence of an underlying condition
             that can reasonably be expected to require treatment with corticosteroids during the
             course of the study.

         12. Use of topical corticosteroids in concentrations in excess of the equivalent of 1%
             hydrocortisone for dermatological conditions during the past 1 month, or presence of
             an underlying condition that can reasonably be expected to require treatment with such
             preparations during the course of the study.

         13. Clinically relevant abnormalities in clinical chemical, hematological or any other
             laboratory variables.

         14. Chronic or clinically relevant acute infections.

         15. Vegetarian diet or other unusual dietary habits that would preclude the subject's
             acceptance of standardized meals.

         16. Blood donation within the last 30 days before start of the study.

         17. Patients that do not have regular sleep patterns (e.g. working at night and sleeping
             during the daylight hours).

         18. Active asthma requiring treatment with inhaled or systemic corticosteroids;
             intermittent use of beta agonists is acceptable.

         19. History of a respiratory infection or disorder [including, but not limited to
             bronchitis, pneumonia, the common cold, acute or chronic sinusitis, flu, severe acute
             respiratory syndrome (SARS)] within the 14 days preceding the Screening Visit (S0), or
             development of a respiratory infection during the Run-in Period.

         20. Use of antibiotic therapy for acute conditions within 14 days prior to the Screening
             Visit (S0). Low doses of antibiotics taken for prophylaxis are permitted if the
             therapy was started prior to the Screening Visit (S0) AND is expected to continue
             throughout the trial.

         21. Initiation of immunotherapy during the study period or dose escalation during the
             study period. However, initiation of immunotherapy 90 days or more prior to the
             Screening Visit (S0) AND use of a stable (maintenance) dose (30 days or more) may be
             considered for inclusion.

         22. Failure to adequately understand and comply with the HFA-BDP instructions or failure
             to properly administer study medication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>AstraZeneca AstraZeneca</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>AstraZeneca</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Altana/Nycomed</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_MED_7111&amp;studyid=4536&amp;filename=BY9010-M1-408-RDS-2005-12-05.pdf</url>
    <description>BY9010-M1-408-RDS-2005-12-05.pdf</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 14, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 15, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 16, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Perennial Allergic Rhinitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Ciclesonide</keyword>
  <keyword>PAR</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic, Perennial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Beclomethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ciclesonide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

