<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00650182</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR006715</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00650182</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety of D-TRANS Fentanyl With Naltrexone in Adult Patients With Chronic Pain and Who Are Opioid Tolerant</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety Evaluation of D-TRANS Fentanyl With Naltrexone HCL in Opioid Tolerant Patients (ALZA C-2002-022)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alza Corporation, DE, USA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alza Corporation, DE, USA</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective was to evaluate the safety of D-TRANS fentanyl with naltrexone HCl
      system compared to the Duragesic (fentanyl transdermal system) in opioid tolerant patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This was a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, double-dummy safety study in adult patients
      who required continuous opioid treatment for chronic pain. Patients had to be on a stable
      dose of duragesic for 21 days prior to the start of the study treatment period and have
      completed a screening period of at least 14 days to enter this study. Eligible patients were
      randomized (2:1) to receive the equivalent strength of D-TRANS fentanyl with naltrexone HCl
      (and placebo Duragesic) or the same dose of Duragesic (and placebo D-TRANS fentanyl with
      naltrexone HCl [D-TRANS fentanyl with naltrexone]) for a 15-day treatment period. If
      necessary, patients could be titrated to higher or lower doses during the 15-day treatment
      period. Each system was worn for 72 hours then replaced by a new system until the end of the
      15-day treatment period. Patients were telephoned 3 times a day during the first 3 days of
      the study and then once daily for the remainder of the study to determine if there were any
      signs of opiate overdose or withdrawal. The patient was to be followed as medically indicated
      based on the responses to the questions. Safety assessments included summarizing the
      incidences of adverse events (including topical adverse events), vital signs measurements,
      and clinical laboratory evaluations. Blood samples were also collected for analysis of
      naltrexone and fentanyl concentrations at scheduled times during the study. Efficacy
      assessments included patient global assessments, investigator global assessments, pain
      intensity, and brief pain inventory. Blood samples were also to be collected for analysis of
      naltrexone and fentanyl prior to any dose change and if a patient experienced a serious
      adverse event possibly or probably related to study drug. Duragesic delivering fentanyl doses
      of 25 mcg/h, 50 mcg/h, 75 mcg/h, or 100 mcg/h, and a D-TRANS placebo on Days 1, 4, 7, 10, and
      13 or D-TRANS fentanyl with naltrexone delivering fentanyl doses of 25 mcg/h, 50 mcg/h, 75
      mcg/h, or 100 mcg/h, and a placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2003</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety of 2 transdermal formulations of fentanyl (D-TRANS fentanyl with naltrexone transdermal system and Duragesic (fentanyl transdermal system) in patients with chronic pain who were opioid tolerant.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy assessments included patient global assessments, investigator global assessments, pain intensity, and brief pain inventory. Blood samples were also to be collected for analysis of naltrexone and fentanyl prior to any dose change.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">406</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fentanyl; naltrexone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of chronic pain who require continuous opioid analgesia

          -  Must enter the study on a stable dose of Duragesic for at least 21 days and consent to
             use a medically acceptable method of contraception throughout the entire study, and
             for females 1 week after the study is completed and for males 3 months after the study
             is completed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Skin disease that precluded the use of a transdermal system

          -  Clinically significant laboratory abnormalities

          -  Significant mental status changes that result in disorientation, memory impairment, or
             inability to report accurately

          -  Illicit drug, prescription drug, or alcohol abuse

          -  Cardiopulmonary disease

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alza Corporation Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>ALZA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=107&amp;filename=CR006715_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>Click here to view the journal abstract from the study manuscript.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>patch</keyword>
  <keyword>fentanyl</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Naltrexone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

