<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00517543</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>109385</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00517543</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Examine the Effect of Particle Size on Bioequivalence and Bioavailability</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open Label, 4 Period Crossover Study in Healthy Subjects to Determine the Effect of Particle Size on the Pharmacokinetics of a Single mg Dose of GW856553</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being conducted to measure the amount of study drug that is in your blood after
      you receive a different type of tablet in each of four study visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1) to demonstrate bioequivalence of four different particle sizes by assay of blood from dosing through 72 hours post dose in each of four study periods</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1) determine/compare relative bioavailability by assay of blood (dosing to 72 hr in 4 study periods) 2) assess safety/tolerability of single oral doses thru AE reporting; vs &amp; ECG monitoring from per 1 dosing thru study f/u</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>determine the relative bioavailability of a single oral dose of 15 mg GW856553 in healthy subjects using a tablet with a particle size of &gt; 20 microns (a milled formulation) compared to tablets with particle sizes of 2 microns, 4 microns, and 6 microns.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</condition>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GW856553</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adult males and females between 18 and 60 years of age, inclusive. Whether a
             subject is &quot;healthy&quot; will be determined by a responsible physician, based on a medical
             evaluation including history, physical examination, laboratory tests, cardiac
             monitoring.

          -  To be eligible, female subjects must have a negative pregnancy test (i.e. serum hCG
             test) and be of:

               1. non-childbearing potential (i.e. physiologically incapable of becoming pregnant).
                  This includes pre-menopausal females with documented (medical report
                  verification) hysterectomy or double oophorectomy or postmenopausal defined as 12
                  months of spontaneous amenorrhea or 6 months of spontaneous amenorrhea with serum
                  FSH levels &gt; 40 mIU/mL or 6 weeks postsurgical bilateral oophorectomy with or
                  without hysterectomy, or documented hysterectomy - tubal ligation is not
                  sufficient.

               2. childbearing potential and agrees to commit to two of the protocol-approved
                  methods of contraception, when used consistently and in accordance with both the
                  product label and the instructions of a physician (and as listed in Appendix 3).

          -  Male subjects must agree to abstain from or use a condom during sexual intercourse
             with pregnant or lactating females; or use a condom/spermicide, in addition to having
             their female partner use another form of contraception, such as an IUD, diaphragm with
             spermicide, oral contraceptive, inject able progesterone, or sub dermal implant if
             engaging in sexual intercourse with a female partner who could become pregnant. This
             criterion must be followed from the time of the first dose of study medication until
             completion of follow up procedures.

          -  Body weight &gt;/ 50 kg (110 pounds) for men and &gt;/ 45 kg (99 pounds) for women and body
             mass index (BMI) between 19 and 31.

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and bilirubin within
             reference range at screening.

          -  Signed and dated written informed consent prior to admission to the study. The subject
             is able to understand and comply with protocol requirements, instructions and
             protocol-stated restrictions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any clinically relevant abnormality identified on the screening medical assessment,
             laboratory examination, or ECG (12 lead) judged by the Investigator and /or GSK
             medical monitor to potentially introduce additional risk factors and/or interfere with
             the study procedures.

          -  Significant cardiac, pulmonary, metabolic, renal, hepatic, neurological, psychiatric,
             or gastrointestinal conditions that in the opinion of the investigator and/or GSK
             medical monitor, places the subject at an unacceptable risk as participant in this
             trial.

          -  History of Gilbert's syndrome.

          -  Elevated blood pressure or history of elevated blood pressure considered clinically
             significant by the Investigator.

          -  History of increased liver function tests [alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate
             aminotransferase (AST) above 1.5 x upper limit of normal (UNL) in the past 6 months.

          -  History of alcohol/drug abuse or dependence within 12 months of the study.

          -  The subject has a positive pre-study drug or alcohol screen.

          -  Positive for Hepatitis C antibody, Hepatitis B surface antigen or HIV.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption averaging &gt; 7 drinks/week for women or &gt; 14
             drinks/week for men. One drink is equivalent to (12 g alcohol) = 5 ounces (150 mL) of
             wine; or 12 ounces (360 mL) of beer; or 1.5 ounces (45 mL) of 80 proof distilled
             spirits within 6 months of screening.

          -  Urinary cotinine levels indicative of smoking. History or regular use of tobacco or
             nicotine-containing products within 6 months prior to screening.

          -  Use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including vitamins, herbal and dietary
             supplements (including St John'sWort, kava, ephedra (ma huang), gingko biloba, DHEA,
             yohimbe, saw palmetto, ginseng and red yeast rice) within 7 days or 5 half-lives
             (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of study medication, unless in the
             opinion of the Investigator and sponsor the medication will not interfere with the
             study procedures or compromise subject safety.

          -  Where participation in this study would result in donation of blood in excess of 500
             mL within a 56-day period.

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  Treatment with an investigational drug within 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to dosing.

          -  Female subjects who are nursing, pregnant, or plan to become pregnant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tacoma</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98418</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 17, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>October 13, 2010</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>October 13, 2010</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2010</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 13, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 13, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Study Director</name_title>
    <organization>GSK</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

