<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00048789</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030025</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-I-0025</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00048789</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Extracorporeal Photopheresis to Treat Chronic Graft-Versus-Host Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Chronic Graft Versus Host Disease With Extracorporeal Photopheresis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the safety and effectiveness of extracorporeal photopheresis (ECP)
      for treating chronic graft-versus-host disease (GvHD). GvHD is a common complication of stem
      cell transplantation using donated stem cells. It occurs when the donor's T-lymphocytes (a
      type of immune cell) see the patient's cells as foreign and mount an immune response to
      reject them. The attack can cause skin rash, mouth sores, liver or lung inflammation, lack of
      appetite, and muscle stiffness. Chronic GvHD can cause serious illness, and even death, from
      the long-term effects of immune dysfunction and from toxic effects of medications (such as
      cyclosporine and prednisone) used to treat it.

      ECP is an experimental treatment designed to stop the lymphocytes from attacking the body. It
      involves collecting some of the cells that cause GvHD, treating them with a combination of
      drug and light therapy and returning them to the body. Sixty to 80 percent of patients with
      chronic GvHD improve with ECP treatment, and some patients can stop treatment with prednisone
      or cyclosporine, or reduce the drug dosages.

      Patients with chronic GvHD whose condition has not improved after a minimum 14-day course of
      cyclosporine and prednisone may be eligible for this study. Patients must be able to travel
      to the NIH Clinical Center in Bethesda, Maryland, twice a week during the 3-month study
      period.

      Upon entering the study, participants will have a baseline evaluation to measure the extent
      of GvHD. This assessment includes blood tests, eye and dental examinations, skin biopsy for
      patients with skin involvement, and CT scans and lung function tests to look for possible
      lung involvement. Biopsies of the lung, liver, mouth, or eye may be requested if needed to
      confirm GvHD in these tissues. The skin will be photographed before starting ECP treatment
      and once a month during the treatment period. Following baseline tests, participants will
      undergo treatment and evaluations as follows:

      ECP Treatment

      Patients will have blood drawn to collect lymphocytes causing GvHD. This may be done with a
      special needle or catheter (tube inserted into a vein) or for patients who need or prefer it
      with a temporary central venous catheter similar to that used for the stem cell
      transplantation. Patients will have three 2- to 3-hour treatments a week for the first week
      and two treatments a week after that for a total of 25 treatments over 3 months. Patients who
      do not tolerate the treatment...
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 2 study of extracorporeal photopheresis (ECP) for treatment of chronic graft
      versus host disease following allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation.
      Extracorporeal exposure of human mononuclear cells to ultraviolet A radiation following
      photosensitization with 8-methoxypsoralen has proven to be an effective treatment for
      cutaneous T-cell lymphoma. Small, single institution studies have suggested efficacy in other
      T-cell mediated diseases such as solid organ rejection and graft versus host disease. This a
      phase 2 study of ECP for treatment of chronic graft versus host disease. Eligible patients
      must have objective evidence of chronic graft versus host disease that is refractory to
      conventional therapy or must have steroid-dependent disease that does not permit steroid dose
      reduction. The primary objective of this study is to better define the safety, efficacy and
      mechanism of action of ECP for treatment of patients with chronic graft versus host disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 4, 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 29, 2009</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of response rate including degree of improvement; steroid sparing effect; types of cGVHD problems which respond to this therapy; assessment of problems or side effects or adverse events associated with the procedure.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>25</enrollment>
  <condition>Graft vs Host Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extracorporeal Photopheresis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Objective evidence of chronic graft versus host disease involving the skin,
                  lungs, gastrointestinal tract, liver, or eyes.

               2. Progressive or stable GvHD despite a minimum of 30 days treatment with a
                  calcineurin inhibitor (cyclosporine or tacrolimus) at therapeutic plasma levels,
                  plus at least one other another agent with a different mechanism of action used
                  concurrently for at least 30 days at doses known to be therapeutic for cGvHD. In
                  most cases this second agent will be a corticosteroid administered either as high
                  level pulse dosing (greater than or equal to mg/kg/day prednisone or equivalent
                  in pulses of 3 days or longer for at least two occasions during the qualifying 30
                  days) and/or daily dosing (greater than or equal to 0.25mg/kg) or alternate day
                  dosing (greater than or equal to 0.50 mg/kg) prednisone or equivalent. In other
                  cases where use of steroids is medically undesirable or contraindicated, the
                  second agent may be mycophenolate mofetil, sirolimus, hydroxychloroquine,
                  clofazimine, thalidomide, azathioprine, pentostatin, etanercept, Infliximab,
                  Rituximab or Daclizumab used at doses and schedule known to provide benefit to
                  patients with cGvHD. Patients in whom calcineurin inhibitors are medically
                  contraindicated may also be eligible for enrollment if there has been at least a
                  30 day trial of prednisone (or equivalent) at the doses/schedules noted above
                  plus one of the second agents listed above. Patients in whom both calcineurin
                  inhibitors and steroids are medically contraindicated or in whom these agents can
                  be used at only limiting doses may also be eligible if at least two of the
                  alternate agents noted above have been tried for 30 days without further
                  improvement in symptoms of cGvHD. Patients who have stabilization of disease on
                  calcineurin inhibitors plus steroids (or the other combinations noted above), but
                  in whom these medications cannot be tapered without disease flare are also
                  eligible.

               3. Adequate (as determined by PI) renal, hepatic, and cardiac reserve to enable the
                  patient to tolerate Extracorporeal Photopheresis.

               4. The patient's malignancy (if applicable) is in complete remission or the patient
                  is not a candidate for further immune-based anti-tumor therapy (such as donor
                  lymphocyte infusions or immunomodulatory cytokines) due to severity of GvHD.

               5. WBC greater than or equal to 1000 and platelets greater than or equal to 25,000.

               6. Weight greater than or equal to 30kg.

               7. Female patients not pregnant and agree to use a reliable method of birth control
                  during the treatment period

               8. Systolic blood pressure greater than or equal to 90 mm Hg.

               9. Karnofsky score or Lansky score greater than or equal to 30.

              10. Predicted life expectancy of at least 3 months.

              11. A minimum of 100 days following stem cell transplantation.

              12. A minimum of 30 days without a response to, and 7 days following cessation of,
                  certain investigational 2nd-line agents for treatment of GvHD (specifically:
                  thalidomide, azathioprine, pentostatin, etanercept, Infliximab, Rituximab or
                  Daclizumab).

              13. History of failure to achieve any clinical benefit from a previous treatment with
                  ECP where at least 3 months (12 weeks) of twice a week every other week therapy
                  was administered.

              14. Signed and witnessed informed consent.

              15. Hemoglobin greater than 9.5, hematocrit greater than 28.5 (patients not meeting
                  this inclusion criterion may be treated with iron supplementation and/or
                  erythropoietin/darbepoetin until their hgb/hct are in the Inclusion range and may
                  then be reconsidered for study entry).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Hypersensitivity or allergy to psoralen (methoxypsoralen).

          2. Hypersensitivity to both heparin and/or citrate products.

          3. Patients who are unable to visit the NIH clinical center twice a week for at least the
             first four week treatment period of ECP treatments; or for the NIH or arranged home
             treatments with ECP thereafter; or for the every 4 week medical evaluation visits to
             NIH.

          4. Frank gastrointestinal bleeding due to GvHD (occult blood positivity excluded).

          5. Patients taking a cancer chemotherapeutic agent for continued treatment of malignancy.

          6. Patients undergoing radiation therapy.

          7. The patient's malignancy (if applicable) is NOT in complete remission or the patient
             is a candidate for further immune-based anti-tumor therapy (such as donor lymphocyte
             infusions or immunomodulatory cytokines) to treat GvHD.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akpek G, Zahurak ML, Piantadosi S, Margolis J, Doherty J, Davidson R, Vogelsang GB. Development of a prognostic model for grading chronic graft-versus-host disease. Blood. 2001 Mar 1;97(5):1219-26. Erratum in: Blood 2002 Jan 1;99(1):14.</citation>
    <PMID>11222363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sullivan KM, Witherspoon RP, Storb R, Deeg HJ, Dahlberg S, Sanders JE, Appelbaum FR, Doney KC, Weiden P, Anasetti C, et al. Alternating-day cyclosporine and prednisone for treatment of high-risk chronic graft-v-host disease. Blood. 1988 Aug;72(2):555-61.</citation>
    <PMID>3042042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoo EK, Rook AH, Elenitsas R, Gasparro FP, Vowels BR. Apoptosis induction of ultraviolet light A and photochemotherapy in cutaneous T-cell Lymphoma: relevance to mechanism of therapeutic action. J Invest Dermatol. 1996 Aug;107(2):235-42.</citation>
    <PMID>8757769</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 29, 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Psoralen</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cell</keyword>
  <keyword>UVA</keyword>
  <keyword>Graft-versus-host Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>GVHD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

