<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00042627</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>020255</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>02-EI-0255</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00042627</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevalence and Risk of Cataracts in Granulocyte Donors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevalence and Risks for Posterior Subcapsular Cataracts in Volunteer Granulocytapheresis Donors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate whether people who donate granulocytes (a type of white blood
      cell) by leukapheresis are at increased risk of developing cataracts (changes in the lens of
      the eye that can impair vision). Apheresis is a method of collecting large numbers of white
      blood cells. The procedure is similar to donating whole blood, but the collected blood is
      circulated through a cell separator machine, the white cells are extracted, and the rest of
      the blood is returned to the donor. Before the procedure, donors are given a steroid called
      dexamethasone. This drug temporarily increases the number of granulocytes circulating in the
      blood, thus allowing twice as many of these cells to be collected.

      Recently, one blood collection center reported greater numbers of cataracts in a small number
      of granulocyte donors who had received repeated doses of steroids for granulocyte
      mobilization. The donors were unaware that they had the cataracts, which were small and did
      not affect their vision. Although people who take high doses of steroids over a long period
      time are known to have an increased risk of cataracts, steroids given infrequently (and in
      the doses used for granulocyte donation) have not been associated with cataracts. This study
      will examine the eyes of granulocyte donors and of platelet donors. Platelets-blood
      components necessary for clotting-are also collected by pheresis, but donors are not given
      steroids before the procedure. The examination findings will be compared to see if there is a
      difference in the risk of cataract formation in the two groups.

      People 18 years of age and older who have donated granulocytes or platelets at the NIH
      Department of Transfusion Medicine four times or more since 1984 may be eligible for this
      study. Participants will undergo the following procedures:

        -  Detailed medical history, including allergies, corticosteroid use, diabetes mellitus,
           and asthma

        -  Detailed eye history, including cataracts, glaucoma, other eye diseases and infections,
           eye trauma, and corrective lenses

        -  Detailed history of sun exposure

        -  Eye examination, including measurement of visual acuity (eye chart test) and eye
           pressure, examination of the lens and retina.

        -  Photographs of the eye using a special camera
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An increased prevalence of cataracts was recently described in a small number of granulocyte
      donors who had received repeated doses of adrenal corticosteroids as part of their
      mobilization regimen for granulocyte donation. Mild posterior subcapsular cataracts (PSCs)
      were found in 4 of 11 (36%) of granulocyte donors versus 0 of 9 platelet donors. Though the
      relationship or corticosteroid administration to the development of PSCs is well established,
      not all steroid recipients develop such lesions. Observational studies suggest that the
      development of PSCs is an associated risk if steroids are given for a prolonged period of
      time (greater than 10 mg/day for 1-2 years). To maximize the cellular yield of
      granulocytapheresis procedures, granulocyte donors are given a single dose of an adrenal
      steroid the day prior to donation. Since 1984, it has been standard practice in the NIH
      Department of Transfusion Medicine (DTM) to administer dexamethasone 8 mg orally 12 hours
      prior to donation. Since 1996 both dexamethasone 8 mg orally as well as granulocyte
      colony-stimulating-factor (G-CSF) 5 microg/kg subcutaneously are administered on the day
      prior to donation to maximize cell yields during apheresis. It is also standard procedure in
      DTM to restrict granulocyte donation to once per month (12 times/year), with few medical
      exceptions. To determine the prevalence of ophthalmologic abnormalities, particularly PSCs,
      in DTM granulocyte donors, we propose to perform a medical history and comprehensive blinded
      ophthalmologic examination on all consenting granulocyte donors. Age and gender-matched
      volunteer plateletpheresis donors will be invited as controls. If an increase in the
      incidence of PSCs or other lens or eye abnormalities is found in the granulocyte donors
      compared with the plateletpheresis donors, we will attempt to correlate the factors operating
      during granulocyte donation that are related to this increased risk.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 30, 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 25, 2007</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>252</enrollment>
  <condition>Apheresis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Signed and understood informed consent.

        Study subjects must be NIH DTM volunteer apheresis donors who have donated granulocytes on
        4 or more occasions since 1984.

        Control subjects must be NIH DTM volunteer apheresis donors who have donated platelets on 4
        or more occasions since 1984.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Persons less than 18 years old.

        Persons who have donated granulocytes outside DTM on more than four occasions.

        Persons who have donated platelets outside DTM on more than four occasions.

        Donors with a known history of cataracts will NOT be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strauss RG. Therapeutic granulocyte transfusions in 1993. Blood. 1993 Apr 1;81(7):1675-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8117344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 25, 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 1, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cataracts</keyword>
  <keyword>Granulocytapheresis</keyword>
  <keyword>Granulocyte Donors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

