<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00049283</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2012-03113</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CWRU 1301</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA099168</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA062502</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00049283</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Erlotinib, Docetaxel, and Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Locally Advanced Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of the Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor, OSI-774, in Combination With Docetaxel and Radiation in Locally Advanced Squamous Cell Cancer of the Head and Neck</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so they stop
      growing or die. Erlotinib may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking the enzymes
      necessary for tumor cell growth. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to damage tumor
      cells. Combining erlotinib with docetaxel may make the tumor cells more sensitive to
      radiation therapy and may kill more tumor cells. Phase I trial to study the maximum tolerated
      dose (MTD) of combining erlotinib with docetaxel and radiation therapy in treating patients
      who have locally advanced head and neck cancer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine MTD and toxicity of combination of EGFR inhibitor (OSI-774), docetaxel, and
      radiation.

      II. Pharmacokinetic profile of OSI-774 alone and in combination with docetaxel.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine the overall and complete response rate of this combination.

      II. Determine overall, disease free, and progression free survival of this combination.

        -  EGFR expression and phosphorylation status

        -  Serum markers of angiogenic activity VEGF, sVEGFR-2, sKIT, ICAM, PDGF

        -  Fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) for EGFR, ERBB2, PDGFR-β for gene
           amplification

        -  DNA-sequencing of EGFR and ERBB2 genes from DNA extracted from pretreatment biopsy
           material for mutation screening

        -  Gene expression profiling on pre-treatment biopsy material to identify predictors of
           response to treatment

        -  Apoptosis (TUNEL assay)

        -  Ki67 (nuclear proliferation antigen).

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of erlotinib and docetaxel.

      Patients receive oral erlotinib alone daily on weeks 1 and 2. Patients then receive oral
      erlotinib daily beginning on day 1 and docetaxel IV over 1 hour on day 3 of weeks 3-9.
      Patients also undergo radiotherapy once daily 5 days a week on weeks 3-9. Patients continue
      erlotinib for up to 2 years in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
      Patients who had N2 or greater cervical lymph node involvement at baseline or have residual
      neck adenopathy after chemoradiotherapy undergo neck dissection 6-8 weeks after completion of
      chemoradiotherapy. Erlotinib is held for 1 week before planned surgery and until healing is
      complete.

      Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of erlotinib and docetaxel until the MTD is
      determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6 patients
      experience dose-limiting toxicity.

      Patients are followed every 16 weeks for 1 year after completion of erlotinib, every 24 weeks
      for 2 years, and then annually thereafter.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Approximately 30 patients will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity assessed using Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) version 3.0 (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic profile (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24 48, and 72 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to disease progression (TTP) (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5.5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS) (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of treatment to date of death or date of disease progression, and to date of last follow-up for those still alive and progression free, assessed up to 5.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated by Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of treatment to date of death, and to date of last follow-up for those still alive, assessed up to 5.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated by Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>True objective response rate (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated based on the number of responses using a binomial distribution and its confidence interval will be estimated using Wilson's method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of EGFR expression and serum markers over time (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to 5.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Wilcoxon signed rank test (the non-parametric version of paired T-test) will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patterns of gene expression data (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cluster analysis including hierarchical clustering, Gaussian clustering, k means clustering, will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer With Occult Primary Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Hypopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Hypopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVC Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Tongue Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer With Occult Primary</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (erlotinib hydrochloride, docetaxel, and radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive oral erlotinib alone daily on weeks 1 and 2. Patients then receive oral erlotinib daily beginning on day 1 and docetaxel IV over 1 hour on day 3 of weeks 3-9. Patients also undergo radiotherapy once daily 5 days a week on weeks 3-9. Patients continue erlotinib for up to 2 years in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients who had N2 or greater cervical lymph node involvement at baseline or have residual neck adenopathy after chemoradiotherapy undergo neck dissection 6-8 weeks after completion of chemoradiotherapy. Erlotinib is held for 1 week before planned surgery and until healing is complete.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>erlotinib hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (erlotinib hydrochloride, docetaxel, and radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CP-358,774</other_name>
    <other_name>erlotinib</other_name>
    <other_name>OSI-774</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (erlotinib hydrochloride, docetaxel, and radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RP 56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>TXT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo radiotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (erlotinib hydrochloride, docetaxel, and radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>irradiation</other_name>
    <other_name>radiotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>therapy, radiation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic conventional surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo neck dissection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (erlotinib hydrochloride, docetaxel, and radiation)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (erlotinib hydrochloride, docetaxel, and radiation)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pharmacological study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (erlotinib hydrochloride, docetaxel, and radiation)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pharmacological studies</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed locally advanced (stage
             III or IV) squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck without distant metastatic
             disease

          -  No prior chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or investigational anti-tumor drug

          -  Measurable disease within 4 weeks prior to registration according to the recommended
             RECIST response criteria

          -  ECOG performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 12 weeks

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/ul

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/ul

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 10 mg/dL

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits

          -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) =&lt; 5 x ULN when alkaline phosphatase is =&lt; ULN

          -  Alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 5 x ULN when AST or ALT =&lt; ULN

          -  Prothrombin time within normal institutional limits

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits or creatinine clearance &gt;= 60
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  No clinically significant heart disease (including NYHA class III or IV heart disease,
             significant arrhythmias requiring medication, symptomatic coronary artery disease,
             myocardial infarction within the previous six months, second or third degree heart
             block or bundle branch block)

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation; men and women of childbearing potential must be
             willing to consent to using effective contraception while on treatment and for at
             least 3 months thereafter; women of childbearing potential must have a negative
             pregnancy test; should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  All histologies other than squamous cell carcinoma

          -  Salivary gland and paranasal sinus squamous cell carcinoma

          -  Patients who have had prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients with known brain metastases or direct cerebral invasion by tumor should be
             excluded from this clinical trial because of their poor prognosis and because they
             often develop progressive neurologic dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of
             neurologic and other adverse events; patients with intracranial extension (but without
             cerebral involvement) may still be eligible to participate

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to OSI-774 or docetaxel, including other drugs formulated with polysorbate
             80

          -  No pre-existing peripheral neuropathy &gt;= grade 2

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated on this protocol

          -  HIV positive patients are excluded from participation

          -  Patients with history of any other malignancy (except squamous cell or basal cell
             cancer of the skin or CIS of cervix) are ineligible unless a period of 5 years has
             elapsed since treatment of the previous cancer and the patient has remained
             continuously disease free

          -  Patients who are felt to be poorly compliant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Panayiotis (Panos) Savvides</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Western Reserve University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Western Reserve University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 27, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Verrucous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nasopharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Unknown Primary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tongue Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erlotinib Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

