<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00048477</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030020</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-H-0020</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00048477</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Nitrite on Blood Vessel Dilation in Normal Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determination of Nitrite as a Source of Bioactive Nitric Oxide in Human Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nitric oxide gas is important in regulating blood vessel dilation, and consequently, blood
      flow. This gas is continuously produced by endothelial cells, which line the blood vessels.
      This study will examine whether nitrite, a molecule that normally circulates in the blood
      stream, can also dilate blood vessels. The results of this study may be valuable in
      developing treatments for people with conditions associated with impaired endothelial
      production of nitric oxide, including high blood pressure, high blood cholesterol, diabetes,
      estrogen deficiency, and others.

      Healthy, non-smoking normal volunteers 21 years of age or older may be eligible for this
      study. People who lack the enzyme G6PD or cytochrome B5 in their red blood cells may not
      participate. Absence of these enzymes can lead to episodes of sudden shortness of breath and
      cyanosis (blueness of the skin due to lack of sufficient oxygen). Participants will undergo
      the procedures described in study Parts A and B, as follows:

        -  Part A - After numbing the skin, small tubes are placed in the artery and vein at the
           inside of the elbow of the dominant arm (right- or left-handed) and a small tube is
           placed in a vein of the other arm. The tubes are used for infusing saline (salt water)
           and for drawing blood samples. A pressure cuff is placed around the upper part of the
           dominant arm, and a rubber band device called a strain gauge is also placed around the
           arm to measure blood flow. When the cuff is inflated, blood flows into the arm,
           stretching the strain gauge at a rate proportional to the flow. Grip-strength of the
           dominant arm is measured with a dynamometer to determine maximum grip-strength. Then,
           several measurements of blood flow, nitrite, hemoglobin, and handgrip are made before
           and after administration of L-NMMA, a drug that blocks endothelial production of nitric
           oxide.

        -  Part B - Part A testing is repeated, except that sodium nitrite dissolved in a saline
           solution is infused into the artery of the forearm for a few minutes before and during
           the hand-grip exercises. In addition, blood samples are drawn before and after each
           handgrip exercise to measure methemoglobin, a substance that, at excessive levels, can
           cause adverse side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nitric oxide (NO) is a soluble gas continuously synthesized by the endothelium and
      contributes importantly to vasodilator tone of the coronary and systemic circulations by
      activating guanylyl cyclase in vascular smooth muscle, causing relaxation. Although regional
      synthesis of NO by the endothelium contributes to local vasodilator tone, we have shown
      previously that NO may be transported in blood, and have biological effects at a distance
      from the site of entry into the circulation. Thus, we found that NO may be transported bound
      to heme iron in red blood cells and released at vascular sites of deficient NO synthesis,
      restoring vasodilator tone. Another potential source of bioactive NO is via nitrite, formed
      by the auto-oxidation of NO. This study is designed to determine the contribution of nitrite
      transported in blood to forearm microvascular dilator tone in healthy subjects at rest and
      during regional hypoxia associated with forearm exercise stress, with measurements made
      before and after regional blockade of endothelial NO synthesis. Findings in this study may be
      relevant to understanding the physiological contribution and therapeutic potential of nitrite
      in the regulation of vasodilator tone in diseases and conditions associated with regional
      endothelial dysfunction and reduced endothelial NO bioactivity (e.g., hypertension, diabetes
      mellitus, hypercholesterolemia, cigarette smoking, estrogen deficiency).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>November 2003</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>42</enrollment>
  <condition>Nitric Oxide</condition>
  <condition>Endothelium-Derived Relaxing Factor</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L-NMMA and Sodium Nitrite</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA

        All volunteer subjects must be at least 21 years of age in good health and have provided
        informed, written consent for participation in this study.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        Subjects with a history or evidence of present or past hypertension (blood pressure greater
        than 145/95 mmHg), hypercholesterolemia (LDL cholesterol greater than 130 mg/dL), diabetes
        mellitus (fasting blood glucose greater than 130 mg/dL), smoking within two years,
        cardiovascular disease, peripheral vascular disease, coagulopathy, or any other disease
        predisposing to vasculitis or Raynaud's phenomenon.

        All subjects will be tested for red blood cell G6PD deficiency; levels below the lower
        limits of normal will result in exclusion from participation in the study.

        Subjects with a known cytochrome B5 deficiency will not participate in this study.

        Subjects with a history of reaction to a medication or other substance characterized by
        dyspnea and cyanosis will not participate in this study.

        Subjects with a baseline methemoglobin level greater than 1% will not receive nitrite
        infusions.

        Lactating and pregnant females.

        No volunteer subject will be allowed to take any medication (oral contraceptive agents are
        allowed), vitamin supplements, herbal preparations, nutriceuticals or other 'alternative
        therapies' for at least one month prior to study and will not be allowed to take aspirin
        for one week prior to study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Furchgott RF, Zawadzki JV. The obligatory role of endothelial cells in the relaxation of arterial smooth muscle by acetylcholine. Nature. 1980 Nov 27;288(5789):373-6.</citation>
    <PMID>6253831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palmer RM, Ferrige AG, Moncada S. Nitric oxide release accounts for the biological activity of endothelium-derived relaxing factor. Nature. 1987 Jun 11-17;327(6122):524-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3495737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palmer RM, Ashton DS, Moncada S. Vascular endothelial cells synthesize nitric oxide from L-arginine. Nature. 1988 Jun 16;333(6174):664-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3131684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 1, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Endothelium</keyword>
  <keyword>Vasodilation</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemoglobin</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

