<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01467843</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01AT006226-01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01467843</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of CAM and Conventional Mind-Body Therapies for Chronic Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of CAM and Conventional Mind-Body Therapies for Chronic Back Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although national expenditures on back pain treatments have increased substantially over the
      past decade, the health and functional status of persons suffering from back pain has
      deteriorated. This trial will evaluate the effectiveness, and cost-effectiveness, of a safe
      and relatively inexpensive &quot;mind-body&quot; therapy that has the potential to provide relief to
      some of the millions of Americans who continue to suffer from chronic back pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic back pain remains one of the most common and challenging public health problems in
      the U.S.. Although the amount of money spent on back pain treatments has increased
      substantially over the past decade in the U.S., the health and functional status of persons
      suffering from back pain has deteriorated. There is a clear need to identify safe, effective,
      and cost-effective treatment options for this often debilitating and expensive problem. Some
      of the more promising treatments for chronic back pain include &quot;mind-body&quot; therapies that
      address both psychological and somatic aspects of the pain experience. This randomized trial
      will compare the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction
      (MBSR), a well-established but inadequately-studied CAM mind-body therapy, with usual care
      for persons with chronic low back pain and dysfunction. This trial will also compare MBSR
      with a conventional mind-body therapy, Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy (CBT), which has been
      found to be a modestly to moderately effective treatment for chronic back pain. Should MBSR
      and/or CBT prove effective in this trial, the mechanisms (mediators) of the effects of these
      two different mind-body therapies on pain and dysfunction will be explored. Because CBT aims
      to alter patients' cognitive and behavioral responses to pain, whereas MBSR focuses on direct
      present moment experience and not on changing the thoughts or feelings about such experience,
      these two therapies are hypothesized to operate by different mechanisms. A total of 342
      adults aged 20 through 70 years who have moderately to severely disabling chronic back pain
      will be recruited and randomized in equal proportions to MBSR, CBT, and treatment as usual
      (usual care). Both the MBSR and CBT interventions will be provided to groups of up to 15
      participants once a week for 8 weeks. The primary outcomes will be back pain-related
      functional limitations (Roland scale) and pain bothersomeness (rated on a 0-10 scale).
      Secondary outcomes include depression, anxiety, perceived stress, pain interference with
      activities, and sleep disturbance. Outcomes will be measured 4, 8, 26, and 52 weeks after
      randomization. If MBSR is at least moderately more effective than usual care, this safe and
      relatively inexpensive therapy would provide an appealing treatment option for chronic back
      pain that could be made more widely available. Because of the high prevalence and costs of
      chronic back pain, treatments with even modest impact on pain and function could produce a
      large benefit on a population level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Back pain-related dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Back-related dysfunction will be measured with the modified Roland Disability Questionnaire (&quot;Roland scale&quot;), which asks whether 23 specific activities were limited due to back pain during the past week (yes or no). This measure has been found to be reliable, valid and sensitive to clinical changes and is appropriate for telephone administration and patients with moderate disability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bothersomeness of back pain</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Symptom bothersomeness will be measured by asking participants to rate how &quot;bothersome&quot; their back pain has been during the previous week on a 0 to 10 scale (0 = &quot;not at all bothersome&quot; and 10 = &quot;extremely bothersome&quot;). This question worked well in our previous trials and is highly correlated with a 0-10 measure of pain intensity (r=0.8 to 0.9). It is also highly correlated with measures of function and other outcome measures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">342</enrollment>
  <condition>Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the CBT intervention will attend eight weekly 2 hour sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the MBSR arm will attend eight weekly 2 hour MBSR sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to Usual Care will continue to receive care for their low back pain as prescribed by his/her Primary Care Physician.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The Cognitive Behavioral Therapy Intervention will be delivered during 8 weekly classes each lasting 2 hours. The classes will be held at a conveniently located Group Health Facility.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness Based Stress Reduction</intervention_name>
    <description>The Mindfulness Based Stress Reduction Classes will be delivered in 8 weekly classes each lasting 2 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  clinical Diagnosis of Low Back Pain lasting at least 3 months

          -  pain of at least 4 on a 0-10 bothersomeness scale

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  do not currently have back pain

          -  current back pain episode less then 3 months in duration

          -  current back pain is only reported as mild in dysfunction and symptoms (i.e., less
             than a score of 7 on the 0-23 modified Roland Scale or a bothersomeness score lower
             than 4 on a 0-10 scale);

          -  sciatica

          -  underlying systemic or visceral disease

          -  pregnancy

          -  abdominal aneurisms

          -  spondylolisthesis

          -  discitis

          -  spinal stenosis

          -  spinal infections

          -  cancer or unexplained weight loss

          -  recent vertebral fracture

          -  current or past participation in classes or therapies closely resembling our MBSR or
             CBT interventions for chronic pain

          -  have physical problems that won't allow them to do yoga (i.e., gross obesity, severe
             pain when bending or twisting, unable to get up and down from the floor)

          -  involved with litigation or compensation claim for back pain

          -  evidence of severe or progressive neurologic deficits

          -  radiculopathy

          -  fibromyalgia diagnosis

          -  rheumatoid arthritis

          -  back surgery within the last 2 years

          -  unstable medical or severe psychiatric conditions

          -  unable to speak or read English

          -  unable to hear

          -  plan to move out of town
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Cherkin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Group Health Cooperative</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Mindfulness Based Stress Reduction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

