<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01469702</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TASMC-11-MG-0232-11-TLV-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01469702</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Efficacy of Prednisone and Azithromycin in the Treatment of Patients With Cat Scratch Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open Label Study of Prednisone and Azithromycin in the Treatment of Patients With Cat Scratch Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bartonella henselae is the etiologic agent of cat scratch disease (CSD). 90% of patients
      present with regional lymphadenitis (typical CSD) while 10% will have disease involving other
      organs, such as neuroretinitis, arthropathy, erythema nodosum, and encephalitis (atypical
      CSD). In most CSD cases resolution occurs in 2 to 3 months although a prolonged course often
      occurs. Data on the efficacy of antibiotic therapy in CSD is limited. Azithromycin has been
      shown to have a small favorable effect in a small comparative study and is commonly
      prescribed for CSD, however its overall effect is not satisfactory. Corticosteroids may be
      effective in the treatment of CSD for the following reasons:

        -  Many experts believe that host response is involved in the pathogenesis of CSD and is
           responsible for the clinical manifestations rather than the direct effect of B.
           henselae. The absence of viable organisms in affected lymph nodes (in the presence of
           positive PCR for B. henselae DNA), and the fact that arthritis, arthralgia and erythema
           nodosum (that are often associated with autoimmune diseases) have been described in CSD,
           support this concept.

        -  Corticosteroids have been anecdotally reported to have been administered to patients
           with CSD, apparently with some success. The purpose of this study is to evaluate the
           efficacy of corticosteroids in addition to azithromycin in CSD. The study hypothesis is
           that corticosteroids will improve out come. Ten patients with typical CSD will be
           treated with a 5-day oral course of prednisone (1 mg/kg up to 60 mg/day) and
           azithromycin (500 mg on day 1 and 250 mg on days 2-5). Patients will be under followed
           up for 3 months. Major outcome measures will include duration of symptoms and signs,
           with particular emphasis on affected lymph node size and duration using a specific
           scoring system (lymphadenitis score, LS). LS will be used to evaluate lymphadenitis at
           each follow-up visit. The time period from baseline LS until 75% and 90% reduction in LS
           in the treatment group will be compared with historical controls. The historical control
           group will be consisted of age, sex, and clinical manifestations-matched CSD patients
           who were treated with azithromycin without corticosteroids.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity score of lymphadenitis using a lymphadenitis Score (LS).</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline in LS until 75% and 90% reduction in LS</time_frame>
    <description>LS will evaluate the severity of lymphadenitis, using the following clinical parameters: size of lymph node in cm; pain estimated by the patient, using a 0-5 scale (0 equals no pain, 5 the most severe pain); tenderness estimated by the physician, (0 equals no tenderness, 5 the most severe tenderness); erythema of the skin overlying the affected lymph-node (0 no erythema, 1 mild erythema, 2 moderate erythema and 3 severe erythema); suppuration of a lymph node will score 5 points, no suppuration will score 0. The total score will consist of the arithmetical summation of the 5 parameters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Cat-scratch Disease</condition>
  <condition>Bartonella Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prednison and azithromycin</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with typical cat-scratch disease will be treated with a 5-day course of prednison and azithromycin.</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prednison, azithromycin</intervention_name>
    <description>Cap Azithromycin 500 mg qd (first day), then 250 mg qd for 4 days and Tab prednison 1 mg/kg/day, not exceeding 60 mg/day, qd, for 5 days.</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prednison, Azenil</intervention_name>
    <description>Cap Azenil 500 mg qd (first day), then 250 mg qd for 4 days and Tab prednison 1 mg/kg/day, not exceeding 60 mg/day qd, for 5 days.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  Patients and/or legally authorized representative(s), if applicable, who have been
             fully informed and have given voluntary written informed consent OR patients unable to
             write and/or read but who fully understand the oral information given by the
             Investigator (or nominated representative) who have given oral informed consent
             witnessed in writing by an independent person.

          -  Ability and willingness to comply with the protocol.

          -  Male and female patients aged 14-60 years at the time of signing informed consent.

          -  Female patients must be non-lactating and at no risk of pregnancy for one of the
             following reasons: Postmenopausal (amenorrhea for at least 1 year); post hysterectomy
             and/or post-bilateral ovariectomy; if of childbearing potential, having a negative
             serum or urine human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) pregnancy test at screening and is
             using a highly effective method of birth control throughout the study; reliable sexual
             abstinence throughout the course of the study is acceptable as a highly effective
             method of birth control for the purposes of this study.

          -  Patients with clinical manifestations consistent with early typical cat scratch
             disease (lymphadenitis) before spontaneous improvement has been recorded and before
             development of suppuration.

          -  Laboratory confirmation (serology and/or PCR) of cat scratch disease

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Known history of allergy, hypersensitivity, or any serious reaction to azithromycin,
             other macrolides or corticosteroids.

          -  Patients for whom azithromycin or corticosteroids is contra-indicated.

          -  Patients at high risk for QT/QTc prolongation, e.g. Baseline prolongation of QTcF
             &gt;/=500 msec; Risk factors for Torsade de Pointes (e.g. uncompensated heart failure,
             abnormal potassium or magnesium levels that cannot be corrected, any unstable cardiac
             condition during the last 30 days, or a family history of long QT syndrome); The use
             of concomitant medications that prolong the QT/QTc interval.

          -  Current treatment with systemic corticosteroids.

          -  Patients with typical late cat scratch disease who has demonstrated constant
             improvement in the clinical manifestations of the involved lymph node.

          -  Atypical cat scratch disease (e.g. encephalitis, pneumonitis, osteomyelitis).

          -  Endocarditis due to Bartonella sp..

          -  Diabetes mellitus.

          -  Peptic ulcer disease or history of upper GI bleeding.

          -  History of inadequately treated tuberculosis or evidence of tuberculosis in the chest
             radiography.

          -  Schizoaffective disorder, anxiety or depression treated with antipsychiatric drugs, at
             present or in the past.

          -  AIDS or positive serology for HIV.

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1000/mm3.

          -  Treatment with any investigational drug in any clinical trial within 30 days prior to
             administration of study medication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Infectious Disease Unit, Tel Aviv Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <zip>64239</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 10, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 10, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 10, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michal Roll PhD,MBA</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>director R&amp;D devision</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cat-scratch disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Bartonella henselae</keyword>
  <keyword>corticosteroids</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cat-Scratch Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bartonella Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

