<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01465737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201103107RC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01465737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidemiology of Uterine Cancer in Taiwan</brief_title>
  <official_title>Importance of Cohort and Histologic Type for Secular Trends in Rising Incidence and Different Survival of Uterine Cancer -a Taiwan Population-based Registry From 1979 to 2008</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endometrial cancer is the second most common gynecologic cancer in Taiwan. Two types of
      endometrial cancer may be distinguished by standard clinicopathologic criteria; type I tumors
      are of low grade, endometrioid histology, estrogen related, and have a good prognosis,
      whereas type II tumors are high grade, of non-endometrioid histologies, unrelated to
      estrogen, and have a poor prognosis. Several clinicopathological parameters were reported to
      correlate with prognosis of endometrial cancer including tumor FIGO stage, cell type,
      cytological grading, depth of myometrial invasion, tumor size, lymph node status, and etc.
      However, there is no epidemiologic data of endometrial cancer in Taiwan. So the investigators
      propose this study to use Taiwan registry database provided by Department of Health to
      analyze the epidemiology and prognosis of uterine cancer patients in Taiwan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study population To evaluate the epidemiology and prognosis of uterine cancer in Taiwan, we
      will conduct a nationwide analysis through linking national cancer registry database. Every
      citizen in Taiwan has a life-long identification number to link individual information,
      including health status. The Taiwan household registry database provided by Department of
      Health will be the source population. National household registry and death certificate will
      be adopted to ascertain the live status of study subjects, and provided individual
      demographic characteristics. All individual linkages between databases will be conducted
      according to the study protocols, i.e. databases will be linked by corresponding
      identification number, name (Chinese characters) and birthday, and all data included in this
      study will be analyzed without individual identification information. The agreement of
      utilizing the databases in the study was obtained from the Bureau of Health Promotion in
      Taiwan.

      Incident and death cases ascertainment Patients with uterine cancer, including uterine
      carcinoma, uterine sarcoma … etc., will be identified from computerized linkage to the Taiwan
      national cancer registry with International Classification of Diseases for Oncology Third
      Edition T-code C540-C543. Histological types will be identified from morphology code in the
      cancer registry database. Women affected by uterine cancer and found death due to uterine
      cancer (International Classification of Diseases 9th edition code 182) in deaths certificate
      will be defined as death cases.

      Statistical Analyses The numbers of person-years at risk of developing and dying for uterine
      cancer will be calculated. Incidence rates will be calculated by dividing the number of
      uterine cancer cases by the person-years at risk of developing uterine cancer. Mortality
      rates will be calculated by dividing the number of uterine cancer deaths by the person-years
      at risk of dying from uterine cancer. The association between mortality and age, histology,
      time periods will be estimated through Kaplan-Meier survival analysis and Cox's proportional
      hazards model. It is defined as significant difference statistically when p value is less
      than 0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From diagnosis of uterine cancer to death or last date of linked data available from the Taiwan Cancer Registry or Death Certification Profile</time_frame>
    <description>The follow-up of each participant (in personyears) was calculated from the date of enrollment to the date of uterine cancer diagnosis, date of death, or last date of linked data available from the Taiwan Cancer Registry or Death Certification Profile, whichever came first until December 31, 2010.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10000</enrollment>
  <condition>Uterine Cancers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with uterine cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients diagnosed with uterine cancer in Taiwan between 1979-2008</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Histologic types</intervention_name>
    <description>evaluate survival among different histologic types</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with uterine cancer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All uterine cancer patients in Taiwan between 1979-2008
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All uterine cancer patients in Taiwan between 1979-2008

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wen-Fang Cheng, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, National Taiwan University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wen-Fang Cheng, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>886-2-23123456</phone>
    <phone_ext>71964</phone_ext>
    <email>wenfangcheng@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>100</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wen-Fang Cheng, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>886-2-23123456</phone>
      <phone_ext>71964</phone_ext>
      <email>wenfangcheng@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 26, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 2, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 2, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>epidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>uterine cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Taiwan</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

