<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03525002</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DopamineGenetics01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03525002</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dopamine Action on Metabolism in Relation to Genotype</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dopamine Action on Metabolism Depending on Genetic Heterogeneity - a Randomized, Placebo-controlled Double Blind Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Tuebingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital of Cologne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Lübeck</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Tuebingen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity is a widespread disease with increasing prevalence and associated with serious
      secondary complications. So far, the origin of the disease, regardless of an existing
      positive energy balance, is not fully understood. In addition to environmental factors, the
      genetic background plays an important role in the pathogenesis of obesity. Of common genetic
      polymorphisms, variants in the fat mass and obesity associated gene (FTO) locus have the
      highest effect size on body weight. Animal and first clinical studies indicate that FTO
      variants interact with dopamine signaling in the brain, thus influencing the risk of
      overweight. In fact, preliminary results indicate that enhancing dopamine signaling with the
      dopamine agonist bromocriptine, depending on the FTO genotype, either induces weight loss or
      has a neutral effect on body weight.

      The planned clinical trial serves to develop a genotype-specific and thus individualized
      therapy approach for obesity. The influence of dopamine agonist therapy on weight loss as a
      function of the FTO (rs8050136) genotype is to be tested.

      Here, the greatest weight loss is expected to occur in subjects carrying the homozygous
      risk-allele (AA).

      So far, there are only a few established conservative therapy forms of obesity, so that
      bariatric interventions with an increasing rate are necessary to achieve weight loss and thus
      a reduction in overall morbidity and mortality. Among the approved drug therapies for
      obesity, bromocriptine is commonly used. In addition, some interventions require injections.
      An early, conservative individualized, genotype-specific treatment with little side-effects
      would enable simple treatment of obesity.

      Study design: 150 obese (BMI &gt; 30) subjects (50 / study center) will be enrolled in the
      study. The subjects will be stratified according to their FTO genotype (rs8050136). Subjects
      will be randomized into placebo or bromocriptine treatment group. Treatment will last for 18
      weeks and a follow-up will be performed 30 weeks after baseline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>double-blind</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Interaction between FTO genotype and treatment on change in body weight.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Interaction between FTO (single nucleotide peptide) SNP rs8050136 genotype and treatment (bromocriptine or placebo) on change in body weight.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on dietary intake</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Dietary intake will be monitored by food diaries</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on processing of food cues in the brain</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Processing of food cues in the brain will be assessed by functional magnetic resonance imaging before and after treatment with bromocriptine or placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on body fat distribution</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Body fat distribution will be assessed by magnetic resonance imaging and magnetic resonance spectroscopy before and after treatment with bromocriptine or placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on whole body insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Whole body insulin sensitivity will be quantified from 5 point 75g oral glucose tolerance test before and after treatment with bromocriptine or placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on insulin secretion</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Insulin secretion will be quantified from 5 point 75g oral glucose tolerance test before and after treatment with bromocriptine or placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on glucose tolerance</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Glucose tolerance will be assessed by 75g oral glucose tolerance test before and after treatment with bromocriptine or placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on brain insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Brain insulin sensitivity will be assessed by functional magnetic resonance imaging combined with intranasal insulin administration before and after treatment with bromocriptine or placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on resting energy expenditure</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Resting energy expenditure will be assessed by indirect calorimetry before and after treatment with bromocriptine or placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Physical activity will be monitored using an accelerometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of bromocriptine vs. placebo on serum prolactin concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (AA), Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with FTO SNP rs8050136 AA receiving matching Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (AA), Bromocriptine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with FTO SNP rs8050136 AAreceiving Bromocriptine up to 5 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (CA), Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with FTO SNP rs8050136 CA receiving matching Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (CA), Bromocriptine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with FTO SNP rs8050136 CA receiving Bromocriptine up to 5 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (CC), Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with FTO SNP rs8050136 CC receiving matching Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (CC), Bromocriptine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with FTO SNP rs8050136 CC receiving Bromocriptine up to 5 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bromocriptine</intervention_name>
    <description>In each FTO genotype group participants will be randomly receive bromocriptine or placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (AA), Bromocriptine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (CA), Bromocriptine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (CC), Bromocriptine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>In each FTO genotype group participants will be randomly receive bromocriptine or placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (AA), Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (CA), Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FTO SNP rs8050136 (CC), Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between &gt;30 kg/m².

          -  Understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent document prior to any study
             related assessments/procedures.

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must agree to utilize a reliable form of
             contraception simultaneously or practice complete abstinence from heterosexual contact
             while participating in the study.

          -  Males must agree to use a latex condom during any heterosexual contact while
             participating in the study and to refrain from donating semen or sperm while
             participating in this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women during pregnancy and lactation.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to the investigational medicinal product or to any drug
             with similar chemical structure or to any excipient present in the pharmaceutical form
             of the investigational medicinal products.

          -  Participation in other clinical trials or observation period of competing trials up to
             30 days prior to this study.

          -  Diabetes mellitus

          -  Treatment with Methyldopa, levodopa, dopamine agonists, metoclopramid, domperidon,
             glycerol nitrate, griseofulvin, azol-antimycotic drugs, macrolide-antibiotics,
             octreotide, orlistat, tamoxifen, liraglutide

          -  Any relevant cardiovascular disease, e.g. myocardial infarction, acute coronary
             syndrome, unstable angina pectoris, Percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty
             (PTCA), heart failure (NYHA III-IV), stroke or transient ischemic attack (TIA)

          -  Acute or chronic viral hepatitis or liver cirrhosis

          -  Impaired renal function, defined as estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate (eGFR) ≤ 60
             ml/min (MDRD formula) as determined during screening.

          -  Medical history of cancer and/or treatment for cancer within the last 5 years.

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Any other clinically significant major organ system disease at screening such as
             relevant gastrointestinal, neurologic, psychiatric, endocrine (i.e. pancreatic),
             hematologic, malignant, infection or other major systemic diseases making
             implementation of the protocol or interpretation of the study results difficult.

          -  Presence of any contraindication for the conduct of an MRI investigation, such as
             cardiac pacemakers, ferromagnetic haemostatic clips in the central nervous system,
             metallic splinters in the eye, ferromagnetic or electronically operated active devices
             like automatic cardioverter defibrillators, cochlear implants, insulin pumps and nerve
             stimulators, prosthetic heart valves etc.

          -  hyperthyroidism

          -  therapy refractary hypertension

          -  peripheral arterial disease

          -  Parkinson´s disease

          -  Known current presence or history of one of the following psychiatric diseases:
             depression, mania, anxiety and panic disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder,
             schizophrenia, psychosis, addiction

          -  pituitary disease

          -  treatment with bromocriptine during 12 month before entering the trial

          -  dementia

          -  gastric or intestinal ulcer

          -  Persons with limited temperature sensation and / or elevated sensitivity to warming of
             the body

          -  Persons with a hearing disorder or a increased sensitivity for loud noises

          -  smoking

          -  Refusal to get informed of unexpected detected pathological findings

        Any other clinical condition that would jeopardize subjects' safety while participating in
        this clinical trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martin Heni, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 7071-29 82711</phone>
    <email>martin.heni@med.uni-tuebingen.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Cologne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cologne</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Faust, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Luebeck</name>
      <address>
        <city>Luebeck</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sebastian Schmid, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Tuebingen, Department of Internal Medicine IV</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tübingen</city>
        <zip>72076</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Martin Heni, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 7071 29 82714</phone>
      <email>martin.heni@med.uni-tuebingen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Andreas Fritsche, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 7071 29 82714</phone>
      <email>andreas.fritsche@med.uni-tuebingen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dopamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bromocriptine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

