<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03523533</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-116</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03523533</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Peripherally Inserted Internal Jugular Catheters: an Observational Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Peripherally Inserted Internal Jugular Catheters: an Observational Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of New Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of New Mexico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational study intended to characterize the time-to-placement of
      peripherally-inserted internal jugular (PIJ) catheters in appropriate patients. As secondary
      outcomes and to ensure patient safety, the investigators will record and evaluate adverse
      outcomes, but the study is not powered to detect rare events.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational study with one arm. All enrolled patients will receive a peripheral
      angiocatheter in the internal jugular vein. Approximately 60 subjects will be enrolled.

      After recruitment and consent, an investigator will place the peripherally-inserted jugular
      (PIJ) catheters for this study, under ultrasound guidance. Clean technique similar to that
      used for traditional peripheral intravenous catheters will be used, including chlorhexidine
      skin preparation, caps, and sterile ultrasound gel with sterile occlusive dressing over the
      ultrasound transducer. For patients included in this study because of a clinically-determined
      need for a second IV line, the catheter will be placed after anesthesia induction. Patients
      included because of difficult IV access will have the PIJ catheter placed prior to induction.

      The size of the angiocatheter will be left to the clinical discretion of the investigator,
      from among these choices: 18G x 2.5 inches, 16G x 2 inches, or 14G x 2 inches. All
      angiocatheters will be radiopaque in order to permit visualization in the event of any
      required imaging. Catheters will be placed with visualization under dynamic ultrasonography
      using a Sonosite S-Nerve ultrasound machine with 13-6 MHz 25 mm linear array. All catheters
      and ultrasound components are being used in accordance with their labeling.

      The depth of catheter insertion into the internal jugular vein will be determined, and the
      catheter will be removed/replaced immediately if it is found to extend less than 1.0 cm into
      the vessel. If the catheter is removed or replaced, routine care will be followed: pressure
      will be held until bleeding subsides and the site dressed appropriately (e.g. gauze with tape
      or adhesive bandage). No more than three attempts will be made before abandoning the effort
      to place a PIJ catheter.

      The PIJ catheter will be secured as per normal practice, with an adhesive IV securing device
      and an occlusive bandage placed over both the IV and its securing device.

      The PIJ catheter will be used as usual during surgery. It will not be used for total
      parenteral nutrition or other continuous nutrient infusions.

      In most cases, the PIJ catheter will be removed as usual before the patient is transferred to
      the floor, intensive care unit, or discharged home. In some cases, however, an appropriately
      authorized clinician may determine that the PIJ catheter should remain in place longer. If
      extended use of the PIJ catheter is indicated, it will be removed when it is either replaced
      as appropriate by another intravenous line or no longer needed.

      Procedural data will be gathered on the day of surgery, and chart review will occur after
      surgery in order to capture any IV-related complications within the first week that were not
      immediately apparent.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is an observational study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Catheter placement time</measure>
    <time_frame>No more than 20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Elapsed time from first contact of skin prep solution to completely secured/covered catheter</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Location of insertion</measure>
    <time_frame>No more than 20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Choice of placement on patient's right or left side</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depth of insertion</measure>
    <time_frame>No more than 20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Depth of catheter insertion in target blood vessel</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of attempts</measure>
    <time_frame>No more than 20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Count of attempts to successfully place catheter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of complications</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Count of complications that are related to catheter placement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Intravenous Drug Usage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peripherally-inserted internal jugular catheter</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All enrolled patients will receive a peripheral angiocatheter in the internal jugular vein, under dynamic ultrasound guidance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Angiocatheter</intervention_name>
    <description>Placement of angiocatheter in internal jugular vein</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peripherally-inserted internal jugular catheter</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: Adult elective-surgery patients at University of New Mexico Hospital
        main operating rooms, who do not require central venous catheters, and who either:

          1. require a second intravenous access line (IV) as determined by the anesthesiologist,
             *or*

          2. require a primary IV *and* are determined by the anesthesiologist to have difficult IV
             access, defined as two or more failed attempts at peripheral IV placement, in the
             absence of an indication for a central venous catheter.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infection over the intended peripheral angiocatheter insertion site

          -  Cervical spine injury or instability

          -  Known abnormal neck anatomy

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Prisoners

          -  Clinical indication for central venous catheter

          -  Any pre-existing suspicion for bacteremia

          -  Adults unable to consent, as determined by ability to provide consent for surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tony Yen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center (HSC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tony Yen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5052722610</phone>
    <email>tyen@salud.unm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Timothy Petersen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>5052722610</phone>
    <email>timpetersen@salud.unm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of New Mexico</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tony Yen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

