<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03529487</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RDD 121</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03529487</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intra-anal Oxymetazoline in Healthy Adult Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Open-Label, Multiple-Ascending Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Intra-anal Application of Topical Oxymetazoline Gel in Healthy Adult Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RDD Pharma Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense grant W81XWH-17-1-0523</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Spaulding Clinical Research LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RDD Pharma Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, open-label, repeat dose, ascending dose study assessing the PK, safety,
      tolerability, PD, and dose- or exposure-response of Topical Oxymetazoline for intra-anal
      application. A total of 20 healthy male and female subjects will be enrolled (4 subjects in
      the first cohort and 8 subjects in the remaining cohorts) and will be exposed to Topical
      Oxymetazoline 1 mg, 5 mg or 10 mg applied intra-anally QD for 11 consecutive days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, open-label, repeat dose, ascending dose study assessing the PK, safety,
      tolerability, PD, and dose- or exposure-response of Topical Oxymetazoline for intra-anal
      application.

      The primary objective of this study is To determine the plasma concentrations and
      pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters, as data allows, of oxymetazoline following single and
      repeated intra-anal application of oxymetazoline gel 1 mg, 5 mg or 10 mg in healthy male and
      female subjects.

      The secondary objective of this study is To evaluate the safety and tolerability of repeated
      intra-anal application of oxymetazoline gel 1 mg, 5 mg or 10 mg in healthy male and female
      subjects.

      A total of 20 healthy male and female subjects will be enrolled (4 subjects in the first
      cohort and 8 subjects in the remaining cohorts) and will be exposed to Topical Oxymetazoline
      1 mg, 5 mg or 10 mg applied intra-anally QD for 11 consecutive days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>11 days</time_frame>
    <description>Oxymetazoline Maximum observed plasma concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>11 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time to maximum concentration (Oxymetazoline), obtained directly from the observed concentration versus time data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUClast</measure>
    <time_frame>11 days</time_frame>
    <description>Oxymetazoline Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to time of last measureable plasma concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>t½</measure>
    <time_frame>11 days</time_frame>
    <description>Oxymetazoline Terminal elimination half-life</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Fecal Incontinence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oxymetazoline applied intra analy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxymetazoline</intervention_name>
    <description>Oxymetazoline gel applied intra-analy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oxymetazoline applied intra analy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. An Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved informed consent is signed and dated
             prior to any study-related activities.

          2. Subject is an adult male or female between the ages of 18 and 60 years, inclusive.

          3. Female subjects of child-bearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test.
             Females of childbearing potential must practice a highly effective method of pregnancy
             prevention (defined as &lt;1% pregnancies per 100 women per year) from one month before
             screening to one month after the follow-up visit, such as: surgical sterilization,
             hormonal implant, intrauterine device, or male condom + female diaphragm + vaginal
             spermicide. Female subject with any of the following circumstances is not required to
             use a highly effective method of pregnancy prevention: status post-hysterectomy; or,
             status post-tubal ligation; or, post-menopausal state (defined as &gt;= 12 months of
             spontaneous amenorrhea) or &lt; 12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea with a blood follicle
             stimulating hormone &gt; 40 MIU/ml.

          4. Subject has a body mass index between 18 and 33 kg/m2 (weight/[height]2).

          5. Subject has normal (or abnormal and clinically insignificant) laboratory values at
             Screening.

          6. Subject is healthy based on a medical evaluation including medical history, physical
             examination, laboratory tests and cardiac monitoring and have no more than 3
             spontaneous bowel movements (SBM) a day or no less than 3 SBMs a week.

          7. Based on single or averaged QTc values of triplicate ECGs over a brief recording
             period (QTc &lt; 450 msec)

          8. Subject has the ability to understand the requirements of the study and a willingness
             to comply with all study procedures, including retaining a rectal gel for at least 60
             min and undergoing repeat rectal manometries lasting 10-15 min

          9. Subject has not consumed and agrees to abstain from taking any prescription or
             non-prescription medications, including herbal and dietary supplements (such as St.
             John's wort) within 14 days prior to the first dose of study medication (except as
             authorized by the Investigator and Medical Monitor).

         10. Subject has not consumed alcohol-containing beverages for 3 days prior to the first
             scheduled dose and agrees not to consume alcohol through the last study visit.

         11. Subject has not used tobacco- and nicotine-containing products for 2 months prior to
             the first scheduled dose and agrees not to use through the last study visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject has a hypersensitivity or allergy to oxymetazoline.

          2. Subject has active or history of cardiovascular or cerebrovascular disease including
             hypertension, unstable angina, myocardial infarction, transient ischemic
             attacks/stroke, clinically significant arrhythmia, congestive heart failure, or
             cardiac valve abnormalities.

          3. Subject has systolic blood pressure &gt;130 mm Hg and/or diastolic blood pressure &gt;80 mm
             Hg and/or resting heart rate &gt;90 bpm or resting heart rate &lt;50 bpm.

          4. Subject has a history of rectal surgery.

          5. Subject has upon physical examination a rectal deformation or signs of rectal disease
             such as fissure, hemorrhoids grade 3, rectal prolapse, fistula, infection or space
             occupying lesion.

          6. Subjects with a history of or present symptoms related to irritable bowel disease,
             inflammatory bowel disease, or chronic constipation.

          7. Subject reporting change in bowel habits in the last 14 days.

          8. Subject reporting episodes of rectal bleeding in the last 90 days.

          9. Subjects taking anticoagulants such as Coumarins, Heparins, and Factor Xa inhibitors.

         10. Subjects taking drugs known to affect rectal tone: nitrates, calcium channel blockers,
             alpha antagonists, and alpha agonists.

         11. Subject has a history illicit drug abuse in the past year or current evidence of such
             abuse in the opinion of the Investigator.

         12. Subject has positive findings on urine drug/alcohol/cotinine screen.

         13. Subject is positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B and/or
             hepatitis C on Screening assessments.

         14. Subject is pregnant or lactating.

         15. Subject has an acute illness within 1 week of the first scheduled dose.

         16. Subject has donated plasma within 7 days of drug administration.

         17. Subject has donated 1 or more pints of blood (or equivalent blood loss) within 30 days
             prior to drug administration.

         18. Subject has participated in an investigational drug study where the last assessment of
             that study was within the 30 days prior to the first scheduled dose.

         19. Subject is an immediate family member of personnel directly affiliated with the study,
             or is personally directly affiliated with the study at the investigative site, or is
             employed or related to the Sponsor, CRO or investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fecal Incontinence</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxymetazoline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Phenylephrine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

