<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03525587</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>346/17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03525587</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development and Validation of a Self-assessment System Based on a Mobile App to Manage Adult Growth Hormone Deficiency</brief_title>
  <acronym>GrASS</acronym>
  <official_title>Development and Validation of a Novel Self-assessment System Based on a Mobile App to Manage Adult Growth Hormone Deficiency (MAGHD App): a Single-Centre Model. GrASS (Growth Hormone Deficiency in Adults Self-assessment System)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Modena</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Modena</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adult Growth Hormone Deficiency (AGHD) is a recognized clinical entity but several barriers
      concerning patient-clinician communication, inadequate patients' awareness of the disease,
      low perceived benefit of replacement therapy and poor compliance still remains.

      The overall goal of the study is to improve AGHD management through a Smartphone app (MAGHD
      App: Manage Adult Growth Hormone Deficiency) integrated with a software framework able to
      merge patients daily data on physical activity, quality of life (QoL), and well-being with
      clinical data collected in institutional databases. The target population consists of 100
      patients with a previous diagnosis of AGHD, whether in treatment with growth hormone or not.

      In a prospective 24 months study, MAGHD App will be developed and connected to MAGHD
      Framework. This system will allow to integrate: 1) Physical Activity Data collected by
      wearable devices, 2) Patient Related Outcomes Data, periodically inserted by the patients
      through MAGHD App in response to questions extrapolated from validated questionnaires, 3) HCP
      Data registered in clinical databases and including medical history, biochemical and
      radiological examination. Data will converge in MAGHD Framework where they will be analyzed
      and used to create reports visible to patients (in MAGHD App) and clinicians (by a monitoring
      dashboard).

      The results are expected to positively influence AGHD management by involving patients in
      care process and giving clinicians a useful tool for clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      AGHD is widely recognized as a specific clinical entity and recombinant human growth hormone
      (r-hGH) therapy has become a standard practice since 90s thanks to its beneficial effects on
      body composition, muscle strength, bone mass, cardiovascular risk and patients' exercise
      capacity and QoL. All the beneficial effects of r-hGH in AGHD patients have been established
      mainly on selected populations by both few randomized controlled trials (RCTs) and several
      clinical trials. Real life studies are also available, but they are mainly based on data
      collected through multicenter sponsored studies such as the Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn International
      Metabolic Database (KIMS) and the Hypopituitary Control and Complications Study International
      Advisory Board (HYPOCCS). All these observational studies suffer from missing data in the
      original databases and/or lack adequate control group (i.e. untreated GHD patients).
      Well-conducted real life studies have the advantage to provide information on long-term
      effects of therapies, as well as on safety, adherence and persistence to therapy.
      Accordingly, in clinical practice it is common to find a disparity between hormonal levels
      and patients' subjective well-being: some individuals with a full-blown AGHD do not report
      any symptom and turn out reluctant to start a treatment, while others with slight GHD
      experience a deterioration in their QoL that deeply improves after GH replacement. This is
      mainly due to the fact that clinical presentation of AGHD is frequently based on nonspecific
      symptoms. Similarly, individual differences in responsiveness to r-hGH are common findings in
      the real life. Moreover, when other hormonal deficits coexist and patients have to face with
      a polytherapy, it can be difficult both for clinicians and patients to relate symptoms to the
      sole AGHD and to verify benefits after treatment. Finally, there is a lack of tools assessing
      patients' physical activity, which is an important factor to consider when evaluating energy
      levels, exercise performance, and well-being. Thus, a gap still remains in the real life
      setting concerning how to measure the improvements occurring in r-hGH treated patients and
      how to make patients and clinicians more aware of these changes. Nowadays, considering the
      shortage of established predictive factors for the overall therapeutic response, the decision
      to whether or not continue treatment depends often on the ratio of perceived and expected
      beneﬁts over cost and risks of treatment, as well as on the persistent motivation of the
      patient. These aspects involve also physician's attitude and patient's propensity to start
      r-hGH replacement therapy. Vice versa the lack of information useful to predict patients'
      individual response to treatment poses some clinical troubles about how to select patients
      who may beneficiate from r-hGH therapy. Considering that r-hGH treatment is a chronic therapy
      requiring a daily self-injection, long-term compliance is still a considerable problem in
      this setting and is influenced by all the above mentioned issues. It is estimated that about
      20 to 30% of patients discontinue the treatment, permanently or for extended periods, making
      therefore an objective evaluation of the therapeutic effects difficult. All these aspects are
      enhanced by the paucity of tools available to improve patients' education and awareness of
      AGHD.

      The widespread use of Smartphone applications and wearable devices presents an opportunity to
      overcome these difficulties in the AGHD management. Although several apps exist to monitor
      chronic endocrinological diseases, no specific app has been tested in AGHD till now.

      In a prospective, 24 months, open-label, monocentric study, an interactive smartphone app
      (MAGHD App) will be developed, connected to an Integrated Framework (MAGHD Framework) and
      tested by automatic software testing procedures before the real validation on patients.
      Subsequently it will be validated on an estimated number of 100 AGHD patients; this system
      will allow to combine patients' information and HCPs clinical outcomes in a single virtual
      platform and to return easily accessible data to both AGHD patients and clinicians.

      The MAGHD App and the integrated MAGHD Framework will be provided by DataRiver, the research
      and technological Partner of the study, which is a Contract Research Organization certified
      by AIFA (Italian drug agency) and accredited as a Research Innovation Institution by the
      Emilia Romagna Region. The MAGHD software framework will allow integrating patient's Physical
      Activity data (PA-D), constantly collected by wearable devices (which will be rented and
      given to patients in the second part of the study), with patient related outcomes data
      (ePRO-D) and HCP data (HCP-D):

        -  PA-D will be obtained through wearable devices and will guarantee the automatic
           collection of data regarding patients' daily life activities. PA recorded by the
           wearable devices will include: physical activity type, daily steps number, daily walking
           distance, daily calories burned, sleep duration, sleep quality.

        -  ePRO-D will be collected via the MAGHD App, which will periodically generate a short
           question extrapolated from the items of validated questionnaires: AGHDA questionnaire
           and QLS-H questionnaire for QoL, the Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-Being Scale (WEMWBS)
           for well-being evaluation, the International Index of Erectile Function Questionnaire
           (IIEF-15) and the Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI) for sexual function evaluation (in
           men and women respectively), the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ)
           for physical activity evaluation and the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) for sleep
           quality evaluation. Additional information on sexual function, working environment,
           hobbies and adherence to r-hGH therapy (the latter only in Group 1) will be collected
           through a simple series of questions taken from a specific chart.

      The App will record the number of the user answers as well as the missing ones and will
      periodically provide a visual satisfaction analogue scale on the use of MAGHD App usability.
      Patients will be notified by the MAGHD App to promptly answer the periodic surveys. The daily
      surveys could expire after a predefined time interval to prevent the participants to complete
      them retrospectively, reducing the risk for recall bias.

        -  HCP data will include:

             -  Data obtained from patient's record chart or by interview: anagraphic data, medical
                history information, comorbidities.

             -  Data obtained at baseline and at subsequent visits by physical examination,
                anthropometric parameters, clinical data and symptoms, r-hGH therapy (weekly dose
                and duration of therapy in months), if ongoing, other hormone replacement
                treatments (and relative dosage) in case of multiple pituitary deficits.

             -  Data obtained at baseline and at subsequent visits by clinical (biochemical and
                radiological) examinations:

        -  pituitary hormones serum levels (IGF-1, insulin-like growth factor binding protein 3,
           adrenocorticotropic hormone, cortisol, 24-hour urinary free cortisol,
           thyroid-stimulating hormone, free thyroxine, free triiodothyronine, luteinizing hormone,
           follicle-stimulating hormone, estradiol and progesterone (in females), testosterone and
           sex hormone-binding globulin (in men), prolactin;

        -  biochemical values (haemoglobin, haematocrit, erythrocytes, leukocytes, platelets, renal
           and hepatic function, electrolytes, glycaemia, TC, HDL-C, LDL-C, triglycerides, bone
           metabolism);

        -  dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) scan for assessing body composition, bone
           mineral content and bone mineral density on whole skeleton, at lumbar site and at
           femoral site.

      The hormonal-biochemical data will be collected at each visit, while the DEXA scan will be
      performed at baseline, at 12 months and at the end of the study.

      PA-D, ePRO-D and HCP-D will converge in the MAGHD Framework where they will be integrated,
      analyzed and used to create graphs and tables visible both to patients (in MAGHD App) and
      clinicians (by a monitoring dashboard).

      Patients will receive periodically a feedback concerning: i) %change of their QoL,
      well-being, sleep quality, sexual function and ii) changes in daily physical activities. This
      kind of report will enhance patient's awareness on day-by-day changes related to their
      clinical condition. In particular frequent feedback on QoL and well-being will provide a more
      objective evaluation of these parameters, thus minimizing possible interference due to life
      events occurred close to the day in which the questionnaires are filled. Moreover, a summary
      of the patient's clinical outcomes will be provided through the MAGHD App in a simple
      graphical way in order to communicate changes in serum IGF-1 and lipid profile.

      The project will be carried out in 24 months. Months 1‐6 will focus on: 1) App development,
      2) Integrated Framework development, 3) App testing.

      Patient enrollment and baseline visits will occur between months 1 and 6, then six-month
      visits (visit 1, visit 2, visit 3 and visit 4) will occur in the next 2 years. In the first
      phase (12 months) the recruited patients, after having signed the informed consent, will be
      followed every six months according to our normal clinical practice without using the App and
      the wearable device (baseline, visit 1 and visit 2). Then they will be trained to use the
      MAGHD App prior to enter the second phase (following 12 months), in which they will be
      evaluated every six months during the use of the App and the wearable device (visit 3 and
      visit 4).

      HCP data will be collected both in phase 1 (usual follow-up without the use of MAGHD App) and
      phase 2 (during the use of MAGHD App). Anamnestic, clinical and biochemical data will be
      collected at each visit (baseline, visit 2, visit 3, visit 4), while DEXA scan (radiological
      data) will be performed only twice (at baseline and at the end of the protocol).

      All the other data will be collected differently in the two consecutive phases:

        -  QoL and well-being data:

             -  In Phase 1 AGHDA questionnaire, QLS-H questionnaire and WEMWBS will be administered
                to patients in paper form at baseline, visit 1 and visit 2.

             -  In Phase 2 MAGHD App will periodically generate a short question extrapolated from
                the items of the same validated questionnaires.

        -  Sexual function:

             -  In Phase 1 IIEF-5 questionnaire (for men) and FSFI questionnaire (for woman) will
                be administered to patients in paper form at baseline, visit 1 and visit 2.

             -  In Phase 2 MAGHD App will periodically generate a short question extrapolated from
                the items of the same validated questionnaires.

        -  Physical activity and sleep quality:

             -  In Phase 1 physical activity will be evaluated through the IPAQ questionnaire and
                sleep quality through the PSQI questionnaire; both will be administered to patients
                in paper form at baseline, visit 1 and visit 2.

             -  In Phase 2 MAGHD App will periodically generate a short question extrapolated from
                the items of the same validated questionnaires; data on physical activity and sleep
                quality will be also automatically collected through wearable devices.

        -  Additional information on sexual function, working environment, hobbies and adherence to
           r-hGH therapy (the latter only in Group 1):

             -  In Phase 1 these aspects will be evaluated at baseline, visit 1 and visit 2,
                through a specific chart in paper form.

             -  In Phase 2 the same questions will be sent through the MAGHD App.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 17, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients with a previous documented AGHD fitting the inclusion/exclusion criteria will be enrolled and grouped as follows:
Group 1: patients on long-term r-hGH therapy;
Group 2: patients previously treated with r-hGH, who had stopped the treatment for any reason (age, concomitant adverse reactions, contraindications or personal will);
Group 3: patients never treated for any reason (according to age, contraindications or lack of patient's consent).
The whole cohort of AGHD patients (n=100) will undergo 2 consecutive phases: in the first phase (12 months) patients will be evaluated as usual every six months according to our standard clinical practice without using the App and the wearable device (baseline visit, visit 1 and visit 2), while in the second phase (following 12 months) they will be evaluated every six months during the use of the App (visit 3 and visit 4).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of quality of life (QoL) from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of QoL score from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. QoL score will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of well-being from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of Well-being score from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. Well-being score will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of physical activity from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of physical activity score from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. Physical activity score will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of sleep quality from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of sleep quality score from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. Sleep quality score will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of sexual function from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of sexual function scores (IIEF-5 score for men and FSFI score for woman) from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. Sexual function scores will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) levels from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of IGF-1 levels from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. IGF-1 levels will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of lipid profile from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) and triglycerides from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. Lipid profile will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of body composition from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of % of lean mass and fat mass from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. Body composition will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of bone mineral density from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes of T-score at lumbar site and at femoral site from baseline for each patient within the three different groups. Bone mineral density will be evaluated and compared before and after the use of the integrated system MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to r-hGH therapy (average number of weekly forgetfulnesses)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of possible changes in adherence to r-hGH therapy (only in patients of Group 1) from Phase 1 and Phase 2.
Average number of weekly forgetfulnesses of r-hGH therapy will be considered to verify the adherence to therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of physical activity on BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the impact of physical activity in AGHD patients (as recorded by the MAGHD App in Phase 2) on BMI. Weight and height will be combined to report BMI in kg/m^2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of physical activity on body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the impact of physical activity in AGHD patients (as recorded by the MAGHD App in Phase 2) on body composition (% of lean mass and fat mass).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of physical activity on lipid profile</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the impact of physical activity in AGHD patients (as recorded by the MAGHD App in Phase 2) on lipid profile (total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, triglycerides).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>User's satisfaction about MAGHD App</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of user's satisfaction about MAGHD App through the number of messages the user has returned in response to the questions of each questionnaire he received. The App will record the number of the user answers as well as the missing ones. For each patient will be considered the following ratio: number of returned messeges/total number of sent messages.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Growth Hormone Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ongoing r-hGH therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients on long-term r-hGH therapy.
Intervention: Use of &quot;MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Previous r-hGH therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients previously treated with r-hGH, who had stopped the treatment for any reason (age, concomitant adverse reactions, contraindications or personal will).
Intervention: Use of &quot;MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Never treated</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients never treated for any reason (according to age, contraindications or lack of patient's consent).
Intervention: Use of &quot;MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Use of &quot;MAGHD App/MAGHD Framework&quot;</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients daily related outcomes will be recorded thanks to the development, implementation and validation of a Smartphone app (MAGHD App) integrated with a software framework able to merge patient's daily activities data on well-being status, QoL, physical activities and sexual function with clinical data collected in their record chart (extrapolated from already available Institutional Databases).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ongoing r-hGH therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Previous r-hGH therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Never treated</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Having a documented diagnosis of AGHD, according to the latest Endocrine Society
             clinical practice guidelines

          2. Being at least 18 years old

          3. Having a good Italian understanding

          4. Owing smartphones with either an Android or iPhone operating system

          5. Patients with other pituitary deficits will be enrolled only if the other hormonal
             deficiencies are well controlled by replacement treatments since six months in order
             to avoid the overlap of effects due to different therapies.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1) Patients who do not plan to continue follow-up at the Endocrinology Unit of Modena 2)
        Patients with a diagnosis of biochemical GHD outside the appropriate clinical context of
        pituitary disease 3) Patients with major psychiatric diseases, chronic highly invalidating
        diseases (these patients will be considered not eligible for being enrolled in the study
        due to the impact of the underlying disease on well-being and daily activities).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vincenzo Rochira, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Modena</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vincenzo Rochira, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>+390593962453</phone>
    <email>vincenzo.rochira@unimore.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Chiara Diazzi, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+390593961816</phone>
    <email>chiaradiazzi@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero - Universitaria di Modena</name>
      <address>
        <city>Modena</city>
        <zip>41124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vincenzo Rochira, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+390593962453</phone>
      <email>vincenzo.rochira@unimore.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Chiara Diazzi, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+39059-3961816</phone>
      <email>chiaradiazzi@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vincenzo Rochira, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chiara Diazzi, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elisa Magnani, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho KK; 2007 GH Deficiency Consensus Workshop Participants. Consensus guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of adults with GH deficiency II: a statement of the GH Research Society in association with the European Society for Pediatric Endocrinology, Lawson Wilkins Society, European Society of Endocrinology, Japan Endocrine Society, and Endocrine Society of Australia. Eur J Endocrinol. 2007 Dec;157(6):695-700.</citation>
    <PMID>18057375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Molitch ME, Clemmons DR, Malozowski S, Merriam GR, Vance ML; Endocrine Society. Evaluation and treatment of adult growth hormone deficiency: an Endocrine Society clinical practice guideline. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2011 Jun;96(6):1587-609. doi: 10.1210/jc.2011-0179.</citation>
    <PMID>21602453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woodhouse LJ, Mukherjee A, Shalet SM, Ezzat S. The influence of growth hormone status on physical impairments, functional limitations, and health-related quality of life in adults. Endocr Rev. 2006 May;27(3):287-317. Epub 2006 Mar 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16543384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Bunderen CC, van Varsseveld NC, Erfurth EM, Ket JC, Drent ML. Efficacy and safety of growth hormone treatment in adults with growth hormone deficiency: a systematic review of studies on morbidity. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2014 Jul;81(1):1-14. doi: 10.1111/cen.12477. Epub 2014 May 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24750271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Höybye C, Christiansen JS. Growth hormone replacement in adults - current standards and new perspectives. Best Pract Res Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2015 Jan;29(1):115-23. doi: 10.1016/j.beem.2014.09.006. Epub 2014 Oct 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25617177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newman CB, Carmichael JD, Kleinberg DL. Effects of low dose versus high dose human growth hormone on body composition and lipids in adults with GH deficiency: a meta-analysis of placebo-controlled randomized trials. Pituitary. 2015 Jun;18(3):297-305. doi: 10.1007/s11102-014-0571-z. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24810900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bengtsson BA, Abs R, Bennmarker H, Monson JP, Feldt-Rasmussen U, Hernberg-Stahl E, Westberg B, Wilton P, Wüster C. The effects of treatment and the individual responsiveness to growth hormone (GH) replacement therapy in 665 GH-deficient adults. KIMS Study Group and the KIMS International Board. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1999 Nov;84(11):3929-35.</citation>
    <PMID>10566630</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Attanasio AF, Bates PC, Ho KK, Webb SM, Ross RJ, Strasburger CJ, Bouillon R, Crowe B, Selander K, Valle D, Lamberts SW; Hypoptiuitary Control and Complications Study International Advisory Board. Human growth hormone replacement in adult hypopituitary patients: long-term effects on body composition and lipid status--3-year results from the HypoCCS Database. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2002 Apr;87(4):1600-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11932289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alexopoulou O, Abs R, Maiter D. Treatment of adult growth hormone deficiency: who, why and how? A review. Acta Clin Belg. 2010 Jan-Feb;65(1):13-22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20373593</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lazure P, Bartel RC, Biller BM, Molitch ME, Rosenthal SM, Ross JL, Bernsten BD, Hayes SM. Contextualized analysis of a needs assessment using the Theoretical Domains Framework: a case example in endocrinology. BMC Health Serv Res. 2014 Jul 24;14:319. doi: 10.1186/1472-6963-14-319.</citation>
    <PMID>25060235</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buijink AW, Visser BJ, Marshall L. Medical apps for smartphones: lack of evidence undermines quality and safety. Evid Based Med. 2013 Jun;18(3):90-2. doi: 10.1136/eb-2012-100885. Epub 2012 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22923708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cui M, Wu X, Mao J, Wang X, Nie M. T2DM Self-Management via Smartphone Applications: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. PLoS One. 2016 Nov 18;11(11):e0166718. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0166718. eCollection 2016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27861583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chin SO, Keum C, Woo J, Park J, Choi HJ, Woo JT, Rhee SY. Successful weight reduction and maintenance by using a smartphone application in those with overweight and obesity. Sci Rep. 2016 Nov 7;6:34563. doi: 10.1038/srep34563.</citation>
    <PMID>27819345</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ryan EA, Holland J, Stroulia E, Bazelli B, Babwik SA, Li H, Senior P, Greiner R. Improved A1C Levels in Type 1 Diabetes with Smartphone App Use. Can J Diabetes. 2017 Feb;41(1):33-40. doi: 10.1016/j.jcjd.2016.06.001. Epub 2016 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27570203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tennant R, Hiller L, Fishwick R, Platt S, Joseph S, Weich S, Parkinson J, Secker J, Stewart-Brown S. The Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale (WEMWBS): development and UK validation. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2007 Nov 27;5:63.</citation>
    <PMID>18042300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosen RC, Riley A, Wagner G, Osterloh IH, Kirkpatrick J, Mishra A. The international index of erectile function (IIEF): a multidimensional scale for assessment of erectile dysfunction. Urology. 1997 Jun;49(6):822-30.</citation>
    <PMID>9187685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosen R, Brown C, Heiman J, Leiblum S, Meston C, Shabsigh R, Ferguson D, D'Agostino R Jr. The Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI): a multidimensional self-report instrument for the assessment of female sexual function. J Sex Marital Ther. 2000 Apr-Jun;26(2):191-208.</citation>
    <PMID>10782451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Craig CL, Marshall AL, Sjöström M, Bauman AE, Booth ML, Ainsworth BE, Pratt M, Ekelund U, Yngve A, Sallis JF, Oja P. International physical activity questionnaire: 12-country reliability and validity. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2003 Aug;35(8):1381-95.</citation>
    <PMID>12900694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Curcio G, Tempesta D, Scarlata S, Marzano C, Moroni F, Rossini PM, Ferrara M, De Gennaro L. Validity of the Italian version of the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). Neurol Sci. 2013 Apr;34(4):511-9. doi: 10.1007/s10072-012-1085-y. Epub 2012 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22526760</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria di Modena</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vincenzo Rochira</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD - Associate Professor of Endocrinology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Quality Improvement</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Smartphone APP</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endocrine System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dwarfism, Pituitary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The University of Modena and Reggio Emilia and the P.I. are the owners of the study data, which will be available for DataRiver for the results' analysis. The project will be disseminated through publication on indexed international journals and will be evaluated by number of papers/citations received in scientific and academic context. Preliminary results will be shown at National and International congresses.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

