<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03529604</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HRZZ IP-09-2014-9376</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03529604</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Salivary Ap4A, SCCA, TROP2 in Oral Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>OCSALTM</acronym>
  <official_title>Isolation, Quantification and Kinetics of Salivary Ap4A, SCCA and TROP2 in Patients With Oral Cancer and Potentially Malignant Oral Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zagreb</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Croatian Science Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zagreb</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      According to the World Health Organization, oral cancer (OC) is the eighth most common cancer
      in the world with a five year survival rate of 50%.

      Oral cancer tumor cells produce biochemical substances, tumor markers, differed from healthy
      individulals in expression or quantitative ratio, detectable in tissues and/or body fluids.

      Saliva, bacause of its accessibility, proximity and noninvasive approach, presents an ideal
      tool for the research of oral cancer tumor markers.

      The aim of this study will be to isolate, quantify, analyze the role and describe the
      kinetics of diadenosine tetraphophate (Ap4A), Squamous Cell Carcinoma associated Antigen
      (SCCA), Trophoblast cell surface antigen (TROP2) in patients with OC, potentially malignant
      disorders (PMOD) and age and sex matched control group with a clear medical history.

      There are number of studies published on OC tumor markers isolated mostly in serum, however
      the satisfactory specificity and sensitivity still hasn't been reached.

      Liqiud chromatography-ion trap-mass spectrometry, Multiple Reaction Monitoring method
      (LC-IT-MS, MRM) will be developed to isolate and quantify the above mentioned tumor markers.
      To our knowledge, this method hasn't yet been used to quantify the above mentioned salivary
      tumor markers. Ap4A and TROP2 have never been isolated from saliva.

      Our goal is to develop a tumor-specific test with a satisfactory statistical sensitivity and
      specificity and dynamically measure the levels of tumor markers, before and immediately after
      therapy - surgery/radiotherapy/chemotherapy or their combination, and during regular
      follow-up one and two years after surgery. As another novelty, we will dtermine the markers
      circadian rhythm.

      A OC tumor specific test, with satisfactory sensitivity and specificity, would enable earlier
      OC diagnosis, possibly before the clinical appearance, raise the survival rate of OC
      patients, enable early diagnosis of recurrence and/or new primary tumors and ensure better
      post-treatment life-quality.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the last few years, treatment of oral cancer (OC) showed improvement due to the combined
      efforts of surgery, radiotherapy and chemotherapy. Nevertheless the long-term survival rate,
      only marginally improved with a five year survival rate of 50%.

      OC is preceded by a preinvasive stage, which may last for many years. Tumor progression in
      epithelia has been classified as normal, hyperplastic (non-dysplastic), dysplastic carcinoma
      in situ and invasive carcinoma. The majority of the initial alterations of precancerous and
      cancerous oral lesions are often non recognizable, even by histopathological examination. The
      basic biology of initiation and progression of these tumors is still obscure. Carcinogenesis
      is a process which includes initiation, promotion and progression, driven by accumulation of
      specific altered genes. Tumor cells produce biochemical substances called tumor markers. Some
      of these substances found in healthy individuals, but with altered quantitative ratio.
      Besides the salivary DNA and RNA, saliva provides us with other markers, such as cell cycle
      markers (p53, p16 etc.), growth factors (EGF, TGF, etc.), cell surface markers, oxidants and
      antioxidants and other. Because of its accessibility, non-invasive approach and location
      proximity, saliva presents an ideal tool for the research of OC tumor markers.

      This study will analyze the role of Diadenosine tetraphophate (Ap4A), Squamous Cell Carcinoma
      associated Antigen 1 and 2 (SCCA1 and 2) and Trophoblast Cell Surface Antigen (TROP2) in the
      development of OC.

      Ap4A is the only diadenosine poyphosphate that can induce a considerable increase in [Ca2+]
      in endothelial cells, indicating that its vasoactive effects are comparable to the known
      effects of arginine vasopressin, angiotensin II and adenosine triphosphate (ATP). Ap4A is a
      ubiquitous diadenosine polyhosphate signal molecule for DNA replication in mammalian cell.

      Level of Ap4A was found to be directly related to the proliferative activity of the cells. It
      is considered that the Ap4A has an important role in the regulation of cellular growth and
      division. In the absence of the tumor suppressor gene FHIT (Fragile Histidine Triad), located
      on the chromosome 3p, Ap4a accumulates and leads to DNA synthesis and multiplication of
      cells. Loss of heterozygosity of the chromosome 3p is believed to be a common event in the
      early phase of carcinogenesis.

      Ap4A could represent a tumor marker for the early stages of carcinogenesis. Possibly it could
      indicate carcinogenesis earlier than patohistological diagnostics. To our knowledge, Ap4a has
      never been isolated in saliva or measured in OC and PMOD patients.

      In healthy individuals, SCCA, a glycoprotein, is located inside the cell. In individuals with
      OC it is released from the cell and thereby, is detectable in serum and saliva. Recent
      reports have shown that SCCA can influence the invasion or metastasis of cancer cells.
      However, it remains unclear how SCCA acts to mediate these biological functions. SCCA has
      already been presented as a potential serum marker for pathologic lymph node metastasis,
      advanced tumor stage, and an increased rate of distant metastasis in patients with OC,
      however, never has it been isolated in saliva in OC patients. Also, to our knowledge, it has
      never been measured in patients with PMOD.

      The human trophoblast cell-surface antigen, TROP2 (also termed GA733-1, M1S1, EGP-1) is
      encoded by the TACSTD2 gene, which is mapped to the human chromosome 1p32. TROP2 function and
      role is still not well understood, although it has previously been suggested that it played a
      role in growth regulation of cancer cells, as well as in fetal lung formation as a calcium
      signal transducer. Two studies showed that TROP2 over-expression may emerge as a prognostic
      tool in patients with oral and laryngeal squamous cell carcinoma. TROP2 antigen has never
      been isolated or measured in saliva in OC and PMOD patients. OC tumor-specific test will
      probably have to involve two or all of the above described tumor markers. However, as
      mentioned, salivary Ap4a alone could present a marker for the earliest stages of OC
      carcinogenesis. Therefore, it could reveal carcinogenesis before the clinical appearance of
      OC. We believe that the saliva proximity to OC could enable us even higher specificity. As
      another novelty, determining the circadian rhythm of the above mentioned markers should
      provide us with more information on their kinetics and role in OC carcinogenesis and rule out
      any potential confounders, such as the influence of a certain nutritive or the influence of
      some habits e.g. smoking.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary tumor marker levels before surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5.2016.-15.9.2018.</time_frame>
    <description>Salivary tumor marker levels before surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary tumor marker levels after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5.2018.-1.9.2019.</time_frame>
    <description>Salivary tumor marker levels after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Oral Cavity Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Saliva Altered</condition>
  <condition>Precancerous Lesions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Cancer group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with patohistologically diagnosed T1 conventional oral squamous cell carcinoma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PMOD group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with clinically diagnosed leukoplakia, erithroplakia and oral lichen planus.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>Age and sex matched subjects</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral Cancer group</intervention_name>
    <description>Measuring the salivary levels of SCCA1, SCCA2, TROP2 and Ap4A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Cancer group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PMOD group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PMOD group</intervention_name>
    <description>Measuring the salivary levels of SCCA1, SCCA2, TROP2 and Ap4A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Cancer group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PMOD group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Measuring the salivary levels of SCCA1, SCCA2, TROP2 and Ap4A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Cancer group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PMOD group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Saliva
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All subjects that meet the inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patohistologically confirmed conventional T1 oral sqamous cell carcinoma

          -  clinically diagnosed leukoplakia, erithroplakia and oral lichen planus

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ate or drank 2 hours before sampling
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Darko Macan, PhD, DDS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Zagreb</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>https://ocsaltm.wixsite.com/hrzz-ocsaltm</url>
    <description>OFFICIAL PROJECT PAGE</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Zagreb</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Darko Macan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oral Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Potentially Malignant Oral Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Saliva</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous cell carcinoma antigen 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous cell carcinoma antigen 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Trophoblast cell surface antigen</keyword>
  <keyword>Diadenosine tetraphosphate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mouth Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diadenosine tetraphosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

