<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03525262</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 092017-018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03525262</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prostate Oncologic Therapy While Ensuring Neurovascular Conservation (POTEN-C)</brief_title>
  <acronym>POTEN-C</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Randomized Controlled Trial of Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiotherapy (SAbR) With or Without Neurovascular Sparing for Erectile Function Preservation in Localized Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Reduction of dose to or 'sparing' of neurovascular structures during stereotactic ablative
      body radiotherapy (SAbR) for localized prostate cancer will improve retention of sexual
      potency, while retaining excellent oncologic control and other secondary health-related
      quality of life (HRQOL) endpoints.

      Primary Objectives:

      • To compare the decline in patient health-related quality of life (HRQOL) instrument-defined
      erectile dysfunction following stereotactic ablative body radiotherapy (SAbR) with or without
      neurovascular sparing

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  Assess acute (within 9 months of treatment) and chronic (&gt;9 months after treatment) SAbR
           related GU and GI toxicities, as well as serial impact on HRQOL metrics over time

        -  Assess biochemical progression free survival, local recurrence, disease-specific
           survival

        -  Evaluate the impact of neurovascular sparing on neurovascular element dose and the
           impact of rectal spacer use on neurovascular element sparing

        -  Evaluate quality of spacer placement and its effect on dose to neurovascular structures

        -  Evaluate rate local recurrence in the area of sparing adjacent to the neurovascular
           elements by biopsy in those with biochemical progression.

        -  Evaluate simplified 'practical' secondary HRQOL sexual potency endpoints that can be
           compared to prior literature.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II randomized, multi-institution, open-label, patient and HRQOL endpoint
      assessor blinded study evaluating the ability of neurovascular element sparing SAbR to
      decrease erectile dysfunction. The study procedure is to reduce 2-year Expanded prostate
      cancer index composite (EPIC) sexual domain score decline by 50% (-20 to -10), there by
      improving potency preservation. This reduction is usually expected to observe in patients
      undergoing the treatment stereotactic ablative body radiotherapy (SAbR) to 40-45 Gy with
      rectal spacer +/- sparing of at least one side's neurovascular structures using
      dose-painting.

      Primary Endpoint:

      • The Expanded prostate cancer index composite (EPIC) health-related quality of life (HRQOL)
      instrument includes a sexual function domain, which is used to produce a composite score of
      0-100 from 9 questions related to ability to achieve an erection with or without aids and
      participate in intercourse. The primary endpoint will be the mean 24-month decline in EPIC
      sexual function domain composite score.

      Secondary Endpoints:

        -  Acute Genitourinary (GU) and Gastrointestinal (GI) toxicity is defined as grade 1-5
           toxicity occurring prior to 270 days from the start of protocol treatment. It is graded
           based on CTCAE v4.0.

        -  Delayed GU and GI toxicity is defined as grade 1-5 toxicity occurring prior to 270 days
           from the start of protocol treatment. It is graded based on CTCAE v4.0.

        -  Non GU and GI toxicity up to six months post treatment.

        -  Biochemical failure Radiation therapy oncology group-American Society for Therapeutic
           Radiology and Oncology (RTOG-ASTRO) definition (also known as Phoenix definition) -
           Thus, when the Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) rises by more than 2 ng/ml above the
           lowest level (nadir) achieved after treatment, biochemical failure has occurred and the
           date of the failure is recorded at the time the nadir plus 2 ng/ml level is reached.
           Patients should be followed for a minimum of 5 years on this study to evaluate this
           endpoint.

        -  Overall survival

        -  Disease-specific survival

        -  Clinical progression including local/regional and distant relapse

        -  HRQOL questionnaires for genitourinary, gastrointestinal, and hormonal domains (EPIC and
           SF-12)

        -  Dosimetric comparison of neurovascular element sparing with rectal spacer on this
           protocol versus without spacer in prior SAbR phase I-II protocol treated patients at
           UTSW

        -  Dosimetric comparison of neurovascular element sparing according to quality of spacer
           placement (maximum spacer distance at mid-gland and at apex), as assessed by study P.I.
           using simulation MRI images.

        -  Biopsy positivity in area of dose sparing (i.e. PTV2-PTV1). To be evaluated only those
           patients in BCR who merit per clinician judgement a biopsy.

      Sample Size: To enroll 120 patients (60 patients in each treatment arm).

      The sample size is estimated, first, assuming that neurovascular element sparing SAbR
      (experimental arm intervention) will result in a mean 24 month decline in EPIC (HRQOL
      instrument) sexual domain composite score of -20, as compared to a decline of -10 in a
      standard SAbR without neurovascular element sparing. A total sample size of 102 patients (51
      patients in each treatment group) achieves 80% power to detect this difference of 10 in EPIC
      sexual domain composite score decline at 24 months after treatment, with an equal standard
      deviation of 20 in both groups and at a two-sided significance level of 0.10, using a
      two-sample t-test (effect size 0.50).

      An attrition rate of EPIC sexual domain questionnaire completion at 2-years of 15% is
      anticipated, based upon yields from multi-center prospective trials in prostate cancer
      radiotherapy with EPIC HRQOL endpoints. A total of 120 patients will be accrued to account
      for this 15% attrition rate.

      Statistical Analysis: For the primary endpoint, a two-sided two-sample t-test will be used to
      compare EPIC sexual function domain score composite declines at 24 months from treatment
      between experimental SAbR arms with and without neurovascular sparing. Our sample size of 60
      patients in each arm gives a calculated 80% power to detect a difference of 10 (considered
      the minimally important difference for sexual domain) at a two-sided significance level 0.10,
      assuming an equal standard deviation of 20 in both groups and allowing for 15% attrition in
      survey completion. Secondary endpoints and their analysis methodology is further specified in
      the protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 16, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 16, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in Expanded prostate cancer index composite (EPIC) sexual function domain composite score from Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Mean 24-Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Expanded prostate cancer index composite (EPIC) Health-related quality of life (HRQOL) instrument includes four sub-scales like Urinary function, Bowel habits, Sexual function, and Harmonal function. The primary outcome (sexual function) which has a range score of 0-100 from 9 questions related to ability to achieve an erection with or without aids and participate in intercourse. Higher the score represents the better outcome. Individual responses are summed for a total score of sexual function.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute &amp; Delayed Genitourinary (GU) and Gastrointestinal (GI) toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Mean 24-Months</time_frame>
    <description>Severity or Toxicity will be assessed according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), version 4.0. Dose adjustments should be made according to the system showing the greatest degree of toxicity. The consequences of gastointestinal/renal/genitourinary/sexual and reproductive toxicity should all be graded 1-5 according to the Common Terminology Criteria For Adverse Events (CTCAE), version 4.0 occurring prior to 270 days from the start of protocol treatment. Other treatment related toxicity attributed to the therapy will be captured, recorded and the consequences of should all be graded 1-5 according to the Common Terminology Criteria For Adverse Events (CTCAE). CTCAE V4.0 along with grades 1-5 is provided in the link for reference (https://evs.nci.nih.gov/ftp1/CTCAE/CTCAE_4.03/CTCAE_4.03_2010-06-14_QuickReference_8.5x11.pdf).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical failure RTOG-ASTRO definition (also known as Phoenix definition)</measure>
    <time_frame>60 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Increase in PSA greater than 2ng/ml above the patients lowest PSA level (nadir) after treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SAbR WITHOUT Neurovascular sparing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>GTV represents MR defined gross radiographic disease, if identifiable.
CTV encompasses the full prostate. At physician's discretion, the insertion of the seminal vesicle upon the prostate on slices containing prostate may be included.
PTV1_30Gy will not be used or created on this arm
PTV2_SAbR will be generated by a 3mm expansion on the CTV. PTV2_SAbR will receive 8-9 Gy per fraction for 5 fractions (40-45 Gy).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SAbR WITH Neurovascular sparing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GTV represents MR defined gross radiographic disease, if identifiable.
CTV encompasses the full prostate. At physician's discretion, the insertion of the seminal vesicle upon the prostate on slices containing prostate may be included.
PTV1_30Gy represents a 3mm expansion on the CTV, excluding the neurovascular structures on the side to be spared (left or right). PTV1 will receive 6 Gy per fraction for 5 fractions (30 Gy).
PTV2_SAbR will be generated by subtracting a 5mm expansion around the neurovascular elements to be spared (at least one side, left or right) from PTV1. These neurovascular structures consist of the neurovascular bundle, penile bulb, and internal pudendal arteries. PTV2 will receive 8-9 Gy per fraction for 5 fractions (40-45 Gy).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>30Gy (Gray) planning target volume (PTV)</intervention_name>
    <description>PTV1_30Gy represents a 3mm expansion on the prostate (and proximal seminal vesicle per physician discretion), excluding the neurovascular structures on the side to be spared (left or right). PTV1 will receive 6 Gy per fraction for 5 fractions (30 Gy).</description>
    <arm_group_label>SAbR WITH Neurovascular sparing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Appropriate staging studies identifying patient as American Joint Committee on Cancer
             (AJCC) 7th edition clinical stage T1 (a, b, or c) or T2 (a, b, or c) adenocarcinoma of
             the prostate gland. The patient should not have direct evidence of regional or distant
             metastases after appropriate staging studies. See Appendix I for details on AJCC 7th
             Edition staging criteria. Histologic confirmation of cancer will be required by biopsy
             performed within 12 months of registration. T-staging may be assessed by
             multi-parametric imaging alone if digital rectal examination was deferred.

          -  The patient's Zubrod performance status must be 0-2 (see Appendix II for definition).

          -  The Gleason summary score should be less than or equal to 7 [Grade group 1 (Gleason
             3+3=6), group 2 (Gleason 3+4=7), and group 3 (Gleason 4+3=7) are allowed]. See
             Appendix III for details on definitions. While a template biopsy is recommended, it is
             not required in the case of MRI fusion biopsy performed on all dominant MR lesions
             (defined as Prostate imaging - reporting and data system (PIRADS) v2 4-5).

          -  Baseline AUA symptom score ≤19 (see Appendix IV for questionnaire) without need for
             maximum medical therapy (specifically, not on tamsulosin 0.8mg daily)

          -  EPIC sexual domain composite score 60-100 (see Appendix V)

          -  Multi-parametric MRI evaluation of the prostate is required for this study within 90
             days of registration. Gross radiographic disease on MRI (defined as PIRADS v2 score
             3-5) must be &gt; 5mm at minimum distance from at least one side's neurovascular bundle,
             which is typically the closest of the neurovascular elements to the prostate.

          -  The serum PSA should be less than or equal to 20 ng/ml within 90 days of registration.

               -  Study entry PSA must not be obtained during the following time frames: (1) 10-day
                  period following prostate biopsy; (2) following initiation of ADT or
                  anti-androgen therapy; (3) within 30 days after discontinuation of finasteride;
                  (4) within 90 days after discontinuation of dutasteride; (5) within 5 days of a
                  digital rectal examination.

          -  Ultrasound or MRI based volume estimation of prostate gland ≤ 80 grams. Cytoreduction
             therapy (finasteride or dutasteride only) may be considered for those with &gt;60 gram
             size.

          -  All patients must be willing and capable to provide informed consent to participate in
             the protocol within the 30 days prior to registration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with clinical (digital rectal examination) evidence of extraprostatic
             extension (T3a) or seminal vesicle involvement (T3b). MRI evidence of
             equivocal/potential but not definite extraprostatic extension is allowed, as long as
             it is unilateral and not on the side of the gland proposed for neurovascular element
             sparing. In equivocal cases of potential extracapsular extension on MRI only,
             discretion is left to the treating physician.

          -  MRI evidence of gross disease (defined as PIRADS v2 score 3-5 lesions) ≤5mm of BOTH
             neurovascular bundles, which are the most proximate of the neurovascular elements
             planned for sparing on this protocol.

          -  Patients with all three intermediate risk factors (PSA &gt;10 and ≤ 20, Gleason 7,
             clinical stage T2b-T2c) who ALSO have ≥50% of the number of their template biopsy
             cores positive for cancer are ineligible.

          -  Inability to undergo multi-parametric MRI.

          -  Evidence of metastatic disease. Note bone scan is not required for this study given
             the low-intermediate NCCN risk cohort to be enrolled.

          -  Evidence of clinical nodal involvement of the pelvis. Biopsy is required for lymph
             nodes over ≥1.5cm in short-axis measured size.

          -  No current ADT or anti-androgen therapy at time of registration is allowed. Further,
             no more than 3 cumulative months of prior ADT or anti-androgen therapy is allowed. If
             either has been used by the patient, there must be a demonstration of full
             testosterone recovery (&gt;280ng/dL serum blood level), EPIC sexual domain score ≥60, and
             at least 1 month between demonstration of testosterone recovery and study registration
             (any one measurement of testosterone recovery suffices).

          -  Testosterone ≤ 280 ng/dL (any one measurement &gt;280 ng/dL suffices for inclusion)

          -  Subjects who have had previous pelvic radiotherapy or have had chemotherapy or surgery
             for prostate cancer.

          -  Subjects who have plans to receive other concomitant or post treatment adjuvant
             antineoplastic therapy while on this protocol including surgery, cryotherapy,
             conventionally fractionated radiotherapy, hormonal therapy, or chemotherapy given as
             part of the treatment of prostate cancer.

          -  Subjects who have undergone previous transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP) or
             ablative procedures to the prostate for benign prostatic hyperplasia or other
             conditions (i.e. cryotherapy, HIFU).

          -  Subjects who have baseline severe urinary symptoms, as defined by AUA symptom score
             &gt;19 (alpha-blocker medication allowed except if taking tamsulosin 0.8mg daily at
             baseline which indicates compensated severe symptoms and also can affect sexual
             function).

          -  Subjects who have a history of significant psychiatric illness that would confound
             informed consent.

          -  Severe, active co-morbidity, defined as follows:

               -  Unstable angina and/or congestive heart failure requiring hospitalization within
                  the last 6 months

               -  Myocardial infarction within the last 6 months

               -  Acute bacterial or fungal infection requiring intravenous antibiotics at time of
                  registration

               -  Patients with active inflammatory colitis (including Crohn's Disease and
                  ulcerative colitis) currently requiring systemic steroids and/or systemic
                  immunosuppression are not eligible.

          -  Subjects with a known allergy to polyethylene glycol hydrogel (rectal spacer material)
             or contraindication to spacer products (Duraseal or SpaceOAR)

          -  Subjects with uncontrolled coagulation disorder which cannot be controlled with
             anticoagulants

          -  Men of reproductive potential who do not agree that they or their partner will use an
             effective contraceptive method such as condom/diaphragm and spermicidal foam,
             intrauterine device (IUD), or prescription birth control pills.

          -  Men who require erectile function medication or aid to achieve an erection sufficient
             for intercourse. Ability to achieve erection sufficient for intercourse without
             medication or aid at least once time in the month prior to registration is sufficient
             for inclusion.

          -  Men who have clinically significant penile malformation (i.e. Peyronie's disease) or
             history of penile implantation are excluded.

          -  If DRE is performed, patient may not have palpable disease on side of gland to be
             planned for neurovascular sparing. Given the poor accuracy of DRE, such a finding
             should be confirmed by MRI and/or biopsy to harbor actual disease before excluding a
             patient on this basis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>120 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Neil B Desai, MD MHS</last_name>
    <phone>2146458525</phone>
    <email>Neil.Desai@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarmistha Sen, MS MHA</last_name>
    <phone>2146451477</phone>
    <email>Sarmistha.Sen@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Hardee, MS</last_name>
      <phone>214-648-1836</phone>
      <email>Sarah.Hardee@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Erectile dysfunction, Neurovascular, Prostate, Rectal spacer, Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

