<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03528512</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-363</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03528512</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IN Ketamine vs IN Midazolam and Fentanyl for Laceration Repair</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Sedation, Pain, and Care Provider Satisfaction Between the Use of Intranasal Ketamine Versus Intranasal Midazolam and Fentanyl During Laceration Repair</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>William Beaumont Hospitals</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>William Beaumont Hospitals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Often, repair of the cuts (laceration repair) proves to be traumatic for the children and the
      parents. Nasal spray (Intranasal/IN) approaches for procedural pain reduction, such as during
      dental work, have been demonstrated to make drug administration painless and well tolerated.
      We are comparing IN ketamine to IN midazolam and fentanyl for pain and reducing anxiety
      during repair of cuts in children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Children frequently present to pediatric emergency center (PEC) with cuts of different body
      parts. Often, repair of the cuts (laceration repair) proves to be traumatic for the children
      and the parents alike. Ideally, repair of the cuts should be as painless and free from
      anxiety as possible. To work towards this goal, different analgesic (pain drugs) and sedative
      ( to calm patients down) management strategies use intravenous (into the vein), intramuscular
      ( into the muscle) and, more recently, intranasal (into the nostrils) routes. Unfortunately,
      intravenous access is hard to establish and may be painful for the child. The intramuscular
      route is often similarly painful. Due to the rich blood supply and large surface area of the
      nasal vestibule, intranasally (IN) administered medications are highly absorbed. IN
      approaches for procedural pain reduction, such as during dental work, have been demonstrated
      to make drug administration painless and well tolerated, making it an attractive potential
      alternative to commonly used intravenous and intramuscular approaches. In several small
      research studies, high doses of intranasal ketamine (9 mg/kg) produce adequate sedation
      during laceration repair with minimal side effects. A recent study compared IN ketamine,
      midazolam, fentanyl or combination of these drugs for pain management and urgent analgesia
      sedation, and demonstrated that they are effective and safe, reporting that ~60% of study
      participants sustained mild to moderate sedation. Unfortunately, there are not enough studies
      done to evaluate the sedation effect of IN ketamine for laceration repair. Small studies
      (Tsze and Nemeth) showed that IN ketamine is an effective alternative but no studies are done
      to compare combination IN midazolam and fentanyl to IN ketamine. Our null hypothesis is that
      there is no difference in sedation scores during laceration repair when comparing the use of
      IN ketamine to IN midazolam and IN fentanyl.

      We will recruit a total of 30 pediatric patients (6 months - 10 y age) in a randomized
      double-blinded pilot study of IN ketamine alone or combined IN midazolam and IN fentanyl for
      laceration repair, comparing levels of pain and sedation scores using validated pediatric
      metrics as the primary outcomes. In addition, we will assess comparative nurse and physician
      satisfaction in each of these two groups. Understanding the relative effectiveness of these
      two approaches will help us identify a safe, effective, and easily administrable method to
      manage pain and anxiety, thereby, improving patient experience and outcomes during the often
      traumatic laceration repair procedure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized double blinded control trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A randomization list created by an online randomization tool will be used to assign participants to a treatment arm (in random blocks of 4, 6, and 8). As participants are enrolled in the study, they will be assigned to the next available sequential treatment arm.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sedation Score</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome variable is the maximum sedation score as measured by the University of Michigan Sedation Scale. This scale consists of an ordinal scale from 0 being awake and alert and 4 being unarousable. Medians will be calculated for each group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of children with maximum sedation score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of children who receive a maximum sedation score of either 1 or 2 (without distinguishing between those values)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scores during laceration repair</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The effect of IN ketamine vs IN midazolam + IN fentanyl on pain scores during laceration repair using either Face, Legs, Activity, Cry, Consolability (FLACC) Scale or Faces Scale pain scale depending for patient age, each a Likert scale from 0 being no pain to 10 being worst pain, median scores for each group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nurse and physician satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Nurse and physician satisfaction will be assessed by a survey which will be filled in the end of the sedation. Response to overall experience question score on Likert scale where 1 is poor and 5 is Excellent. Proportion of responders giving answers of 4 or 5 will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of failure</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Rates of failure to repair laceration due to agitation or intolerable pain with the switch to intravenous medications will be compared between two groups. Percentage failure will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vitals</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of children who have any significant change in vitals during analgosedation (any desaturation - Oxygen saturation &lt; 90, and hypotension per age-related norms) will be compared between the two groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Laceration of Skin</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IN ketamine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intranasal ketamine 3mg/kg (max 100 mg) + saline 0.03 ml/kg (max 2ml)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IN midazolam and fentanyl</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intranasal midazolam 0.3 mg/kg (max 10 mg) + fentanyl 1.5mcg/kg (max 100 mcg)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Intranasal ketamine 3mg/kg (max 100 mg) + saline 0.03 ml/kg (max 2ml)</description>
    <arm_group_label>IN ketamine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midazolam and fentanyl</intervention_name>
    <description>Intranasal midazolam 0.3 mg/kg (max 10 mg) + fentanyl 1.5mcg/kg (max 100 mcg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>IN midazolam and fentanyl</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pediatric patients 6 months to 10 years who required laceration repair in the
             pediatric emergency center.

          -  Laceration should be less than 5 cm long, require 2 or more sutures and no consult
             subspeciality consult for repair.

          -  Topical anesthetic (lidocaine-epinephrine-tetracaine topical solution/XAP) will be
             applied to all lacerations for 20 minutes duration before giving the intranasal
             medications.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 6 months

          -  Documented allergy or adverse effect to ketamine, midazolam or fentanyl

          -  Epistaxis

          -  Partial upper airway obstruction

          -  Oxygen requirement via nasal cannula

          -  Acute mental status changes (e.g. obtunded or somnolent)

          -  Documented increased intracranial pressure or increased ocular pressure

          -  Documented porphyria

          -  Previously involved in the study

          -  Parent or patient refusal

          -  Acutely compromised vitals (hypotension, desaturations, respiratory distress)

          -  Any known heart disease

          -  If any previous opioid use for analgesia during the visit

          -  Need for staples

          -  Scalp wounds

          -  General trauma requiring additional sedation

          -  Patients who received pain medications (acetaminophen or ibuprofen) before laceration
             repair
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kelly Levasseur, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>William Beaumont Hospitals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ali Ozcan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>7187758031</phone>
    <email>ali.ozcan@beaumont.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mara Branoff, RN</last_name>
    <phone>2488981792</phone>
    <email>mara.branoff@beaumont.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>William Beaumont Hospitals</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kelly Levasseur, DO</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Pediatric Emergency Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>pain control</keyword>
  <keyword>sedation</keyword>
  <keyword>intranasal ketamine</keyword>
  <keyword>intranasal midazolam</keyword>
  <keyword>intranasal fentanyl</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lacerations</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Midazolam</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Undecided</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

