<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03526887</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GECP 17/02_REPLAY</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03526887</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Re-challenge Pembrolizumab Study as a Second or Further Line in Patients With Advanced NSCLC</brief_title>
  <acronym>Replay</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Open-label Multicenter Exploratory Study to Assess Efficacy of Pembrolizumab Re-challenge as Second or Further Line in Patients With Advanced Non - Small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Spanish Lung Cancer Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Spanish Lung Cancer Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Exploratory phase II trial of intravenous (IV) Pembrolizumab MK-3475 as second or further
      line with advanced Non-small cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) who have failed to a prior treatment
      with anti-PDL1 drug.

      Pembrolizumab 200 mg ,Q3W, IV infusion, Day 1 of each 3 week cycle will be administered until
      disease progression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center exploratory phase II trial of intravenous (IV) Pembrolizumab MK-3475
      as second or further line with advanced Non-small cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) who have failed to
      a prior treatment with anti-PDL1 drug.

      110 patients will be enrolled in this trial to examine the efficacy and outcomes of these
      patients.

      In addition to the usual procedures in a phase II study (evaluation of response, toxicity,
      etc.) special attention will be paid in this trial to the molecular assessment in biological
      samples.

      Subjects will receive Pembrolizumab at a fixed dose of 200 mg every 3 weeks (Q3W). Subjects
      will be evaluated with radiographic imaging to assess response to treatment. Investigators
      will make all treatment-based decisions using the Immune-Related Response Criteria (irRC).
      However, for determination of overall response rate (ORR) and progression-free survival
      (PFS), the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 will be used.

      Adverse events will be monitored throughout the trial and graded in severity according to the
      guidelines outlined in the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version
      4.0. Treatment with Pembrolizumab will continue until documented disease progression,
      unacceptable adverse event(s), intercurrent illness that prevents further administration of
      treatment, investigator's decision to withdraw the subject, subject withdraws consent,
      noncompliance with trial treatment or procedure requirements, or administrative reasons.

      After the end of treatment, each subject will be followed for a minimum of 30 days for
      adverse event monitoring (serious adverse events will be collected for up to 90 days after
      the end of treatment unless the subject starts a new anticancer therapy between days 31 and
      90). Subjects will have post-treatment follow-up for disease status, including initiating a
      non-study cancer treatment and experiencing disease progression, until death, withdrawing
      consent, or becoming lost to follow-up.

      Participation in this trial will be dependent upon supplying tumor tissue from a newly
      obtained formalin-fixed specimen from locations not radiated prior to biopsy. The specimen
      will be evaluated at a central laboratory facility for expression status of PD-L1 in a
      prospective manner. Only subjects whose tumors express PD-L1 as determined by the central
      laboratory facility will be eligible for inclusion in this study. Also it is highly recommend
      to send archival tumor tissue from the patient.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>2 groups depending on when the progression disease is diagnosed but the treatment after progression will be the same: Pembrolizumab</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of Pembrolizumab re-challenge measured by Overall Response Rate per RECIST v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 50 months.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of Pembrolizumab re-challenge administered 200 mg iv every 21 days in second or further line for advanced NSCLC after progression to monotherapy check point PD1 / PDL1 inhibitors measured by Overall Response Rate (ORR) per RECIST v1.1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of Pembrolizumab re-challenge measured by Progression Free Survival per RECIST v1.1.</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 50 months.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of Pembrolizumab re-challenge administered 200 mg iv every 21 days in second or further line for advanced NSCLC after progression to monotherapy check point PD1 / PDL1 inhibitors measured by Progression Free Survival (PFS) per RECIST v1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0.</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of the first infusion of medication until 90 days after the last dose, assessed up to 50 months.</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the safety and tolerability profile of pembrolizumab Re-challenged as a Second or further line in previously treated patients.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who experienced progression disease while on treatment progression disease &lt; 12 weeks after stopping treatment. After that the patients took chemotherapy ≥ 4 cycles and progressed again. After the last progression the patient is included in the study to be retreated with Pembrolizumab 200mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stop treatment and progression &gt; 12 weeks after stopping treatment. After the last progression the patient is included in the study to be retreated with Pembrolizumab 200mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg, Q3W</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg, Q3W</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with hystologically or cythologicalconfirmed NSCLC advanced or locally
             advanced disease not amenable to radical treatment (IIIA, IIIB, IV), squamous or
             non-squamous, recurrent after at least one prior line.

          2. The subject must be willing and able to provide written informed consent/assent for
             the trial.

          3. Patient must be aged ≥ 18 years of age on day of signing informed consent.

          4. Measurable disease (at least 1 lesion) based on RECIST 1.1. Patients will not be
             eligible if this lesion was irradiated before inclusion.

          5. Documented prior benefit (Stable Disease, Partial Response, Complete Response) to
             check point PD1/PDL1 inhibitor (Nivolumab, Pembrolizumab, Darvolumab, Atezolizumab,
             Avelumab or others) for at least 16 weeks (Stable Disease, Partial Response, Complete
             Response) and progression while on treatment (or &lt;12 weeks after stopping) with the
             same PD-1/PD-L1 inhibitors. These patients should have received subsequent treatment
             with Chemotherapy for at least 4 courses (Cohort 1) OR Documented prior benefit
             (Stable Disease, Partial Response, Complete Response) to check point PD1/PDL1
             inhibitor (Nivolumab, Pembrolizumab, Darvolumab, Atezolizumab, Avelumab or others) for
             at least 16 weeks (Stable Disease, Partial Response, Complete Response) and
             progression &gt;12 weeks after stopping treatment (Cohort 2). No subsequent treatment
             before rechallenge is allowed in this cohort

          6. Patient must be willing to provide tissue from a newly obtained core or excisional
             biopsy of a tumor lesion. PDL1 must be evaluable and at least 1% positive in tumor
             tissue. Newly-obtained is defined as a specimen obtained up to 6 weeks (42 days) prior
             to initiation of treatment on Day 1. Subjects for whom newly-obtained samples cannot
             be provided (e.g. inaccessible or subject safety concern) may submit an archived
             specimen only upon agreement from the Sponsor.

          7. Have a performance status of 0-2 on the ECOG Performance Scale.

          8. Demonstrate adequate organ function, all screening labs should be performed within 7
             days of treatment initiation.

          9. Female subject of childbearing potential should have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy within 72 hours prior to receiving the first dose of study medication. If
             the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy test
             will be required.

         10. Female subjects of childbearing potential must be willing to use an adequate method of
             contraception (for the course of the study through 120 days after the last dose of
             study medication).

             Note: Abstinence is acceptable if this is the usual lifestyle and preferred
             contraception for the subject.

         11. Male subjects of childbearing potential must agree to use an adequate method of
             contraception (starting with the first dose of study therapy through 120 days after
             the last dose of study therapy).

             Note: Abstinence is acceptable if this is the usual lifestyle and preferred
             contraception for the subject.

         12. All patients will be required to submit a tumor sample for PD-L1 IHC expression. If
             the sample is inadequate for analysis, another sample could be provided or the patient
             will be considered ineligible for further randomization in the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Is currently participating and receiving study therapy or has participated in a study
             of an investigational agent and received study therapy or used an investigational
             device within 4 weeks of the first dose of treatment.

          2. Has a diagnosis of immunodeficiency or is receiving systemic steroid therapy or any
             other form of immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of trial
             treatment.

          3. Has a known history of active TB (Bacillus Tuberculosis)

          4. Hypersensitivity to pembrolizumab or any of its excipients.

          5. Has had a prior anti-cancer monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to study
             Day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at baseline) from adverse events
             due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          6. Has had prior chemotherapy, targeted small molecule therapy, or radiation therapy
             within 2 weeks prior to study Day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at
             baseline) from adverse events due to a previously administered agent.

             Note: Subjects with ≤ Grade 2 neuropathy are an exception to this criterion and may
             qualify for the study.

             Note: If subject received major surgery, they must have recovered adequately from the
             toxicity and/or complications from the intervention prior to starting therapy.

          7. Has a known additional malignancy that is progressing or requires active treatment.
             Exceptions include basal cell carcinoma of the skin or squamous cell carcinoma of the
             skin that has undergone potentially curative therapy or in situ cervical cancer.

          8. Has known active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous
             meningitis. Subjects with previously treated brain metastases may participate provided
             they are stable (without evidence of progression by imaging for at least four weeks
             prior to the first dose of trial treatment and any neurologic symptoms have returned
             to baseline), have no evidence of new or enlarging brain metastases, and are not using
             steroids at a dose over 10 mg of prednisone or equivalent, for at least 7 days prior
             to trial treatment. This exception does not include carcinomatous meningitis which is
             excluded regardless of clinical stability.

          9. Has active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2 years
             (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs). Replacement therapy (eg., thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment.

         10. Has a history of (non-infectious) pneumonitis that required steroids or current
             pneumonitis.

         11. Has an active infection requiring systemic therapy.

         12. Documented EGFR sensitizing mutation.

         13. Documented ALK translocation.

         14. Has a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality
             that might confound the results of the trial, interfere with the subject's
             participation for the full duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of
             the subject to participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator.

         15. Has known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with
             cooperation with the requirements of the trial.

         16. Is pregnant or breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive or father children within the
             projected duration of the trial, starting with the pre-screening or screening visit
             through 120 days after the last dose of trial treatment.

         17. Has a known history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) (HIV 1/2 antibodies).

         18. Has known active Hepatitis B (e.g., HBsAg reactive) or Hepatitis C (e.g., HCV RNA
             [qualitative] is detected).

         19. Has received a live vaccine within 30 days of planned start of study therapy. Note:
             Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection are generally inactivated flu vaccines and
             are allowed; however intranasal influenza vaccines (e.g., Flu-Mist®) are live
             attenuated vaccines, and are not allowed.

         20. Received radiation therapy to the lung of &gt;30Gy within 6 months of the first dose of
             trial treatment.

         21. Evidence of interstitial lung disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luís Paz Ares, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital 12 de Octubre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eva Pereira</last_name>
    <phone>+34934302006</phone>
    <email>epereira@gecp.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario de Elche</name>
      <address>
        <city>Elche</city>
        <state>Alicante</state>
        <zip>03203</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>María Guirado, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>María Guirado, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Germans Trias i Pujol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Badalona</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08916</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Enric Carcereny, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+ 34 93 430 20 06</phone>
      <email>ecarcereny@iconcologia.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Enric Carcereny, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Parc Taulí</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sabadell</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08208</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elsa Dalmau, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elsa Dalmau, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Consorci Sanitari de Terrassa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Terrassa</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08227</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jordi Alfaro, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jordi Alfaro, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Hospitalario de la Coruña</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Coruña</city>
        <state>Coruña</state>
        <zip>15006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rosario García Campelo, MD-phD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rosario García Campelo</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clínica Universidad de Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jesús Corral, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jesús Corral, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Basurto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bilbao</city>
        <state>Vizcaya</state>
        <zip>48013</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mª Ángeles Sala, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mª Ángeles Sala, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Santa Creu i Sant Pau</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08025</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Margarita Majem, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Margarita Majem, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H.U.Vall D´Hebrón</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Enriqueta Felip, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+34932746085</phone>
      <email>efelip@vhebron.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Enriqueta Felip, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Dr. Josep Trueta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Girona</city>
        <zip>17007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joaquim Bosch, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joaquim Bosch, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Hospitalario de Jaén</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jaén</city>
        <zip>23007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ana Laura Ortega, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Laura Ortega, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Asistencial Universitario de León</name>
      <address>
        <city>León</city>
        <zip>24071</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pilar Diz, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pilar Diz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fundación Jiménez Díaz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28040</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manuel Dómine, MD-phD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manuel Dómine, MD-phD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. 12 de Octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Santiago Ponce, MD-phD</last_name>
      <phone>+34914692313</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Santiago Ponce, MD-phD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Son Llàtzer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palma de Mallorca</city>
        <zip>07198</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Juan Coves, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+34871202000</phone>
      <phone_ext>1143</phone_ext>
      <email>jcoves@sll.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Juan Coves, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario de Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ana Blasco Cordellat, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Blasco, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46026</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Miguel Servet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zaragoza</city>
        <zip>50009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ángel Artal, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ángel Artal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.gecp.org</url>
    <description>Grupo Español de Cáncer de Pulmón</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

