<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03523572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DS8201-A-U105</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-000371-32</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03523572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trastuzumab Deruxtecan (DS-8201a) With Nivolumab in Advanced Breast and Urothelial Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b, Multicenter, Two-Part, Open-Label Study of DS-8201a, an Anti-Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor-2 (HER2)-Antibody Drug Conjugate (ADC), in Combination With Nivolumab, an Anti-PD-1 Antibody, for Subjects With HER2-expressing Advanced Breast and Urothelial Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this phase 1b study is to test the combination of an experimental drug known
      as DS-8201a given along with Nivolumab (a marketed drug) in participants with HER2-expressing
      breast and urothelial cancer who had disease progression during or after prior therapies, did
      not respond to standard therapies, or for whom no standard therapy is available.

      The study will be performed in 2 parts.

        -  Part 1 is to look at different doses of DS-8201a when given along with a fixed dose of
           nivolumab, and establish the most effective and safe dose (maximum/recommended tolerated
           dose) when used in combination with nivolumab.

        -  Part 2 is to understand the positive or negative effects of this dose combination on the
           participant's body and disease.

      The study will also determine the pharmacokinetics of DS-8201a when administered with
      nivolumab.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Part 1 will be a sequential dose-finding (dose escalation) study, Part 2 will consist of a single group of four cohorts who receive the recommended dose (determined during Part 1)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with dose-limiting toxicity at each dose level</measure>
    <time_frame>2 cycles (within 2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Categories: Low Dose, Medium Dose, High Dose</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: Dose expansion - Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>ORR during the dose expansion part as assessed by the Independent Imaging Vendor (Central Imaging Review) based on RECIST Version 1.1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response (DoR)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Response based on central review</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR</measure>
    <time_frame>within 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>ORR, as assessed by investigator and defined as the percentage of participants who achieved a confirmed response (CR or PR) during study treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Concentration (Cmax) of Trastuzumab deruxtecan (DS-8201a) and metabollite (MAAA-1181a)</measure>
    <time_frame>21-day Cycles 1 (Days 1, 8 and 15), 2 (Day 1) and 3 (Day 1) (within 3 months)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Concentration of Total HER2 Antibody</measure>
    <time_frame>21-day Cycles 1 (Days 1, 8 and 15), 2 (Day 1) and 3 (Day 1) (within 3 months)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">99</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Urothelial Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part 1 will enroll participants meeting the eligibility criteria set up for any of the 4 cohorts of Part 2 specified below using a 3 + 3 + 3 design. Escalating doses of trastuzumab deruxtecan (DS-8201a) in combination with nivolumab will be assessed. DS-8201a and nivolumab will be administered on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 1 (n=30): Advanced HER2-positive breast cancer [as defined by American Society of Clinical Oncology/College of American Pathologists (ASCO-CAP) guidelines 2013] participants who have previously received ado-trastuzumab emtansine (T-DM1) with documented progression.
Participants will receive the Part 1 recommended dose of trastuzumab deruxtecan (DS-8201a) and the same dose of nivolumab as in Part 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 2 (n=15): Advanced HER2 low-expressing breast cancer (HER2 IHC 1+ or IHC 2+/ISH-) participants who have exhausted treatments that can confer any clinically meaningful benefit (eg, other therapies such as hormonal therapy for patients who are hormone receptor positive).
Participants will receive the Part 1 recommended dose of trastuzumab deruxtecan (DS-8201a) and the same dose of nivolumab as in Part 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 3 (n=30): Advanced HER2 high-expressing urothelial cancer (HER2 IHC 2+ or IHC 3+) participants who received prior platinum-based therapy with documented progression.
Participants will receive the Part 1 recommended dose of trastuzumab deruxtecan (DS-8201a) and the same dose of nivolumab as in Part 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 4 (n=15): Advanced HER2 low-expressing urothelial cancer (HER2 IHC 1+) participants who have received prior platinum-based therapy with documented progression.
Participants will receive the Part 1 recommended dose of trastuzumab deruxtecan (DS-8201a) and the same dose of nivolumab as in Part 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trastuzumab deruxtecan (DS-8201a)</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigational product is a sterile lyophilized powder, which is made into solution for intravenous administration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Experimental product</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Nivolumab is an aqueous solution formulated at 10 mg/mL to be administered at a flat dose of 360 mg IV over 30 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Expansion - Cohort 4</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Is the age of majority in their country

          -  Has histologically confirmed unresectable or metastatic breast or bladder cancer. The
             cancer is refractory and progressed after the last treatment

          -  Has at least 1 measurable lesion assessed by the investigator based on Response
             Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1

          -  Meets the HER2 status in tumor tissue sample as confirmed by the central laboratory

          -  Is willing and able to provide an adequate archival tumor sample or is willing to
             undergo a tissue biopsy after the completion of the most recent treatment regimen

          -  Has Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status (ECOG PS) of 0 to 1

          -  Demonstrates adequate organ functions: Required cardiac, bone marrow, kidney, liver
             and blood clotting functions as per protocol

          -  Has adequate washout period for previous surgery and other treatment before
             registration

          -  Agrees to use highly effective method of contraception starting with the first dose of
             study therapy through 7 months (for male) and 5 months (for female) after the last
             dose of study drug

          -  If a female of childbearing potential, has a negative urine or serum pregnancy within
             72 hours prior to receiving the first dose of study medication. If the urine test is
             positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy test will be required.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Was previously treated with HER2-targeted therapy for HER2-positive breast cancer

          -  Was previously treated with medications such as anti-Programmed Death 1 PD-1 (or
             anti-PD-L1) or anti-Programmed Death Ligand 2 (anti-PD-L2), or anti-CTLA-4 antibody,
             or any other antibody or drug that specifically targets T-cell co-stimulation or
             checkpoint pathways.

          -  Has medical history of myocardial infarction, symptomatic congestive heart failure
             (CHF) (NYHA classes II-IV), unstable angina or serious cardiac arrhythmia

          -  Has a corrected QT (QTc) interval prolongation to &gt; 450 millisecond (ms) in males and
             &gt; 470 ms in females

          -  Has a medical history of clinically significant lung disease such as non-infectious
             interstitial lung disease or pneumonitis and require steroid treatment

          -  Requires treatment with either corticosteroids (&gt;10 mg daily prednisone equivalent) or
             other immune suppression medications within 14 days of start of study treatment

          -  Is pregnant or breastfeeding, or planning to become pregnant

          -  Is suspected to have certain other protocol-defined diseases based on past medical
             history, physical exam, blood tests, eye test and imaging at screening period

          -  Has history of any disease, medical condition, metastatic condition, drug/medication
             use or other condition that might, per protocol or in the opinion of the investigator,
             compromise:

               1. safety or well-being of the participant or offspring

               2. safety of study staff

               3. analysis of results
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Global Team Leader</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Human epidermal growth factor receptor-2</keyword>
  <keyword>HER2</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Urothelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Transitional Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Camptothecin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoconjugates</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data (IPD) and applicable supporting clinical trial documents may be available upon request at https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com//. In cases where clinical trial data and supporting documents are provided pursuant to our company policies and procedures, Daiichi Sankyo will continue to protect the privacy of our clinical trial participants. Details on data sharing criteria and the procedure for requesting access can be found at this web address: https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com/Study-Sponsors/Study-Sponsors-DS.aspx</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

