<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00305357</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H5612-16138</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00305357</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evolution of Pain From Herpes Zoster</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evolution of Pain and Neural Dysfunction From Acute Herpes Zoster to Post-Herpetic Neuralgia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evolution of pain and neural injury will be evaluated at 2 years or longer after the onset of
      AHZ by multiple measures. Assessments at 2 years or longer will be compared to those
      collected during the first 6 months after HZ in order to test whether or not sensory function
      and cutaneous innervation continues to normalize beyond 6 months in subjects who recover from
      HZ without severe PHN.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pain, nerve trunk inflammation, and neuronal injury are hallmarks of acute herpes zoster
      (AHZ). We hypothesize that the development of post-herpetic neuralgia (PHN) strongly depends
      on two factors: 1) the severity of the initial neural injury and 2) the ability to recover
      from the initial neural injury. To test this hypothesis, we will prospectively follow 150
      patients at high risk for development of PHN. Evolution of pain and neural injury will be
      evaluated at 2-6 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months and at 2 years or longer after the onset
      of AHZ by multiple measures. Assessments at 2 years or longer will be compared to those
      collected during the first 6 months after HZ in order to test whether or not sensory function
      and cutaneous innervation continues to normalize beyond 6 months in subjects who recover from
      HZ without severe PHN.

      Preliminary analysis of study data showed reduced innervation in HZ skin, mirror image skin
      and distant control skin in the acute phase of HZ that was not specific to the persistence of
      pain at 3 months. The innervation appeared to recover more fully by 6 months in distant
      control skin than in mirror-image skin and HZ skin, despite the fact that the subjects were
      continuing to experience a further reduction in their zoster-associated pain. This suggests
      that the symptoms of pain and sensory dysfunction are not due to a mere loss in overall
      innervation density. The proposed subsequent ≥ 2 year study visit and analysis will allow us
      to directly correlate pain resolution with resolution of sensory and innervation
      abnormalities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-Herpetic Neuralgia</condition>
  <condition>Acute Herpes Zoster</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Males and females aged 50 or older with outbreak of herpes zoster occurring less than 6
        weeks prior to study entry.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females aged 50 or older and in stable general health.

          2. Able and willing to provide written informed consent.

          3. Able to understand and follow the instructions of the investigator, including the pain
             intensity rating scales.

          4. Subjects must have an acute outbreak of cervical, thoracic or lumbosacral HZ with
             unilateral skin rash and pain; the diagnosis will be based on physical examination and
             review of available medical records confirming the outbreak.

          5. The outbreak of herpes zoster must have occurred less than 6 weeks prior to study
             entry.

          6. PHN pain must be of at least moderate severity, defined as self-report of average pain
             level of 20 mm on a 100 mm visual analog scale.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The AHZ outbreak is complicated by stroke or myelopathy.

          2. Patients with facial or cranial AHZ.

          3. Patients with signs of spinal cord or brainstem injury from HZ.

          4. Patients who are considered unreliable as to study compliance or adherence to
             scheduled appointments as determined by the Investigators.

          5. Patients, who are undergoing active treatment for cancer, are infected with the Human
             Immunodeficiency Virus, or are being acutely and intensively immunosuppressed
             following a transplantation procedure.

          6. Bleeding disorders.

          7. Patients with known skin pathology.

          8. Use of topical steroids, capsaicin, local anesthetics or topical aspirin/NSAID
             preparations within two weeks of the study sessions.

          9. Another pain problem of equal or greater severity than AHZ.

         10. Allergy or idiosyncratic reaction to lidocaine or capsaicin.

         11. Neurological dysfunction or psychiatric disorder severe enough to interfere with
             assessment of pain and sensory systems.

         12. Has received neuroablative nerve blocks or neurosurgical procedures for AHZ pain prior
             to entering the study.

         13. Patients who are unable to read or speak English.

         14. Those, in the opinion of the investigator, who are unlikely to comply with the study
             protocol or who are unsuitable for any other reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karin Petersen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 21, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Karin Petersen, MD</name_title>
    <organization>University of California, San Francisco</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Post-Herpetic Neuralgia</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Herpes Zoster</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Herpes Zoster</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia, Postherpetic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

