<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03066206</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0783</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>FP00000804</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-00831</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03066206</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Poziotinib in EGFR Exon 20 Mutant Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) and HER2 Exon 20 Mutant NSCLC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Poziotinib in EGFR Exon 20 Mutant Advanced Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) and HER2 Exon 20 Mutant NSCLC</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lung Cancer Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Spectrum Pharmaceuticals, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if poziotinib can help to control
      EGFR-positive non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) that is locally advanced or metastatic (has
      spread). EGFR-positive NSCLC means that there is a mutation (a type of genetic change) on the
      EGFR gene.

      The safety of poziotinib will also be studied.

      This is an investigational study. Poziotinib is not FDA approved or commercially available.
      It is being used for research purposes only. The study doctor can explain how the study drug
      is designed to work.

      Up to 80 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      Each study cycle is 28 days.

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will take 2 poziotinib
      tablets by mouth 1 time every day while you are on study. Each dose should be taken at about
      the same time each day (preferably in the morning) with a glass (about 8 ounces) of water.

      If you miss a dose, take it as soon as possible on the same day with a return to the normal
      schedule the following day. You should not take any extra doses on the following day to make
      up for any forgotten doses.

      You will be given a pill diary to complete. You should record in the diary each dose of
      poziotinib you take, including when you took it. You should bring this diary with you to each
      study visit.

      Length of Study:

      You may continue taking the study drug for as long as the doctor thinks it is in your best
      interest. You will no longer be able to take the study drug if the disease gets worse, if
      intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation in this study will be over after follow-up.

      Study Visits:

      On Day 1 (+/- 7 days) of all cycles and Day 15 of Cycle 1:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2½ teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      At Week 16, you will have an EKG.

      At Month 3 and every 6 months after that, you will have an ECHO or MUGA scan.

      Every 8 weeks, you will have an CT scan and/or an MRI to check the status of your disease.

      Follow-Up Visit:

      About 30 days after your last dose of study drug:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2½ teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will have an EKG and either an ECHO or MUGA scan.

      Long Term Follow-Up:

      Every 6 months, you will come to the clinic to have an ECHO or MUGA scan. During these visits
      you will be asked how you are doing and if you have started any new drugs or treatment. If
      you cannot come to the clinic, you will be called by the study staff to answer these
      questions. Each call should last about 10 minutes.

      You will continue to have CT scans or MRIs every 8 weeks (+/- 14 days). If the disease
      appears to get worse, you will stop having these scans.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 17, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR) to Poziotinib in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Participants with EGFR Exon 20 Mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>ORR calculated as the percent of patients whose best confirmed response is complete response (CR, defined as disappearance of all target lesions) or partial response (PR, defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of longest diameter (LD) of target lesions taking as reference the baseline sum LD).
ORR assessed according to RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events of Poziotinib in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Participants with EGFR Exon 20 Mutations or HER2 Exon 20 Mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events assessed by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 4.03.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR) to Poziotinib in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Participants with HER2 (ErBB2) Exon 20 Mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>ORR calculated as the percent of patients whose best confirmed response is complete response (CR, defined as disappearance of all target lesions) or partial response (PR, defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of longest diameter (LD) of target lesions taking as reference the baseline sum LD).
ORR assessed according to RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate of Poziotinib in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Participants with EGFR Exon 20 Mutations</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after initiation of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Disease control rate defined as the percentage of patients have either a partial response (PR), a complete response (CR), or stable disease (SD) lasting at least 8 weeks after initiation of treatment.
Response assessed by RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate of Poziotinib in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Participants with HER2 exon 20 mutant NSCLC</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks after initiation of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Disease control rate defined as the percentage of patients have either a partial response (PR), a complete response (CR), or stable disease (SD) lasting at least 8 weeks after initiation of treatment.
Response assessed by RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasm of Respiratory and Intrathoracic Organ</condition>
  <condition>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Poziotinib - EGFR exon 20 mutant NSCLC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participant takes 2 Poziotinib tablets by mouth 1 time every day.
Each study cycle is 28 days.
Participant may continue taking the study drug for as long as the doctor thinks it is in their best interest.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Poziotinib - HER2 exon 20 mutant NSCLC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participant takes 2 Poziotinib tablets by mouth 1 time every day.
Each study cycle is 28 days.
Participant may continue taking the study drug for as long as the doctor thinks it is in their best interest.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Poziotinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Poziotinib given at a dose of 16 mg by mouth daily (two tablets of 8mg).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Poziotinib - EGFR exon 20 mutant NSCLC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Poziotinib - HER2 exon 20 mutant NSCLC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed recurrent non-small cell lung cancer not
             amenable to curative intent therapy or stage IV NSCLC

          2. Cohort 1 specific inclusion criteria: Documented EGFR exon 20 mutation by one of the
             following CLIA certified tests: OncoMine Comprehensive Assay (OCA), Guardant360 Assay
             (using plasma), or FoundationOne Assay or by an FDA approved device using cobas® EGFR
             mutation test v2 or therascreen EGFR RGQ PCt kit. Eligible mutations include
             A763_Y764insFQEA, D770_N771insSVD, D770_N771insNPG, V769_D770insASV, H773_V774insNPH,
             or any other exon 20 in-frame insertion or point mutation excluding T790M.

          3. Patients must be previously treated with one or more regimens of systemic therapy for
             locally advanced or metastatic disease. Previously untreated patients are eligible
             only if EGFR Exon 20 mutation is confirmed using an FDA approved device: cobas® EGFR
             Mutation Test v2 or therascreen® EGFR RGQ PCR Kit prior to study enrollment.

          4. Cohort 2 specific inclusion criteria: Documented HER2 exon 20 mutation by a CLIA
             certified laboratory. Eligible mutations include A775_G776insYVMA, G776_V777insVC, or
             P780_Y781insGSP, or any other in-frame exon 20 insertion mutation or point mutation
             including, but not limited to, L755S, G776V, and V777L.

          5. Measurable disease by RECIST 1.1.

          6. Age &gt;/= 18 years.

          7. ECOG performance status 0 or 1.

          8. Ability to take pills by mouth

          9. Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below: leukocytes &gt;/=
             3,000/mcL; absolute neutrophil count &gt;/= 1,500/mcL; platelets &gt;/= 100,000/mcL;
             hemoglobin &gt;/= 9.0 g/dL; total bilirubin &lt;/= 2 x upper limit of normal (ULN);
             AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT)/Alkaline phosphatase &lt;/= 2.5 institutional upper limit of normal
             of &lt;/= 5 x ULN if liver metastases are present; creatinine clearance &gt;/50 mL/min/1.73
             m^2 by Cockcroft-Gault equation (creatinine clearance = ([140-age] x body mass/(plasma
             creatinine x 72) x gender correction factor) or by 24-hours urine collection

         10. Brain metastases are allowed, as long as they are stable and do not require treatment
             with anticonvulsants or escalating doses of steroids.

         11. Females of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             and must agree to use adequate contraception for the duration of the study and six
             months after. Adequate contraception methods include: birth control pills (eg combined
             oral contraceptive pill), barrier protection (eg condom plus spermicide,
             cervical/vault or intrauterine device), and abstinence. Females of childbearing
             potential are defined as those who are not surgically sterile (ie, bilateral tubal
             ligation, bilateral oophorectomy, or complete hysterectomy) or postmenopausal (defined
             as 12 months with no menses without an alternative medical cause). Women will be
             considered post-menopausal if they have been amenorrheic for the past 12 months
             without an alternative medical cause. Inclusion Criterion cont'd in # 12.

         12. Continuation from inclusion criterion # 11: The following age-specific requirements
             must also apply: Women &lt; 50 years old: they would be considered post-menopausal if
             they have been amenorrheic for the past 12 months or more following cessation of
             exogenous hormonal treatments. The levels of Luteinizing Hormone (LH) and
             Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) must also be in the post-menopausal range (as per
             the institution). Women &gt;/= 50 years old: they would be considered post-menopausal if
             they have been amenorrheic for the past 12 months or more following cessation of all
             exogenous hormonal treatments, or have had radiation-induced oophorectomy with the
             last menses &gt; 1 year ago, or have had chemotherapy-induced menopause with &gt; 1 year
             interval since last menses, or have had surgical sterilization by either bilateral
             oophorectomy or hysterectomy.

         13. Non-sterilized males who are sexually active with a female partner of childbearing
             potential must use adequate contraception for the duration of the study and 90 days
             after the last dose of study medication. Adequate contraception methods include: birth
             control pills (eg combined oral contraceptive pill), barrier protection (eg condom
             plus spermicide, cervical/vault cap or intrauterine device), and abstinence.

         14. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. EGFR T790M mutation or any other acquired EGFR exon 20 mutation. Patients with
             coexisting primary EGFR exon 20 and T790M mutations are eligible.

          2. Have received or are receiving an investigational medicinal product (IMP) or other
             systemic anticancer treatment within 2 weeks prior to the first dose of study
             treatment.

          3. Any concurrent chemotherapy, immunotherapy, biologic, or hormonal therapy for cancer
             treatment.

          4. Have known or suspected brain metastases or spinal cord compression, unless the
             condition has been asymptomatic, has been treated with surgery and/or radiation, and
             has been stable without requiring escalating corticosteroids nor anti-convulsant
             medications for at least 4 weeks prior to the first dose of study medication.

          5. Known hypersensitivity to poziotinib or history of allergic reactions attributed to
             compounds of similar chemical or biologic composition to poziotinib.

          6. Cardiac conditions as follows: Patient has a history of congestive heart failure (CHF)
             Class III/IV according to the New York Heart Association (NYHA) Functional
             Classification or serious cardiac arrhythmias requiring treatment. Patient has a
             cardiac ejection fraction &lt;50% by either echocardiogram or multi-gated acquisition
             (MUGA) scan

          7. Have any unresolved chronic toxicity with CTCAE version 4.03 Grade &gt;/= 2, from
             previous anticancer therapy, except for alopecia.

          8. Patient is unable to take drugs orally due to disorders or diseases that may affect
             gastrointestinal function, such as inflammatory bowel diseases (eg, Crohn's disease,
             ulcerative colitis) or malabsorption syndrome, or procedures that may affect
             gastrointestinal function, such as gastrectomy, enterectomy, or colectomy.

          9. Have any condition or illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, might
             compromise patient safety or interfere with the evaluation of the safety of the drug

         10. Pregnant or breastfeeding women

         11. History of another primary malignancy within 2 years prior to starting study
             treatment, except for adequately treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin
             or cancer of the cervix in situ

         12. Recent major surgery within 4 weeks prior to starting study treatment, with the
             exception of surgical placement for vascular access

         13. Male or female patients of reproductive potential who are not employing an effective
             method of birth control. Adequate contraception methods include: birth control pills
             (eg combined oral contraceptive pill), barrier protection (eg condom plus spermicide
             cervical/vault cap or intrauterine device), and abstinence.

         14. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, uncompensated
             respiratory, cardiac, hepatic, or renal disease, active infection (including hepatitis
             B, hepatitis C, HIV, and active clinical tuberculosis), or renal transplant; ongoing
             or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
             cardiac arrhythmia, active peptic ulcer disease or gastritis, or psychiatric
             illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements.

         15. Active bleeding disorders.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Heymach, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Heymach, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-6363</phone>
    <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Research Operations</last_name>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malignant Neoplasm of Respiratory and Intrathoracic Organ</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>NSCLC</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced</keyword>
  <keyword>EGFR exon 20 mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>EGFR-positive</keyword>
  <keyword>Poziotinib</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

