<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03066336</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EC_LL_MYC_PS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03066336</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to See if Low Level Laser Light Can Help to Treat Toenail Fungus</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Evaluation of the Effect of the Erchonia LunulaLaser for the Treatment of Toenail Onychomycosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Erchonia Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Erchonia Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether low level laser therapy (LLLT) using the
      Erchonia LunulaLaser device is effective in clearing toenails with onychomycosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nail onychomycosis, or fungus infection, is typically caused by a fungus called
      dermatophytes, but may also be caused by yeasts and molds. These microscopic organisms invade
      the skin through tiny invisible cuts or through a small separation between the nail and the
      nail bed. Under conditions of warmth and moisture, the fungi grow and spread. The infection
      begins as a white or yellow spot under the tip of the nail, and as it spreads deeper into the
      nail, causes unsightly and potentially painful nail discoloration, thickening and the
      development of crumbling edges. Onychomycosis occurs more commonly in toenails than in
      fingernails because toenails are often confined in a dark, warm, moist environment inside
      shoes where fungi can thrive. Toenail fungus affects approximately 23 million people in the
      US - about 10% of all adults.

      Potential complications of onychomycosis include pain in the nails, permanent damage to the
      nails, development of other serious infections that can spread beyond the feet for
      individuals with a suppressed immune system due to medication, diabetes or other conditions,
      such as leukemia and AIDS.

      Nail fungus can be difficult to treat, and repeated infections are common. Currently
      available treatments for onychomycosis include oral antifungal medications, antifungal
      lacquer, and topical medications, surgical nail removal and photodynamic therapy. There is no
      perfect cure for toenail fungus. Even the most effective oral medications are successful only
      about half of the time, and topical medications are successful less than 10% of the time.
      Recently, research has found laser therapy to show promise as a novel alternative treatment
      for toenail onychomycosis. Unlike medication-driven treatments for toenail fungus which can
      have many side effects including serious ones such as liver toxicity, laser therapy presents
      minimal to no risk of side effects. Laser therapy is applied to toenail onychomycosis by
      shining a laser light through the toenail into the tissue below. The laser light vaporizes
      the fungus while leaving the skin and surrounding healthy tissue unharmed.

      Low level laser therapy operates under the principle of photochemistry with a photoacceptor
      molecule absorbing the emitted photons and inducing a biological cascade. Like our eukaryotic
      cell, fungi contain the highly complex organelle the mitochondria, which is responsible for
      the manufacturing of the energy molecule adenosine triphosphate (ATP). Within the inner
      mitochondrial membrane is cytochrome c oxidase, an identified photoacceptor molecule. It is
      believed that laser therapy could perhaps provide a means to photo-destroy the fungi
      responsible for onychomycosis (OM) by inducing the release of highly reactive superoxides.
      Moreover, laser therapy has been shown to promote superoxide dismutase (SOD), a process
      responsible for the destruction of foreign invaders. Extracellular release of low levels of
      mediators associated with SOD can increase the expression of chemokines, cytokines, and
      endothelial leukocyte adhesion molecules, amplifying the cascade that elicits the
      inflammatory response. The physiologic function of hydrogen peroxide, superoxide anion, and
      hydroxyl free radical is to destroy phagocytosed microbes. By enhancing the natural processes
      of the immune system and impacting the structural integrity of the fungi strain, it is
      believed that laser therapy may provide a means for clinicians to effectively treat OM
      without the onset of any adverse events.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent (%) of toenails attaining mycologic cure at study endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mycologic cure is defined as both negative Potassium Hydroxide (KOH) and negative Fungal Culture results, or two serial negative Fungal Culture results.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Onychomycosis of Toenail</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Erchonia LunulaLaser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Erchonia LunulaLaser emits both red light (635 nm) and blue light (405 nm) to the affected toenail for 12 minutes per treatment for 4 treatments, each treatment one week apart.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erchonia LunulaLaser</intervention_name>
    <description>Active Low Level Laser Light Therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erchonia LunulaLaser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Visual clinical presentation of onychomycosis in the target great toenail is distal
             subungual onychomycosis (DSO), visualized as a nail with normal surface texture and
             thickness but variable &quot;bays&quot; of white nail that extend from the distal nail tip
             proximally into the area of the nail bed

          -  Clinical involvement of onychomycosis in the target toenail is up to 60%

          -  Confirmation of the presence of fungal infection through a positive KOH stain finding
             and a positive fungal culture finding

          -  Identification through fungal culture of the growth of Trichophyton rubrum (T. rubrum)
             or other common dermatophyte or C. albicans or mixed dermatophyte/Candida infection.
             In the event of the KOH stain and the fungal culture provide conflicting results,
             i.e., one is positive and the other negative, resolution may be obtained by a second
             negative fungal culture finding from a nail clipping from the same nail

          -  Subject is willing and able to refrain from employing other (non-study) treatments
             (traditional or alternative) for his or her toenail onychomycosis throughout study
             participation.

          -  Subject is willing and able to refrain from the use of nail cosmetics such as clear
             and/or colored nail lacquers throughout study participation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Visual clinical presentations of onychomycosis in the target great toenail that are
             inconsistent with the clinical presentation of distal subungual onychomycosis (DSO),
             in whole or in part (i.e. indicative of mixed etiology); specifically proximal
             subungual onychomycosis (PSO); superficial white onychomycosis (SWO); complete
             dystrophy; other nail changes.

          -  Identification through fungal culture of the growth of a rare fungal species (i.e. not
             Trichophyton rubrum (T. rubrum) or other common dermatophyte or C. albicans or mixed
             dermatophyte/Candida infection) or non-fungal organisms such as mold or bacteria

          -  Less than 2mm clear (unaffected) nail plate length beyond the proximal fold

          -  Presence of dermatophytoma (thick masses of fungal hyphae and necrotic keratin between
             the nail plate and nail bed)

          -  Infection involving lunula e.g., genetic nail disorders, primentary disorders

          -  Severe plantar (moccasin) tinea pedis

          -  Psoriasis of the skin and/or nails, lichen planus, or other medical conditions known
             to induce nail changes

          -  Onychogryphosis

          -  Trauma from ill-fitting shoes, running, or overly-aggressive nail care

          -  Previous toenail surgery

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus

          -  Peripheral vascular disease

          -  Recurrent cellulitis

          -  Lymphatic insufficiency

          -  Immune compromise (whether due to underlying medical disorders or immuno-suppressive
             treatments)

          -  Other compromised states of health

          -  Known photosensitivity disorder

          -  Use of oral antifungal drugs in the prior 6 months

          -  Use of topical treatment of the skin or nails within the prior 2 months

          -  Any abnormality of the toenail that could prevent a normal appearing nail from
             occurring if clearing of infection is achieved.

          -  Current trauma, open wound on or about the treatment area

          -  Deformity of the target toe/toenail secondary to fungal infection/onychomycosis due to
             prior injury, surgical procedures or another medical condition

          -  Pregnant or planning pregnancy prior to the end of study participation

          -  Serious mental health illness such as dementia or schizophrenia; psychiatric
             hospitalization in the past two years

          -  Developmental disability or cognitive impairment that would preclude adequate
             comprehension of the informed consent form and/or ability to follow study subject
             requirements and/or record the necessary study measurements

          -  Involvement in litigation and/or receiving disability benefits related in any way to
             the parameters of the study

          -  Participation in a clinical study or other type of research in the past 30 days.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonella Tosti, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ted Rosen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>unaffilliated</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carol Kittles</last_name>
    <phone>305-243-8485</phone>
    <email>CKittles@med.miami.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Of Miami Department of Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33146</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonella Tosti, MD</last_name>
      <phone>305-243-8205</phone>
      <email>ATosti@med.miami.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Onychomycosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

