<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03064581</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSUFR01CA149324</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA149324</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03064581</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pap Test Intervention to Enhance Decision Making Among Pacific Islander Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pap Test Intervention to Enhance Decision Making Among Pacific Islander Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>California State University, Fullerton</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>California State University, Fullerton</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This community-based randomized trial tested the effects of a social support intervention to
      increase Chamorro, Samoan, and Tongan women's Pap test behavior and social support among
      their male spouses or significant others in Southern California.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this five-year community-based randomized trial was to: 1) examine the Pap
      test decision making process in Pacific Islander women; 2) assess the role of social support
      within the decision making process; and 3) develop and test an intervention to increase Pap
      testing among Pacific Islander women, and support among their male spouses/significant
      others. The intervention was created utilizing a Multi-Attribute Utility model and social
      support theory resulting in gender-specific educational workshops consisting of a social
      support intervention that informed both Pacific Islander women and men about cervical cancer
      and the importance of Pap testing for Pacific Islander women, and aimed to increase social
      support among their male spouses/significant others.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in receipt of a Pap test</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>One question regarding whether the woman received a Pap test, among those who had not received one within the past 3 years at baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knowledge of cervical cancer risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Six true/false questions regarding whether risk increases if woman has family history, smokes, has poor hygiene, spouse has many sex partners, had intercourse starting at early age, and has had more than one sex partner</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fatalistic attitudes towards cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Five agree/disagree questions regarding whether woman would undergo treatment if diagnosed with cervical cancer, would rather not know if she has cervical cancer, whether she believed there is not much she can do to prevent getting cervical cancer, whether cervical cancer is punishment from god, and whether she would feel less like a woman if she had cervical cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in perceived social support</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and 6-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Fifteen items from the RAND Medical Outcomes Study (MOS) social support survey that use a 4-point likert scale (none, some, a lot, all the time) regarding how much the woman can count on husband to: listen, provide info, give advice, can confide, advice is wanted, can share private worries, will give suggestions, is understanding, can help if bedridden, can take to doctor, can prepare meals, can help with daily chores, shows love, makes women feel wanted, and hugs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scheduled a Pap test</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 6 month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women who reported scheduling a Pap test, among women who had not received a Pap test within the past 3 years at baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1014</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Gender-specific culturally tailored social-support informed educational intervention session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care with delayed intervention at the end of study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The educational session consisted of a one-hour small group discussion (5-10 people). Gender-specific community health educators facilitated sessions for Pacific Islander women and for their spouses/significant others that included an educational video and other materials (brochure, calendar, and resource list). The video emphasized the importance of Pap testing for Pacific Islander women, and showed men supporting their women to get tested. Women's sessions provided basic information on cervical cancer and pap testing, and ended with verbal commitments and target screening dates by women to get screened. The men's education sessions contained similar information, with supplemental information on how to provide support for their wives to get tested and exercises on showing their support.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women ages 21 to 65

          -  Of Chamorro, Samoan, and/or Tongan ethnicity

          -  Has a significant other (married or in a long-term relationship for more than 5
             years).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not a member of one of the churches or clans visited for recruitment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sora Park Tanjasiri, DrPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>California State University, Fullerton</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lola Sablan-Santos</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Guam Communications Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>California State University, Fullerton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fullerton</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92831</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://wincart.fullerton.edu/cancer_edu/ToolkitSOW.htm</url>
    <description>The toolkit used to promote cervical cancer awareness, prevention, and screening among Chamorro, Samoan, and Tongan women and men.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cervical Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Pap Test</keyword>
  <keyword>Pacific Islander Americans</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>After completion of each data collection activity, all program project datasets will be de-identified and then made available for secondary analysis on the California State University, Fullerton, Health Promotion Research Institute website. A consultant, who is experienced in large multi-site controlled trials, will assist with the protocols (in years 2 and 3) required for dataset documentation and distribution. Researchers will be able to access the data, documentation, and surveys by registering on the website, obtaining approval from the Health Promotion Research Institute steering committee, and downloading the files. Care will be taken to ensure that respondents cannot be identified from the information in the public-use dataset. The final dataset will be stripped of identifiers (i.e., individual respondent identifying information, such as names and phone numbers, will be removed) prior to release for sharing.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

