<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03061019</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-1297</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03061019</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Two Oral Myofunctional Reeducation Methods for Children With Obstructive Sleep Apnea</brief_title>
  <acronym>PERSIST-B</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of Two Oral Myofunctional Reeducation Methods for Children With Obstructive Sleep Apnea Before Adenotonsillectomy : a Randomized Controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Université de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Justine's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Université de Montréal</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Myofunctional therapy has been shown to be effectively reduce symptoms of paediatric sleep
      apnea. As the effectiveness of reeducation relies on parental involvement and child's
      compliance, the investigator's research question was to evaluate two methods of myofunctional
      therapy (daily oral exercices versus a flexible oral appliance, both in combination with
      nasal hygiene), compared to nasal hygiene alone (control group).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Paediatric Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) is a multifactorial condition,
      associated with significant comorbidities, affecting cardiovascular health, cognitive
      development and quality of life. Its main cause is adenotonsillar hypertrophy, but some
      co-factors such as obesity, orofacial dysfunctions and craniofacial abnormalities contribute
      to the severity of symptoms or their persistance after adeno-tonsillectomy.

      Aim : Myofunctional therapy has been shown to reduce Apnea-Hyponea indexes (AHI) of children,
      and can serve as an adjunct to other therapies, but the level of compliance is a limiting
      factor. The investigator's aim is to evaluate two methods of oral reeducation in a group a
      children scheduled for adeno-tonsillectomy (in association with nasal hygiene) and to compare
      them with nasal hygiene alone (control group).

      Methods : The design of the study is a randomized Controlled Trial, enrolling 60 children
      with significant obstructive sleep apnea and divided into 3 groups : Group 1 following daily
      oral exercises (+nasal hygiene), Group 2 using of a flexible oral appliance during quiet
      activities and sleep (+nasal hygiene), and Group 3 using nasal hygiene alone (control group).
      The objective assessment of sleep parameters is performed at home using an ambulatory device
      (AHI, desaturation index, minimal oxygen saturation, flow limitation, snoring), before and
      after therapy, in a 3 months interval. An orthodontic and craniofacial assessment, the
      examination of orofacial functions and tongue/lip strength measurements (IOPI system), as
      well as quality of life questionnaires (OSA-18) are also performed on participants, before
      and after therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 7, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Parameters Changes : Apnea Hypopnea Index (AHI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Full Night Polygraph using an ambulatory device Type III (cardio-respiratory); measurement of the index of apnea and hypopnea/ in relation to total sleep time, according the American Association of Sleep Medicine (AASM) recommandations for children.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Parameters Changes : Oxygen desaturation index (ODI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Full Night Polygraph using an ambulatory device Type III (cardio-respiratory); measurement of the index of oxygen desaturation per hour/ in relation to total sleep time, according the American Association of Sleep Medicine (AASM) recommandations for children (oximetry).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep Parameters Changes : Flow Limitation index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Full Night Polygraph using an ambulatory device Type III (cardio-respiratory); measurement of flow limitations per hour , in relation to total sleep time, according the American Association of Sleep Medicine (AASM) recommandations for children (nasal canula or thermistance).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oral muscles strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lip and Tongue strength and endurance measurement with the IOPI measurement system: Measurement of Anterior and Posterior tongue elevation strength (kPa), Lip Seal strength (kPa)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nasal Resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Nasal resistance measurements with a anterior rhino-manometry : effective resistance left nostril (expiration, inspiration), effective resistance right nostril Pa/cm3/s during expiration, inspiration) ,total breath resistance (Pa/cm3/s during expiration, inspiration), vertex resistance right, vertex resistance left (Pa/cm3/s during inspiration, expiration).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>OSA 18 Questionnaire, consisting of a 18-items score and Visual Analog scale (from 0 to 10), filled by parents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Myofunctional Oral Exercices</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents and participants of this group will receive instructions for nasal and oral myo-functional exercises, to perform at home each day, for 5 to 10 minutes. A booklet (measure of adherence) and an Phone application for Android/Apple with descriptions/videos of those exercices will be given to them. These exercises will include nasal hygiene procedures, nasal cartilage exercices, lingual posture rehabilitation exercises, lip tone enhancement exercises, and swallowing rehabilitation exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Soft Oral Appliance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents and participants will be instructed in wearing the soft/flexible oral appliance and how to perform nasal hygiene in order to better tolerate the device. The oral appliance comes in several sizes, adapted to the age of the child; it is constructed in a soft elastomer material, in a position of slight propulsion and opening of the mandible to help clear the pharynx. It has a ramp to guide the tongue in a good position, a labial screen to stretch the labial strap and prevent the tongue from protruding between front teeth.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents and Participants of this group will be reminded the nasal hygiene procedures (application of saline in each nostril three times a day), and given a diary to report daily use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral Myofunctional Therapy with exercices</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral-Motor training of oral muscles (tongue, lips) associated with nasal hygiene with daily repetition of exercices and parental support.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Myofunctional Oral Exercices</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Oral reeducation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral Myofunctional Therapy with soft oral appliance</intervention_name>
    <description>Ora-Motor training of oral muscles (tongue, lips) associated with nasal hygiene, with reduced parental support.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Soft Oral Appliance</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Oral Trainer</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: participants must:

          -  present signs of obstructive sleep apnea: snoring, apnea / respiratory pauses audible
             by the entourage (objectivized by a score, to the hierarchical questionnaire of
             severity of Spruyt and Gozal, greater than or equal to 2,72- This questionnaire
             comprises six Questions and has a good sensitivity (60%) and specificity (82%) in
             screening for pediatric sleep apnea.

          -  be programmed for adenoidectomy, tonsillectomy or adeno-tonsillectomy within 3 months
             (or more).

        Exclusion Criteria: participants should not:

          -  present with a craniofacial syndrome nor a severe medical condition with complex
             medical management,

          -  present with an abnormality of the neuromuscular tone (such as Duchenne myopathy or
             cerebral palsy)

          -  receive orthodontic therapy during the study

          -  have a class III malocclusion (mandibular prognathy type), for which a propulsion oral
             appliance is contraindicated because it may aggravate mandibular prominence. Maxillary
             deficiency is not a exclusion criterion.

          -  A non-nutritive oral habit such as digital sucking (or pacifier) that persists because
             it interferes with oral reeducation, and is a contraindication to orthodontic
             treatments. Children who have recently stopped such a habit may be included in the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nelly Huynh, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Montréal, Montréal, Québec, Canada</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marie-Claude Quintal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hôpital Sainte-Justine, Montréal, QC, Canada</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Sainte Justine, Université de Montréal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Université de Montréal</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nelly Huynh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>child</keyword>
  <keyword>myofunctional therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>adenotonsillectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

