<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03066128</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00001466</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21AI124719</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03066128</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Point-of-care Viral Load Testing to Enable Streamlined Care and Task Shifting for Chronic HIV Care</brief_title>
  <acronym>STREAM</acronym>
  <official_title>Point-of-care Viral Load Testing to Enable Streamlined Care and Task Shifting for Chronic HIV Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Effective management of patients on antiretroviral therapy (ART) is essential to improve
      clinical outcomes and prevent HIV transmission, but monitoring life-long ART for over 15
      million HIV-infected people has become a challenge, particularly in low- and middle-income
      countries (LMICs). As programs continue to focus on identifying HIV-infected people and
      starting ART at higher CD4 thresholds, HIV providers have been overburdened, which has
      resulted in falling retention rates. As ART coverage scales up to include millions more
      people, additional strain will be placed on HIV clinicians and laboratories to manage stable
      patients on chronic ART. Implementing point-of-care HIV VL testing to enable task shifting to
      nurses for chronic HIV care may help mitigate these burdens. Point-of-care Viral Load (VL)
      testing is intended to differentiate patients who are potentially failing on their ART, so
      that they can be referred to the next level of care for possible ART regiment change, from
      patients who are virally suppressed on ART and can be managed by nurses. The investigator's
      scientific objective is to test the clinical equivalence and reduced cost of implementing a
      model for chronic HIV care that uses a point-of-care HIV VL assay to enable streamlined care
      and task shifting among healthcare workers at an urban clinic in South Africa. The central
      hypothesis is that rapid HIV VL testing, implemented by nurses, is an effective and
      cost-efficient strategy for management of chronic HIV infection in the majority of patients,
      thereby allowing more resources to be directed at the minority of patients who need greater
      attention. This work is innovative because it uses a randomized evaluation of an
      implementation model that combines a novel diagnostic point-of-care test with streamlined
      care and task shifting among healthcare workers compared to standard of care for chronic HIV
      care in a resource-limited setting. This randomized trial will then form the basis of a
      larger, multicountry proposal to demonstrate the clinical equivalence and cost-effectiveness
      of implementing an integrated point-of-care HIV VL testing and streamlined care model for
      chronic HIV care in LMICs. If nurses using clinic-based HIV VL testing are cost-effective for
      achieving both viral suppression and retention in care among patients on ART, then
      implementation of this chronic HIV care model would alleviate the strain on existing HIV
      providers and laboratories in LMICs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study design will be an open-label, randomized, non-inferiority implementation trial with
      2 study arms. Patients will be enrolled when due their 6 month VL since initiating ART.

      Standard of Care Arm:

      Participants in the Standard-of-Care (SOC) control arm will receive the standard-of-care for
      the clinic consisting of visits with a professional clinician (Physician or Professional
      Nurse) and once stable, community pharmacy ART collection through CCMDD. Viral load
      monitoring will be lab-based. Participants will be assessed for clinical symptoms/signs of
      tuberculosis, other opportunistic infections, and ART side effects at each clinical
      encounter. Participants who have a high lab-based HIV VL (≥1,000 copies/mL) will receive
      intensive adherence counseling and be asked to return to the clinic in 2 months for repeat
      HIV VL testing. If the HIV VL remains high (≥1,000 copies/mL) after the 2 months of intensive
      adherence counseling, then the patient will be switched to a second-line ART regimen by a
      physician.

      Intervention Arm:

      Participants in the Intervention Group will receive chronic ART management from a
      Professional Nurse and/or Enrolled Nurse every 2 months, and if stable after 6 months,
      community pharmacy ART collection through CCMDD. Viral load monitoring will be POC. Enrolled
      Nurse visits will consist of a clinical symptom and ART side effect checklists, and an ART
      adherence questionnaire, which trigger up-referral to a Professional Nurse/MO where
      appropriate. Point-of-care Xpert® HIV-1 VL testing will be performed while the participant is
      in the clinic to ensure that participants receive the VL results on the same day.
      Participants who have a high HIV VL (≥1,000 copies/mL) will be referred to a Professional
      Nurse. As with the standard-of-care arm, they will receive intensive adherence counseling and
      be asked to return to the clinic in 2 months for repeat point-of-care Xpert® HIV-1 VL
      testing. Participants who continue to have a high HIV VL (≥1,000 copies/mL) after 2 months of
      intensive adherence counseling will be switched to second-line ART by a physician.

      Participants will also be followed for a 12-month study period to assess the study outcome
      measures. This study will follow all aspects of South Africa's ART guidelines, except stable
      patients randomized to the intervention arm will receive Nurse-based care and Xpert® VL
      monitoring, as a comparison to the standard of care.

      At the end of the 12-month study period, all participants will have a repeat CD4 count and
      lab-based HIV VL testing by Roche Taqman v.2.0 assay. The lab-based HIV VL testing will be
      important to use the same HIV VL assay to compare the primary outcomes measures. In addition,
      the research team will evaluate the outcome of &quot;retention in care&quot;, which will be defined as
      collecting ART refills at the study exit visit.

      Cost-Effectiveness Component:

      The investigators will use an activity-based micro-costing approach, including time and
      motion studies, to estimate the costs incurred and averted, along with the primary study
      outcomes (viral suppression and retention in care) to estimate the cost per HIV-positive
      person virally suppressed and retained in care in the Intervention Group, as compared to the
      Standard-of-Care Group.

      Time and motion studies will determine the nurse time necessary to conduct the point-of-care
      HIV VL testing and the clinical visit with a stable HIV-infected patient. Time and motion
      studies will be conducted during study initiation and again when the intervention is running
      at full capacity. An experienced research assistant will collect data on the time required to
      complete each step of the chronic care visit (VL testing, clinical assessment, counseling)
      for both study arms. Initial results will be shared with the teams to implement strategies
      for improved efficiency. Observing multiple visits will allow estimation of the average time
      taken for each step; the time taken for research purposes (e.g. data collection) will be
      noted separately from the estimated time needed for monitoring. Multiple staff will be
      observed to capture the range of time required for a successful real-time chronic HIV care.
      Interviews with study staff will also quantify the effort required for each step of visit.
      Through time and motion studies the number of participants who could be supported by a clinic
      will be estimated. The staff time taken for the intervention captures the opportunity cost of
      the chronic care intervention, i.e. staff time that could be spent on a different program.
      The micro-costing data, time and motion studies, and clinical outcomes will be used to
      estimate the average cost per HIV-positive client achieving viral suppression and retained in
      care in the chronic care model compared to the standard of care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 24, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 27, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 27, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite measure of virological suppression and retention in care</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>HIV VL &lt;200 copies/mL at 12-month study visit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion retained in care</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients collecting ART at the 12-month study visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to detection</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 2 months within the 12-month follow up period</time_frame>
    <description>Time to detection of virological failure, subsequent intensive adherence counselling, and initiation of second line regimen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Entry into CCMDD</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 2 months between 6 and 12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients entered appropriately into CCMDD, and time to appropriate entry into CCMDD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average cost per HIV-positive client</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Average cost per HIV-positive client achieving viral suppression and retained in care</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of clinical visits</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Mean number of clinical visits per patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Loss to follow up or mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion lost to follow up or deceased</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CD4 count</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in CD4 count from enrolment to 12-month study exit visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion on same ART regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients collecting ART at the 12-month study visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">390</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic HIV Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the Intervention Group will receive chronic ART management from a Professional Nurse and/or Enrolled Nurse every 2 months, and if stable after 6 months, community pharmacy ART collection through CCMDD. Viral load monitoring will be by a point-of-care viral load testing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the Standard-of-Care control arm will receive the standard-of-care for the clinic consisting of visits with a professional clinician (Physician or Professional Nurse) and once stable, community pharmacy ART collection through CCMDD.Viral load monitoring will be by lab-based viral load testing</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Point-of-care viral load testing</intervention_name>
    <description>Point-of-care viral load testing will be performed while the participant is in the clinic to ensure that participants receive the viral load results on the same day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lab-based viral load testing</intervention_name>
    <description>Viral load testing will be lab based and follow standard of care procedures</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-infected and receiving antiretroviral therapy (ART)

          -  Receiving care at Prince Cyril Zulu Clinic in Durban

          -  Stable on Current ART Regimen and due the 6 month follow-up visit post ART initiation

          -  Willing/able to provide written informed consent to participate in the stud

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have significant signs/symptoms of illness that requires active medical care by a
             clinic doctor.

          -  Does not plan to receive HIV care at the Prince Cyril Zulu Communicable Diseases
             Clinic for the following 12 months.

          -  Currently pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Drain, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nigel Garrett, MBBS, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for the AIDS Programme of Research in South Africa (CAPRISA), University of KwaZulu-Natal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for the AIDS Programme of Research in South Africa (CAPRISA), University of KwaZulu-Natal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durban</city>
        <state>KwaZulu-Natal</state>
        <zip>4013</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul Drain</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Task shifting</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data for all outcome measures will be made available after study completion</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

