<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03069898</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-08-9047</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03069898</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TRUE Dads: Evaluation of an Intervention Focusing on Father Involvement, Co-parenting, and Employment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the TRUE Dads Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>It's My Community Initiative</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>It's My Community Initiative</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      With an emphasis on 12 3-hour group workshops, the TRUE Dads fatherhood intervention program
      focuses on establishing or strengthening three of men's key roles in the family: 1) their
      role as providers, through fostering employment and economic self-sufficiency, 2) their role
      as fathers, in building and maintaining positive engagement with their children, and 3) their
      role in having and keeping a positive relationship with their co-parenting partner (wife,
      intimate partner, or other co-parent). The study is a randomized clinical trial that compares
      participants in a program track with participants a study track (no treatment control group)
      over a one-year period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Interventions to strengthen men's roles as providers, as fathers, and as co-parents have
      typically been addressed in separate intervention and research silos. The TRUE Dads program
      proposes a unique integration of employment, fathering, and co-parenting services, with the
      overarching goal of strengthening fathers and the family unit by: 1) increasing fathers'
      economic stability and self-sufficiency, 2) enhancing the quantity and quality of father's
      engagement with their children, 3) improving the quality of the collaborative relationship
      between fathers and mothers or men and their co-parenting partners, 4) improving the
      relationship quality of fathers in their intimate partner relationships (with the co-parent
      or new partner), and 5) positively affecting children's behavior and development.

      Twelve hundred fathers will be recruited for the study. After an initial interview of the
      fathers and their co-parenting partners, who will complete Baseline survey, 720 of the 1,200
      fathers and co-parents will be assigned to the TRUE Dads intervention (Program track), and
      480 to a no-treatment control condition (Study track). Participants will be informed that the
      program consists of participation in a series of 12 three-hour meetings. Those 12 sessions
      include six meetings covering a core fatherhood curriculum, attended with the co-parent,
      combined with one of three intensives selected by the father: a) six sessions with an
      emphasis on employment, b) six sessions with an emphasis on building healthy romantic
      relationships with the co-parent, or c) six sessions with an emphasis on parenting with a
      participating co-parent. Participants in the Program track may be referred for additional
      employment, mental health, or other needed services. Both program and control participants
      (fathers and co-parents) will fill out a Follow-up survey one year from their entrances into
      the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Paraticipants are randomly assigned to intervention (TRUE Dads) and Control tracks, assessed at Baseline and again one year later. The intervention primarily involves attendance at 12 3-hour workshops for fathers and their co-parents.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Father involvement</measure>
    <time_frame>Change or maintenance of positive behavior relative to the control group will be assessed at Baseline and 1 year post Baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by a composite of self-report survey items filled out by both fathers and co-parents, assessing fathers' involvement in childcare tasks, time spent in specific activities with target child, parenting styles, and parenting behaviors.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Father/Co-parent relationship quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Change or maintenance of positive behavior relative to the control group will be assessed at Baseline and 1 year post Baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by a composite of self-report survey items filled out by fathers and co-parents, assessing perceptions of co-parent relationship quality, communication and conflict management abilities, and relationship stability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Economic Self-sufficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Change or maintenance of positive behavior relative to the control group will be assessed at Baseline and 1 year post Baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by a composite of self-report survey items filled out by fathers and co-parents, assessing employment status, income, behaviors to find a job or acquire new job skills.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child well-being</measure>
    <time_frame>Change or maintenance of positive behavior relative to the control group will be assessed at Baseline and 1 year post Baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by a composite of self-report survey items filled out by fathers and co-parents, assessing child temperament, externalizing behavior problems (aggression, hyperactivity) and internalizing behavior problems (anxiety, depression, shy/withdrawn behavior).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Individual physical and mental health</measure>
    <time_frame>Change or maintenance of positive behavior relative to the control group will be assessed at Baseline and 1 year post Baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by a composite of self-report survey items filled out by fathers and co-parents, assessing health behaviors, anxiety, and depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2400</enrollment>
  <condition>Father-Child Relations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TRUE Dads program track</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the TRUE Dads program, fathers and co-parents begin with a Core workshop meeting weekly for 6 weeks. After a check-in, a male-female group leader team focuses on a single topic that represents one of the three main goals of the project as a whole: Co-parenting relationships, Parenting, or Employment and financial stability. From 10 to 18 couples, seated at small tables in a large room, hear mini-lectures, watch videos, and engage in interactive exercises. Fathers then choose to attend one of three intensive workshops focused on couple relationships OR parenting OR economic self-sufficiency meeting 3 hours per week for the next 6 weeks. On an as-needed basis, fathers may be referred for employment programs and fathers and co-parents may be referred for mental health or other services.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control condition study track</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants (fathers and co-parents) complete intake interview and fill out Baseline survey. They fill out follow-up survey one year later</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TRUE Dads</intervention_name>
    <description>The TRUE Dads intervention consists of a set of 12 3-hour workshops that focus on enhancing fathers' role as co-parent, parent, and provider</description>
    <arm_group_label>TRUE Dads program track</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        This study begins with a focus on fathers. We are initially recruiting men who:

          -  Are 18 or older

          -  Are residing in Oklahoma County/Metro

          -  Are expecting a child or already have a child age (0-12), with an emphasis on 0-6,

          -  Have spent time with the child the prior month (or with mother if expecting)

          -  Are English-speaking. Have not previously participated in the Family Expectations
             program offered by Public Strategies (Oklahoma) in the last 3 years

        Exclusion criteria:

        Because this an intervention for fathers that attempts to improve the relationship with the
        fathers' co-parent, we are accepting fathers only if the co-parent agrees to attend at
        least the first 6 workshops. In pilot trials, almost all the co-parents are women (wives,
        intimate partners, grandmothers), but a few are men (the fathers' father, brother, intimate
        partner)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Either or both partners have taken part in the Family Expectations project during the
             past three years, located in the same building, run by Public Strategies
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>The primary focus of the study is on fatherhood, so the entrance to the study begins with fathers. But each father must bring the primary person with whom he is co-parenting his child -- wife, romantic partner, friend, mother. Usually the co-parent is a woman, but occasionally a man (father's father, intimate partner).</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philip A. Cowan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>It's My Community Initiative</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Philip A. Cowan, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>510-526-2586</phone>
    <email>pcowan@berkeley.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carolyn P. Cowan, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>510-914-8336</phone>
    <email>ccowan@berkeley.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>It's My Community Initiative</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc L. Taylor</last_name>
      <phone>405-418-3863</phone>
      <email>marc.taylor@TRUEdads.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Patrick Marc-Charles</last_name>
      <phone>405-418-3921</phone>
      <email>Patrick Marc-Charles &lt;Patrick.Marc-Charles@TrueDads.com&gt;</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>It's My Community Initiative</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Philip A. Cowan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Psychology Emeritus, University of California, Berkeley</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Marital relationship</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

