<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03067220</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ConnollyHB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03067220</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can A Virtual Clinic Review Replace A Surgical Clinic Visit After Discharge?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can A Virtual Clinic Review Replace A Surgical Clinic Visit After Discharge?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Connolly Hospital Blanchardstown</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Connolly Hospital Blanchardstown</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess if a virtual out patient clinic via a telephone review was an acceptable and safe
      alternative to a clinic attendance for a broad range of general surgical patients discharged
      following a hospital admission.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The surgical out patients is often the first point of contact between a surgeon and patient
      after being referred by their general practitioner (GP). Here new patients are assessed,
      investigations are requested and treatment plans devised. On completion of treatment it has
      been common practice to review all patients post operatively (1). However the routine review
      of patients following low risk procedures contribute to increasing healthcare costs without
      necessarily a significant benefit for the patient. It may indeed be a burden on patients and
      families, who may miss work or college, have to travel long distances and wait for prolonged
      periods to be seen. There is also a financial burden associated with travel to appointments
      and on-site parking fees. Unnecessary appointments also contribute to increased waiting times
      for new referrals to be seen. This has the potential to lead to delayed diagnosis of serious
      conditions (2) and further increase the workload of overburdened emergency departments.

      Previous studies have demonstrated a safe and acceptable alternative to traditional
      outpatient appointments with telephone follow up in certain paediatric and adult surgical
      patients (1,3,4). Improved efficiency and high levels of patient satisfaction have also been
      demonstrated in an Irish setting with the establishment of a virtual outpatient department
      (VOPD) following endoscopy (5). In an oncology setting telephone follow up has also been
      identified as an effective means of delivering care (6,7). In particular nurse led follow up
      of lung, breast and colorectal cancer patients has been associated with a high level of
      patient satisfaction (8).

      The aim of this study was to determine whether a virtual out patient clinic via a telephone
      review was an acceptable and safe alternative to a clinic attendance for a broad range of
      general surgical patients discharged following a hospital admission.

      If eligible for inclusion the patient was approached prior to discharge and the study
      rationale, randomisation and methods of follow up were explained. If they agreed to
      participate written consent was obtained and an information leaflet about the study was
      provided. Randomisation was performed by selecting an unmarked white envelope which contained
      either a coloured card indicating a telephone call follow up within 6-8 weeks or a white card
      indicating follow up with an outpatient appointment at 6-8 weeks.

      After randomisation the patient was provided with a letter detailing their specific follow up
      arrangements and a contact number was provided if they had any further questions after
      discharge. Patients' were sent a further letter by administration staff after discharge, with
      the specific date of either the clinic appointment or phone follow up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome was the rate of complications or on going issues requiring further assessment in either group.</measure>
    <time_frame>At each patients review appointment approximately 6 weeks after discharge.</time_frame>
    <description>Any unexpected outcome reported by the patient if contacted by telephone or reported and assessed by a doctor on their review at a standard clinic appointment. This would be expected to be an issue resulting in a deviation from a normal and expected post discharge recovery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcomes included a &quot;did not respond&quot; (DNR) or did not attend (DNA) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At each patients review appointment approximately 6 weeks after discharge.</time_frame>
    <description>If an attempt to contact the patient by telephone to conduct their review appointment is unsuccessful this will be recorded as a did not respond. A DNA will be recorded if a patient fails to attend for their scheduled review appointment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients listed for further procedures, investigation or referral to other specialities based on their review.</measure>
    <time_frame>At each patients review appointment approximately 6 weeks after discharge.</time_frame>
    <description>If the patient is not discharged from follow up by the hospital service to the care of their general practitioner, these are the anticipated outcomes of the follow up review for each patient not discharged</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction and opinions regarding their follow up arrangements</measure>
    <time_frame>6-8 weeks after their review appointment</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire that allows participants to provide free text responses about their experience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">209</enrollment>
  <condition>Outpatients General Surgery Virtual Clinic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard outpatient clinic appointment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be sent an appointment letter to return to a scheduled outpatient clinic for review approximately 6 weeks after their discharge from hospital</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual out patient clinic appointment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be sent an appointment letter stating a specific day approximately 6 weeks after their discharge from hospital in which they will be contacted by telephone for a review by a junior doctor from the discharging team.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual outpatient clinic appointment</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be sent an appointment letter stating a specific day approximately 6 weeks after their discharge from hospital in which they will be contacted by telephone for a review by a junior doctor from the discharging team.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual out patient clinic appointment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard outpatient clinic appointment</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be sent an appointment letter to return to a scheduled outpatient clinic for review approximately 6 weeks after their discharge from hospital</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard outpatient clinic appointment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Over 16 years old

          -  Could provide written consent

          -  Comprised one of four categories based on reason for admission

               -  Category 1 - minor surgery

               -  Category 2- elective or emergency surgery such as appendicectomy, hernia repair,
                  thyroidectomy

               -  Category 3- admitted for investigation or management of conditions such as non
                  specific abdominal pain, head injury, cellulitis

               -  Category 4- attended for surveillance endoscopy for conditions such as colonic
                  polys or Barrett's oesophagus

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Declined to participate

          -  Had a previous, new or suspected diagnosis of malignancy

          -  On-going issues requiring follow up such as wound healing problems

          -  Required further investigation such as endoscopy after admission with e.g.
             diverticulitis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Walsh, MD MCh FCRSI</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of General Surgery, Connolly Hospital and Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Connolly Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dublin</city>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ireland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>McVay MR, Kelley KR, Mathews DL, Jackson RJ, Kokoska ER, Smith SD. Postoperative follow-up: is a phone call enough? J Pediatr Surg. 2008 Jan;43(1):83-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2007.09.025.</citation>
    <PMID>18206461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allgar VL, Neal RD. Delays in the diagnosis of six cancers: analysis of data from the National Survey of NHS Patients: Cancer. Br J Cancer. 2005 Jun 6;92(11):1959-70.</citation>
    <PMID>15870714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gray RT, Sut MK, Badger SA, Harvey CF. Post-operative telephone review is cost-effective and acceptable to patients. Ulster Med J. 2010 May;79(2):76-9.</citation>
    <PMID>21116423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosbe KW, Jones D, Jalisi S, Bray MA. Efficacy of postoperative follow-up telephone calls for patients who underwent adenotonsillectomy. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2000 Jun;126(6):718-21; discussion 722.</citation>
    <PMID>10864107</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ryan EM, Rogers AC, Hanly AM, McCawley N, Deasy J, McNamara DA. A virtual outpatient department provides a satisfactory patient experience following endoscopy. Int J Colorectal Dis. 2014 Mar;29(3):359-64. doi: 10.1007/s00384-013-1801-y. Epub 2013 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24309978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sardell S, Sharpe G, Ashley S, Guerrero D, Brada M. Evaluation of a nurse-led telephone clinic in the follow-up of patients with malignant glioma. Clin Oncol (R Coll Radiol). 2000;12(1):36-41.</citation>
    <PMID>10749018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Booker J, Eardley A, Cowan R, Logue J, Wylie J, Caress AL. Telephone first post-intervention follow-up for men who have had radical radiotherapy to the prostate: evaluation of a novel service delivery approach. Eur J Oncol Nurs. 2004 Dec;8(4):325-33.</citation>
    <PMID>15550362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beaver K, Williamson S, Chalmers K. Telephone follow-up after treatment for breast cancer: views and experiences of patients and specialist breast care nurses. J Clin Nurs. 2010 Oct;19(19-20):2916-24. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2702.2010.03197.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20649914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Connolly Hospital Blanchardstown</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul Healy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Surgical Registrar</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>outpatients</keyword>
  <keyword>general surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>virtual clinic</keyword>
  <keyword>patient satisfaction</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

