<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03066531</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MOTIVOB-ACTonFOODsection</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03066531</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MOTIVOB-(Acceptance and Commitment Therapy Group Intervention for Obesity)Section</brief_title>
  <acronym>MOTIVOB-ACT</acronym>
  <official_title>Acting Flexible, Acting Resistant: the Upsides of an ACT Choice. A Randomized Comparison of Acceptance and Commitment Therapy Group Intervention and Cognitive Behavioral Therapy Group for the Treatment of Obese Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituto Auxologico Italiano</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Auxologico Italiano</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the present study is to compare an Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT)
      group intervention and a Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) group in a sample of obese
      individuals with respect to mid-term outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Effective weight-management programs often include a combination of physical activity, diet,
      and psychological intervention, in particular Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT). The effects
      of these programs are frequently not stable, and usually the maintenance of achieved
      weight-loss lasts only for a short period of time. Acceptance and Commitment Therapy, ACT,
      keeps on gaining recognition in obesity treatment. The purpose of the study is to compare
      weight loss and indicator of psychological functioning in a population of obese subjects
      belonging to three different diagnostic categories: without ED, with ED NAS and with BED.
      Participants were exposed respectively to a CBT or an ACT treatment and were assessed three
      times: pre intervention, post intervention and follow-up. The investigators hypothesize that
      CBT and ACT are both effective in the post-intervention. ACT intervention should be more
      effective in the follow-up both for weight and psychological functioning, due to its focus on
      the flexible managing of the global context instead of the focus on the pathology itself,
      more typical in standard CBT treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CORE-OM</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Post-Treatment (one month in-patient rehabilitation intervention) - FollowUp at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in the score of CORE-OM measured in three time points, before treatment (baseline), post treatment (after one month in-patient rehabilitation program) and at 6 months Follow-Up. CORE-OM (Italian version by Palmieri et al., 2009) is a self-report measure designed for use as a baseline and outcome measure in psychological therapies and after its conclusion. It assesses the subjective experience of a person, as well as the way he or she functions in the world. It is composed by 34 items on a 5-points likert-scale from 0 (never) to 4 (always). Low scores correspond to high wellbeing. The CORE-OM provided 5 scales: wellness, symptoms, functioning, risk and total. The investigator involved in administering and interpreting the CORE-OM were blinded to treatment assignment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AAQ-II</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Post-Treatment (one month in-patient rehabilitation intervention) - FollowUp at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in the score of AAQ-II measured in three time points, before treatment (baseline), post treatment (after one month in-patient rehabilitation program) and at 6 months Follow-Up.The Acceptance and Action Questionnaire (AAQ; Hayes et al., 2004) is the most widely used measure of experiential avoidance and psychological inflexibility. We used the 7-item Italian (7-points likert-scale from 0-never true to 7-always true) version of AAQ-II (Pennato, Berrocal, Bernini &amp; Rivas, 2013) that shows adequate indexes of validity and reliability with a single-factor structure. In the case of AAQ-II higher scores indicate greater psychological flexibility.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Post-Treatment (one month in-patient rehabilitation intervention) - FollowUp at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in the weight, expressed in kilograms, measured in three time points, before treatment (baseline), post treatment (after one month in-patient rehabilitation program) and at 6 months Follow-Up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">156</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACT-based intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The ACT-based intervention integrates educational topics on heart healthy behaviours with mindfulness and acceptance training regarding difficult thoughts and feelings, clarification of health-related values and commitment to behave in the valued direction while contacting difficult experiences.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-based intervention included in Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>These programs are based on current guidelines for the long- term multi-disciplinary rehabilitation and prevention of obese patients, including Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT), in a group setting, as Gold Standard.
Assigned Interventions: Behavioral: usual care (CBT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACT-based intervention</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ACT-based intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CBT-based intervention</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>CBT-based intervention included in Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. between the ages of 18 and 70 years

          2. obesity according to the WHO criteria (BMI ≥ 30)

          3. fluency in spoken and written Italian language

          4. expression of written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. other severe psychiatric disturbance different form eating disorders diagnosed by
             DSM-5 criteria (SCID-Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV-TR Disorders I and II
             and DSM 5 manual, administered by an independent clinical psychologist, were used as
             screening tools for psychiatric disorders)

          2. concurrent severe medical condition not related to obesity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baer RA, Smith GT, Hopkins J, Krietemeyer J, Toney L. Using self-report assessment methods to explore facets of mindfulness. Assessment. 2006 Mar;13(1):27-45.</citation>
    <PMID>16443717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juarascio AS, Forman EM, Herbert JD. Acceptance and commitment therapy versus cognitive therapy for the treatment of comorbid eating pathology. Behav Modif. 2010 Mar;34(2):175-90. doi: 10.1177/0145445510363472.</citation>
    <PMID>20308357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cattivelli R, Pietrabissa G, Ceccarini M, Spatola CA, Villa V, Caretti A, Gatti A, Manzoni GM, Castelnuovo G. ACTonFOOD: opportunities of ACT to address food addiction. Front Psychol. 2015 Apr 9;6:396. doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2015.00396. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25914662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Istituto Auxologico Italiano</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gianluca Castelnuovo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>prof.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ACT</keyword>
  <keyword>CBT obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Eating disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Health psychology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

