<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03067922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TataMC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03067922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Postmastectomy Pain Syndrome in an Indian Cancer Hospital</brief_title>
  <official_title>Post Mastectomy Pain Syndrome at an Indian Tertiary Cancer Centre: Incidence, Pain Severity, Impact on Daily Function and Quality of Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tata Memorial Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tata Memorial Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer is the most common cancer in women in India and accounts for 27% of all cancers
      in women. Incidence rises in early thirties, peaks at 50-64 years. Approximately 48% are
      below 50 years of age. Most present when symptoms develop, so are 2B and beyond. Treatment
      depends on the stage of the disease. Surgical removal of the tumour is part of the treatment
      attempting a cure.

      Simple mastectomy involves removal of breast tissue without axillary lymph node dissection or
      removal of chest wall muscles. Radical mastectomy involves removal of the entire breast,
      skin, pectoralis major and minor muscles and ipsilateral axillary lymph nodes. Modified
      radical mastectomy involves removal of the breast and ipsilateral axillary lymph nodes. The
      pectoralis muscle is preserved. Breast conserving surgery involves removal of tumour with or
      without axillary dissection. The extent of surgery tells us about the nerve damage, local
      tissue handling. For example operating in upper and outer quadrant of breast and axilla
      increases nerve handling in that particular region. Local radiation also plays a role.

      Persistent pain after mastectomy was first reported in the 1970s by Wood and defined by
      International Association for Study of Pain (IASP) as pain in the anterior aspect of the
      thorax, axilla, and/or upper half of the arm beginning after mastectomy or quadrantectomy and
      persisting for more than three months after surgery and known as Postmastectomy pain Syndrome
      (PMPS). It is a common problem, with a 25- 60% incidence. The pain is described as burning or
      tenderness with paroxysms of lancinating, shock-like pain, and also described by some as
      dysesthesia (perception of non noxious stimuli as painful). Risk factors for PMPS include
      age, raised Body mass index (BMI), severity of postoperative pain, type of surgery,
      susceptibility to pain with a history of other pains such as headache and dysmenorrhoea.
      Axillary hematoma and postoperative radiotherapy have also been implicated in the development
      of PMPS.

      Tata Memorial Hospital, is a tertiary cancer institute in India. Around 4000 patients with
      suspected breast cancers register annually at the hospital and approximately 2800 breast
      cancer surgeries are performed yearly. Very few studies on PMPS in Indian population exist.
      We therefore plan to identify the incidence of PMPS in our patients and also the severity of
      pain along with its impact on daily function and quality of life
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tata Memorial Hospital, a 629 bed tertiary cancer institute conducts approximately 6000
      surgeries per year. Approximately 4000 (4239 in 2015) patients with suspected breast cancers
      register annually at the hospital and around 2800 breast cancer surgeries are performed every
      year. Very few studies on PMPS in Indian population exist. The investigators therefore, aim
      to identify the incidence of post mastectomy pain syndrome PMPS) in this population. The
      investigators also aim to identify the severity of postmastectomy pain along with its impact
      on daily function and quality of life.

      STUDY DESIGN:

      Prospective study over 12 months with follow up until 6th month from enrollment with interim
      analysis in the month of November for presentation of the CoPI's thesis.

      MATERIALS &amp; METHODS:

      Prospective study over a period of 12 months from commencement of study after Institutional
      ethics committee approval, at Tata Memorial hospital and ACTREC. Female patients scheduled
      for undergoing surgery for breast cancer conservative and radical and willing to participate
      will be enrolled in the study after obtaining a written informed consent. Pain scores will be
      assessed using Numerical rating scale [with pain score 1-3 mild, 4 to 6 moderate and 7 and
      above severe]. History of predisposition to recurrent headaches and dysmenorrhea will be
      noted. Details of disease stage, chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy will also be documented
      from the Electronic medical records. Analgesia will be managed by the primary surgical team
      as is currently being done. The analgesia administered to the patient will also be recorded.
      participants noted to have moderate to severe pain despite analgesics prescribed by the
      surgical team will be referred to the acute pain service (APS) for further management.

      Postoperative pain severity both the average &amp; worst pain will be recorded at discharge from
      hospital, 1st, 4th and 6th month after the surgery. The Details of postoperative pain
      analgesic use and effect on daily function will be documented with the help of postal cards
      with questionaires in envelop addressed to the investigators. Study will emphasize on the
      type, severity, the site of pain whether, lateral or anterior chest wall, axilla, ipsilateral
      medial upper arm or back, the type of pain (burning, tingling, shooting, stabbing etc) and
      effects on daily function and quality of life. Details of postoperative hematoma, infection,
      local recurrence will also be recorded from the history, electronic medical records and
      documents of participants. Details of postoperative chemotherapy and radiation will also be
      obtained from patient's notes and the electronic medical record All participants will be
      administered the short form of the Brief Pain inventory [BPI], EORTC QLQ 30, preoperatively,
      at 1 month, 4 months &amp; 6 months after surgery.

      The Brief pain inventory {BPI} (obtained with permission from MD Anderson), which assesses
      the severity of pain and impact of pain on daily functions will be administered to the
      participant in the language familiar to them, preoperatively, at 1 month, 4th and 6th month
      postoperatively. The short form comprises of nine questions related to the severity of pain,
      impact of pain on daily function, location of pain, pain medications and amount of pain
      relief in the past 24 hours or the past week.It has been widely used and validated in several
      languages the world over.

      EORTC QLQ [Quality of life Questionaries ] is an integrated system for assessing quality of
      life [health related ]. This self administered questionnaires incorporates five functional
      scales, physical [PF], role [RF], cognitive [CF], emotional [ef], and social; three symptoms
      scale for fatigue, pain and nausea/vomiting; a global health quality of life scale and
      several single items for financial impact and additional symptoms like diarrhea, appetite
      loss, sleep disturbance. This would help identify the quality of life of the participants and
      its affection.

      If a participant cannot follow up at the said intervals, the pain scores would be obtained
      telephonically and the BPI, EORTC QLQ 30 form in prepaid envelopes would be given to them at
      discharge which they would have to duly fill in and post them to the given address at the
      appropriate intervals. If the next follow up to the hospital coincides with the 4th or 6th
      postoperative month, the participant will visit the pain clinic for an assessment and
      completing the BPI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 6, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 6, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 6, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>6 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Post mastectomy pain syndrome (PMPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>presence of pain around the mastectomy site and ipsilateral arm after the mastectomy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pain severity</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>How severe the pain is after mastectomy from the Pain intensity obtained from the Brief Pain inventory questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pain severity</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>How severe the pain is after mastectomy from the pain intensity obtained from the Brief Pain inventory questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pain severity</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>How severe the pain is after mastectomy from the pain intensity obtained from the Brief Pain inventory questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on daily function</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>How the pain after mastectomy per se affects day to day functioning of the patient and how the quality of her life is affected. The impact of pain on daily life will be identified from the Brief Pain inventory questionnaire which the patient would have to complete at this time point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of the mastectomy on Quality of life of the patient would be assessed from the EORTC-QLQ 30 questionnaire completed by the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on daily function</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>How the pain per se affects day to day functioning of the patient.The impact of pain on daily life will be identified from the Brief Pain inventory questionnaire which the patient would have to complete at this time point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of the mastectomy on the quality of life of the patient would be assessed from the EORTC-QLQ 30 questionnaire completed by the patient at his time point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on daily function</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>How the pain per se affects day to day functioning of the patient .The impact of pain on daily life will be identified from the Brief Pain inventory questionnaire which the patient would have to complete at this time point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>the impact of teh mastectomy on the quality of life of the patient would be assessed from the EORTC-QLQ 30 questionnaire completed by the patient at this time point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Mastectomy</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non interventional study</intervention_name>
    <description>Not applicable. No intervention will be done. it is an observational study assessing pain after mastectomy and the quality of life as assessed from validated questionnaires given to the patients at regular intervals</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Female patients scheduled for undergoing surgery for breast cancer conservative and radical
        and willing to participate will be enrolled in the study after obtaining a written informed
        consent
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female patient undergoing mastectomy simple radical with or without axilla dissection

          -  Literate and can read and write in either English, Hindi, Marathi

          -  Willing to fill forms and post them and/or answer questions on phone

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Refusal of consent

          -  Patient who has previously undergone major surgery around breast and chest wall

          -  Benign breast pathology

          -  Patient's with impaired cognitive function

          -  Emergency surgery

          -  PECs block study (PECTORALIS BLOCK)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>APARNA S CHATTERJEE, MD,FCARCSI</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tata Memorial Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tata Memorial Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mumbai</city>
        <state>Maharashtra</state>
        <zip>400012</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Smith WC, Bourne D, Squair J, Phillips DO, Chambers WA. A retrospective cohort study of post mastectomy pain syndrome. Pain. 1999 Oct;83(1):91-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10506676</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Couceiro TC, Menezes TC, Valênça MM. Post-mastectomy pain syndrome: the magnitude of the problem. Rev Bras Anestesiol. 2009 May-Jun;59(3):358-65. Review. English, Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>19488550</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mejdahl MK, Andersen KG, Gärtner R, Kroman N, Kehlet H. Persistent pain and sensory disturbances after treatment for breast cancer: six year nationwide follow-up study. BMJ. 2013 Apr 11;346:f1865. doi: 10.1136/bmj.f1865.</citation>
    <PMID>23580693</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bray F, Ren JS, Masuyer E, Ferlay J. Global estimates of cancer prevalence for 27 sites in the adult population in 2008. Int J Cancer. 2013 Mar 1;132(5):1133-45. doi: 10.1002/ijc.27711. Epub 2012 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22752881</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wood KM. Intercostobrachial nerve entrapment syndrome. South Med J. 1978 Jun;71(6):662-3.</citation>
    <PMID>663696</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gärtner R, Jensen MB, Nielsen J, Ewertz M, Kroman N, Kehlet H. Prevalence of and factors associated with persistent pain following breast cancer surgery. JAMA. 2009 Nov 11;302(18):1985-92. doi: 10.1001/jama.2009.1568. Erratum in: JAMA. 2012 Nov 21;308(19):1973.</citation>
    <PMID>19903919</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Andersen KG, Kehlet H. Persistent pain after breast cancer treatment: a critical review of risk factors and strategies for prevention. J Pain. 2011 Jul;12(7):725-46. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2010.12.005. Epub 2011 Mar 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21435953</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Miguel R, Kuhn AM, Shons AR, Dyches P, Ebert MD, Peltz ES, Nguyen K, Cox CE. The effect of sentinel node selective axillary lymphadenectomy on the incidence of postmastectomy pain syndrome. Cancer Control. 2001 Sep-Oct;8(5):427-30.</citation>
    <PMID>11579339</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Steegers MA, Wolters B, Evers AW, Strobbe L, Wilder-Smith OH. Effect of axillary lymph node dissection on prevalence and intensity of chronic and phantom pain after breast cancer surgery. J Pain. 2008 Sep;9(9):813-22. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2008.04.001. Epub 2008 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18585963</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Glechner A, Wöckel A, Gartlehner G, Thaler K, Strobelberger M, Griebler U, Kreienberg R. Sentinel lymph node dissection only versus complete axillary lymph node dissection in early invasive breast cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur J Cancer. 2013 Mar;49(4):812-25. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2012.09.010. Epub 2012 Oct 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23084155</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 10, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tata Memorial Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Aparna Chatterjee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mastectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Severity</keyword>
  <keyword>Life quality</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Somatoform Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

