<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02208726</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KaronWillson200731900</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>AEC44-01-2013</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02208726</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Picricum Acidum and Phosphoricum Acidum Homaccord on Perceived Levels of Anxiety in University Students</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Picricum Acidum and Phosphoricum Acidum Homaccord on Perceived Levels of Anxiety in University Students</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Johannesburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Johannesburg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Increased levels of stress and anxiety are experienced by many students. Stress can have a
      negative influence on academic outcome and performance, as well as on the student's mental
      health. Conventional treatment options for anxiety include counseling, as well as anxiolytics
      and antidepressants, which may have various adverse effects. Picricum acidum and Phosphoricum
      acidum are homeopathic remedies that may be helpful in alleviating anxiety in students;
      however there has been no research done to date to show their efficacy for this condition.

      The aim of this study is to determine the effect of Picricum acidum and Phosphoricum acidum
      Homaccord on perceived levels of anxiety in university students, by means of the
      State-Trait-Anxiety-Inventory and Anxiety Symptom Score Card.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study, conducted over a
      two-week period at the University of Johannesburg (UJ) Health Clinic, Doornfontein Campus.
      Thirty university students, aged between 18 and 45 years, will be recruited into the study by
      means of advertisements placed on the campus with relevant permission given. Participants
      will attend an initial consultation and will be requested to sign a Participant Information
      and Consent form, complete the Participant Information Sheet, and a Remedy Symptom
      Questionnaire to determine inclusion into the study. Participants' vital signs will be
      measured. Participants will then receive a 16ml vial of either the Picricum acidum and
      Phosphoricum acidum Homaccord pillules, or a placebo (unmedicated sucrose pillules), which
      will be randomized and dispensed by the UJ Homeopathic Dispenser. Participants will be
      requested to take 5 pillules in a daily dose for 14 days, commencing 21 days before and
      ceasing 7 days prior to the start of examinations. The State-Trait-Anxiety-Inventory (STAI)
      and the Anxiety Symptom Score Card will be completed 21 days prior to the first academic
      examination, as well as on the last day of taking the medication. Data will be collected and
      analyzed by Statkon, using the Shapiro-Wilk test, the Mann-Whitney test and the Wilcoxon
      signed ranks test.

      The outcome of this research may show that the Homeopathic Picricum acidum and Phosphoricum
      acidum Homaccord has a positive effect in alleviating anxiety in university students,
      allowing for further studies in the field.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>State-Trait-Anxiety-Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>The State-Trait-Anxiety-Inventory is an established, acceptably reliable, validated and commonly utilized tool for measuring an individual's level of anxiety.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety Symptom Score Card</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Anxiety Symptom Score Card is based on a 5-point grading scale and is designed to monitor anxiety-related symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sucrose pillules</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Unmedicated sucrose pillules will be taken once daily, in the morning, 30 minutes after breakfast, for 14 days, up to 7 days before the first academic examination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Homeopathic homaccord</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sucrose pillules medicated with Picricum acidum and Phosphoricum acidum in potencies of 6CH, 30CH and 200CH. Pillules will be taken once daily, in the morning, 30 minutes after breakfast, for 14 days, up to 7 days before the first academic examination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sucrose pillules</intervention_name>
    <description>Unmedicated sucrose pillules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sucrose pillules</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Saccharum officinale</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Homeopathic homaccord</intervention_name>
    <description>Sucrose pillules medicated with Picricum acidum and Phosphoricum acidum in potencies of 6CH, 30CH and 200CH.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Homeopathic homaccord</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Picricum acidum and Phosphoricum acidum homaccord</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, between the ages of 18 and 45;

          -  Registered University students;

          -  Participants must experience anxiety symptoms, manifesting six or more of the
             following criteria: muscle tension, increased perspiration, rapid heartbeat,
             headaches, stomach aches, agitation, irritability, hostility, fear, extreme
             sensitivity to rejection or failure, motor restlessness, procrastination, excessive
             worry, concentration difficulties, attention difficulties and memory problems;

          -  Participants must be writing a major examination one week after the study ends;

          -  Participants must have six or more of the symptoms relating to Picricum acidum and
             Phosphoricum acidum (Appendix D); and

          -  Participants must have a cell phone and on-line computer access.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Have been diagnosed with: A psychological anxiety disorder, Psychiatric disorders
        (Bipolar disorder, Depression), Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder and Epilepsy.

          -  Are taking any chronic medication for anxiety or mood stabilizing

          -  Are pregnant or lactating
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janice Pellow, M.Tech Hom</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Johannesburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Johannesburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Johannesburg</city>
        <state>Gauteng</state>
        <zip>2028</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 17, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Johannesburg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr J. Pellow</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>students</keyword>
  <keyword>examinations</keyword>
  <keyword>Homeopathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

