<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02200445</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-P00009599</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015P000016</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02200445</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low Dose IL-2 for Ulcerative Colitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Low Dose Subcutaneous Interleukin-2 (IL-2) For The Treatment of Ulcerative Colitis.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Scott Snapper</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety and maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of
      Interleukin-2 in subjects with moderate-to-severe ulcerative colitis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Interleukin-2 (IL-2) is a T cell growth factor. IL-2 is currently licensed for the treatment
      of metastatic renal cell carcinoma and metastatic melanoma, where it promotes the expansion
      of anti-cancer cytotoxic T cells and natural killer (NK) cells. However at low doses
      (100-times lower than those used in cancer therapy), IL-2 promotes the selective expansion of
      regulatory T cells (Tregs): an immune modulating subset of CD4+ lymphocytes.

      A recent phase 1 clinical trial from our collaborators at the Dana Farber Cancer Institute
      showed that low-dose IL-2 selectively expands Tregs in patients with treatment-resistant
      Graft vs. Host Disease (GvHD), and that low-dose IL-2 is safe in this condition. A detailed
      immunological analysis of samples from this study showed that low-dose IL-2 treatment was
      associated with increased Treg proliferation, increased de novo thymic generation of Tregs,
      and a resolution of defects in intracellular signalling and apoptosis seen in Tregs in
      chronic GvHD. A recent phase 1 study from another group showed that low-dose IL-2 is safe in
      the treatment of HCV-associated vasculitis. Low-dose IL-2 has also been shown to be
      well-tolerated in subjects with HIV.

      Ulcerative colitis (UC) is a chronic inflammatory disease of the colon. Evidence from
      pre-clinical models of intestinal inflammation, and also from patients with monogenetic
      defects in Treg function, suggests that Tregs play a role in the prevention of inflammation
      in the intestine.

      The treatment (or intervention) in this study is a once-daily, subcutaneous injection of
      IL-2, for a total of 8 weeks. The first 2 doses of the study drug will be administered by
      research nurses at Boston Children's Hospital. Further doses will be self-administered, at
      home. Training will be provided for correct self-administration.

      This is a 3+3 dose escalation study of IL-2 in moderate-to-severe UC. This study design is
      powered to identify the MTD of low-dose IL-2 in UC. Once the MTD is identified, a further 10
      subjects will receive IL-2 at that dose. Recruitment of between 2 and 28 patients is planned.

      Dose levels are based on the experience of our collaborators in GvHD. In addition to
      determining the MTD, this study will determine if low-dose IL-2 is safe and well-tolerated in
      patients with moderate-to-severe ulcerative colitis. A detailed immunological analysis of
      samples obtained from this study will determine if low-dose IL-2 expands Tregs in vivo, in
      patients with moderate-to-severe UC. Immunological changes will then be correlated with
      clinical response.

      The study will take place at Boston Children's Hospital. The study will involve 10 study
      visits. Most of the study visits involve blood tests. A flexible sigmoidoscopy or colonoscopy
      will be performed as part of the screening process. A flexible sigmoidoscopy will also be
      performed on completion of therapy, to determine clinical response.

      The first two subjects to receive the study drug will be admitted overnight following the
      first dose. Subsequent doses will be administered on an out-patient basis. All other subjects
      will receive IL-2 on an out-patient basis.

      Responders (with an acceptable side-effect profile) will be allowed to continue the study
      drug for at least 1 year. Compensation will be provided for participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with serious and non-serious adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Enumeration of the serious and non-serious adverse events seen in the study. Enumeration of any dose limiting toxicity seen in the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Identification of the dose cohort at which the MTD occurs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical efficacy.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a composite endpoint.
The Mayo score, a validated disease activity score, will be used to categorize subjects into three groups, based on their response to treatment. Category definitions are as follows:
Clinical Response: Subjects with a decrease from baseline in the total Mayo score of at least 3 points and at least 30%, with an accompanying decrease in the rectal bleeding sub-score of at least 1 point or an absolute rectal bleeding sub-score of 0 or 1.
Clinical Remission: Subjects with a total Mayo score of 2 points or lower, with no individual sub-score exceeding 1 point.
No Response: Subjects who do not meet the criteria described above.
The number of subjects who achieve endoscopic healing of their colonic mucosa will also be enumerated. Category definitions are as follows:
Mucosal Healing Present: An absolute Mayo endoscopy subscore of 0 or 1.
Mucosal Healing Absent: Subjects who do not meet the definition of mucosal healing described above.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological response.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Enumeration of the number of subjects with a change in the absolute number of immune cells in the peripheral blood and lamina propria of subjects during the 8 weeks of treatment, and during the 4 weeks following cessation of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interleukin-2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study drug: Interleukin-2 (aldesleukin, Proleukin, IL-2).
Each subject will receive an 8-week course of once-daily, subcutaneously administered IL-2. There will be three dose cohorts. Each subject will be recruited into a single dose cohort and receive a single dose level of IL-2 throughout the study.
The dose levels will be as follows:
Cohort 1: 0.3x10^6 IU/m^2/day.
Cohort 2: 1.0x10^6 IU/m^2/day.
Cohort 3: 1.5x10^6 IU/m^2/day.
Up to 6 subjects will be recruited to each dose cohort.
Once the maximum tolerated dose has been identified, a further 10 subjects will receive IL-2 at the maximum tolerated dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interleukin-2 (aldesleukin).</intervention_name>
    <description>Description of intervention is covered in &quot;Arm&quot;, above.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interleukin-2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Proleukin.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-70 years.

          -  A diagnosis of UC made by standard clinical, radiological, endoscopic and histological
             criteria.

          -  Moderate to severe UC with a Mayo score of 6-12.

          -  Failure to tolerate or failure to respond to at least one conventional therapy with
             the intention of inducing or maintaining remission (examples include oral
             corticosteroids, oral 5-aminosalicylates, azathioprine and/or 6-mercaptopurine, or a
             tumor necrosis factor (TNF) antagonist). Corticosteroid dependency (inability to taper
             oral corticosteroids without a recurrence of disease activity) is also included in
             this category.

          -  Stable doses of concomitant medications.

          -  A negative pregnancy test in the 2 weeks prior to anticipated commencement of the
             study drug, in female subjects of child-bearing age. Men and women of reproductive
             potential must agree to use an acceptable method of birth control during treatment and
             for six months after completion of treatment.

          -  Ability to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of Crohn's disease or Inflammatory Bowel Disease - Unspecified (IBD-U, a
             diagnostic classification formerly termed &quot;indeterminate colitis&quot;).

          -  Requirement for immediate surgical, endoscopic or radiological intervention for toxic
             megacolon, massive hemorrhage, perforation, sepsis, or intra-abdominal or perianal
             abscess.

          -  Ileostomy, proctocolectomy or subtotal colectomy with ileorectal anastomosis.

          -  History of colorectal cancer or dysplasia.

          -  Positive stool test for Clostridium difficile.

          -  Current medically significant infection.

          -  Significant laboratory abnormalities, including;

               1. Hb &lt; 8.0 g/dL, WBC &lt; 2.5 x 103/mm3, Plt &lt; 100 x 103/mm3.

               2. Creatinine ≥ 1.5x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN).

               3. Total bilirubin &gt; 2.0 mg/dL, ALT &gt; 2x institutional ULN, GGT &gt; 2x institutional
                  ULN. Elevated unconjugated bilirubin related to Gilbert's syndrome is allowed.

               4. Abnormal thyroid function tests.

          -  Positive serology for HIV, hepatitis B virus (HBV) or HCV.

          -  Positive screening test for tuberculosis (TB).

          -  First dose of an anti-TNF medication within 4 weeks of anticipated study commencement,
             or a subsequent dose within 2 weeks of commencement; or ciclosporin or tacrolimus
             within 2 weeks of anticipated study commencement.

          -  Received another investigational new drug (IND) within 5 half-lives of that agent
             before the planned commencement of SC IL-2.

          -  Malignancy within the last 5 years.

          -  Allergy to any component of the study drug.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women.

          -  Inability to comply with the study protocol or inability to give informed consent.

          -  Prior exposure to IL-2.

          -  Uncontrolled cardiac angina or symptomatic congestive cardiac failure (NYHA Class III
             or IV).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott B Snapper, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jessica R Allegretti, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maddie Carrellas</last_name>
    <phone>617-732-9173</phone>
    <email>mcarrellas@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alexandra B Griffith</last_name>
    <phone>617-919-4592</phone>
    <email>alexandra.griffith@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anastasia Nelina</last_name>
      <phone>617-919-4592</phone>
      <email>anastasia.nelina@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alexandra Griffith</last_name>
      <phone>617-919-4592</phone>
      <email>alexandra.griffith@childrens.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Athos Bousvaros, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham &amp; Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Madeline Carrellas, BS</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-9223</phone>
      <email>mcarrellas@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ami Merker, BS</last_name>
      <email>amerker@partners.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua Korzenik, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jessica Allegretti, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matt Hamilton, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koreth J, Matsuoka K, Kim HT, McDonough SM, Bindra B, Alyea EP 3rd, Armand P, Cutler C, Ho VT, Treister NS, Bienfang DC, Prasad S, Tzachanis D, Joyce RM, Avigan DE, Antin JH, Ritz J, Soiffer RJ. Interleukin-2 and regulatory T cells in graft-versus-host disease. N Engl J Med. 2011 Dec 1;365(22):2055-66. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1108188.</citation>
    <PMID>22129252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matsuoka K, Koreth J, Kim HT, Bascug G, McDonough S, Kawano Y, Murase K, Cutler C, Ho VT, Alyea EP, Armand P, Blazar BR, Antin JH, Soiffer RJ, Ritz J. Low-dose interleukin-2 therapy restores regulatory T cell homeostasis in patients with chronic graft-versus-host disease. Sci Transl Med. 2013 Apr 3;5(179):179ra43. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3005265.</citation>
    <PMID>23552371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saadoun D, Rosenzwajg M, Joly F, Six A, Carrat F, Thibault V, Sene D, Cacoub P, Klatzmann D. Regulatory T-cell responses to low-dose interleukin-2 in HCV-induced vasculitis. N Engl J Med. 2011 Dec 1;365(22):2067-77. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1105143. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2014 Feb 20;370(8):786.</citation>
    <PMID>22129253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schroeder KW, Tremaine WJ, Ilstrup DM. Coated oral 5-aminosalicylic acid therapy for mildly to moderately active ulcerative colitis. A randomized study. N Engl J Med. 1987 Dec 24;317(26):1625-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3317057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rutgeerts P, Sandborn WJ, Feagan BG, Reinisch W, Olson A, Johanns J, Travers S, Rachmilewitz D, Hanauer SB, Lichtenstein GR, de Villiers WJ, Present D, Sands BE, Colombel JF. Infliximab for induction and maintenance therapy for ulcerative colitis. N Engl J Med. 2005 Dec 8;353(23):2462-76. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2006 May 18;354(20):2200.</citation>
    <PMID>16339095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 25, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Scott Snapper</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ulcerative colitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory bowel disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin-2</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-2</keyword>
  <keyword>Regulatory T Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Tregs</keyword>
  <keyword>T-Lymphocytes, Regulatory</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

