<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02200913</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WYodchaisarn</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02200913</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Core Stabilization Exercise on Balance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Core Stabilization Exercise on Balance in Low Back Pain Patients With Clinical Lumbar Instability</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Khon Kaen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Khon Kaen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent studies indicate that patients with chronic low back pain (LBP) present problems in
      balance. Alterations in proprioception are the possible causes of alteration of postural
      balance in LBP.

      Previous studies reported an improvement of CSE on joint mobility, pain, functional
      disability, and trunk muscle activation pattern in patients with clinical lumbar instability
      (CLI); however, it was an immediate effect. However, previous studies did not report indirect
      effect may occur in CLI as postural balance and other kinds of exercise as strengthening in
      CLI. The general trunk strengthening exercise is common used in physical therapy clinic on
      LBP, that improve pain, physical disability, and trunk muscles activity. To our knowledge,
      the usefulness of CSE has not yet been investigated in CLI patients with outcome measure of
      balance.

      The present study will conduct to fill the gaps of previous studies which will provide
      immediate-, accumulative- and detraining-effects of CSE on postural balance, pain intensity
      and ratio activation of trunk muscles and included blinding process of the assessor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Low back pain (LBP) is the most common musculoskeletal complaint. In most LBPs, it is benign
      and disappears within six weeks, but approximately 20% of individuals with LBP do not show
      any improvement in their condition, which may progress to chronic low back pain. LBP not only
      interferes with biomechanical change, but also causes ability to work leading to reduced
      productivity, economic burden to individuals and society for medical costs Recent studies
      indicate that patients with chronic low back pain present diminished postural control,
      manifesting problems in balance. Postural balance is controlled by sensory information,
      central processing and neuromuscular responses. Alterations in proprioception are the
      possible causes of alteration of postural balance in individuals with low back pain.

      For clinical studies using core stabilization exercise (CSE) as treatment have revealed
      conflicting findings on pain, functional disability and muscle responses in chronic LBP. The
      few studies that investigated CSE as an isolated factor. Kumar (2011) reported an improvement
      of CSE on joint mobility and pain pressure threshold in patients with clinical lumbar
      instability; however, it was an immediate effect of CSE and blinding process was not
      performed. However, an effectiveness of CSE on pain intensity, functional disability, and
      trunk muscle activation pattern were improved in clinical lumbar instability (CLI). In
      addition, after 10-week CSE provides greater training and retention effects on pain-related
      outcomes and induced activation of deep abdominal muscles in CLI compared with conventional
      treatment (stretching exercise and hot pack). However, previous studies did not report
      indirect effect may occur in CLI as postural balance and other kinds of exercise as
      strengthening in CLI. The general trunk strengthening exercise is common used in physical
      therapy clinic on LBP, that improve pain, physical disability, and trunk muscles activity. To
      our knowledge, the usefulness of CSE technique as abdominal drawing-in maneuver (ADIM) has
      not yet been investigated in CLI patients with outcome measure of balance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>center of pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3-months after the last intervention session</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Lumbar Spine Instability</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>core stabilization exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>core stabilization exercise 2 times/week 10 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>general trunk strengthening exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>general trunk strengthening exercise, 2 times/week, 10 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>core stabilization exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>core stabilization exercise, 2 times/week, 10 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>general trunk strengthening exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>general trunk strengthening exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>general trunk strengthening exercise, 2 times/week, 10 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>core stabilization exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  male or female

          -  aged between 20-60 years

          -  low back pain (LBP) with or without radiating leg pain for period of at least 12 weeks

          -  answer 'yes' at least seven items of questionnaire

          -  present positive sign of the aberrant movement sign

          -  Present at least one positive sign from painful catch , prone instability catch test,
             or apprehension symptom

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Be pregnant.

          -  Have serious spinal pathology: spinal fracture, spinal malignancy or spinal infection

          -  Have quada equina syndrome

          -  Have neurological deficit (at least 2 of the following signs: weakness of lower limbs
             (muscle power &lt; grade 3 using manual muscle test), reflex changes, or abnormality or
             loss of sensation of lower limbs associated with the spinal nerve root

          -  Have obvious abnormal movement of the lumbar motion segment when assessed by
             flexion-extension radiographs: sagittal plane translation larger than 4.5mm or 15
             percent of vertebral body width according to other vertebral segment, or sagittal
             plane rotation larger than 15 degrees at L1-L2, L2-L3 or L3-L4, 20 degrees at L4-L5 or
             25 degrees at L5-S1

          -  Have visual disorder, vestibular disorder, neuromuscular diseases such as
             polyneuropathy, or diabetes neuropathy

          -  Participate in their intervention less than 5 out of the 10 week of intervention.

          -  Regularly treat with core stabilization exercise (CSE), or trunk strengthen exercises.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wantanee Yodchaisarn, M.Sc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Research Center in Back, Neck, Other Joint Pain and Human Performance, Khon Kaen University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wantanee Yodchaisarn, M.Sc.</last_name>
    <phone>+66874948991</phone>
    <email>ywantane@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Center in Back, Neck, Other Joint Pain and Human Performance</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muang</city>
        <state>Khon Kaen</state>
        <zip>40000</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wantanee Yodchaisarn, M.Sc.</last_name>
      <phone>+66874948991</phone>
      <email>ywantane@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wantanee Yodchaisarn, M.Sc.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Puntumetakul R, Areeudomwong P, Emasithi A, Yamauchi J. Effect of 10-week core stabilization exercise training and detraining on pain-related outcomes in patients with clinical lumbar instability. Patient Prefer Adherence. 2013 Nov 19;7:1189-99. doi: 10.2147/PPA.S50436. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24399870</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 25, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Khon Kaen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wantanee Yodchaisarn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Center in Back, Neck, Other Joint Pain and Human Performance</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

