<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01450891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-3-038</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>02N-101</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01450891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Health Technology Assessment of Diagnostic Approaches in Alzheimer's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Novel Diagnostic Approaches for the Diagnosis of Alzheimer's Disease: Technology Assessment and Clinical Effectiveness</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Center for Translational Molecular Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Leiden University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VU University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: New research criteria for the diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease (AD) have recently
      been developed to enable an early diagnosis of AD pathophysiology by relying on emerging
      biomarkers. To enable efficient allocation of health care resources, evidence is needed to
      support decision makers on the adoption of emerging biomarkers in clinical practice. The
      research goals are to 1) assess the diagnostic test accuracy (of current clinical diagnostic
      work-up and emerging biomarkers in Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI), Positron Emission
      Tomography (PET) and Cerebrospinal Fluid (CSF), 2) perform a cost-consequence analysis and 3)
      assess long-term cost-effectiveness by an economic model.

      Methods/design: In a cohort design 304 consecutive patients suspected of having a primary
      neurodegenerative disease are approached in four academic memory clinics and followed for two
      years. Clinical data and data on quality of life data, costs and emerging biomarkers are
      gathered.

      Diagnostic test accuracy is determined by relating the clinical practice and new research
      criteria diagnoses to the reference diagnosis. The clinical practice diagnosis at baseline is
      reflected by a consensus procedure among experts using clinical information only (no
      biomarkers). The diagnosis based on the new research criteria is reflected by decision rules
      that combine clinical and biomarker information. The reference diagnosis is determined by a
      consensus procedure among experts based on clinical information on the course of symptoms
      over a two-year time period.

      A decision analytic model is build combining available evidence from different resources
      among which (accuracy) results from the study, literature and expert opinion to assess
      long-term cost-effectiveness of the emerging biomarkers.

      Discussion: Several other multi-centre trials study the relative value of new biomarkers for
      early evaluation of AD and related disorders. The uniqueness of this study is the assessment
      of resource utilization and quality of life to enable an economic evaluation. The study
      results are generalizable to a population of patients who are referred to a memory clinic due
      to their memory problems.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic accuracy of Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic test accuracy (in terms of sensitivity and specificity) of three MRI markers (Whole brain and hippocampal volume, white matter integrity, and functional connectivity) is determined by relating the particular marker to a reference diagnosis. The reference diagnosis is determined by a consensus procedure among experts based on clinical information on the course of symptoms over a two-year time period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognition at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Mini-mental state examination (MMSE).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in dementia severity at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the clinical dementia rating (CDR) scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months follow up, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Euro-Qol-5D both by the patient and caregiver and measured by the Quality of life Alzheimer's disease state (QoL-AD) both by the patient and caregiver.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health care resource use during 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months follow up, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>By means of questionnaires the health care resource usage is measured by the Resource Utilization in Dementia-questionnaire (RUD-lite) over a period of 2 years using 4 measurement moments to interpolate the data.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in productivity at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months follow up, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Work status, income, and productivity losses of both the patient and caregiver are assessed by the adjusted PRODISQ (PROductivity and DISease Questionnaire). The consequences of informal caregiving on paid or unpaid work are assessed by the Health and Labour Questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic accuracy of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic test accuracy (in terms of sensitivity and specificity) of three CSF markers (CSF total tau, CSF phosphorylated tau, and CSF Aβ1-42) is determined by relating the particular marker to a reference diagnosis. The reference diagnosis is determined by a consensus procedure among experts based on clinical information on the course of symptoms over a two-year time period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic changes at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Course of cognitive symptoms, Civil status, and Living situation are assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>General clinical changes at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Smoking behaviour, alcohol intake, length, weight, blood pressure, neuropsychological problems, and co-morbidities are assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in behavioural and psychological problems at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in basic and instrumental activities in daily activities at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Disability assessment for Dementia (DAD).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depression at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the geriatric depression scale 15 (GDS-15).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive functioning at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>A neuropsychological examination is performed using the:
Rey's Verbal Learning Test, Visual Association Test, and Digit-Span to assess memory;
Letter Digit Substitution Test to assess mental processing rate; and
Stroop Color-Word Test and Trail Making Test to assess attention, concentration and interference.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sense of competence at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Sense of Competence Questionnaire (SoCQ).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Care-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months follow up, 1 year follow up, 2 year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by the CarerQol by the informal caregiver.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">304</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurodegenerative Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Memory Disturbances</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>total patient group</arm_group_label>
    <description>all new consecutive patients of the participating memory clinics who are suspected of having a primary neurodegenerative disease, meaning that all patients with subjective as well as objective memory complaints are included</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Cerebrospinal fluid
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        304 consecutive patients, of four academic memory clinics specialized in the diagnosis and
        treatment of memory disorders, who were suspected of having a primary neurodegenerative
        disease were approached for participating in the study. This included all patients with
        subjective and/or objective memory complaints. Eligibility criteria were chosen to
        represent current clinical situation and enable generalisability to clinical practice.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All new consecutive patients of the participating memory clinics who are suspected of
             having a primary neurodegenerative disease. This means all patients with subjective
             and/or objective memory complaints.

          -  CDR 0, 0.5 or 1

          -  MMSE score must be 20 or higher.

          -  Availability of a reliable informer or proxy (who visits or contacts the patient at
             least once a week).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Normal Pressure Hydrocephalus (NPH)

          -  Huntington's disease

          -  Recent Transient Ischaemic Attack (TIA) (&lt;2 years) or Cerebral Vascular Accident (CVA)
             or TIA/CVA followed by cognitive impairment (within 3 months)

          -  History of Schizophrenia, other psychotic disorders (&lt; 12 months)

          -  Major depression (&lt; 12 months)

          -  Alcohol abuse

          -  Brain-tumor, epilepsy, encephalitis

          -  Absence of a reliable informant

          -  Probably not available for follow-up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VU University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1100 DD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leiden University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <zip>2333 ZA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <zip>6200 MD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboud University Nijmegen Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6500 HC</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ctmm.nl</url>
    <description>organizational framework for the study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Handels RL, Aalten P, Wolfs CA, OldeRikkert M, Scheltens P, Visser PJ, Joore MA, Severens JL, Verhey FR. Diagnostic and economic evaluation of new biomarkers for Alzheimer's disease: the research protocol of a prospective cohort study. BMC Neurol. 2012 Aug 10;12:72.</citation>
    <PMID>22883691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 20, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Costs</keyword>
  <keyword>Benefits</keyword>
  <keyword>subjective and/or objective memory complaints</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurodegenerative Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

