<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01457326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>34409</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01457326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Standardized Weight Bearing Utilizing Immersion Therapy Following Periarticular Lower Extremity Fractures</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Standardized Weight Bearing Utilizing Immersion Therapy Following Periarticular Lower Extremity Fractures: Clinical and Radiographic Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this prospective study is evaluate the effect of a standardized early weight
      bearing physical therapy protocol that utilizes immersion therapy on the clinical outcomes of
      lower extremity periarticular fractures. The investigators null hypothesis is that the early
      weight bearing protocol will have the same effect as a traditional 10-week non-weight bearing
      protocol on clinical outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fractures of the lower extremity are common injuries that can lead to temporary or permanent
      disability.13 Fracture healing, regardless of treatment, is a multifactorial process that is
      influenced by time, biomechanics, and host biology (among other variables). The degree,
      timing, progression, and type of weight bearing after fractures involving the pelvis and
      lower extremities is an area of debate in the clinical management of a broad spectrum of
      orthopedic injuries.1,2,4-9,11,15 Periarticular fractures of weight bearing joints are an
      area of particular interest with regard to post-operative weight bearing due to the prolonged
      periods that patients must be non-weight bearing after surgery.

      Some degree of impairment is inevitable with any traumatic injury. The majority of authors
      writing about post-fracture weight bearing have determined that timing and extent of weight
      bearing has an effect on fracture healing, while a small number of authors have published
      results demonstrating the opposite.14,16,19,21 In addition to potential impacts on healing
      rates, limited or non-weight bearing carries the added insult of loss of bone density and
      muscle mass.3,10,12,17,20,22

      Traditionally, patients with periarticular fractures have been required to be non-weight
      bearing on their effected extremity for up to 12 weeks. At this institution, most patients
      have been required to remain non-weight bearing for 10 weeks, followed by progressively
      increased levels of weight bearing according to patient tolerance. One of the orthopaedic
      traumatologists at this institution uses immersion therapy to allow patients with
      periarticular fractures to begin weight bearing prior to the ten-week mark.

      Immersion therapy requires that patients perform their physical therapy, with a trained
      therapist, in a swimming pool. The use of the pool in post-fracture care may be able to
      provide a structured and standardized partial weight-bearing environment that could allow for
      early mobilization. It also has the potential to improve clinical outcomes by mitigating at
      least some of the loss in bone and muscle mass during the post-operative period; thereby,
      potentially speeding functional recovery. Immersion therapy is currently utilized on-site at
      the University of Utah Orthopedic Center for a variety of diagnoses, including in
      post-fracture care.

      There is essentially no orthopedic literature regarding immersion therapy in the management
      of post-fracture rehabilitation with regard to early weight bearing. Specifically, the
      investigators are aware of no clinical outcome studies that investigate standardized early
      weight bearing protocols following periarticular fractures of the lower extremity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Loss to follow-up rate too high for publication and data on completed patients does not allow
    for a powered analysis.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immersion Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Standard ROM while in the hospital
two weeks of immersion therapy, patients perform their physical therapy immersed in the pool to their neck (5-10% total body weight).
weeks 6-8, patients are immersed to their mid-chest (nipple level- 15-30% total body weight).
weeks 8-10, patients are progressed to physical therapy while immersed only to their waist (navel level- 50-60% total body weight).
ten weeks, patients are allowed to weight bear as tolerated and begin formal dry land ambulation training under the supervision of a licensed physical therapist .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Traditional non-weightbearing</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ROM therapy initiated in the hospital.
Passive Motion therapy for 4 weeks.
Formal physical therapy continued as needed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Musculoskeletal Function Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Time to return to work. Assessed at each clinical visit, and by mailings if necessary.
Standard radiographs will be obtained from the study patients per usual at post-operative visits. Any loss of fixation will be assessed. No additional radiographs will be obtained outside of the current standard of care.
Adverse events will be tabulated.
The short Musculoskeletal Function Assessment (SMFA) will be administered at patient's 3 month, 6 month and 1 year follow-up clinic appointments and/or by mail, as necessary.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">122</enrollment>
  <condition>Lower Extremity Periarticular Fractures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immersion Therapy- Study</arm_group_label>
    <description>1. Patients who participate in the immersion therapy post-operative protocol and begin progressive weight bearing at 4 weeks (study)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>2. Patients who undergo the traditional 10-week non-weight bearing post-operative care protocol (control)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This study is a prospective cohort study with a retrospective chart review. Patients who
        are treated by the PI, Dr. Erik Kubiak, will participate in an immersion therapy
        post-operative protocol. Immersion therapy post-operative protocols have been and are
        currently used routinely by Dr. Kubiak.

        Patients who are treated by Dr. Dan Horwitz and Dr. Thomas Higgins will undergo a
        traditional 10 week non-weight bearing post-operative care per their standard of procedure.
        In addition, patients of Dr. Kubiak who are unable to participate in immersion therapy for
        logistical reasons will be asked to participate in the traditional 10- week non-weight
        bearing post-operative care protocol. These patients will make up the control cohort.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria for the patient population under study consists of both male and
             female adults, at least 18 years old, who are treated for periarticular fractures of
             the lower extremity. The periarticular fractures included in this study will be:
             acetabular, tibial plateau, tibial plafond fractures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Wound complications deemed to be unsafe for immersion.

          -  Multiple extremity articular fractures

          -  Other injuries that preclude their safe participation in physical therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Erik Kubiak, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah Orthopedics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah Orthopedics Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 19, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Utah</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eric Kubiak</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.D.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immersion therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>early weight bearing physical therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

