<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01450839</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E2022-J081-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01450839</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>E2022 Patch Formulation Multiple Dose Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>E2022 Patch Formulation Multiple Dose Phase I Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eisai Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eisai Inc.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of a E2022 16 mg tape when applied
      repeatedly for 17 days to healthy elderly Japanese male subjects, using E2022 placebo tape as
      the control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite (or Profile) of Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>predose, 0,1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8,1 2, 24, 48, 72, 96 hours post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax, Area Under Curve, Tmax</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>E2020 5 mg tablet and tape</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>E2022</intervention_name>
    <description>The treatment period consists of 2 periods, Period I and Period II. In Period I, one 5 mg E2020 tablet will be administered in a single dose. In Period II, the tape containing 16 mg E2022 (which corresponds to one 5 mg E2020 tablet) will be applied repeatedly for 17 days. A washout period of at least 8 days will be allowed between the day of single dose administration in Period I and the first day of repeated application in Period II. A post-treatment examination will be performed at least 21 days after the last removal of the investigational product in Period II.</description>
    <arm_group_label>E2020 5 mg tablet and tape</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching Placebo tablets and tape</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Subjects who are non-smoking males (not smoking for at least 4 weeks before the
             administration of the investigational product in Period I) 65 years or older at the
             time of giving informed consent

          2. Subjects whose body mass index (BMI) is 18.5 kg/m^2 to less than 28.0 kg/m^2 at the
             screening

          3. Subjects who give voluntary written consent to participate in the study

          4. Subjects who have been fully informed of matters subjects are required to observe
             during the study and can, and are willing to, comply with the rules.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Subjects with a history of treatment-requiring disease within 8 weeks before
             administration of the investigational product in Period I or history of infection
             within 4 weeks before administration of the investigational product in Period I

          2. Subjects who have, within 4 weeks before administration of the investigational product
             in Period I, a disease that might affect the evaluation of the investigational
             product, such as mental, gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, respiratory, endocrine,
             hematological, nervous, or cardiovascular diseases, and inborn error of metabolism

          3. Subjects with a history of surgical treatment of the gastrointestinal tract (e.g.,
             resection of the liver, kidney, gastrointestinal tract, etc.) that may affect the
             pharmacokinetics of the investigational product

          4. Subjects with a history of treatment-requiring drug or food allergy or with seasonal
             allergy at the screening

          5. Subjects with a change in body weight of more than 10% at 1 day before investigational
             product administration in Period I, compared with that observed at the screening

          6. Subjects with clinically significant, treatment-requiring symptoms or impairment of
             organ function, judging from the subjective symptoms/objective findings, vital signs,
             12-lead ECG, or laboratory test performed during the period from the screening to
             immediately before investigational product administration in Period I

          7. Subjects with QTc&gt;450 ms on 12-lead ECG performed at the screening or immediately
             before investigational product administration in Period I

          8. Subjects who are positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody, hepatitis B
             virus surface antigen (HBs antigen), hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody, or qualitative
             syphilis test, at the screening

          9. Subjects with a history of, or suspected diagnosis of, drug or alcohol dependence or
             Subjects who are positive for urine drug test at the screening or 1 day before
             investigational product administration in Period I

         10. Subjects who took caffeine-containing or alcoholic beverage within 72 hours before
             investigational product administration in Period I

         11. Subjects who took, within 2 weeks before investigational product administration in
             Period I, nutritional supplements, herb-containing drug preparations (including
             Chinese medicines) or other foods or beverages (e.g., grapefruit-containing foods or
             beverages) that may affect drug-metabolizing enzymes or transporters

         12. Subjects who took drug preparations containing St. John's wort within 4 weeks before
             investigational product administration in Period I

         13. Subjects who took prescription drugs within 4 weeks before investigational product
             administration in Period I

         14. Subjects who took non-prescription drugs within 2 weeks before investigational product
             administration in Period I

         15. Subjects who participated in another clinical study within 16 weeks before
             investigational product administration in Period I and used an investigational product
             or medical device

         16. Subjects who received blood transfusion within 12 weeks, had 400 mL or more whole
             blood collected within 12 weeks, had 200 mL or more whole blood collected within 4
             weeks, or donated blood components within 2 weeks, before investigational product
             administration in Period I

         17. Subjects who performed strenuous exercise at a frequency of 5 days or more per week or
             who performed, even once, a strenuous exercise lasting 1 hour or more, within 2 weeks
             before admission for Period I

         18. Subjects with past or current clinical signs of cutaneous hypersensitivity or atopic
             dermatitis to external medicines

         19. Subjects in whom the investigational product and the fixing sheet cannot be applied to
             6 or more non-overlapping sites on the back (except the vertebral region and the site
             around the angulus inferior scapulae) by rotation method

         20. Subjects with excessive hair at the application site (back)

         21. Subjects with conditions at the application site (back), such as skin diseases (e.g.,
             eczema, dermatitis and pigmentary abnormality), external injuries, and scars, that may
             affect the evaluation of skin symptom

         22. Subjects who, or whose partners, are not willing to take reliable contraceptive
             measures until the completion of the post-treatment examination

         23. Subjects who are judged by the investigator or subinvestigator to be inappropriate as
             subjects of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hidetaka Hiramatsu</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Neuroscience Cliical Development Section, Japan /Asia Clinical Research PCU</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kagoshima</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 30, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 30, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transdermal Administration</keyword>
  <keyword>Japanese</keyword>
  <keyword>elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>male</keyword>
  <keyword>volunteers</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

