<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01454960</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1RC4AG039115-01-2</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1RC4AG039115-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01454960</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Behavioral Economics to Improve Treatment of Acute Respiratory Infections (Pilot Study)</brief_title>
  <acronym>BEARI</acronym>
  <official_title>Use of Behavioral Economics to Improve Treatment of Acute Respiratory Infections (Pilot Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bacteria resistant to antibiotic therapy are a major public health problem. The evolution of
      multi-drug resistant pathogens may be encouraged by provider prescribing behavior.
      Inappropriate use of antibiotics for nonbacterial infections and overuse of broad spectrum
      antibiotics can lead to the development of resistant strains. Though providers are adequately
      trained to know when antibiotics are and are not comparatively effective, this has not been
      sufficient to affect critical provider practices.

      The intent of this study is to apply behavioral economic theory to reduce the rate of
      antibiotic prescriptions for acute respiratory diagnoses for which guidelines do not call for
      antibiotics. Specifically targeted are infections that are likely to be viral.

      The objective of this study is to improve provider decisions around treatment of acute
      respiratory infections.

      The participants are practicing attending physicians or advanced practice nurses (i.e.
      providers) at participating clinics who see acute respiratory infection patients. A maximum
      of 550 participants will be recruited for this study.

      Providers consenting to participate will fill out a baseline questionnaire online. Subsequent
      to baseline data collection and enrollment, participating clinic sites will be randomized to
      the study arms, as described below.

      There will be a control arm, with clinic sites randomized in a multifactorial design to up to
      three interventions that leverage the electronic medical record: Order Sets that are
      triggered by EHR workflow containing exclusively guideline concordant choices (SA, for
      Suggested Alternatives); Accountable Justification (AJ) triggered by discordant prescriptions
      that populate the note with provider's rationale for guideline exceptions ; and performance
      feedback that benchmarks providers' own performance to that of their peers (PC, for Peer
      Comparison).

      The outcomes of interest are antibiotic prescribing patterns, including prescribing rates and
      changes in prescribing rates over time.

      The intervention period will be over one year, with a one-year follow up period to measure
      persistence of the effect after EHR features are returned to the original state and providers
      no longer receive email alerts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each consented provider will be randomized to 1 of 8 cells in a factorial design with equal
      probability. If results of retrospective data analysis imply that design will be improved by
      stratification, randomization will be stratified by factors that could influence outcomes.

      Data will be collected from Northwestern University's Enterprise Data Warehouse which houses
      copies of data recorded in the Epic electronic health record. Data elements from qualifying
      office visits will be collected from coded portions of the electronic health record.

      An encounter is eligible for intervention if the patient's diagnosis is in the selected group
      of acute respiratory infections. The intervention EHR functions will be triggered when
      clinicians initiate an antibiotic prescription or enter a diagnosis for an acute respiratory
      infection that has a defined Order Set. If an antibiotic from a list of frequently
      misprescribed antibiotics is ordered and a diagnosis has not yet been entered, providers will
      be prompted to enter a diagnosis. If the diagnosis entered is acute nasopharyngitis; acute
      laryngeopharyngitis/acute upper respiratory infection; acute bronchitis; bronchitis not
      specified as acute or chronic; or flu; the interventions will be triggered. The
      diagnosis-appropriate order set will pop-up for providers in the Suggested Alternatives (SA)
      arm, while clinicians randomized to the Accountable Justification (AJ) arm will receive an
      alert and be required to enter a brief statement justifying their antibiotic prescription if
      antibiotics are not indicated for the diagnosis entered. This note will then be added to the
      patient's medical record.

      Clinicians randomized to the Peer Comparison (PC) condition will receive monthly updates
      about their antibiotic prescribing practices relative to other clinicians in their practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibiotic Prescribing Rate for 5 Specific Acute Respiratory Infection Diagnoses</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in antibiotic prescribing rate for the following ICD-9 diagnoses:
460 Acute nasopharyngitis (common cold)
465 Acute laryngeopharyngitis/acute upper respiratory infection
466 Acute bronchitis
490 Bronchitis not specified as acute or chronic
487 Flu</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibiotic Prescribing Rates for Expanded List of Acute Respiratory Infection Diagnoses</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>We will monitor overall prescribing for the specified diagnoses and other Acute Respiratory Infection diagnoses, including cough/fever and pneumonia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Respiratory Infections (ARIs)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SA, AJ, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants are given all 3 interventions:
Suggested Alternatives, Accountable Justification, and Peer Comparison.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SA, AJ</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive the Suggested Alternatives and Accountable Justification interventions, but not the Peer Comparison intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SA, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive the Suggested Alternatives and Peer Comparison interventions, but not the Accountable Justification intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AJ, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive the Accountable Justification and Peer Comparison interventions, but not the Suggested Alternatives intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peer Comparison</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive the Peer Comparison intervention, but do not receive the Suggested Alternatives or Accountable Justification interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Suggested Alternatives</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive the Suggested Alternatives intervention, but not the Accountable Justification or Peer Comparison interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Accountable Justification</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive the Accountable Justification intervention, but do not receive the Suggested Alternatives or Peer Comparison interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants do not receive any of the 3 interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical Decision Support: Accountable Justification</intervention_name>
    <description>Accountable Justification is triggered by discordant prescriptions that populate the EHR note with provider's rationale for guideline exceptions (AJ).</description>
    <arm_group_label>SA, AJ, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SA, AJ</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>AJ, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Accountable Justification</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AJ</other_name>
    <other_name>Accountable Justification</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Audit and Feedback: Peer Comparison</intervention_name>
    <description>Performance feedback that benchmarks providers' own performance to that of their peers (PC, for Peer Comparison).</description>
    <arm_group_label>SA, AJ, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SA, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>AJ, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Peer Comparison</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PC</other_name>
    <other_name>Peer Comparison</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CDS Order Sets: Suggested Alternatives</intervention_name>
    <description>Order Sets that are triggered by EHR workflow containing exclusively guideline concordant choices (SA, for Suggested Alternatives).</description>
    <arm_group_label>SA, AJ, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SA, AJ</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SA, PC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Suggested Alternatives</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SA</other_name>
    <other_name>Suggested Alternatives</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        A practicing attending physician or advanced practice nurse (&quot;provider&quot;) at Northwestern
        University's NMFF GIM Clinic in 2011-2013 who sees acute respiratory infection patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Persell, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jason N Doctor, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern Medical Faculty Foundation General Internal Medicine Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611-2923</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 18, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 19, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jason Doctor</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Antibiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Inappropriate Prescribing</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory Tract Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral Research</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

