<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01459718</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CICL670AGR02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2009-018091-34</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01459718</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Deferasirox in Combination With Desferoxamine in β-thalassaemia Patients With Severe Cardiac Iron Overload</brief_title>
  <acronym>MACS1097</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicenter Open Label Phase II Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Deferasirox in Combination With Deferoxamine Followed by Transitioning to Deferasirox Monotherapy in β-thalassemia Patients With Severe Cardiac Iron Overload</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary efficacy endpoint of this interventional study is to evaluate the number of
      patients achieving a complete response (CR), defined as patients switching from intensive
      deferasirox -DFO treatment, at any time point during the 24 months of study, to deferasirox
      monotherapy based on improvement in the cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) T2* value to
      &gt;10ms, and continue to maintain their MRI T2* to values &gt;10 msec.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients achieving a complete response (CR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Complete Response is defined as patients that stop intensive deferasirox -DFO treatment, at any time point during the 24 months of study, based on an improvement in the cardiac MRI T2* value being &gt;10ms, and continue to be treated with deferasirox monotherapy without any further need for reverting back to intensive iron chelation treatment during the 24 months of study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients achieving a partial response (PR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Partial Response is defined as patients that stop intensive deferasirox -DFO treatment at any time point during the 24 months study and transition to receive deferasirox monotherapy, but due to a deterioration in cardiac MRI T2* to a value &lt; 10 ms revert back to intensive deferasirox -DFO iron chelation therapy during the 24 months of study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with stable disease (SD</measure>
    <time_frame>24 nmonths</time_frame>
    <description>Stable Disease is defined as those patients that never achieved an improvement in the cardiac MRI T2* to values &gt;10ms during the 24 months of study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability will be measured by the number of post baseline adverse events (AEs) (clinical and laboratory abnormalities), severity and relationship to study i.e ocular/ auditory exams</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory abnormalities qualifying as AEs include occurrence of post baseline abnormal parameters of serum creatinine, creatinine clearance, liver transaminases (AST/ALT), bilirubin and proteinuria and by the patients who discontinue the study due to AEs.
Patients who discontinue the study due to AEs for each of the treatment regimens, i.e., deferasirox-DFO combination and deferasirox monotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in cardiac iron overload of patients in intensive iron chelation therapy consisting of deferasirox-DFO and after transition to deferasirox monotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>screening, 6, 12, 18, 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in cardiac iron overload will be determined by the changes in cardiac MRI T2* from screening, at 6, 12, 18 and 24 months for each response group.
Reduction in cardiac iron overload will also be measured by the monthly velocity of heart T2* for each response group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time for a patient with severe cardiac iron receiving intensive deferasirox-DFO regimen to achieve a cardiac MRI T2* &gt; 10 ms</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in Liver iron concentration (LIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>screening, 6, 12, 18, 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in LIC will be determined by change in liver MRI T2* from screening, at 6, 12, 18 and 24 months for each response group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trends and associations between serum ferritin levels and LIC</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12, 18, 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Trends and associations will be evaluated by the observed changes at 6, 12, 18, 24 months at a given time point for each response group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in cardiac function</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12, 18, 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determined as change in cardiac magnetic resonance (CMR) measured left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) (%) at 6, 12, 18, 24 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Transfusion-dependent β-thalassemia Patients</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Iron Overload</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Deferasirox</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Monotherapy of deferasirox</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Deferasirox + Deferioxamine (DFO)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combination Therapy: Deferasirox-DFO</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deferasirox</intervention_name>
    <description>Deferasirox monotherapy treatment of intensive iron chelation treatment. Medication label will comply with the Greek legal requirements and be printed in Greek. A subject identifier will be entered on the medication label.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Deferasirox</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ICL670</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deferasirox + Deferoxamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Deferasirox-DFO regimen for intensive iron chelation treatment. Medication labels will comply with the Greek legal requirements and will be printed in Greek. A subject identifier will be entered on the medication label.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Deferasirox + Deferioxamine (DFO)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ICL670</other_name>
    <other_name>DFO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients with β-thalassemia major, at least 18 years old, having given
             written consent to participate in the study.

          -  Cardiac MRI T2* value ranging from &lt;=4 to &lt;=10 ms.

          -  LVEF ≥ 56 % as determined by CMR.

          -  Patients with LIC &gt; 10mg Fe/g dw will be included in the protocol. Study will evaluate
             the first 10 patients at 6 months, and if no safety signals are present, patients with
             LIC&gt;5 mg Fe/g dw will be allowed to be included.

          -  Prior iron chelation treatment with DFO, DFP, DFX or combination DFO-DFP

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with symptoms of cardiac dysfunction symptoms (shortness of breath at rest or
             exertion, orthopnea, exercise intolerance, lower extremity edema, arrhythmias).

          -  Patients with cardiac T2* MRI &lt; 4 or &gt; 10 ms.

          -  Patients not compliant to intensive iron chelation therapy regimens such i.v DFO 24 hr
             infusions or DFO-DFP combination.

          -  Patients with documented liver failure (presence of portal hypertension, hepatic
             edemas, ascites).

          -  Patients unable to undergo study assessments, including blood sampling, MRI, e.g., are
             claustrophobic to MRI, have a pacemaker, ferromagnetic metal implants other than those
             approved as safe for use in MRI scanners (e.g., some types of aneurysm clips, shrapnel
             in proximity to vital organs such as the retina), are obese (exceeding the equipment
             limits).

          -  Patients with serum creatinine &gt; ULN or with significant proteinuria as indicated by a
             urinary protein/creatinine ratio ≥ 1.0 in a non-first void urine sample at
             baseline.Patients with creatinine clearance &lt;60 ml/min will be excluded.

          -  Patients with ALT (SGPT) levels &gt; 5 x ULN.

          -  Patients with considerable impaired gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that
             may significantly alter the absorption of oral deferasirox / ICL670 (e.g., ulcerative
             diseases, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, or small
             bowel resection.

          -  History or clinical evidence of pancreatic injury or pancreatitis.

          -  Patients with a known hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs or the drug's
             excipients.

          -  History of clinically relevant ocular and/or auditor toxicity related to iron
             chelation therapy.

          -  Patients with psychiatric or addictive disorders which prevent them from giving their
             informed consent or undergoing any of the treatment options or patients unwilling or
             unable to comply with the protocol.

          -  Patients with a known history of HIV seropositivity (Elisa or Western blot).

          -  History of malignancy of any organ system, treated or untreated, within the past 5
             years whether or not there is evidence of local recurrence or metastases, with the
             exception of localized basal cell carcinoma of the skin.

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or breast feeding.

          -  Female patients of reproductive potential not employing an effective method of birth
             control. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test ≤
             48 hours prior to the study drugs.

          -  Patients participating in another clinical trial or receiving an investigational drug.

          -  History of non-compliance with medical regimens or patients who are considered
             potentially unreliable and/or not cooperative, unwilling or unable to comply with the
             protocol.

        Other protocol-defined inclusion/exclusion criteria may apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>GR</state>
        <zip>115 27</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>GR</state>
        <zip>GR-115 27</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>GR</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Patras</city>
        <zip>26500</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 20, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 9, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 9, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 10, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe cardiac iron overload</keyword>
  <keyword>deferasirox</keyword>
  <keyword>β-thalassaemia</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac dysfunction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thalassemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Iron Overload</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>beta-Thalassemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Iron</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deferasirox</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deferoxamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 28, 2015</submitted>
    <returned>August 21, 2015</returned>
    <submitted>January 11, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>February 8, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>March 10, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>April 8, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>April 11, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>May 16, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>November 30, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>January 24, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>February 20, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>April 4, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

