<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01457040</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HDE-ALL-2011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01457040</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intensified Conditioning Regimen With High-Dose-Etoposide for Allo-HSCT for Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Study of Intensified Conditioning Regimen With High-Dose-Etoposide for Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia in China</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nanfang Hospital of Southern Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fujian Medical University Union Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Hospital of Sun Yat-Sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Third Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-Sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Xiangya Hospital of Central South University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nanfang Hospital of Southern Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evolving paradigms in the treatment of adult ALL include the application of intense pediatric
      regimens to the treatment of adolescents and young adults (AYA) and the optimization of
      allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (allo-HSCT) in the cure of patients. The
      Cancer and Leukemia Group B (CALGB) and the Children's Cancer Group (CCG) first asked whether
      AYA between the ages of 16 and 20 fared differently whether they were treated on pediatric
      protocols. The results of this study demonstrated that although the complete remission rates
      were identical for the AYAs treated on the CALGB and CCG trials, the AYAs had a 63%
      event-free survival (EFS) and 67% OS at 7 years on the CCG trials compared with 34% and 46%,
      respectively, on the CALGB trials.

      High relapse and transplantation-related-mortality still remains great challenge for HSCT of
      adult ALL, which both range between 25% and 30%. Recently, risk-adapted indication and
      optimization of conditioning regimen are highlighted, which aiming to reduce TRM and relapse
      rate, respectively.City of Hope National Medical Center studied the substitution of etoposide
      (VP-16) for CY in the treatment of ALL patients receiving HCT. The result suggested that
      etoposide and TBI are associated with a decreased relapse rate following transplantation for
      ALL, compared with those receiving CY and TBI. Japanese and Germany reports pronounced the
      advantage of VP-16 in intensified regimen for adult ALL. On the same time, the investigators
      previous researches have confirmed the effect and safety of FA-intensified conditioning
      regimen on relapse and refractary leukemia.

      Based on mentioned above, the investigators speculate that VP-16-intensified conditioning
      regimen could improve the outcome for adult ALL. The potential mechanism will be attributed
      to reduce MRD and promote GVL effect via providing enough time-window for
      immuno-reconstitution by high-dose preparative regimen.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the first decade of the new millennium, multiple studies have begun to change our thinking
      about the treatment of adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL). In pediatric patients
      cure rates in the range of 80% to 90% are now attainable. While adult patients with ALL now
      have a 90% complete remission (CR) with modern chemotherapy, most patients will relapse, and
      leukemia-free survival with 3 to 7 years of follow-up in large series is only in the range of
      30% to 40%. The poor outcome of chemotherapy in adults with ALL as compared to children
      relates to multiple factors, including poor tolerance of intensive courses of chemotherapy
      and a higher incidence of poor prognostic subtypes of ALL such as Philadelphia
      chromosome-positive ALL and a lower incidence of favorable subtypes such as the t (12; 21).

      Evolving paradigms in the treatment of adult ALL include the application of intense pediatric
      regimens to the treatment of adolescents and young adults (AYA) and the optimization of
      allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (allo-HSCT) in the cure of patients. Adult
      regimens are typically less intense than pediatric regimens. The Cancer and Leukemia Group B
      (CALGB) and the Children's Cancer Group (CCG) first asked whether AYA between the ages of 16
      and 20 fared differently whether they were treated on pediatric protocols. The results of
      this study demonstrated that although the complete remission rates were identical for the
      AYAs treated on the CALGB and CCG trials, the AYAs had a 63% event-free survival (EFS) and
      67% OS at 7 years on the CCG trials compared with 34% and 46%, respectively, on the CALGB
      trials. These results have prompted new studies where pediatric ALL regimens have been
      adapted to the treatment of younger adults. With short follow-up, GRAALL-2003 reports suggest
      EFS and OS outcomes in the range of 60%. This improved outcome was more pronounced in the
      standard-risk patients with a donor who had an OS at 5 years of 69%. On the same time, our
      previous researches have confirmed the effect and safety of FA-intensified conditioning
      regimen on relapse and refractary leukemia.

      Based on mentioned above, we speculate that VP-16-intensified conditioning regimen could
      improve the outcome for adult ALL. The potential mechanism will be attributed to reduce MRD
      and promote GVL effect via providing enough time-window for immuno-reconstitution by
      high-dose preparative regimen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Over Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after HSCT</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Leukemia-Free-Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after HSCT</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>relapse rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Stem Cell Transplantation, Hematopoietic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Complete Remission (CR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CR Cohort: high-risk ALL in CR and standard-risk ALL in the status of ≥CR2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Remission (NR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NR Cohort: ALL in non-remission</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TBI+CY+VP-16</intervention_name>
    <description>CR Cohort will receive conditioning regimen of TBI+CY+VP-16: TBI: 4.5Gy/d, -5d, -4d; CY: 60mg/kg/d, -3d, -2d; VP-16: 15mg/kg/d, -3d, -2d</description>
    <arm_group_label>Complete Remission (CR)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FA+TBI+CY+VP-16</intervention_name>
    <description>NR Cohort will receive conditioning regimen of FA+TBI+CY+VP-16: Flu: 35mg/m2/d: -10~-6d; AraC: 1g/m2/d, -10d~-6d; TBI: 4.5Gy/d, -5d,-4d; CY:60mg/kg/d, -3d, -2d; VP-16: 15mg/kg, -3d, -2d</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Remission (NR)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age: 14 years to 65 years

          2. Diagnosis of High-risk acute lymphoblastic leukemia or standard-risk ALL in ≥CR2

          3. Patient will receive allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation

          4. The informed consent form has been signed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient with severe cardiac dysfunction with less than 50% EF

          2. Patient with severe lung dysfunction

          3. Patient with severe hepatic or renal dysfunction with more than 3 times the upper
             limit of normal range (ULN) of serum ALT or AST levels, or with more than 2 times the
             upper limit of normal range (ULN) of serum TBIL level or less than 40% of normal
             prothrombin time activity (PTA); or with more than 2 times the ULN of serum Cr

          4. Patient with severe active infection

          5. Patient with allergy history about suspected drug in conditioning regimen

          6. Patient with other conditions considered unsuitable for the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Qifa Liu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Hematology, Nanfang Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Hematology, Nanfang Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510515</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu QF, Fan ZP, Zhang Y, Jiang ZJ, Wang CY, Xu D, Sun J, Xiao Y, Tan H. Sequential intensified conditioning and tapering of prophylactic immunosuppressants for graft-versus-host disease in allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for refractory leukemia. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2009 Nov;15(11):1376-85. doi: 10.1016/j.bbmt.2009.06.017. Epub 2009 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19822296</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ottmann OG, Pfeifer H. Management of Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (Ph+ ALL). Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program. 2009:371-81. doi: 10.1182/asheducation-2009.1.371.</citation>
    <PMID>20008223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laport GG, Alvarnas JC, Palmer JM, Snyder DS, Slovak ML, Cherry AM, Wong RM, Negrin RS, Blume KG, Forman SJ. Long-term remission of Philadelphia chromosome-positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia after allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation from matched sibling donors: a 20-year experience with the fractionated total body irradiation-etoposide regimen. Blood. 2008 Aug 1;112(3):903-9. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-03-143115. Epub 2008 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>18519812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seibel NL. Treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia in children and adolescents: peaks and pitfalls. Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program. 2008:374-80. doi: 10.1182/asheducation-2008.1.374. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19074113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pui CH, Evans WE. Treatment of acute lymphoblastic leukemia. N Engl J Med. 2006 Jan 12;354(2):166-78. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16407512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kantarjian H, Thomas D, O'Brien S, Cortes J, Giles F, Jeha S, Bueso-Ramos CE, Pierce S, Shan J, Koller C, Beran M, Keating M, Freireich EJ. Long-term follow-up results of hyperfractionated cyclophosphamide, vincristine, doxorubicin, and dexamethasone (Hyper-CVAD), a dose-intensive regimen, in adult acute lymphocytic leukemia. Cancer. 2004 Dec 15;101(12):2788-801.</citation>
    <PMID>15481055</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowe JM, Buck G, Burnett AK, Chopra R, Wiernik PH, Richards SM, Lazarus HM, Franklin IM, Litzow MR, Ciobanu N, Prentice HG, Durrant J, Tallman MS, Goldstone AH; ECOG; MRC/NCRI Adult Leukemia Working Party. Induction therapy for adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: results of more than 1500 patients from the international ALL trial: MRC UKALL XII/ECOG E2993. Blood. 2005 Dec 1;106(12):3760-7. Epub 2005 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>16105981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstone AH, Richards SM, Lazarus HM, Tallman MS, Buck G, Fielding AK, Burnett AK, Chopra R, Wiernik PH, Foroni L, Paietta E, Litzow MR, Marks DI, Durrant J, McMillan A, Franklin IM, Luger S, Ciobanu N, Rowe JM. In adults with standard-risk acute lymphoblastic leukemia, the greatest benefit is achieved from a matched sibling allogeneic transplantation in first complete remission, and an autologous transplantation is less effective than conventional consolidation/maintenance chemotherapy in all patients: final results of the International ALL Trial (MRC UKALL XII/ECOG E2993). Blood. 2008 Feb 15;111(4):1827-33. Epub 2007 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18048644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huguet F, Leguay T, Raffoux E, Thomas X, Beldjord K, Delabesse E, Chevallier P, Buzyn A, Delannoy A, Chalandon Y, Vernant JP, Lafage-Pochitaloff M, Chassevent A, Lhéritier V, Macintyre E, Béné MC, Ifrah N, Dombret H. Pediatric-inspired therapy in adults with Philadelphia chromosome-negative acute lymphoblastic leukemia: the GRAALL-2003 study. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Feb 20;27(6):911-8. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.18.6916. Epub 2009 Jan 5. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2009 May 20;27(15):2574. Dosage error in article text.</citation>
    <PMID>19124805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marks DI, Forman SJ, Blume KG, Pérez WS, Weisdorf DJ, Keating A, Gale RP, Cairo MS, Copelan EA, Horan JT, Lazarus HM, Litzow MR, McCarthy PL, Schultz KR, Smith DD, Trigg ME, Zhang MJ, Horowitz MM. A comparison of cyclophosphamide and total body irradiation with etoposide and total body irradiation as conditioning regimens for patients undergoing sibling allografting for acute lymphoblastic leukemia in first or second complete remission. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2006 Apr;12(4):438-53.</citation>
    <PMID>16545728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 19, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nanfang Hospital of Southern Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hongsheng Zhou</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Lymphoblastic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

