<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01450085</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01AI093316-01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01450085</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chepetsa TB - Reducing TB Among HIV-Infected Malawians</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of a New Molecular Tuberculosis (TB) Test on TB/HIV Outcomes Among HIV-</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aims of this project are: (1) to compare the impact of using the routine
      screening and GeneXpert algorithms for TB case detection on Tuberculosis (TB)- and
      HIV-related outcomes; (2) to compare the impact of using the routine screening and GeneXpert
      algorithms for exclusion of TB prior to initiation of IPT and ART on TB- and HIV-related
      outcomes; and (3) to assess the relative cost-effectiveness of the routine screening and
      GeneXpert algorithms for TB case detection and exclusion of TB. The GeneXpert is a
      &quot;disruptive technology&quot;10 that could allow TB/HIV programs in resource-limited settings to
      leapfrog over solid and liquid culture-based TB diagnostic algorithms, and to remove a key
      barrier to scale up of ICF and IPT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      HIV and tuberculosis (TB) are, along with malaria, the leading infectious causes of death
      worldwide and in sub-Saharan Africa.1 In 2008, there were 2 million deaths from AIDS and 1.8
      million deaths from TB worldwide.2, 3 The HIV epidemic has fueled an increase in the
      incidence of, prevalence of and mortality due to TB in the past 3 decades. 15% of TB cases
      are HIV co-infected worldwide.34 78% of HIV-infected TB cases are in Africa.3 TB is the
      leading cause of death and opportunistic infection among persons living with HIV/AIDS
      (PLWHA). The HIV epidemic has challenged time-tested TB control methods that are now failing
      in high HIV prevalence settings.5 The World Health Organization (WHO) has recommended that
      the Three I's - intensified case-finding for TB (ICF), isoniazid preventive therapy (IPT) and
      infection control for TB - be targeted at PLWHA.6 ICF and IPT have not been adequately
      implemented in part due to the absence of sensitive, specific and rapid TB tests. The Cepheid
      GeneXpert System, a new diagnostic test for TB, is a self-contained sputum-processing and
      real-time PCR system to detect the M. tuberculosis complex as well as rifampin resistance.78
      The GeneXpert is rapid, highly sensitive and specific, can be used as a point-of-care test,
      and has low human resource, laboratory and infection control requirements.7, 8 The WHO
      Strategic and Advisory Group for TB has endorsed recommendations for widespread use of the
      GeneXpert.9 WHO strongly recommended that the GeneXpert should be used as the initial
      diagnostic test in HIV-infected TB suspects and multidrug-resistant TB (MDR-TB) suspects.9
      WHO also recommended that implementation of the GeneXpert be phased in within the context of
      comprehensive national and MDR-TB strategic plans.9 WHO recognized that several operational
      conditions need to be met for successful implementation, including but not limited to stable
      electrical supply, security against theft, trained personnel and annual calibration of the
      instrument by a commercial supplier.9 WHO also noted that it is important to document the
      impact and cost-effectiveness of the GeneXpert for TB case detection.9

      Trial Concept The overall objective of this proposal is to conduct a cluster-randomized trial
      of the relative impact and cost-effectiveness of a routine TB screening algorithm -- symptom
      screening and point-of-care LED fluorescence sputum smear microscopy - versus a
      GeneXpert-based TB screening algorithm - symptom screening and point-of-care GeneXpert
      testing - on reducing morbidity and mortality due to TB among HIV-infected Malawians. 12
      public sector clinics in southern Malawi will be randomized to 1 of 2 algorithms for TB case
      detection as part of ICF and for exclusion of TB prior to IPT and antiretroviral therapy
      (ART) initiation. In the clinics assigned to the GeneXpert algorithm, newly diagnosed
      HIV-infected patients will be screened for symptoms of TB and, if symptomatic, will provide
      sputum for GeneXpert point-of-care TB testing. Under the routine screening algorithm,
      patients at a clinic will be screened for symptoms of TB and, if symptomatic, will provide
      sputum for point-of-care LED fluorescence smear microscopy. The current standard of care in
      Malawi and most of Africa is symptom screening and sputum smear microscopy using
      Ziehl-Neelsen stain (not LED fluorescence microscopy) alone. There is not sufficient evidence
      at this time to demonstrate whether point-of-care LED microscopy versus GeneXpert testing is
      likely to be superior with respect to clinical impact and/or cost-effectiveness. Outcomes
      will be measured at the clinic level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 30, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival of newly-diagnosed HIV-infected patients at 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GeneXpert</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Point of care GeneXpert</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LED Microscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Point of care LED Microscopy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GeneXpert</intervention_name>
    <description>Point of care GeneXpert</description>
    <arm_group_label>GeneXpert</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LED Microscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Point of care LED Microscopy</description>
    <arm_group_label>GeneXpert</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>LED Microscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All HIV-infected men and women &gt; 18 years of age with newly diagnosed HIV at the 12 study
        clinics will be asked to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded from participation if they have a current diagnosis of TB
             and/or if they are currently taking IPT, TB treatment and/or ART.

          -  Patients will also be excluded from participation if they cannot speak English or
             Chichewa;

          -  if they have a language or hearing impairment; or

          -  if they are prisoners.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Corbett, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Malawi Liverpool Wellcome Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Dowdy, MD. PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Unviversity</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lawrence Moulton, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Blantyre</city>
        <state>Thyolo District</state>
        <country>Malawi</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Blantyre</city>
        <country>Malawi</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malawi</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

