<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00739037</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3186A1-1103</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00739037</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Evaluating PAZ-417 in Cerebrospinal Fluid in Subjects With Alzheimer's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Single Dose, Placebo-Controlled, 2 Period Crossover Study of the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of PAZ 417 in Cerebrospinal Fluid, When Administered Orally to Subjects With Alzheimer's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wyeth is now a wholly owned subsidiary of Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wyeth is now a wholly owned subsidiary of Pfizer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to assess biomarker known as amyloid beta peptide 40
      (Ab40) in Cerebrospinal Fluid (CSF), following a single oral dose of PAZ-417 in subjects with
      Alzheimer Disease (AD). This study will also consider another biomarker amyloid beta peptide
      42 (Ab42) in Cerebrospinal Fluid in subjects with Alzheimer Disease and assess the safety,
      tolerability and pharmacokinetic profile of PAZ-417 in both plasma and Cerebrospinal Fluid in
      these subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>This study is the measurement of a biomarker known as amyloid beta peptide 40 (Ab40) in Cerebrospinal Fluid (CSF), following a single oral dose of PAZ-417 in subjects with Alzheimer Disease (AD).</measure>
    <time_frame>6 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure both amyloid beta peptide 42 (Ab42) and PAZ-417 in both plasma and CSF and assess safety using the results of physical examinations, vital sign measurements, ECGs, cardiac telemetry, standard laboratory tests and collection of AES.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PAZ-417</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion:

          1. Men or women of non-childbearing potential, 55 years of age or older with a probable
             diagnosis of Alzheimer's Disease (AD), according to the National Institute of
             Neurological and Communicative Disorders and Stroke-Alzheimer's Disease and Related
             Disorders Association (NINCDS-ADRDA) criteria. Subjects will have AD that is mild to
             moderate in severity, as qualified by a score of 12 to 26 on the Mini-Mental State
             Examination (MMSE). Woman of non-childbearing potential must be either surgically
             sterile (hysterectomy and/or oophorectomy) or postmenopausal at least 1 year and must
             have a negative serum pregnancy test result within 48 hours before administration of
             test article. Sexually active men must agree to use a medically acceptable form of
             contraception during the study and continue it for 12 weeks after test article
             administration.

          2. Body mass index in the range of 18 to 32 kg/m2 and body weight greater than or equal
             to 50 kg.

          3. Subjects must be generally healthy, with the exception of AD but may be enrolled with
             a stable, chronic illness, if it is well controlled and does not interfere with the
             primary objective of the study. Subjects may be included with clinically important
             deviations from normal limits in medical history, physical examination findings, vital
             sign measurements, findings on 12 lead electrocardiogram (ECG), or chronic laboratory
             test results that are associated with stable, well controlled chronic illness.

        Exclusion:

          1. Any surgical or medical condition that may interfere with the absorption,
             distribution, metabolism, or excretion of the test article.

          2. Any significant unstable or uncontrolled cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, respiratory,
             gastrointestinal, endocrine, immunologic, dermatologic, hematologic, neurologic, or
             psychiatric disease.

          3. History of vascular disorders (peripheral, coronary, venous), chronic inflammatory
             disorders (eg, rheumatoid arthritis), hematologic disorders, or bleeding disorders
             (eg, hemophilia, idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura, VonWillebrand disease).

          4. History of thrombotic events.

          5. Presence or history of symptomatic vertigo, significant cardiac valvular disease,
             congestive heart failure, angina pectoris, significant cardiac arrhythmia, or
             seizures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Monitor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Wyeth is now a wholly owned subsidiary of Pfizer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>California Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glendale</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 15, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 21, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 3, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 3, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 4, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Wyeth (Registry Contact: Clinical Trial Registry Specialist)</name_title>
    <organization>Wyeth</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

