<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00738179</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SAVE001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ANZCTR 12608000409370</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00738179</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure Treatment of Obstructive Sleep Apnea to Prevent Cardiovascular Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>SAVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Sleep Apnea cardioVascular Endpoints Study - Investigating the Effectiveness of Treatment With CPAP vs Standard Care in Reducing CV Morbidity and Mortality in Patients With Co-existing CV Disease and Moderate-severe Obstructive Sleep Apnea.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Philips Respironics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Health and Medical Research Council, Australia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ResMed</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The George Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Health Research Council, New Zealand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) is a condition in which a person stops breathing for several
      seconds at a time due to relaxation of the throat muscles. This can occur many times during
      sleep. It is known to cause sleepiness and poor concentration during the day. Research
      indicates that OSA may be a modifiable risk factor for cardiovascular disease due to its
      association with hypertension, stroke, heart attack and sudden death. The standard therapy
      for symptomatic OSA is continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP). CPAP has been shown to
      effectively reduce snoring, obstructive episodes and daytime sleepiness and to modestly
      reduce blood pressure and other risk factors for cardiovascular disease. The overall aim of
      SAVE is to determine if CPAP can reduce the risk of heart attack, stroke or heart failure for
      people with OSA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is increasing evidence to indicate that OSA is an important modifiable risk factor for
      CV disease including stroke, MI, and heart failure. Increased nocturnal arterial blood
      pressure (BP), hypercoagulability, oxidative stress, inflammation, insulin resistance and
      cardiac arrhythmias are all associated with OSA. These effects are presumed to accelerate the
      progression of atheromatous disease, particularly within the coronary or cerebral
      vasculature. Moreover, OSA also appears to increase the risk of sudden death during sleep,
      which is different from the circadian pattern of sudden death in those without OSA,
      suggesting that episodes of apnea may have a direct triggering effect for cardiac arrhythmias
      or MI.

      CPAP is now standard therapy for symptomatic OSA, with adherence to treatment comparable to
      that of other therapies for common chronic diseases. CPAP can eliminate apneas and improve
      daytime sleepiness, mood and quality of life. Furthermore, short term (1-3 months) randomised
      controlled trials of CPAP have shown modest reductions in blood pressure (BP) and other
      markers of CV disease, including C-reactive protein (CRP) and coagulation. However, the
      epidemiological data is complicated by potential residual confounding factors and the
      randomised evidence is limited. Thus, a direct causal link between OSA and CV disease remains
      inconclusive. The management of OSA, therefore, remains principally directed towards symptom
      control rather than CV risk modification.

      The present trial aims to test whether long-term use of CPAP can reduce the incidence of CV
      events. If the trial shows that CPAP treatment of OSA reduces the incidence of CV events it
      will influence clinical practice toward the early detection and management of OSA, and add
      CPAP to the range of strategies available for the prevention of CV disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A composite of the CV endpoints of CV death, non-fatal acute myocardial infarction, non-fatal stroke, hospital admission for heart failure, and new hospitalisation for unstable angina or transient ischaemic attack.</measure>
    <time_frame>Reviewed 6-monthly; average patient follow up, 4.5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of CV death, MI &amp; ischaemic stroke; components of primary composite endpoint; re-vascularisation procedures; all-cause death; new onset atrial fibrillation; new onset diabetes; OSA symptom scores; mood; health-related quality of life.</measure>
    <time_frame>Reviewed 6-monthly; average patient follow up, 4.5 years.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In a sub-sample of 600 subjects pathophysiological mechanisms of CPAP-induced CV event reduction will be explored by assessing various intermediate markers of CV risk</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and at 6-months, 2 and 4 years following randomisation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac MRI to assess effects of CPAP on cardiac structure and function.</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomisation and at 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>In a sub-sample of 150 participants (75 from the CPAP plus standard treatment and 75 from the standard treatment arms) the effect of CPAP on cardiac and vascular function using cardiac MRI will be investigated. The sub-study will evaluate left and right ventricular mass, volume and systolic/diastolic function and compliance of the aorta.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2500</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CPAP plus standard care of cardiovascular risk factors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard care alone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP)</intervention_name>
    <description>CPAP worn nightly</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard care of cardiovascular risk factors</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females, any race, and aged between 45 and 75 years

          2. Evidence of established coronary or cerebrovascular disease as evident by:

               -  Coronary artery disease

                    -  Previous MI (equal to or greater than 90 days prior to ApneaLinkTM
                       assessment)

                    -  Stable angina or unstable angina (Clinical event equal to or greater than 30
                       days and confirmatory test equal to or greater than 7 days prior to
                       ApneaLinkTM assessment) defined as either ≥70% diameter stenosis of at least
                       one major epicardial artery segment, or ≥50% diameter stenosis of the left
                       main coronary artery, or &gt;50% stenosis in at least two major epicardial
                       arteries.; or positive stress test (ST depression equal to or greater than 2
                       mm or a positive nuclear perfusion scintigram)

                    -  Multi-vessel percutaneous angioplasty (PTCA) and/or stent equal to or
                       greater than 90 days prior to ApneaLinkTM assessment

                    -  Multi-vessel coronary artery bypass surgery (CABG) &gt;1 year prior to
                       ApneaLinkTM assessment

               -  Cerebrovascular disease

                    -  Previous stroke (includes definite or presumed cerebral ischaemia/infarction
                       and intracerebral but not subarachnoid haemorrhage) equal to or greater than
                       90 days prior to ApneaLinkTM assessment or minor disabling stroke with
                       minimal residual neurological disability (modified Rankin Score of '0 = no
                       symptoms' or '1 = No significant disability despite symptoms, able to carry
                       out all usual duties and activities' within 7 days of stroke onset) ≥7 days
                       prior to ApneaLinkTM assessment.

                    -  Previous transient ischaemic event (TIA) of the brain or retina (symptoms
                       &lt;24 hours) but not of presumed vertebrobasilar system ischemia. The TIA
                       diagnosis must be confirmed by a suitably qualified clinician (≥7 days but
                       &lt;1year prior to ApneaLinkTM assessment)

          3. Patients have moderate-severe OSA (equivalent to apnea plus hypopneas index [AHI] &gt;30
             per hour of sleep) as determined by a ≥ 4% oxygen dip rate &gt; 12/ h on overnight
             testing using the ApneaLinkTM device and confirmed by the SAVE core lab in Adelaide
             upon receipt of the ApneaLinkTM data

          4. Patients are able and willing to give appropriate informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients will be excluded from entry if ANY of the criteria listed below are met:

          1. Any condition that in the opinion of the responsible physician or investigator makes
             the potential participant unsuitable for the study. For example,

               -  co-morbid disease with severe disability or likelihood of death

               -  significant memory, perceptual, or behavioural disorder

               -  neurological deficit (e.g. limb paresis) preventing self administration of the
                  CPAP mask

               -  contraindication to CPAP use e.g. pneumothorax

               -  residence sufficiently remote from the clinic to preclude follow-up clinic visits

          2. Any planned coronary or carotid revascularisation procedure in the next 6 months

          3. Severe respiratory disease defined as

               -  severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (FEV1/FVC &lt; 70% and FEV1 &lt; 50%
                  predicted), or

               -  resting, awake SaO2 &lt; 90% by ApneaLinkTM device

          4. New York Heart Association (NYHA) categories III-IV of heart failure

          5. Other household member enrolled in SAVE trial or using CPAP

          6. Prior use of CPAP treatment for OSA

          7. Increased risk of a sleep-related accident and/or excessive daytime sleepiness,
             defined by any one of the following:

               -  driver occupation (eg truck, taxi)

               -  'fall-asleep' accident or 'near miss' accident in previous 12 months

               -  high (&gt; 15) score on the Epworth Sleepiness Scale

          8. Severe nocturnal desaturation documented on the ApneaLinkTM device as &gt; 10% overnight
             recording time with arterial oxygen saturation of &lt; 80%

          9. Cheyne-Stokes Respiration (CSResp)

               -  CSResp identified on ApneaLinkTM nasal pressure recording by typical
                  crescendo-decrescendo pattern of respiration with associated apneas and/or
                  hypopneas in the absence of inspiratory flow limitation.

               -  patients excluded if &gt; 50% of nasal pressure - defined apneas and hypopneas
                  judged to be due to CSResp.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>R D McEvoy</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health, Repatriation General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Adelaide</city>
        <state>South Australia</state>
        <zip>5041</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brazil Principal Investigator: Geraldo Lorenzi Filho, Heart Institute, University of São Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regional Coordinating Centre China: The George Institute China Beijing</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100088</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regional Coordinating Centre India: The George Institute India 839C, Road No. 44A Jubilee Hills</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyderabad</city>
        <state>Andhra Pradesh</state>
        <zip>500 033</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regional Coordinating Centre Spain: Spanish Respiratory Society (Sociedad Española de Neumología y Cirugía Torácica) (SEPAR)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08029</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>China</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.savetrial.org</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 19, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Professor R. Doug McEvoy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP)</keyword>
  <keyword>Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular (CV)</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical Trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

