<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00730210</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EudraCT #008-000606-36)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00730210</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Hypoparathyroidism With Subcutaneous PTH (1-84) Injections: Effects on Muscle Function and Quality of Life</brief_title>
  <acronym>HypoPTH</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment of Hypoparathyroidism With Subcutaneous PTH (1-84) Injections: Effects on Muscle Function and Quality of Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aarhus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aarhus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study is to assess whether PTH (1-84) therapy posses advantages compared to
      conventional treatment in patients with hypoparathyroidism on muscle function, quality of
      life, calcium homeostasis, bone metabolism, and body composition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypoparathyroidism is one of the only hormonal insufficiency states that is usually not
      treated by replacing the missing hormone. Currently, Standard therapy includes treatment with
      calcium and an 1alpha-hydroxylated forms of vitamin D (e.g. calcitriol or alphacalcidol) in
      order to relieve the symptoms associated with hypocalcaemia. However, recent studies have
      shown that calcium homeostasis can be well regulated by PTH replacement therapy in patients
      with hypoparathyroidism. It seems that PTH treatment is safe and that it even may posses
      advantages compared to conventional treatment with vitamin D. As the renal calcium excretion
      is decreased by PTH therapy, the risk of renal calcifications causing an impaired renal
      function may be reduced. In addition, some of the hypoparathyroid patients treated with PTH
      reported less fatigue and increased endurance in response to treatment. This may be due to
      either a better regulated (i.e. more physiological) calcium homeostasis during PTH therapy,
      or due to a direct effect of PTH on the neuromuscular system. Therefore, further studies are
      needed on the effects of PTH replacement in patients with hypoparathyroidism.

      Outcome measures:

        -  Muscle- and balance function: Effects of treatment on muscle strength and balance
           function are determined using a dynamometer and a stadiometer (Meititur Ltd, Finland).
           In addition, effects of treatment on muscle function are assessed through muscle
           biopsies, electromyographic, echocardiography, and by biochemical measures (muscle
           enzymes).

        -  Quality of life: Effect of treatment on indices of quality of life is assessed using the
           SF-36v2- and the WHO-Five Well-Being Index (WHO-5)-survey.

        -  Calcium homeostasis, bone metabolism, and body composition. Effects of treatment are
           assessed by measurements of calcitropic hormones, biochemical markers of bone turnover,
           and iliac crest biopsies. In addition, bone mineral density and body composition is
           measured.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in maximal voluntary knee extension</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Balance function: Is assessed using a stadiometer (Meititur Ltd, Finland)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of treatment on indices of quality of life is assessed using the SF-36v2- and WHO-Five Well-Being Index (WHO-5)-survey.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of treatment on muscle function are assessed through muscle biopsies, electromyographic, and by biochemical measures (muscle enzymes).</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone mineral density and body composition is measured</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calcium homeostasis and bone metabolism. Effects of treatment are assessed by measurements of calcitropic hormones, biochemical markers of bone turnover, and bone biopsies</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Q CT scan of hip and spine</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of treatment on diurnal variations of measured biochemical indices, as assessed at the end of the treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours at the end of the 6 month treatment period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of treatment on indices of cardiovascular health (ECG and blood pressure), as measured at the end of the treatment period just prior to and 1 hour after injection of study medication.</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of the 6 months treatment period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">62</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoparathyroidism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>a: PTH (1-84) 100 ug s.c.inj. once a day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>PTH (1-84) 100 ug subcutaneous injections once a day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>b: placebo 100 ug s.c. inj. once a day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo 100 ug sub cutaneous injection once a day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>a: PTH (1-84)</intervention_name>
    <description>preotact 100 microgram subcutaneous a day in 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>a: PTH (1-84) 100 ug s.c.inj. once a day</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>preotact</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>b:placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>100 microgram placebo subcutaneous a day for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>b: placebo 100 ug s.c. inj. once a day</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A low endogenous PTH production as verified by low plasma levels of intact PTH,
             necessitating treatment with 1alpha-hydroxylated vitamin D analogs.

          -  At least one years of continuous alphacalcidol, calcitriol, or dihydrotachysterol
             treatment prior to study entry.

          -  Prior to start of study, participants are required to have received a daily supplement
             of at least 400 IU (10 microgram) of vitamin D (ergocalciferol or cholecalciferol) for
             at least 3 months or 25hydroxyvitamin D levels above 50 nmol/l. Subjects may be
             treated with ergocalciferol or cholecalciferol during a run-in period of three months
             before entering the study.

          -  Normal plasma magnesium level (If not, magnesium supplements may be provided during a
             3 months run in period).

          -  Plasma calcium levels within the normal reference range or slightly below (P-Ca
             ionized 1.00 to 1.30).

          -  Use of safe contraceptive methods (fertile women).

          -  Speak and read Danish.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known allergic reactions to any of the compounds in the trial medication.

          -  Severely impaired renal function (plasma creatinine &gt; 200 micromol/l).

          -  Severely impaired hepatic function (Plasma alanine aminotransferase (ALAT) &gt; 100 U/l
             and/or alkaline phosphatase &gt; 400 U/l).

          -  Previous or present malignancies (except a treated skin cancer that is not melanoma or
             treated carcinoma in situ, 2 years since last therapy).

          -  Prior radiation therapy involving the skeleton.

          -  Current treatment with raloxifene, calcitonin, systemic corticosteroids above 5 mg a
             day, fluoride, lithium, PTH, or digoxin.

          -  Treatment with anticonvulsant's (within the last 2 years).

          -  Immobilization (more than two week within the last 6 months).

          -  Granulomatous disease.

          -  Paget's disease of bone.

          -  Pregnancy / planned within the next year. Hospitalized due to chronic drug or alcohol
             abuse. Severe malabsorption syndrome.

          -  Major medical or social problems that will be likely to preclude participation for one
             year.

          -  Unwillingness to participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lars Rejnmark, MD,DrMed</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tanja Sikjær, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Osteoporoseklinikken, Aarhus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <state>Jutland</state>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 24, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypoparathyroidism</keyword>
  <keyword>HypoPTH</keyword>
  <keyword>PTH</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypoparathyroidism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

