<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00143832</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P03.0465C</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>METC 04/124</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00143832</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Risk for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder Expressed in Brain Functioning</brief_title>
  <official_title>Genetic Risk for Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder Expressed in Brain Functioning</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UMC Utrecht</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Poor inhibitory control has been proposed to be central to the cognitive deficits and
      symptomatology associated with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD). ADHD is a
      highly heritable disorder with an increased incidence among the siblings of affected
      individuals. In the current proposal we investigate the expression of genetic susceptibility
      for ADHD in brain functioning. We will study cognitive functioning in patients with ADHD,
      their unaffected siblings and healthy matched controls. Our aims are 1) to determine whether
      increased familial risk for ADHD is associated with differential patterns of brain activation
      compared to normally developing children, during the performance of tasks designed to probe
      cognitive functions that are compromised in ADHD and 2) to determine whether differential
      patterns of activation are similar for boys with ADHD and their unaffected siblings.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Poor inhibitory control has been proposed to be central to the cognitive deficits and
      symptomatology associated with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD). ADHD is a
      highly heritable disorder with an increased incidence among the siblings of affected
      individuals. Although studies investigating candidate genes are underway, as yet it remains
      unclear via which mechanisms the presence of risk genes leads to symptomatology. There is
      evidence to suggest that individuals at increased genetic risk display some of the cognitive
      deficits associated with the disorder. In particular poor inhibitory control has been put
      forward as a potential marker for familial ADHD. Neuroimaging techniques now make it possible
      to investigate the neural substrate of cognitive deficits associated with psychiatric
      disorders. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) has been used to demonstrate that the neural
      substrate of cognitive brain function is affected in ADHD. Using a task that taxes inhibitory
      systems at varying levels of task demands, we demonstrated that increased susceptibility to
      interference in children with ADHD is paralleled by differences in brain activation, with
      these children displaying a relative lack of fronto-striatal activation. In a recent study,
      we demonstrated that the unaffected siblings of patients with ADHD show cortical volumetric
      deficits, similar to patients themselves. This suggests that individuals at increased risk
      for ADHD share some of the neural basis of cognitive deficits associated with this disorder.
      In the current proposal we set out to investigate the expression of genetic susceptibility
      for ADHD in brain functioning. We will study cognitive functioning in patients with ADHD,
      their unaffected siblings and healthy matched controls focusing on cognitive control. Our
      aims are 1) to determine whether increased familial risk for ADHD is associated with
      differential patterns of brain activation compared to normally developing children, during
      the performance of tasks designed to probe cognitive functions that are compromised in ADHD
      and 2) to determine whether differential patterns of activation are similar for boys with
      ADHD and their unaffected siblings. We intend to include 30 boys with ADHD, 30 of their
      brothers without ADHD, and 30 matched normal controls in 3 studies focusing on cognitive
      control and similar cognitive functions that are compromised in ADHD. We will include 10 boys
      in each group for each study. The proposed studies will utilize variations of a parametric go
      nogo paradigm previously developed. All subjects will be asked to participate in a functional
      MR scanning session lasting up to an hour. The whole visit will last a maximum of two hours.
      There are no known risks associated with MR scanning, therefore this procedure is considered
      completely safe. By participating in a simulation prior to the scan, we will also minimize
      anxiety for the subjects. Furthermore, the study will immediately be terminated if a subject
      becomes anxious, or otherwise indicates that he no longer wishes to participate. All subjects
      will be offered a gift certificate as a token of appreciation for their effort. In addition,
      they will be reimbursed for travel expenses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2004</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control, Natural History</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional, Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>90</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 8 - 20 years

          -  Male

        Inclusion Criteria for Patients with ADHD:

          -  DSM-IV (APA, 1994) diagnosis of ADHD, according to DISC interview

          -  Scores in the clinical range on the Child Behavior Checklist (CBCL) and Teacher Rating
             Form(TRF)

          -  One brother who meets the inclusion criteria for siblings

        Inclusion Criteria for Unaffected Siblings:

          -  No DSM-IV (APA, 1994) diagnosis according to DISC interview

          -  No scores in the clinical range on the Child Behavior Checklist (CBCL) and Teacher
             Rating Form (TRF)

        Inclusion Criteria for Controls:

          -  No DSM-IV (APA, 1994) diagnosis, according to DISC interview

          -  No scores in the clinical range on the Child Behavior Checklist (CBCL) and Teacher
             Rating Form (TRF)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  IQ &lt; 70

          -  Illness of the cardiovascular, the endocrine, the pulmonal or the gastrointestinal
             system

          -  Presence of metal objects in or around the body (pacemaker, dental braces)

          -  History of or present neurological disorder

          -  For individuals over 12 years of age: legal incompetence, defined as the obvious
             inability to comprehend the information that is presented by the investigator and is
             outlined in the Information letter and on which the decision to participate in the
             study is to be based
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>20 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah Durston, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>RMI of Neuroscience, UMC Utrecht</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Herman van Engeland, M.D. Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>RMI of Neuroscience, UMC Utrecht</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah Durston, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+31 30 250 8161</phone>
    <email>S.Durston@umcutrecht.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dept. of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, UMC Utrecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Martijn Mulder, M.Sc.</last_name>
      <phone>+31 30 250 8161</phone>
      <email>M.Mulder-7@azu.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Janna van Belle, M.Sc.</last_name>
      <phone>+31 30 250 3275</phone>
      <email>J.vanBelle@umcutrecht.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martijn Mulder, M.Sc.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.niche-lab.nl</url>
    <description>Lab homepage with info for subjects (in Dutch)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fmri.nl/people/niche.html</url>
    <description>Lab homepage with info in English</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Durston S, Mulder M, Casey BJ, Ziermans T, van Engeland H. Activation in ventral prefrontal cortex is sensitive to genetic vulnerability for attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder. Biol Psychiatry. 2006 Nov 15;60(10):1062-70. Epub 2006 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>16712804</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 31, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 2, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 20, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

