<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00147693</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCAD</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ZonMw grant no 945-04-152</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00147693</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Systematic Care for Informal Caregivers of Dementia Patients: An Efficient Approach?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Systematic Care for Informal Caregivers of Dementia Patients: An Efficient Approach?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ZonMw: The Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radboud University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective is to ascertain the potential efficiency of a systematic care programme for
      caregivers of dementia patients. The research questions are:

        -  What are the costs and benefits of the Systematic Care Programme - Dementia
           (SCP-Dementia), as compared with usual care?

        -  What are the effects on the quality of life of patients and informal caregivers (spouse,
           relative), as compared with usual care?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A major challenge for future health care is the care for dementia patients and their informal
      caregivers. In usual care, the problems of caregivers often remain invisible until a crisis
      occurs. This inhibition is partly the result of informal caregivers paying scant attention to
      their own problems. Another reason is that professionals may not know how to support informal
      caregivers pro-actively (Van Hout et al., 2000). Therefore the family support programme
      (Bengtson, 1985: Vernooij et al., 2000) has been transformed into a Systematic Care Programme
      (SCP-Dementia). The reasons for choosing and studying the efficiency of this programme are
      the potential to diagnose and treat problems systematically, to cover a wide range of
      individual problems, its flexibility in connecting interventions to these problems, its
      suitability for pro-activity and the positive effects of the programme found in our previous
      study (Vernooij et al., 2000). To study its efficiency a cluster randomised controlled trial
      design will be used. Randomisation will take place in each of three participating regions.
      Professionals in the ambulatory mental health care services (psychologists and social
      psychiatric nurses) will be randomly assigned to either the intervention group or the control
      group before the recruitment of patients and informal caregivers. The study population
      consists of pairs of patients and their informal caregivers visiting the ambulatory mental
      health care service for the first time. The intervention is the training in SCP-Dementia and
      its subsequent use. SCP-Dementia consists of an assessment of the caregiver's sense of
      competence and suggestions on how to deal with deficiencies in competence. The follow-up
      period is one year. The primary outcome is patients´ admissions to nursing homes or
      residential homes. The secondary outcome is quality of life. Caregivers´ quality of life is
      assessed by sense of competence (SCQ), depression (CES-D) and physical quality of life
      (EuroQol). Patients´ quality of life by behavioral problems is assessed by the NPI-Q and the
      QOL-AD-Scale. The difference in proposed effect was based on previous research in which 14%
      of the patients in the intervention group and 28% in the control group were institutionalized
      (Vernooij-Dassen, 1993;1995). To detect a 50% reduction in institutionalization rates with
      80% power at the two sided significance level of 0.05, 132 patient-caregiver dyads would be
      needed for each of the intervention and control arm. We inflated this sample size by a design
      effect of 1.15 to 152 dyads per trial arm to allow for correlation of dyads within the same
      cluster (i.e. professional), assuming an average cluster size of four and an intracluster
      correlation coefficient of 0.05. Assuming a 25% dropout rate of patient-caregiver dyads, the
      study needed an final enrolment of 190 dyads in each trial arm. The economic evaluation is a
      cost-effectiveness analysis regarding a societal perspective. In the economic evaluation both
      costs and effects will be monetarized and consequently will result in a net benefit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients admissions to nursing homes or residential homes. This outcome is the most important input for the estimation of cost differences between the intervention group and controls.</measure>
    <time_frame>after one year follow-up period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary outcome for cost estimation is patient and caregiver related costs estimated by &quot;Resource Utilisation in Dementia&quot; (RUD), including time spent on caregiving, use of health care services by caregivers and patients and additional productivity.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">304</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia, Vascular</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <condition>Lewy Body Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diagnosis of caregivers' problems</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Professional service: treatment of problems by counseling or practical support</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pairs of patients and their informal caregivers visiting the ambulatory mental health
             care service for the first time and treated by the professionals participating in the
             study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients and caregivers not mastering the Dutch language
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Myrra M Vernooij-Dassen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Coordinator Alzheimer Centre UMC Nijmegen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboud University Nijmegen Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 1, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Prof.dr. M. Vernooij-Dassen</name_title>
    <organization>Scientific Institute for Quality of Healthcare (IQ Healthcare) and Alzheimer Centre Radboud University, Radboud University Nijmegen Medical Centre</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Lewy-Body</keyword>
  <keyword>Cost*</keyword>
  <keyword>Community (dwelling)</keyword>
  <keyword>Caregiver(s)</keyword>
  <keyword>Institutionalization</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized Control Trail</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular dementia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lewy Body Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia, Vascular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

