<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00148538</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GA-3-05-1903-RS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00148538</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Type 1 Diabetes Aerobic and Resistance Exercise (T1-DARE)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Type 1 Diabetes Aerobic and Resistance Exercise (T1-DARE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled trial evaluating different exercise modalities in previously
      inactive subjects with type 1 diabetes.

      The primary objective of this study is to determine the effects of resistance exercise
      training, and of aerobic exercise training, on glycemic control (A1c) in previously inactive
      individuals with type 1 diabetes, with background therapy meeting modern standards, including
      multiple daily insulin injections or insulin pump, carbohydrate counting, frequent glucose
      monitoring, and utilization of glucose monitoring to adjust CHO and insulin for exercise.

      Secondary aims: In type 1 diabetic individuals receiving therapy meeting the criteria above,
      to determine the effects of resistance exercise training and aerobic exercise training on
      frequency of hypoglycemia, body composition, lipids, C-reactive protein and quality of life.

      Hypotheses:

        1. Subjects randomized to resistance exercise (R and AR combined) will have greater
           reductions in A1c than in those not randomized to resistance exercise (A and C
           combined).

        2. Subjects randomized to aerobic exercise (A and AR combined) will show a trend to greater
           HbA1c reduction than those not randomized to aerobic exercise (R and C combined).

      Secondary hypotheses: We expect that both aerobic and resistance exercise will show trends to
      improvement in most listed secondary outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Type 1 diabetes is characterized by complete or near-complete absence of insulin
      secretion, generally due to autoimmune disease. Cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk in type 1
      diabetes is just as great as in type 2 diabetic individuals of the same age, even though type
      1 diabetic individuals usually have fewer additional CVD risk factors. This is likely due to
      earlier age of onset of diabetes and therefore much longer exposure to hyperglycemia. The
      incidence of type 1 diabetes is increasing throughout the world. The reasons for this are
      thought to be environmental although the exact nature of the environmental precipitants is
      not well understood. In contrast to type 2 diabetes, in which it is clear that aerobic
      exercise improves glycemic control, studies in type 1 diabetes have generally not found a
      significant beneficial effect for aerobic exercise on glycemic control, even though there is
      often reduction in insulin requirements and improved insulin sensitivity. This paradoxical
      finding may be because individuals with type 1 diabetes are at much higher risk of
      hypoglycaemia than type 2 and tend to increase their carbohydrate intake in an effort to
      avoid exercise-induced drops in glucose.

      The acute effects of resistance exercise on glycemia in type 1 diabetes have not been
      established; it is possible that resistance exercise results in a smoother or more
      predictable decline in blood glucose than aerobic training does, which might reduce fear of
      hypoglycemia and consequent overcompensation. Resistance exercise training increases insulin
      receptor protein expression, which is not true of aerobic exercise training .

      Study Design: This will be a randomized, controlled trial with a 2 by 2 factorial design
      (resistance training versus no resistance training; aerobic training versus no aerobic
      training) in previously inactive subjects with type 1 diabetes. After screening, qualifying
      subjects will enter a 5-week stabilization/run in period prior to randomization. During this
      period their diet and insulin therapy will be assessed and optimized, and in weeks 2-5 they
      will also undergo three supervised sessions of low-intensity exercise per week. Those
      demonstrating adequate compliance during the run-in period will then be randomized in equal
      numbers to Aerobic Training (A) progressing to 45 min 3X/wk at 75% of maximum heart rate,
      Resistance Training (R) 3X/week progressing to 3 sets, 8 repetitions of 8 exercises at the
      maximum load that can be lifted 8 times (8RM), both Aerobic Training and Resistance Training
      (AR) or waiting-list control (C). The exercise intervention will take place at YMCAs in
      metropolitan Ottawa. Subjects cannot be blinded as to group assignment after randomization,
      but the main study outcomes will be measured by blinded individuals (lab technologists) using
      objective methods. Subjects randomized to waiting list control will begin a program of their
      choice (A, R or AR) after all 6-month outcome measures are collected.

      Significance: This study addresses questions of clinical and scientific importance. It will
      help clarify the benefits and risks of aerobic and resistance exercise training in people
      with type 1 diabetes. Depending on the strength of any differences found, the study will
      either stand alone or provide pilot data that will set the stage for a larger definitive
      study. Even if results are substantially different from our expectations, this study will
      provide valuable new information on the effects of different exercise modalities on metabolic
      control, body composition, cardiovascular risk factors, and quality of life in this high-risk
      population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1c at the end of the 6-month exercise period</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>frequency of hypoglycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>fructosamine</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>lipid concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>apolipoproteins A1 and B</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>C-reactive protein</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FFA</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>body composition (CT &amp; DEXA)</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>compliance with the exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>exercise</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resistance and/or Aerobic Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Resistance and/or Aerobic Exercise</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>non applicable</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 diabetes mellitus as defined by the 2003 CDA guidelines (16) requiring insulin
             therapy starting within one year of diagnosis and continuously thereafter

          -  Male or female, age 16-45 years, A1c 0.066-0.090

          -  Physically inactive (see exclusion criteria below)

          -  Willingness and ability to work closely with the study physicians, nurse and dietitian
             and follow intensive diabetes therapy including carbohydrate counting, glucose
             monitoring ≥ 4 times per day, and intensive insulin therapy--either by multiple daily
             injections (MDI--insulin aspart or lispro before meals and NPH or insulin glargine
             1-2X/day) or continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) by pump therapy using
             insulin aspart or lispro for the duration of involvement in the study. CSII will only
             be an option for those already on CSII prior to entry in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation during the previous 4 months in a regular program of exercise or aerobic
             sports greater than 2 times per week for at least 20 minutes per session, or in any
             resistance training.

          -  Hypoglycemia unawareness, or severe hypoglycemia requiring assistance from another
             person within the previous 3 months.

          -  &quot;Brittle&quot; diabetes, characterized by frequent and unpredictable hypoglycemia (even if
             not requiring assistance from others) and hyperglycemia.

          -  Restrictions in physical activity due to disease: intermittent claudication, severe
             peripheral neuropathy or active proliferative retinopathy, unstable cardiac or
             pulmonary disease, disabling stroke, severe arthritis.

          -  Known or suspected clinically significant gastroparesis.

          -  Body mass index less than or equal to 32 kg/m2.

          -  Fasting serum c-peptide less than 0.2 nmol/l.

          -  Recent significant weight change (increase or decrease of 5% of body weight during the
             two months before enrollment).

          -  An expected requirement within the subsequent 6 months for medications (other than
             insulin) that will affect glucose metabolism (e.g. corticosteroids).

          -  If age &lt; 18 yr, linear growth of 1cm during the previous year.

          -  Significant renal disease: serum creatinine greater than 200 mEq/l. or proteinuria &gt; 1
             g/24 hours.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension: BP &gt; 150 mm Hg systolic or &gt; 95 mm Hg diastolic in a
             sitting position.

          -  Other illness, judged by the patient or investigators to make participation in this
             study inadvisable.

          -  Cognitive deficit resulting in inability to understand or comply with instructions.

          -  Pregnancy at the start of the study, or intention to become pregnant in the next year.

          -  Inability to communicate in English or French.

          -  Unwillingness to sign informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ronald J Sigal</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Ottawa Health Research Institute, The Ottawa Hospital, The University of Ottawa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Goldfield</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Glen Kenny</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Ottawa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stasia Hadjiyannakis</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa Health Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4E9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ohri.ca</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 27, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Type 1 Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Resistance Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Aerobic Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise &amp; Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

