<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02177682</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>115960</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02177682</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Afuresertib Monotherapy in Japanese Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Dose Escalation, Phase I Study to Evaluate the Tolerability, Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Afuresertib Monotherapy in Japanese Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Afuresertib, an AKT inhibitor, has shown in vitro and in vivo activity in multiple myeloma
      models. AKT inhibitor has also demonstrated encouraging clinical activity in multiple
      myeloma. This study is designed to determine the tolerability, safety, pharmacokinetics and
      efficacy of afuresertib as monotherapy in Japanese relapsed multiple myeloma patients. This
      is an open label, dose-escalating, phase I study. Afuresertib will be given daily until the
      subjects meet any study treatment withdrawal criteria including disease progression. A total
      of up to 24 subjects will be enrolled in the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 13, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 9, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with Dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) when afuresertib is given as monotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to 21 of Cycle 1</time_frame>
    <description>DLT is defined as an adverse event which is applicable to any of the criteria specified in the protocol and judged to have a reasonable causal relationship with afuresertib. The DLT evaluation period will be from the day of the first dosing in Cycle 1 to Day 21 of Cycle 1 or the day of DLT occurrence if any DLT occurred before Day 21 of Cycle 1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day -3 until 30 days after the last dose of afuresertib</time_frame>
    <description>The performance status will be assessed using the ECOG scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day -3 until 30 days after the last dose of afuresertib</time_frame>
    <description>Vital sign measurements will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure and pulse rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day -3 until 30 days after the last dose of afuresertib</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation subject, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day -3 until 30 days after the last dose of afuresertib</time_frame>
    <description>laboratory assessments will include haematologic tests, blood chemistry tests, coagulation tests, urine tests and lipid panel</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day -3 until 30 days after the last dose of afuresertib</time_frame>
    <description>Triple 12-lead ECGs will be obtained at designated time points during the study using an ECG machine that automatically calculates the heart rate and measures pulse rate (PR), QRS, QT, and QTc intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day -3 until 30 days after the last dose of afuresertib</time_frame>
    <description>Echocardiogram and/or Multi-gated Acquisition (MUGA) scans will be performed for evaluation for LVEF</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters of afuresertib monotherapy administered as single and repeated dose</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 0 (Pre-dose, 0.5 hour [hr],1 hr, 2 hr, 3 hr, 4hr, 6 hr, 8 hr, 24 hr, 48 hr, 72 hr) and Cycle 1 Day 8 (Pre-dose, 0.5 hr,1 hr, 2 hr, 3 hr, 4hr, 6 hr, 8 hr, 24 hr)</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters will include area under the concentration-time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinite time [AUC (0-infinity)], area under the concentration-time curve over the dosing interval [AUC (0-tau)], maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax), last observed quantifiable concentration (Clast), apparent clearance following oral dosing (CL/F), pre-dose (trough) concentration at the end of the dosing interval (Ctau), time of occurrence of Cmax (tmax), terminal phase half-life (t1/2), steady state ratio (Rs) and observed accumulation ratio (Ro)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate and clinical benefit rate (rate of minor response or better)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 weeks of Day 1 Cycle 1, at start of each cycle (except Cycle 1), and then every 6 to 9 weeks until 30 days after the last dose of afuresertib</time_frame>
    <description>Response evaluations will be determined according to the Response Criteria for multiple myeloma as stringent complete response (sCR), complete response (CR), very good partial response (VGPR), partial response (PR), and minor response (MR). Response rate will be defined as the percentage of subjects with sCR, CR, VGPR or PR. Subjects with unknown or missing response will be treated as non-responder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms, Haematologic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Afuresertib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three subjects will be enrolled and given afuresertib 125 mg orally and monitored for toxicity. After completion of PK sampling in 3 days (Cycle 0), daily repeated dose of 125 mg will be given for 21 days (Cycle 1). If no DLT event is found after 21 days of repeated dosing, up to 6 subjects will be enrolled and given afuresertib 150 mg. If afuresertib 150 mg is assessed to be tolerable, up to 6 subjects can be enrolled and given afuresertib 200 mg. If afuresertib 200 mg is assessed to be intolerable, up to 6 subjects will be enrolled and given afuresertib 150mg or 175 mg. In any Dose levels, if DLT occurs in more than 2 subjects, that Dose level will be considered as intolerable.&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Afuresertib</intervention_name>
    <description>Size 4 and Size 1 opaque white capsules containing 25 mg and 100 mg of afuresertib, respectively, to be administered orally.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Afuresertib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent is provided.

          -  Japanese females or males aged 20 years or older (at the time consent is obtained).

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of relapsed multiple myeloma.

          -  Performance score of 0 and 1 according to the ECOG scale.

          -  Relapsed after at least 1 line of systemic therapy. The preparative regimen (with or
             without total body irradiation) and subsequent autologous stem cell rescue used for an
             autologous stem cell transplant are considered as one line of therapy.

          -  Able to swallow and retain oral medication.

          -  Male subjects with a female partner of childbearing potential must have had a prior
             vasectomy or agree to use adequate contraception from the time of the first dose of
             study drug until three months after the last dose of study drug.

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of: (A) Non-childbearing
             potential (i.e. physiologically incapable of becoming pregnant): Pre-menopausal
             females with a documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy; Postmenopausal defined as 12
             months of spontaneous amenorrhea [if unclear, simultaneous follicle stimulating
             hormone &gt;40 milli-international units (MIU)/milliliter (mL) and oestradiol &lt;40
             picograms (pg)/mL (&lt;140 picomoles [pmol]/L) is required as confirmation]. (B) Females
             on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) and whose menopausal status is in doubt must
             discontinue HRT to confirm post-menopausal status prior to study enrolment. Following
             confirmation, they can resume HRT during the study without use of a contraceptive
             method. (C) Child-bearing potential, has a negative serum pregnancy test within 7 days
             prior to enrolment, and agrees to use adequate contraception from screening until four
             weeks after the last dose of study drug. Note: The recommended contraceptive methods
             are abstinence of sexual intercourse, use of intrauterine device/system, vasectomy,
             and use of condom with spermicidal agent. An oral contraceptive drug does not offer a
             reliable contraceptive method as a drug-drug interaction may occur.

          -  Adequate organ system functions as defined in the protocol

          -  Subjects with a history of autologous stem cell transplant are eligible provided the
             following criteria are met: transplant completed &gt;180 days prior to enrolment; no
             active infection (e.g. cytomegalovirus, varicella-zoster virus); meets the remainder
             of the eligibility criteria outlined in this protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chemotherapy, radiotherapy, immunotherapy or other anti-myeloma therapy within 28 days
             prior to enrolment. In addition, any toxicity (except alopecia) should be recovered to
             &lt;=Grade 1 by National Cancer Institute - Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse
             Events (NCI-CTCAE), version 4.0.

          -  Use of an investigational drug within 30 days or five half-lives, whichever is longer.

          -  History of an allogenic stem cell transplant. For patients with history of autologous
             stem cell transplant, inclusion criteria 10 must be met.

          -  History of PI3K/AKT inhibitors.

          -  Current use of prohibited medication or subject who requires any of these medications
             during treatment of afuresertib, as well as subject who cannot meet the protocol
             specified meals and dietary restrictions

          -  Current use of oral corticosteroids, except inhaled or topical use.

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus by diet, exercise or medicinal therapies including
             insulin, and with fasting serum glucose &gt;=130 mg/dL (&gt;=7.28 millimoles [mmol]/L).

          -  Use of anticoagulants other than low dose (prophylactic) anticoagulants for subject
             whose Prothrombin time (PT)/international normalization ratio (INR) and activated
             partial thromboplastin time (APTT) is &lt;=1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN).

          -  Presence of active Gastro-intestinal (GI) disease or other condition that could affect
             GI absorption (e.g. malabsorption syndrome) or predispose subject to GI ulceration.

          -  Any major surgery that required hospitalization within last four weeks.

          -  Any serious or unstable pre-existing medical, psychiatric, or other conditions
             (including lab abnormalities) that could interfere with subject safety or obtaining
             informed consent.

          -  Active infection requiring parenteral or oral anti-infective treatment.

          -  Evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases (e.g., unstable or uncompensated
             respiratory, hepatic, renal, or cardiac disease).

          -  Central nervous system malignancies, primary or metastatic.

          -  Diagnosis of or treatment history for another malignancy within 2 years, with the
             exception of complete resection of basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma of
             the skin, an in situ malignancy, or low-risk prostate cancer after curative therapy.

          -  History of known infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          -  Positive hepatitis B surface (HBs) antigen or hepatitis B virus (HBV) Deoxyribonucleic
             acid (DNA). If negative for HBs antigen and positive for both or either of hepatitis B
             core (HBc) and HBs antibodies, HBV DNA needs to be negative.

          -  Positive hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody

          -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt;450 milliseconds (msec) or QTc &gt; 480 msec for patients
             with bundle branch block. The QTc is the QT interval corrected for heart rate
             according to Fridericia's formula (QTcF). Note: The QTc should be based on single or
             averaged QTc values of triplicate ECGs obtained over a brief recording period.

          -  Other clinically significant ECG abnormalities, including 2nd or 3rd degree
             atrioventricular block.

          -  History of myocardial infarction, acute coronary syndromes (including unstable
             angina), coronary angioplasty or stenting or bypass grafting within the past six
             months.

          -  Class III or IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart Association (NYHA)
             functional classification system

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any components of the study treatment.

          -  Others who are considered as inappropriate to participate in this study by
             investigators.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aichi</city>
        <zip>467-8602</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <zip>811-1395</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miyagi</city>
        <zip>980-8574</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Niigata</city>
        <zip>951-8566</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>104-0045</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 29, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 30, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AKT inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Afuresertib</keyword>
  <keyword>multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

