<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02172703</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>aICP_CH_TBI_SAH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02172703</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-invasive Brain Pressure Monitoring After Trauma or Hemorrhage</brief_title>
  <official_title>Validation of Non-invasive Absolute Intracranial Pressure Monitoring in Patients After Traumatic Brain Injury and Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Javier Fandino, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kaunas University of Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kantonsspital Aarau</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Increased intracranial pressure (ICP) is considered to be the most important
      intracranial mechanism causing secondary injury in patients admitted after acute traumatic
      brain injury (TBI) and intracranial haemorrhage (ICB) including subarachnoid haemorrhage
      (SAH). Currently, ICP can be measured and monitored only using invasive techniques. The two
      ICP measurement methods available - intraventricular and intraparenchymal - require both a
      neurosurgical procedure in order to implant the catheter and probes within the brain. The
      invasiveness of current methods for ICP measurement limits the diagnoses reliability of many
      neurological conditions in which intracranial hypertension is a treatable adverse event. A
      reliable, accurate and precise non-invasive method to measure ICP would be of considerable
      clinical value, enabling ICP measurement without the need of a surgical intervention.

      Aim:

      The aim of this study is to validate a novel non-invasive ICP measurement device by comparing
      its measurement with the &quot;gold standard&quot; invasive ICP-measurement by intracranial probe. The
      device used in this study has been been developed in the Telematic Science Laboratory at the
      Kaunas University of Technology, Lithuania.

      Methods:

      The non-invasive ICP measurement method will be assessed prospectively using repeatable
      simultaneous non-invasive and invasive (standard with intracranial probe) ICP measurements on
      patients presenting with TBI and SAH. The device method is based on two-depth transcranial
      doppler (TCD) technique for simultaneously measuring flow velocities in the intracranial and
      extracranial segments of the ophthalmic artery (OA). The intracranial segment of the OA is
      compressed by ICP and the extracranial segment of the OA is compressed by the pressure Pe
      externally applied by the device. Two-depth TCD device is used as an accurate indicator of
      the balance point (Pe = ICP) when the measured parameters of blood flow velocity waveforms in
      the intracranial and extracranial segments of OA are identical. The device has the same
      ultrasound transmission parameters as existing TCD devices and meets all patient safety
      criteria.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Simultaneously measured non-invasive and invasive ICP values in mmHg (millimeters of mercury)</measure>
    <time_frame>Max. 3 times/day - approx. 24hours to 30 days after addmission (as long as patient is monitored with invasive ICPprobe)</time_frame>
    <description>Physiological parameters of TBI or SAH patients of primary interest are simultaneously measured paired non-invasive and invasive ICP values.
New measurement is only initiated if ICP changes for more than 4mmHg in comparison to proceeding measurement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI)</condition>
  <condition>Subarachnoid Hemorrhage (SAH)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-invasive ICP measurement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>non-invasive ICP measurement with NON-INVASIVE ICP ABSOLUTE VALUE METER (carried out simultainusly with standard invasive ICP measurement catheter and probes)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-invasive ICP measurement device</intervention_name>
    <description>The non-invasive ICP measurement device used in this study has been developed in the Telematic Science Laboratory at the Kaunas University of Technology, Lithuania.
The non-invasive method is based on two-depth TCD technique for simultaneously measuring flow velocities in the intracranial and extracranial segments of the ophthalmic artery (OA).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-invasive ICP measurement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NON-INVASIVE ICP ABSOLUTE VALUE METER</other_name>
    <other_name>(Vittamed 205)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients, age ≥ 18 years, admitted after TBI or SAH at the Neurosurgical
             Department, Kantonsspital Aarau, Switzerland.

          -  Patients under sedation and ICP monitoring

          -  Informed consent will be obtained from the relatives prior to initiation of the
             measurements.

          -  study inclusion/informed consent from relatives possible between hour 24 to 72 after
             admission to the hospital

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 years at study entry.

          -  Patients with wounds, scars including the front orbital region.

          -  Perforating or penetrating mechanism of TBI

          -  Patients with orbital injury or abnormal blood flow in both Ophthalmic Arteries

          -  Patients with previous retina surgery

          -  Patients with previous cataract surgery

          -  Patients with any known ocular condition that may be worsened by sustained eye
             pressure in the opinion of the subject's ophthalmologist

          -  Patients with radiological signs of calcification or atheromatose plaques in the
             internal carotid artery detected by CT or angiography (performed prior and
             independently of the study)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Javier Fandino, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Kantonsspital Aarau, Aarau, Switzerland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kantonsspital Aarau, Department of Neurosurgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarau</city>
        <state>Aargau</state>
        <zip>5001</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 10, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kantonsspital Aarau</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Javier Fandino, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chairman, Department of Neurosurgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TBI</keyword>
  <keyword>SAH</keyword>
  <keyword>ICP</keyword>
  <keyword>non invasive measurement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

