<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02179177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00048953</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02179177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Apixaban in Patients With Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Daily Prophylaxis Dose Anticoagulation With a Factor Xa Inhibitor (Apixaban) in Patients With Sickle Cell Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nirmish Shah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In patients with SCD, the use of low dose anticoagulation as an outpatient may lead to a
      significant decrease in morbidity and as a result, decrease healthcare utilization and costs.
      This study attempts to critically avoid admissions by reducing daily pain scores and pain
      crisis as an outpatient by use of a novel oral anticoagulant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is not only significant morbidity associated with patients with SCD, but also costs
      associated with the numerous hospitalizations. Small studies have been unable to show clear
      benefit of the use of low dose anticoagulation in SCD due to limited sample size or the
      inclusion of very specific populations. However, studies have shown a decrease in the level
      of elevated prothrombotic markers with anticoagulation, and one study using full dose
      anticoagulation in patients with a generally milder form of SCD (with high protective
      hemoglobin) showed more rapid decrease in clinical pain with use of anticoagulation,
      suggesting a possible benefit of such therapy. Due to the paucity of data to support
      therapeutic dose LMWH in the more severe forms of SCD seen in the United States, we have
      chosen prophylactic dose anticoagulation. This study proposal attempts to critically avoid
      admissions by reducing daily pain scores and pain crisis as an outpatient by use of a novel
      oral anticoagulant.

      The development of novel anticoagulants such as oral direct factor Xa (FXa) inhibitors allows
      the realistic use of daily prophylactic dosing as an outpatient. Past studies as detailed
      earlier have been limited by attempts to use subcutaneous injections or frequent, close
      monitoring for acenocoumarol treatment, both which are not ideal for chronic daily use.
      Furthermore, the use of global assays such calibrated automated thrombography (CAT) have
      shown further details about thrombin generation in a population which is hypercoagulable at
      baseline.

      This is a double blind, parallel group, placebo controlled feasibility study with an
      enrollment target of 60 patients (30 per arm). All subjects that meet inclusion criteria as
      an outpatient, following a 1 month observation, will be randomized to receive an oral
      prophylactic dose factor Xa inhibitor (Apixaban 2.5mg po bid) or placebo for 6 months.
      Subjects will return for a 30 day (+/- 5 days) follow-up visit after the End of Treatment
      (EOT) visit. Initial randomization will occur by computerized randomization technique by the
      investigational drug services (IDS) at Duke University Medical Center.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean daily pain score in outpatients with SCD</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>After randomization and initial blood draw,patients will be given a daily pain log. Patients record daily pain scores and return in 1 month (+/- 5 days) at which time patients will be given a 1 month supply of study drug. Patients will return monthly (+/- 5 days) to return daily pain logs, verify compliance to medication, review completion of daily pain logs, and give additional study drug for the next month. Patients must adhere to daily administration of study drug and miss no more than 2 doses per week. Clinical pain scores will also be performed with each visit. The primary pain assessment tool will be a 10-cm horizontal visual analog scale (VAS), with &quot;0&quot; corresponding to no pain at one end and &quot;10&quot; indicating the worst pain at the other. The daily pain log will include the VAS and if the patient classifies their pain as 'crisis' or not. Patients will be called monthly between in person visits to assess for AE/SAE and to reinforce the importance of medication compliance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in thrombin generation from enrollment to 2 months following initiation of study drug.</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment to 2 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigator will analyze the change in thrombin generation from enrollment to 2 months following initiation of study drug. The investigator hypothesizes that the anticoagulation drug will cause a decrease in thrombin generation from baseline to two months. From the literature the standard deviation of the D-dimer measure per patient is 500. With a total of 60 patients randomized equally to each drug sequence, and conservatively assuming no correlation between D-dimer values from baseline to 2 months on the same patient, we achieve a power of 0.863 to detect a mean D-dimer difference in the change from baseline to 2 months between the placebo and the daily prophylactic anticoagulation dose groups of 250 mg/l {= [(1000-750) - (1000-1000)] mg/l} for a one-sided 0.05 test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of daily pain scores while hospitalized between treatment arms</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary analysis will be performed to evaluate differences when patients are hospitalized and on study drug versus placebo, as well as healthcare utilization for patients treated with Apixaban.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of hospitalizations during each treatment period.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary analysis will be performed to evaluate differences when patients are hospitalized and on study drug versus placebo, as well as healthcare utilization for patients treated with Apixaban.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Vaso-occlusive Crisis</condition>
  <condition>Reduction in Hospitalizations</condition>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active drug Apixaban 2.5mg taken by mouth twice a day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sugar pills that look like Apixaban that will be taken by mouth twice a day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apixaban</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug is taken by mouth twice a day for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  documented HgbSS, SC or HgbS-beta0 thalassemia,

          -  age ≥18 years old and ≤80,

          -  seen in outpatient clinic ≥2 times in past year

          -  seen for an acute care visit (hospitalization, emergency department, or day hospital
             visit) for pain &gt;2 times in the past year.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hospitalization or day hospital visit for pain crisis within the past 2 weeks

          -  Patients with ≥10 acute care visits within the past year will be excluded

          -  Creatinine &gt;3.0 mg/dL

          -  creatinine ≥1.5 mg/dL AND weight ≤60 kg

          -  chronic use of antiplatelet or anticoagulation medication

          -  Patients with known vasculopathy or Moya-Moya

          -  platelet count &lt;100 X 109/L

          -  AST or ALT &gt;3 times normal

          -  chronic red blood cell transfusions (scheduled transfusions)

          -  packed red blood cell transfusion within the past 2 months

          -  Use of CYP3A4 and P-gp inhibitor medications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nirmish Shah, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nirmish Shah</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vaso-occlusive crisis</keyword>
  <keyword>Reduction in hospitalizations</keyword>
  <keyword>Sickle Cell Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apixaban</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

