<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02176980</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00046518</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02176980</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hepatitis C Alcohol Reduction Treatment</brief_title>
  <acronym>HepART-RCT</acronym>
  <official_title>Hepatitis C Alcohol Reduction Treatment - Randomized Controlled Trial (Hep ART-RCT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Durham VA Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Subjects are being asked to take part in a research study to test two levels of alcohol
      services for patients with hepatitis C virus (HCV) who drink alcohol. The two levels differ
      in intensity of alcohol services and in whether or not they include a focus on liver health.
      The study will look at which level of alcohol services best decreases alcohol use among
      patients with HCV.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For people infected with hepatitis C virus (HCV), alcohol use increases the risk of
      hepatocellular carcinoma and progressive liver fibrosis, which can lead to cirrhosis and
      liver-related mortality. Integrated models of care that incorporate treatment for alcohol
      use, substance use, and mental health comorbidities have been called for, but few empirically
      tested models exist.

      In an R21 study, we developed and manualized an integrated behavioral-medical treatment model
      for patients with HCV who consume alcohol. Investigators successfully implemented a
      standardized alcohol screening in a liver clinic using the Alcohol Use Disorders
      Identification Test (AUDIT) instrument; recruited 60 patients; retained participants in group
      and individual therapy; integrated care between an addictions therapist and medical
      providers; and achieved an 85% six-month interview response rate. The alcohol abstinence rate
      improved from 0% at baseline to 44% at 6 months. Mean Addiction Severity Index scores were
      reduced by 50% for alcohol from .24 to .12, and decreased for drug use from .05 to .03. The
      percentage of heavy drinkers decreased from 47% to 24% (Proeschold-Bell et al., 2011).

      This study will conduct a randomized controlled trial that compares medical
      provider-delivered brief alcohol counseling plus our on-site six-month integrated treatment
      to brief alcohol counseling plus outside alcohol treatment referral in 279 HCV-infected
      patients with qualifying AUDIT alcohol scores at baseline. Participants in both arms will be
      treated at the Duke and UNC Liver Clinics and the Durham Veterans Affairs Medical Center.
      Outcome variables will be assessed at baseline, 3, 6, and 12 months. The aims are to 1)
      evaluate alcohol abstinence; 2) determine differences in secondary outcomes between study
      arms; and 3) conduct a cost effectiveness analysis. Investigators hypothesize that the
      intervention will significantly improve alcohol abstinence rates and significantly decrease
      relapse rates compared to the comparison. Investigators further hypothesize that intervention
      participants will report fewer drinks per week than comparison participants, have fewer
      positive drug screens than comparison participants, and meet the $50,000 per quality-adjusted
      life year gained standard established in the health economics literature.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol abstinence rates at 6 months after consent</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will compare the two treatment arms on occurrence and amount of past 180 days of drinking using the timeline follow-back method, allowing the investigators to assess change in number of drinking days, periods of abstinence, and total grams of alcohol consumed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse rate at 12 months after consent</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will compare the two treatment arms on periods of abstinence and number of drinking days using the timeline follow-back method for the 180 days between 6 and 12 months since study consent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other alcohol use indicators</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>At 3, 6 and 12 months, investigators will assess the number of heavy drinking days and grams of alcohol consumed and compare between the two treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Illicit drug use</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>At 3, 6 and 12 months, investigators will assess illicit drug use based on positive/negative urine toxicology screens and compare between the two treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost effectiveness analysis of the intervention versus brief alcohol counseling and referral out</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) will be absolute difference in costs divided by the absolute difference in various effectiveness measures between the 2 interventions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">182</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C, Chronic; AUD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medical provider (MP) brief alcohol counseling &amp; referral</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Screening of HCV-infected patients for alcohol use using the 10-item Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT).
Patients self-administer the AUDIT.
HCV providers review the AUDIT with the patient.
If the patient is using any alcohol, the HCV provider conducts brief alcohol counseling using the FRAMES model, based on the evidence-based Screening, Brief Intervention, and Referral to Treatment (SBIRT) method.
Medical provider will explain the importance of alcohol abstinence in the presence of HCV infection.
Patient is referred to an alcohol treatment programs outside the liver clinic. Typical counseling will take the form of individual and group therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brief alcohol counseling &amp; 6 months of HCV-alcohol treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Steps 1 through 5 as described in comparator arm above.
6 months of group therapy, offered weekly.
6 months of individual therapy, in person or by phone, offered every two weeks.
Therapy content emphasizes interplay between alcohol use and liver health/HCV.
Informal collaboration between HCV providers and addictions therapists.
Shared EMR charting.
Referral to study-provided psychiatry as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brief alcohol counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Medical provider gives feedback on how the patient's alcohol use may affect their current and future health, noting that it is the patient's responsibility to change behavior; giving advice to stop drinking based on medical concern; giving a menu of options for cutting down on drinking; expressing empathy; and reinforcing the patient's self-efficacy to change.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Medical provider (MP) brief alcohol counseling &amp; referral</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group and Individual Therapy Sessions</intervention_name>
    <description>Session content integrates HCV and alcohol issues in treatment, liver health, and personal realms. Sessions include psychoeducational content on how alcohol affects the liver among people with HCV; HCV stigma; family issues around drinking and the HCV diagnosis; nutrition; life goals and positive affect; and alcohol reduction strategies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Brief alcohol counseling &amp; 6 months of HCV-alcohol treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  Ever HCV-infected chronic HCV

          -  Appropriate score on the Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test (AUDIT)

               -  Females, ≥4

               -  Males, ≥8

          -  Consumed alcohol in past 60 days

          -  Not currently attending alcohol treatment services more than once every two weeks. If
             you attend treatment services at least once every two weeks, you must have either
             drunk alcohol heavily in the past 2 weeks or have drunk alcohol at least 7 of the past
             14 days or your medical provider must have assessed that you would benefit from
             alcohol treatment services offered by this study

             * Patient at one of the 3 clinic sites

          -  18 or older

          -  English-speaking

          -  OK to have HIV, substance use or other co-morbidities, or receiving HCV antiviral
             treatment

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Psychotic

          -  Insurmountable transportation barriers (can receive individual therapy by phone but
             need appointments with HCV provider at 3 and 6 months and ideally some in-person group
             therapy)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Muir, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Proeschold-Bell RJ, Patkar AA, Naggie S, Coward L, Mannelli P, Yao J, Bixby P, Muir AJ. An integrated alcohol abuse and medical treatment model for patients with hepatitis C. Dig Dis Sci. 2012 Apr;57(4):1083-91. doi: 10.1007/s10620-011-1976-4. Epub 2011 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22134784</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HCV</keyword>
  <keyword>hepatitis C</keyword>
  <keyword>alcohol</keyword>
  <keyword>integrated care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

