<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02178722</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INCB 24360-202/ ECHO-202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02178722</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1/2 Study Exploring the Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) in Combination With Epacadostat (INCB024360) in Subjects With Selected Cancers (INCB 24360-202 / MK-3475-037 / KEYNOTE-037/ ECHO-202)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Study Exploring the Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) in Combination With Epacadostat (INCB024360) in Subjects With Selected Cancers (KEYNOTE-037/ ECHO-202)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Incyte Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Incyte Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the safety, tolerability, and efficacy when combining
      MK-3475 and INCB024360 in subjects with certain cancers. This study will be conducted in 2
      phases, Phase 1 and Phase 2.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1: Number of subjects with dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) of INCB024360 in combination with MK-3475</measure>
    <time_frame>56 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: Objective response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed every 9 weeks for duration of study participation which is estimated to be 18 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Response is measured every 9 weeks for duration of study participation which is estimated to be 18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability of INCB024360 in combination with MK-3475</measure>
    <time_frame>Adverse events are assessed every 3 weeks for duration of study participation which is estimated to be 18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients are checked for survival every 12 weeks for duration of study participation which is estimated to be 18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">508</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer (CRC)</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma (RCC)</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <condition>UC (Urothelial Cancer)</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1: MK-3475 + INCB024360</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase 1: MK-3475 + INCB024360 25 mg twice a day (BID) as starting dose, followed by dose escalations (Phase 1) until recommended phase 2 dose of INCB024360 is determined</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2: MK-3475 + INCB024360</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>(recommended phase 2 dose)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3475</intervention_name>
    <description>IV infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1: MK-3475 + INCB024360</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2: MK-3475 + INCB024360</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>INCB024360</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral daily dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1: MK-3475 + INCB024360</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2: MK-3475 + INCB024360</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with histologically or cytologically NSCLC, melanoma, transitional cell
             carcinoma of the genitourinary (GU) tract, renal cell cancer, triple negative breast
             cancer, adenocarcinoma of the endometrium or squamous cell carcinoma of the head and
             neck (Phase 1).

          -  Subjects with histologically confirmed melanoma, NSCLC, transitional cell carcinoma of
             the GU tract, TNBC, SCCHN, ovarian cancer, MSI high colorectal cancer (CRC), RCC,
             gastric cancer, HCC and DLBCL (Phase 2).

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 12 weeks.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 - 1.

          -  Presence of measurable disease per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors
             (RECIST) 1.1 or Lugano Classification for subjects with DLBCL.

          -  Laboratory and medical history parameters within protocol-defined range.

          -  For Phase 1: Subjects who have advanced or metastatic disease as noted above that have
             received at least one prior therapy or have advanced or metastatic disease for which
             no curative treatment is available may be enrolled.

          -  For Phase 2 expansion cohorts: Subjects with NSCLC, melanoma (checkpoint inhibitor
             naïve, primary refractory melanoma, relapsed melanoma), transitional cell carcinoma of
             the GU tract, SCCHN, ovarian cancer, MSI high CRC, RCC, DLBCL, and TNBC.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: NSCLC

                    -  Subjects who have received at least 1 prior platinum-based therapy. Subjects
                       who have a non-platinum-based regimen may be enrolled with medical monitor
                       approval.

                    -  Tumors with epidermal growth factor receptor mutation positive or anaplastic
                       lymphoma kinase fusion oncogene positive treated with a tyrosine kinase
                       inhibitor are permitted; however, subjects should have progressed on or be
                       intolerant to the targeted therapy.

                    -  Subjects must not have received immunotherapy with programmed death
                       receptor-1 (PD-1) or cytotoxic T-lymphocyte antigen (CTLA-4) targeted
                       therapy.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: Melanoma

                    -  Documentation of V600E-activating BRAF mutation status.

                    -  Prior systemic therapy requirements.

                    -  Melanoma immune checkpoint-naïve: Subjects must not have received
                       immunotherapy with anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-CTLA-4 therapy. Exception:
                       Prior anti−CTLA-4 in the adjuvant setting would be permitted.

                    -  Primary refractory melanoma: Subjects must have received prior treatment
                       with anti-PD-1 or anti-PD-L1 therapy (alone or as part of a combination) in
                       the advanced or metastatic setting and have progressive disease as their
                       best response to treatment that is confirmed 4 weeks later.

                    -  Relapsed melanoma: Subjects must have received prior anti−PD-1 or anti−PD-L1
                       therapy (alone or as part of a combination) in the advanced or metastatic
                       setting and achieved partial response ore complete response but later have
                       confirmed progressive disease.

                    -  Subjects enrolling in the primary refractory or relapsed melanoma must be
                       willing to undergo mandatory pretreatment and on-treatment biopsies.

                    -  Ocular melanoma is excluded.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: Transitional cell carcinoma of the GU tract

                    -  Metastatic or locally advanced and not amenable to curative therapy with
                       disease progression on or after platinum-based chemotherapy or alternative
                       therapy if platinum-based therapy is not appropriate.

                    -  Prior PD-1 or CTLA-4 targeted therapies are excluded

               -  Phase 2 expansion: SCCHN

                    -  Histologically confirmed metastatic or recurrent squamous cell carcinoma not
                       amenable to local therapy with curative intent (surgery or radiation with or
                       without chemotherapy). Carcinoma of the nasopharynx, salivary gland, or *
                       *Subjects must have received at least 1 prior systemic chemotherapy regimen
                       that must have included a platinum-based therapy.

                    -  Prior PD-1 or CTLA-4 targeted therapies are excluded.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: Ovarian cancer

                    -  Subjects with FIGO Stage Ic, Stage II, Stage III, Stage IV, recurrent, or
                       persistent (unresectable) histologically confirmed epithelial ovarian
                       cancer, primary peritoneal cancer, or fallopian tube carcinoma.

                    -  Subjects must have received a platinum-taxane-based regimen as first-line
                       therapy.

                    -  Prior PD-1 or CTLA-4 targeted therapies are excluded.

                    -  Borderline, low-malignant-potential epithelial carcinoma per histopathology
                       is excluded.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: Relapsed or refractory DLBCL

                    -  Prior allogeneic stem-cell transplantation is excluded.

                    -  Must have received &gt; or = 1 prior treatment regimen.

                    -  Not a candidate for curative therapy or hematopoietic stem-cell
                       transplantation (either due to disease burden, fitness, or preference).

                    -  Prior PD-1 or CTLA-4 targeted therapies are excluded.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: TNBC

                    -  Histologically confirmed breast adenocarcinoma that is unresectable loco
                       regional, or metastatic

                    -  Pathologically confirmed as triple negative, source documented, defined as
                       both of the following:

                    -  Estrogen receptor (ER) and progesterone receptor (PgR) negative.

                    -  Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) negative as per American
                       Society of Clinical Oncology/College of American Pathologists guidelines.

                    -  Subject must have received at least 1 prior systemic regimen for advanced or
                       metastatic disease

                    -  Prior PD-1 or CTLA-4 targeted therapies are excluded.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: RCC

                    -  Subjects with histological or cytological confirmation of clear cell RCC.

                    -  Not curable by surgery.

                    -  Subjects must have received prior antiangiogenic therapy.

                    -  Subjects must not have received prior immunotherapy with anti-PD-1,
                       anti-PD-L1, or anti-CTLA-4 therapy.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: MSI high CRC

                    -  Subjects with histological confirmation of locally advanced unresectable or
                       metastatic MSI high CRC.

                    -  MSI status is, respectively, determined by examining CRC tumor.

                    -  Subjects may have received no more than 2 lines of prior therapy for
                       advanced disease.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: Gastric Cancer

                    -  Must have histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of gastric or
                       gastroesophageal junction adenocarcinoma.

                    -  Must have progression on or after therapy containing
                       platinum/fluoropyrimidine or refused standard therapy.

                    -  Subjects may have received no more than 2 lines of prior therapy for
                       advanced disease.

                    -  Prior PD-1 or CTLA-4 targeted therapies are excluded.

               -  Phase 2 expansion: HCC

                    -  Must have histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of HCC
                       (fibrolamellar and mixed hepatocellular/cholangiocarcinoma subtypes are not
                       eligible).

                    -  Barcelona Clinic Liver Cancer (BCLC) Stage C disease (Llovet et al 1999), or
                       BCLC Stage B disease.

                    -  Subjects may have received no more than 2 lines of prior therapy for the
                       advanced disease

                    -  Must have progressed on, refused, or were intolerant of sorafenib.

                    -  The following are excluded: Subjects with liver transplants, clear invasion
                       of the bile duct or main portal branch(es), or hepatorenal syndrome, or
                       subjects who have required esophageal variceal ablation within 28 days of
                       starting study treatment.

                    -  Prior PD-1 or CTLA-4 targeted therapies are excluded.

               -  Tumor biopsies are required. If a subject has inaccessible lesions, such as in
                  ovarian cancer, HCC, or gastric cancer, or highly vascular lesions, such as RCC,
                  enrollment may be considered with medical monitor approval, and archived tissue
                  may be acceptable.

               -  Females of child-bearing potential and males who use adequate birth control
                  through 120 days post dose.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who participated in any other study in which receipt of an investigational
             study drug or device occurred within 2 weeks or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer)
             prior to first dose.

          -  Has received prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2, anti-CD137, or
             anti-Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated antigen-4 (CTLA-4) antibody (including
             ipilimumab or any other antibody or drug specifically targeting T-cell co-stimulation
             or checkpoint pathways). Exception: Prior anti−CTLA-4 in the adjuvant setting for
             subjects with melanoma would be permitted.

          -  Has known active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous
             meningitis. Subjects with previously treated brain metastases may participate provided
             they are stable.

          -  Has an active autoimmune disease.

          -  Has evidence of noninfectious pneumonitis that required steroids or current
             pneumonitis.

          -  Live vaccine use within 30 days of first dose of study medication.

          -  Monoamine oxidase inhibitors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Jones, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Incyte Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Incyte Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-855-463-3463</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC San Diego Moores Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alita Newsome</last_name>
      <phone>858-822-7742</phone>
      <email>amnewsome@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Angeles Clinic and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90025</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Saba Mukarram</last_name>
      <phone>310-231-2181</phone>
      <email>smukarram@theangelesclinic.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>US Davis Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nichole Mahaffey</last_name>
      <phone>916-734-8381</phone>
      <email>nmahaffey@ucdavis.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Of Colorado Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lauren Draper</last_name>
      <phone>720-848-7341</phone>
      <email>lauren.draper@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Connecticut Health Center Carole And Ray Neag Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farmington</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06030-1601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher T. Sampson</last_name>
      <phone>860-679-6580</phone>
      <email>sampson@uchc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami Cancer Institute at Baptist Health, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33176</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Danieska Sandino</last_name>
      <phone>786-596-7710</phone>
      <email>DanieskaS@baptisthealth.net</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgia Cancer Specialists affiliated with Northside Hospital Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30342</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anila Lokhandwala</last_name>
      <phone>404-256-4777</phone>
      <phone_ext>9242</phone_ext>
      <email>Anila.lokhandwala@gacancer.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Chicago Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Gajewski</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-4601</phone>
      <email>tgajewsk@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Francis Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Topeka</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66618</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelly Knoebber-Carr</last_name>
      <phone>785-270-7410</phone>
      <email>Kelly.knoebber-carr@sclhs.net</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greater Baltimore Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Judy Bosley</last_name>
      <phone>443-849-3122</phone>
      <email>jbosley@gbmc.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Agnes Hospital Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Chandler</last_name>
      <phone>667-234-2966</phone>
      <email>echandle@ascension.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Center for Cancer and Blood Disorders (RCCA MD LLC- Maryland Division)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natalie Bongiorno</last_name>
      <phone>301-571-2016</phone>
      <email>nbongiorno@ccbdmd.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Hospital and Health Systems</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>University of Michigan's &quot;Cancer AnswerLine&quot;</last_name>
      <phone>800-865-1125</phone>
      <email>canceranswerline@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Health Partners Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis Park</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55426</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sophie Steele (Horton)</last_name>
      <phone>952-993-6071</phone>
      <email>sophie.horton@parknicollet.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center - John Theurer Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Morgan Finlay</last_name>
      <phone>551-996-5256</phone>
      <email>Morgan.Finlay@hackensackmeridian.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Christ Hospital Hematology Oncology, Lindner Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marsha Zartman</last_name>
      <phone>513-585-2165</phone>
      <email>Marsha.zartman@thechristhospital.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Nurse</last_name>
      <phone>215-662-7758</phone>
      <email>maryann.gallagher@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111-2497</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bernadette Foster</last_name>
      <phone>215-214-1604</phone>
      <email>Bernadette.Foster@fccc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center Hillman Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Natalie Streeter</last_name>
      <phone>412-235-1276</phone>
      <email>streeternr@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greenville Health System Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gina Norris</last_name>
      <phone>864-241-6251</phone>
      <email>gnorris@ghs.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Germantown</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38120</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bradley G. Somer</last_name>
      <phone>901-683-0055</phone>
      <email>afletcher@westclinic.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Research Institute at Tennessee Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203-2173</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erin Fisher</last_name>
      <phone>615-524-4059</phone>
      <email>Erin.Fisher2@sarahcannon.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Of Texas Southwestern Medical Center At Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pamela Kurian</last_name>
      <phone>214-648-5874</phone>
      <email>Pamela.Kurian@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Cancer Specialists</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arlington</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22031</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claudia Phillips</last_name>
      <phone>703-208-9268</phone>
      <email>Claudia.Phillips@usoncology.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Chile</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

