<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00940524</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-046</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00940524</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Induction Therapy With Cytarabine, High-Dose Mitoxantrone and Dasatinib for Patients With Philadelphia-Chromosome Positive (Ph+) Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study of Induction Therapy With Cytarabine, High-Dose Mitoxantrone and Dasatinib for Patients With Philadelphia-Chromosome Positive (Ph+) Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL): ALL-6 Protocol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is for people with a specific type of leukemia called Philadelphia
      chromosome positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (the type the patients have). The
      investigators plan to give you combination of 3 drugs (dasatinib, mitoxantrone, cytarabine)
      for the first part of the chemotherapy (called Induction). The investigators have previously
      shown that the combination of mitoxantrone and cytarabine is very effective in your kind of
      leukemia. The purpose of this study is to establish a safe dose range of dasatinib in
      combination with this standard induction chemotherapy based on side effects. If possible, the
      trial will also give us an idea of how well this combination might work in treating your
      leukemia. Previous studies have shown that dasatinib can produce responses when given alone
      for your kind of leukemia. By using the dasatinib together with the chemotherapy, the
      investigators believe that we can kill even more leukemia cells than with either treatment
      alone. The investigators will initially treat patients with a low dose of dasatinib and
      monitor for side-effects. If the initial group of patients is able to tolerate this low-dose
      of dasatinib, then future patients will receive higher doses of dasatinib. Mitoxantrone and
      cytarabine chemotherapy is the standard therapy at the investigators' institution for the
      patient's leukemia and it is the combination of dasatinib with this chemotherapy that is new
      and investigational in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the dose of dasatinib that can be safely administered with cytarabine, and high-dose mitoxantrone in patients with Ph+ ALL / lymphoid blast crisis of known chronic myelogenous leukemia.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the toxicity of this combination in these patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine Abl-mutational status at baseline and at the time of disease progression as a possible mechanism of resistance.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A phase I study designed to determine the dose of dasatinib that can be safely administered with cytarabine and high-dose mitoxantrone in Ph+ ALL / lymphoid blast crisis of known chronic myelogenous leukemia patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dasatinib, Mitoxantrone, Cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>INDUCTION- Dasatinib† (dose levels 1-3) *continuously Cytarabine 3 g/m2 IV over 3 hours Mitoxantrone 80 mg/m2 IV Myeloid growth factor on day 7 until ANC &gt; 1,000/μl x 2 days Allopurinol 300 mg BID-TID x 7 days (starting 6-12 hours prior to chemotherapy) Dexamethasone 0.1% eye drops q6h while on cytarabine (start prior to the first dose of cytarabine and continuing at least 24 hours after the last dose) IT Methotrexate 12 mg days 2 and 4
CONSOLIDATION A-Dasatinib† (dose levels 1-3) *continuously Vincristine 2 mg IV Dexamethasone 10 mg/m2/d days 2 to 29, then taper over 10 days Sulfamethoxazole/Trimethoprim 1 DS BID three times weekly days 2 to 29, then BID daily days 30 to 45 IT Methotrexate 12 mg days 8, 15, 22 and 29</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CONSOLIDATION B-Dasatinib† (dose levels 1-3) *continuously</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamide 4 g/m2 IV (age &gt; or = 60 yrs 3 g/m2)</other_name>
    <other_name>Myeloid growth factor on day 7 until ANC &gt; 1,000/μl x 2 days</other_name>
    <other_name>CONSOLIDATION C-Dasatinib† (dose levels 1-3) *continuously</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytarabine 200 mg/m2/d IVCI (continuous infusion)</other_name>
    <other_name>Etoposide 200 mg/m2/d IV</other_name>
    <other_name>IT Methotrexate 12 mg x 2 (between days 1-7)</other_name>
    <other_name>CONSOLIDATION D-Dasatinib† (dose levels 1-3) *continuously</other_name>
    <other_name>Pegaspargase 2,000 IU/m2 IV (preferred) or IM day 1 (Patients age &gt; or = 60 yrs receive 1,000 IU/m2)</other_name>
    <other_name>*If Pegaspargase is unavailable, L-asparaginase should be substituted</other_name>
    <other_name>L-asparaginase 10,000 IU/m2/d IV (preferred) or IM, three times weekly x 6 doses</other_name>
    <other_name>(Patients age &gt; or = 60 yrs receive 6,000 IU/m2/d IV or IM, three times weekly x 6 doses)</other_name>
    <other_name>Patients in CR will proceed to Maintenance therapy.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Previously untreated and treated adult patients (&gt; or = 18 years old) with a diagnosis
             of:

               -  Philadelphia-chromosome positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia

               -  Lymphoid blast crisis of known chronic myelogenous leukemia NOTE: Patients must
                  have evidence of a t(9;22) in leukemic cells based on chromosomal or molecular
                  analysis.

        NOTE: The diagnosis must be confirmed by the pathology department at MSKCC. NOTE: It is
        recognized that newly diagnosed patients may be started on therapy with cytarabine and
        high-dose mitoxantrone (which is the standard of care at our institution for treating adult
        ALL) prior to the identification of t(9;22) in leukemic cells. These patients will remain
        eligible for participation on study and will be evaluable for response if it is possible to
        start treatment with dasatinib within 30 days of receiving induction chemotherapy.

          -  Patients with adequate hepatic function (AST and ALT &lt; or = 2.5 the institutional ULN,
             bilirubin &lt; or = 2.0 mg/dl).

          -  Patients with adequate renal function (creatinine &lt; or = 2.0 mg/dl or creatinine
             clearance &gt; 50 ml/min).

          -  Patients with an LVEF &gt; or = 50%.

          -  Karnofsky performance status &gt; or = 20%.

          -  Ability to take oral medication (dasatinib must be swallowed whole).

          -  Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy
             test (sensitivity &gt; or = 25IU HCG/L) within 72 hours prior to the start of study drug
             administration. Persons of reproductive potential must agree to use and utilize an
             adequate method of contraception throughout treatment and for at least 6 months after
             study drug is stopped. Prior to study enrollment, women of childbearing potential must
             be advised of the importance of avoiding pregnancy during trial participation and the
             potential risk factors for an unintentional pregnancy.

          -  concomitant Medications: Patient agrees to discontinue St. Johns Wort while receiving
             dasatinib therapy (discontinue St. Johns Wort at least 5 days before starting
             dasatinib); Patient agrees that IV bisphosphonates will be withheld for the first 8
             weeks of dasatinib therapy due to risk of hypocalcemia.

          -  Signed informed consent, which indicates the investigational nature of this study,
             within 30 days of treatment initiation, is required.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or lactating. Women and men of childbearing age
             should use effective contraception.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled active infections.

          -  Patients who are receiving other systemic chemotherapy. Patients must have been off
             prior antileukemic therapy for at least 2 weeks (hydroxyurea is considered
             acceptable).

        NOTE: Patients who had previously received combination therapy with cytarabine, high-dose
        mitoxantrone and dasatinib will be excluded from the trial. All other prior therapies will
        be allowed, including prior tyrosine kinase inhibitors usage. Prior dasatinib use will be
        allowed (as a single agent or in combination therapy, other than the combination therapy
        with cytarabine and high-dose mitoxantrone).

          -  Concomitant active secondary malignancy requiring treatment (other than squamous cell
             and basal cell carcinoma of skin).

          -  Concurrent medical condition which may increase the risk of toxicity, including: grade
             ≥ 2 pleural or pericardial effusion.

          -  Cardiac Symptoms; any of the following should be considered for exclusion:

               -  Uncontrolled angina, congestive heart failure or MI within (6 months).

               -  Diagnosed congenital long QT syndrome.

               -  Any history of clinically significant ventricular arrhythmias (such as
                  ventricular - tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, or Torsades de pointes).

               -  Prolonged QTc interval on pre-entry electrocardiogram (&gt; 450 msec).

               -  Subjects with hypokalemia or hypomagnesemia if it cannot be corrected prior to
                  dasatinib administration.

          -  History of significant bleeding disorder unrelated to cancer, including:

               -  Diagnosed congenital bleeding disorders (e.g., von Willebrand's disease).

               -  Diagnosed acquired bleeding disorder within one year (e.g., acquired anti-factor
                  VIII antibodies).

        Ongoing or recent (&lt; or = 3 months) significant gastrointestinal bleeding

          -  Concomitant Medications, any of the following should be considered for exclusion:

               -  Category I drugs that are generally accepted to have a risk of causing Torsades
                  de Pointes including: (Patients must discontinue drug 7 days prior to starting
                  dasatinib)

               -  quinidine, procainamide, disopyramide amiodarone, sotalol, ibutilide, dofetilide
                  erythromycin, clarithromycin chlorpromazine, haloperidol, mesoridazine,
                  thioridazine, pimozide cisapride, bepridil, droperidol, methadone, arsenic,
                  chloroquine, domperidone, halofantrine, levomethadyl, pentamidine, sparfloxacin,
                  lidoflazine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renier Brentjens, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/mskcc/html/44.cfm</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 14, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 16, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 10, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>ALL</keyword>
  <keyword>ALLOPURINOL</keyword>
  <keyword>CARMUSTINE (BCNU)</keyword>
  <keyword>CYCLOPHOSPHAMIDE (CYTOXAN)</keyword>
  <keyword>CYTARABINE (ARA-C)</keyword>
  <keyword>DACTINOMYCIN</keyword>
  <keyword>DASATINIB</keyword>
  <keyword>DEXAMETHASONE</keyword>
  <keyword>DOXORUBICIN/ADRIAMYCIN</keyword>
  <keyword>ETOPOSIDE (VP-16)</keyword>
  <keyword>MERCAPTOPURINE</keyword>
  <keyword>METHOTREXATE</keyword>
  <keyword>MITOXANTRONE</keyword>
  <keyword>PEGASPERGASE</keyword>
  <keyword>VINCRISTINE</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Philadelphia Chromosome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pegaspargase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vincristine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dasatinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitoxantrone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asparaginase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Allopurinol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitogens</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

