<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00948922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-15697</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>XO5271</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00948922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Melphalan+Bortezomib as a Conditioning Regimen for Autologous and Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplants in Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Melphalan+Bortezomib as a Conditioning Regimen for Autologous and Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplants in Multiple Myeloma After Cytoreductive Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of Bortezomib when added to
      standard chemotherapy medicine(s) for treatment of Multiple Myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectives of this study are:

        -  To determine the 2 year-progression free survival in multiple myeloma with an allogeneic
           transplant using a conditioning regimen of melphalan + fludarabine + Bortezomib in
           patients &lt; 60 years of age and available HLA-matched donor and compare it with the 2
           year-progression-free-survival after an autologous stem cell transplant with
           melphalan+Bortezomib conditioning in patients &lt; 60 years.

        -  To determine the 2 year-progression free survival in multiple myeloma with an autologous
           stem cell transplant using a conditioning regimen of melphalan + Bortezomib. for
           patients &gt; 60 years of age and patients &lt; 60 years of age who decline allogeneic stem
           cell transplant.

      The secondary objectives of this study are:

        -  To determine the overall survival in multiple myeloma with autologous or allogeneic stem
           cell transplants using the above conditioning regimens

        -  To determine the response rates in multiple myeloma using the above regimens.

        -  To determine minimal residual disease status using allele specific oligonucleotides
           (ASO-PCR) by PCR and flow-cytometry for multiple myeloma cells.

        -  To correlate minimal residual disease status with 2 year progression free survival and
           overall survival.

        -  To determine the incidence of acute and chronic graft-versus-host disease (GVHD) in
           multiple myeloma with allogeneic stem cell transplant using the above conditioning
           regimen.

        -  To examine quality of life in patients treated with allogeneic and autologous stem cell
           transplants using the above conditioning regimen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 18, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS) - Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant in Multiple Myeloma Arm</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post enrollment of last participant</time_frame>
    <description>PFS with allogeneic stem cell transplant using melphalan+fludarabine+bortezomib as the conditioning regimen. Survival time will be measured from the date of transplant to the date of progression, death or the last follow-up, whichever comes first.
Progressive Disease (PD): Increase of ≥ 25% from lowest response value in any one or more of the following:
Serum M-component and/or
Urine M-component and/or
Only in patients without measurable serum and urine M-protein levels; the difference between involved and uninvolved FLC levels. The absolute increase must be &gt; 10 mg/dL.
Bone marrow plasma cell percentage; absolute percentage ≥ 10%
Definite development of new bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas or definite increase in the size of existing bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas.
Development of hypercalcaemia that can be attributed solely to the plasma cell proliferative disorder.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS) - Autologous Stem Cell Transplant in Multiple Myeloma Arm</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post enrollment of last participant</time_frame>
    <description>PFS with autologous stem cell transplant in multiple myeloma using melphalan+bortezomib as the conditioning regimen. Survival time will be measured from the date of transplant to the date of progression, death or the last follow-up, whichever comes first.
Progressive Disease (PD): Increase of ≥ 25% from lowest response value in any one or more of the following:
Serum M-component and/or
Urine M-component and/or
Only in patients without measurable serum and urine M-protein levels; the difference between involved and uninvolved free light chain (FLC) levels. The absolute increase must be &gt; 10 mg/dL.
Bone marrow plasma cell percentage; absolute percentage ≥ 10%
Definite development of new bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas or definite increase in the size of existing bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas.
Development of hypercalcaemia that can be attributed solely to the plasma cell proliferative disorder.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Regimen Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post enrollment of last participant</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity will be assessed according to Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Effects (CTCAE) 4.0 criteria and any grade 4 non-hematological toxicity up to 100 days will be recorded in all patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS) Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post enrollment of last participant</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival in patients with multiple myeloma treated with Bortezomib (Velcade®) containing conditioning regimen and autologous as well as allogeneic transplantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Molecular Complete Response (CR) Rates in Patients with Multiple Myeloma</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years post enrollment of last participant</time_frame>
    <description>Complete Response according to International Myeloma Working Group uniform response criteria. CR: Negative immunofixation on the serum and urine and disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas and &lt; 5% plasma cells in bone marrow.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">124</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Autologous Stem Cell Transplant: Melphalan+Bortezomib followed by Autologous Rescue.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant: Fludarabine+Melphalan+Bortezomib followed by Allogeneic Rescue.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>AUTOLOGOUS ARM: Day -3 bortezomib (1.3 mg/m^2) as an intravenous push over 3 to 5 seconds (follows Melphalan infusion). ALLOGENEIC ARM: Day -3 bortezomib (1.3 mg/m^2) as an intravenous push over 3 to 5 seconds (follows fludarabine and melphalan infusion).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Melphalan</intervention_name>
    <description>AUTOLOGOUS ARM: Day -4 and Day -3 Melphalan 100 mg/m^2/day IV over 30 minutes. ALLOGENEIC ARM: Day -4, Day -3 Melphalan 70 mg/m^2/day IV over 30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alkeran(R)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous Stem Cell Transplant</intervention_name>
    <description>Autologous Stem Cell Transplant: Autologous Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Rescue. Day 0 Infusion of autologous stem cells.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Days -6,-5,-4,-3 Fludarabine 30 mg/m^2/day IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fludara(R)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</intervention_name>
    <description>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant: Allogeneic Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Rescue. Day 0 Infusion of allogeneic peripheral blood stem cells.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Multiple Myeloma Criteria(International Uniform Response Criteria for Multiple Myeloma)

          -  Patients with responsive disease after any line of induction therapy

          -  A complete response

          -  A very good partial response

          -  A partial response

          -  Patients greater than or equal to 18 years of age are eligible. There is upper age
             limit of 60 years for allogeneic transplants.

          -  Patients must have a histologically confirmed diagnosis.

          -  All patients should have a life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.

          -  Patients must have undergone a complete psychosocial evaluation and have been
             considered capable of compliance.

          -  Meet the following criteria for allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplant:

          -  Must have an identified donor match defined as: HLA-A, HLA-B, HLA- C, DRB1 8/8 allele
             matched sibling, family member, or unrelated donor. [7/8 would go on separate
             mismatched trials] and be &lt; 60 years of age.

          -  Calculated hematopoietic cell transplantation-specific comorbidity index (HCT-CI) &lt;3

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who do not achieve at least a partial response (PR) by the criteria mentioned
             above with induction therapy.

          -  Patient has a platelet count of &lt;30 x 10^9/L within 14 days before enrollment.

          -  Patient has &gt;/= Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy within 30 days before enrollment.

          -  Patient has an absolute neutrophil count of &lt;1.0 x 10^9/L within 30 days before
             enrollment.

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to enrollment or has New York Hospital
             Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure, uncontrolled angina, severe
             uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, or electrocardiographic evidence of acute
             ischemia or active conduction system abnormalities. Prior to study entry, any ECG
             abnormality at screening has to be documented by the investigator as not medically
             relevant in order for the subject to be considered eligible. Left ventricular ejection
             fraction (LVEF) by multiple gated acquisition (MUGA) scan &lt; 40%.

          -  Patient has hypersensitivity to bortezomib, boron or mannitol.

          -  Female subject is pregnant or breast-feeding. Confirmation that the subject is not
             pregnant must be established by a negative serum beta-human chorionic gonadotropin
             (beta-hCG) pregnancy test result obtained during screening. Pregnancy testing is not
             required for post-menopausal or surgically sterilized women.

          -  Patient has received other investigational drugs with 30 days before enrollment

          -  Serious medical or psychiatric illness likely to interfere with participation in this
             clinical study.

          -  Patients with a diffusing capacity of lung for carbon monoxide (DLCO) less than 50%
             (adjusted) of normal or with symptomatic obstructive or restrictive lung disease are
             ineligible.

          -  Patients with a total bilirubin greater than 2.0 mg/dL excluding Gilbert's syndrome
             and serum glutamate oxaloacetate transaminase (SGOT) or serum glutamate pyruvate
             transaminase (SGPT) greater than two and a half times normal (unless due to primary
             malignancy), or a history of severe hepatic dysfunction are ineligible.

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance &lt;/= 30 ml/min within 30 days before enrollment

          -  Patients with active infections are ineligible.

          -  Patients who are HIV positive are ineligible.

          -  Patients with active leptomeningeal involvement are ineligible. Patients with a
             history of previous cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) tumor involvement without symptoms or
             signs are eligible provided the CSF is now free of disease on lumbar puncture, and MRI
             of the brain shows no tumor involvement. Patients with severe symptomatic central
             nervous system (CNS) disease of any etiology are ineligible.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus defined as a random
             glucose level of &gt; 400 in the 30 days prior to initiation of study therapy; or
             uncompensated major thyroid or adrenal dysfunction are ineligible.

          -  Patients with an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of &gt;/=
             2(Karnofsky &lt; 50%) are ineligible.

          -  Patients with an ECOG performance status of 2 to 3(Karnofsky 30-50%), secondary to
             bone pain, may be enrolled.

          -  Patients with an ECOG performance status of 2 to 3(Karnofsky 30-50%), secondary to a
             potentially reversible disease-related problem, may be enrolled.

          -  Patients with any previous malignancy other than non-melanoma skin cancer are
             ineligible, unless the patient is without evidence of disease &gt;/= 5 years after the
             treatment for the cancer was completed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melissa Alsina, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.moffitt.org</url>
    <description>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center &amp; Research Institute website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 28, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 28, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 29, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>myeloma proteins</keyword>
  <keyword>autologous</keyword>
  <keyword>allogeneic</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

