<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02103959</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CMX-2043-2aK</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02103959</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of CMX-2043 for Protection of the Heart and Kidneys in Subjects Undergoing Coronary Angiography</brief_title>
  <acronym>CARIN</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Comparative, Randomized, Multi-Center, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled, Phase 2a Study of the Safety and Efficacy of CMX-2043 for Periprocedural Injury Protection in Subjects Undergoing Coronary Angiography at Risk of Radio-contrast Induced Nephropathy (CARIN)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ischemix, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ischemix, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate CMX-2043 for prevention of renal and cardiac
      injury associated with coronary angiography in patients with acute coronary syndrome (ACS),
      but excluding ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) patients. This study will
      specifically examine the ability of CMX-2043 to prevent acute renal injury following coronary
      angiography. The study will also examine the ability of CMX 2043 for prevention of
      periprocedural cardiac injury. Information will be obtained relating to the ability of CMX
      2043 for prevention of major adverse cardiac and renal events following the procedure.
      Additional information will be obtained in this study to evaluate safety of the drug. Dose
      and regimen information will also be obtained for future clinical studies of CMX-2043.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevention of acute kidney injury (AKI).</measure>
    <time_frame>Three days</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in the incidence of AKI as determined by the KDIGO definition of AKI compared to placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in biomarkers of AKI</measure>
    <time_frame>Three days</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in renal injury as determined by renal biomarkers in the treatment groups compared to placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trends in clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of major adverse cardiac events (MACE) or major adverse kidney events (MAKE) or other clinical complications in the treatment groups compared to placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevention of cardiac injury in unstable angina (UA) subjects who go on to PCI.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three days</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in cardiac injury as determined by cardiac biomarkers in the treatment groups compared to placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessments of treatment emergent adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">361</enrollment>
  <condition>Non STEMI</condition>
  <condition>Unstable Angina</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CMX-2043 2.4 mg/Kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bolus injection of investigational product given prior to the cardiac catheterization and placebo given 24 hours after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CMX-2043 3.6 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bolus injection of investigational product given prior to the cardiac catheterization and placebo given 24 hours after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CMX-2043 2.4 mg/kg given twice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bolus injection of investigational product given prior to the cardiac catheterization and again 24 hours after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo comparator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo comparator (PBS) given prior to cardiac catheterization and again 24 hours after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CMX-2043</intervention_name>
    <description>Slow bolus IV administration of CMX-2043</description>
    <arm_group_label>CMX-2043 2.4 mg/Kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CMX-2043 3.6 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CMX-2043 2.4 mg/kg given twice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo comparator</intervention_name>
    <description>Slow bolus IV administration of PBS</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo comparator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female subjects at least 18 years of age.

          2. Subjects with acute coronary syndrome (excluding STEMI).

          3. Subjects undergoing coronary angiography with the possibility of going on to PCI.
             However, if it is known that the patient is unlikely to undergo PCI, the patient
             should not be enrolled.

          4. Subjects must meet either one of the following criteria:

               1. An eGFR &lt; 45 mL/min as determined by the MDRD equation

               2. An eGFR &lt; 60 mL/min as determined by the MDRD equation and at least one of the
                  following:

             i. Over 75 years of age ii. Diabetes mellitus iii. Ejection fraction less than 40% iv.
             Hypotension v. Congestive heart failure (NYHA stage II or higher) vi. Anemia
             (hemoglobin below 10 g/dL at screening)

          5. Female subjects must also meet any one of the following criteria:

               1. Surgically sterile with bilateral tubal ligation or hysterectomy

               2. Post-menopausal for at least one year

               3. If of child-bearing potential, practicing an acceptable method of birth control
                  for the duration of the study as judged by the investigator, such as condoms,
                  foams, jellies, diaphragm, intrauterine device or abstinence.

          6. Subjects free of non-cardiac acute injuries or illnesses that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, could put the subject at risk or obscure the interpretation of results.

          7. Subjects willing to undergo pre-and post-study blood and urine collection, physical
             exams and laboratory investigations.

          8. Subjects willing to provide signed written informed consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects undergoing elective coronary angiography (i.e., stable angina).

          2. Subjects with end-stage renal disease (i.e., eGFR &lt; 15).

          3. Subjects with ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI)

          4. Subjects who experienced cardiac arrest associated with the current admission which
             required chest compressions or cardiopulmonary resuscitation.

          5. Subjects who experienced a life threatening arrhythmia associated with the current
             admission such as ventricular fibrillation or ventricular tachycardia.

          6. Subjects who weigh over 125 kg.

          7. Subjects with an active history of psychiatric disorders likely to limit the validity
             of consent to participate in the study or limit the ability to comply with the
             protocol requirements.

          8. Subjects with a history of alcohol or drug abuse within one year of screening.

          9. Subjects with uncorrected clinically significant abnormalities of clinical laboratory
             tests which in the investigators opinion will interfere with the study conduct.

         10. Subjects with non-cardiac acute illness or injuries in which the investigator
             considers will increase the risk to the subject or to the study's success or which
             will obscure the interpretation of the results.

         11. Subject with chronic diseases considered by the investigator unfit for the procedure
             or which will increase the risk to the subject or to the study's success or which will
             obscure the interpretation of results.

         12. Subjects who are currently enrolled or who have participated in a clinical study
             within 30 days of screening or within 5 half-lives of another study drug, whichever is
             longer.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alan S Lader, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ischemix, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 1, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Angina, Unstable</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thioctic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

