<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02101918</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2014-00642</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00642</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-0954</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9604</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9604</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00039</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02101918</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ziv-Aflibercept in Treating and Computed Tomography Perfusion Imaging in Predicting Response in Patients With Pancreatic Neuroendocrine Tumors That Are Metastatic or Cannot Be Removed by Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Perfusion CT as Predictive Biomarker in a Phase II Study of Ziv-Aflibercept in Patients With Advanced Pancreatic Neuroendocrine Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies ziv-aflibercept in treating and perfusion computed tomography
      perfusion imaging in predicting response in patients with pancreatic neuroendocrine tumors
      that have spread to other parts of the body or cannot be removed by surgery. Ziv-aflibercept
      may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking blood flow to the tumor. Diagnostic
      procedures, such as computed tomography perfusion, imaging may help measure a patient's
      response to ziv-aflibercept treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Estimate the objective response rate (RR) of ziv-aflibercept among patients with advanced
      pancreatic neuroendocrine tumors (NET)s according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid
      Tumors (RECIST) 1.1.

      II. Test the following hypotheses: that baseline perfusion computed tomography (CT)
      parameters can predict which patients with advanced pancreatic neuroendocrine tumors (pNETs)
      will respond to treatment with ziv-aflibercept.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Estimate progression free survival (PFS) duration among patients treated with
      ziv-aflibercept.

      II. Evaluate the relationship between response rate and baseline blood volume (BV) and
      between response rate and baseline permeability surface (PS).

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine whether post-treatment changes in BV expressed as relative change from baseline
      correlate with response to ziv-aflibercept.

      II. Determine whether post-treatment tumor blood flow (BF) (absolute measurement) correlates
      with response to ziv-aflibercept.

      III. Determine whether post-treatment changes in BF and, BV, expressed as relative change
      from baseline, correlate with relative change in sum of tumor diameters (RECIST 1.1
      measurements).

      IV. Determine the effect of ziv-aflibercept therapy on post-treatment blood flow (BF), BV,
      mean transit time (MTT), and PS at 4 weeks after treatment.

      V. Evaluate the changes in tumor perfusion parameters at time of progression.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive ziv-aflibercept intravenously (IV) over 60-120 minutes on day 1. Courses
      repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients
      undergo computed tomography perfusion imaging at baseline, day 21 of course 1, and at time of
      progression.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up periodically.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 18, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>90% exact confidence interval will be constructed for the overall group and for all the marker subgroups respectively. Fisher's exact test will be applied to test the equal response rates between the two groups with a one-sided 5% type I error rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated for all eligible patients using the Kaplan Meier method and reported with confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline blood volume (BV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The relationship between response rate and baseline BV will be evaluated. In addition to hypothesis testing using externally generated cut-points, refinement of optimal cut points in baseline BV separating responders and non-responders will be performed. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves will be generated. Response rates of perfusion computed tomography (pCT) subgroups defined by these cut-points will be compared using chi-square test. Response profiles of pCT subgroups defined by these cut-points will be compared using non-parametric test (Wilcoxon rank sum test).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline permeability surface (PS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The relationship between response rate and baseline PS will be evaluated. In addition to hypothesis testing using externally generated cut-points, refinement of optimal cut points in baseline PS separating responders and non-responders will be performed. ROC curves will be generated. Response rates of pCT subgroups defined by these cut-points will be compared using chi-square test. Response profiles of pCT subgroups defined by these cut-points will be compared using non-parametric test (Wilcoxon rank sum test).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in BV</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Median will be used as cut point for correlation of post-treatment changes in BV expressed as relative change from baseline with response. Response rates will be compared using chi-square test or Fisher's exact test whenever appropriate. Response profiles will be compared using non-parametric test (Wilcoxon rank sum test).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Post-treatment tumor blood flow (BF)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Median will be used as cut point for correlation of post-treatment tumor BF (absolute measurement) with response. Response rates will be compared using chi-square test or Fisher's exact test whenever appropriate. Response rates will be compared using chi-square test or Fisher's exact test whenever appropriate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Post-treatment change in BF</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Continuous parameters in relative change in pCT parameters will be plotted against best relative change in sum of tumor diameters from RECIST 1.1 tumor measurements. Pearson correlation will be used to test statistical significance. Non-parametric test will be used if appropriate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Post-treatment change in BV</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Continuous parameters in relative change in pCT parameters will be plotted against best relative change in sum of tumor diameters from RECIST 1.1 tumor measurements. Pearson correlation will be used to test statistical significance. Non-parametric test will be used if appropriate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patient parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The effect of ziv-aflibercept therapy on post-treatment BF, BV, mean transit time, and PS will be determined. Descriptive statistics of pre and post treatment values will be given. Distribution of pre and post treatment values will be graphed. Treatment induced change in values will be compared using paired-t test. Non-parametric test will be used if appropriate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor perfusion parameters at time of progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Summary statistics will be given to describe change from baseline and change from post treatment pCT. Differences will be compared using paired-t test. Non-parametric test will be used if appropriate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia Type 1</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Neuroendocrine Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ziv-aflibercept, perfusion CT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive ziv-aflibercept IV over 60-120 minutes on day 1. Courses repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients undergo computed tomography perfusion imaging at baseline, day 21 of course 1, and at time of progression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computed Tomography Perfusion Imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo computed tomography perfusion imaging</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ziv-aflibercept, perfusion CT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ziv-aflibercept, perfusion CT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ziv-Aflibercept</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ziv-aflibercept, perfusion CT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AFLIBERCEPT</other_name>
    <other_name>AVE0005</other_name>
    <other_name>Eylea</other_name>
    <other_name>vascular endothelial growth factor trap</other_name>
    <other_name>VEGF Trap</other_name>
    <other_name>VEGF Trap R1R2</other_name>
    <other_name>VEGF-Trap</other_name>
    <other_name>Zaltrap</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed low or intermediate grade
             pancreatic NET; patients with neuroendocrine tumors associated with multiple endocrine
             neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) syndrome will be eligible

          -  Patients must have unresectable or metastatic disease

          -  Patients must have at least one measurable site of disease according to RECIST 1.1
             that has not been previously irradiated

          -  Patients must have at least one lesion suitable for perfusion CT; the lesion should be
             greater than or equal to 3 cm in size in the cranial caudal direction

          -  Patient must have no contraindication for CT with iodinated contrast

          -  Patients who are on a somatostatin analogue for control of hormonal syndromes must be
             on a stable dose (no change in mg dose of long acting octreotide or lanreotide,
             changes in dosing interval of +/- 1 week is allowed) for 2 months prior to date of
             study entry

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7
             days prior to date of study entry; women who have had menses within the past 2 years,
             who have not had a hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or bilateral oophorectomy
             are considered to be of child-bearing potential; patients with elevated human
             chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) at baseline that is judged to be related to the tumor are
             eligible if hCG levels do not show the expected doubling when repeated 5-7 days later,
             or pregnancy has been ruled out by vaginal ultrasound

          -  Any number of prior lines of systemic anti-neoplastic therapy are allowed; treatment
             with =&lt; 1 prior VEGF inhibitor will be allowed

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2.5 x institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits OR creatinine clearance &gt;= 60
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  Urine protein:creatinine ratio =&lt; 1.0 OR 24-hour urine protein =&lt; 500 mg (24-hour
             total urine protein only need be obtained if urine protein:creatinine ratio &lt; 1.0)

          -  Patients must have prothrombin time (PT)/international normalized ratio (INR)/partial
             thromboplastin time (PTT) within 1.2 x the upper limit of normal

          -  Patients must have resting blood pressure (BP) no greater than 140 mmHg (systolic) or
             90 mmHg (diastolic) for eligibility; initiation or adjustment of BP medication is
             permitted prior to study entry

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 28 days elapsed from prior radiotherapy, from prior surgery and prior
             chemotherapy to the time of randomization; less than 42 days elapsed from prior major
             surgery to the time of randomization

          -  Adverse events (with exception of alopecia, peripheral sensory neuropathy and those
             listed in specific exclusion criteria) from any prior anti cancer therapy of grade &gt; 1
             (National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria [NCI CTCAE] version [v.]4.0)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) &gt; 2

          -  History of brain metastases, uncontrolled spinal cord compression, or carcinomatous
             meningitis or new evidence of brain or leptomeningeal disease

          -  Other prior malignancy; adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer,
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix or any other cancer from which the patient has been
             disease free for &gt; 5 years are allowed

          -  Participation in another clinical trial and any concurrent treatment with any
             investigational drug within 30 days prior to study entry

          -  Any of the following within 6 months prior to study entry: myocardial infarction,
             severe/unstable angina pectoris, coronary/peripheral artery bypass graft, New York
             Heart Association (NYHA) class III or IV congestive heart failure, stroke or transient
             ischemic attack

          -  Any of the following within 3 months prior to study entry: grade 3-4 gastrointestinal
             bleeding/hemorrhage, treatment resistant peptic ulcer disease, erosive esophagitis or
             gastritis, infectious or inflammatory bowel disease, diverticulitis, pulmonary
             embolism or other uncontrolled thromboembolic event

          -  Occurrence of deep vein thrombosis within 4 weeks, prior to study entry

          -  Acquired immuno deficiency syndrome (AIDS-related illnesses) or known human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) disease requiring antiretroviral treatment

          -  Any severe acute or chronic medical condition, which could impair the ability of the
             patient to participate to the study or to interfere with interpretation of study
             results

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding women; positive pregnancy test (serum or urine beta-human
             chorionic gonadotropin [HCG]) for women of reproductive potential

          -  Patient with reproductive potential (female and male) who do not agree to use an
             accepted effective method of contraception (hormonal or barrier methods, abstinence)
             during the study treatment period and for at least 3 months following completion of
             study treatment; for female patient enrolled, the following methods of contraception
             are acceptable: oral contraceptives accompanied by the use of a second method of
             contraception, or intra uterine device (IUD) or women who are surgically sterile, or
             women who are post -menopausal or other reasons have no chance of becoming pregnant

          -  Absence of signed and dated Institutional Review Board-approved patient informed
             consent from prior to enrollment in the study

          -  EXCLUSION CRITERIA RELATED TO ZIV-AFLIBERCEPT

          -  Urine protein-creatinine ratio (UPCR) &gt; 1 urinalysis or total urine protein &gt; 500
             mg/24 hours (h)

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN); if creatinine 1.0-1.5 x ULN,
             creatinine clearance, calculated according to Cockcroft-Gault formula, &lt; 60 ml/min
             will exclude the patient

          -  History of uncontrolled hypertension, defined as systolic blood pressure &gt; 150 mmHg
             while simultaneous diastolic blood pressure &gt; 100 mmHg, or systolic blood pressure &gt;
             180 mmHg when diastolic blood pressure &lt; 90 mmHg, on at least 2 repeated
             determinations on separate days within 3 months prior to study enrollment

          -  Patients on anticoagulant therapy with unstable dose of warfarin and/or having an
             out-of- therapeutic range INR (&gt; 3) within the 4 weeks prior to study entry

          -  Evidence of clinically significant bleeding diathesis or underlying coagulopathy (e.g.
             INR &gt; 1.5 without vitamin K antagonist therapy), non-healing wound
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Halperin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moffitt Cancer Center-International Plaza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moffitt Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 2, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuroendocrine Tumors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Neuroendocrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenoma, Islet Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endocrine Gland Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Islet Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endothelial Growth Factors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

