<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02105740</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UNB19739513900000030</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02105740</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypnosis in Pain Management, Anxiety and Depression in Oncological Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>HPMADOP</acronym>
  <official_title>Hypnosis as a Complementary Practice in Pain Management, Anxiety and Depression in Oncological Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gil Montenegro</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Brasilia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Brasilia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this trial is to compare and evaluate the effects of hypnosis in cancer patients,
      to reduce the level of pain, anxiety and depression. The comparison was made through the
      scores on the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) and the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale
      (HADS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Volunteers cancer patients of both gender, aged between 40 and 70 years, susceptible to
      hypnosis, with pain scores ≥ 3 measured by Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), will be randomized
      into two groups of 12 participants each. They might or might not present metastasis, whether
      or not performed cancer surgery, regardless of the location of the primary tumor, with or
      without concomitant surgical indication. It will be used the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) and
      Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) at 3 different times: at baseline, after 7 days
      and after 2 weeks of the first assessment. It will be done, in the hypnosis group, an
      hypnosis intervention. It consists of two 40-minute sessions, with an interval of 7 days
      between them, emphasizing the pain blocking, the well-being of the patient and the reduction
      of the symptoms of anxiety and depression. Then, it will be evaluated the intensity of the
      pain as well as depression and anxiety in both groups. Finally, the results of both groups
      will be compared.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Pain Score in the Visual Analogue Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>The study was done with each patient in the first three consecutive weeks after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison was made through the scores in the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) to measure the effect of hypnosis in pain among the 12 patients of the hypnosis group comparing to the 11 patients of the control group. The scale ranged from 0 to 10 points, without subscales. The better outcome occurs when the mean of the second or the third week decrease 3 points comparing with the first week, or when the mean of the third week decrease 3 points comparing with the second week.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Anxiety and Depression in the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</measure>
    <time_frame>The study was done with each patient in the first three consecutive weeks after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison was made through the scores in the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to measure the effect of hypnosis in anxiety and depression among the 12 patients of the hypnosis group comparing to the 11 patients of the control group. The scale has 14 items, seven of which are directed to the evaluation of anxiety (HADS-A) and seven to depression (HADS-D). Each item can be scored from zero to three, establishing a score range of 0 to 21 points for each subscale. The better outcome occurs when the mean is lower or equal to 9 for each subscale. The subscales are independent for each result of depression and anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Depression Anxiety Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypnosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Use of hypnosis in the reduction of the levels of pain, depression and anxiety.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Comparison of the effects of hypnosis between the control group and the experimental group regarding pain, anxiety and depression with the application of the scales.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypnosis</intervention_name>
    <description>The hypnosis intervention consists of two 40-minute sessions, with an interval of 7 days between them, emphasizing the pain blocking, the well-being of the patient and the reduction of the symptoms of anxiety and depression of the same.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypnosis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>The control and experimental groups respond in 3 different moments to Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for the evaluation of pain, and to Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to evaluate depression and the anxiety. The first meeting will be made before the hypnosis. In the second meeting, within an interval of 7 days, the scales will be applied in all patients. Before applying the scales, the hypnosis group will be submitted to the session. The third meeting will occur two weeks later, where the scales will be only applied to compare the groups.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of Both sexes

          -  Aged 40-70 years susceptible to hypnosis

          -  Who have cancer of the digestive tract and pain resulting from this cancer treatment
             These may or may not have metastasis, have done or not cancer surgery, regardless of
             the location of the primary tumor or its presence,with or without concomitant surgical
             indication.This will include patients who have pain scores ≥ 3 in the Visual Analogue
             Scale (VAS).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient not suggestible to hypnosis

          -  Psychotropic drug users,

          -  Patients with severe psychiatric disorder, except depression and anxiety

             ,- Patient terminally ill cancer

          -  Patients with tumor or cancer metastasis in the central nervous system, _ Deaf and
             people with mental disabilities and cognitive.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GIL MONTENEGRO, DOUTORANDO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNB- Universidade de Brasilia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brasilia</city>
        <state>Distrito Federal</state>
        <zip>70910900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bardia A, Barton DL, Prokop LJ, Bauer BA, Moynihan TJ. Efficacy of complementary and alternative medicine therapies in relieving cancer pain: a systematic review. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Dec 1;24(34):5457-64. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17135649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lalla RV, Sonis ST, Peterson DE. Management of oral mucositis in patients who have cancer. Dent Clin North Am. 2008 Jan;52(1):61-77, viii. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18154865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montgomery GH, Bovbjerg DH, Schnur JB, David D, Goldfarb A, Weltz CR, Schechter C, Graff-Zivin J, Tatrow K, Price DD, Silverstein JH. A randomized clinical trial of a brief hypnosis intervention to control side effects in breast surgery patients. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2007 Sep 5;99(17):1304-12. Epub 2007 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>17728216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Porter LS, Keefe FJ. Psychosocial issues in cancer pain. Curr Pain Headache Rep. 2011 Aug;15(4):263-70. doi: 10.1007/s11916-011-0190-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21400251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spiegel D, Bloom JR. Group therapy and hypnosis reduce metastatic breast carcinoma pain. Psychosom Med. 1983 Aug;45(4):333-9.</citation>
    <PMID>6622622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trijsburg RW, van Knippenberg FC, Rijpma SE. Effects of psychological treatment on cancer patients: a critical review. Psychosom Med. 1992 Jul-Aug;54(4):489-517. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1502290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Landier W, Tse AM. Use of complementary and alternative medical interventions for the management of procedure-related pain, anxiety, and distress in pediatric oncology: an integrative review. J Pediatr Nurs. 2010 Dec;25(6):566-79. doi: 10.1016/j.pedn.2010.01.009. Epub 2010 Mar 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21035021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>August 11, 2016</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>February 12, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Brasilia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gil Montenegro</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD student in medical science</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>BEHAVIORAL</keyword>
  <keyword>HYPNOSIS</keyword>
  <keyword>ANXIETY</keyword>
  <keyword>DEPRESSION</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>The recruitment process was conducted from March to December 2015. Thirty nine patients were invited. They had cancer of digestive tract from both genders, of 40-70 years, with pain scores ≥ 3 by (EVA). Were excluded: patients that used psychotropic drugs, with psychiatric disorders, terminally ill cancer, hearing impaired and mentally disabled.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Were excluded: 3 patients weren't suggestible, 3 patients who had terminal cancer, 2 patients who reported low scores, and 7 patients for other reasons such as religious issues or not accepting the technique. One patient dropped out the treatment because he had limited mobility to return to the hospital.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Hypnosis</title>
          <description>Use of hypnosis in the reduction of the levels of pain, depression and anxiety.
Hypnosis: The hypnosis intervention consists of two sessions of 40-minute, with an interval of 7 days between them, emphasizing the pain blocking, the well-being of the patient and the reduction of the symptoms of anxiety and depression.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>Comparison of the effects of hypnosis between the control group and the hypnosis group regarding pain, anxiety and depression with the application of the scales.
Control x Hypnosis Group: The control and hypnosis groups respond in 3 different distinct moments, with the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for the evaluation of pain, and the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to evaluate the depression and the anxiety. The first evaluation will be made before the research. The second within an interval of 7 days, so being that in the experimental group the same will happen after the hypnosis session and in the control group, after the follow-up visit. The third evaluation will occur two weeks later, in order to provide a follow-up to assess the efficacy of the technique. The experimental group and the control group will be compared in relation to the intensity of the pain, depression and anxiety.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="12">Application of EVA and HADS scales and after that application of hypnosis intervention</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="12">Application of EVA and HADS scales</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Second</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="12">Intervention with hypnosis and application of EVA scales and HADS (n = 12)</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="11">Application of EVA and HADS scales. One accompanying lost</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="12">Application of EVA and HADS scales and data analysis</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="11">Application of EVA and HADS scales and data analysis</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>Participated in the study, patients with cancer of the digestive tract of the Clinic Palliative Care of Brasilia Base Hospital (HBDF) who present pain ≥ 3 on the Visual Analogue Scale</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Hypnosis</title>
          <description>Use of hypnosis to reduct the levels of pain, depression and anxiety.
Hypnosis: The hypnosis intervention consists of two sessions of 40-minute, with an interval of 7 days between them, emphasizing the pain blocking, the well-being of the patient and the reduction of the symptoms of anxiety and depression of the same.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>Comparison of the effects of hypnosis between the control group and the experimental group regarding pain, anxiety and depression with the application of the scales.
Control : The control and experimental groups respond in 3 different moments to Visual Analog Scale (VAS) for the evaluation of pain, and to Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to evaluate depression and the anxiety. The first meeting was made before the hypnosis. In the second meeting, within an interval of 7 days, the scales were applied in all patients. Before applying the scales, the hypnosis group was submitted to the session. The third meeting occurred two weeks later, where the scales were only applied to compare the groups.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="12"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="12"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="24"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="55.4" spread="6.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="55.8" spread="7.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="55.5" spread="6.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Ethnicity (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="24"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Brazil</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="24"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Pain</title>
          <description>The Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) consist in a straight line in ascending order from left to right, which may be numbered from 0 to 10, in which the patient report pain intensity. Values above 03 are already considered significant for pain.</description>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7.3" spread="2.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5.6" spread="2.0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6.4" spread="2.3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Anxiety</title>
          <description>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) has 14 questions, seven are aimed at evaluating anxiety (HADS-A) and seven for depression (HADS-D). Each item can be scored from 0 to 3, establish a maximum score of 21 points for each subscale. Values ≥ 9 for each subscales indicate the symptom.</description>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="11.5" spread="4.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="11.3" spread="4.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11.4" spread="4.4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Depression</title>
          <description>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale has 14 questions, seven are aimed at evaluating anxiety (HADS-A) and seven for depression (HADS-D). Each item can be scored from zero to three, establish a maximum score of 21 points for each scale adopted as the cut points for both ≥ 9 subscales to the symptom diagnosis</description>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9.8" spread="5.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="9.0" spread="3.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9.4" spread="4.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Change of Pain Score in the Visual Analogue Scale</title>
        <description>Comparison was made through the scores in the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) to measure the effect of hypnosis in pain among the 12 patients of the hypnosis group comparing to the 11 patients of the control group. The scale ranged from 0 to 10 points, without subscales. The better outcome occurs when the mean of the second or the third week decrease 3 points comparing with the first week, or when the mean of the third week decrease 3 points comparing with the second week.</description>
        <time_frame>The study was done with each patient in the first three consecutive weeks after randomization</time_frame>
        <population>24 cancer patients were allocated. They were aged between 40-70 years, of both genders, with pain scores ≥ 3 measured by Visual Analogue Scale (VAS). One patient of the control group left the research.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Hypnosis</title>
            <description>Use of hypnosis to change the levels of pain.
Hypnosis: The hypnosis intervention consists of two 40-minute sessions, with an interval of 7 days between them, emphasizing the pain blocking, the well-being of the patient and the reduction of the symptoms.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Control</title>
            <description>Comparison of the effects of hypnosis between the control group and the hypnosis group regarding pain with the application of the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS).
Control x Hypnosis Group: The control and the hypnosis groups respond in 3 different distinct moments, using the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) to evaluate the pain. The first evaluation was made before the research. The second within an interval of 7 days, so being that in the experimental group the same will happen after the hypnosis session and in the control group after the follow-up visit. The third evaluation was made two weeks later, in order to provide a follow-up to assess the efficacy of the technique.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change of Pain Score in the Visual Analogue Scale</title>
          <description>Comparison was made through the scores in the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) to measure the effect of hypnosis in pain among the 12 patients of the hypnosis group comparing to the 11 patients of the control group. The scale ranged from 0 to 10 points, without subscales. The better outcome occurs when the mean of the second or the third week decrease 3 points comparing with the first week, or when the mean of the third week decrease 3 points comparing with the second week.</description>
          <population>24 cancer patients were allocated. They were aged between 40-70 years, of both genders, with pain scores ≥ 3 measured by Visual Analogue Scale (VAS). One patient of the control group left the research.</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="11"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>First Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7.33" spread="2.38"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5.58" spread="2.06"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Second Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.67" spread="2.77"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5.67" spread="3.36"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Third Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2.08" spread="2.61"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4.75" spread="3.13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>The clinical significance was considered with a difference of 3 points on the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for both arms with a statistical power of 95%, significance level of 5%. Statistical analysis first compared the difference of means between hypnosis and control groups during three weeks.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.034</p_value>
            <method>ANOVA</method>
            <param_type>Mean Difference (Final Values)</param_type>
            <param_value>2.67</param_value>
            <dispersion_type>Standard Deviation</dispersion_type>
            <dispersion_value>1.178</dispersion_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.224</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>5.110</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>The clinical significance was considered with a difference of 3 points on the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) with a statistical power of 95%, significance level of 5%. Statistical analysis compared the difference in pain average between the first and the second week in the hypnosis group.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.004</p_value>
            <method>ANOVA</method>
            <param_type>Mean Difference (Net)</param_type>
            <param_value>3.66</param_value>
            <dispersion_type>Standard Deviation</dispersion_type>
            <dispersion_value>0.856</dispersion_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>1.253</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>6.080</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>The clinical significance was considered with a difference of 3 points on the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) with a statistical power of 95%, significance level of 5%. Statistical analysis compared the difference in pain average between the first and the third week in the hypnosis group.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.000</p_value>
            <method>ANOVA</method>
            <param_type>Mean Difference (Net)</param_type>
            <param_value>5.25</param_value>
            <dispersion_type>Standard Deviation</dispersion_type>
            <dispersion_value>0.827</dispersion_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>2.918</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>7.582</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change of Anxiety and Depression in the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</title>
        <description>Comparison was made through the scores in the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to measure the effect of hypnosis in anxiety and depression among the 12 patients of the hypnosis group comparing to the 11 patients of the control group. The scale has 14 items, seven of which are directed to the evaluation of anxiety (HADS-A) and seven to depression (HADS-D). Each item can be scored from zero to three, establishing a score range of 0 to 21 points for each subscale. The better outcome occurs when the mean is lower or equal to 9 for each subscale. The subscales are independent for each result of depression and anxiety.</description>
        <time_frame>The study was done with each patient in the first three consecutive weeks after randomization</time_frame>
        <population>Were allocated 24 cancer patients, aged between 40-70 years, of both genders, with depression and anxiety score ≥ 9 in Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). One patient of the control group left the research.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Hypnosis</title>
            <description>Use of hypnosis in the reduction of the levels depression and anxiety.
Hypnosis: The hypnosis intervention consists of two 40-minute sessions, with an interval of 7 days between them, emphasizing the pain blocking, the well-being of the patient and the reduction of the symptoms of anxiety and depression of the same.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Control</title>
            <description>Comparison of the effects of hypnosis between the control group and the experimental group regarding anxiety and depression with the application of the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS).
Control x Experimental Group: The control and experimental groups respond in 3 different distinct moments, with the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to evaluate depression and anxiety. The first evaluation was made before the research. The second within an interval of 7 days, so being that in the experimental group the same will happen after the hypnosis session and in the control group after the follow-up visit. The third evaluation was two weeks later, in order to provide a follow-up to assess the efficacy of the technique. The experimental group and the control group was compared in relation to the intensity of the depression and anxiety</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change of Anxiety and Depression in the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</title>
          <description>Comparison was made through the scores in the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to measure the effect of hypnosis in anxiety and depression among the 12 patients of the hypnosis group comparing to the 11 patients of the control group. The scale has 14 items, seven of which are directed to the evaluation of anxiety (HADS-A) and seven to depression (HADS-D). Each item can be scored from zero to three, establishing a score range of 0 to 21 points for each subscale. The better outcome occurs when the mean is lower or equal to 9 for each subscale. The subscales are independent for each result of depression and anxiety.</description>
          <population>Were allocated 24 cancer patients, aged between 40-70 years, of both genders, with depression and anxiety score ≥ 9 in Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). One patient of the control group left the research.</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="11"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Anxiety First Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="11.50" spread="4.60"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="11.33" spread="4.41"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Anxiety Second Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8.17" spread="3.76"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="11.50" spread="2.43"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Anxiety Third Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7.50" spread="3.39"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="8.89" spread="5.96"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Depression First Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9.75" spread="5.32"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="9.00" spread="3.76"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Depression Second Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7.00" spread="5.46"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="8.75" spread="4.75"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Depression Third Week</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6.25" spread="3.98"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="7.75" spread="5.10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Statistical analysis evaluated if the difference of averages of anxiety at the hypnosis and control groups in the third week.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <param_type>Mean Difference (Final Values)</param_type>
            <param_value>1.39</param_value>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>Statistical analysis evaluated if the difference of averages of depression at the hypnosis and control groups in the third week.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <param_type>Mean Difference (Final Values)</param_type>
            <param_value>1.5</param_value>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Hypnosis</title>
          <description>Use of hypnosis in the reduction of the levels of pain, depression and anxiety.
Hypnosis: The hypnosis intervention consists of two 40-minute sessions, with an interval of 7 days between them, emphasizing the pain blocking, the well-being of the patient and the reduction of the symptoms of anxiety and depression of the same.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>Comparison of the effects of hypnosis between the control group and the experimental group regarding pain, anxiety and depression with the application of the scales.
Control x Experimental Group: The control and experimental groups respond in 3 different distinct moments, with the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) for the evaluation of pain, and the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) to evaluate the depression and the anxiety. The first evaluation will be made before the research. The second within an interval of 7 days, so being that in the experimental group the same will happen after the hypnosis session and in the control group after the follow-up visit. The third evaluation will be two weeks later, in order to provide a follow-up to assess the efficacy of the technique. The experimental group and the control group will be compared in relation to the intensity of the pain, depression and anxiety</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>The hypnosis group were not blinded to the intervention. A short follow-up was given to each patient. The use of drugs was imbalanced among participants.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Gil Montenegro</name_or_title>
      <organization>Universidade de Brasília</organization>
      <phone>556181487323</phone>
      <email>prof.gilmontenegro@gmail.com</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

