<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02103348</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-13242</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02103348</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterizing Asthma Sputum Elasticity in the UCSF Severe Asthma Research Program</brief_title>
  <acronym>CAESAR</acronym>
  <official_title>Characterizing Asthma Sputum Elasticity in the UCSF Severe Asthma Research Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to characterize subjects in terms of their sputum phenotype. The
      purpose of this study is to learn more about the impact of having abnormally elastic sputum
      on asthma severity by comparing subjects with severe as well as mild/moderate asthma to
      healthy controls. The characterization will include medical history, pulmonary function
      testing, imaging of the lungs and biospecimen collection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Asthma is a heterogeneous disease characterized by airway hyperreactivity and chronic airway
      inflammation. Published literature from the last few years has shown that asthma does not
      behave like a single disease but is more of a syndrome with vast heterogeneity in
      pathogenesis, severity, and treatment response. Various clinical phenotypes and endotypes
      have been described that advance our understanding of these differences and the mechanisms
      underlying them. We propose there is a subgroup of asthmatic patients that have sputum with
      abnormal biophysical properties. Healthy airway mucus is composed of a lightly cross-linked
      gel that is easily transported by the mucociliary apparatus, coughed and expectorated or
      swallowed. Pathologic mucus has, in contrast, abnormally high elasticity. This is due to a
      more cross linked structure which gives the sputum the properties of solid and makes sputum
      difficult to mobilize. Increased sputum elasticity makes expectoration of sputum more
      difficult and leads to airflow obstruction. Pathologic mucus contributes to airflow
      obstruction and airway infection in multiple lung diseases, including asthma. Mucus plugs are
      a particular problem in asthmatic patients with allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis
      (ABPA)The identification of phenotype of severe asthma with pathologic mucus contributing to
      disease severity may change how we think about severe asthma, moving towards therapies
      targeting mucus clearance such as in other conditions such as cystic fibrosis. Pathologic
      mucus in severe asthma is characterized by cellular inflammation, high concentrations of
      mucins and DNA polymers. Knowledge of specific cellular and biochemical constituents of
      pathologic mucus in severe asthma can guide targeted mucolytic treatment with
      n-acetylcysteine, rhDNAse, or novel mucolytic agents.

      As part of the Severe Asthma Research Program (SARP), UCSF is in a unique position to recruit
      a large number of severe asthmatic subjects within which we expect a portion will demonstrate
      high sputum elasticity. We will also through CAESAR recruit additional subjects with moderate
      to severe airflow obstruction. We will perform rheological measurement on all subjects that
      are recruited to our site and from this identify a group of asthmatic cases that have an
      elastic modulus of ≥1 or &lt;1 and compare properties of sputum from these subjects to healthy
      controls.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lung function</measure>
    <time_frame>Cross sectional over 4-6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Lung function as a measure of asthma severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory cellular markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Cross sectional over 4-6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in inflammatory cellular markers in sputum and blood. We will measure various indicators of airway inflammation and compare them with various phenotypic characteristics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CT Chest</measure>
    <time_frame>Cross sectional over 4-6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Examining CT chest in asthmatics for evidence of retained mucus.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mild-to-Moderate Asthma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Those with mild-to-moderate persistent asthma as defined by the NAEPP EPR-3 guidelines.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Severe Asthma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Major Criteria: (1 required)
Treatment with oral corticosteroids for at least 6 of the previous 12 months
Treatment with high-dose inhaled corticosteroids for at least 10 of the previous 12 months
Minor Criteria: (2 required)
Daily treatment with an asthma controller medication in addition to inhaled, or
Asthma symptoms requiring short-acting bronchodilator use on a daily or near daily basis (defined as at least 5 of 7 days), or
Persistent airway obstruction with baseline FEV1 &lt;80% predicted, or
≥ 1 urgent visits for asthma in the previous 12 months, or
≥ 3 systemic corticosteroid bursts in the previous 12 months, or
Prompt deterioration with a reduction in oral or inhaled corticosteroid dose, or
A near-fatal asthma event (i.e., intubation) in the past.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Those without asthma or other chronic lung disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Samples of induced sputum and blood for DNA and RNA extraction, plasma, and serum will be
      banked in the UCSF Airway Tissue Bank.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A diverse sample of subjects with asthma is needed to gain better understanding of asthma
        and its endotypes. CAESAR will therefore enroll subjects between 18 and 65 years with a
        physician diagnosis of asthma as well as a group of healthy subjects. The target
        recruitment goal for UCSF is 50 adults with asthma and 25 healthy controls (age 18 and
        older). Within the asthma group, an attempt will be made to enroll 60% of subjects with
        severe with the rest of the subjects mild to moderate asthma.Within the cohort, an attempt
        will be made to enroll at least 50% females and 10% minorities.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  FEV1 bronchodilator reversibility ≥12% or airway hyperresponsiveness reflected by a
             methacholine PC20 ≤16 mg/mL

          -  An exception will be made for enrollees whose FEV1 is &lt; 50% predicted (&lt;70% in
             children aged 6 to 17 years), precluding methacholine challenge testing. If
             bronchodilator reversibility is &lt;12% in these participants, a diagnosis of asthma
             acceptable to the investigator is sufficient for inclusion in CAESAR.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy,

          -  Current smoking,

          -  Smoking history &gt; 10 pack years if ≥30 years of age, or smoking history &gt; 5 pack years
             if &lt;30 years of age,

          -  Other chronic pulmonary disorders associated with asthma-like symptoms, including (but
             not limited to) cystic fibrosis, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic
             bronchitis, vocal cord dysfunction (that is the sole cause of respiratory symptoms and
             at the PI's discretion), severe scoliosis or chest wall deformities that affect lung
             function, or congenital disorders of the lungs or airways,

          -  History of premature birth before 35 weeks gestation,

          -  Planning to relocate from the clinical center area before study completion,

          -  Any other criteria that place the subject at unnecessary risk according to the
             judgment of the Principal Investigator and/or attending physician(s) of record, or

          -  Currently participating in an investigational drug trial.

        Healthy Controls:

        Inclusion criteria: Healthy subjects between the age of 18y and 65y. At least 3 of the 7
        subjects per center should be aged 35y or older.

        Exclusion criteria

          -  History of chronic diseases that affect the lungs.

          -  A history suggestive of allergic rhinitis, eczema or chronic sinusitis.

          -  An improvement in FEV1 of more than 12% following 4 puffs of albuterol.

          -  Smoking history &gt; 10 pack years if ≥30 years of age, or smoking history &gt; 5 pack years
             if &lt;30 years of age, or any smoking within the past year.

          -  Respiratory tract infection within the past 4 weeks.

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  History of premature birth (&lt;35 weeks).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John V Fahy, M.D. M.SC.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gina M Grayson</last_name>
    <phone>415-502-3472</phone>
    <email>Gina.Evans-Young@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John V Fahy, M.D. M.Sc</last_name>
      <phone>415-502-4849</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://acrc.ucsf.edu</url>
    <description>Airway Clinical Research Center website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 24, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Sputum</keyword>
  <keyword>Mucolysis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

