<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02104492</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UMA_RMTP_2014/SM</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Respiratory Sclerosis Multple</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02104492</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of a 12-week Respiratory Muscles Training Program in Persons With Relapsing- Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Research on the Effect of a 12-week Respiratory Muscles Training Program in Persons With Relapsing-remitting Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Malaga</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Malaga</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple sclerosis (MS) is the most common inflammatory demyelinating chronic disease of the
      central nervous system and the second leading cause of disability in young adults. Motor
      deficits also involve respiratory muscles. This involvement is present from early stages of
      disease and is frequently dismissed by professionals until advanced stages of disease. The
      effect of a training program of respiratory muscles is not sufficiently studied. The aim of
      this research is to assess the clinical and functional response of a 12-week respiratory
      muscles training program (RMTP) for persons with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis
      (RRMS).

      This study is consisted with two sub research:

      Firstly, a single-blind randomized clinical trial will be carried out in 40 persons with
      RRMS. Participants either will be received (n = 20) peripheric resistive muscle training
      program which will be supplemented by a 12-week Respiratory Muscles Training Program (RMTP)
      with ORYGEN Dual® device for 50 minutes, twice a week during three months or (n = 20) they
      will be received peripheric resistive muscle training program and health education program.
      Main outcomes will be strength of the respiratory muscles assessed by maximal inspiratory and
      expiratory pressure measurements (MIP and MEP). The secondary outcomes will be assessed the
      quality of life (MSQOL-54), walking speed (T25-FW, MSWS-12 and Hauser ambulatory index),
      fatigue (MFIS), endurance of the respiratory muscles (10RM) manoeuvre and peripherical muscle
      strength (Multiple-Sit-to-Stand Test and handgrip strength).

      Secondly, the qualitative research where researchers will interview participants about their
      interest in carrying out the intervention (difficulties and advantages) and identify themes
      of interest about changes in quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal inspiratory pressures (MIP) and maximal expiratory pressures (MEP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in respiratory muscle function strength with transducer measuring maximal inspiratory (MIP) and expiratory pressures (MEP)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary function test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary function test will be performed using spirometer &quot;DATOSPIR 120&quot; according to the Guidelines of American Thoracic Society and the European Respiratory Society.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Handgrip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Handgrip strength will be determined using hydraulic hand dynamometer &quot;JAMAR&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multiple-Sit-to-Stand Test (MSTS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Lower limb strength using the Multiple-Sit-to-Stand Test (MSTS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The 12 item MS Walking Scale (MSWS-12)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Walking Capacity using the 12 item MS Walking Scale (MSWS-12)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed 25 foot walk (T25FW)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Exercise Capacity using the Shorter timed walking tests with Timed 25 foot walk (T25FW)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Gait analysis (the Hauser ambulatory index) with which will be assessed the time and effort used by the patient to walk 25 feet (8 meters)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The 54 items Specific Questionnaire Quality of Life Multiple Sclerosis (MSQOL-54)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>Change in quality of life using the 54 items Specific Questionnaire Quality of Life Multiple Sclerosis (MSQOL-54)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>10 Maximum Resistance (10RM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in endurance of the respiratory muscles with the 10RM manoeuvre</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceptions Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Post interview with participants to qualitatively identify themes of interest and quality of life effects After that the respiratory muscles training program, researchers will interview participants about their interest in carrying out the intervention (difficulties and advantages) and changes in quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsing-remitting Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>a 12-week respiratory muscles training program (RMTP) with ORYGEN Dual® device and peripheric resistive muscle training program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Peripheric resistive muscle training program and Health Education Program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>a 12-week Respiratory Muscles Training Program (RMTP)</intervention_name>
    <description>Every session will be lasted 50 minutes and performed under supervision of a physiotherapist. It will be comprised of 30 minutes of progressive aerobic training program followed by peripheric resistive muscle training program which will be supplemented by a 12-week Respiratory Muscles Training Program (RMTP) with ORYGEN Dual® device for 20 minutes. Patients will be instructed to maintain adequate inspiration and expiration while using the Origen-Dual® valve at a rate of 15-20 breaths/minute. Participants will be performed five sets of 10 repetitions followed by 1-2 minutes of unloaded recovery breathing off the device, once a day, 2 days per week, for 12 weeks. The respiratory muscles training will be begun at 30% of MIP achieved at baseline and increased by 5% each week to reach 60% of the baseline assessment MIP.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Intervention Group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active Comparator</intervention_name>
    <description>Every session will be comprised of 30 minutes of progressive aerobic training program followed by peripheric resistive muscle training program and Health Education Program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control Group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females older 18 years of age with diagnosis relapsing-remitting multiple
             sclerosis according to revised McDonald Criteria 2005.

          -  Have mild or moderate impairment of gait according to Hauser ambulatory index. The
             score 1 and 5 will be included (both values inclusive).

          -  Subjects who have read, understood, signed and dated the informed consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Disability caused by other diseases

          -  Clinically relevant cognitive or linguistic disorders which are unable to fill in the
             questionnaires by him/herself

          -  Subjects used medication with corticosteroids within the last month (or 30 days) prior
             to study day 1.

          -  Have a recent outbreak (last month) not stabilized prior to inclusion in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Málaga</name>
      <address>
        <city>Málaga</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 1, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 1, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 4, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Malaga</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rocío Martín Valero</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Ph D</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>respiratory muscle strength</keyword>
  <keyword>maximal inspiratory pressure (MIP)</keyword>
  <keyword>maximal expiratory pressure (MEP)</keyword>
  <keyword>respiratory muscle endurance</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>qualitative research</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis, Relapsing-Remitting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

