<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02108080</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140080</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-AA-0080</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02108080</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterization Imaging Instruments in Alcoholics and Non-Alcoholics</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characterization Imaging Instruments in Alcoholics and Non-Alcoholics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - People with alcoholism have differences in their brains compared with healthy people.
      People who are dependent on alcohol also perform differently on behavioral tasks. Researchers
      want to find out more about these differences. They also want to see if these differences are
      related to DNA.

      Objective:

      - To see if differences in brain structure relate to personality and behavior differences in
      people with and without alcohol dependence.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults age 18 and older.

      Design:

        -  Participants will visit the NIH Clinical Center once during the study.

        -  Participants will be screened with a medical history, EKG, and physical exam. They will
           give blood and urine samples and undergo a psychiatric interview.

        -  Participants will be asked about their alcohol drinking, to see if they have an alcohol
           use disorder.

        -  Participants will play three computerized games. Some will play these games inside a
           magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scanner.

        -  MRI: strong magnetic field and radio waves take pictures of the brain. Participants lie
           on a table that slides in and out of a cylinder. They will be in the scanner for about
           90 minutes. They may lie still for up to 20 minutes at a time. The scanner makes loud
           knocking noises. They will get earplugs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: The purpose of this protocol is to obtain a standard set of assessments, including
      brain behavioral, structural, functional, and connectivity (structural and functional)
      information, on all NIAAA research participants, referred to hereinafter as Characterization
      Imaging Instruments (CII); a) to determine how individual differences in brain structure and
      evoked responses relate to generalized trait personality and behavior differences (as
      assessed by psychometric questionnaire instruments and behavioral measures); and b) to
      determine whether these individual differences relate specifically to genetic polymorphisms
      in genes governing neurotransmitter activity. Thus, our goal of the CII is to identify the
      brain structural, functional, behavioral, genetic, and other phenotypic factors that are
      associated with alcoholism.

      Study population: Non-treatment seeking adult volunteers and inpatient participants with
      alcohol dependence (ADs). Inpatient ADs refer to individuals diagnosed as alcohol dependent
      through DSM-IV-RT criteria or at least Moderate Alcohol Use Disorder as determined by DSM-5.

      Design: This study will require one visit that will include an MRI scan (if the participant
      is determined to be eligible for the scanner) consisting of a whole brain structural MRI,
      Diffusion Tensor MRI, Resting State MRI (rsMRI) as well as several task-based functional
      MRIs, while performing computerized behavioral, motivational, and cognitive/emotional tasks.
      If the participant does not qualify for the MR scans, he/she will perform only the
      computerized behavioral, motivational, and cognitive/emotional tasks outside the scanner.
      These instruments include instruments in common with a similar protocol at NIDA.

      Outcome measures: The outcome measures are differences in behavioral responses using standard
      statistical methods, in brain structural data using AFNI, FSL, SPM and FreeSurfer software,
      and in blood oxygenation level dependent (BOLD) signal measured using standard fMRI
      techniques and analyzed using AFNI and FSL software. Secondary outcome measures are to
      compare the genetic, behavioral and phenotypic factors to imaging and behavioral data
      acquired across other protocols.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 8, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The purpose of this protocol is to obtain a standard set of assessments, including brain behavioral, structural, functional, and connectivity (structural and functional) information, on all NIAAA research participants, referred to hereinafter as...</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Drinking</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol-Related Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <condition>Brain Mapping</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA: ADULT PARTICIPANTS

        All adult participants must have:

          -  Enrolled in screening protocol 14-AA-0181*, Unit and Clinic Evaluation, Screening,
             Assessment, and Management or have been determined eligible for another NIAAA study.

          -  Task performance (behavioral and fMRI) only: Are cleared based on neuromotor
             examination as determined by the screening protocol 14-AA-0181.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA: ADULT PARTICIPANTS

          -  Exclusion criteria for MR scan**

               -  Presence of ferromagnetic objects in the body that are contraindicated for MRI of
                  the head (pacemakers or other implanted electrical devices, brain stimulators,
                  some types of dental implants, aneurysm clips, metallic prostheses, permanent
                  eyeliner, implanted delivery pump, or shrapnel fragments) or fear of enclosed
                  spaces. Eligibility will be determined by a &quot;MRI Safety Screening Questionnaire&quot;
                  and verified, if necessary, by a physician.

               -  Cannot lie comfortably flat on back for up to 2 hours in the MRI scanner.

               -  Uncomfortable in enclosed spaces (has claustrophobia) such that they would feel
                  discomfort in the scanner

               -  Women: Are pregnant

               -  Are left-handed.

          -  Inpatient participants with alcohol dependence who have symptoms of alcohol withdrawal
             as indicated by the most recent measurement within the past 30 days, as measured by
             the Clinical Institute Withdrawal Assessment (CIWA-Ar) score &gt;= 8.

               -  We will utilize SCID diagnoses (as part of the screening protocol 14-AA-0181) to
                  determine AUD diagnosis and any potential Axis I disorders. However, for
                  inpatients, since the nursing practice is initially focused on patient
                  detoxification and treatment, the SCID diagnoses might not always take place
                  prior to enrollment in this study. This could seriously hamper the inpatient
                  subject recruitment in this study. We will conduct the MR scan of eligible
                  participants (based on the above inclusion/exclusion criterion) according to
                  study timeline regardless of SCID diagnoses. Once the SCID diagnose is completed,
                  we will assign the participants to the AUD group if applicable, according to SCID
                  diagnoses, and use any potential Axis I disorder as a study confound.
                  Additionally, we will collect information on medications being taken by patients
                  currently or within the last month, including dose, schedule, and timeline. This
                  will be used as a covariate in the statistical design to control for variation
                  associated with these medications.

                    -  Subjects excluded from MR scan may still perform the behavioral tasks which
                       otherwise would be performed in the scanner, if they qualify for behavioral
                       tasks.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Reza Momenan, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Reza Momenan, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-6972</phone>
    <email>rezam@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-AA-0080.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andrews MM, Meda SA, Thomas AD, Potenza MN, Krystal JH, Worhunsky P, Stevens MC, O'Malley S, Book GA, Reynolds B, Pearlson GD. Individuals family history positive for alcoholism show functional magnetic resonance imaging differences in reward sensitivity that are related to impulsivity factors. Biol Psychiatry. 2011 Apr 1;69(7):675-83. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2010.09.049. Epub 2010 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21126735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baker KG, Harding AJ, Halliday GM, Kril JJ, Harper CG. Neuronal loss in functional zones of the cerebellum of chronic alcoholics with and without Wernicke's encephalopathy. Neuroscience. 1999;91(2):429-38.</citation>
    <PMID>10366000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bjork JM, Hommer DW, Grant SJ, Danube C. Impulsivity in abstinent alcohol-dependent patients: relation to control subjects and type 1-/type 2-like traits. Alcohol. 2004 Oct-Nov;34(2-3):133-50.</citation>
    <PMID>15902907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 26, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 8, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alcohol</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Adults</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

