<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02102802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MP8-S1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02102802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exploring Mechanisms of Action in MDMA-assisted Psychotherapy for PTSD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exploring Mechanisms of Action of ±3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA)- Assisted Psychotherapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Multidisciplinary Association for Psychedelic Studies</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Multidisciplinary Association for Psychedelic Studies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study measures biological and psychological processes that might help researchers to
      better understand what is taking place during low or medium dose and full dose MDMA-assisted
      psychotherapy treatment in people with PTSD. Heart rate variability (HRV) will be measured up
      to three times; before and once or twice after receiving MDMA-assisted psychotherapy. Brain
      activity will be measured before and after MDMA-assisted psychotherapy in response to
      personalized trauma-related scripts. Participants will complete a measure of self-compassion
      at baseline and two months after a final experimental treatment session. Therapy techniques
      observed during recorded treatment sessions will be classified using a standardized clinical
      measure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PTSD is a complex psychiatric disease characterized by a deficit in fear extinction,
      hyperarousal, emotional numbing, and intrusive symptoms that cause the patient to
      persistently re-experience a traumatic event over a period longer than a month. PTSD is
      considered chronic when symptoms are present for at least six months. MDMA-assisted
      psychotherapy is an innovative experimental mode of treatment that combines psychotherapeutic
      techniques with the administration of MDMA. It may amplify certain aspects of psychotherapy,
      as the pharmacological action of MDMA is thought to act as an adjunct to psychotherapy. With
      positive results in two studies and ongoing Phase 2 clinical studies it is important to
      further characterize the psychotherapeutic processes that occur during treatment sessions
      conducted according to the manualized method of MDMA-assisted psychotherapy. Changes in
      physiological status or brain activity that are associated with improvement or recovery in
      people with chronic PTSD may offer a means of assessing treatment response that relies less
      on self-report. This may be particularly important in studies with MDMA-assisted
      psychotherapy where blinding is difficult due to the psychoactive nature of the
      investigational product. This study is also interested in identifying and categorizing
      psychotherapeutic processes taking place during MDMA-assisted psychotherapy. The sub-study
      will also examine elements of the experience with a self-report measure of self-compassion.

      This exploratory sub-study will identify psychotherapeutic processes occurring during MDMA-
      assisted psychotherapy in people with chronic PTSD and assess the feasibility of exploring
      physiological correlates of clinical outcomes in subjects enrolled in the ongoing clinical
      trial of MDMA-assisted psychotherapy, NCT #: NCT01211405. The sub-study will be conducted in
      collaboration with researchers at the Medical University of South Carolina (MUSC), Smith
      College and the New School for Social Research.

      To support the clinical outcomes measured by CAPS from the MP-8 study, the sponsor is
      interested in correlations of outcomes with treatment-related changes in potential biological
      markers of PTSD, measured by HRV and fMRI. Brain activity while listening to neutral and
      personalized trauma-related scripts will take place at baseline and after experimental
      MDMA-assisted psychotherapy with low or medium or full dose MDMA. The fMRI scan will be
      followed by a Diffusion Tensor Imaging (DTI) scan. After each scanning session, pulse
      measurements will be extracted as a digital data file from which HRV will be calculated. FMRI
      scans and HRV measurements will occur at baseline for participants in all conditions, one
      month after the second experimental session and again after a final experimental session for
      participants in the low or medium dose condition, and two months after the final experimental
      session for participants in the full dose condition. Participants will complete the
      Self-Compassion Scale, a self-report measure of self-compassion at Baseline and after the
      final MDMA-assisted psychotherapy session. Psychotherapeutic processes will be assessed via
      observing psychotherapy and sorting a set of 100 therapy-related items as a means of
      describing the interactions. Trained coders will observe at least one pre-drug psychotherapy
      session, one experimental (drug-assisted psychotherapy) session and one post-drug
      psychotherapy session.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in brain activity measured via fMRI while listening to trauma scripts</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, two months after final experimental session</time_frame>
    <description>Brain activity measured via functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) after listening to trauma-related scripts.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in heart rate variability in response to trauma script</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one month post-drug</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of Heart rate variability (HRV) in response to trauma-related scripts; a potential physiological correlate of response to treatment for PTSD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self Compassion Scale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one month post-drug</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of self-compassion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in heart rate variability in response to trauma script</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, two months post final drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of Heart rate variability (HRV) in response to trauma-related scripts; a potential physiological correlate of response to treatment for PTSD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self Compassion Scale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, two months post final drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of self-compassion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in brain activity measured via fMRI while listening to trauma scripts</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, one month post-drug</time_frame>
    <description>Brain activity measured via functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) after listening to trauma-related scripts</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Psychotherapy Process Q-set (PSQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 - 7 weeks post enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>System of coding psychotherapeutic processes in observed psychotherapy (pre-drug)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Psychotherapy Process Q-set (PSQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 - 16 weeks post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>System of coding psychotherapeutic processes in observed psychotherapy (drug-assisted psychotherapy session)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Psychotherapy Process Q-set (PSQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>17-27 weeks post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>System of coding psychotherapeutic processes in observed psychotherapy (end of treatment after final experimental session)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low or medium dose MDMA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive 30 mg MDMA possibly followed 1.5 to 2 h later by 15 mg or participants receive 75 mg MDMA possibly followed by 37.5 mg MDMA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Full dose MDMA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 125 mg MDMA possibly followed 1.5 to 2 h later by 62.5 mg MDMA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low or Medium dose MDMA</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receiving 30 or 75 mg MDMA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low or medium dose MDMA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine</other_name>
    <other_name>MDMA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Full dose MDMA</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receiving 125 mg MDMA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Full dose MDMA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine</other_name>
    <other_name>MDMA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrolled in the parent study, &quot;A Randomized, Triple-Blind, Phase 2 Pilot Study
             Comparing 3 Different Doses of MDMA in Conjunction with Manualized Psychotherapy in 24
             Veterans, Firefighters, and Police Officers with Chronic, Treatment-Resistant
             Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD).&quot; NCT #: NCT01211405

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Mass brain lesion

          -  Have metal in their skulls,

          -  Having brain or heart pacemakers

          -  History of major head trauma

          -  Have past or present panic or extreme discomfort with being in small enclosed spaces
             (claustrophobia)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael C Mithoefer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Private practice</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Offices of Michael Mithoefer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mount Pleasant</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29464-4345</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>March 24, 2017</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>March 24, 2017</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Actual">March 28, 2017</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>MDMA</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain activity</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart rate variability</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiological correlate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>N-Methyl-3,4-methylenedioxyamphetamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

