<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00350662</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DF-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00350662</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study With Deferiprone and/or Desferrioxamine in Iron Overloaded Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Open-label Phase III Study With Deferiprone and/or Desferrioxamine in Iron Overloaded Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lipomed</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lipomed</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Comparison of efficacy and toxicity of the combination treatment of deferiprone and
      desferrioxamine with the single agent treatment of either drug
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with refractory anemias requiring regular blood transfusions accumulate iron at the
      rate of approximately 0.5 mg/kg/day, which may lead to serious organ toxicity. The human body
      has no active mechanism for the excretion of excess iron. Therefore multiply transfused
      patients will develop a secondary hemosiderosis, if no iron excretion is achieved by a
      chelating agent. Symptoms of iron-overload occur when body iron stores reach 10-20 g. At
      higher levels severe, even fatal complications, particularly cardiac failure, may develop.

      Desferrioxamine (DFO, Desferal) is the established and commonly used iron-chelating drug, but
      is expensive and must be given by slow subcutaneous or intravenous infusion for 8-12 hours a
      day during 5-7 days weekly at a dosage of 40-50mg/kg body weight/day. This often leads to
      failure of compliance of the patient and therefore to inefficient iron chelation. Further
      some patients are hypersensitive to desferrioxamine and others suffer from toxicity, e.g. to
      the ears or eyes.

      Deferiprone (L1; CP20; 1,2 dimethyl-3-hydroxy-pyrid-4-one) is an orally active iron chelator
      investigated in various clinical trials since 1987. Dosages of 75 - 100mg/kg body weight/day
      of L1 have been found effective to maintain stable iron balance (urinary iron excretion of
      0.5mg/kg/day) and to reduce serum ferritin levels between 6% and 25% within one year of
      treatment in iron-overloaded thalassemic patients. There exists long-term experience with
      patients who have received deferiprone continuously for more than 10 years so far. However,
      only few controlled comparison studies with L1 and DFO have been performed so far in order to
      confirm the effectiveness of deferiprone.

      The main side effects encountered during a deferiprone therapy are arthropathy,
      gastrointestinal symptoms, headache, and mild zinc deficiency. These adverse effects are
      usually reversed on reducing the dose or discontinuing the drug. Except for severe joint
      symptoms in few patients, most of the subjects in different clinical trials have been able to
      continue with L1 therapy for a long-term. The most severe and rare complication following L1
      administration is agranulocytosis or neutropenia.

      A new treatment regimen by combining deferiprone with desferrioxamine is currently being
      investigated in many countries. Preliminary data could demonstrate that the combined use of
      both drugs is highly active showing a synergistic or even additive effect (significant
      decrease of serum ferritin and hepatic iron content, increase of urinary iron excretion).
      This synergism could be explained by the different mode of activity of the two drugs. It
      could be demonstrated that patients who were not sufficiently chelated with desferrioxamine
      or deferiprone, could achieve a negative iron balance with the combination treatment of both
      drugs. The combined regimen was generally well-tolerated and there is evidence that the
      individual toxicity profile of both drugs can be positively influenced by the simultaneous
      administration of L1 and DFO. The daily treatment with L1 tablets combined with a twice a
      week administration of parenteral desferrioxamine is more patient-convenient and therefore
      may enhance the compliance of the patient. In addition, this new treatment regimen will
      reduce the overall therapy expenses if compared to the high Desferal and material costs
      related to the parenteral administration of DFO on 5 to 7 days per week.

      The results of the previous studies with deferiprone are often not comparable, e.g.
      laboratory parameters, toxicities and side effects vary from study to study. The number of
      patients included in the clinical investigations was in general too low to allow
      statistically significant evaluations. Further, there is no controlled randomized study
      comprising an appropriate number of patients in order to allow a comparison between the
      combination arm and the single agent control arms. This study protocol aims to evaluate the
      feasibility of the combination treatment by comparing the efficacy and safety of the combined
      drugs with the single agent treatment of L1 and DFO in iron-overloaded patients with
      thalassemia or refractory anemia in a controlled randomized multicenter study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2002</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical efficacy (Iron balance and liver iron concentration)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile (general, hematologic, and organ toxicity)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3-monthly intervals</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver histology</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (patient's subjective of compliance and tolerance)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3-monthly intervals</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Actual treatment duration (ATD)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemochromatosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Deferiprone + Desferrioxamine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Deferiprone single agent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Desferrioxamine single agent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deferiprone (L1)</intervention_name>
    <description>75 mg/kg body weight daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Deferiprone + Desferrioxamine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Deferiprone single agent</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Desferrioxamine</intervention_name>
    <description>In combination with deferiprone: 40-50 mg/kg body weight 2-times weekly As single agent: 40-50 mg/kg body weight 5- to 7-times weekly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Deferiprone + Desferrioxamine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Desferrioxamine single agent</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Iron-overloaded patients without prior iron chelation therapy as well as pretreated
             patients

          -  Age: 4 years and older

          -  Sex: male and female

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children &lt; 4 years of age

          -  Patients non-compliant to DFO or L1

          -  Patients with known DFO or L1 toxicity/intolerance

          -  Neutropenia (neutrophils &lt; 1.5 x 10exp9/L)

          -  Thrombocytopenia (platelets &lt; 100 x 10exp9/L)

          -  Renal, hepatic (liver enzymes 2.5x of upper normal level and higher) or decompensated
             heart failure

          -  Active viral illness currently treated with interferon-alpha/ribavirin

          -  Patients with repeated Yersinia infections

          -  HIV-positivity

          -  Pregnancy and nursing

          -  Female and male of reproductive age planning for family, sexually active but not
             taking adequate contraceptive precaution
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amal M El-Beshlawy, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Pediatric Hospital, Cairo University, Cairo, Egypt</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yesim Aydinok, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>EGE University Medical School Bornova, Izmir, Turkey</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Hospital, Cairo University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>EGE University Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bornova, Izmir</city>
        <state>Izmir</state>
        <zip>35100</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>El-Beshlawy A, Manz C, Naja M, Eltagui M, Tarabishi C, Youssry I, Sobh H, Hamdy M, Sharaf I, Mostafa A, Shaker O, Hoffbrand AV, Taher A. Iron chelation in thalassemia: combined or monotherapy? The Egyptian experience. Ann Hematol. 2008 Jul;87(7):545-50. doi: 10.1007/s00277-008-0471-2. Epub 2008 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18351337</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aydinok Y, Ulger Z, Nart D, Terzi A, Cetiner N, Ellis G, Zimmermann A, Manz C. A randomized controlled 1-year study of daily deferiprone plus twice weekly desferrioxamine compared with daily deferiprone monotherapy in patients with thalassemia major. Haematologica. 2007 Dec;92(12):1599-606.</citation>
    <PMID>18055982</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aydinok Y, Evans P, Manz CY, Porter JB. Timed non-transferrin bound iron determinations probe the origin of chelatable iron pools during deferiprone regimens and predict chelation response. Haematologica. 2012 Jun;97(6):835-41. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2011.056317. Epub 2011 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22180427</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 10, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 16, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 16, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 19, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deferiprone</keyword>
  <keyword>L1</keyword>
  <keyword>Desferrioxamine</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemochromatosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Iron overload</keyword>
  <keyword>Thalassemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemochromatosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Deferiprone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deferoxamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

