<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00352794</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2005-0206</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00352794</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lenalidomide for Patients With Myelofibrosis (MF)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Lenalidomide (CC-5013) and Prednisone as a Therapy for Patients With Myelofibrosis (MF)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if lenalidomide in combination with
      prednisone can help to control myelofibrosis. The safety of lenalidomide and prednisone for
      the treatment of myelofibrosis will also be studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lenalidomide is designed to change the body's immune system. It may also interfere with the
      development of tiny blood vessels that help support tumor growth. Therefore, in theory, it
      may decrease or prevent the growth of cancer cells. Prednisone is designed to improve the
      results of lenalidomide and to help reduce the side effects.

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will take 1-2 capsules of
      lenalidomide by mouth daily. You will take lenalidomide daily for 21 days followed by 1 week
      rest. This 28-day period is called a study &quot;cycle.&quot;

      Swallow lenalidomide capsules whole with water at the same time each day. Do not break, chew
      or open the capsules.

      If you miss a dose of lenalidomide, take it as soon as you remember on the same day. If you
      miss taking your dose for the entire day, take your regular dose the next scheduled day (do
      NOT take double your regular dose to make up for the missed dose).

      You will take prednisone by mouth every day during Cycles 1-2, and every other day during
      Cycle 3. You may only take prednisone for Cycles 1-3.

      You will be given a study drug diary. In this diary, you will record when you take the study
      drug(s).

      During treatment, blood (about 1 tablespoon) will be drawn once every 1-2 weeks. Following
      the completion of 24 cycles, blood (about 1 tablespoon) will be drawn every 1- 3 months. The
      tests may be repeated more frequently to check for side effects.

      Every month for the first 3 months, and then every 3 months, until you complete 24 cycles,
      you will have a study visit. You will have a bone marrow biopsy/aspirate every 3 months.
      Lenalidomide will be provided to you as a monthly (28-day) supply.

      Following the completion of Cycle 24, you will have a study visit every 6 months. You will
      have a bone marrow biopsy/aspirate every 12 months. Lenalidomide will be provided to you as a
      monthly (28-day) supply.

      Depending on side effects and the activity of the study drug against the disease, your dose
      of the study drug may be increased or decreased.

      You may stay on study for as long as you are benefitting. You will be taken off study if you
      are not or are no longer benefitting or intolerable side effects occur.

      This is an investigational study. Lenalidomide and prednisone are both FDA approved and
      commercially available. Lenalidomide is approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA)
      for the treatment of patients with transfusion-dependent anemia due to Low- or
      Intermediate-1-risk myelodysplastic syndromes associated with the chromosome 5 abnormality
      with or without other chromosome abnormalities. Lenalidomide is also approved in combination
      with dexamethasone for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma that have received at
      least one prior therapy. MDS and MM are cancers of the blood. It is currently being tested in
      a variety of cancer conditions. In this case it is considered experimental. Prednisone is on
      the market for many different things but not specifically for Myelofibrosis. The use of these
      drugs in combination is considered investigational in this study. Up to 41 patients will take
      part in this study. All will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with Objective Response (Complete and Partial Response + Hematological Improvement)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and with each 28 Day Cycle</time_frame>
    <description>Time to response defined as the time from start of therapy until the response criteria are fulfilled. Response duration defined as the time from response until relapse (progressive disease) or death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Myelofibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + Prednisone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lenalidomide oral 10 mg daily/days 1-21 of 28 day cycle. Prednisone starting dose oral 30 mg/day during cycle 1, 15 mg/day during cycle 2, and 15 mg every other day during cycle 3, and then it will be discontinued.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral 10 mg daily/days 1-21 of 28 day cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + Prednisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prednisone</intervention_name>
    <description>Starting dose oral 30 mg/day during cycle 1, 15 mg/day during cycle 2, and 15 mg every other day during cycle 3, and then it will be discontinued.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + Prednisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of myelofibrosis requiring therapy, including those previously treated and
             relapsed or refractory, or if newly diagnosed, with intermediate or high risk
             according to Lille scoring system (risk factors are: Hb &lt; 10 g/dl, WBC &lt; 4 or &gt; 30 x
             109/L; risk group: 0 factor(s) = low, 1 factor(s) = intermediate, 2 factor(s) = high)
             or with symptomatic splenomegaly

          2. Understanding and voluntary signing an IRB-approved informed consent form.

          3. Age &gt;/= 18 years at the time of signing the informed consent.

          4. Disease-free of prior malignancies for &gt;/= 2-years with exception of basal cell or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma &quot;in situ&quot; of the cervix or breast.

          5. ECOG performance status 0 to 2.

          6. Patients must have adequate organ function as demonstrated by the following: Total
             bilirubin &lt;/= 2.0 mg/dL (unless higher due to MF); Serum creatinine &lt;/= 2.0 mg/dL
             (unless higher due to MF); Absolute neutrophil count &gt;/= 1 x 10^9/L; ALT &lt;/= 3 x upper
             limit of normal (unless higher due to MF).

          7. Females of childbearing potential (FCBP)† must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 50 mIU/mL within 10 - 14 days prior to
             and again within 24 hours of starting lenalidomide and must either commit to continued
             abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of birth
             control, one highly effective method and one additional effective method AT THE SAME
             TIME, at least 4 weeks before she starts taking lenalidomide. FCBP must also agree to
             ongoing pregnancy testing.

          8. Continuation of 7. Men must agree to use a condom during sexual contact with a female
             of child bearing potential even if they have had a successful vasectomy. All patients
             must be counseled at a minimum of every 28 days about pregnancy precautions and risks
             of fetal exposure. See Appendix J: Risks of Fetal Exposure, Pregnancy Testing
             Guidelines and Acceptable Birth Control Methods

          9. footnote to no 7. † A female of childbearing potential is a sexually mature woman who:
             1) has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or 2) has not been
             naturally postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e., has had menses at
             any time in the preceding 24 consecutive months).

         10. All study participants must be registered into the mandatory RevAssist® program, and
             be willing and able to comply with the requirements of RevAssist®.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Use of any other standard (e.g. hydroxyurea, anagrelide, growth factors) or
             experimental drug or therapy within 28 days of starting lenalidomide and/or lack of
             recovery from all toxicity from previous therapy to grade 1 or better.

          2. Known prior clinically relevant hypersensitivity reaction to thalidomide, including
             the development of erythema nodosum if characterized by a desquamating rash.

          3. Prior therapy with lenalidomide.

          4. Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subject from signing the informed consent form.

          5. Suspected Pregnancy. Pregnant or lactating females.

          6. Any condition, including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which places the
             subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study or confounds
             the ability to interpret data from the study.

          7. Known positive for HIV or infectious hepatitis, type A, B or C.

          8. Known prior clinically relevant hypersensitivity to prednisone.

          9. Participants with a heart rate (HR) of less than or equal to 50, as a HR less than 50
             indicates underlying cardiac abnormalities.

         10. Participants with prior history of thromboembolic disease (i.e.-deep venous thrombosis
             [DVT] or pulmonary embolism [PE]) within the last six months, as Lenalidomide has
             demonstrated a significantly increased risk of DVT or PE.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Srdan Verstovsek, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 14, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 14, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 17, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Combination chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Myelofibrosis (MF)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Primary Myelofibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

