<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00403663</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>06-02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-0206-E</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00403663</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Body Mass Index on the Dose of Intrathecal Hyperbaric Bupivacaine for Elective Cesarean Section</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Body Mass Index on the ED95 of Intrathecal Hyperbaric Bupivacaine for Elective Cesarean Section</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Samuel Lunenfeld Research Institute, Mount Sinai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Samuel Lunenfeld Research Institute, Mount Sinai Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Combined spinal - epidural (CSE) anesthesia is a well established technique used for elective
      Cesarean section. As its name suggests, it combines two anesthesia techniques - spinal and
      epidural. Adjusting the dose of freezing medication for body size is not as simple as giving
      a larger dose to a larger person. This study asks a simple, yet important question: does your
      body mass index (BMI) influence the amount of freezing medication needed for adequate CSE
      anesthesia for Cesarean section? BMI is a number calculated from your height and weight. In
      patients with a higher BMI, freezing medication appears to spread farther (to a higher level)
      in the spinal fluid. When freezing is too high, it can cause unwanted side effects.
      Therefore, in order to provide optimal spinal anesthesia to patients with a higher BMI, it
      may be advisable to administer less freezing medication. In this study, we want to find the
      ideal dose of freezing medication for patients with a higher body mass index, and compare it
      to the dose found to be ideal for patients with normal body mass index.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Spinal anesthesia is the most common anesthetic technique used for Cesarean section. It
      offers many advantages over epidural and general anesthesia. However, one of the limitations
      of spinal anesthesia in Obstetrics is the use of a single shot technique as the continuous
      technique is associated with unacceptable incidence of PDPH. It is difficult to predict the
      exact level of sensory block because many factors affect the spread of local anesthetic
      injected into the CSF. Theoretically, obese patients may have greater intra-abdominal
      pressure, leading to compression of the inferior vena cava and engorgement of the epidural
      venous plexus, which in turn increases the pressure inside the epidural space. This augmented
      pressure is transmitted to the dural sac and diverge the CSF from the lumbosacral region,
      leading to a decrease in CSF volume. It has been demonstrated that the volume of CSF in
      lumbosacral region is an important factor affecting intrathecal spread of anesthetics.

      Our hypothesis is that obese women require less intrathecal hyperbaric bupivacaine than do
      normal weight women to achieve satisfactory surgical anesthesia for elective Cesarean
      section.Two groups of patients will be studied separately. Patients with BMI greater than or
      equal to 30 will be included in the obese group, also denominated study group. Patients with
      BMI less than 25 will be included in the normal weight group, also denominated control group.
      BMI will be calculated based on the patient's pre-pregnancy weight. For each group, the
      up-down sequential allocation method based on the Narayana rule will be used to find the
      minimum effective dose of intrathecal hyperbaric bupivacaine 0.75% associated with opioids
      necessary for satisfactory outcome in 95% of the pregnant women undergoing cesarean section,
      i.e. ED95.

      There are two possible outcomes in our study: a satisfactory outcome is defined if the
      sensory block reaches at least at T6 and the patient does not complain of any pain or
      discomfort that requires intraoperative supplemental drugs; an unsatisfactory outcome is
      defined if the sensory block reaches a level lower than T6 or the patient complains of pain
      or discomfort that requires intraoperative supplemental drugs. The decision whether or not
      the supplementation is required will be made exclusively by the patient, and not by the
      physician in charge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome will be the success/failure of the block. Success meaning a sensory block level at least at T6 within 15 minutes after intrathecal injection and no requirement of any supplemental analgesic by the patient throughout the CS.</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Upper level of sensory blockage determined by the pinprick at midaxillary line</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VAPS during surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose of lidocaine 2% required as supplementation</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose of IV fentanyl or ketamine required as supplementation</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Conversion to general anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bupivacaine 0.75% with fentanyl and morphine</intervention_name>
    <description>the following administered once, by spinal injection; 9-12 mg 0.75% hyperbaric bupivacaine 10 mcg fentanyl 100 mcg morphine</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Obese group: All pregnant women at term (over 37 weeks) scheduled for elective
             Cesarean section, with pre-pregnancy BMI greater than 30

          -  Normal weight group: All pregnant women at term (over 37 weeks) scheduled for elective
             Cesarean section, with pre-pregnancy BMI less than 25.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient's refusal.

          -  Patients with any absolute or relative contraindication for spinal/epidural
             anesthesia.

          -  Patients with BMI between 25 and 30.

          -  Patients with more than one fetus.

          -  Patients unable to communicate in English effectively.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jose CA Carvalho, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Anesthesia and Pain Management, Mount Sinai Hospital, University of Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 23, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 27, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 30, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Body mass index</keyword>
  <keyword>Combined Spinal-Epidural Anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Cesarean section</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

