<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00401011</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Perifosine 218</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00401011</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety &amp; Efficacy Study of Perifosine + Bortezomib +/- Dexamethasone for Multiple Myeloma Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label Phase I/II Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Perifosine and Bortezomib With or Without Dexamethasone for Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma Previously Treated With Bortezomib</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AEterna Zentaris</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AEterna Zentaris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I/II study of perifosine in combination with bortezomib—with or without
      dexamethasone—for patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma previously treated
      with bortezomib. The current protocol will enroll patients with relapsed or refractory
      multiple myeloma who have been previously treated with bortezomib. The patients will be
      treated with perifosine, 50 mg or 100 mg qhs, in combination with bortezomib to determine if
      there is any preliminary evidence that the addition of perifosine improves the outcome for
      these patients. Previous treatment with perifosine will be allowed in this study. Patients
      progressing on treatment with perifosine and bortezomib will receive dexamethasone 20 mg on
      days 1, 2, 4, 5, 8, 9, 11, 12, 15, 16, 18, and 19 of each 21-day cycle in addition to
      bortezomib and perifosine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the phase I portion is to determine the maximum tolerated dose of
      perifosine in combination with bortezomib in patients previously treated with bortezomib.

      All patients will receive daily perifosine qhs with food. In the initial phase I study, 3
      patients will be entered into a specified combination of perifosine and bortezomib cohorts.
      If no dose-limiting toxicity is observed, then three additional patients will be entered in
      cohort 4 - a full dose of bortezomib (1.3 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8 and 11 every 3 weeks). If
      this dose is tolerated it will be used for the phase II study, otherwise an intermediate dose
      of 1 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 every 3 weeks will be employed.

      The phase II study will use the maximum tolerated dose of bortezomib and perifosine. The
      primary objective of phase II portion is to determine the response rate (the combined CR + PR
      + MR) following treatment with perifosine + bortezomib in patients with multiple myeloma who
      have relapsed following initial front-line therapy, are refractory to their most recent
      therapy, and were previously treated with bortezomib. The secondary objectives of the phase
      II portion are;

        1. To further assess the safety and tolerability of perifosine in combination with
           bortezomib—with or without dexamethasone—in patients with multiple myeloma.

        2. To obtain correlative data in patients with multiple myeloma treated with perifosine in
           combination with bortezomib—with or without dexamethasone (NOTE Centers may choose not
           to participate in correlative studies).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In the Phase I part, maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is determined in sequential cohorts of patients. All patients will start with perifosine and bortezomib (cf. arms and interventions). In case of progression, dexamethasone 20 mg will be added to treatment. Phase II: open-label single treatment arm.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD). Phase II: To determine response rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Phase I: To determine the MTD of perifosine in combination with bortezomib in patients previously treated with bortezomib.
Phase II: The primary endpoint of the study was 6-month progression-free survival.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Tolerability and Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the safety and tolerability of perifosine in combination with bortezomib — with or without dexamethasone.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Correlative data</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To obtain correlative data in patients with multiple myeloma treated with perifosine in combination with bortezomib—with or without dexamethasone</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma in Relapse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will start with perifosine at bedtime daily and Bortezomib IV on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 q 21 days. Patients will be evaluated at q 3 weeks. If the patient has a CR, PR, MR or stable disease, they will continue treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II: Perifosine + Bortezomib + Dexa</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>If the patient shows progressive disease, dexamethasone 20 mg will be added on days 1, 2, 4, 5, 8, 9, 11, 12, 15, 16, 18, and 19 to perifosine at bedtime and bortezomib IV on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 q 21 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 1: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Perifosine 50 mg at bedtime and bortezomib 1 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 every 3 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 2: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Perifosine 100 mg at bedtime and bortezomib 1 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 every 3 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 3: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Perifosine 50 mg at bedtime and bortezomib 1.3 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 every 3 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 4: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Perifosine 100 mg at bedtime and bortezomib 1.3 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 every 3 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Perifosine</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I: Patients will receive daily perifosine (doses 50 mg/m2 or 100 mg/m2) at bedtime.
Phase II: All patients will receive daily perifosine at bedtime. Patients will be evaluated every 3 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II: Perifosine + Bortezomib + Dexa</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 1: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 2: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 3: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 4: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>D-21266</other_name>
    <other_name>KRX-0401</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I: Patients will receive 1 mg/m2 or 1.3 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 every 3 weeks. Phase II: Patients will receive bortezomib on days 1,4,8 and 11 every 3 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II: Perifosine + Bortezomib + Dexa</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 1: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 2: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 3: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I: Dose 4: Perifosine + Bortezomib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase II: If the patient shows progressive disease after 3 weeks, dexamethasone 20 mg will be added to perifosine and bortezomib on days 1, 2, 4, 5, 8, 9, 11, 12, 15, 16, 18, and 19 to perifosine at bedtime and bortezomib IV on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 q 21 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II: Perifosine + Bortezomib + Dexa</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dexa</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject was previously diagnosed with multiple myeloma based on standard diagnostic
             criteria, as follows.

             Major criteria:

               -  Plasmacytomas on tissue biopsy.

               -  Bone marrow plasmacytosis (&gt; 30% plasma cells).

               -  Monoclonal immunoglobulin spike on serum electrophoresis immunoglobulin G (IgG)
                  &gt;3.5 g/dL or immunoglobulin A (IgA) &gt; 2.0 g/dL; kappa or lambda light chain
                  excretion &gt; 1 g/day on 24 hour urine protein electrophoresis.

             Minor criteria:

               -  Bone marrow plasmacytosis (10 to 30% plasma cells).

               -  Monoclonal immunoglobulin present but of lesser magnitude than given under major
                  criteria.

               -  Lytic bone lesions.

               -  Normal IgM &lt; 50 mg/dL, IgA &lt; 100 mg/dL or IgG &lt; 600 mg/dL.

          2. Any of the following sets of criteria will confirm the diagnosis of multiple myeloma:

          3. Any two of the major criteria.

          4. Major criterion 1 plus minor criterion b, c, or d.

          5. Major criterion 3 plus minor criterion a or c.

          6. Minor criteria a, b, and c or a, b, and d.

          7. Patients must have relapsed or refractory disease (refractory is defined as
             progression during treatment or within 60 days after the completion of treatment).

          8. Patients must have been previously treated with bortezomib. Patients may have received
             prior perifosine.

          9. Age &gt;= 18 years at the time of signing informed consent document.

         10. All necessary baseline studies for determining eligibility must be obtained within 14
             days prior to enrollment. (Pregnancy test must be within 7 days for women of
             childbearing potential.)

         11. Subject has an ECOG (Zubrod) performance status of 0 to 2.

         12. Subject must be able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol
             requirements.

         13. Subject must understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent document.

         14. Women of child-bearing potential (WCBP)— must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy
             test within 72 hours prior to enrollment. In addition, all sexually active WCBP and
             male patients must agree to use adequate contraceptive methods (oral, injectable, or
             implantable hormonal contraceptive; tubal ligation; intra-uterine device; barrier
             contraceptive with spermicide; or vasectomized partner) throughout the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Renal insufficiency (serum creatinine levels &gt; 3 mg/dL).

          2. Patients who present with either ALT or AST &gt;= 2.5 X upper limit of normal (ULN)
             and/or patients with bilirubin &gt;= 1.5 X ULN.

          3. History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to perifosine (miltefosine or edelfosine).

          4. Concomitant medications that include corticosteroids (except as indicated for other
             medical conditions or up to 100 mgs of hydrocortisone or equivalent as premedication
             for administration of certain medications or blood products), chemotherapy, or other
             therapy that is or may be active against myeloma within 2 weeks prior to Cycle 1 Day
             1. Nitrosoureas must be discontinued 6 weeks prior to Cycle 1 Day 1.

          5. Subjects with hemoglobin &lt; 8.0 g/dL.

          6. Subjects with an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt;= 500 cells/mm3.

          7. Peripheral neuropathy of grade 3 or greater. Patients with painful grade 2 neuropathy
             are also excluded.

          8. Subjects with evidence of mucosal or internal bleeding and/or platelet refractory
             (i.e., unable to maintain a platelet count &gt;= 50,000 cells/mm3).

          9. Previous history of intolerance of bortezomib or perifosine.

         10. Any condition, including laboratory abnormalities, that in the opinion of the
             investigator places the subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in
             the study.

         11. WCBP who are pregnant or breast-feeding or men and women who are not using adequate
             contraception.

         12. Plasma cell leukemia at time of study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Richardson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Richardson PG, Wolf J, Jakubowiak A, Zonder J, Lonial S, Irwin D, Densmore J, Krishnan A, Raje N, Bar M, Martin T, Schlossman R, Ghobrial IM, Munshi N, Laubach J, Allerton J, Hideshima T, Colson K, Poradosu E, Gardner L, Sportelli P, Anderson KC. Perifosine plus bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma previously treated with bortezomib: results of a multicenter phase I/II trial. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Nov 10;29(32):4243-9. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.33.9788. Epub 2011 Oct 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21990396</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 16, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 17, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>February 20, 2018</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2018</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2018</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Perifosine</keyword>
  <keyword>Bortezomib</keyword>
  <keyword>Dexamethasone</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

