<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00402181</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR012631</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>C0328T05</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2006-001897-26</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00402181</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Efficacy and Safety Study of Siltuximab in Participants With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Multicenter Study of CNTO 328 (Anti IL-6 Monoclonal Antibody) in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centocor, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centocor, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of siltuximab in
      participants with relapsed (the return of a disease or the signs and symptoms of a disease
      after a period of improvement.) or refractory (cancer that does not respond to treatment)
      multiple myeloma (a type of cancer that begins in plasma cells [white blood cells that
      produce antibodies]).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label (all people know the identity of the intervention), multicenter (when
      more than one hospital or medical school team work on a medical research study),
      non-randomized (a clinical trial in which the participants are not assigned by chance to
      different treatment groups), prospective (study following participants forward in time)
      safety and efficacy study of siltuximab in participants with relapsed or refractory multiple
      myeloma. The study consists of 3 Phases: Screening Phase (from first visit until the first
      dose of study drug), Treatment Phase (from the first dose to the end-of-treatment), and
      Follow-up Phase (after end-of-treatment until the end of study). The duration of
      participation in the study for an individual participant will be up to 4 weeks for Screening
      Phase, approximately 52 weeks for Treatment Phase and until death, lost to follow-up,
      withdraw of consent or end of study, whichever, comes first for Follow-up Phase. Treatment
      will be administered on a 28-day cycle. The study is designed with 2 alternative treatment
      plans. Treatment Plan A: during first 2 cycles siltuximab will be administered alone,
      dexamethasone may be added to the treatment regimen based on the participant's response to
      treatment. Treatment Plan B: siltuximab and dexamethasone combination for the duration of the
      study. The first 14 eligible participants will follow Treatment Plan A and data evaluation
      will be conducted for participants after 2 cycles of treatment and 2 post baseline disease
      assessments. If at least one complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) is observed in
      14 participants, all subsequent participants will follow Treatment Plan A. However, if no
      responses (CR or PR) are observed, all subsequent participants will follow Treatment Plan B.
      The primary efficacy endpoint will be percentage of participants with overall response.
      Participants' safety will be monitored throughout the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Overall Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of study (Day 807)</time_frame>
    <description>The overall response is defined as percentage of participants having confirmed Complete Response (CR) and Partial Response (PR) by using the European Group for Blood and Marrow Transplantation (EBMT) criteria. CR is absence of the original monoclonal protein (M-protein) in serum and urine maintained for a minimum of 6 weeks, and disappearance of soft tissue plasmacytomas. PR is greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 50 percent reduction in the level of the serum M-protein maintained for a minimum of 6 weeks and &gt;= 50 percent reduction in the size of soft tissue plasmacytomas.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of study (Day 807)</time_frame>
    <description>The TTP is defined as the time interval in days between the date of first administration of study treatment (as monotherapy or as combination therapy) to the date of first documented evidence of confirmed progressive disease (including relapse from CR). CR is absence of the original M-protein in serum and urine maintained for a minimum of 6 weeks, and disappearance of soft tissue plasmacytomas.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of study (Day 807)</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of response is defined as the time from initial documented response (Complete Response [CR] or Partial Response [PR]), to the first documented sign of progression. CR is absence of the original M-protein in serum and urine maintained for a minimum of 6 weeks, and disappearance of soft tissue plasmacytomas. PR is &gt;= 50% reduction in the level of the serum M-protein maintained for a minimum of 6 weeks and &gt;= 50% reduction in the size of soft tissue plasmacytomas.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Immune Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (Cycle 1 [pre-dose]), treatment discontinuation, and every 3 months after the last dose (up to 3 times)</time_frame>
    <description>Immune response is defined as antibody (type of protein that helps to protect the body against foreign matter, such as bacteria and viruses) response to siltuximab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change From Baseline in C-Reactive Protein (CRP) Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Before siltuximab administration in Cycles 1, 2, and 3 on Days 1 and 15; thereafter, on Day 1 of each cycle up to12 cycles</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change in CRP is equal to CRP at time of measurement minus CRP at baseline divided by CRP at baseline multiplied by 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change From Baseline in C-telopeptide (CTx) Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Before siltuximab administration on Day 1 of cycles 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change in CTx is equal to CTx at time of measurement minus CTx at baseline divided by CTx at baseline multiplied by 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change From Baseline in N-telopeptide (NTx) Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Before siltuximab administration on Day 1 of cycles 1, 2, and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change in NTx is equal to NTx at time of measurement minus NTx at baseline divided by NTx at baseline multiplied by 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Plan A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Siltuximab 6 milligram per kilogram (mg/kg) as intravenous (directly into the vein) infusion once every 2 weeks for 12 cycles and duration of each cycle is 28 days (if participant have complete or partial response) along with dexamethasone (starting from Cycle 2, If participant do not have complete or partial response) 40 mg tablet orally on Day 1 to 4, 9 to 12 and 17 to 20 for maximum 4 cycles after that on Day 1 to 4 up to 12 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Plan B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Siltuximab 6 mg/kg as intravenous infusion once every 2 weeks along with dexamethasone 40 mg tablet orally on Day 1 to 4, 9 to 12 and 17 to 20 for maximum 4 cycles (duration of each cycle is 28 days) after that on Day 1 to 4 up to 12 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Siltuximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Siltuximab 6 mg/kg as intravenous infusion once every 2 weeks for 12 cycles and duration of each cycle is 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Plan A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Plan B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CNTO 328</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Dexamethasone 40 mg tablet orally on Day 1 to 4, 9 to 12 and 17 to 20 for maximum 4 cycles after that on Day 1 to 4 up to 12 cycles and duration of each cycle is 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Plan A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Plan B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of multiple myeloma with relapsed or refractory disease after
             failing at least 2 prior lines of therapy

          -  Prior treatment regimen must have included bortezomib (alone or in combination with
             other agents)

          -  Measurable secretory disease defined as either serum monoclonal paraprotein (M-
             protein) greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 1 gram per deciliter (g/dL) or urine monoclonal
             (light chain) protein (greater than (&gt;) 200 milligram/24 hours)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of less than or
             equal to (&lt;=) 2 - Participants of childbearing potential must use adequate birth
             control measures, female participants of childbearing potential must have a negative
             serum pregnancy test at screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment with systemic cancer therapy (including clarithromycin) or radiotherapy
             within 30 days before the first dose of study agent - Treatment with nitrosoureas (a
             group of alkylating agents used as antineoplastic drugs in the chemotherapy) within 42
             days before the first dose of study agent

          -  Major surgery within 30 days before the first dose of study agent or planning to have
             surgery (except for minor surgical procedures) during the study

          -  Serious concurrent illness (medical or psychiatric), uncontrolled infection, or
             significant cardiac disease characterized by significant ischemic coronary disease (an
             imbalance between myocardial functional requirements and the capacity of the coronary
             vessels to supply sufficient blood flow) or congestive heart failure (condition in
             which the heart is unable to pump out sufficient blood to meet the metabolic need of
             the body) not under medical control, or any uncontrolled medical condition (for
             example: uncontrolled diabetes), including the presence of clinical laboratory
             abnormalities, that places the subject at unacceptable risk by participating in the
             study or confounds the ability to interpret data from the study

          -  Known to be seropositive (giving a positive result in a test of blood serum) for Human
             Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), or active hepatitis A, B or C infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Centocor, Inc. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Centocor, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Norwalk</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>N Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Den Haag</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=175&amp;filename=CR012631_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>A Phase 2 Multicenter Study of CNTO 328 (Anti IL-6 Monoclonal Antibody) in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 17, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 22, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 14, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Intravenous</keyword>
  <keyword>Monoclonal antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>Siltuximab</keyword>
  <keyword>Dexamethasone</keyword>
  <keyword>CNTO 328</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Siltuximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

