<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01218178</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P/479/CE/2010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01218178</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sodium Bicarbonate and N-Acetylcysteine for Nephroprotection in Acute Myocardial Infarction</brief_title>
  <acronym>BINARIO</acronym>
  <official_title>BIcarbonato di Sodio e N-Acetilcisteina Nella Prevenzione Della Nefropatia da Mezzo di Contrasto Nell'infaRto mIocardico acutO(Registro BINARIO)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Policlinico Casilino ASL RMB</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Contrast-induced nephropathy (CIN) represents a potential complication of diagnostic and
      therapeutic procedures in interventional cardiology, especially in the acute setting of
      primary PCI. The investigators will test the efficacy of sodium bicarbonate (NaHCO3) and
      N-acetylcysteine (NAC) on the prevention of acute events and CIN in patients with acute
      myocardial infarction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction Contrast-induced nephropathy (CIN) represents a potential complication of
      diagnostic and therapeutic procedures in interventional cardiology. In the setting of
      elective procedures, the strategy of sodium bicarbonate (NaHCO3) and N-acetylcysteine (NAC)
      infusion has been shown to reduce the incidence of CIN in high-risk patients. The efficacy of
      this strategy has not been demonstrated in the case of primary percutaneous coronary
      intervention (PCI).

      Aim of the study The aim is to assess the efficacy of the strategy of sodium bicarbonate
      154mEq/l + glucose solution 5% (infusion rate: 3 mL • kg-1 • h-1 for 1 hour followed by 1 mL
      • kg-1 • h-1 for 6 hours) and NAC (1200 mg i.v. followed by 1200 mg bid for the next 48
      hours) in reducing the incidence of CIN in patients with STEMI undergoing primary or rescue
      PCI. As control group, a population of STEMI patients treated with NAC (1200 mg i.v. followed
      by 1200 mg bid for the next 48 hours) + conventional hydration with saline solution 0.9% will
      be retrospectively enrolled. According to the common definition, CIN will be defined as
      increase of the level of serum creatinine &gt;0,5 mg/dL and/or increase ≥25% serum creatinine
      and/or decrease ≥25% of the glomerular filtration rate (GFR) as calculated with the MDRD
      Modification of Diet in Renal Disease)formula at 48 hours after PCI compared with baseline
      value after primary PCI.

      Study Design This is a two-center (Policlinico Gemelli and Policlinico Casilino, Rome,
      Italy), prospective, spontaneous (not sponsored) observational study.

      Patient population

      Inclusion criteria:

        -  Consecutive patients with ST-Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction (STEMI) as
           diagnosed according to the ACC (American College of Cardiology) criteria:

             -  ischemic symptoms;

             -  ECG variations: ST-elevation (&gt;0,05 mV) in two or more contiguous leads;

             -  Increase of the biochemical markers of myocardial necrosis (troponin T, cTNT).

        -  Indication to urgent coronary angiography and primary or rescue PCI

      Exclusion criteria:

        -  Patients with history of allergic reaction to NAC (Fluimucil, Zambon Group Spa, Milan,
           Italy)

        -  Chronic hemodialysis

        -  Age &gt; 90 years

      Study protocol Patients will be treated with 154 mEq/L of sodium bicarbonate and glucose 5%
      solution (infusion rate of 3 mL • kg-1 • h-1 for 1 hour followed by 1 mL • kg-1 • h-1 for 6
      hours) plus NAC (1200 mg i.v. followed by 1200 mg bid for the next 48 hours). As control
      group, a population of STEMI patients treated with conventional hydration with saline
      solution 0,9% and NAC (1200 mg i.v. followed by 1200 mg bid for the next 48 hours) according
      to the common clinical practice of the Department of Cardiovascular Medicine of the
      Policlinico Agostino Gemelli and of Cardiology Department of the Policlinico Casilino will be
      retrospectively enrolled.

      Endpoints:

      Primary endpoint:

      - Composite endpoint (death/need for dialysis/CIN)

      Secondary endpoints:

        -  assessment of individual major adverse events (death, re-infarction, need for dialysis)
           during at 1, 6 and 12 months

        -  assessment of the incidence of CIN defined as increase of the level of serum creatinine
           &gt;0,5 mg/dL and/or increase ≥25% serum creatinine and/or decrease ≥25% of the glomerular
           filtration rate (GFR) as calculated with the MDRD formula at 48 hours after PCI compared
           with baseline value.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality, contrast-induced nephropathy and need of dialysis.</measure>
    <time_frame>2010</time_frame>
    <description>To test the efficacy of sodium bicarbonate plus N-acetylcysteine vs saline hydration plus N-acetylcysteine to reduce mortality and to prevent contrast-induced nephropathy in the setting of primary PCI.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">520</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Acute Kidney Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sodium bicarbonate plus NAC</arm_group_label>
    <description>Sodium bicarbonate plus NAC</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline hydration plus NAC</arm_group_label>
    <description>Saline hydration plus NAC</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sodium bicarbonate plus NAC</intervention_name>
    <description>154 mEq/L sodium bicarbonate (infusion rate of 3 ml/Kg for 1 hour followed by 1 ml/Kg for 6 hours) plus NAC (1200 mg bid for 48 hours)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sodium bicarbonate plus NAC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline hydration plus NAC</intervention_name>
    <description>0.9% saline (1 ml/Kg for 12 hours) plus NAC (1200 mg bid for 48 hours)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline hydration plus NAC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        • Consecutive patients admitted from ER of the Policlinico Agostino Gemelli and Casilino of
        Rome with a ST-Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction undergoing urgent PCI
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ST-Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction (STEMI) as diagnosed according to the ACC
             (American College of Cardiology) criteria:

          -  ischemic symptoms;

          -  ECG variations: ST-elevation (&gt;0,05 mV) in two or more contiguous leads;

          -  Increase of the biochemical markers of myocardial necrosis (troponin T, cTNT). •
             Indication to urgent coronary angiography and primary or rescue PCI

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with history of allergic reaction to NAC

          -  Chronic hemodialysis

          -  Age &gt;= 90 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonio Maria Leone, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart, Rome</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinico Agostino Gemelli and Policlinico Casilino</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00168</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levey AS, Bosch JP, Lewis JB, Greene T, Rogers N, Roth D. A more accurate method to estimate glomerular filtration rate from serum creatinine: a new prediction equation. Modification of Diet in Renal Disease Study Group. Ann Intern Med. 1999 Mar 16;130(6):461-70.</citation>
    <PMID>10075613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merten GJ, Burgess WP, Gray LV, Holleman JH, Roush TS, Kowalchuk GJ, Bersin RM, Van Moore A, Simonton CA 3rd, Rittase RA, Norton HJ, Kennedy TP. Prevention of contrast-induced nephropathy with sodium bicarbonate: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2004 May 19;291(19):2328-34.</citation>
    <PMID>15150204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehran R, Aymong ED, Nikolsky E, Lasic Z, Iakovou I, Fahy M, Mintz GS, Lansky AJ, Moses JW, Stone GW, Leon MB, Dangas G. A simple risk score for prediction of contrast-induced nephropathy after percutaneous coronary intervention: development and initial validation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 Oct 6;44(7):1393-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15464318</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright RS, Reeder GS, Herzog CA, Albright RC, Williams BA, Dvorak DL, Miller WL, Murphy JG, Kopecky SL, Jaffe AS. Acute myocardial infarction and renal dysfunction: a high-risk combination. Ann Intern Med. 2002 Oct 1;137(7):563-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12353943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marenzi G, Lauri G, Assanelli E, Campodonico J, De Metrio M, Marana I, Grazi M, Veglia F, Bartorelli AL. Contrast-induced nephropathy in patients undergoing primary angioplasty for acute myocardial infarction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 Nov 2;44(9):1780-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15519007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adolph E, Holdt-Lehmann B, Chatterjee T, Paschka S, Prott A, Schneider H, Koerber T, Ince H, Steiner M, Schuff-Werner P, Nienaber CA. Renal Insufficiency Following Radiocontrast Exposure Trial (REINFORCE): a randomized comparison of sodium bicarbonate versus sodium chloride hydration for the prevention of contrast-induced nephropathy. Coron Artery Dis. 2008 Sep;19(6):413-9. doi: 10.1097/MCA.0b013e3283021ac6.</citation>
    <PMID>18955835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marenzi G, Assanelli E, Marana I, Lauri G, Campodonico J, Grazi M, De Metrio M, Galli S, Fabbiocchi F, Montorsi P, Veglia F, Bartorelli AL. N-acetylcysteine and contrast-induced nephropathy in primary angioplasty. N Engl J Med. 2006 Jun 29;354(26):2773-82.</citation>
    <PMID>16807414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tepel M, van der Giet M, Schwarzfeld C, Laufer U, Liermann D, Zidek W. Prevention of radiographic-contrast-agent-induced reductions in renal function by acetylcysteine. N Engl J Med. 2000 Jul 20;343(3):180-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10900277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chandel NS, McClintock DS, Feliciano CE, Wood TM, Melendez JA, Rodriguez AM, Schumacker PT. Reactive oxygen species generated at mitochondrial complex III stabilize hypoxia-inducible factor-1alpha during hypoxia: a mechanism of O2 sensing. J Biol Chem. 2000 Aug 18;275(33):25130-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10833514</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiMari J, Megyesi J, Udvarhelyi N, Price P, Davis R, Safirstein R. N-acetyl cysteine ameliorates ischemic renal failure. Am J Physiol. 1997 Mar;272(3 Pt 2):F292-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9087670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Briguori C, Airoldi F, D'Andrea D, Bonizzoni E, Morici N, Focaccio A, Michev I, Montorfano M, Carlino M, Cosgrave J, Ricciardelli B, Colombo A. Renal Insufficiency Following Contrast Media Administration Trial (REMEDIAL): a randomized comparison of 3 preventive strategies. Circulation. 2007 Mar 13;115(10):1211-7. Epub 2007 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17309916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solomon R, Deray G; Consensus Panel for CIN. How to prevent contrast-induced nephropathy and manage risk patients: practical recommendations. Kidney Int Suppl. 2006 Apr;(100):S51-3.</citation>
    <PMID>16612402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCullough PA, Wolyn R, Rocher LL, Levin RN, O'Neill WW. Acute renal failure after coronary intervention: incidence, risk factors, and relationship to mortality. Am J Med. 1997 Nov;103(5):368-75.</citation>
    <PMID>9375704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Navaneethan SD, Singh S, Appasamy S, Wing RE, Sehgal AR. Sodium bicarbonate therapy for prevention of contrast-induced nephropathy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Am J Kidney Dis. 2009 Apr;53(4):617-27. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2008.08.033. Epub 2008 Nov 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19027212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solomon R. The role of osmolality in the incidence of contrast-induced nephropathy: a systematic review of angiographic contrast media in high risk patients. Kidney Int. 2005 Nov;68(5):2256-63. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16221227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ozcan EE, Guneri S, Akdeniz B, Akyildiz IZ, Senaslan O, Baris N, Aslan O, Badak O. Sodium bicarbonate, N-acetylcysteine, and saline for prevention of radiocontrast-induced nephropathy. A comparison of 3 regimens for protecting contrast-induced nephropathy in patients undergoing coronary procedures. A single-center prospective controlled trial. Am Heart J. 2007 Sep;154(3):539-44.</citation>
    <PMID>17719303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 8, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 11, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 13, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Antonio Maria Leone</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute myocardial infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>acute kidney injury</keyword>
  <keyword>contrast induced nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>primary PCI</keyword>
  <keyword>sodium-bicarbonate</keyword>
  <keyword>N-acetylcysteine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Kidney Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetylcysteine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>N-monoacetylcystine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

