<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01213290</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AR0007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01213290</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial Of Endoscopic Ultrasound-Guided Fine-Needle Aspiration With And Without A Stylet</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial Of Endoscopic Ultrasound-Guided Fine-Needle Aspiration With And Without A Stylet : A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>American Society for Gastrointestinal Endoscopy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Midwest Biomedical Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kansas City Veteran Affairs Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) has become an important tool in
      the diagnostic evaluation of gastrointestinal tract lesions and other organ sites such as
      mediastinal and intra-abdominal lymphadenopathy, pancreatic masses, liver masses, left
      adrenal masses and gastrointestinal submucosal lesions. It provides crucial information that
      can have tremendous impact on patient management. FNA is typically performed using a 22- or
      25-gauge needle with a stylet under EUS guidance. The lesion is punctured with a stylet in
      place in the needle. After withdrawal of the stylet, the needle is moved to and fro within
      the lesion and this process is repeated for each needle pass. It is currently believed that
      the use of a stylet for EUS-FNA improves the quality of specimens by preventing the tip of
      the needle being clogged up with tissue and hence enhances the diagnostic yield of specimens
      obtained. However, there are no data demonstrating clearly that the use of a stylet improves
      the yield of EUS-FNA. The reason why this question is important is because the use of a
      stylet during EUS-FNA is cumbersome, time and energy consuming and increases the costs of
      EUS-FNA needle systems.

      In this prospective randomized controlled trial, patients referred for EUS-FNA of mediastinal
      and intra-abdominal lymphadenopathy, pancreatic mass, liver mass, left adrenal mass and
      gastrointestinal submucosal tumors will be included. FNA will be performed with a 22-gauge
      needle under EUS guidance using suction with a 10 mL syringe by two experienced
      endosonographers. The technique to be used for fine needle sampling i.e. with a stylet in
      place or without a stylet for each FNA pass will be assigned by using a preprinted
      randomization scheme obtained from a sealed envelope and clearly documented. Each lesion will
      be sampled for a minimum of four needle passes. The pathologists providing the final
      interpretation will be blinded to technique of EUS-FNA (with or without stylet). The degree
      of cellularity, contamination, amount of blood, adequacy of sample, frequency with which a
      positive diagnosis is made will be compared between the two groups (EUS-FNA with stylet vs.
      EUS-FNA without stylet). The sensitivity, specificity, accuracy, positive predictive value
      and negative predictive value of each technique when compared to the final diagnosis will be
      calculated. Inter-observer agreement among cytopathologists will be assessed for specimens
      obtained from EUS-FNA with stylet and for those obtained from EUS-FNA without a stylet.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Various techniques have been described to optimize accuracy, efficiency, and quality of
      EUS-FNA specimens. FNA is typically performed using a 22- or 25-gauge needle with a stylet
      under EUS guidance. The lesion is punctured with a stylet in place or slightly withdrawing
      the needle. After puncture, the stylet is pushed out of the needle tip and then the needle is
      moved to and fro within the lesion and this process is repeated for each needle pass. It is
      currently believed that the use of a stylet for EUS-FNA helps prevent clogging of the needle
      by gut wall tissue, which could limit the ability to aspirate cells from the target lesion.
      This may improve the quality of specimens and hence enhance the diagnostic yield of specimens
      obtained. This is a logical assumption, but there are no data demonstrating clearly that the
      use of a stylet increases the yield of EUS-FNA. At the present time, it is recommended that
      the stylet is re-inserted back into the needle prior to each FNA pass. The use of a stylet
      during EUS-FNA is cumbersome, time and energy consuming and increases the costs of EUS-FNA
      needle systems. In some circumstances, the stylet may actually make EUS-FNA very difficult as
      it may be impossible to advance or remove the stylet once the target has been punctured. This
      tends to occur when the echoendoscope or the needle is bent and a large (19 gauge) needle is
      being used. In addition, the data comparing the effectiveness of EUS-FNA with stylet to FNA
      without stylet is limited. Paquin et al compared the adequacy, the bloodiness, and the yield
      of FNA samples obtained with a stylet to FNA without a stylet. In this study, the use of
      stylet for EUS-FNA was associated with a reduced specimen adequacy and more bloody passes. 13
      Thus the use of a stylet for EUS-FNA is questionable and needs further investigation. If the
      diagnostic yield, adequacy and quality of specimens obtained by EUS-FNA without a stylet is
      found to be equivalent to that with a stylet, this could potentially make a strong case for
      not using a stylet and thus making the procedure easier, more time- and cost-efficient. The
      hypothesis and specific aims of this prospective randomized controlled trial are as follows:

      First hypothesis: There is no difference in the degree of cellularity, contamination, and
      amount of blood in samples obtained by EUS-FNA with and without a stylet Specific Aim #1: To
      compare the degree of cellularity, contamination, and amount of blood in samples obtained by
      EUS-FNA with and without a stylet

      Second hypothesis: There is no difference in the diagnostic yield of malignancy in specimens
      obtained by EUS-FNA with a stylet compared with EUS-FNA without a stylet.

      Specific Aim #2: To compare the diagnostic yield of malignancy in specimens obtained by
      EUS-FNA with and without a stylet.

      Third hypothesis: An acceptable level of inter-observer agreement exists among
      cytopathologists in the assessment of specimens obtained from EUS-FNA with stylet and EUS-FNA
      without a stylet.

      Specific Aim #3: To assess the inter-observer agreement among cytopathologists in the
      evaluation of specimens obtained from EUS-FNA with stylet and specimens obtained from EUS-FNA
      without a stylet.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the degree of cellularity, contamination, and amount of blood in samples obtained by EUS-FNA with and without a stylet</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>First hypothesis: There is no difference in the degree of cellularity, contamination, and amount of blood in samples obtained by EUS-FNA with and without a stylet Specific Aim #1: To compare the degree of cellularity, contamination, and amount of blood in samples obtained by EUS-FNA with and without a stylet</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the diagnostic yield of malignancy in specimens obtained by EUS-FNA with and without a stylet.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Second hypothesis: There is no difference in the diagnostic yield of malignancy in specimens obtained by EUS-FNA with a stylet compared with EUS-FNA without a stylet.
Specific Aim #2: To compare the diagnostic yield of malignancy in specimens obtained by EUS-FNA with and without a stylet.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Mediastinal or Intra-abdominal Lymphadenopathy,</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Masses,</condition>
  <condition>Left Adrenal Masses,</condition>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Submucosal Lesions, and</condition>
  <condition>Liver Masses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-FNA with stylet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) with stylet. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) has become a useful tool in the diagnostic evaluation of gastrointestinal tract lesions as well as other accessible organ sites and has found a wide use in the management of various gastrointestinal and non-gastrointestinal lesions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-FNA without stylet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) without stylet. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) has become a useful tool in the diagnostic evaluation of gastrointestinal tract lesions as well as other accessible organ sites and has found a wide use in the management of various gastrointestinal and non-gastrointestinal lesions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EUS - FNA with stylet</intervention_name>
    <description>Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) with stylet. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) has become a useful tool in the diagnostic evaluation of gastrointestinal tract lesions as well as other accessible organ sites and has found a wide use in the management of various gastrointestinal and non-gastrointestinal lesions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-FNA with stylet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FNA Stylet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA)</intervention_name>
    <description>Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA)without stylet. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA) has become a useful tool in the diagnostic evaluation of gastrointestinal tract lesions as well as other accessible organ sites and has found a wide use in the management of various gastrointestinal and non-gastrointestinal lesions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-FNA without stylet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FNA without stylet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age greater than 18 years

          -  Presence of mediastinal or intra-abdominal lymphadenopathy, solid pancreatic mass,
             left adrenal mass, gastrointestinal submucosal lesions or liver mass confirmed by at
             least a single investigational modality - CT scan, magnetic resonance imaging,
             endoscopy.

          -  Capable of providing informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe coagulopathy (INR &gt; 1.5) or thrombocytopenia (platelet count &lt; 50,000)

          -  Lesion unable to be sampled due to the presence of intervening blood vessels

          -  Results of EUS-FNA would not impact patient management

          -  Inability to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amit Rastogi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kansas City Veterans Affairs Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kansas City VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64128</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Veterans Affairs Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64128</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 30, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 1, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 1, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Amit Rastogi, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Kansas City Veteran Affairs Medical Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration (EUS-FNA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Stylet</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphadenopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

