<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01213875</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UFRGS and HCPA 09112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01213875</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Multifaceted Nurse-based Strategy Reduces HEart FaiLure Morbidity in PatiENts Admitted for Acute Decompensated Heart Failure in Brazil</brief_title>
  <acronym>HELEN II</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multifaceted Nurse-based Strategy Reduces HEart FaiLure Morbidity in PatiENts Admitted for Acute Decompensated Heart Failure in Brazil</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado do Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The home based intervention is a multidisciplinary approach that has shown benefit in the
      follow-up of patients with Heart Failure (HF). It is considered one of the most effective
      approaches and humanized by education and care for the patient in his environment of routine.
      In this study the monitoring of HF patients in the home after hospital discharge will include
      the reinforcement, monitoring and reassessment of previously provided guidance on the disease
      and self-care, compliance to prescribed medications and especially the early recognition of
      signs and symptoms of decompensation by patients and their caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The epidemiological picture of cardiovascular disease in which the IC sets itself as the
      leading cause of readmissions in the National Health System and that has not changed over the
      years, undertake the management of the limited resources of the public health system.
      Moreover, the IC contributes to significant loss of quality of life of patients, many in
      socially productive ages resulting in absenteeism and early retirement. This study aims to
      evaluate the impact of home monitoring, intercalated with telephone contact by the nursing
      staff at the HF patients, after hospital discharge in relation to the rate of hospital
      readmissions, compliance and cost-effectiveness this intervention, compared to conventional
      monitoring of patients within 6 months without this intervention, as well as building a
      structure that allows the use computerized forms of assessment in nursing in cardiology by
      mobile technology, assess the knowledge of the disease and the skills to self-care; assess
      compliance, assess the quality of life, linking the sociodemographic characteristics and
      clinical with adherence to treatment and rates of readmission in both groups, and check the
      cost of home monitoring. For this purpose, a randomized clinical trial was designed in two
      centers, blinded to outcomes and costs of readmission.

      Summary of the study:

      The home based intervention is a multidisciplinary approach that has shown benefit in the
      follow-up of patients with Heart Failure (HF). It is considered one of the most effective
      approaches and humanized by education and care for the patient in his environment of routine.
      In this study the monitoring of HF patients in the home after hospital discharge will include
      the reinforcement, monitoring and reassessment of previously provided guidance on the disease
      and self-care, compliance to prescribed medications and especially the early recognition of
      signs and symptoms of decompensation by patients and their caregivers.

      Detailed description: The epidemiological picture of cardiovascular disease in which the IC
      sets itself as the leading cause of readmissions in the National Health System and that has
      not changed over the years, undertake the management of the limited resources of the public
      health system. Moreover, the IC contributes to significant loss of quality of life of
      patients, many in socially productive ages resulting in absenteeism and early retirement.
      This study aims to evaluate the impact of home monitoring, intercalated with telephone
      contact by the nursing staff at the HF patients, after hospital discharge in relation to the
      rate of hospital readmissions, compliance and cost-effectiveness this intervention, compared
      to conventional monitoring of patients within 6 months without this intervention, as well as
      building a structure that allows the use computerized forms of assessment in nursing in
      cardiology by mobile technology, assess the knowledge of the disease and the skills to
      self-care; assess compliance, assess the quality of life, linking the sociodemographic
      characteristics and clinical with adherence to treatment and rates of readmission in both
      groups, and check the cost of home monitoring. For this purpose, a randomized clinical trial
      was designed in two centers, blinded to outcomes and costs of readmission.

      Intervention: There will provided education about what is heart failure, its causes, how to
      recognize signs and symptoms, monitoring of weight and blood pressure, the importance of
      compliance to treatment. Patients will be instructed about the medications they are using. A
      guide to rest and exercise, sexual activity, vaccines, travel and diet (water and salt
      restriction) will be provided. The involvement of the family will be encouraged and
      reinforced at every home visit. The contact with the team should be done when: patient
      observes an increase of 1 or 2 kg of weight in 2-3 days, worsening of dyspnea on effort,
      edema in legs / abdomen, worsening of cough, persistent vomiting, syncope, sputum with blood,
      fever, persistent tachycardia, motor deficit / paralysis and / or unexplained chest pain. In
      phone calls made between home visits, the compliance to treatment will be evaluated and
      reinforced.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome was a composite end-point of a first visit to the emergency department (lasting less than 24 hours), or a first hospital readmission (&gt; 24h) or all-cause death, assessed during the first 6 months of follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 36 months.</time_frame>
    <description>This primary outcomes will be measured at each visit, which will have different intervals, according to the research protocol, with a final evaluation after the last home visit.
Home visits (HV): 7 days after discharge, 15 days after 1st phone call (PC), 30 days after 2nd PC, 30 days after 3rd PC.
Phone calls (PC): 7-10 days after 1st HV, 30 days after 2nd HV, 30 days after 3rd HV, 15 days after 4th HV.
All patients come to Hospital evaluation after the 4th phone call.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness of visits to the emergency department and length of hospitalization.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Costs for intervention group include time of nurses home visit and telephone contacts. The effectiveness will be assessed in life earned years.
Home visits (HV): 7 days after discharge, 15 days after 1st phone call (PC), 30 days after 2nd PC, 30 days after 3rd PC.
Phone calls (PC): 7-10 days after 1st HV, 30 days after 2nd HV, 30 days after 3rd HV, 15 days after 4th HV.
All patients come to Hospital evaluation after the 4th phone call.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary outcomes were each individual end-points</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>All end-points were prospectively evaluated by a researcher that was blinded to group assignment, based on the final 6-months visit and the revision of available electronic records. Whenever it was not available, validation was also based on clinical discharge notes (from emergency departments or hospitals distinct from the institution of origin).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">252</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Intervention and control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>I: Experimental Routine monitoring by health team in the reference institution, four home visits and four telephone contacts with trained nurses.
II: Control Routine monitoring by health team in the reference institution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home based education</intervention_name>
    <description>There will provided education about what is heart failure, its causes, how to recognize signs and symptoms, monitoring of weight and blood pressure, the importance of compliance to treatment. Patients will be instructed about the medications; a guide to rest and exercise, sexual activity, vaccines, travel and diet will be provided. The involvement of the family will be encouraged; the contact with the team should be done when: patient observes an increase of 1 or 2 kg of weight in 2-3 days, worsening of dyspnea on effort, edema in legs / abdomen, worsening of cough, persistent vomiting, syncope,sputum with blood, fever, persistent tachycardia. In phone calls made between home visits, the compliance to treatment will be evaluated and reinforced.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Intervention and control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Education on Heart Failure</other_name>
    <other_name>Home Intervention</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of both sexes, aged 18 years or above, with a diagnosis of heart failure with
             systolic dysfunction (ejection fraction ≤ 45%), hospitalized for decompensation of HF

          -  Who agree to participate in the study by signing the Informed Consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with communication disabilities and people with degenerative neurological
             diseases.

          -  Are also excluded patients who presented acute coronary syndrome (ACS) in the last 6
             months before randomization

          -  Patients with renal, hepatic, pulmonary or systemic disease that may confuse the
             interpretation of the findings or result in limited life expectancy

          -  Surgical plan or therapeutic that might influence the follow-up

          -  Pregnancy, diagnosis of acute heart failure secondary to:

               -  sepsis

               -  myocarditis

               -  myocardial infarction

               -  acute peripartum and other cause

          -  Have no interest in receiving home visits

          -  Living at a distance greater than 10 km from the hospital of origin

          -  Not be able to contact by telephone.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eneida R Rabelo da Silva, RN, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>HCPA and UFRGS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul - Post Graduated Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>Rio Grande do Sul</state>
        <zip>90035003</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 1, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 4, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 1, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 1, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 3, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital de Clinicas de Porto Alegre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eneida Rejane Rabelo da Silva</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor; PhD.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>nursing</keyword>
  <keyword>home based intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>cost</keyword>
  <keyword>efficacy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

