<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02937597</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>eISBAR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02937597</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>E-learning Proficiency Based Progression Training Programme for Clinical Communication on ISBAR Performance (eISBAR)</brief_title>
  <acronym>eISBAR</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of an E-learning Proficiency Based Progression Training Programme for Clinical Communication on ISBAR Performance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College Cork</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College Cork</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      To determine the effectiveness of proficiency based inter-professional communication training
      in an online environment on medical student's use of the ISBAR (Identify, Situation,
      Background, Assessment, Recommendation) communication escalation protocol in the
      deteriorating patient

      Setting: The study will be conducted in University College Cork, Ireland. Participants: Fifth
      year medical students, who are scheduled to undertake ISBAR training as part of the National
      Early Warning Score (NEWS) programme.

      Intervention: Participants will be prospectively randomized to one of three groups for
      training before undertaking a performance assessment of an ISBAR communication relevant to a
      deteriorating patient in a low fidelity simulation environment: HSE group (the national
      e-learning programme only); S group (national e- learning plus access to online scenarios and
      facilitator when requested) and PBP group (national e-learning plus access to online
      scenarios training course with in-built proficiency-based progression, and facilitator when
      requested).

      Main outcome and measures: A proficiency benchmark on the performance of ISBAR communication
      in the context of an acutely deteriorating patient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The first successful simulation validation study used a proficiency-based progression
      methodology. Since then the approach has been successfully deployed to produce superior
      technical skills but has not yet been validated for non-technical (communication) skills. It
      has also not yet been validated through the medium of virtual learning. The ISBAR (Identify,
      Situation, Background, Assessment and Recommendation) has been selected as the standardised
      tool for clinical communication in relation to an acutely deteriorating patient in many
      healthcare organisations worldwide, including Ireland.

      The aim of this study is to explore whether proficiency-based progression (PBP) could be
      applied to an e-learning training course for ISBAR performance to produce a superior skill
      set.

      The study will compare performance outcomes of students who receive the national e-learning
      programme only with those who receive it in combination with either standard e-learning
      course with scenarios or proficiency-based progression (PBP) e-learning course with
      scenarios.

      Participants will be prospectively randomized to one of three training groups. Following a
      pre-test observation through low-fidelity simulation, they will then undergo their respective
      training courses before undertaking a post-test performance assessment of an ISBAR
      communication relevant to a deteriorating patient in a low fidelity simulation environment:

        1. Online learning only (HSE) -the national e-learning programme only

        2. Scenarios (S) -national online learning plus online scenario course training

        3. Proficiency based progression (PBP) -national online learning plus proficiency-based
           progression online scenario course training.

      Main outcome and measures: A proficiency benchmark on the performance of ISBAR communication
      in the context of an acutely deteriorating patient.

      All participants will be required to supply baseline demographic information before
      undertaking the training.

      Performance metrics have previously been identified, operationally defined and agreed upon at
      a modified Delphi panel meeting consisting of medical experts for a series of paper-based
      simulation cases and a standardised high fidelity simulation case used as the assessment
      case. This case will be used in this study in a low fidelity environment. The proficiency
      benchmark for each case has been set based on the performance of experienced medical
      personnel on each case as a series of steps, errors and critical errors.

      Outcome assessment will be scored by reviewing auditory recordings of ISBAR performance by
      each participant on the standardised case in the low fidelity simulated environment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of those reaching the benchmark on the assessment case</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Independent review by two blinded assessors of audio recorded ISBAR phone call conducted in the low fidelity simulation setting</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>recording of data in learning management system for various course attempts</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>recording of data in learning management system for various course attempts</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of completed steps</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of successfully completed steps as predefined by the metrics for the assessment case</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of total errors</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of total errors as predefined by the metrics for the assessment case</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of errors/critical errors</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of errors/critical errors as predefined by the metrics for the assessment case</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of attempts required to reach proficiency on each of the 4 cases in ePBP</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of attempts required to reach proficiency on each of the 4 cases as recorded by the e-learning course ePBP</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">114</enrollment>
  <condition>Communication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>National e-learning programme only (HSE)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active Comparator: National e-learning programme only (HSE) National e-learning programme only Recent successful completion of the National e-learning programme by certificate will be displayed. Students then undergo performance assessment via low fidelity simulation and complete a questionnaire.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>eS: eScenarios</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recent successful completion of the National e-learning e-learning programme by certificate will be displayed. Students will proceed to an online learning course with 4 scenarios to work through but no requirement to meet a proficiency benchmark. Following training students undergo performance assessment via low fidelity simulation and complete a questionnaire.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ePBP: eProficiency Based Progression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recent successful completion of the National e-learning programme by certificate will be displayed. Students will proceed to a PBP e-learning course using the same series of cases as S. PBP students will be scored according to predefined metrics and will be required to reach proficiency benchmarks for the cases within the e-learning course to allow progression through the cases. Following training students undergo performance assessment via low fidelity simulation and complete a questionnaire.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ePBP: eProficiency Based Progression</intervention_name>
    <description>National e-learning programme plus Proficiency-based progression through 4 scenarios in an online learning course and facilitator when requested</description>
    <arm_group_label>ePBP: eProficiency Based Progression</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>eS: eScenarios</intervention_name>
    <description>National e-learning programme plus access to 4 scenarios in an online learning course and facilitator when requested</description>
    <arm_group_label>eS: eScenarios</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HSE</intervention_name>
    <description>National HSE e-learning programme only</description>
    <arm_group_label>National e-learning programme only (HSE)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  final year medical students in UCC

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  lack of consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony Gallagher, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Director Technology Enhanced Learning ASSERT, UCC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College Cork</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cork</city>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ireland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gallagher AG, Seymour NE, Jordan-Black JA, Bunting BP, McGlade K, Satava RM. Prospective, randomized assessment of transfer of training (ToT) and transfer effectiveness ratio (TER) of virtual reality simulation training for laparoscopic skill acquisition. Ann Surg. 2013 Jun;257(6):1025-31. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e318284f658.</citation>
    <PMID>23426342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Angelo RL, Ryu RK, Pedowitz RA, Beach W, Burns J, Dodds J, Field L, Getelman M, Hobgood R, McIntyre L, Gallagher AG. A Proficiency-Based Progression Training Curriculum Coupled With a Model Simulator Results in the Acquisition of a Superior Arthroscopic Bankart Skill Set. Arthroscopy. 2015 Oct;31(10):1854-71. doi: 10.1016/j.arthro.2015.07.001. Epub 2015 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>26341047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Sickle KR, Ritter EM, Baghai M, Goldenberg AE, Huang IP, Gallagher AG, Smith CD. Prospective, randomized, double-blind trial of curriculum-based training for intracorporeal suturing and knot tying. J Am Coll Surg. 2008 Oct;207(4):560-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2008.05.007. Epub 2008 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18926460</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University College Cork</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nora McCarthy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Lecturer in Medical Education</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>proficiency based progression</keyword>
  <keyword>feedback</keyword>
  <keyword>computer based assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>non technical skills</keyword>
  <keyword>deteriorating patient</keyword>
  <keyword>ISBAR</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease Progression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

