<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02936856</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GuangxiMUBT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02936856</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hepatic Arteriography in Liver Cancer Diagnosis and Staging Applications</brief_title>
  <acronym>RDSA</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guangxi Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guangxi Medical University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary liver cancer is one of the most common malignant tumor and leading cause of
      cancer-related death worldwide. Basically therapeutic strategies were considered and given
      based on the staging of liver cancer. Thus, the confirmatory diagnosis of numbers and
      distribution of malignant lesions were extreme important. Enhanced CT or MRI is routinely
      imaging scans to detect and identify lesions. Unfortunately, some malignant lesions usually
      presented untypical imaging characteristics, especially among lesions no larger than 1 cm,
      which misleading to the exact staging of liver cancer and the optimal therapeutic strategies.

      Basically most of blood supply for malignant liver tumors is from the hepatic artery. Based
      on this fact, hepatic arterial digital subtraction angiography could potentially elevate the
      accuracy and sensitivity of detection malignant lesions numbers and distribution.

      In this study the investigators will compare the numbers and distribution of malignant
      lesions before and after hepatic arteriography, then to revise the staging of liver cancer
      and to provide better therapeutic strategies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of numbers of confirmatory diagnosis of malignant lesions before and after hepatic arteriography</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the numbers and distribution of confirmatory diagnosis (positive/negative) of malignant lesions before and after hepatic arteriography, which to re-evaluate the staging of primary liver cancer and to further provide better therapeutic strategies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of distribution of confirmatory diagnosis of malignant lesions before and after hepatic arteriography</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the distribution of confirmatory diagnosis (positive/negative) of malignant lesions before and after hepatic arteriography, which to re-evaluate the staging of primary liver cancer and to further provide better therapeutic strategies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>HepatoCellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>After Hepatic Arteriography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Before Hepatic Arteriography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hepatic Arteriography</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>After Hepatic Arteriography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Before Hepatic Arteriography</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with primary liver cancer who is firstly diagnosed in Affiliated Tumor
             Hospital of Guangxi Medical University after November 2015, and the clinical
             diagnostic criteria is according to China's &quot;primary liver cancer diagnostic and
             treatment practices (2011)&quot;. Clinical diagnostic criteria: In all solid tumors, there
             is only hepatocellular carcinoma can use clinical diagnostic criteria, which is
             recognized by domestic and foreign countries. Combined with China's national
             conditions, history of the national standards and clinical practice, the Expert Group
             can establish the clinical diagnosis of hepatocellular carcinoma requested the
             following conditions 1 + 2a or 1 + 2b + 3 at the same time satisfy:

               -  Patients have evidence of liver cirrhosis or HBV and / or HCV infection (HBV and
                  / or HCV antigen positive).

               -  Typical imaging features of hepatocellular carcinoma: liver lesion shows arterial
                  hypervascularity and venous or delayed phase washout in multidetector CT scan and
                  / or dynamic contrast enhanced MRI. a: If the liver lesion diameter≥2cm, the
                  diagnosis of hepatocellular carcinoma can be made when typical imaging features
                  show in one of the imaging methods. b: If the liver lesion diameter is between 1
                  to 2cm, the diagnosis of hepatocellular carcinoma can be made when typical
                  imaging features show in both of the imaging methods.

               -  Serum AFP≥400μg/L for 1 month or ≥200μg/L for 2 month, and can rule out other
                  causes of AFP increasing (pregnancy, reproductive system embryo-derived tumors,
                  active liver disease and secondary liver cancer, etc.).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients do not conform to China's &quot;primary liver cancer diagnostic and treatment
             practices (2011)&quot;.

          -  Patients allergic to Iodine-containing contrast agents or with obvious
             hyperthyroidism.

          -  Patients with severe cardiovascular disease or liver or renal insufficiency, who do
             not tolerate digital subtraction angiography or will significantly increase the risk
             of diseases.

          -  Patients have severe coagulation disorders or are extreme weak.

          -  Patients have fever or have infection on the puncture site.

          -  Patients suffer from mental illness or cannot cooperate with the treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>TaoBai</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanning</city>
        <state>Guangxi</state>
        <zip>530000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bai Tao, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+86 13878862632</phone>
      <email>25859373@qq.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 14, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Guangxi Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>TaoBai</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

