<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02933645</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>T210/2015</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-005392-24</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02933645</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Intranasal Insulin Administration on Tissue Specific Insulin Sensitivity</brief_title>
  <acronym>NASO-PET</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Intranasal Insulin Administration on Tissue Specific Insulin Sensitivity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Turku University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Tuebingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Turku University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent research has suggested that intranasally administered insulin can reach the brain
      quickly without passing through circulation and evoke increased insulin sensitivity and
      tissue glucose consumption during insulin stimulation (low-dose hyperinsulinemic, euglycemic
      clamp). It is still not known what mechanism causes these changes or what tissues are
      involved in this.

      In this study, the changes in tissue-specific insulin sensitivity and glucose uptake will be
      investigated by using glucose-analogue radiotracer ([18F]-fluorodeoxyglucose) with positron
      emission tomography (PET) imaging during insulin stimulation. Ten healthy males are studied,
      each receiving nasal sprays containing insulin or placebo in a randomized order on two
      separate days. After spray administration, glucose uptake in skeletal muscle, liver,
      subcutaneous and visceral adipose tissue, myocardium, intestines, brown adipose tissue and
      brain assessed by PET imaging and glucose uptake in these tissues is analyzed. Endogenous
      glucose production is calculated facilitating the measurements glucose and radiotracer uptake
      in tissues and tracer loss into urine.

      As skeletal muscle consumes most of the glucose available, it is likely that administration
      of insulin sprays will result in an increased uptake in this tissue. Some increase in glucose
      uptake might also be seen in other tissue types after insulin spray versus placebo spray
      administration.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to investigate the effects of intranasally administered
      insulin versus placebo on tissue specific glucose uptake of the key metabolic organs as well
      as on endogenous glucose production.

      SAMPLE SIZE:

      A total of ten (n=10) healthy males are planned to be included, and the study is conducted
      with a cross-over design with each subject being investigated twice, once using intranasal
      insulin and once using intranasal placebo in single-blinded randomized order.

      SCREENING VISIT/ELIGIBILITY:

      Main inclusion and exclusion criteria will be evaluated at a screening visit. This visit will
      include a frequently-sampled 75 g oral glucose tolerance test as well as anthropometric
      measurements and clinical examination.

      PET STUDY VISITS:

      On the PET study days two cannulas will be inserted, one in a radial or an antecubital vein
      for tracer injection and infusion of glucose and insulin, another in the opposite radial or
      antecubital vein for blood sampling. The arm where the samples are taken will be kept warm to
      obtain arterialized venous blood. The subjects will rest in supine position on the PET/CT
      scanner bed during the study.

      HYPERINSULINEMIC EUGLYCEMIC CLAMP:

      Whole-body insulin sensitivity will be assessed by hyperinsulinemic euglycemic clamp with an
      primed insulin infusion rate of 0.25 mU/kg/min. To maintain the glucose level at 5.0 mmol/l
      intravenous glucose infusion is administered individually as needed to maintain euglycemia.

      NASAL SPRAY ADMINISTRATION:

      After 30 minutes of intravenous insulin infusion, the subjects will receive either 160 IU
      human insulin or placebo intranasally. The small amount of insulin known to be absorbed into
      circulation after the insulin nasal spray will be mimicked on placebo day. Therefore subjects
      will be administered 2.5 mU/kg of additional intravenous insulin over 15 minutes together
      with placebo spray administration.

      LABORATORY SAMPLES:

      To verify comparable insulin levels in circulation during the study, serum insulin and
      C-peptide levels will be determined in fasting state, and repeatedly throughout the
      experiment.

      BLINDING:

      The clinician and the study nurse are aware which spray is given, but subjects are blinded
      and additional insulin infusion on placebo day is done in a manner that the subjects remain
      blinded. The sprays are given on a randomized order. The randomization code was generated by
      a statistician using SAS, version 9.3 for Windows. The randomization block size was four and
      the method was permuted block randomization. The randomization was done for 16 subjects in
      case of discontinuations.

      HEART RATE VARIABILITY:

      Heart rate variability is recorded to evaluate changes in autonomous nervous system activity
      after spray administration on both visits. Polar RS800CX heart rate monitor (Polar Electro
      Ltd., Kempele, Finland) with two electrodes is used.

      FDG-PET-IMAGING:

      70 minutes after the start of clamp and 40 minutes after the application of nasal sprays the
      positron emission tomography (PET) scanning is started with the injection of glucose-analogue
      tracer labeled with positron-emitting fluorine-18 ([18F]-fluorodeoxyglucose, [18F]-FDG).
      PET/CT, GE DiscoveryTM ST System (General Electric Medical Systems, Milwaukee, WI, USA) with
      final resolution of 3.75 mm in PET images is used. All data will be corrected for dead-time,
      decay and measured photon attenuation. Dynamic PET-scans will be reconstructed with iterative
      reconstruction method. Radiotracer [18F]-FDG is produced in the PET Centre radiochemistry
      laboratory. Plasma radioactivity is measured with an automatic gamma counter by a medical
      technologist in the laboratory of the Turku PET Centre (Wizard 1480 3&quot;, Wallac, Turku,
      Finland).

      PET-IMAGE ANALYSIS:

      To determine tissue-specific glucose uptake during insulin stimulation from PET data,
      time-activity-curves of tissue activity and activity measured from plasma during the scanning
      are analysed graphically to define tracer's fractional uptake (Ki). To calculate glucose
      uptake rate (reported as µmol/kg/min), Ki is multiplied with plasma glucose level, divided
      with a constant that accounts for the differences in transport and dephosphorylation rates
      between D-glucose and FDG (lumped constant, LC) and divided with tissue specific gravity.
      Based on previous studies the LC is 1,2 for skeletal muscle; 1,0 for heart and liver; 1,14
      for adipose tissue; 1,1 for intestines and 0,8 for brain. After the PET/CT an urine sample
      will be collected to quantify endogenous glucose production (EGP). This will be determined by
      subtracting urine loss and glucose infusion rate from rate of glucose disappearance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Skeletal muscle glucose uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>Data is collected during 100 min PET scan started 40 min after spray administration.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in skeletal muscle insulin stimulated glucose uptake (μmol/min/kg) after insulin versus placebo nasal spray administration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endogenous glucose production</measure>
    <time_frame>Data is collected during 100 min PET scan started 40 min after spray administration.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in endogenous glucose production after insulin versus placebo nasal spray administration (μmol/min/kg) . Endogenous glucose production is determined by subtracting urine loss and glucose infusion rate from rate of glucose disappearance facilitating measurements of fluorodeoxyglucose concentrations in plasma after the injection and in urine right after the end of PET scanning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver glucose uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>Data is collected during 100 min PET scan started 40 min after spray administration.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in liver insulin stimulated glucose uptake (μmol/min/kg) after insulin versus placebo nasal spray administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Insulin Resistance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects administer 2 intranasal sprays into each nostril every minute for 4 minutes, a total of 16 sprays. Sprays contain fast-acting human insulin Actrapid (Novo Nordisk A/S, Bagsvaerd, Denmark). The glass spray flasks are produced by AeroPump GmBH, Germany and give 0,1 ml of fluid per spray. To account for the small amount of insulin absorbed into circulation after the insulin nasal sprays, on the placebo day subjects will be administered 2.5 mU/kg of additional intravenous insulin (Actrapid, Novo Nordisk A/S, Bagsvaerd, Denmark) over 15 minutes.
30 min before spray administration a hyperinsulinemic euglycemic clamp will be started and continued for 170 minutes. 40 min after spray administration [18F]-FDG PET-CT scan lasting 100 min is started.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects administer 2 intranasal sprays into each nostril every minute for 4 minutes, a total of 16 sprays. Sprays contain Insulin Diluting Medium for Novorapid and Levemir (Novo Nordisk A/S, Bagsvaerd,Denmark). The glass spray flasks are produced by AeroPump GmBH, Germany and give 0,1 ml of fluid per spray. To account for the small amount of insulin absorbed into circulation after the insulin nasal sprays, on the placebo day subjects will be administered 2.5 mU/kg of additional intravenous insulin (Actrapid, Novo Nordisk A/S, Bagsvaerd,Denmark) over 15 min.
30 min before spray administration a hyperinsulinemic euglycemic clamp will be started and continued for 170 minutes. 40 min after spray administration [18F]-FDG PET-CT scan lasting 100 min is started.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Actrapid</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects administer 2 intranasal sprays into each nostril every minute for 4 minutes, a total of 16 sprays or 160 IU of fast-acting human insulin (Actrapid, Novo Nordisk A/S, Bagsvaerd, Denmark). The glass spray flasks are produced by AeroPump GmBH, Germany and give 0,1 ml of fluid per spray.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ATC-code A10AB01</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects administer 2 intranasal sprays into each nostril every minute for 4 minutes, a total of 16 sprays. Sprays contain Insulin Diluting Medium for Novorapid and Levemir (Novo Nordisk A/S, Bagsvaerd, Denmark). The glass spray flasks are produced by AeroPump GmBH, Germany and give 0,1 ml of fluid per spray. To account for the small amount of insulin absorbed into circulation after the insulin nasal sprays, on the placebo day subjects will be administered 2.5 mU/kg of additional intravenous insulin (Actrapid, Novo Nordisk A/S, Bagsvaerd, Denmark) over 15 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Insulin Diluting Medium for Novorapid and Levemir</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[18F]-FDG PET-CT</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will undergo two positron emission tomography (PET) studies. On both visits they are injected with 185 MBq [18F]-fluorodeoxyglucose and scanned with a combined PET and computed tomography scanner.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tissue specific insulin sensitivity measurement</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hyperinsulinemic euglycemic clamp</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will undergo two hyperinsulinemic euglycemic clamp studies. The insulin infusion will be administered intravenously at a steady rate of 0.25 mU/kg/min for approximately 170 minutes. Glucose will be administered intravenously as a 200 mg/ml fluid to at varying rate to maintain euglycemia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo nasal spray</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Whole-body insulin sensitivity measurement</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. BMI 18,5-25 kg/m2

          2. Fasting plasma glucose less than 6.1 mmol/l

          3. Normal 2-hour oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any chronic disease or medication that could affect glucose metabolism

          2. History of anorexia nervosa or bulimia

          3. Smoking of tobacco, taking of snuffs, or use of narcotics

          4. Abusive use of alcohol

          5. Any other condition that in the opinion of the investigator could create a hazard to
             the subject safety, endanger the study procedures or interfere with the interpretation
             of study results
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pirjo Nuutila, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Turku University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Turku PET Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Turku</city>
        <zip>20520</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heni M, Wagner R, Kullmann S, Veit R, Mat Husin H, Linder K, Benkendorff C, Peter A, Stefan N, Häring HU, Preissl H, Fritsche A. Central insulin administration improves whole-body insulin sensitivity via hypothalamus and parasympathetic outputs in men. Diabetes. 2014 Dec;63(12):4083-8. doi: 10.2337/db14-0477. Epub 2014 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>25028522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heni M, Kullmann S, Preissl H, Fritsche A, Häring HU. Impaired insulin action in the human brain: causes and metabolic consequences. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2015 Dec;11(12):701-11. doi: 10.1038/nrendo.2015.173. Epub 2015 Oct 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26460339</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Born J, Lange T, Kern W, McGregor GP, Bickel U, Fehm HL. Sniffing neuropeptides: a transnasal approach to the human brain. Nat Neurosci. 2002 Jun;5(6):514-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11992114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeFronzo RA, Tobin JD, Andres R. Glucose clamp technique: a method for quantifying insulin secretion and resistance. Am J Physiol. 1979 Sep;237(3):E214-23.</citation>
    <PMID>382871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patlak CS, Blasberg RG. Graphical evaluation of blood-to-brain transfer constants from multiple-time uptake data. Generalizations. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 1985 Dec;5(4):584-90.</citation>
    <PMID>4055928</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peltoniemi P, Lönnroth P, Laine H, Oikonen V, Tolvanen T, Grönroos T, Strindberg L, Knuuti J, Nuutila P. Lumped constant for [(18)F]fluorodeoxyglucose in skeletal muscles of obese and nonobese humans. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2000 Nov;279(5):E1122-30.</citation>
    <PMID>11052968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bøtker HE, Böttcher M, Schmitz O, Gee A, Hansen SB, Cold GE, Nielsen TT, Gjedde A. Glucose uptake and lumped constant variability in normal human hearts determined with [18F]fluorodeoxyglucose. J Nucl Cardiol. 1997 Mar-Apr;4(2 Pt 1):125-32.</citation>
    <PMID>9115064</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iozzo P, Jarvisalo MJ, Kiss J, Borra R, Naum GA, Viljanen A, Viljanen T, Gastaldelli A, Buzzigoli E, Guiducci L, Barsotti E, Savunen T, Knuuti J, Haaparanta-Solin M, Ferrannini E, Nuutila P. Quantification of liver glucose metabolism by positron emission tomography: validation study in pigs. Gastroenterology. 2007 Feb;132(2):531-42. Epub 2006 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>17258736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Virtanen KA, Peltoniemi P, Marjamäki P, Asola M, Strindberg L, Parkkola R, Huupponen R, Knuuti J, Lönnroth P, Nuutila P. Human adipose tissue glucose uptake determined using [(18)F]-fluoro-deoxy-glucose ([(18)F]FDG) and PET in combination with microdialysis. Diabetologia. 2001 Dec;44(12):2171-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11793018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Honka H, Mäkinen J, Hannukainen JC, Tarkia M, Oikonen V, Teräs M, Fagerholm V, Ishizu T, Saraste A, Stark C, Vähäsilta T, Salminen P, Kirjavainen A, Soinio M, Gastaldelli A, Knuuti J, Iozzo P, Nuutila P. Validation of [18F]fluorodeoxyglucose and positron emission tomography (PET) for the measurement of intestinal metabolism in pigs, and evidence of intestinal insulin resistance in patients with morbid obesity. Diabetologia. 2013 Apr;56(4):893-900. doi: 10.1007/s00125-012-2825-5. Epub 2013 Jan 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23334481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu HM, Bergsneider M, Glenn TC, Yeh E, Hovda DA, Phelps ME, Huang SC. Measurement of the global lumped constant for 2-deoxy-2-[18F]fluoro-D-glucose in normal human brain using [15O]water and 2-deoxy-2-[18F]fluoro-D-glucose positron emission tomography imaging. A method with validation based on multiple methodologies. Mol Imaging Biol. 2003 Jan-Feb;5(1):32-41.</citation>
    <PMID>14499160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iozzo P, Gastaldelli A, Järvisalo MJ, Kiss J, Borra R, Buzzigoli E, Viljanen A, Naum G, Viljanen T, Oikonen V, Knuuti J, Savunen T, Salvadori PA, Ferrannini E, Nuutila P. 18F-FDG assessment of glucose disposal and production rates during fasting and insulin stimulation: a validation study. J Nucl Med. 2006 Jun;47(6):1016-22.</citation>
    <PMID>16741312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Insulin</keyword>
  <keyword>Intranasal</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucose/metabolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucose homeostasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin, Globin Zinc</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Detemir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Aspart</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

