<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02935907</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>APG-115-US-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02935907</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>APG-115 in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors or Lymphomas</brief_title>
  <acronym>APG-115</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of the Safety, Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic Properties of Orally Administered APG-115 in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors or Lymphomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ascentage Pharma Group Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ascentage Pharma Group Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      APG-115 is a novel, orally active small-molecule mouse double minute 2 homolog (MDM2)
      inhibitor. Mechanistically, APG-115 increases p53 and p21 overexpression, activates p53 -
      mediated apoptosis in tumor cells retaining wild-type p53. APG-115 has shown strong dose- and
      schedule-dependent antitumor activities in multiple human cancer xenograft and a patient
      derived xenograft (PDX) models. The preclinical data generated from APG-115 suggest that it
      may have a broad therapeutic potential for the treatment of human cancer as a single agent
      and in combination with other classes of anticancer drugs. APG-115 is intended for the
      treatment of patients with advanced solid tumors and lymphomas. Upon completion of the Phase
      1 dose escalation study to establish the maximum tolerated dose (MTD), dose-limiting
      toxicities (DLTs), and/or recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D), several phase Ib/II studies will
      be implemented accordingly.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patients with APG-115 treatment related adverse events (AE), serious adverse events (SAE) will be assessed according NCI CTCAE Version 4.0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response will be evaluated every 2 cycles (8 weeks), according to the revised RECIST Guideline, Version 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>18-24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) of APG-115 on Day 1-3 and Day 21-23 post APG-115 treatment on cycle 1</measure>
    <time_frame>23 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of APG-115 on Day 1 -3 and Day 21 - 23 post APG-115 treatment on cycle 1</measure>
    <time_frame>23 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Patients With Advanced Solid Tumor or Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>APG-115</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>APG-115 to be explored sequentially during accelerated dose escalation. This will continue until either the occurrence in Cycle 1 of one DLT or two Grade 2 toxicities (graded as per the National Cancer Institute's Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events [NCI CTCAE] version 4.0) that are related or possibly related to APG-115. When either of these criteria is fulfilled, dose escalation will be converted to a standard 3+3 escalation scheme,</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>APG-115</intervention_name>
    <description>Multiple dose cohorts, PO, every other day of a 28 day cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>APG-115</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed locally advanced or metastatic solid tumor
             or lymphoma that has relapsed from or is refractory to standard treatment, or no
             standard treatment is available. Only patients with advanced/metastatic cancer who
             have disease progression after treatment with all available therapies that are known
             to confer clinical benefit.

          2. Male or non-pregnant, non-lactating female patients age ≥18 years

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status ≤ 2

          4. Adequate hematologic and bone marrow functions

          5. Adequate renal and liver function

          6. Troponin (I) ≤ Upper Limit of Normal

          7. Brain metastases with clinically controlled neurologic symptoms, defined as surgical
             excision and/or radiation therapy followed by 21 days of stable neurologic function &amp;
             no evidence of CNS disease progression as determined by CT or MRI within 21 days prior
             to the first dose of study drug.

          8. Willingness to use contraception by a method that is deemed effective by the
             investigator by both males and female patients of child bearing potential
             (postmenopausal women must have been amenorrheal for at least 12 months to be
             considered of non-childbearing potential) and their partners throughout the treatment
             period and for at least three months following the last dose of study drug.

          9. Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent form (the
             consent form must be signed by the patient prior to any study-specific procedures).

         10. Willingness and ability to comply with study procedures and follow-up examination.

         11. Willingness to provide and there is confirmed availability of pre-existing diagnostic
             or resected tumor samples, such as paraffin-embedded sections. Providing fresh tumor
             biopsy is optional for subjects in dose escalation cohorts.

         12. Willingness to undergo tumor genotyping for P53 mutation at screening. Confirmation of
             P53 non-mutant status is encouraged, but not required.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Receiving concurrent anti-cancer therapy (chemotherapy, radiation therapy, surgery,
             immunotherapy, hormonal therapy, targeted therapy, biologic therapy, with the
             exception of hormones for hypothyroidism or estrogen replacement therapy (ERT), anti
             estrogen analogs, agonists required to suppress serum testosterone levels); or any
             investigational therapy within 14 days prior to the first dose of study drug.

          2. Steroid therapy for anti-neoplastic intent within 7 days prior to the first dose of
             study drug.

          3. Continuance of toxicities due to prior radiotherapy or chemotherapy agents that do not
             recover to ≤ Grade 2.

          4. Has gastrointestinal conditions that could affect the absorption of APG-115 in the
             opinion of the Investigator.

          5. Use of therapeutic doses of anti-coagulants is excluded, along with anti-platelet
             agents; low-dose anticoagulation medications that are used to maintain the patency of
             a central intravenous catheter are permitted.

          6. Received a biologic (granulocyte colonystimulating factor, granulocyte-macrophage
             colony-stimulating factor or erythropoietin) within 14 days prior to the first dose of
             study drug.

          7. Failure to recover adequately, as judged by the investigator, from prior surgical
             procedures. Patients who have had major surgery within 28 days from study entry, and
             patients who have had minor surgery within 14 days of study entry.

          8. Unstable angina, myocardial infarction, or a coronary revascularization procedure
             within 180 days of study entry.

          9. Neurologic instability per clinical evaluation due to tumor involvement of the central
             nervous system (CNS). Patients with CNS tumors that have been treated, are
             asymptomatic and who have discontinued steroids (for the treatment of CNS tumors) for
             &gt; 28 days may be enrolled.

         10. Active symptomatic fungal, bacterial and/or viral infection including, but not limited
             to, active human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or viral hepatitis (B or C).

         11. Diagnosis of fever and neutropenia within 1 week prior to study drug administration.

         12. Uncontrolled concurrent illness including, but not limited to: serious uncontrolled
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             the study requirements.

         13. Prior treatment with MDM2 inhibitors.

         14. Any other condition or circumstance of that would, in the opinion of the investigator,
             make the patient unsuitable for participation in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Drew Resco, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>South Texas Accelerated Research Therapeutics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yifan Zhai, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>240-505-6608</phone>
    <email>yzhai@ascentagepharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>START Midwest</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grand Rapids</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>49503</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathy Estkowski, BS, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>616-954-5554</phone>
      <email>kathy.estkowski@startmidwest.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Yvette C Cole, RN, BSN, OCN</last_name>
      <phone>616-954-5554</phone>
      <email>yvette.cole@startmidwest.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nehal Lakhani, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The START Center for Cancer Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Isabel Jimenez, RN, MSN</last_name>
      <phone>210-593-5265</phone>
      <email>isabel.jimenez@start.stoh.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 14, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

