<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00909948</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Protocol 07-068</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00909948</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00981760</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intentional Rejection of the Donor Graft Using Recipient Leukocyte Infusion(s) Following Nonmyeloablative Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</brief_title>
  <acronym>RLI</acronym>
  <official_title>Intentional Rejection of the Donor Graft Using Recipient Leukocyte Infusion(s) Following Nonmyeloablative Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study is based on our observation of paradoxical tumor regression after
      rejection of the donor graft in conjunction with the results of our murine experiments. We
      hypothesize that clinically meaningful responses can be achieved in patients with advanced
      malignancies with a transplant strategy using nonmyeloablative conditioning and related
      mismatched donor stem cell transplant where the intention will be to initially achieve mixed
      chimerism which will be followed by recipient lymphocyte infusion (RLI) in an attempt to
      deliberately reject the donor graft. This will lead to the development of novel transplant
      strategies for achieving antitumor effects without the risk of graft versus host disease
      (GVHD). This proposed protocol is a Pilot Study that will evaluate the safety of this
      outpatient transplant strategy, i.e., establishment of initial mixed chimerism followed by
      RLI for donor graft rejection, in patients with advanced lymphomas, and multiple myeloma.

      In addition, because RLI have been reported to reverse ongoing GVHD, this approach might
      potentially reverse GVHD while achieving antitumor responses if this complication
      unexpectedly occurs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow Accrual
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the safety at ≤100 days of a non myeloablative mismatched related HCT when followed by recipient leukocyte infusion to induce deliberate rejection of the donor graft.</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days post transplant</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the incidence of acute and chronic GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the incidence of loss of donor grafts</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate progression-free and overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate antitumor responses following this transplant strategy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Non Hodgkin's Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Hodgkin Disease</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fludarabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients in this cohort will receive fludarabine 30 mg/m2/day on days -4 to -2 and 200 cGy TBI on day 0.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TBI only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be given 200 centiGray (cGy) total body irradiation (TBI) in one fraction. TBI will be given on day 0, 4 to 6 hours prior to HCT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine and total body irradiation</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients in the second cohort will receive fludarabine 30 mg/m2/day on days -4 to -2 and 200 cGy TBI on day 0.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fludarabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total body irradiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive 200 cGy TBI on day 0,4-6 hours prior to HCT.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TBI only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with chemorefractory non-Hodgkin's or Hodgkin's lymphoma or multiple myeloma.

             Criteria for consideration of enrollment will include:

               1. primary refractory or refractory relapsed disease for which autologous HCT is
                  unlikely to be beneficial;

               2. relapse after autologous HCT

               3. ineligibility for standard myeloablative or nonmyeloablative allo-HCT because of
                  either lack of a donor or patient considerations

          2. Non Hodgkin's lymphoma, or Hodgkin's lymphoma: primary refractory or refractory
             relapse

          3. Multiple myeloma; primary refractory or refractory relapse

          4. Patients with the above malignancies who have had a previous autologous or allogeneic
             bone marrow or stem cell transplant.

          5. An estimated disease-free survival of less than one year.

          6. Age 18 to age &lt; 75 years

          7. ECOG performance status of 0, 1, or 2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients whose life expectancy is limited by diseases other than their malignancy

          2. Patients who have a 5/6 or better matched related donor or a 4/6 or better umbilical
             cord blood donor and who are medically eligible for conventional myeloablative or
             non-myeloablative transplant will be excluded

          3. Cardiac disease: symptomatic congestive heart failure or RVG or echocardiogram
             determined LVEF ogf&lt; 30%, active angina pectoris or uncontrolled hypertension

          4. Pulmonary disease: severe chronic obstructive lung disease, or symptomatic restrictive
             lung disease, or corrected DLCO &lt; 40% of predicted

          5. Renal disease: serum creatinine &gt; 3.0 mg/dl.

          6. Hepatic disease: serum bilirubin &gt; 3.0 mg/dl or alkaline phosphatase, SGOT or SGPT &gt; 3
             x ULN

          7. Neurologic disease: symptomatic leukoencephalopathy, active CNS malignancy or other
             neuropsychiatric abnormalities believed to preclude transplantation (pervious CNS
             malignancy presently in CR is not an exclusion)

          8. Uncontrolled infection.

          9. Recipient leukocyte infusion (RLI) might involve the infusion of circulating tumor
             cells to the patients. To minimize this risk patients who have evidence of circulating
             tumor cells by light microscopy and flow cytometry will be excluded

         10. Patients with acute leukemia will be excluded because they will likely have much
             greater circulating tumor burden, which would increase the risk of infusion of clonal
             tumor cells
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bimalangshu R Dey, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MGH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bortin MM, Rimm AA, Saltzstein EC. Graft versus leukemia: quantification of adoptive immunotherapy in murine leukemia. Science. 1973 Feb 23;179(4075):811-3.</citation>
    <PMID>4405359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hill GR, Krenger W, Ferrara JL. The role of cytokines in acute graft-versus-host disease. Cytokines Cell Mol Ther. 1997 Dec;3(4):257-66. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9740354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dey BR, McAfee S, Colby C, Sackstein R, Saidman S, Tarbell N, Sachs DH, Sykes M, Spitzer TR. Impact of prophylactic donor leukocyte infusions on mixed chimerism, graft-versus-host disease, and antitumor response in patients with advanced hematologic malignancies treated with nonmyeloablative conditioning and allogeneic bone marrow transplantation. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2003 May;9(5):320-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12766882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sykes M, Romick ML, Sachs DH. Interleukin 2 prevents graft-versus-host disease while preserving the graft-versus-leukemia effect of allogeneic T cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1990 Aug;87(15):5633-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2377601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mapara MY, Kim YM, Wang SP, Bronson R, Sachs DH, Sykes M. Donor lymphocyte infusions mediate superior graft-versus-leukemia effects in mixed compared to fully allogeneic chimeras: a critical role for host antigen-presenting cells. Blood. 2002 Sep 1;100(5):1903-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12176915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kraus AB, Shaffer J, Toh HC, Preffer F, Dombkowski D, Saidman S, Colby C, George R, McAfee S, Sackstein R, Dey B, Spitzer TR, Sykes M. Early host CD8 T-cell recovery and sensitized anti-donor interleukin-2-producing and cytotoxic T-cell responses associated with marrow graft rejection following nonmyeloablative allogeneic bone marrow transplantation. Exp Hematol. 2003 Jul;31(7):609-21.</citation>
    <PMID>12842706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spitzer TR, McAfee S, Sackstein R, Colby C, Toh HC, Multani P, Saidman S, Weyouth DW, Preffer F, Poliquin C, Foley A, Cox B, Andrews D, Sachs DH, Sykes M. Intentional induction of mixed chimerism and achievement of antitumor responses after nonmyeloablative conditioning therapy and HLA-matched donor bone marrow transplantation for refractory hematologic malignancies. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2000;6(3A):309-20.</citation>
    <PMID>10905768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubio MT, Kim YM, Sachs T, Mapara M, Zhao G, Sykes M. Antitumor effect of donor marrow graft rejection induced by recipient leukocyte infusions in mixed chimeras prepared with nonmyeloablative conditioning: critical role for recipient-derived IFN-gamma. Blood. 2003 Sep 15;102(6):2300-7. Epub 2003 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>12791660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ballen KK, Becker PS, Emmons RV, Fitzgerald TJ, Hsieh CC, Liu Q, Heyes C, Clark Y, Levy W, Lambert JF, Chiafari F, Szymanski I, Rososhansky S, Popovsky MA, Stewart FM, Quesenberry PJ. Low-dose total body irradiation followed by allogeneic lymphocyte infusion may induce remission in patients with refractory hematologic malignancy. Blood. 2002 Jul 15;100(2):442-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12091334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Colby C, Sykes M, Sachs DH, Spitzer TR. Cellular modulation of acute graft-vs.-host disease. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 1997 Dec;3(6):287-93. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9502295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bimalangshu Dey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Related stem cell transplant,</keyword>
  <keyword>TBI,</keyword>
  <keyword>Mismatched stem cell transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Fludarabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-myeloablative</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

