<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00909350</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>06-005272</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00909350</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Micro-RNA (miR) Expression in Upper Gastrointestinal Mucosal Tissue</brief_title>
  <official_title>Micro-RNA (miR) Expression in Upper Gastrointestinal Mucosal Tissue: A Potential Target for Understanding and Preventing the Progression of Barrett's Esophagus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a laboratory-based, exploratory study using tissue obtained from our clinical
      practice. The purpose of this study is to confirm our ability to characterize miR expression
      in various tissues (proximal and distal esophagus, stomach and duodenum) obtained from the
      upper gastrointestinal tract in preparation for the study of MiR in patients with Barrett's
      esophagus and other inflammatory conditions of the upper gastrointestinal tract.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of esophageal adenocarcinoma has increased dramatically over the past three
      decades. These adenocarcinomas usually arise from columnar lined epithelium of the esophagus
      known as Barrett's esophagus (BE). There is an established association between
      gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) and the development of BE and esophageal
      adenocarcinoma. In an attempt to diagnose esophageal adenocarcinoma at an earlier and more
      treatable stage, efforts have been directed at identifying patients with BE and enrolling
      them in surveillance protocols. Several authors have challenged this strategy since it has
      not yet been proven to save lives and is very expensive. A major unresolved problem is the
      fact that the clinical factors considered to be somewhat predictive of the presence or
      absence of BE are neither sufficiently sensitive nor specific. In addition, once BE is
      identified, predicting who may or may not progress to cancer is far from perfect. A molecular
      understanding of why certain patients develop BE and why certain of those progress to cancer
      is of obvious importance.

      The molecular pathway from normal esophageal mucosa to Barrett's esophagus and on to
      adenocarcinoma is not well understood. Micro-RNA (miR) RNAs have recently emerged as
      important regulators of carcinogenesis and have not been studied in BE. We seek to confirm
      our ability to characterize miR expression in various tissues (esophagus, stomach and
      duodenum) obtained from the upper gastrointestinal tract in preparation for the study of MiR
      in patients with Barrett's esophagus and other inflammatory conditions of the upper
      gastrointestinal tract.

      This study will involve collection of tissue via endoscopic biopsy in 10 patients with normal
      endoscopic appearance from the esophagus, stomach and duodenum. Ambion miR oligonucleotide
      arrays will be utilized to profile miRs that are specifically expressed in epithelial
      biopsies from the duodenum, stomach, and esophagus. Total RNA will be extracted from
      independent biopsy samples using the mirVana(R) micro RNA isolation kit from Ambion. The
      Ambion Flash PAGE(R) electrophoresis system will be used to resolve mature miRs from the
      larger pre-miR species. Mature miRs will be labeled and hybridized to Ambion mirVana
      miR(R)arrays, which will be scanned to identify miRs that are regulated under these
      circumstances. Signals from the microarrays will be processed using the R functions of
      Bioconductor for normalization and background correction and RMA for summarization.
      Statistical significance will be determined using Insightful S+ functions and assuming a
      least pooled error model. Potential targets will be confirmed by northern blotting. The
      routine histology sample will be reviewed simply to exclude other, unexpected microscopic
      pathology. Benign histologic findings such as minor inflammation, will not exclude the
      patient from inclusion. If there is a wide variation in miR expression, then the histology
      might be needed to help explain such variation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>miR expression between tissue from Barrett's esophagus and that from normal tissues</measure>
    <time_frame>time it takes to have standard of care biopsies taken during one routine Upper Endoscopy</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>expression of miR in Barrett's esophagus patients with cancer in comparison to those who do not progress to cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>time it takes to have standard of care biopsies during one routine Upper Endoscopy</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Barrett's Esophagus</condition>
  <condition>Esophageal Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No treatment</arm_group_label>
    <description>genetic research project; to meet inclusion criteria, participants must have normal upper GI tract upon upper endoscopy, for study biopsies to be taken</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      biopsy tissue from proximal and distal esophagus, stomach and duodenum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study subjects identified from individuals referred for upper endoscopy at Mayo Clinic in
        Jacksonville, Florida
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  willingness to give consent

          -  normal gross appearance of the esophagus, stomach and duodenum

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  contraindication to mucosal biopsy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth R. DeVault,, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 12, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kenneth R. DeVault, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Chair, Department of Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville Florida</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Barrett's esophagus</keyword>
  <keyword>BE</keyword>
  <keyword>esophageal adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Micro-RNA</keyword>
  <keyword>miR expression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Barrett Esophagus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

