<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00903084</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R21MH085598</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21MH085598</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DAHBR 9A-ASPQ</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00903084</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Examining Hair to Determine Tenofovir Exposure</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Pharmacokinetic Study of Varying Dosing Patterns on Tenofovir Concentrations in Hair</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Public Health Foundation Enterprises, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Public Health Foundation Enterprises, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will determine whether a hair test can reveal how much of the anti-HIV medication
      tenofovir a person without HIV has been exposed to.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) is a new strategy for the prevention of HIV infection. It
      involves providing antiretroviral medications—those that treat HIV infections—to people
      before they are exposed to HIV. In clinical trials of PrEP, several of which are currently
      under way, accurate measurements are needed of how much exposure participants have to the
      PrEP medications. Current methods, such as self-reports of medication adherence or pill
      counting, can lead to inaccurate readings of PrEP exposure because participants may forget to
      take pills and individual differences may affect levels of exposure. Measuring PrEP exposure
      levels in hair yields an objective marker of exposure that is not subject to self-report
      errors and that takes into account individual differences. This study will test the use of a
      hair sample for assessing the level of exposure to tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF), an
      antiretroviral medication, in people not infected with HIV.

      Participation in this study will last 9 months. Participants will undergo baseline testing
      and then will be randomly assigned to begin one of three conditions, based on dosing
      schedule: receiving TDF 2, 4, or 7 days per week. All participants will complete each of
      these dosing schedules, but the order in which they are completed will be randomly assigned.
      Each dosing schedule will last 6 weeks, with a break of several weeks between them. During
      each dosing schedule, study staff will confirm that participants are taking each scheduled
      dose by watching them take the pills on weekdays and calling them on weekends. Follow-up
      visits will occur at Days 1, 21, and 42 of each dosing schedule. During the baseline and
      follow-up visits, the following will be completed: an HIV rapid test; counseling about HIV
      prevention; a brief physical exam; a talk with a staff member about health, symptoms, and
      other medications; a blood draw, which will be used for several tests; collection of a urine
      sample and pregnancy test; and optional donation of a sample of pubic hair. On the last day
      of each dosing schedule, a small sample of hair will be cut from each participant's scalp. An
      additional follow-up visit will occur after participants complete 4 weeks of the 7-day dosing
      schedule. This visit will last 24 hours and will involve collection of additional blood
      samples.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tenofovir hair concentration under each dosing condition</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured 6 weeks after starting each dosing condition</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 7 doses per week, then 4 doses per week, then 2 doses per week (each for 6 weeks) of tenofovir, with a break in between dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 7 doses per week, then 2 doses per week, then 4 doses per week (each for 6 weeks) of tenofovir, with a break in between dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 4 doses per week, then 7 doses per week, then 2 doses per week (each for 6 weeks) of tenofovir, with a break in between dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 4 doses per week, then 2 doses per week, then 7 doses per week (each for 6 weeks) of tenofovir, with a break in between dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 2 doses per week, then 7 doses per week, then 4 doses per week (each for 6 weeks) of tenofovir, with a break in between dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 2 doses per week, then 4 doses per week, then 7 doses per week (each for 6 weeks) of tenofovir, with a break in between dosing periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tenofovir Disoproxil Fumarate</intervention_name>
    <description>300-mg tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>6</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Viread</other_name>
    <other_name>Tenofovir</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to speak English

          -  HIV-1 uninfected, based on HIV rapid testing performed during screening and enrollment

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 60 mL/min by the
             Cockcroft-Gault creatinine clearance formula

          -  Serum creatinine less than or equal to the site laboratory upper limit of normal

          -  Urine dipstick with negative or trace result for both glucose and protein

          -  Negative urine beta human chorionic gonadotropin (beta-HCG) test for women

          -  Adequate hepatic function, defined as total bilirubin and hepatic transaminases (ALT
             and AST) less than or equal to twice the upper limit of normal

          -  Adequate hematologic function, defined as an absolute neutrophil count greater than or
             equal to 1,500/mm3, platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm3, and
             hemoglobin greater than or equal to 10 g/dL

          -  Ability to participate in modified directly observed dosing of study drug

          -  Ability to provide a personal cell phone number to be contacted on for unobserved
             modified directly observed therapy (mDOT) visits

          -  Minimum length of 3 cm scalp hair in occipital region

          -  Willing to provide hair and plasma samples as specified by the protocol

          -  Dark hair (brown or black), as assessed by the study clinician

          -  Volunteers born female must agree to consistently use effective contraception from at
             least 21 days prior to enrollment through the last protocol visit for sexual activity
             that could lead to pregnancy and agree not to seek pregnancy through alternative
             methods, such as artificial insemination or in vitro fertilization until after the
             last scheduled protocol visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active and serious medical problems, including heart or lung disease, diabetes
             requiring hypoglycemia medications, previously diagnosed malignancies expected to
             require further treatment, and serious infections

          -  Hepatitis B surface antigen positivity

          -  History of chronic kidney disease

          -  Known osteoporosis, osteomalacia, or osteopenia

          -  History of pathological bone fractures not related to trauma

          -  Receiving ongoing therapy with any of the following: antiretroviral therapy,
             interferon or interleukin therapy, aminoglycoside antibiotics, amphotericin B,
             cidofovir, systemic chemotherapeutic agents, other agents with significant nephrotoxic
             potential, other agents that may inhibit or compete for elimination via active renal
             tubular secretion (e.g., probenecid), or other investigational agents

          -  Evidence of a gastrointestinal malabsorption syndrome or chronic nausea or vomiting
             that may confer an inability to receive an orally administered medication

          -  Use of hair dyes or hair permanent products in the last 3 months (streaking is
             acceptable)

          -  Current participation in any other research study involving drugs, investigational
             agents, or medical devices

          -  Breastfeeding at screening or enrollment, per participant report

          -  Active alcohol or drug use considered sufficient by clinician to hinder compliance
             with study procedures

          -  Elevated risk of HIV infection, as defined in the study protocol

          -  At enrollment, has any social or medical condition that, in the investigator's
             opinion, would preclude provision of informed consent, make participation in the study
             unsafe, complicate interpretation of study outcome data, or otherwise interfere with
             achieving the study objectives
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Albert Liu, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>San Francisco Department of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Francisco Department of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://helpfighthiv.org</url>
    <description>Click here for the San Francisco Department of Public Health HIV Research Section</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gandhi M, Ameli N, Bacchetti P, Gange SJ, Anastos K, Levine A, Hyman CL, Cohen M, Young M, Huang Y, Greenblatt RM; Women's Interagency HIV Study (WIHS). Protease inhibitor levels in hair strongly predict virologic response to treatment. AIDS. 2009 Feb 20;23(4):471-8. doi: 10.1097/QAD.0b013e328325a4a9.</citation>
    <PMID>19165084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang Y, Gandhi M, Greenblatt RM, Gee W, Lin ET, Messenkoff N. Sensitive analysis of anti-HIV drugs, efavirenz, lopinavir and ritonavir, in human hair by liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry. Rapid Commun Mass Spectrom. 2008 Nov;22(21):3401-9. doi: 10.1002/rcm.3750.</citation>
    <PMID>18837069</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gandhi M, Greenblatt RM. Hair it is: the long and short of monitoring antiretroviral treatment. Ann Intern Med. 2002 Oct 15;137(8):696-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12379072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Liu AY, Yang Q, Huang Y, Bacchetti P, Anderson PL, Jin C, Goggin K, Stojanovski K, Grant R, Buchbinder SP, Greenblatt RM, Gandhi M. Strong relationship between oral dose and tenofovir hair levels in a randomized trial: hair as a potential adherence measure for pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP). PLoS One. 2014 Jan 8;9(1):e83736. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0083736. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24421901</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Anderson PL, Glidden DV, Liu A, Buchbinder S, Lama JR, Guanira JV, McMahan V, Bushman LR, Casapía M, Montoya-Herrera O, Veloso VG, Mayer KH, Chariyalertsak S, Schechter M, Bekker LG, Kallás EG, Grant RM; iPrEx Study Team. Emtricitabine-tenofovir concentrations and pre-exposure prophylaxis efficacy in men who have sex with men. Sci Transl Med. 2012 Sep 12;4(151):151ra125.</citation>
    <PMID>22972843</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 13, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 15, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 6, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Public Health Foundation Enterprises, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Albert Liu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, HIV Prevention Intervention Studies SFDPH/Bridge HIV</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics in Hair</keyword>
  <keyword>Tenofovir</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Concentrations</keyword>
  <keyword>Hair</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tenofovir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

