<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00908791</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D0906</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00908791</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Proof of Principle Trial to Determine if Nutritional Supplement Conjugated Linoleic Acid (CLA) Can Modulate the Lipogenic Pathway in Breast Cancer Tissue</brief_title>
  <official_title>An in Vivo Proof of Principle Trial to Determine Whether the Nutritional Supplement Conjugated Linoleic Acid (CLA, Clarinol™) Can Modulate the Lipogenic Pathway in Breast Cancer Tissue</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Conjugated Linoleic Acid (CLA) is obtained in the human diet by consumption of foods
      containing ruminant fat. Milk and dairy products have shown the highest amounts of CLA.
      Clarinol (CLA), is considered a natural supplement and is not regulated by the Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA). CLA is known to inhibit proliferation of human breast cancer cells and
      tumors in rodent breast cancer models and reduced Spot 14 (THRSP, S14) and Fatty Acid
      Synthase (FASN) gene expression in breast cancer cells and tht the two major CLA isomers used
      in nutritional supplements (C9, t11 and t10, c12) were equipotent in reducing breast cancer
      cell growth. This study looks at the hypothesis that S14 expression is decreased by CLA and
      will characterize the major pharmacodynamic (PD) effects of CLA in newly diagnosed Breast
      cancer patients on Tumor tissue lipogenic pathway. FASN, S14 and Lipoprotein Lipase (LPL),
      Ki67 and apoptotic index expression will be assessed by quantitative immunohistochemistry
      (IHC) in initial breast cancer biopsies and compared to that in resected breast tumor tissue
      after the study subject has been taking CLA for ten to twenty-eight days. Tissue from
      adjacent breast adipocytes will also be analyzed to determine whether adipose tissue effects
      can serve as a surrogate marker for those in tumor tissue. A sample of the original biopsy
      will be compared to the tumor resection sample to determine the levels of CLA in the breast
      cancer cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether CLA consumption suppresses expression of markers of lipogenesis (Spot 14, FASN, LPL, Ki67 and apoptotic index ) in breast cancer tissue in vivo.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether CLA consumption suppresses expression of lipogenesis markers in adipose tissue.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure the baseline and steady state blood/plasma CLA concentrations in breast cancer patients taking CLA, and explore their relationship to the expression of lipogenesis markers in breast tumor tissue and adipocytes.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conjugated Linoleic Acid (CLA)</intervention_name>
    <description>Conjugated linoleic acid (CLA, Clarinol™) oral soft gel capsules will be administered in an open-labeled, manner to all subjects enrolled in the study. Subjects will be treated with 7.5 grams of oral CLA daily, taken in divided dose, twice daily between 8 am and 12 noon and between 8 pm and 12 midnight. CLA will be taken for a minimum of ten days prior to surgical resection of their breast malignancy. In the event that the subject's surgical resection date is delayed, subjects may take CLA for up to 28 days. The last dose of CLA prior to the surgical resection will be taken at 12 midnight or as close as possible to that time and the patient will record the time of the last dosing.</description>
    <other_name>Clarinol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All study patients must have histologically confirmed invasive adenocarcinoma of the
             breast. Their breast cancer must be resectable clinical stage I or II breast cancer as
             defined by the current AJCC TNM Staging System (Greene FL, Page DL, Fleming ID, et
             al.: editors. AJCC cancer staging manual, 6th edition. New York: Springer; 2002).

          -  All patients must be able to and give informed consent indicating they are aware of
             the investigational nature of this treatment, prior to entry into the study.

          -  All subjects must be Age &gt;18 years.

          -  All subject must have adequate hepatic and renal function documented prior to study
             entry to include: hepatic transaminases (AST or ALT) ≤ 1.5 times the upper limits of
             normal, total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times the upper limits of normal, serum creatinine ≤ 1.5
             times the upper limit of normal or eCRCl ≥ 60 mL/min.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Patients who have received prior or be receiving radiation therapy for their breast
             cancer will be excluded.

          -  Patients who have received prior chemotherapy or receiving chemotherapy or hormonal
             therapy for their breast cancer will not be included.

          -  Women must be surgically sterilized or post-menopausal or women of childbearing
             potential must be using an adequate method of contraception. Women of childbearing
             potential must be using at least one of the following: oral, implanted, injectable
             contraceptive hormones, or mechanical products such as an intrauterine device or
             barrier methods (diaphragm, condoms, spermicides) to prevent pregnancy or practicing
             abstinence or have a partner that is sterile (e.g., vasectomy). Women of childbearing
             potential must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test within 72 hours prior to
             start of study therapy. Women who are pregnant or breast-feeding and women of
             childbearing potential not using an adequate method of birth control will be excluded.

          -  Patients with gastrointestinal abnormalities including: inability to take oral
             medication, requirement for intravenous alimentation, or prior surgical procedures
             affecting nutrient /drug absorption will be excluded.

          -  A serious uncontrolled medical disorder or active infection which would impair their
             ability to receive study treatment will be excluded. Significant cardiac disease,
             including uncontrolled high blood pressure, unstable angina, and congestive heart
             failure, myocardial infarction within the previous 3 months or serious cardiac
             arrhythmias will be excluded. Dementia or significantly altered mental status that
             would prohibit the understanding or rendering of informed consent and compliance with
             the requirements of this protocol will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margit M McGowan, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Norris Cotton Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dartmouth Hitchcock Medical Center, Norris Cotton Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cancer.dartmouth.edu/</url>
    <description>Norris Cotton Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 26, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 11, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Conjugated Linoleic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Proof of Principle</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipogenic Pathway</keyword>
  <keyword>Clarinol</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 14, 2014</submitted>
    <returned>August 6, 2014</returned>
    <submitted>April 10, 2015</submitted>
    <returned>April 28, 2015</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

