<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00908414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR016195</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PEPI-TIDP23-C104</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00908414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PEPI-TiDP23-C104 is a First in Human Study With a Single Dose Escalation Part and a Multiple Dosing Part for Compounds TMC589337 and TMC589354.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I, Double-blind, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Trial in Healthy Volunteers to Examine Safety, Tolerability, Plasma Pharmacokinetics of TMC589337&amp;TMC589354 After Increasing Single Oral Doses &amp; in an Open-label Part After Different Repeated Doses in Combination With Single Oral Dose of TMC310911</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals, Ireland</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals, Ireland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine the safety, tolerability, and plasma
      pharmacokinetics (i.e., the levels of TMC589337 and TMC589354 circulating in your blood over
      time) of increasing single oral doses of TMC589337 and TMC589354 and of multiple increasing
      oral doses followed by a single dose of TMC310911 to assess the potential boosting effect on
      the latter compound. In this study 3 investigational new drugs are involved. These new
      investigational drugs called TMC589337 and TMC589354 (from the PEPI family) and TMC310911 are
      in process of development for the treatment of Human Immunodeficiency Virus-Type 1 (HIV-1).
      TMC589337 and TMC589354 are novel molecules with no antiviral activity to be used to enhance
      the pharmacokinetics profile of a drug. TMC310911 is a novel and potent compound and belongs
      to a medication class called protease inhibitors (PI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a First-in-Human Phase I, double-blind (neither physician or patient knows the name
      of the assigned study drug), randomized (study medication assigned by chance),
      placebo-controlled (a group of study participants who receive an inactive substance in place
      of a medication) trial to examine the safety, tolerability, and plasma pharmacokinetics (pk)
      after increasing single oral doses of TMC589337 and TMC589354, and in an open-label (both the
      physician and study participant know the name of the assigned study drug) part after
      different repeated oral doses in combination with a single oral dose of TMC310911 to assess
      the potential pharmacokinetic enhancement on the latter compound. TMC589337 and TMC589354 are
      molecules to be used to enhance the pharmacokinetics profile of a drug, e.g., a Human
      Immunodeficiency Virus-Type 1 (HIV-1) protease inhibitors (PI). TMC310911 is an
      investigational PI, currently studied in healthy volunteers. The trial consists of 2 parts: a
      single dose escalation part (double-blind, placebo-controlled) and a multiple dosing part
      (open label) for both PEPI-compounds: TMC589337 and TMC589354. The single dose escalation
      part of the trial will include 2 panels of 8 healthy adult volunteers each (Panel 1 and 2).
      Each panel will have 4 oral escalating single dose sessions of either TMC589337 (Panel 1) or
      TMC589354 (Panel 2). Healthy volunteers will receive doses of 40 mg (Session Ia), 100 mg
      (Session IIa), 200 mg (Session IIIa) and 400 mg (Session IVa) of TMC589337 or placebo. Panel
      2 will receive doses of 40 mg (Session Ib), 100 mg (Session IIb), 200 mg (Session IIIb) and
      400 mg (Session IVb) of TMC589354 or placebo. Both panels can run in parallel. In each
      session, 6 healthy volunteers will receive active treatment and 2 healthy volunteers will
      receive placebo with standard meals. Doses of 40 mg, 100 mg, 200 mg and 400 mg of TMC589337
      or TMC589354 or placebo will be administered as a single oral administration. The treatment
      schedule will be made in such a way that for both panels over 4 sessions each healthy
      volunteer will receive active treatment 3 times and placebo once. A washout period (a period
      where no treatment will be taken in view of having all the medication eliminated from the
      body before starting a new treatment) of at least 10 days will be respected between
      consecutive TMC589337, TMC589354 or placebo dosing within each panel. Each single dosing
      session will have a staggered approach meaning that first 4 healthy volunteers will be dosed
      and 48 hours later the next 4 healthy volunteers will be dosed. Multiple dosing will be
      started when the 200 mg sessions of TMC589337 and/or TMC589354 are found to be generally safe
      and well tolerated as decided by the Investigator and the Sponsor and approved as such by the
      local ethics committee. Multiple dosing of TMC589337 and/or TMC589354 will not be started if
      the plasma pk profile is not supportive to evaluate repeated dosing. The multiple dose part
      of the trial is open-label and will include 5 panels of 6 healthy adult volunteers each
      (Panels 3, 4, 5, 6 and 7). Each panel will have 1 session in which TMC589337 or TMC589354
      will be administered. Treatment is anticipated to be a twice daily regimen, and different
      dose regimens will be tested. Final doses will be determined according to the results
      obtained from the single dose sessions but will not be higher than a total daily dose of 400
      mg. If multiple dosing is found to be generally safe and well tolerated in Panel 3 and 4,
      doses for Panels 5-7 can be determined. Both Panels 3 and 4, and Panels 5 and 6 can run in
      parallel. In Panel 7, 1 compound, either TMC589337 or TMC589354, will be selected for a twice
      daily or once daily regimen for 7 days. In addition, the healthy volunteers of Panels 3, 4, 5
      and 6 will receive a single oral dose of 300 mg of TMC310911 on Day 7 of these sessions to
      assess the enhancing effect of repeated administration of TMC589337 and TMC589354 on the pk
      profile of a single dose of TMC310911. Healthy volunteers of Panel 7 will receive either a
      300 mg dose of TMC310911 or a dose of 600 mg TMC310911 at the same conditions. Study
      medication will be given under fed conditions in Panels 3-6, and under fed or fasted
      conditions (depending on the findings of previous sessions) in Panel 7. After a washout
      period of at least 14 days healthy volunteers of Panels 3 to 7 will have an additional
      session in which a single oral dose of 300 mg (or 600 mg for Panel 7 only) of TMC310911 alone
      will be administered (Sessions VIIIa, VIIIb, IXa, IXb and X). Full pk profiles of TMC589337
      and TMC589354 will be determined up to 72 hours after single dosing and after the morning
      dosing of Day 7 (multiple dosing), and over 12 hours (or over 24 hours for Panel 7 when given
      once daily.) after the morning dose on Days 1 and 6 of the multiple dosing sessions. Full pk
      profiles of TMC310911 will be determined over 24 hours when given alone and on Day 7 of the
      TMC589337 and TMC589354 multiple dosing sessions. Safety and tolerability will be evaluated
      continuously and documented (safety report) before stepping up to the next dose. Dose
      escalation in the single and multiple ascending dose regimens will continue only if the
      previous dose was found safe and generally well tolerated by the Investigator and the Sponsor
      and approved as such by the ethics committee. Actual doses may be adapted pending on the
      outcome of the previous sessions. The expected duration of the study (excluding screening) is
      at least 8 weeks. Safety and tolerability evaluations will be recorded at regular intervals
      throughout the trial period. Illnesses and side effects will be monitored continuously. Blood
      and urine samples will be taken at screening, in Panel 1 and 2 on Day 1, 2 and 4 of sessions
      I to IV, in Panel 3 to 7 on Day 1, 3, 6, 7, 8 and 10 of session V, VI and VII, on Day 1 and 2
      of session VIII, IX and X and at the 2 follow-up visits 10 to 14 days and 30 to 32 days after
      last drug intake. Electrocardiogram (ECG) will be taken and vital signs (blood pressure and
      heart rate) will be measured at screening, in Panel 1 and 2 at each session day ( on Day -1
      only ECGs), in Panel 3 to 7 at Day -1 (only ECG), Day 1, 3, 6, 7, 8 and 10 in session V, VI
      and VII and on Day 1 and 2 of session VIII, IX and X and at the 2 follow-up visits. Physical
      examination will be done at screening, on Day 4 of each session in Panel 1 and 2, on Day 6
      and 10 of session V, VI and VII, on Day -1 and 2 of session VIII, IX and X and at the 2
      follow-up visits. Continuous ECG data will be obtained during the first 8 hours after intake
      of study medication in the single dose escalation part of the study.
      TMC589337,TMC589354,TMC310911 and placebo are formulated as oral drinkable solutions. Panel
      1-2 consist of single dose of TMC589337 or TMC589354 and placebo from 40-400mg (2ml to 5ml)
      on Day 1 of each session. Panel 3-7 consist of TMC589337,TMC589354 or placebo twice daily (or
      once daily in Panel 7), from Day 1 to Day 7 with maximum daily dose of 400mg (5ml) plus a
      single morning intake of 300mg (12ml) (or 600mg for Panel 7 only) TMC310911 on Day 7 and on
      Day 1 in 2nd session.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    strategic decision
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The trial objectives are to determine the safety, tolerability and plasma pk of TMC589337/TMC589354 after increasing single oral doses from 40 mg up to 400 mg and after increasing multiple oral doses.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks. This includes a treatment, washout and follow up period and is excluding screening period of maximum 21 days before first medication intake)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The trial objectives are to determine the safety, tolerability and plasma pk interaction between TMC310911 and TMC589337 or TMC589354.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks. This includes a treatment, washout and follow up period and is excluding screening period of maximum 21 days before first medication intake)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>7</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 1: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Panel 1 will receive doses of 40 milligram (mg) (Session Ia), 100 mg (Session IIa), 200 mg (Session IIIa) and 400 mg (Session IVa) of TMC589337 or placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 2: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Panel 2 will receive doses of 40 mg (Session Ib), 100 mg (Session IIb), 200 mg (Session IIIb) and 400 mg (Session IVb) of TMC589354 or placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 3: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>AA mg (Final doses will be selected based upon data obtained in the single dose sessions (i.e., Sessions I, II, and III) TMC589337 (n=6) b.i.d. (twice daily) during 7 days (Session Va) plus a single oral dose of 300 mg of TMC310911 on Day 7. After at least 14 days following Day 7 of multiple dosing, participants will receive 300 mg TMC310911, single dose (Session VIIIa).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 4: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BB mg (final doses will be selected based upon data obtained in the single dose sessions (i.e., Sessions I, II, and III) TMC589354 (n=6) b.i.d. during 7 days (Session Vb) ) plus a single oral dose of 300 mg of TMC310911 on Day 7. After at least 14 days following Day 7 of multiple dosing, participants will receive 300 mg TMC310911, single dose (Session VIIIb).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 5: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CC mg (final doses will be selected based upon data obtained in the single dose sessions (i.e., Sessions I, II, and III) TMC589337 (n=6) b.i.d. during 7 days (Session VIa) plus a single oral dose of 300 mg of TMC310911 on Day 7. After at least 14 days following Day 7 of multiple dosing, participants will receive 300 mg TMC310911, single dose (Session IXa).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 6: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>DD mg (final doses will be selected based upon data obtained in the single dose sessions (i.e., Sessions I, II, and III) TMC589354 (n=6) b.i.d. during 7 days (Session VIb) ) plus a single oral dose of 300 mg of TMC310911 on Day 7. After at least 14 days following Day 7 of multiple dosing, participants will receive 300 mg TMC310911, single dose (Session IXb).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 7: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>EE mg (final doses will be selected based upon data obtained in the single dose sessions (i.e., Sessions I, II, and III) TMC589337 (n=6) or YY mg TMC589354 (n=6) b.i.d. or q.d. during 7 days (Session VII) ) plus a single oral dose of 300 mg or 600mg of TMC310911 on Day 7. After at least 14 days following Day 7 of multiple dosing, participants will receive 300 mg or 600 mg TMC310911, single dose (Session X).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589337 40 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589337 40 mg in Session Ia of Panel 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 1: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589337 100 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589337 100 mg in Session IIa of Panel 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 1: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589337 200 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589337 200 mg in Session IIIa of Panel 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 1: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589337 400 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589337 400 mg in Session IVa of Panel 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 1: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589354 40 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589354 40 mg in Session Ib of Panel 2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 2: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589354 100 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589354 100 mg in Session IIb of Panel 2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 2: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589354 200 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589354 200 mg in Session IIIb of Panel 2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 2: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589354 400 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589354 400 mg in Session IVb of Panel 2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 2: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589337 AA mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589337 AA mg on Days 1 to 7 in Session Va of Panel 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 3: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589354 BB mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589354 BB mg on Days 1 to 7 in Session Vb of Panel 4.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 4: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589337 CC mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589337 CC mg on Days 1 to 7 in Session VIa of Panel 5.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 5: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589354 DD mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589354 DD mg on Days 1 to 7 in Session VIb of Panel 6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 6: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589337 EE mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589337 EE mg on Days 1 to 7 in Session VII of Panel 7.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 7: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC589354 YY mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC589354 YY mg on Days 1 to 7 in Session VII of Panel 7.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 7: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC310911 300 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC310911 300 mg in Panel 3, 4, 5, 6 and 7.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 3: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 4: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 5: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 6: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 7: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC310911 600 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive TMC310911 600 mg in Panel 7.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 7: Multiple dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive matching placebo to TMC589337 or TMC589354 in Panel 1 and 2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 1: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Panel 2: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Nonsmokers for at least 3 months prior to selection

          -  Weight as defined by a Body Mass Index (BMI, weight in kg divided by the square of
             height in meters) of 18.0 to 30.0 kg/m2, extremes included

          -  Informed Consent Form (ICF) signed voluntarily

          -  Able to comply with protocol requirements

          -  Healthy on the basis of a pretrial physical examination, medical history, the results
             of blood biochemistry and hematology tests, a urinalysis, vital signs, and a 12-lead
             electrocardiogram (ECG).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Past history of clinically significant heart arrhythmias (extrasystolic, tachycardia
             at rest)

          -  having baseline prolongation of QTc interval &gt; 450 ms, history of risk factors for
             Torsade de Pointes syndrome (hypokalemia, family history of long QT Syndrome)

          -  Female, except if postmenopausal for more than 2 years, or posthysterectomy or
             postsurgical sterilization (without reversal operation)

          -  Currently active clinically relevant or significant underlying gastrointestinal,
             cardiovascular, nervous system, psychiatric, metabolic, renal, hepatic, respiratory,
             inflammatory, or infectious disease

          -  History of clinically relevant skin disease or allergy including drug allergy as well.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals Limited Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Tibotec Pharmaceutical Limited</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 25, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 27, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 27, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PEPI-TiDP23-C104</keyword>
  <keyword>PEPI-C104</keyword>
  <keyword>PEPI</keyword>
  <keyword>TMC589337</keyword>
  <keyword>TMC589354</keyword>
  <keyword>TMC310911</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

