<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00907218</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009-P-000444</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00907218</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chantix in Adult Smokers With Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Pilot Study of Varenicline (Chantix) in Adult Smokers With Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD): Effects on ADHD and Cigarette Smoking</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to learn about the efficacy of a medication called
      varenicline (Chantix) in treating ADHD in adults and in reducing cigarette smoking in adults
      with ADHD. The investigators hypothesize that ADHD symptomatology in adults with ADHD will be
      improved with varenicline treatment. The investigators also hypothesize that varenicline
      treatment will result in significant reductions in cigarette smoking. Another objective of
      this study is to more fully evaluate the response and tolerability to varenicline in this
      group of cigarette smoking adults with ADHD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    extremely slow enrollment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The DSM-IV Based Adult ADHD Investigator Symptom Rating Scale (AISRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The AISRS is an 18-item questionnaire administered by the clinician assessing each of the individual DSM-IV symptoms of ADHD. Each symptom is rated on a scale of severity from 0 (none) to 3 (severe), and the 18 symptom questions are summed to calculate a total score. The minimum total score is a 0, while the maximum total score is a 54.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time Line Follow Back of Cigarette Smoking</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The reduction in cigarette smoking, defined as the change from baseline on the amount of cigarettes per day smoked (cpd), using the time-line follow back method. This method involves asking subjects to retrospectively estimate their cigarette use 7 days to 2 years prior to the interview date.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exhaled CO Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly over 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>At baseline and all weekly study visits,exhaled carbon monoxide (CO) levels were read.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of Smoking Cessation</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Varenicline has efficacy in smoking sensation; therefore smoking cessation was measured at baseline and at all study visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ADHD Clinical Global Impressions Scale Improvement (CGI-I) and Severity (CGI-S)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Clinical Global Impression Scale of ADHD for Improvement and Severity assess overall severity and change in severity of ADHD. The CGI-I scale is rated from 1 to 7 (1=very much improved; 7=very much worse). The CGI-S is rated from 1 to 7 as well (1=not ill; 7=extremely ill).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs were collected at each study visit, including height, weight, blood pressure, and heart rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spontaneous Reports of Adverse Effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reports of adverse events were completed at baseline and weekly visits throughout the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adults who meet DSM-IV-TR criteria for ADHD and smoke cigarettes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Varenicline (Chantix)</intervention_name>
    <description>Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if tolerated. Maximum dose will be 2 mg daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chantix(varenicline) is a smoking cessation medicine.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female outpatients from 18-60 years of age;

          -  A cigarette smoking history of at least 3 months, and currently smoking;

          -  An interest in quitting smoking and a willingness to comply with all study procedures
             and medication instructions;

          -  A current DSM-IV-TR diagnosis of ADHD confirmed by clinical psychiatric evaluation
             and/or ADHD module of structured diagnostic interview, completed by study clinician.

          -  For females of child-bearing potential: pregnancy test at screening visit is negative
             and the subject does not plan to become pregnant during the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding;

          -  Clinically significant and/or unstable medical condition including renal, hepatic, or
             neurological, based upon a medical history and vital signs;

          -  Ongoing treatment with medications which may be affected (altered blood levels) if
             subjects stop smoking in the study, including insulin, theophylline, and blood
             thinners, as determined by clinician;

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular history, including myocardial infarction,
             untreated hypertension, atrial fibrillation, or arrhythmia;

          -  Current untreated psychiatric comorbidity which the investigator judges to be of
             greater than mild severity, including Major Depressive Disorder;

          -  Current psychiatric comorbidity, including suicidality, homicidality, psychosis,
             determined by the clinician to be clinically significant and/or unstable

          -  Lifetime history of DSM-IV Bipolar I disorder, Schizophrenia, or suicide attempt as
             determined through clinical evaluation or diagnostic interview;

          -  Currently (within 3 months) meets DSM-IV criteria for abuse or dependence for any
             psychoactive substance other than nicotine;

          -  Current treatment with mood stabilizers, anti-psychotics, nicotine replacement
             therapies, or varenicline;

          -  Mental retardation (IQ &lt; 75);

          -  History of intolerance or allergy to varenicline.

          -  Clinically significant abnormal screening values including:

               -  Consistent readings of hypertension (&gt;140/90) during screening period (including
                  screening and baseline visits), defined as two or more readings (each being the
                  average of three measurements) at a single visit with systolic blood pressure,
                  SBP &gt; 140 and/or diastolic blood pressure, DBP, &gt; 90, and confirmed by manual
                  reading.

        Subjects with isolated incidences (of triplicate average BP) of SBP &gt; 140 and/or DBP &gt; 90
        at baseline/week 0 visit, confirmed by manual reading, which are determined to be
        clinically significant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy Wilens, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>May 9, 2013</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>July 31, 2013</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">September 23, 2013</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Timothy Wilens, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ADHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>ADHD medication</keyword>
  <keyword>Chantix</keyword>
  <keyword>varenicline</keyword>
  <keyword>smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>smoking cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>quit smoking</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varenicline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>2 studies were recruited. They participated in a previous study in our department and signed consent for the data to be used for this study.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Recruitment was extremely slow and therefore the study was terminated early</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for Attention Deficit Hyper</title>
          <description>Varenicline (Chantix) : Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>No Data Was Analyzed</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="2"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="37.5" spread="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>The DSM-IV Based Adult ADHD Investigator Symptom Rating Scale (AISRS)</title>
        <description>The AISRS is an 18-item questionnaire administered by the clinician assessing each of the individual DSM-IV symptoms of ADHD. Each symptom is rated on a scale of severity from 0 (none) to 3 (severe), and the 18 symptom questions are summed to calculate a total score. The minimum total score is a 0, while the maximum total score is a 54.</description>
        <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for ADHD and Smoke Cigarett</title>
            <description>Varenicline (Chantix): Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if tolerated. Maximum dose will be 2 mg daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>The DSM-IV Based Adult ADHD Investigator Symptom Rating Scale (AISRS)</title>
          <description>The AISRS is an 18-item questionnaire administered by the clinician assessing each of the individual DSM-IV symptoms of ADHD. Each symptom is rated on a scale of severity from 0 (none) to 3 (severe), and the 18 symptom questions are summed to calculate a total score. The minimum total score is a 0, while the maximum total score is a 54.</description>
          <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Time Line Follow Back of Cigarette Smoking</title>
        <description>The reduction in cigarette smoking, defined as the change from baseline on the amount of cigarettes per day smoked (cpd), using the time-line follow back method. This method involves asking subjects to retrospectively estimate their cigarette use 7 days to 2 years prior to the interview date.</description>
        <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for ADHD and Smoke Cigarett</title>
            <description>Varenicline (Chantix): Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if tolerated. Maximum dose will be 2 mg daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time Line Follow Back of Cigarette Smoking</title>
          <description>The reduction in cigarette smoking, defined as the change from baseline on the amount of cigarettes per day smoked (cpd), using the time-line follow back method. This method involves asking subjects to retrospectively estimate their cigarette use 7 days to 2 years prior to the interview date.</description>
          <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Exhaled CO Levels</title>
        <description>At baseline and all weekly study visits,exhaled carbon monoxide (CO) levels were read.</description>
        <time_frame>Weekly over 7 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for ADHD and Smoke Cigarett</title>
            <description>Varenicline (Chantix): Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if tolerated. Maximum dose will be 2 mg daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Exhaled CO Levels</title>
          <description>At baseline and all weekly study visits,exhaled carbon monoxide (CO) levels were read.</description>
          <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Rates of Smoking Cessation</title>
        <description>Varenicline has efficacy in smoking sensation; therefore smoking cessation was measured at baseline and at all study visits.</description>
        <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for ADHD and Smoke Cigarett</title>
            <description>Varenicline (Chantix): Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if tolerated. Maximum dose will be 2 mg daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Rates of Smoking Cessation</title>
          <description>Varenicline has efficacy in smoking sensation; therefore smoking cessation was measured at baseline and at all study visits.</description>
          <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>ADHD Clinical Global Impressions Scale Improvement (CGI-I) and Severity (CGI-S)</title>
        <description>The Clinical Global Impression Scale of ADHD for Improvement and Severity assess overall severity and change in severity of ADHD. The CGI-I scale is rated from 1 to 7 (1=very much improved; 7=very much worse). The CGI-S is rated from 1 to 7 as well (1=not ill; 7=extremely ill).</description>
        <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for ADHD and Smoke Cigarett</title>
            <description>Varenicline (Chantix): Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if tolerated. Maximum dose will be 2 mg daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>ADHD Clinical Global Impressions Scale Improvement (CGI-I) and Severity (CGI-S)</title>
          <description>The Clinical Global Impression Scale of ADHD for Improvement and Severity assess overall severity and change in severity of ADHD. The CGI-I scale is rated from 1 to 7 (1=very much improved; 7=very much worse). The CGI-S is rated from 1 to 7 as well (1=not ill; 7=extremely ill).</description>
          <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Vital Signs</title>
        <description>Vital signs were collected at each study visit, including height, weight, blood pressure, and heart rate.</description>
        <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for ADHD and Smoke Cigarett</title>
            <description>Varenicline (Chantix): Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if tolerated. Maximum dose will be 2 mg daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Vital Signs</title>
          <description>Vital signs were collected at each study visit, including height, weight, blood pressure, and heart rate.</description>
          <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Spontaneous Reports of Adverse Effects</title>
        <description>Reports of adverse events were completed at baseline and weekly visits throughout the trial.</description>
        <time_frame>Weekly for 7 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for ADHD and Smoke Cigarett</title>
            <description>Varenicline (Chantix): Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if tolerated. Maximum dose will be 2 mg daily.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Spontaneous Reports of Adverse Effects</title>
          <description>Reports of adverse events were completed at baseline and weekly visits throughout the trial.</description>
          <population>Data was not collected due to study termination, 2 subjects were recruited however their data was not analyzed</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>adverse event data was not collected</time_frame>
      <desc>only 2 subjects were recruited and they had previously participated in a study and we used the data for that study. Therefore there was no adverse events</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Adults Who Meet DSM-IV-TR Criteria for Attention Deficit Hyper</title>
          <description>Varenicline (Chantix) : Upon completion of screening procedures and meeting eligibility criteria, subjects will begin taking varenicline daily until Week 6 of the study. At Week 6 they will discontinue varenicline and return one week later for their final study visit to assess return of ADHD symptomatology. Subjects will start on 0.5 mg of varenicline per day for the first week of treatment. The dose will be increased to 0.5 mg twice a day at the end of week 1 visit, and then increased to 1 mg twice a day at the end of week 2 visit, to remain at this dose until the week 6 visit. At week 6, all subjects will be openly discontinued from varenicline, to return to the office the following week for re-assessment one week off the medication. If significant adverse effects (AE) occur, the daily dose may be reduced by 0.5 to 1 mg. At subsequent visits, a higher dose may be resumed if</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Extremely slow enrollment so the study was terminated early.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Timothy Wilens</name_or_title>
      <organization>MassGH</organization>
      <phone>617-724-5226</phone>
      <email>twilens@partners.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

