<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01506076</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>07446/07-08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01506076</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bioequivalence Study of Levocetirizine DiHCl Tablets 5mg of Dr. Reddy's Under Fasting Conditions</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Balanced, Randomized, Two-treatment, Two-period, Two-sequence, Single Oral Dose, Crossover, Bioequivalence Study of Levocetirizine DiHCl Tablets 5mg With XYZAL® Tablets 5 mg in Healthy Subjects Under Fasting Conditions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the Bioequivalence of Levocetirizine DiHCl Tablets 5mg
      with XYZAL tablets 5 mg and to monitor clinical status, adverse events and laboratory
      investigations and assess relative safety and tolerance, under fasting conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A pivotal study to compare the Bioequivalence of Levocetirizine DiHCl Tablets 5 mg of
      Dr.Reddy's Laboratories Limited with XYZAL® Tablets 5 mg of UCB Farchim S.A. in healthy,
      human subjects under fasting conditions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bioequivalence is based on Cmax and AUC parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>2 month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Fasting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Levocetirizine DiHCl Tablets, 5 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Levocetirizine DiHCl Tablets, 5 mg of Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Ltd.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>XYZAL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>XYZAL Tablets 5 mg of UCB Farchim S.A.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levocetirizine DiHCl</intervention_name>
    <description>Levocetirizine DiHCl Tablets 5 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Levocetirizine DiHCl Tablets, 5 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>XYZAL</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>XYZAL</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will provide written informed consent.

          -  Subjects must be healthy adults within 18-45 years of age (inclusive).

          -  Body mass index of ≥18.5 kg/m2 and ≤25 kg/m2, with body weight not less than 50 kg.

          -  Subjects must be of normal health as determined by medical history and physical
             examination performed within 15 days prior to the commencement of the dosing in
             Period-I.

          -  Have normal ECG, chest X-Ray and vital signs and clinically non significant changes in
             ECG &amp; chest X-Ray.

          -  Availability of subject for the entire study period and willingness to adhere to
             protocol requirements as evidenced by written informed consent.

          -  Subjects will be Non smokers or moderate smokers (less than 10 cigarettes a day) for
             at least 6 months.

          -  If subject is a female volunteer and is of child bearing potential practicing an
             acceptable method of birth control for the duration of the study as judged by the
             investigator(s), such as condoms, foams, jellies, diaphragm, intrauterine device(IUD),
             or abstinence.

        or is postmenopausal for at least 1 year. is surgically sterile (bilateral tubal ligation,
        bilateral oophorectomy, or hysterectomy has been performed on the subject)

        •Each female subject will be given a urine pregnancy test at screening, check-in for
        period-1, period-2 and post study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects incapable of understanding the informed consent.

          -  Subjects with BP lesser than 90/60 mm of Hg or BP greater than or equal to 140/90 mm
             of Hg.

          -  History of hypersensitivity or idiosyncratic reaction to Levocetirizine or other
             related drugs.

          -  Any evidence of impairment of renal, hepatic, gastro intestinal, lung and cardiac
             function.

          -  Subjects with a history of tuberculosis, epilepsy, asthma (during past 5 years),
             diabetes, psychosis or glaucoma will not be eligible for the study.

          -  Regular smoker who smokes more than ten cigarettes daily or has difficulty in
             abstaining from smoking for the duration of each study period.

          -  Subjects who have taken over the counter or prescribed medications, including any
             enzyme modifying drugs or any systemic medication within the past two weeks prior to
             prior to dosing in Period-1.

          -  History of any psychiatric illness, which may impair the ability to provide written,
             informed consent.

          -  Subject is mentally or legally incapacitated, or has a history of significant
             psychiatric disorder.

          -  Subjects who have a history of alcohol or substance/ drug of abuse within the last 5
             years.

          -  Subjects with clinically significant abnormal values of laboratory parameters,
             including positive results of HIV, HBV, HCV, RPR tests.

          -  Subjects who participated in any other clinical investigation using experimental drug
             or had bled more than 350 mL in the past 3 months.

          -  Subjects who are unable to or likely to be non-compliant with protocol requirements or
             restrictions.

          -  Subjects who are intolerant to venipuncture.

          -  Any subject in whom Levocetirizine Dihydrochloride is contraindicated for medical
             reasons.

          -  Female volunteers who has used implanted or injected hormonal contraceptives anytime
             during the 6 months prior to study or used hormonal contraceptives within 14 days
             before dosing.

          -  Female volunteers demonstrating a positive pregnancy screen.

          -  All female subjects will be screened for pregnancy at screening, check-in each study
             period. Subjects with positive or inconclusive results will be withdrawn from the
             study.

          -  Female volunteers who are currently breast feeding. Female subjects who are pregnant,
             breast-feeding or who are likely to become pregnant during the study will not be
             allowed to participate. Female subjects of child bearing potential must either abstain
             from sexual intercourse or use a reliable barrier method (e.g. condom, IUD) of
             contraception during the course of the study (first dosing until last blood
             collection) or they will not be allowed to participate.

          -  Subjects with positive urine screen for drugs of abuse at the time of admission
             check-in for each period will be excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sudershan Vishwanath, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vimta Labs Ltd.,</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vimta Labs Ltd.,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyderabad</city>
        <state>A.P</state>
        <zip>500 051</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 6, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 6, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Levocetirizine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cetirizine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

