<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01507649</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09101031</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01507649</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of a Telephone-based Intervention on Postnatal Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of a Telephone-based Cognitive-behavioral Intervention on Postnatal Depression: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: To evaluate the effectiveness of a telephone-based intervention using
      cognitive-behavioral approach in preventing postnatal depression and improving quality of
      life in first-time Chinese mothers.

      Hypothesis: Women who receive the telephone-based cognitive-behavioral intervention will have
      a lower level of depressive symptoms (primary outcome) and a higher level of quality of life
      at 6 weeks and 6 months postpartum than those who receive the usual postpartum care.

      Design and subjects: Randomized controlled trial is used. A sample of postpartum women with
      high risk of postnatal depression (EPDS &gt; 9, n = 498) will be randomly assigned to either the
      experimental (n = 249) or the control groups (n = 249). The experimental group receives the
      intervention and the control group receives usual postpartum care.

      Study instruments: EPDS and Medical Outcomes Study Short Form Health Survey (SF-12).

      Interventions: The intervention is based on the cognitive-behavioral approach. It consists of
      five, 30-minutes sessions delivered weekly from postpartum week one to week five via
      telephone.

      Main outcome measures and analysis: Outcomes on postnatal depression and quality of life will
      be measured by EPDS and SF-12, respectively, at 6 weeks and 6 months postpartum. A
      repeated-measures multivariate analysis of variance will be used to compare differences
      between two groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to design, implement and evaluate a telephone-based intervention
      using cognitive-behavioral approach for first-time mothers during the immediate postpartum
      period. The objective is to evaluate the effect of a telephone-based intervention using
      cognitive-behavioral approach on postnatal depression and quality of life at 6 weeks and 6
      months postpartum.

      A longitudinal, randomized, pre and post-test control group design will be used. This design
      involves providing a 5-week telephone-based intervention using cognitive-behavioral approach
      at the immediate postpartum period (first five weeks postpartum) to women with high risk of
      postnatal depression. The experimental group receives the intervention on top of the usual
      postpartum care, while the control group receives the usual postpartum care only.
      Participants will be recruited through the postnatal wards at three regional public hospitals
      in Hong Kong. Eligible participants will be randomly assigned to either the telephone-based
      intervention or control group. The allocation schedule will be prepared in advanced using a
      restricted randomization scheme (random permutated blocks of six) by a random number table.
      The random numbers will be placed in sequentially numbered, opaque and sealed envelopes.
      After the women have given informed written consent at 2-3 days postpartum at the postnatal
      units, the research assistant will open the envelope containing the group assignment.

      Participants will be postpartum women who meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The
      research nurse will determine if the women meet the sample inclusion criteria from their
      records. Potential eligible participants will be approached on the second or third postpartum
      day at the postnatal units. Women will be provided with essential information on the nature
      of the study and invited to complete the EPDS. Women who score above 9 on EPDS are considered
      at risk of postnatal depression and they will be invited to participate in the study. Verbal
      and written explanations of the purpose and the procedure of the study will be provided by
      the research nurse and written consent will be obtained from women who agree to participate
      in the study. Participants will be asked to complete the baseline measures, including EPDS
      and SF-12. Post-test measures will be collected at 6 weeks and 6 months postpartum through
      mail.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>change from baseline depressive symptoms at 6 weeks postpartum and change from baseline depressive symptoms at 6 months postpartum</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 6 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>change from baseline quality of life at 6 weeks postpartum and change from baseline quality of life at 6 months postpartum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">397</enrollment>
  <condition>Postnatal Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone-based intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>telephone-based cognitive-behavioral intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is based on the cognitive-behavioral approach. It consists of five, 30-minutes sessions delivered weekly from postpartum week one to week five via telephone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone-based intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  aged 18 or above

          -  first-time mother

          -  have given birth to a single full-term healthy baby

          -  able to speak and read the Chinese language

          -  Hong Kong residents

          -  score above 9 on EPDS.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  single

          -  having complications after delivery

          -  having regular follow up with psychiatrists

          -  currently taking antidepressant or antipsychotic drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Hong Kong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 3, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>postnatal depression</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression, Postpartum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

