<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01501552</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ECGA259268</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01501552</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial Testing the Effect of Strategies on Performance of Brief Intervention Programmes for Harmful Alcohol Consumption</brief_title>
  <acronym>ODHIN_RCT</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomised Controlled Trial Testing the Incremental Effect of Strategies That Raise Awareness, Acceptance and Performance of Identification and Brief Intervention Programmes for Harmful Alcohol Consumption in Primary Health Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundacion Clinic per a la Recerca Biomédica</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Commission</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stichting Katholieke Universiteit</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Newcastle Upon-Tyne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>King's College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Goeteborgs Universitet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Linkoeping University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Health, Generalitat de Catalunya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Panstwowa Agencja Rozwiazywania Problemow Alkoholowych</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maastricht University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pomorski Uniwersytet Medyczny w Szczecinie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundacion Clinic per a la Recerca Biomédica</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective is to study if training and support, financial reimbursement and
      referral to an internet based brief intervention programme, singly or in combination, may
      increase implementation of evidence based methods of identification and brief intervention
      for excessive alcohol consumption in routine primary health care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be a stepped cluster RCT in 5 countries and the endpoint of the study is the
      number of interventions delivered during a certain time period. More specifically, the RCT
      will examine:

        -  The effect of Continuous Medical Education (CME) to PHC providers

        -  The effect of financial reimbursement to PHC providers as a pay-for-performance of brief
           alcohol interventions

        -  Whether an alternative internet based method of delivering brief intervention can
           increase the proportion of patients reached

        -  If one implementation strategy will give an added value to one already enforced.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of screening tests carried out in primary health care settings to detect excessive alcohol consumption care</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>Screening rates will be calculated at five time points: during a four week period during the third month before the start of the study (baseline measurement), in three consecutive four week blocks during the twelve week intervention period (intervention measurement) and during a four week block during the sixth month after the end of the intervention period (follow-up measurement).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of brief interventions for excessive alcohol consumption delivered in primary health care settings</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>Brief intervention rates will be calculated at five time points: during a four week period during the third month before the start of the study (baseline measurement), in three consecutive four week blocks during the twelve week intervention period (intervention measurement) and during a four week block during the sixth month after the end of the intervention period (follow-up measurement).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of role security of primary health care providers measured by their answers to the SAAPPQ instrument</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Role security of the primary health care providers will be measured through their responses to the SAAPPQ (a validated instrument based on factor analysis (Anderson &amp; Clement 1987) of the original alcohol and alcohol problems perception questionnaire developed and validated by Cartwright (1980))at three time points: baseline, end of intervention period, and follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of therapeutic commitment of primary health care providers measured by their answers to the SAAPPQ instrument</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Therapeutic commitment of the primary health care providers will be measured through their responses to the SAAPPQ (a validated instrument based on factor analysis (Anderson &amp; Clement 1987) of the original alcohol and alcohol problems perception questionnaire developed and validated by Cartwright (1980))at three time points: baseline, end of intervention period, and follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the no-intervention treatment as usual group, a package, containing a summary card of the national guideline recommendation, will be delivered to each provider unit without demonstration. In Poland, the summary card will be adapted from the PHEPA guidelines (ref) for the purposes of this trial. The treatment as usual group will be requested to screen and offer person-to-person SBI at the PHCU.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training &amp; support (T&amp;S)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The T&amp;S only group will be offered two face-to-face educational meetings of at least one hour and a maximum of 2 hours, and one telephone support call of at least ten minutes and a maximum of 30 minutes. The telephone call will be offered to one of the GPs ('leader'). Depending on the needs of the PHCU, one additional face to face training (1 to 2 hours) may be offered. The time interval between meetings will be on average 2 weeks. The training sessions will address improving knowledge, skills, attitudes, and perceived barriers and facilitators by combining theory and practice-based training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Financial incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The financial incentive only group will receive a financial incentive depending on their screening and brief intervention activities. They will be paid for the performance, with the country dependent system of pay (fee for item or fee for achieving set rates) and based on normal practices and financial rates for financial incentives for clinical preventive activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>E-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The e-SBI (online screening and brief intervention)only group are expected to refer identified at-risk patients to an approved e-SBI programme, which will be either country specific (where these exist) or based on the WHO e-SBI programme (Poland).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S and financial incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The T&amp;S and financial incentive group will be offered two face-to-face educational meetings of at least one hour and a maximum of 2 hours, and one telephone support call of at least ten minutes and a maximum of 30 minutes. Also, they will receive a financial incentive depending on their screening and brief intervention activities. They will be paid for the performance, with the country dependent system of pay (fee for item or fee for achieving set rates) and based on normal practices and financial rates for financial incentives for clinical preventive activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The T&amp;S and e-SBI group will be offered two face-to-face educational meetings of at least one hour and a maximum of 2 hours, and one telephone support call of at least ten minutes and a maximum of 30 minutes. The telephone call was offered to one of the GPs ('leader'). Depending on the needs of the PHCU, one additional face to face training (1 to 2 hours) was offered. Also this group is expected to refer identified at-risk patients to an approved e-SBI (online screening and brief intervention) programme, which will either be country specific (where these exist) or based on the WHO e-SBI programme (Poland).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Financial incentive and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The financial incentive and e-SBI (online screening and brief intervention) group will be paid for screening and referral performance instead of actual delivery of e-SBI by themselves as in line with the e-SBI only group, with the country dependent system of pay (fee for item or fee for achieving set rates) and based on normal practices and financial rates for financial incentives for clinical preventive activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S, financial incentive and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The T&amp;S, financial incentive and e-SBI (online screening and brief intervention) group will be offered two face-to-face educational meetings of at least one hour and a maximum of 2 hours, and one telephone support call of at least ten minutes and a maximum of 30 minutes. The telephone call will be offered to one of the GPs ('leader'). Also, they are expected to offer screening at the PHCU and to refer screen positive patients to e-SBI programmes. Additionally, they will be paid for screening and referral performance, with the country dependent system of pay (fee for item or fee for achieving set rates) and based on normal practices and financial rates for financial incentives for clinical preventive activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training and support (T&amp;S)</intervention_name>
    <description>Two face-to-face educational meetings of at least one hour and a maximum of 2 hours, and one telephone support call of at least ten minutes and a maximum of 30 minutes. The telephone call will be offered to one of the GPs ('leader'). Depending on the needs of the PHCU, one additional face to face training (1 to 2 hours) may be offered. The time interval between meetings will be on average 2 weeks. The training sessions will address improving knowledge, skills, attitudes, and perceived barriers and facilitators by combining theory and practice-based training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training &amp; support (T&amp;S)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S and financial incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S, financial incentive and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Financial incentive</intervention_name>
    <description>Groups will receive a financial incentive depending on their screening and brief intervention activities. They will be paid for the performance, with the country dependent system of pay (fee for item or fee for achieving set rates) and based on normal practices and financial rates for financial incentives for clinical preventive activities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Financial incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S and financial incentive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Financial incentive and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S, financial incentive and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>E-SBI (online screening and brief intervention)</intervention_name>
    <description>Referring identified at-risk patients to an approved e-SBI programme, which will be either country specific (where these exist) or based on the WHO e-SBI programme (Poland).</description>
    <arm_group_label>E-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Financial incentive and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>T&amp;S, financial incentive and e-SBI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary Health Care Units (PHCU) of approximate size of 5.000-20.000 registered
             patients

          -  Primary Health Care Units (PHCU) located in Spain, Poland, Sweden, England or The
             Netherlands

          -  Providers must be physicians or nurses

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary Health Care Units with less than 5.000 registered patients or over 20.000
             registered patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Preben - Bendtsen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Linkoeping University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fredrik - Spak, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Goeteborgs Universitet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter - Anderson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maastricht University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <zip>229 ER</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stichting Katholieke Universiteit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6525 HP</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pomorski Uniwersytet Medyczny w Szczecinie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Szczecin</city>
        <zip>70 204</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Panstwowa Agencja Rozwiazywania Problemow Alkoholowych</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warsaw</city>
        <zip>01 458</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Departament de Salut de la Generalitat de Catalunya</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <state>Catalonia</state>
        <zip>08005</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Goeteborgs Universitet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goeteborg</city>
        <zip>PO Box 100, SE-405 30</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Linköping University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Linköping</city>
        <zip>SE-581 83</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>King's College London</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>SE1 8WA</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College, London</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>WC1E 6HJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Newcastle Upon-Tyne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle Upon-Tyne</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>NE1 7RU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.odhinproject.eu</url>
    <description>Optimizing delivery of health interventions project's website.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 27, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 29, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 5, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 5, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Clinic of Barcelona</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Antoni Gual</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of the Alcohol Unit</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Primary health care</keyword>
  <keyword>Identification and Brief Intervention Programmes</keyword>
  <keyword>Hazardous and harmful alcohol consumption</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

