<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02814864</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P130935</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-001462-99</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02814864</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial Evaluating the Efficacy of Systemic Mesenchymal Stromal Cell (MSC) Injections for the Treatment of Severe and Chronic Radiotherapy-induced Abdomino-pelvic Complications (Pelvic Radiation Disease, PRD) Refractory to Standard Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRISME</acronym>
  <official_title>Clinical Phase II Trial Evaluating the Efficacy of Systemic Mesenchymal Stromal Cell (MSC) Injections for the Treatment of Severe and Chronic Radiotherapy-induced Abdomino-pelvic Complications (Pelvic Radiation Disease, PRD) Refractory to Standard Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients receiving radiation therapy are still at risk for side effects due to off-target
      radiation damage of normal tissues The number of cancer patients is expected to increase from
      14.1 million around the world in 2012 to 19.3 million in 2025. Up to ten percent will develop
      late severe gastrointestinal complications (i.e. Pelvic Radiation Disease - PRD). Symptoms
      are proctopathy (5-20%) and radiation-induced cystitis (3,5%) that affect quality of life.
      The treatment of PRD is limited to managing the symptoms; new alternatives should be
      proposed.

      Clinical trials using MSCs to treat hemorrhagic cystitis, proctopathy have demonstrated the
      feasibility to used MSCs in these pathologies :

        -  MSCs successfully repair hemorrhagic cystitis, and perforated colon in patients with
           hemorrhagic cystitis, perforated colon and peritonitis.

        -  Six clinical trials are currently ongoing for proctopathy, 3 are phase III. Results
           suggest an inhibition of chronic inflammation and fistulization and interruption of
           hemorrhagic syndromes.

        -  Clinical trials to evaluate the efficacy of MSCs to treat hemorrhagic cystitis is in
           progress.

        -  A decrease in pain after the injection of MSCs was observed in patients treated by
           radiotherapy for breast cancer, radiation burns, and radiotherapy over-dosage.

        -  Four patients, were treated with MSCs after receiving overdose pelvic irradiation for
           prostate cancer. A decrease in pain (EN score), bleeding and diarrhea was observed.

      MSCs will represent a promising alternative strategy in the treatment of severe enteritis,
      rectitis and cystitis after radiotherapy, and may avoid surgical treatment and may diminish
      the adverse effect of PRD in terms of chronicity, morbidity, mortality and health costs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -Chemo-radiation enhances survival but also increases the risk of PRD. The result will be an
      increasing

        -  Cost for society (repeated hospitalization for palliative care)

        -  An ethical problem to help these patients with irreversible degraded quality of life.

      Results from conventional therapies for PRD reveal a poor long-term efficacy:

      i. Coagulation by plasma argon is insufficient, 58% at 6 months; ii. The efficacy of formalin
      is questionable (48%), as is 5-amino-salicylate, sulfasalazine, vitamin E and pentoxifylline
      ; iii. The efficacy of short chain fatty acids and hyperbaric oxygen therapy is low (40%);
      iv. Steroids are of limited efficacy (37%). v. A surgical operation in an irradiated field is
      associated with difficult or impossible healing as well as with risks of infection (mortality
      of 5% within 40 months) Furthermore, conventional therapies are palliative and badly
      tolerated. More effective approaches are thus crucial.

        -  PRD unfortunately remains a major side effect of radiotherapy and there is no
           established effective treatment. Consequently, the recruitment of the aforementioned
           number of patients by participating radiotherapy centers is ensured.

        -  MSC therapy is a safe and suitable option in severe PRD.

             -  The investigators propose a proof of concept.

             -  MSC production and injection protocol has already been successfully employed in
                compassionate therapy on four patients, who suffered from chronic and fistulizing
                colitis, after radiotherapy for prostate cancer.

        -  PRISME is a network project which includes St Antoine Hospital, INSERM (National
           Institute of Health and Medical Research), EFS (French Blood Establishment ), CTSA (Army
           Centre of Blood Transfusion) ECellFrance, IRSN (Institute for Radiological Protection
           and Nuclear Safety), IGR (Gustave Roussy Institute), and Institute of cancerology of
           west France. Our consortium has robust experience of the treatment of radiation damages,
           preclinical models and the medical management of PRD using biotherapy. Clinical and
           scientific achievements, previous collaborations of the different groups and preliminary
           partner's data assure the fulfillment of the program.

             -  Patient selection will be performed by the six radiotherapy centers participating
                in this study. The expected recruitment per center had been concluded from the
                average number of potentially eligible patients treated and surveyed in each of the
                following centers (St Antoine Hospital, Gustave Roussy Institute, Institute of
                cancerology of west France).

             -  The ECellFrance platform will ensure MSC production. This platform includes two
                locations in Parisian region: EFS (in the city of Creteil) and CTSA.

             -  Support, trials and intervention protocols will be handled in the Department of
                Clinical Hematology at St Antoine Hospital, renowned for its expertise in the
                treatment of overdosed radiation therapy patients, i.e. Epinal cases) and which has
                managed a PHRC using MSCs.

             -  Participation of a research group with robust experience in stem cells,
                transplantation (Research centre Saint Antoine, INSERM) and radiobiology, cell
                therapy treatment of radiation accidents (IRSN, CTSA). These groups will carry out
                the characterization of the biological activity and immunological properties of the
                native MSC bone marrow tissue in vitro (INSERM) and in vivo (IRSN) and
                immunological monitoring of patients treated with the MSC (INSERM).

      It is expected to achieve the healing of chronic refractory diseases, leading to lower health
      expenses by reducing patient treatment and hospitalization, and to an increase in their
      quality of life by a:

        -  Decrease in rectorrhagia and hematuria, pain, drug-consumption;

        -  Inhibition of hemorrhagic syndromes and chronic inflammation accompanied by a sustained
           fistulization arrest due to the repairing capability of MSC.

      The expected results for the public will be the healing of chronic refractory diseases,
      leading to lower health expenses by reducing patient treatment and hospitalization, and to an
      increase in their quality of life.

      Hypothesis: MSC injections provide an efficient alternative approach in the treatment of PRD
      for patient refractories to conventional treatments.

      Patient study scheduled:

      D-60: Screening by 6 radiotherapy centers. D-1: Inclusion in Saint Antoine Hospital. D0, D7
      and D14: IV MSC injection (2x106 - 6x106/kg MSC). M2 and M4: follow-up visit. End of
      patient's participation to the study at M4. Total number of scheduled patients: 12 patients
      suffering from PRD. Simon minimax plan, P0=25%, P1=60%, Alpha=5% and Beta=20%.

      Stopping rules:

      Step 1: (n1=5) inclusion of 5 patients r1=1: if the number of success is &lt;2, the study will
      end for MSC inefficacy. If the number of success is ≥2, proceed to step 2. Step 2: (n2=7)
      inclusion of up to 7 patients r2=5: as soon as the number of successes reaches 6 (&gt;r2),
      inclusions will be discontinued and MSC will be considered as sufficiently promising for
      further studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease of one grade on the LENT SOMA</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after the first injection of MSCs</time_frame>
    <description>Decrease of one grade for rectorrhagia or hematuria on the LENT SOMA scale (Late Effects Normal Tissue Task Force -Subjective, Objective, Management, Analytic), 4 months after the first injection of MSCs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of treatment on analgesic drug consumption (analgesic, opiates).</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after the first injection of MSCs</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of drug consumption (analgesic, opiate)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of treatment on quality of life with SF36 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after the first injection of MSCs</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life evaluated by SF36 questionnaire (short form survey)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of treatment on quality of life with HADS questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after the first injection of MSCs</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life evaluated by questionnaire Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of treatment on pain</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after the first injection of MSCs</time_frame>
    <description>Mean pain intensity evaluated by Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) during the week prior to the visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of diarrhea</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after the first injection of MSCs</time_frame>
    <description>diminution of the frequency of diarrhea</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Pelvic Radiation Therapy</condition>
  <condition>Radiation-induced Hemorrhagic Cystitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mesenchymal Stromal Cell (MSC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient with chronic radiotherapy-induced abdomino-pelvic complications refractory to standard therapy: 12 patients suffering of PRD (LENT-SOMA scale&gt;2)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mesenchymal Stromal Cell (MSC) injections</intervention_name>
    <description>12 patients suffering of PRD (LENT-SOMA scale&gt;2) will receive Mesenchymal Stromal Cell (MSC) injections</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mesenchymal Stromal Cell (MSC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cell therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥18 years and &lt;80 years;

          -  Any pelvic cancerous pathology irradiated with a history of pelvic complications of
             grade &gt; 2 LENT SOMA scale);

          -  Absence of metastasis objectified by bone scintigraphy;

          -  After failure following at least three lines of conventional treatment;

          -  Good physical condition (WHO-performance status 0-1)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancies (Pregnancy test carried out during the inclusion examination).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamad MOHTY, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>mohamad.mohty@inserm.fr</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mohamad MOHTY, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01 49 28 26 20</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>mohamad.mohty@inserm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alain CHAPEL, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0158359546</phone>
    <phone_ext>-33</phone_ext>
    <email>alain.chapel@irsn.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hématologie et thérapie cellulaire, Hôpital Saint Antoine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75012</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mohamad MOHTY, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>01 49 28 26 20</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>mohamad.mohty@inserm.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alain CHAPEL, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0158359546</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>alain.chapel@irsn.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hematology</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesenchymal Stromal Cell</keyword>
  <keyword>radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>gastro-intestinal complications</keyword>
  <keyword>lower digestive tract cancers</keyword>
  <keyword>colitis</keyword>
  <keyword>bleeding</keyword>
  <keyword>diarrhea</keyword>
  <keyword>pelvic radiation disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cystitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

