<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02813343</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB # 2016-0010-E</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02813343</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluate the Value of Telehomecare for Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluate the Value of Telehomecare for Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Women's College Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>North York General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>William Osler Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Joseph's Care Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ontario Telemedicine Network (OTN)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Women's College Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a mixed methods study that evaluates the effectiveness of the BlueStar app and its
      implementation in 3 hospital/health system sites across Ontario. The 6 month study includes
      300 participants that are randomized to an immediate treatment group or a delayed
      intervention group. The primary outcomes include changes in HbA1c and patient reported
      outcomes and experience measures. Qualitative interviews with various stakeholders will
      explore issues relating to successful implementation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      BlueStar is a smart-phone enabled application that is designed to serve as a virtual coach
      for patients. The app sends daily evidence-based, real-time messages as well as longitudinal
      feedback on how to improve diabetes management. Benefits have been demonstrated in time
      periods as brief as three months. One US based study showed a decrease in hospitalizations
      and emergency department visits among participants who use the application. The BlueStar
      application is the first application in the USA to be given FDA approval as a Mobile
      Prescription Therapy. There is a need to explore the effectiveness, utility and cost of the
      intervention in context of Canadian healthcare, before it can be scaled across the system.

      This study is based on a model of &quot;integrated knowledge translation&quot;, where the knowledge
      users of the study have been central to the development of the research project from the very
      beginning. By using this integrated knowledge translation strategy, this study is far more
      likely to demonstrate impact in health system policy and decision-making.

      Research Objective:

      The primary objective is to determine if a smart-phone based application designed to improve
      diabetes self-management and experience of care among patients with Type II diabetes improves
      clinical outcomes, patient experience and health system costs compared to the control group.

      Study Hypothesis:

      Patients randomized to receive the BlueStar application will have improved HbA1c levels
      compared with the control group. The intervention group will also show improved self-reported
      outcomes related to quality of life, disease self-management and experience of care. The
      intervention will also reduce episodes of self-reported hypoglycemia.

      Intervention:

      As part of the intervention, patients will be given a Samsung Smart phone with the BlueStar
      application pre-loaded. Participants will be able to interact with the application over the
      study period however they would like. They can enter a range of baseline clinical
      information. They are also able to enter ongoing information related to diabetes management
      including blood glucose values, food intake and activity levels.

      Based on this information, the BlueStar system will attempt to improve diabetes management
      through two processes. First, the app provides customized, real-time, evidence based messages
      that impact motivation, behavior and education. The messaging is based on the Trans
      Theoretical Model on Behavior Change, which incorporates motivation, education and
      affirmation to create sustained behavior changes for positive health. The app also contains a
      library of videos that patient can access at any time including information on healthy
      eating, complications of unmanaged diabetes and how to use a glucometer.

      Second, the application facilitates the transfer of this data to the clinician through Smart
      Visit reports that provides a clinical overview of their diabetes including recent blood
      sugar readings. The app will remind participants to print this document and bring it to
      clinical appointments every 3 months. However, if advised by their clinician, participants
      can print the smart report more frequently and send via fax to the clinician. This may be
      required for example if rapid titration of insulin and close monitoring of blood sugars are
      required.

      Throughout the study participants will be able to contact their usual clinician at the
      diabetes education center if they have any questions about the application or the information
      presented. If the clinician is unable to answer the question they will have clear protocols
      on who to triage the question to (OTN IT support, PI etc.).

      Study Design:

      The study is a randomized, wait-list-control trial with 300 participants. The outcome
      assessors will be blinded to group allocation to compare the impact of the BlueStar
      application to usual care.

      Participants will be randomized into one of two groups: an immediate treatment group (ITG)
      and a wait-list-control (WLC). The ITG group will immediately begin using the application,
      for a total duration of six months. The WLC will receive usual care for the first three
      months, at which point they will cross over to the intervention arm and use the application
      for a total of 3 months.

      Recruitment:

      Participants will be recruited from three institutions across Ontario, Canada over a 3 month
      period. The sites include the Diabetes Health Center in Thunder Bay, the Diabetes Education
      Center at North York General Hospital, and the Diabetes Education Centers belonging to the
      William Osler Health System in Brampton and Etobicoke, Ontario. These sites serve a diverse
      range of patients with diabetes and other complex health and social care needs, representing
      a wide range of the population of Ontario, including a large population of aboriginal people
      and new immigrants. Patients are typically followed at these clinics with appointments every
      3 months.

      Baseline Information:

      The following information will be collected at baseline from all participants:

        1. HbA1c: Patients will require an HbA1c value within 2 weeks of the enrollment date.

        2. Baseline characteristics: Baseline information including demographics and health status
           will be collected using a case report form (CRF).

        3. Standardized patient-reported outcome measures(PROMs)/patient-reported experience
           measures (PREMs): A set of standardized questionnaires related to the study hypothesis.

        4. Patient reported health outcomes and utilization

      Data Management:

      All data generated by participants through the BlueStar application will be stored on OTN's
      highly secure, Toronto based data centers.

      Utilization data generated through the BlueStar application will also be stored on the OTN
      data centers.

      Management of additional research data for this multi-center study will be centrally
      coordinated by the Applied Health Research Centre (AHRC), which is a not-for-profit academic
      research organization at St. Michael's Hospital in Toronto, Canada. The AHRC has created and
      will host a secure, web-based data entry system, using REDCap™ software. Research assistants
      will enter clinical data and outcomes into the REDCap database, and administer patient
      surveys through this tool. AHRC will determine the randomization sequence. Data quality and
      completeness will be monitored on a weekly basis by the AHRC data manager throughout the data
      collection period, which is 6 months after randomization.

      Healthcare utilization and cost outcome measures will be obtained from health administrative
      data available through the Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences (ICES). At the time of
      study enrollment, patients will be asked to provide consent to link their Ontario Health
      Insurance Plan (OHIP) number to health administrative data. This data will be used to
      determine frequency and intensity of healthcare utilization and overall individual costs
      using methods developed for use with Ontario data.

      Data Analyses:

      All analyses will be intention to treat.

      Qualitative Realist Evaluation - Background:

      In order to understand the contextual influences and practical processes by which the
      BlueStar application is implemented in practice, the investigators will use methods of
      qualitative Realist Evaluation. Realist Evaluation is a methodology used to &quot;unpack the black
      box of implementation&quot;, examining the actual actions required by those involved in
      implementation to ensure the BlueStar application is taken up and used by the patients,
      caregivers, and health care providers involved. This methodology enables a rigorous
      assessment of the contextual influences and strategies by which the application is adopted or
      rejected, enabling researchers to understand how and why the implementation succeeds or
      fails.

      Objectives:

      The objective of the qualitative realist evaluation component of this study is to (a)
      understand how the BlueStar application is implemented in practice, (b) explore participants'
      perspectives of the usability and acceptability of the BlueStar application, and (c) examine
      the key issues associated with scaling applications such as BlueStar up across Ontario.

      Methods:

      The Realist Evaluation will occur alongside the pragmatic randomized trials described above,
      and will include two key methods. The first is qualitative interviews with key stakeholders
      involved in the implementation process, and the second is observations of the introduction
      and use of the virtual care interventions among participants. Specifically, qualitative
      interviews will be conducted with participants at each implementation site. Participants
      recruited for interviews will include 4 to 6 patients at each site (caregivers will be
      invited to participate in those interviews as well); 3 to 5 health care providers involved in
      the implementation process at each site (including at least one physician in each location);
      2-4 organizational leaders who oversee the implementation process at each site (for example,
      Diabetes Education Centre Managers); and 5-7 health system decision makers involved in the
      implementation of virtual care initiatives in Ontario (for example, Local Health Integration
      Network leaders, Ministry of Health and Long Term Care staff and OTN leaders).

      Qualitative interviews will include questions about (a) participants' experiences of learning
      about and using the technology; (b) changes to health care provider workflow required to
      effectively use the technology; (c) organizational changes required to support the
      technology; and (d) health system barriers and facilitators to effective implementation and
      evaluation. These qualitative interviews will be audio recorded and transcribed verbatim, and
      analyzed using thematic analysis strategies by the investigator team to identify key themes
      related to the implementation and evaluation of the virtual care initiatives in actual
      contexts of health care delivery in Ontario.

      Observations as a qualitative method in this study will involve a researcher sitting in on
      the Health Care Provider (HCP) education session (led by the application service provider) in
      which the Blue Star application is introduced at 2 of the sites. The researcher will take
      detailed notes regarding how the technology is introduced to HCPs, any questions raised by
      HCPs, and general observations around the initial perception of the technology. Where
      possible, the researcher will take notes on how the HCP interact with the technology to
      understand its capabilities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose control (HbA1c levels)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in HbA1c from baseline to 6 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported health outcomes and utilization - ER visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>a. Emergency department visits for hyper/hypoglycemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported health outcomes and utilization - Hypoglycemic episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>b. Hypoglycemic episodes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported health outcomes and utilization - Hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>c. Hospitalizations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported health outcomes and utilization - Physician visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>d. Physician visits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported health outcomes and utilization - Med Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>e. Medication Adherence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported health outcomes and utilization - Blood glucose monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>f. Frequency of blood glucose monitoring</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health system utilization data collected using Institute for Clinical and Evaluative Sciences (ICES).</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be collected using the patient OHIP number.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>An adapted version of the Mobile App Rating Scale will collected from all participants</measure>
    <time_frame>After 3 or 6 months on the app.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>App utilization data - time of use</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 3 or 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>a. Time spent with each use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>App utilization data - Frequency of use</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 3 or 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>b. Frequency of Utilization (i. Over study period; ii. By app feature; iii. Time of day)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standardized PROMs/PREMs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months for all participants</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">221</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Immediate Treatment group will receive access to the study intervention - BlueStar app, immediately after consenting for a total duration of 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Delayed Treatment group will receive access to the study intervention - BlueStar app, 3 months after consenting for a total duration of 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BlueStar app</intervention_name>
    <description>BlueStar is a smart-phone enabled application that is designed to serve as a virtual coach for patients. The app sends daily evidence-based, real-time messages as well as longitudinal feedback on how to improve diabetes management. The Bluestar app has been shown to be effective at teaching patients about dietary impacts on their blood glucose levels, encouraging patients to generate higher-quality blood glucose data for enhanced self-monitoring, and to improve overall management of diabetes as represented by reductions in levels of HgbA1c. Benefits have been demonstrated in time periods as brief as three months. One US based study showed a decrease in hospitalizations and emergency department visits among participants who use the application.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults, 18 years or older, currently being treated for Type II diabetes

          2. HgbA1C greater or equal to 8.0% and at least 1.0% above target within the last 3
             months

          3. Have a functional email address or be willing to obtain one

          4. Be functional in reading the English language (self reported)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have Type I diabetes or Latent autoimmune diabetes of adults (LADA)

          2. Are on continuous glucose monitoring

          3. Have an insulin pump

          4. Are on dialysis

          5. Are pregnant.

          6. Are unable to use a computer or mobile phone due to severe mental or physical
             impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sacha Bhatia, MD, FRCP(C)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Women's College Hospital Institute for Health Systems Solutions and Virtual Care (WIHV)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 1B2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quinn CC, Clough SS, Minor JM, Lender D, Okafor MC, Gruber-Baldini A. WellDoc mobile diabetes management randomized controlled trial: change in clinical and behavioral outcomes and patient and physician satisfaction. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2008 Jun;10(3):160-8. doi: 10.1089/dia.2008.0283.</citation>
    <PMID>18473689</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katz R, Mesfin T, Barr K. Lessons from a community-based mHealth diabetes self-management program: &quot;it's not just about the cell phone&quot;. J Health Commun. 2012;17 Suppl 1:67-72. doi: 10.1080/10810730.2012.650613.</citation>
    <PMID>22548601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pawson R. The science of evaluation: a realist manifesto. Sage. 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marchal B, van Belle S, van Olmen J, Hoerée T, Kegels G. Is realist evaluation keepings its promise? A review of published empirical studies in the field of health systems research. Evaluation. 2012;18(2):192-212.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qualitative Research in Psychology. 2006;3(2):77-101.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 21, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There are agreements in place to share individual participant data between all the study sites and Women's College Hospital</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

