<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02814474</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1-10-72-104-14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02814474</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Experimental Hyperketonemia on Myocardial Metabolism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Ketone Bodies on Myocardial Glucose and Fatty Acid Metabolism in Healthy Volunteers: A Positron Emission Tomography Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aarhus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aarhus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Starvation and metabolic stress increase circulating ketone bodies, potentially providing the
      heart with an alternative oxidative fuel. Hyperketonemia reduces myocardial fatty acid
      consumption. It is unclear whether this is due to inhibited peripheral lipolysis or
      diminished uptake per se.

      Aim: To test whether infusion of 3-hydroxybutyrate (BHB) inhibits myocardial glucose and
      fatty acid uptake.

      Methods: Randomized, single blinded, cross-over interventional study in 8 healthy volunteers.
      Myocardial glucose and fatty acid metabolism studied by 11C-palmitate and 18F-FDG PET/CT.
      Experimental elevation of circulating ketone bodies by infusion of
      β-hydroxy-β-methylbutyrate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Ketone bodies are produced by the liver in conditions of increased fatty acid oxidation,
      serving as important fuel sources during fasting and starvation. They are metabolized to
      acetyl-CoA which enters the tricarboxylic acid cycle, enabling ATP production independently
      of glycolysis and resulting in lower oxygen consumption per mole of produced ATP compared to
      glucose [ref]. Their primary physiological function appears to be as an alternative
      protein-sparing source of energy for extrahepatic tissues in times of reduced carbohydrate
      availability, preventing muscle wasting. The principal ketone bodies in humans are
      beta-hydroxybutyrate (BHB) and acetoacetate. Increased ketogenesis is a feature common to
      fasting, starvation and diabetes mellitus. Ketones have been shown to have a number of
      neuroprotective effects including anticonvulsant activity, improving cognitive function in
      Alzheimer's disease and decreasing the effects of acute brain injury and ischemic damage
      [ref], as well as antitumoral effect in gliomas. This has led to the suggestion that ketones
      could be used therapeutically for a number of diseases though currently the only recognized
      therapeutic use of ketones is in the form of ketogenic diets for the treatment of epilepsy.

      There are limited in vivo studies on the effect of ketones on the heart. It is known that
      fatty acids are the preferred myocardial fuel substrate and that this shifts to increased use
      of glucose, and to a lesser extent ketones, in times of acutely increased demand.
      Interestingly, acute ketone infusion in pigs appears to inhibit myocardial fatty acid
      oxidation. In vitro studies suggest ketones decrease myocardial glucose uptake and affect
      myocardial contractility, with either increased or decreased contractility when ketones are
      the only energy source. This has not been further investigated in vivo. It is therefore
      unclear to what extent ketones can contribute to myocardial metabolism in conditions of
      hyperketonemia, and how this affects contractility.

      The present project thus proposes to address the issues outlined above, by measuring human
      cerebral and cardiac uptake of energy substrates, together with functional parameters, using
      PET imaging and appropriate radiotracers, under experimental hyperketonemia.

      Hypotheses:

      1. An acute increase in blood ketone concentration without previous ketoadaptation will
      decrease cardiac palmitate and glucose uptake in healthy humans.

      Materials and methods

      Effect of acute ketone infusion on cardiac perfusion and 18F-FDG and 11C-palmitate uptake in
      healthy subjects:

      Study population: 10 healthy volunteers. All study subjects will be instructed to follow a
      standardised diet for 1 week before the study. On the study day, they will undergo a baseline
      dynamic cardiac PET scan with 15O-water followed by 11C-palmitate and 18F-FDG tracers,
      together with baseline blood samples, muscle biopsy and subcutaneous fat biopsy to assess
      peripheral metabolic status. An intravenous infusion of sodium betahydroxybutyrate will then
      be initiated at a concentration and rate sufficient to achieve 1-2 mM ketonemia after 30
      minutes (assessed by blood sample). A second dynamic PET scan identical to the first will
      then be performed under continuous ketone infusion at a constant rate. Finally, a second set
      of blood samples, muscle and subcutaneous fat biopsies will be taken after the scan before
      stopping the ketone infusion.

      Perspectives:

      The results of this research are expected to provide insights into how human heart metabolism
      respond to increased ketone bodies, and whether there are significant functional
      improvements. It should contribute to further understanding the possible therapeutic benefits
      of both exogenous ketone administration and of fasting in relation to cardiac function, with
      implications for the treatment of various diseases such as diabetes and heart failure.
      Knowledge of ketones' effects on the kinetics of various radionuclide tracers also has
      importance for the appropriate clinical use of diagnostic PET scans in patients with elevated
      blood ketone levels. In addition, the implementation and validation of a ketone PET tracer
      will allow further future non-invasive studies that directly measure ketone metabolism in
      various tissues and disease states.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial Glucose uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>After 330 minutes of ketone infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic 18F-FDG PET/CT scan - 50 minutes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial Fatty Acid Metabolism</measure>
    <time_frame>After 210 minutes of ketone infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic 11C-palmitate PET/CT scan - 50 minutes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial Blood Flow</measure>
    <time_frame>After 180 minutes of ketone infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic 15O-H2O PET/CT scan - 6 minutes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Time 0-390 of the ketone body infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Glucose infusion rate (GIR) during a 0.3 mIE/kg/min hyperinsulinemic- euglycemic clamp</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SALINE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infusion of saline (0.9 %)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>KETONE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infusion of Na-3-Hydroxybutyrate (0.18 g/kg/hour) for 390 minutes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Na-3-hydroxybutyrate</intervention_name>
    <description>Infusion of Na-3-hydroxybutyrate (0.18 g/kg/hour) for 390 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>KETONE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>Infusion of 0.9 % saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>SALINE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy volunteers

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Decreased cardiac function

          -  Kidney disease

          -  Pulmonary disease

          -  Current malignant disease

          -  Substance abuse

          -  Blood donation within 6 month prior to the study

          -  Participation in studies involving ionising radiation within 12 month prior to the
             study

          -  Known claustrophobia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Niels Møller, MD DMsc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Aarhus University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Nuclear Medicine &amp; PET Center, Aarhus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Research Laboratories</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 24, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PET/CT</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart failure</keyword>
  <keyword>hydroxybutyrate</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

