<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02814071</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Early Feeding Pancreatitis</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02814071</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Feeding in Acute Pancreatitis in Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Feeding in Acute Pancreatitis in Children - A Randomised Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shaare Zedek Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shaare Zedek Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute pancreatitis (AP) in children has an increasing incidence and is at times associated
      with significant morbidity and mortality. Despite this, there is no high-quality
      evidence-based treatment for childhood AP and current practice is based entirely on
      historical approach and extrapolation from adult studies.

      In this study, we evaluate the use of early enteral feeding in children with AP. The
      traditional approach to treating AP relies on fasting and intravenous fluids (or occasionally
      parenteral nutrition) assuming that this minimizes stimulation of an already inflamed
      pancreas. Contrary to this, evidence exists that early feeding of patients with AP may be
      beneficial. Randomized controlled trials of fasting vs. early oral diet in adult patients
      with mild AP, showed no differences in pain, serum amylase and CRP levels, but also shorter
      hospital stay in those fed earlier. Further data in adults with severe AP demonstrated that
      early enteral nutrition was associated with decreased mortality, infections and multiorgan
      failure. These benefits were lost if enteral nutrition was commenced 48 hour after admission.
      Suggested explanations for these findings include the possibility that enteral nutrition may
      maintain integrity and function of intestinal mucosa and reduce gut-origin sepsis.

      Historically, nasojejunal (NJ) feeds were felt to be safer than oral or nasogastric feeds in
      the setting of AP by avoiding cephalic and gastric pancreatic stimulation. NJ feeds require
      moderately invasive tube insertion under radiographic or endoscopic guidance. Recent data
      suggest that oral feeding with a low fat diet was as safe as NJ feeding.

      Several animal models of AP demonstrate that the exocrine pancreas is resistant to
      cholecystokinin (CCK) stimulation after the onset of AP, suggesting a mechanism for the lack
      of concern of exacerbating pancreatitis with enteral feeds.

      Considering this data it is less certain that diet and fat restriction contribute to
      treatment of AP. To further challenge the prior conceptions of AP management it is necessary
      to explore the use of unrestricted diet (full fat) in mild-moderate pediatric AP, a
      population with recognized low complication risk.

      Despite the mounting evidence to the contrary, it is still standard clinical practice to fast
      children with AP, and only slowly reintroduce feeds depending on the clinical improvement.
      This is largely due to the lack of clinical interventional studies in children with AP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized controlled trial in children with acute pancreatitis, which
      aims to demonstrate that, compared with the current standard approach of fasting with
      intravenous fluids, early enteral (oral or nasogastric) feeding with standard diet or formula
      will improve the following measures of outcome:

        1. Length of hospital admission.

        2. Serum amylase, lipase, electrolytes, calcium, magnesium, phosphate, urea, creatinine,
           liver function tests, C-reactive protein (biomarker of inflammation), and full blood
           count - routine blood tests performed daily until normalisation of serum lipase or until
           discharge and as directed by treating clinician thereafter.

        3. Weight at presentation and &quot;ready for discharge&quot;, and at day 30 post-discharge clinic
           review.

        4. Systemic complications including hemodynamic instability, renal failure, intensive care
           admission.

        5. Analgesic requirement.

        6. Local complications including pancreatic necrosis, abscess, pseudocyst.

        7. Abdominal ultrasound findings during hospital admission (or other abdominal imaging as
           directed by treating clinicians).

      At day 30-60 post-discharge, a routine ultrasound (to assess for localized complication(s)
      e.g. pseudocyst) and clinical follow-up will be undertaken.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to ready for discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>Time to ready for discharge- measured from onset of admission to time when medically assessed ready for discharge. Assessed between 5-10 days up to 14 days.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Length of hospital stay- measured from onset of admission until time of actual discharge from hospital. Assessed between 5-10 days up to 14 days.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical resolution of acute pancreatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>Time to clinical resolution of acute pancreatitis- time from onset of hospital admission until painfree and absence of nausea with no need for analgesia or other symptomatic therapy. Assessed between 5-10 days up to 14 days.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to biochemical resolution of acute pancreatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>Time to biochemical resolution of acute pancreatitis- time from onset of hospital admission to resolution of lipase and/or amylase below upper limit of normal. Assessed between 5-10 days up to 14 days.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Pancreatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fasting with intravenous fluids</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The child will be kept fasted. Intravenous fluids will be at a rate and type as directed by the treating clinician. A low fat oral diet will be commenced once abdominal pain resolves and serum amylase/lipase levels decrease from the peak levels as per treating clinician. In the event that the patient is unable to tolerate oral feeding, tube feeding or parenteral nutrition may be commenced based on the clinical decision of the treating clinician(s). This will be recorded as an adverse event. Patients will be re-trialed on oral feeds once initial limiting symptoms or factors have improved or settled as per treating clinician's discretion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early enteral feeding</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will commence on an unrestricted oral diet within 24 hours of presentation, meeting 50% of EER with a regular diet and no fat restriction for the first 24 hours of enteral feeding. A 75-100% EER is targeted ≥ 24 hours of enteral feeding.If the targeted EER is not met orally, a nasogastric tube will be inserted to provide bolus feeds of a standard formula with standard fat content. If the patient fails to tolerate both oral and bolus nasogastric tube feeding, continuous nasogastric tube feeding will be provided. If all fails, enteral nutrition by nasojejunal tube feeding or parenteral nutrition may be commenced based on the clinical decision. Patients will be re-trialed on oral feeds once initial limiting symptoms or factors have improved or settled.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Early enteral feeding</intervention_name>
    <description>Early enteral feeding as per description</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early enteral feeding</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of acute pancreatitis according to international consensus criteria
             (Morinville et al. JPGN 2012), which requires at least 2 of the 3 following criteria:

               -  Abdominal pain compatible with acute pancreatitis

               -  Serum amylase and/or lipase ≥ 3 times upper limits of normal

               -  Imaging findings consistent with acute pancreatitis Each episode of acute
                  recurrent pancreatitis will be accepted if each episode is distinct, at least 4
                  weeks apart from previous episode with intervening normalisation of serum amylase
                  and lipase.

          2. Age 3-18 years.

          3. Hemodynamically stable.

          4. Ability to consent and participate in the study and follow study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Severe pancreatitis associated with organ dysfunction and requiring intensive care
             admission at presentation.

          2. Biliary cause of pancreatitis including gallstone pancreatitis and choledochal cyst

          3. Autoimmune pancreatitis.

          4. High grade traumatic pancreatitis including partial or complete disruption of the
             pancreatic duct.

          5. Presence of other conditions restricting enteral nutrition.

          6. Different treatment approach taken by treating clinician due to medical reasons.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Oren Ledder, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Gastroenterology and Nutrition, Shaare Zedek Medical Center, Jerusalem, Israel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Oren Ledder, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+972-2-6666743</phone>
    <email>orenl@szmc.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marina Lekar, M.Sc</last_name>
    <phone>+972-2-5645303</phone>
    <email>marinal@szmc.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Pediatric Gastroenterology, Sydney Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sydney</city>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Keith Ooi, Dr</last_name>
      <email>keith.ooi@hongyee.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Keith Ooi, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shaare Zedek Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>oledder</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Oren Ledder</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Early Feeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Pancreatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

