<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02811276</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00066006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02811276</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of a High Protein Diet on Substrate Oxidation and Energy Metabolism</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Cross-over Trial Investigating the Impact of a High Protein Diet on Substrate Oxidation and Energy Metabolism in Healthy Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Almased Wellness GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the 19th century, researchers found out that the differences in the energy content of
      macronutrients (protein, carbohydrate and fat) can elicit different responses in the amount
      of calories individuals burn per day. It was demonstrated that protein has a metabolic
      advantage when compared to the other macronutrients (carbohydrate and fat). Since these
      findings, researchers all over the world started to study how diets differing in
      macronutrient distribution could result in different responses to energy metabolism. Diets
      with high amounts of protein (i.e. meats, eggs, dairy products, and grains) are becoming more
      popular, and studies have shown that when people eat high quantities of protein they lose
      weight and fat mass, maintain the weight loss, and burn more calories per day.

      The investigators hypothesize that giving high amounts of protein to healthy women will
      increase the amount of calories and fat they burn per day, increase their satiety, and
      improve health markers when compared to a normal diet. The increased protein level will be
      achieved using a nutrition supplement consisted of soy protein, yogurt and honey.

      To test this, the investigators plan to divide the participants in two groups: one will eat a
      normal diet and the other a diet with high amounts of protein during one and a half day.
      After one month they will change groups and eat the other diet for the same period of time.
      During this period consuming the diets (1.5 days), participants will stay inside a whole body
      calorimetry suite, which is similar to a hotel bedroom and is able to inform in the most
      precise way the amount of calories participants will burn and if they are burning more fat.
      Additionally, before and after each meal participants will have to answer a questionnaire
      about their appetite sensations and blood will also be collected to analyze health markers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate the impact of a high protein diet (achieved through
      the use of a high protein supplement) versus standard diet on substrate oxidation and energy
      expenditure using a state-of-the-art live-in whole body calorimetry unit (WBCU).

      This study will be an acute randomized, controlled, cross-over trial. Healthy women (n=24)
      will receive a run-in diet for three days and will then be randomly allocated into one of the
      following groups: 1) Control group receiving an eucaloric standard diet (55% of carbohydrate,
      15% of protein, and 30% of lipid); 2) High-protein group: eucaloric high protein diet (35% of
      carbohydrate, 40% of protein, and 25% of fat) constructed around a soy protein-based meal
      replacement. The wash-out period will be of approximately one month. While receiving the
      diets in the WBCU for 32 hours, participants' overall change in energy metabolism including
      respiratory quotient will be assessed. Additional assessments include metabolic blood markers
      (glucose, insulin, lipid panel, peptide tyrosine-tyrosine, ghrelin, leptin, free glycerol,
      and free fatty acids), and appetite sensations (hunger and satiety). Body composition and
      energy requirements will be assessed at baseline using dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry and
      indirect calorimetry, respectively.

      It is expected that the high-protein diet will increase lipid oxidation, and energy
      expenditure, with other favorable changes in the additional markers when compared to the
      control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in respiratory quotient assessed by indirect calorimetry using a whole body calorimetry unit.</measure>
    <time_frame>During a 32-hour period at baseline and a month later during the dietary intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline respiratory quotient (for resting, exercise and overnight fasting) will be assessed while participants spend 32 hours inside the whole body calorimetry unit during the dietary intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in energy metabolism assessed by indirect calorimetry using a whole body calorimetry unit.</measure>
    <time_frame>During a 32-hour period at baseline and a month later during the dietary intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline energy expenditure will be assessed while participants spend 32 hours inside the whole body calorimetry unit during the dietary intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in appetite sensations assessed by a visual analogue scale (VAS 100 mm) questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>During a 32-hour period (before and after each meal and snack) at baseline and a month later during the dietary intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline hunger and satiety will be assessed immediately before and after each meal and snack using the VAS 100 mm questionnaire while participants spend 32 hours inside the whole body calorimetry unit during the dietary intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Dietary Modification</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Those assigned to the Control Group will receive a eucaloric diet (a diet designed to meet the person's energy needs and maintain body weight) composed of 55% of carbohydrate, 15% of protein, and 30% of lipid.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-Protein Diet Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Those assigned to the High-Protein Diet Group will receive a eucaloric diet composed of 35% of carbohydrate, 40% of protein, and 25% of lipid constructed around a soy protein-based meal replacement (Almased®).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>The High-Protein Diet Group will receive a eucaloric diet composed of 35% of carbohydrate, 40% of protein, and 25% of lipid constructed around a soy protein-based meal replacement (Almased®) for one and a half day. Participants will consume 1 gram ± 0.1 of Almased® per kg of body weight mixed with linseed oil and skim milk in their breakfast, lunch and dinner. Two snacks (afternoon and evening) composed of 1 gram ± 0.1 of Almased® per kg of body weight mixed with vegetable juice and linseed oil will also be provided.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High-Protein Diet Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy;

          -  Non-smoker;

          -  Female;

          -  Aged 18 to 34.9 years;

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 18.5 and 24.9 kg/m² (preferably between 20 and 24.9
             kg/m²);

          -  Regular menstrual cycle (lasting between 25 and 35 days).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have previously been diagnosed with any kind of disease;

          -  Are taking any medications which may alter energy metabolism or body composition;

          -  Are lactose, gluten and/or soy allergic/intolerant;

          -  Follow a vegetarian, vegan or restrictive dietary pattern;

          -  Are pregnant or lactating;

          -  Have used nutritional supplements in the past two months;

          -  Perform over an hour per day of leisure time physical activity or more than seven
             hours per week of strenuous activity;

          -  Have had a nuclear medicine scan or injection of an X-ray dye in the past week;

          -  Have had a barium test/exam in the last two weeks;

          -  Claustrophobia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carla MM Prado, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arya Sharma, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Unviersity of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2E1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 16, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carla Prado</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor; CAIP Chair in Nutrition, Food and Health; and Director of the Human Nutrition Research Unit</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>High-protein diet</keyword>
  <keyword>Energy metabolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Substrate oxidation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

