<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02819986</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1784</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02819986</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Using the Progressive Goal Attainment Program in Anxiety and Mood Disorders</brief_title>
  <acronym>PGAP</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness and Feasibility of Using the Progressive Goal Attainment Program in Anxiety and Mood Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the present study is to determine the effectiveness and feasibility of the
      Progressive Goal Attainment Program (PGAP) with individuals with anxiety and mood disorders.
      PGAP has been suggested as an effective therapy to reduce psychosocial barriers and help
      individuals return to life roles including readiness to return to work. PGAP has been shown
      to be effective with some chronic health conditions however has not been specifically studied
      in mental health populations. The study consists of 10 one hour weekly therapy sessions that
      focus on reducing psychosocial risk factors that result in disability through the use of goal
      setting, activity planning and activation, monitoring and challenging thoughts about return
      to work, and problem solving. Participants will also be asked to complete short self-report
      questionnaires as well as a semi-structured interview about the participants anxiety, mood,
      impact of disability, and current functioning at the beginning of session one and within two
      weeks after session 10. Two short questionnaires will also be completed at each session
      measuring the degree to which the participants daily life impacts and is affected by anxiety
      or mood symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the present study is to determine the effectiveness of the Progressive Goal
      Attainment Program (PGAP) with individuals with anxiety and mood disorders. PGAP has been
      suggested as an effective therapy to reduce psychosocial barriers and help individuals return
      to life roles including readiness to return to work. PGAP has been shown to be effective with
      some chronic health conditions however has not been specifically studied in mental health
      populations.

      The study consists of 10 one hour weekly therapy sessions with a clinician and follow the
      PGAP manual. The therapy sessions focus on reducing psychosocial risk factors that result in
      disability through the use of goal setting, activity planning, activation and re-engagement
      in activities, monitoring and challenging thoughts about return to work, and problem solving.
      Participants are also encouraged to participate in homework which involves daily activity
      planning, participating in planned activities, and tracking the activities completed.
      Participants will also be asked to complete short self-report questionnaires as well as a
      semi-structured interview about the participants anxiety, mood, impact of disability, and
      current functioning at the beginning of session one and within two weeks after session 10.
      Two short questionnaires will also be completed at each session measuring the degree to which
      the participants daily life impacts and is affected by anxiety or mood symptoms.

      Our first hypothesis is that participants who receive PGAP will report significant reductions
      in functional disability as measured by self-report as well as by interview, decreases in
      self-reported work avoidance, increases in work readiness, and decreases in self-reported
      symptoms of anxiety and depression. Our second hypothesis is that mean reductions in the
      above-noted outcome variables will be similar in magnitude to those reported in published
      studies that have examined PGAP in chronic medically ill populations. Retention rates and
      satisfaction of the therapy will also be assessed to determine feasibility of implementing
      the program on a larger scale.

      To examine the effectiveness of PGAP with participants with an anxiety or a mood disorder,
      the investigators will conduct a series of dependent sample t-tests on the outcome variables
      pre and post intervention. The investigators will also compare mean changes on the outcome
      variables to those in the published literature. The investigators will calculate retention
      rates with the aim of retaining more than 75% of participants, which is comparable to
      retention and drop out rates for psychotherapy trials with participants completing at least 8
      out of 10 sessions or having returned to employment. Feasibility will also be measured by
      looking at satisfaction ratings. A minimal standard will be an average satisfaction rating
      across participants of midpoint (neutral) or above in terms of the therapy received.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 16, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of PGAP on disability (participant perception)</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Level of disability will be measured using a modified version of the Pain Disability Index ( a 7 item self-report measure).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of PGAP on symptom change</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Mood and anxiety symptoms will be measured using the Depression and Anxiety Stress Scales (a 21 item self-report measure).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of PGAP on level of interference from mood and anxiety symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Level of interference from mood and anxiety symptoms will be measured using the Illness Intrusiveness Rating Scale (13 item self-report measure).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of PGAP on fear avoidance beliefs</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Fear avoidance beliefs will be measured using the Fear Avoidance Beliefs Questionnaire (11 item self-report measure).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PGAP retention rates</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Retention rates will be measured by tracking drop out rates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with the PGAP</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction with the therapy will be assessed by using The Satisfaction with Therapy and Therapist Scale-Revised (13 item self-report measure).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of PGAP on disability (clinician report)</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Level of disability will be measured using the Multidimensional Scale of Independent Functioning (semi-structured interview).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of PGAP on role functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Role functioning will be measured using the Multidimensional Scale of Independent Functioning (semi-structured interview).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Mood Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Goal Attainment Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 one hour weekly therapy sessions focused on behavioural interventions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Progressive Goal Attainment Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioural intervention that consists of 10 one hour weekly therapy sessions that focus on goal setting, challenging thoughts about return to work, problem solving, behavioural activation, and resuming occupational roles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Goal Attainment Program</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PGAP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Participants will be

          1. between the ages of 18 and 65 years

          2. have a principle diagnosis of an anxiety or mood disorder

          3. have had changes in their work functioning, either currently not working due to their
             disability or on modified/reduced work.

          4. be registered outpatients of the Anxiety Treatment and Research Clinic or Outpatient
             Mood Disorders Program, St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton,

          5. are interested in return to work or have work related goals.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. current significant substance use

          2. acute mental health (e.g. suicidality, psychosis, mania) that would interfere with the
             program completion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tanja Colonerus, MADS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tanja Colonerus, MADS</last_name>
    <phone>905 522-1155</phone>
    <phone_ext>39867</phone_ext>
    <email>tcoloner@stjoes.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karen Rowa, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>905 522-1155</phone>
    <phone_ext>33656</phone_ext>
    <email>krowa@stjoes.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 3K7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tanja Colonerus, MADS</last_name>
      <phone>905 522-1155</phone>
      <phone_ext>39867</phone_ext>
      <email>tcoloner@stjoes.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Karen Rowa, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>905 522-1155</phone>
      <email>krowa@stjoes.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 30, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tanja Colonerus</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Priniciple Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>occupational functioning</keyword>
  <keyword>Worries</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Disability</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

