<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00295464</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACG Trial</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Betamethasone</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00295464</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Antenatal Rescue Course of Glucocorticoids in Threatened Premature Birth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Trial on Efficacy and Safety of the Antenatal Rescue Course of Glucocorticoids in Threatened Premature Birth (ACG Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oulu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oulu</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Administration of steroid to the mother in imminent preterm delivery is a known effective
      practice to decrease the risk of respiratory distress syndrome and intraventricular
      haemorrhage in preterm infants if given with a week of the preterm delivery. This randomized
      clinical trial is performed to test the possibility whether the repeat dose of steroid
      results in further reduction of these diseases in case the mother is in imminent preterm
      delivery more than a week after the first antenatal steroid treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RANDOMIZED TRIAL ON EFFICACY AND SAFETY OF THE ANTENATAL RESCUE COURSE OF GLUCOCORTCOID IN
      THREATENED PREMATURE BIRTH (ACG trial)

      Introduction

      Prematurity is the main cause of neonatal mortality and morbidity. Immature infants have many
      serious diseases such as respiratory distress syndrome (RDS), intracranial hemorrhage (ICH),
      chronic lung disease (CLD), necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC) and retinopathy of prematurity
      (ROP). Corticosteroids have the maturational effects on fetal cardiovascular, respiratory,
      nervous and gastrointestinal systems (1). Antenatal corticosteroids (ANC) have been widely
      used for prevention of RDS and other serious diseases in preterm infants since 1972’s, when
      the controlled trial of antepartum glucocorticoid treatment was published. Administration of
      s of 12 mg of betamethasone given twice intramuscularly 24 hours apart has shown to be
      effective (2,3,4,39). Strong evidence exists for neonatal benefits from a complete course of
      ANC starting at 24 hours and lasting up to 7 days after treatment (2,39). Betamethasone and
      dexamethasone have similar biological activity and both are associated with a significant
      reduction in the risk of RDS, but only betamethasone with a significant decrease of the
      neonatal mortality. The clinical benefit had not been documented beyond 7 days after the
      onset of ANC therapy. (1,2)

      Several randomized studies have shown that a single course of antenatal corticosteroid
      treatment improves the survival of preterm infants born at 24-34 weeks gestation and
      decreases the incidence of RDS, ICH and NEC. ANC therapy reduces the incidence of RDS by
      approximately 50%.(1,2) ANC treatment also reduces the need of exogenous surfactant (4). The
      protective effect against RDS is thought to be due to the structural maturation of the lungs,
      increased surfactant synthesis, improved resistance to lung injury and improved
      cardiovascular adaptation. Glucocorticoid speeds up the normal thinning of the gas-exchange
      walls with double capillary loops between the air sacs. ANC thus accelerates the structural
      development of the respiratory airways, but reduces the number of alveoli. Glucocorticoid
      increases surfactant synthesis by enhancing maturation of the surfactant- producing type II
      pneumocytes and stimulating the secretion of surfactant complex (1,6,7,8,9,40). Serial doses
      of ANC may possibly downregulate steroid receptors resulting in decreased or disordered
      surfactant production.(ref) ANC has not been shown to decrease the incidence of CLD at 28
      days of age either in the meta-analysis or in the recent retrospective studies (2,13,14,15).

      ANC treatment is associated with maturation of the cardiovascular system and normalisation of
      the low blood pressure in the small premature infant at birth.(ref) This influence was
      evident after administration of surfactant.(4) According to meta-analysis, ANC had no effect
      on the incidence of PDA. However in several studies, use of ANC was associated with increased
      spontaneous closure of PDA(2,3,4, ).

      ANC decreases the incidence of ICH in preterm infants (2,3,4). Severe prematurity decreases
      autoregulation of the cerebral circulation and predisposes to ICH or cerebral ischemia.
      Glucocorticoids accelerate differentiation of neuronal cells and possibly enhance maturation
      of germinal matrix vessels (1,33,34). ANC therapy has been associated also with a lower
      incidence of periventricular leukomalacia (PVL) and cerebral palsy (CP), but these effects
      were not significant in Crowley’s meta-analysis (2,3,4,5). In a recently published
      retrospective study, antenatal administration of betamethasone was associated with a
      decreased risk of PVL compared to antenatal dexamethasone or no treatment (17).

      Betamethasone is clinically used as a mixture of betamethasone phosphate (6 mg) and
      betamethasone acetate (6 mg), providing a rapid exposure from the phosphate form and a
      sustained exposure from the acetate form. Maximal fetal serum level of betamethasone was
      attained 1-2 hours after ANC treatment (27). The half life of antenatally administered
      betamethasone is about 12 hours in fetal circulation (1,36). Decrease in the incidence of RDS
      is evident when ANC is administered between 24 hours and 7 days before delivery. However, the
      incidence of ICH is decreased even with treatment initiated less than 24 hours prior to
      delivery (2,3,4). According to the animal studies the short term ANC (&lt;24 hours) improves the
      postnatal lung function, decreases the protein leak into the lung and alters postnatal blood
      pressure regulation in the premature. ANC also seems to augment the postnatal neuroendocrine
      and endocrine responses to hypoxic challenge (28,29,30).

      According to meta-analysis there is no significant decrease in birthweight and in physical or
      psychological development at the age 3-12 years following a single course of ANC treatment of
      fetuses (2,18,19). According to follow-up studies, prenatal single course of steroid
      treatment is safe and enhanced survival is not associated with a higher incidence of
      disabilities or developmental disturbances in survivors during childhood and young adulthood
      (2,3,5,18,19,35). Single course of ANC treatment did not increase the risk of fetal or
      neonatal infections or the incidence of maternal infections (2). When administered during the
      subclinical chorioamnionitis, ANC treatment seem to decrease the incidence of RDS, ICH, PVL
      and neonatal mortality without apparent increase in neonatal sepsis (32).

      However, there is concern about possible negative effect of multiple course of ANC on
      birthweight, head circumference and growth later in childhood. Data from numerous animal
      studies suggest that ANC has a negative effect on pre- and postnatal growth. Most studies
      deal with rodents who have a short gestation and period of growth (10,11,12,37). In animal
      studies multidose ANC exposure has also decreased lung growth, which seems to be irreversible
      and persistent into adulthood (10,11,12). Also, in several animal studies ANC exposure has
      shown decreased brain growth and cell proliferation, which may also be due to short duration
      of gestation and long duration of exposure (10,11,12,37).

      There are concerns about potential suppressive effects of ANC on the fetal
      hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal axis. Transient suppression of the pituitary-adrenal glands in
      preterm infants whose mothers have received 1-2 doses of antenatal glucocorticoid, reportedly
      recovers within 7 days of life (23,24,25,26,36). Infants delivered shortly after one course
      of ANC are normally responsive to stress after birth (e.g. RDS and asphyxia).(36)

      Clinical practice administering antenatal corticosteroids varies greatly between individual
      centers during the late 1990’s. The practice of repeating the course of ANC has become
      widespread. However the safety or efficacy of serial courses of glucocorticoid is not known.
      According to recently published non-randomized studies there is conflicting data on growth
      and neonatal morbidity of infants exposed to single vs. multiple course of ANC (13,14,15).
      There is also concern particularly in women with prolonged premature rupture of fetal
      membranes (PPROM) that repetitive doses may increase maternal and fetal infections (21,22).
      In a retrospective study the multiple course of ANC was associated with an increased
      incidence of maternal postpartum infections (13).

      The effect of multiple courses of ANC on the HPA-axis is not well known. In recent studies a
      mild adrenal suppression was evident in some of the preterm infants whose mothers received
      more than eight courses of ANC (15). It has also been proposed that perinatal stress and
      exposure to corticosteroids induces long lasting changes in HPA-axis and is associated with a
      decrease in stress induced CRH release in adulthood (24,34). However, there is no existing
      data about function of HPA-axis in young adults, who have been exposed to antenatal
      corticosteroids during fetal life.

      There is insufficient data about optimal interval of ANC administration. According to recent
      studies there is not additive positive effects of the practice of repeating the course of ANC
      at 7 days intervals. However, it is known that the positive influence of the one course of
      ANC is not evident after 7 days of administration. It is interesting whether one additional
      rescue course of ANC given within 24 hours before premature delivery is more effective than
      single course of ANC. No prospective studies or randomized, controlled trials comparing
      single versus second rescue course of antenatal corticosteroids have been published.

      Specific aim and hypothesis

      The present aim is to study whether in recipients of ANC a single dose of betamethasone given
      shortly before spontaneous or elective premature birth (gestation 24 + 0 – 33 + 6 wk)
      improves the neonatal outcome without causing serious side effects. According to protocol,
      aim is to start the placebo or the second rescue course of ANC in 48 hours before expected
      delivery. The first hypothesis states that administration of second rescue course of ANC is
      more effective than the single course of ANC in increasing the intact survival at term of all
      infants without major neonatal morbidity, defined by the protocol. The principal outcome is
      survival of premature infants without major morbidity until the age of 36+0 weeks and
      survival of infants born at term during early neonatal period without the major morbidity, as
      defined by the protocol.

      Study design

      Present study is a multicenter, randomized, blinded, placebo-controlled trial comparing the
      benefits and side effects of single vs. second rescue course of antenatal corticosteroid.

      Entry criteria

      The pregnant women will be eligible for the trial entry if all following criteria are met:

        -  administration of a course of antenatal corticosteroid at least 7 days before the trial
           entry

        -  gestational age is less than 33.0 weeks 6 days*

        -  very high risk of premature delivery**

        -  none of the following therapies complications or therapies maternal long term systemic
           corticosteroid therapy severe clinical chorioamnionitis (maternal fever, increased CRP
           or another acute phase protein, uterine tenderness) lethal disease of the fetus

        -  informed consent obtained

        -  premature rupture of membranes is not contraindication for the trial entry

           *Gestational age will be calculated from the mother’s last menstrual period and
           confirmed by ultrasound before 20 weeks’ gestation. In case the discrepancy in the
           estimates exceeds two weeks, ultrasound date is accepted.

           **Very high risk of premature delivery is described as follows:

        -  elective delivery within within 4-48 hours, as indicated by the obstetrician on the
           basis of the clinical status of the mother and/or the fetus

        -  very high risk of spontaneous delivery within 4-48 hours, i.e.

        -  cervix is open &gt; 3 cm

        -  contractions of the uterus at 5-10 min intervals

        -  rupture of the membranes after the first course of ANC

        -  fetal and/or maternal indication for elective premature delivery or cesarean section

      Trial entry

      The investigator or his/her designated representative will evaluate the pregnant women for
      the above eligibility criteria. Administration of one course of antenatal glucocorticoid
      identifies the pregnant mothers that are potentially eligible to present study. Oral and
      written informed consent will be obtained from the women (if appropriate). The study entry
      (randomization and administration of the drug) takes place when all entry criteria are met.
      The parturient and her randomization number will be recorded on the trial data form and on
      patient records to enable later description of the women and to assist follow up. At the time
      of delivery the infants of the trial participants will be recorded to the trial data form and
      on patient records.

      Randomization

      The eligible women will be randomly and blindly assigned to receive either betamethasone or
      saline placebo. The randomization will take place separately in each Center according to the
      following strata:

      I gestation at entry less than 28.0 weeks + 0 days and singleton pregnancy

      II gestation at entry 28.0 weeks + 0 days or more but less than 33.0 weeks + 6 days and
      singleton pregnancy

      III gestation at entry less than 28.0 weeks + 0 days and multiple pregnancy

      IV gestation at entry 28.0 weeks + 0 days or more but less than 33.0 weeks + 6 days and
      multiple pregnancy

      Study intervention

      The first course of ANC prior to the trial entry will be given according to the clinical
      indications of the Center. Administration of further courses of ANC before the trial entry
      will disqualify the mother from the ACG trial. The study course of betamethasone or placebo
      will be given to each eligible woman at least 7 days after the first course of ANC. After the
      entry criteria are met betamethasone (12mg) or placebo (normal saline) will be drawn to a
      sealed syringe containing the randomization number. The drug or placebo is administered
      intramuscularly.

      Within 1 hour the betamethasone dose increases the fetal serum levels of glucocorticoid to
      those obtained during neonatal stress

      Other obstetric and neonatal management

      Other management given to the participating women will be decided by the obstetrician. After
      the entry to the trial administration of ANC outside study protocol is not allowed. In an
      event premature delivery did not occur after ACG, any further administration of ANC is not
      indicated. The premature infants are treated in whatever way their condition demands, the
      decision is made by pediatrician. The ACG trial infants born after 33.0 + 6 weeks of
      pregnancy are included in the neonatal and the follow-up studies.

      Fetuses that died after the trial entry will be recorded. The pathologic examination of these
      fetuses is strongly encouraged.

      Measurement of outcome

      Primary outcome of the trial:

      Term birth or survival of the infants at the gestational age of 36.0 weeks + 0 days without
      any of the following:

      RDS need of supplemental oxygen &gt; 48 h or surfactant therapy and characteristic radiographic
      findings

      Severe ICH (grades 3-4) infants born in term will be evaluated by ultrasound

      Maternal-antenatal outcomes:

      Clinical chorioamnionitis Any maternal infection Fetal death

      Secondary outcomes after birth:

      CLD requirement of supplemental oxygen at 36 weeks’ postmenstrual age PVL (gr 3-4) Severe NEC
      (Bell stages 3-4) perforation of the intestine intestinal pneumatosis air in portal vein ROP
      according to The International Classification of Retinopathy of Prematurity

      Neonatal infections early neonatal infections (onset &lt; 72 hours) proven nosocomial bacterial
      or fungal sepsis during neonatal period (days 3-28) Gastrointestinal bleeding or perforation
      Number of days on assisted ventilation Number of days on supplemental oxygen Duration of
      primary hospital stay Growth characteristics at birth

      Treatments requirements:

      surfactant postnatal steroids indomethacin for PDA PDA surgery

      Primary outcome at follow up study

      Survival without neurologic, sensory or neuromotor impairment at the age 2 years, corrected
      for gestation. All infants will be studied. For the high-risk group, the following indices
      and studies will be performed:

      Mental Development Index (MDI) (&lt;70) Psychomotor development will be measured by Bayley Scale
      (PDI) Behavioral development index (percentile) Definition of abnormalities in neurological
      status, speech development, major visual handicap and hearing defect

      Secondary outcomes during the follow-up:

      Growth characteristics during the first two years of corrected age Recurrent infections
      Reactive airway disease Hospital treatment during early childhood

      Data collection

      Information will be collected at the time of delivery, during the hospital stay and when the
      baby leaves the hospital or dies. Perinatal data will include prenatal history, assessment of
      entry criteria and following information of postnatal condition: blood pressure monitoring,
      assessment of growth at birth, day 28 and at 36 weeks gestational age (height, weight and
      head circumference). Cranial ultrasound will be made on all infants at least between days 4-8
      of life and at 36.0 w + 0 d (± 3 days) gestational age or before discharge. The worst grade
      of ICH and PVL will be reported. The first ophthalmologic examination for retinopathy of
      prematurity will be done 4 to 7 weeks after birth or at 32 weeks gestational age.

      Clinical status will be assessed at the time of discharge. The cause of death will be defined
      when possible at autopsy.

      The surviving children will be studied at two years of age (corrected for gestational age).
      Their growth and neurodevelopment will be evaluated using a questionnaire and a clinical
      evaluation.

      Sample size justification

      The primary goal of the study is to detect the effects of two vs. single course of ANC on
      survival without RDS and/or severe ICH (grade 3-4) by 36 weeks + 0 days of gestational age.

      Sample size analysis is based on morbidity and mortality from the Finnish perinatal
      statistics (National Research and Development Centre for Welfare and Health) and from Vermont
      Oxford Network Database (VON). We estimate that a second additional dose of betamethasone
      would increase the survival without RDS and severe ICH from 50% to 62.5%. According to power
      analysis the sample size of 220 women would be required in each arm to reject the null
      hypothesis with and α of 0.05 and power of 80%.

      The aim of the follow up study is to find out that one course of ANC result in equal or
      better neurodevelopmental outcome at the corrected age of two years, compared a single course
      of ANC.

      Statistical analysis

      Primary outcome

      Analysis of the primary outcomes will be based on an intention to treat analysis of all
      randomized subjects. Another analysis will be performed excluding infants who had congenital
      lethal malformation that was not detected at the onset. The outcome will be compared for the
      two vs. single course of ANC using the Mantel-Haenszel chi square test stratifying by the
      prenatal variables.

      Secondary outcomes

      The frequencies of categorical outcomes will be compared using appropriate chi square tests.
      The growth parameters, duration of ventilation, supplemental oxygen administration and
      hospitalization will be compared using analysis of variance or nonparametric tests when
      applicable. Survival rate will be compared using chi square tests and survival to term using
      survival analysis.

      Interim analysis

      The neonatal and the follow-up results for adverse outcomes will be prepared by the Data
      Safety Monitoring Committee when altogether 350 study infants have reached to the term or
      when the trial has been going on for 24 months, whichever comes first.

      Ethical considerations

      A written informed consent will be obtained from all the parents of the infants before the
      enrollment. The participation in the study does not cause any extra cost to the mother or the
      family. Participation is voluntary and withdrawing from the study is possible whenever
      desired during the pregnancy, the hospital stay or during the follow up period. Withdrawal
      does not affect the treatment or the follow up of the infant or the mother. If desired,
      approval from the ethical committees of each participating center will be obtained.

      Publication policy

      The perinatal-neonatal trial and the follow up study will be published separately. The list
      of authors includes Antenatal Multiple Betamethasone Trial Study Group (AMBTS). Each
      participant of the study from each Center will be listed. Each Center has an antenatal and a
      postnatal trial coordinator.

      Ancillary studies

      The participants are free to perform ancillary studies provided that a separate protocol,
      submitted together with the present one, is accepted by the local ethics committees.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2001</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intact survival without RDS and/or severe (gr 3-4) ICH</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow-up study at corrected age of two years</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A number of diseases in preterm infants</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of mothers with premature delivery</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>440</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Distress Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Intraventricular Haemorrhage</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Betamethasone sodium phos (drug)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The pregnant women will be eligible for the trial entry if all following criteria are met:

          -  administration of a course of antenatal corticosteroid at least 7 days before the
             trial entry

          -  gestational age is less than 33.0 weeks 6 days*

          -  very high risk of premature delivery**

          -  none of the following therapies complications or therapies maternal long term systemic
             corticosteroid therapy severe clinical chorioamnionitis (maternal fever, increased CRP
             or another acute phase protein, uterine tenderness) lethal disease of the fetus

          -  informed consent obtained

          -  premature rupture of membranes is not contraindication for the trial entry

             *Gestational age will be calculated from the mother’s last menstrual period and
             confirmed by ultrasound before 20 weeks’ gestation. In case the discrepancy in the
             estimates exceeds two weeks, ultrasound date is accepted.

             **Very high risk of premature delivery is described as follows:

          -  elective delivery within within 4-48 hours, as indicated by the obstetrician on the
             basis of the clinical status of the mother and/or the fetus

          -  very high risk of spontaneous delivery within 4-48 hours, i.e.

          -  cervix is open &gt; 3 cm

          -  contractions of the uterus at 5-10 min intervals

          -  rupture of the membranes after the first course of ANC

          -  fetal and/or maternal indication for elective premature delivery or cesarean section
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mikko N Hallman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital, Univ. of Oulu</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Outi M Peltoniemi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital, Univ. of Oulu</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pentti Jouppila, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Oulu Central Hospital, Dept. of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Helsinki University Central Hospital, Finland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00029 HUS</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Joensuu Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Joensuu</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jyväskylä Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jyväskylä</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kuopio University Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuopio</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lahti Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lahti</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oulu University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oulu</city>
        <zip>90029 OYS</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Hospital of Pori</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pori</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seinäjoki Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seinäjoki</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tampere University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampere</city>
        <zip>33521</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Turku Central Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Turku</city>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 21, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Antenatal glucocorticoid</keyword>
  <keyword>Premature birth</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glucocorticoids</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Betamethasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

