<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00299312</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RDCRN 5201</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U54HD061222</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ARP 5201</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00299312</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic and Physical Characteristics of Rett Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Rett Syndrome Natural History: Genetic and Physical Characteristics of Rett Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Greenwood Genetic Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Rochester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rush University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital &amp; Research Center Oakland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of South Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rett Syndrome (RTT) is a genetic brain disorder that occurs almost exclusively in females and
      is usually caused by a change (mutation) in the gene MECP2. The disorder is characterized by
      multiple developmental problems, as well as behavioral features, such as repetitive
      stereotypic hand movements, including hand washing, wringing, and tapping. While there is no
      cure for RTT, recent advances in the understanding of the disease suggest that the
      development of new, effective therapies is promising. This study will gather information on
      the genetic defects that cause RTT, the physical expressions of these defects, and disease
      progression. In turn, this may direct the development of future treatments. Expanded studies
      include individuals with MECP2 Duplication disorder, and RTT-related disorders including
      individuals with MECP2 mutations, but not meeting obligatory criteria for the diagnosis of
      RTT and individuals with mutations in CDKL5 and FOXG1 some of whom meet criteria for atypical
      RTT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RTT is a brain disorder that causes problems with childhood development. It is usually caused
      by an abnormality (mutation) in the gene MECP2. RTT can cause severe impairments in movement
      and communication skills, including speech and social interaction. The first signs of RTT
      include loss of acquired speech and loss of purposeful hand use for activities such as eating
      or playing. Individuals may also develop abnormal walking, repetitive hand movements, such as
      clapping or wringing, and abnormal breathing while awake.

      Effective treatments for RTT are currently lacking. There is also inadequate information
      about the link between RTT clinical features and its genetic basis. In order to prepare for
      future clinical trials that may lead to effective therapies, it is important to collect
      accurate information about the characteristics of RTT and the pattern of disease progression.
      This study will gather historical and physical examination data to establish
      phenotype-genotype correlations. Data on survival and quality of life in females with RTT and
      males with MECP2 gene mutations will also be evaluated.

      MECP2 Duplication disorder affects principally males who have one and rarely more than one
      additional copy of MECP2 as well as a variable number of other duplicated genes. These males
      have absent spoken language, shuffling gait, epilepsy, and, in some, frequent upper
      respiratory infections or sinusitis. Mother of these males are generally normal due to
      favorable skewing of X-chromosome inactivation, but in some instances may have
      neurodevelop-mental delays. Effective treatments are lacking. It is critical to develop
      phenotype-genotype correlations and longitudinal natural history data to assist the conduct
      of clinical trials.

      RTT-related disorders feature a variety of involvements either due to MECP2, CDKL5, and FOXG1
      as well as other potential causes of atypical RTT. Phenotype-genotype studies and
      longitudinal natural history data are essential to the conduct of future clinical trials.

      Participants in this observational study will be recruited from the four sites at which the
      study is being conducted, as well as through the Rare Disease Clinical Research Network and
      the International Rett Syndrome Association (IRSA). Prior to study entry, potential
      participants are expected to be tested for a mutation in the MECP2 gene. No treatment will be
      administered at any time during this study. Study visits will occur every 6 months until the
      child is 6 years old and once a year thereafter. At each study visit, participants will be
      examined to assess physical characteristics of the disorder, such as motor behavior and
      disease severity. Additionally, participants will complete questionnaires about medical
      history, contact information, and quality of life. The first visit will last approximately
      1.5 hours, and every subsequent visit will last approximately 1 hour.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic and Physical Characteristics of Rett Syndrome</measure>
    <time_frame>July 31, 2019</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is to determine the variables related to clinical outcome in terms of genotype and phenotype. The variables include growth, head circumference, stereotypic movements, periodic breathing, epilepsy, scoliosis, and longevity. Summative data are provided by the Clinical Severity Scale (CSS) and the Motor Behavioral Assessment (MBA) and specific neurophysiologic and neuroimaging studies in selected participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic and Physical Characteristics of Rett syndrome</measure>
    <time_frame>Through July 31, 2019</time_frame>
    <description>The principal secondary outcome measures include quality of life assessments of the participants (CHQ) and the principal caregiver (SF-36).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic and Physical Characteristics of Rett Syndrome, MECP2 Duplication disorder, and RTT-related conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>July 31, 2019</time_frame>
    <description>No other pre-specified outcome measures are planned</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Rett Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>MECP2 Duplication Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Rett-related Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals fulfilling consensus clinical criteria for Classic or Variant Rett Syndrome,
        individuals with MECP2 mutations who do not meet the clinical criteria, or individuals who
        have a duplication of Xq28 including the MECP2 locus or individuals who have mutations in
        CDKL5 or FOXG1.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Meets clinical criteria for classic or variant RTT or tests positive for an MECP2 gene
             mutation or a MECP2 duplication or a mutation in CDKL5 or FOXG1.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unwilling or unable to travel to study sites for annual or biannual evaluations
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alan K Percy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Oakland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94709</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92123</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045-2571</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14627-0140</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104-4318</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greenwood Genetic Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenwood</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29646</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.rettsyndrome.org/</url>
    <description>Click here for the International Rett Syndrome Foundation website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laccone F, Jünemann I, Whatley S, Morgan R, Butler R, Huppke P, Ravine D. Large deletions of the MECP2 gene detected by gene dosage analysis in patients with Rett syndrome. Hum Mutat. 2004 Mar;23(3):234-44. Erratum in: Hum Mutat. 2004 Apr;23(4):395.</citation>
    <PMID>14974082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schanen C, Houwink EJ, Dorrani N, Lane J, Everett R, Feng A, Cantor RM, Percy A. Phenotypic manifestations of MECP2 mutations in classical and atypical Rett syndrome. Am J Med Genet A. 2004 Apr 15;126A(2):129-40.</citation>
    <PMID>15057977</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neul JL, Fang P, Barrish J, Lane J, Caeg EB, Smith EO, Zoghbi H, Percy A, Glaze DG. Specific mutations in methyl-CpG-binding protein 2 confer different severity in Rett syndrome. Neurology. 2008 Apr 15;70(16):1313-21. doi: 10.1212/01.wnl.0000291011.54508.aa. Epub 2008 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>18337588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bebbington A, Anderson A, Ravine D, Fyfe S, Pineda M, de Klerk N, Ben-Zeev B, Yatawara N, Percy A, Kaufmann WE, Leonard H. Investigating genotype-phenotype relationships in Rett syndrome using an international data set. Neurology. 2008 Mar 11;70(11):868-75. doi: 10.1212/01.wnl.0000304752.50773.ec.</citation>
    <PMID>18332345</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalman LV, Tarleton JC, Percy AK, Aradhya S, Bale S, Barker SD, Bayrak-Toydemir P, Bridges C, Buller-Burckle AM, Das S, Iyer RK, Vo TD, Zvereff VV, Toji LH. Development of a genomic DNA reference material panel for Rett syndrome (MECP2-related disorders) genetic testing. J Mol Diagn. 2014 Mar;16(2):273-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jmoldx.2013.11.004. Epub 2014 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>24508304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leonard H, Ravikumara M, Baikie G, Naseem N, Ellaway C, Percy A, Abraham S, Geerts S, Lane J, Jones M, Bathgate K, Downs J; Telethon Institute for Child Health Research. Assessment and management of nutrition and growth in Rett syndrome. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2013 Oct;57(4):451-60. doi: 10.1097/MPG.0b013e31829e0b65.</citation>
    <PMID>24084372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Percy AK. Rett syndrome: exploring the autism link. Arch Neurol. 2011 Aug;68(8):985-9. doi: 10.1001/archneurol.2011.149. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21825235</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Percy A. The American history of Rett syndrome. Pediatr Neurol. 2014 Jan;50(1):1-3. doi: 10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2013.08.018. Epub 2013 Nov 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24200039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neul JL, Glaze DG, Percy AK, Feyma T, Beisang A, Dinh T, Suter B, Anagnostou E, Snape M, Horrigan J, Jones NE. Improving Treatment Trial Outcomes for Rett Syndrome: The Development of Rett-specific Anchors for the Clinical Global Impression Scale. J Child Neurol. 2015 Nov;30(13):1743-8. doi: 10.1177/0883073815579707. Epub 2015 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25895911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Neul JL, Kaufmann WE, Glaze DG, Christodoulou J, Clarke AJ, Bahi-Buisson N, Leonard H, Bailey ME, Schanen NC, Zappella M, Renieri A, Huppke P, Percy AK; RettSearch Consortium. Rett syndrome: revised diagnostic criteria and nomenclature. Ann Neurol. 2010 Dec;68(6):944-50. doi: 10.1002/ana.22124.</citation>
    <PMID>21154482</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Percy AK, Neul JL, Glaze DG, Motil KJ, Skinner SA, Khwaja O, Lee HS, Lane JB, Barrish JO, Annese F, McNair L, Graham J, Barnes K. Rett syndrome diagnostic criteria: lessons from the Natural History Study. Ann Neurol. 2010 Dec;68(6):951-5. doi: 10.1002/ana.22154.</citation>
    <PMID>21104896</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Percy AK, Lee HS, Neul JL, Lane JB, Skinner SA, Geerts SP, Annese F, Graham J, McNair L, Motil KJ, Barrish JO, Glaze DG. Profiling scoliosis in Rett syndrome. Pediatr Res. 2010 Apr;67(4):435-9. doi: 10.1203/PDR.0b013e3181d0187f.</citation>
    <PMID>20032810</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Glaze DG, Percy AK, Skinner S, Motil KJ, Neul JL, Barrish JO, Lane JB, Geerts SP, Annese F, Graham J, McNair L, Lee HS. Epilepsy and the natural history of Rett syndrome. Neurology. 2010 Mar 16;74(11):909-12. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181d6b852.</citation>
    <PMID>20231667</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kirby RS, Lane JB, Childers J, Skinner SA, Annese F, Barrish JO, Glaze DG, Macleod P, Percy AK. Longevity in Rett syndrome: analysis of the North American Database. J Pediatr. 2010 Jan;156(1):135-138.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2009.07.015.</citation>
    <PMID>19772971</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>McCauley MD, Wang T, Mike E, Herrera J, Beavers DL, Huang TW, Ward CS, Skinner S, Percy AK, Glaze DG, Wehrens XH, Neul JL. Pathogenesis of lethal cardiac arrhythmias in Mecp2 mutant mice: implication for therapy in Rett syndrome. Sci Transl Med. 2011 Dec 14;3(113):113ra125. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3002982.</citation>
    <PMID>22174313</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Motil KJ, Caeg E, Barrish JO, Geerts S, Lane JB, Percy AK, Annese F, McNair L, Skinner SA, Lee HS, Neul JL, Glaze DG. Gastrointestinal and nutritional problems occur frequently throughout life in girls and women with Rett syndrome. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2012 Sep;55(3):292-8. doi: 10.1097/MPG.0b013e31824b6159.</citation>
    <PMID>22331013</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bebbington A, Downs J, Percy A, Pineda M, Zeev BB, Bahi-Buisson N, Leonard H. The phenotype associated with a large deletion on MECP2. Eur J Hum Genet. 2012 Sep;20(9):921-7. doi: 10.1038/ejhg.2012.34. Epub 2012 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22473088</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bebbington A, Percy A, Christodoulou J, Ravine D, Ho G, Jacoby P, Anderson A, Pineda M, Ben Zeev B, Bahi-Buisson N, Smeets E, Leonard H. Updating the profile of C-terminal MECP2 deletions in Rett syndrome. J Med Genet. 2010 Apr;47(4):242-8. doi: 10.1136/jmg.2009.072553. Epub 2009 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19914908</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tarquinio DC, Motil KJ, Hou W, Lee HS, Glaze DG, Skinner SA, Neul JL, Annese F, McNair L, Barrish JO, Geerts SP, Lane JB, Percy AK. Growth failure and outcome in Rett syndrome: specific growth references. Neurology. 2012 Oct 16;79(16):1653-61. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e31826e9a70. Epub 2012 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>23035069</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Motil KJ, Barrish JO, Lane J, Geerts SP, Annese F, McNair L, Percy AK, Skinner SA, Neul JL, Glaze DG. Vitamin D deficiency is prevalent in girls and women with Rett syndrome. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2011 Nov;53(5):569-74. doi: 10.1097/MPG.0b013e3182267a66.</citation>
    <PMID>21637127</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lane JB, Lee HS, Smith LW, Cheng P, Percy AK, Glaze DG, Neul JL, Motil KJ, Barrish JO, Skinner SA, Annese F, McNair L, Graham J, Khwaja O, Barnes K, Krischer JP. Clinical severity and quality of life in children and adolescents with Rett syndrome. Neurology. 2011 Nov 15;77(20):1812-8. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3182377dd2. Epub 2011 Oct 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22013176</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chapleau CA, Lane J, Kirwin SM, Schanen C, Vinette KM, Stubbolo D, MacLeod P, Glaze DG, Motil KJ, Neul JL, Skinner SA, Kaufmann WE, Percy AK. Detection of rarely identified multiple mutations in MECP2 gene do not contribute to enhanced severity in Rett syndrome. Am J Med Genet A. 2013 Jul;161A(7):1638-46. doi: 10.1002/ajmg.a.35979. Epub 2013 May 21. Erratum in: Am J Med Genet A. 2014 May;164A(5):1346. Glaze, Daniel G [added]; Motil, Kathleen J [added]; Neul, Jeffrey L [added]; Skinner, Steven A [added]; Kaufmann, Walter E [added].</citation>
    <PMID>23696494</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cuddapah VA, Pillai RB, Shekar KV, Lane JB, Motil KJ, Skinner SA, Tarquinio DC, Glaze DG, McGwin G, Kaufmann WE, Percy AK, Neul JL, Olsen ML. Methyl-CpG-binding protein 2 (MECP2) mutation type is associated with disease severity in Rett syndrome. J Med Genet. 2014 Mar;51(3):152-8. doi: 10.1136/jmedgenet-2013-102113. Epub 2014 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>24399845</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Neul JL, Lane JB, Lee HS, Geerts S, Barrish JO, Annese F, Baggett LM, Barnes K, Skinner SA, Motil KJ, Glaze DG, Kaufmann WE, Percy AK. Developmental delay in Rett syndrome: data from the natural history study. J Neurodev Disord. 2014;6(1):20. doi: 10.1186/1866-1955-6-20. Epub 2014 Jul 22.</citation>
    <PMID>25071871</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Killian JT, Lane JB, Cutter GR, Skinner SA, Kaufmann WE, Tarquinio DC, Glaze DG, Motil KJ, Neul JL, Percy AK. Pubertal development in Rett syndrome deviates from typical females. Pediatr Neurol. 2014 Dec;51(6):769-75. doi: 10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2014.08.013. Epub 2014 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>25283752</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tarquinio DC, Hou W, Neul JL, Lane JB, Barnes KV, O'Leary HM, Bruck NM, Kaufmann WE, Motil KJ, Glaze DG, Skinner SA, Annese F, Baggett L, Barrish JO, Geerts SP, Percy AK. Age of diagnosis in Rett syndrome: patterns of recognition among diagnosticians and risk factors for late diagnosis. Pediatr Neurol. 2015 Jun;52(6):585-91.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2015.02.007. Epub 2015 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25801175</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 3, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 6, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alan Percy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Pediatrics, Neurolgy, Neurobiology, Genetics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Loss of Purposeful Hand Use Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Loss of Communication</keyword>
  <keyword>Stereotypic Hand Movements</keyword>
  <keyword>MECP2 mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>MECP2 duplication</keyword>
  <keyword>CDKL5 mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>FOXG1 mutation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rett Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

