<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00299663</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GAS-HMO-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00299663</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Long Term Follow-up of Patients With Group A Streptococcal Infection Originating From the Genital Tract</brief_title>
  <official_title>Long Term Follow-up of Patients With Group A Streptococcal Infection Originating From the Genital Tract</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Group A streptococcus (GAS) causes a variety of human infections. It is also an uncommon but
      serious cause of postpartum infections. In contrast to group B streptococcus (GBS) infection,
      which causes illness and death in newborns disproportionately more often than it does in
      mothers, perinatal GAS infection primarily affects mothers . Invasive GAS infection is
      defined by the isolation of GAS from a normally sterile site (e.g., blood) or by the
      isolation of GAS from a nonsterile site in the presence of the streptococcal toxic shock
      syndrome or necrotizing fasciitis. A postpartum case of invasive GAS is defined as isolation
      of GAS during the postpartum period, in association with a clinical postpartum infection
      (e.g., endometritis) or from either a sterile site or a wound infection.

      Because of the burden and severity of invasive GAS infection, the Centers for Disease Control
      and Prevention (CDC) hosted a meeting in to formulate guidelines for responding to postpartum
      and postsurgical GAS infections. However, we could not find any recommendations for long-term
      follow-up of patients who had GAS infection subsequent to delivery or gynaecological
      procedures, or further recommendations regarding subsequent delivery or gynaecological
      invasive procedures. It is possible that women who had GAS as a cause of vaginal infection
      may have a tendency to be carriers of this organism, but this has never been proven. We
      believe it is of importance to determine if women who have had one infection may be long-term
      carriers which may pose a risk during future pregnancies.

      The objective of the present study is to evaluate the incidence of long term gynaecological
      carrier state of patients who had GAS invasive infection following delivery, and to provide
      guidelines for follow-up and treatment of such patients.

      The proposed study may answer the question whether this endogenous GAS origin represents
      chronic GAS carrier state, similar to the known GBS carrier state. As some of these patients
      had severe infections (sometimes life threatening) a protocol for long-term follow up and
      management is necessary in case an invasive procedure is done (IUD insertion, endometrial
      biopsy, curettage or delivery) in order to prevent recurrent infection. The information
      collected in the study will enable us to afford recommendations for follow up and prophylaxis
      in the future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research plan The study population will include patients diagnosed with GAS invasive
      infection following delivery or gynaecological procedures (such as endometrial biopsy, D&amp;C or
      IUD insertion) at Hadassah university hospitals, and patients in whom an isolation of GAS
      from the vagina without infection was reported. The study will consist of two parts,
      prospective and retrospective.

        1. Retrospective study

             1. The records of all patients diagnosed with GAS infection/isolation in the past 3
                years (2003-2005) will be reviewed. The estimated occurrence of GAS isolation from
                the genital tract in Hadassah hospital is 15 cases every year (Moses personal
                communication).

             2. Patients' files will be reviewed for demographic and clinical variables associated
                with the development of GAS infection (age, parity, obstetric history), its
                clinical course and subsequent progress to septic shock, and the site of GAS
                isolation (blood, vaginal discharge, wound etc).

             3. Additional information will be obtained from the patients in order to evaluate the
                incidence of gynaecological infections and risk factors for such infections. These
                include events of pelvic inflammatory disease, contraceptive methods, subsequent
                deliveries or D&amp;C (a questionnaire is attached).

             4. Vaginal cultures and pharyngeal swabs will be taken from all women with previous
                gynecological GAS infection/isolation participating in the study, in order to
                evaluate whether carriage of GAS in the vagina occurs.

        2. emm typing Since we have the original isolates from women with invasive disease (those
           presenting with bacteremia) we will be able to compare the specific type isolate
           obtained in consequent cultures with the original isolate. Isolates will be compared by
           several known bacterial attributes such as emm type, T type, and the presence of genes
           for the different exotoxins. emm typing PCR of streptococcal isolates will be performed
           as previously described [11], according to the recommendations of the Division of
           Bacterial and Mycotic Diseases, Streptococcus pyogenes emm sequence database
           (http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/biotech/strep/doc.htm).

        3. Prospective study- In addition to the above patients, women presenting from the
           beginning of the study for two years, with an isolation of GAS from the vagina (even
           without overt disease), will be followed in order to evaluate the significance of such
           isolates. These isolates will be collected for comparison with surveillance cultures
           which will be taken in the future. Vaginal cultures and pharyngeal swabs will be taken
           every 2 months during the year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">61</enrollment>
  <condition>Streptococcal Infections</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The population that participate in the study are women who were udentified with positive
        culture of group A streptoccoci in the genital tracts, starting from 2003 and on.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with GAS infection/isolation in the past 3 years (2003-2005)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>ALLON MOSES</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah Medical Organization</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>1. Chuang I, Van Beneden C, Beall B, Schuchat A. Population-based surveillance for postpartum invasive group a streptococcus infections, 1995-2000. Clin Infect Dis. 2002:15;35:665-70. 2. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Active bacterial core surveillance (ABCs) report: group A Streptococcus, 2000. 3. The Working Group on Severe Streptococcal Infections. Defining the group A streptococcal toxic shock syndrome. Rationale and consensus definition. JAMA 1993; 269:390 1. 4. Stevens DL, Tanner MH, Winship J, et al. Severe group A streptococcal infections associated with a toxic shock like syndrome and scarlet fever toxin A. N Engl J Med 1989; 321:1 7. 5. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Case definitions for infectious conditions under public health surveillance. MMWR Recomm Rep 1997;46(RR-10):1 55. 6. Prevention of Invasive Group A Streptococcal Infections Workshop Participants .Prevention of invasive group A streptococcal disease among household contacts of case patients and among postpartum and postsurgical patients: recommendations from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Clin Infect Dis. 2003 15;36:243.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 7, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 18, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Ahinoam Lev-Sagie, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Hadassah Medical Organization</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>group A streptococcal infection</keyword>
  <keyword>genital tract</keyword>
  <keyword>CARRIER</keyword>
  <keyword>patients with GAS isolation</keyword>
  <keyword>Streptococcus Group A</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Streptococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

