<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03421834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PREVENTIVE VT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03421834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of PREVENTIVE Substrate Ablation of Coronary Chronic Total Occlusion on Implantable cardioVerTer-Defibrillator Interventions</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREVENTIVE VT</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of PREVENTIVE Substrate Catheter Ablation on Implantable cardioVerter-defibrillaTor Interventions in Patients With Ischaemic Cardiomyopathy and Infarct-related Coronary Chronic Total Occlusion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to assess whether preventive substrate ablation of chronic total
      occlusion infarct-related artery (CTO-IRA) area in heart failure (HF) patients correlates
      with lower appropriate implantable cardiac defibrillator (ICD) therapies. In addition, the
      purpose of the study is to determine whether prophylactic substrate ablation at the time of
      primary ICD implantation in high-risk ischemic patients affects unplanned hospitalization, HF
      progression, and quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Implantable cardioverter-defibrillators (ICDs) improve survival among patients with ischemic
      heart failure (HF) who have not previously had a sustained ventricular arrhythmia. However,
      ICD shocks that terminate ventricular tachycardia (VT) are associated with higher mortality,
      which may be a reflection of ICD shocks being a marker of more advanced disease versus shocks
      causing a worse prognosis. In addition, ICD shocks are associated with decreased functional
      status and quality of life. Antiarrhythmic medications (AAD) reduce ICD shocks but have high
      rates of side effects and lack of compliance within 1 year of initiation. Some randomized,
      controlled clinical trials have shown that catheter ablation (CA) of VT can decrease the
      number of episodes of VT and ICD shocks which could translate to an improvement in patient
      outcomes.

      Regarding the approach to CA of VT, several controversies and gaps of knowledge can be found
      in the literature. Some authors target predominantly &quot;clinical VTs&quot; (activation and
      entrainment mapping), while others focus on the substrate causing VTs without focusing on VT
      morphologies (elimination of local abnormal ventricular activities and late potentials). In
      addition, data on timing of the CA procedure is inconsistent. However, early CA strategy
      seems feasible as end-stage cardiovascular disease increases procedural risk and is
      associated with arrhythmias that may be less amenable to successful treatment with ablation.

      The current focus on risk stratifying patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy who could benefit
      from a primary prevention ICD solely on basis of ejection fraction and NYHA class is far from
      ideal. In patients with ischemic HF, the presence of the coronary chronic total occlusion
      (CTO) is related to worse long-term prognosis. Moreover, in a subgroup of ischemic patients,
      CTO associated with a previous infarction in its territory was an independent predictor of
      ventricular arrhythmias. Recent studies reported that primary prevention patients with CTO of
      an infarct-related artery (CTO-IRA) have a very high risk of appropriate ICD therapies due to
      fast VTs. As post-myocardial infarction scar is a well-recognized substrate of VTs, these
      patients might benefit from prophylactic substrate ablation at the time of primary ICD
      implantation.

      Eligible and consenting patients on optimal medical HF treatment with confirmed CTO-IRA will
      be equally randomized to receive either a primary prevention ICD or a CA procedure and an
      ICD. Catheter ablation with a uniform procedural endpoint and definition of acute procedural
      success was to be performed before ICD implantation. ICD programming will be standardized for
      all subjects according to primary prevention settings.

      Subjects will be seen at baseline randomization, then 1 month after ICD implantation and
      every 6 months thereafter until the end of the study. Subjects will be followed up for a
      minimum of 24 months. Quality of life questionnaires will be done at each visit.

      The aim of this study is to assess whether preventive substrate ablation of CTO-IRA area in
      HF patients correlates with lower appropriate ICD therapies. In addition, the purpose of the
      study is to determine whether prophylactic substrate ablation at the time of primary ICD
      implantation in high-risk ischemic patients affects unplanned hospitalization, HF
      progression, and quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first event comprising appropriate ICD therapy and unplanned hospital admission for symptomatic ventricular tachycardia (VT)/ ventricular fibrillation (VF)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization until official study end or drop-out, patients will be followed and assessed at least 24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Appropriate ICD therapy defined as shock or ATP therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to appropriate ICD therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 24 months after enrolment</time_frame>
    <description>Appropriate ICD therapy defined as shock or ATP therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of appropriate ICD therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 24 months after enrolment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to unplanned hospital admission for symptomatic ventricular tachycardia (VT)/ ventricular fibrillation (VF)</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 24 months after enrolment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to unplanned cardiac hospital admission</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 24 months after enrolment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to electrical storm</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 24 months after enrolment</time_frame>
    <description>Electrical storm defined by 3 or more sustained episodes of ventricular tachycardia (VT), ventricular fibrillation (VF), or appropriate ICD therapy within 24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardio-vascular mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 24 months after enrolment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality of life using the EQ-5D questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 24 months after enrolment</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D is a standardised measure of health status consisting of 2 pages - the EQ-5D descriptive system (descriptive system with 3 levels) and the EQ visual analogue scale ranging from 0 (worst state) to 100 (best state).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychometric evaluation of ICD shock-related anxiety using The Florida Shock Anxiety Scale (FSAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At least 24 months after enrolment</time_frame>
    <description>Questions were designed to capture patient opinion on perceptions of current health status, as well as a subjective opinion of how the ICD has affected them in specific areas, including anxiety levels. A higher score indicates an positive response and a lower score indicates a negative response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Ventricular Tachycardia</condition>
  <condition>Ischemic Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylactic VT ablation prior to ICD implantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ICD implantation and optimal medical treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>ICD implantation and optimal medical care until at least 2 appropriate ICD shock occurs or an arrhythmic storm and catheter ablation thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Catheter ablation of ventricular tachycardia</intervention_name>
    <description>Catheter ablation with a uniform mapping system, procedural endpoint, and definition of acute procedural success.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylactic VT ablation prior to ICD implantation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Optimal medical treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Optimal guidelines-based heart failure treatment and antiarrhythmic drugs. Antiarrhythmics will be avoided if possible in the ablation group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylactic VT ablation prior to ICD implantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ICD implantation and optimal medical treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Ischemic cardiomyopathy with reduced ejection fraction (EF ≤ 40%) estimated by cardiac
             MRI or echocardiography within 30 days before enrollment

          2. Coronary Chronic Total Occlusion (CTO) associated with a previous MI confirmed by
             coronary angiography and late gadolinium enhancement MRI or myocardial perfusion
             imaging within 30 days before enrollment

          3. Implantable cardioverter-defibrillator (ICD) indication for primary prevention

          4. Patient has provided written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt; 18 years or &gt; 85 years

          2. Documented sustained ventricular tachycardia before enrollment

          3. Class IV New York Heart Association (NYHA) heart failure

          4. CTOs not associated with a prior infarction in their territory

          5. Acute myocardial infarction (MI) or acute coronary syndrome

          6. Subjects with active ischemia that are eligible for revascularization

          7. Documented history of MI less than 6 months before enrollment

          8. Patients requiring chronic renal dialysis

          9. Thrombocytopenia or coagulopathy

         10. Pre-existing implantable cardioverter-defibrillator (ICD)

         11. Pregnancy or breastfeeding women

         12. Acute illness or active systemic infection

         13. Life expectancy less than 12 months

         14. Unwillingness to participate or lack of availability for follow-up

         15. Valvular heart disease or mechanical heart valve precluding access to the left
             ventricle
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matjaz Sinkovec, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Centre Ljubljana (Slovenia)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrej Pernat, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Centre Ljubljana (Slovenia)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Zizek, Assist. Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Centre Ljubljana (Slovenia)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Zizek, Assist. Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+38615228534</phone>
    <email>davidzizek@yahoo.com, david.zizek@kclj.si</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Luka Klemen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+38615228528</phone>
    <email>luka.klemen@kclj.si</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General Hospital Celje</name>
      <address>
        <city>Celje</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rafael Skale, MD</last_name>
      <email>skaler59@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General Hospital Izola</name>
      <address>
        <city>Izola</city>
        <zip>6310</zip>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jurij Avramovic-Gregoric, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Centre Ljubljana - Cardiology department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ljubljana</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Zizek, Assist. Prof.</last_name>
      <email>david.zizek@kclj.si</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Luka Klemen, MD</last_name>
      <email>luka.klemen@kclj.si</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Centre Ljubljana - Cardiovascular surgery department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ljubljana</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matevz Jan, MD</last_name>
      <email>matevz.jan@kclj.si</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Slovenia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ponikowski P, Voors AA, Anker SD, Bueno H, Cleland JGF, Coats AJS, Falk V, González-Juanatey JR, Harjola VP, Jankowska EA, Jessup M, Linde C, Nihoyannopoulos P, Parissis JT, Pieske B, Riley JP, Rosano GMC, Ruilope LM, Ruschitzka F, Rutten FH, van der Meer P; ESC Scientific Document Group . 2016 ESC Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure: The Task Force for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC)Developed with the special contribution of the Heart Failure Association (HFA) of the ESC. Eur Heart J. 2016 Jul 14;37(27):2129-2200. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehw128. Epub 2016 May 20. Erratum in: Eur Heart J. 2016 Dec 30;:.</citation>
    <PMID>27206819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poole JE, Johnson GW, Hellkamp AS, Anderson J, Callans DJ, Raitt MH, Reddy RK, Marchlinski FE, Yee R, Guarnieri T, Talajic M, Wilber DJ, Fishbein DP, Packer DL, Mark DB, Lee KL, Bardy GH. Prognostic importance of defibrillator shocks in patients with heart failure. N Engl J Med. 2008 Sep 4;359(10):1009-17. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa071098.</citation>
    <PMID>18768944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reddy VY, Reynolds MR, Neuzil P, Richardson AW, Taborsky M, Jongnarangsin K, Kralovec S, Sediva L, Ruskin JN, Josephson ME. Prophylactic catheter ablation for the prevention of defibrillator therapy. N Engl J Med. 2007 Dec 27;357(26):2657-65.</citation>
    <PMID>18160685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dinov B, Arya A, Bertagnolli L, Schirripa V, Schoene K, Sommer P, Bollmann A, Rolf S, Hindricks G. Early referral for ablation of scar-related ventricular tachycardia is associated with improved acute and long-term outcomes: results from the Heart Center of Leipzig ventricular tachycardia registry. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2014 Dec;7(6):1144-51. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.114.001953. Epub 2014 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>25262159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Biase L, Burkhardt JD, Lakkireddy D, Carbucicchio C, Mohanty S, Mohanty P, Trivedi C, Santangeli P, Bai R, Forleo G, Horton R, Bailey S, Sanchez J, Al-Ahmad A, Hranitzky P, Gallinghouse GJ, Pelargonio G, Hongo RH, Beheiry S, Hao SC, Reddy M, Rossillo A, Themistoclakis S, Dello Russo A, Casella M, Tondo C, Natale A. Ablation of Stable VTs Versus Substrate Ablation in Ischemic Cardiomyopathy: The VISTA Randomized Multicenter Trial. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2015 Dec 29;66(25):2872-2882. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2015.10.026.</citation>
    <PMID>26718674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nombela-Franco L, Mitroi CD, Fernández-Lozano I, García-Touchard A, Toquero J, Castro-Urda V, Fernández-Diaz JA, Perez-Pereira E, Beltrán-Correas P, Segovia J, Werner GS, Javier G, Luis AP. Ventricular arrhythmias among implantable cardioverter-defibrillator recipients for primary prevention: impact of chronic total coronary occlusion (VACTO Primary Study). Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2012 Feb;5(1):147-54. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.111.968008. Epub 2011 Dec 28.</citation>
    <PMID>22205684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Marco A, Anguera I, Teruel L, Dallaglio P, González-Costello J, León V, Nuñez E, Manito N, Gómez-Hospital JA, Sabaté X, Cequier Á. Chronic total occlusion of an infarct-related artery: a new predictor of ventricular arrhythmias in primary prevention implantable cardioverter defibrillator patients. Europace. 2017 Feb 1;19(2):267-274. doi: 10.1093/europace/euw009.</citation>
    <PMID>28175266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Marco A, Anguera I, Teruel L, Muntane G, Campbell NG, Fox DJ, Brown B, Skene C, Davidson N, Leon V, Dallaglio P, Elzein H, Garcia-Romero E, Gomez-Hospital JA, Cequier A. Chronic total occlusion in an infarct-related coronary artery and the risk of appropriate ICD therapies. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2017 Oct;28(10):1169-1178. doi: 10.1111/jce.13290. Epub 2017 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>28675508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Žižek, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ventricular Tachycardia</keyword>
  <keyword>Ischemic Cardiomyopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Failure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia, Ventricular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

