<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03426293</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>M016-045</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03426293</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Measuring the ACT During Non-cardiac Arterial Procedures.</brief_title>
  <acronym>MANCO</acronym>
  <official_title>MANCO: Measuring the ACT During Non-cardiac Arterial Procedures.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Westfriesgasthuis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medtronic</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Westfriesgasthuis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim of the MANCO study is to establish for once and for all that monitoring the effect of
      heparin during NCVI (Non-Cardiac Vascular Interventions) is essential to ensure the
      individual patient of safe and tailor-made anticoagulation. Not measuring the effect of the
      administered heparin exposes the patient to unnecessary risks of thrombo-embolic and bleeding
      complications. First aim of the MANCO study is to prove that the standardized bolus of 5000
      IU of heparin, used by 90% of vascular specialists in Europe, results in inadequate
      anticoagulation in more than 80% of patients. These measurements will be performed using the
      Hemostasis Management System by Medtronic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Heparin is used worldwide by all vascular surgeons and interventional radiologists (IR)
      during non-cardiac vascular interventions (NCVI), both open and endovascular. Heparin is used
      to reduce or prevent arterial thrombo-embolic complications (ATEC). Heparin reduces the
      clotting of blood and thereby coagulation. This also explains the negative side-effect of
      using heparin: its use can lead to bleeding-complications, possibly causing the need for
      blood tranfusions, more hematomas necessitating re-interventions and increasing the risk of
      infections.

      Since the 1970's it is well known that heparin has a non-linear dose response curve and also
      a non-linear elimination curve in the individual patient.

      Despite this fact, more than 95% of all vascular surgeons and IR use a standardized bolus of
      5000 IU in every patient. Multiple studies have demonstrated that up to 70% of patients is
      not adequately anticoagulated during NCVI using that bolus of 5000 IU.

      During open or endovascular cardiac interventions the effect of heparin is always routinely
      measured using the activated clotting time (ACT).

      Despite this knowledge the percentage of vascular surgeons and/or IR that measure the effect
      of heparin during NCVI routinely is astonishing low: 0-5%, in the US this percentage is
      probably higher (30%), possibly due to medico-legal reasons. Existing guidelines on NCVI
      depict different regimes on the use of heparin or do not mention this use at all.

      The Hemostasis Management System (HMS, Medtronic) measures the ACT, but it also calculates a
      heparin dose response curve in the individual patient. This curve supplies the vascular
      surgeon or IR a tool to administer the exact amount of heparin needed to reach a desired ACT.
      Also the exact dose of protamine can be calculated to neutralize the effect of remaining
      circulating heparin in the individual patient. The use of the HMS in cardiac vascular
      procedures has to led to a reduced need for blood transfusions, less postoperative bleeding
      complications and a reduction of peri-procedural myocardial infarctions and other ATEC.

      To determine if the HMS can be of equal high value during NCVI, a pilot study was performed
      at the VUMC, called Hepvasc. Results of this pilot (submitted) and other sparse results from
      literature, show that HMS can be used during NCVI. Furthermore, results indicated that the
      bolus of 5000 IU resulted in inadequate anticoagulation in 7 out of 18 included patients.
      This exposes those patients to a higher risk of ATEC.

      As a result of this pilot, the MANCO study is designed with the HMS during NCVI. The MANCO
      study will evaluate the data of heparin management with the HMS in number of large vascular
      centers, starting in the Netherlands and after that in Europe. Measurements with the HMS will
      be used for the evaluation of the local heparin protocol by the individual vascular surgeon
      or IR. The MANCO study will be started permitting every center to apply their current heparin
      protocol. This includes the dosage of heparin and possible extra dosing of heparin to reach a
      desired ACT. The MANCO study is started as a prospective data registry and observational
      study of the ACT with an extensive case record form (CRF). Regular blood samples for ACT
      measurements will be done, so no extra invasive measurements are performed in the patient.
      Data will be collected according to all legal requirements and permission of local medical
      ethics committees is granted.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 21, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 21, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 21, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Activated Clotting Time</measure>
    <time_frame>ACT measured before heparin, 5 minutes after and than at 30 minutes intervals. After a repeated dose of heparin again after 5 minutes and 30 minutes intervals</time_frame>
    <description>Change of Activated Clotting Time, before and after administration of heparin</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days or same admission, 6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>All complications as depicted in Suggested Standards for reports on arterial procedures and local complication registration. Vascular and non-vascular</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Arterial Disease</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <condition>PTA</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arterial procedure and ACT measurement</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients undergoing an open or endovascular arterial procedure in which heparin is used peri-procedurally and the ACT is measured to determine effect of heparin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Measuring the ACT to determine effect of heparin</intervention_name>
    <description>Measuring the ACT to determine effect of heparin during non-cardiac arterial procedures</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arterial procedure and ACT measurement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        - All patients in participating centers undergoing NCVI, older than 18 years
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients in participating centers undergoing Non-Cardiac Vascular (arterial)
             Intervention open or endovascular, older than 18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a known history of coagulation disorders or a EGFR lower than 30 ml/min.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arno M Wiersema, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Westfriesgasthuis</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Arno M Wiersema, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0031653444515</phone>
    <email>arno@wiersema.nu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vincent Jongkind, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0031229257257</phone>
    <email>v_jongkind@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vrije Universiteit Medisch Centrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>Noord-Holland</state>
        <zip>1081HV</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kakkhee Yeung, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0031204444444</phone>
      <email>kakkhee.yeung@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westfriesgasthuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hoorn</city>
        <state>Noord-Holland</state>
        <zip>1624NP</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arno M Wiersema, MD, Phd</last_name>
      <phone>0031229208206</phone>
      <email>a.wiersema@westfriesgasthuis.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vincent Jongkind, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0031229257257</phone>
      <email>v_jongkind@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Isala klinieken</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zwolle</city>
        <zip>8025 AB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maurice Pierie, Md, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0031384245000</phone>
      <email>maurice_pierie@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiersema AM, Watts C, Durran AC, Reijnen MM, van Delden OM, Moll FL, Vos JA. The Use of Heparin during Endovascular Peripheral Arterial Interventions: A Synopsis. Scientifica (Cairo). 2016;2016:1456298. doi: 10.1155/2016/1456298. Epub 2016 Apr 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27190678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiersema A, Jongkind V, Bruijninckx C, Reijnen M, Vos J, Van Delden O, Zeebregts C, Moll F. Prophylactic intraoperative antithrombotics in open infrainguinal arterial bypass surgery: a systematic review. J Cardiovasc Surg (Torino). 2015 Feb;56(1):127-43. Epub 2014 Mar 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24594802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiersema AM, Vos JA, Bruijninckx CMA, van Delden OM, Reijnen MMPJ, Vahl A, Zeebregts CJ, Moll FL. Periprocedural prophylactic antithrombotic strategies in interventional radiology: current practice in the Netherlands and comparison with the United kingdom. Cardiovasc Intervent Radiol. 2013 Dec;36(6):1477-1492. doi: 10.1007/s00270-013-0558-6. Epub 2013 Feb 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23404518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiersema AM, Jongkind V, Bruijninckx CM, Reijnen MM, Vos JA, van Delden OM, Zeebregts CJ, Moll FL; CAPPAStudy Group Consensus on Arterial PeriProcedural Anticoagulation. Prophylactic perioperative anti-thrombotics in open and endovascular abdominal aortic aneurysm (AAA) surgery: a systematic review. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2012 Oct;44(4):359-67. doi: 10.1016/j.ejvs.2012.06.008. Epub 2012 Jul 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22831869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finley A, Greenberg C. Review article: heparin sensitivity and resistance: management during cardiopulmonary bypass. Anesth Analg. 2013 Jun;116(6):1210-22. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e31827e4e62. Epub 2013 Feb 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23408671</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mabry CD, Thompson BW, Read RC. Activated clotting time (ACT) monitoring of intraoperative heparinization in peripheral vascular surgery. Am J Surg. 1979 Dec;138(6):894-900.</citation>
    <PMID>507308</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldhammer JE, Zimmerman D. Pro: Activated Clotting Time Should Be Monitored During Heparinization For Vascular Surgery. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2018 Jun;32(3):1494-1496. doi: 10.1053/j.jvca.2017.04.047. Epub 2017 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>28943189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Veerhoek D, Groepenhoff F, van der Sluijs MGJM, de Wever JWB, Blankensteijn JD, Vonk ABA, Boer C, Vermeulen CFW. Individual Differences in Heparin Sensitivity and Their Effect on Heparin Anticoagulation During Arterial Vascular Surgery. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2017 Oct;54(4):534-541. doi: 10.1016/j.ejvs.2017.07.006. Epub 2017 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>28802634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Westfriesgasthuis</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Arno Wiersema</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>heparin;ACT;non-cardiac vascular;peri-procedural</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium heparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heparin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All ACT values can be obtained after trial with PI</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

