<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03423238</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00046110</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R56HL134989-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03423238</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeting Obesity to Optimize Health in Cardiac Rehab (TOPCARE)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TOPCARE</acronym>
  <official_title>Targeting Obesity to Optimize Health in Cardiac Rehab (TOPCARE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although coronary heart disease (CHD) treatment guidelines recognize obesity as a major
      modifiable risk factor,2 nearly half of all CHD patients are obese and the current standard
      of care fails to implement evidence-based obesity treatment for this high-risk population.
      Multiple lines of evidence suggest that weight loss improves outcomes in CHD patients. The
      primary goal of this study is to determine the feasibility of adding a 6-month behavioral
      weight loss intervention to exercise-based cardiac rehabilitation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although coronary heart disease (CHD) treatment guidelines recognize obesity as a major
      modifiable risk factor,2 nearly half of all CHD patients are obese and the current standard
      of care fails to implement evidence-based obesity treatment for this high-risk population.
      The efficacy of exercise-based cardiac rehabilitation for improving exercise capacity and CHD
      risk factors is markedly blunted in CHD patients with obesity. Current programs largely focus
      on nutrient intake and produce minimal weight loss, on average. Our data show that despite
      appropriate exercise prescription and adherence, only 22% of CHD patients with obesity lose
      even the minimum recommended body weight over a 3-month program. These findings indicate that
      targeting reductions in caloric intake is needed to optimize outcomes in these patients and
      suggest that current programs are too short to produce adequate weight loss and ensure the
      necessary behavioral adaptations for long-term maintenance. Randomization to diet-induced
      weight loss in combination with aerobic exercise improves exercise capacity, quality of life,
      and CHD risk factors more than exercise alone and reduces long-term mortality in overweight
      and obese adults. The primary goal of this study is to determine the feasibility of adding a
      6-month behavioral weight loss intervention to exercise-based cardiac rehabilitation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>All assessments will take place by study staff blinded to the participant's treatment assignment. To ensure that staff remain blinded, participants will be asked not to discuss their intervention with the assessor</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Study Feasibilty</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be assessed in terms of the ability to 1) recruit study participants (i.e., total number randomized divided by total number eligible); 2) retain participants in the study for the full 6 months (i.e., the proportion of randomized participants who return for follow-up testing).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be assessed in terms of the ability to obtain adequate compliance to the prescribed intervention (i.e., total number of exercise/counseling sessions attended divided by total number of sessions prescribed).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Body weight in measured in kgs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 6 minute walk (6MW) test</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>The 6MW test is a valid and reproducible measure of submaximal exercise capacity that reflects the level at which most activities of daily living are performed, predicts clinical events in cardiac patients, and is therefore a clinically meaningful outcome in cardiac rehabilitation studies. Participants will be asked to walk at their own maximal pace on an established course, covering as much ground as they can during the allotted time, without running. Performance will be measured by the total distance covered in feet.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Expanded Short Physical Performance Battery (eSPPB)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>The expanded Short Physical Performance Battery (eSPPB) is a modified version of a widely used assessment of lower extremity physical function that consists of 3 standing balance tasks held for 10 seconds each (side-by-side, tandem and semi-tandem), two 4-m walk tests to assess usual gait speed, and 5 repeated chair stands. To minimize ceiling effects and maximize overall dispersion of test scores, the eSPPB increases the holding time of the semi- and full-tandem stands to 30 seconds and adds a single leg stand and a narrow walk test of balance (walking at usual pace within lines of tape spaced 20 cm apart). eSPPB scores are continuous and range from 0 to 4, with higher scores indicative of better performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Grip strength will be measured twice in each hand using an isometric hydraulic hand dynamometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mobility</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Mobility will be assessed using the MAT-sf, a 10-item computer-based, self-administered assessment that uses animated video clips of 10 different tasks to illustrate various mobility-related challenges that cover a broad range of functioning. Participants provide an assessment of their ability to perform each task on the computer by clicking the appropriate response (yes/no, number of minutes, number of times). Scores range from 30 to 80, with higher scores indicative of better mobility.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Health-related quality of life will be assessed using the Medical Outcomes Study Short Form 36 (SF-36), a self-report measure with well-documented psychometric properties across a wide range of populations. The SF-36 generates eight subscale scores (general health perceptions; physical functioning; role limitations due to physical problems; bodily pain; mental health; role limitations due to emotional problems; vitality; and social functioning) which will be used to derive a physical component summary (PCS) score and a mental component summary (MCS) score, with higher scores indicating more favorable quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Arterial stiffness- pulse wave velocity (PWV)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Arterial stiffness will be assessed as carotid-femoral pulse wave velocity (PWV). Carotid-femoral PWV will be measured in the supine position using the SphygmoCor XCEL system. PWV is calculated by dividing the distance between the carotid and femoral arteries by the pulse transit time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure will be measured with the participant in a seated or supine position after resting quietly for 5-10 minutes. Brachial and central (aortic) blood pressure will be measured using a conventional mercury sphygmomanometer and the SphygmoCor XCEL system, respectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Hemoglobin A1c will be measured in whole blood using a turbidimetric inhibition immunoassay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3, and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Insulin will be determined by a chemiluminescent immunoassay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Weight Loss</condition>
  <condition>CHD - Coronary Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to Rehab only using a randomization scheme with blocking stratified by sex and obesity severity (BMI&lt;30 vs. BMI≥30 kg/m2). All participants will undergo standard exercise-based cardiac rehabilitation, which includes meeting with dietitian, exercise, health education, and exercise compliance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab+Weight Loss (WL)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to Rehab+WL using a randomization scheme with blocking stratified by sex and obesity severity (BMI&lt;30 vs. BMI≥30 kg/m2). All participants will undergo standard exercise-based cardiac rehabilitation in addition to a weight-loss intervention, which includes meeting with dietitian, exercise, health education, and exercise compliance, calorie-restricted diet, behavioral modification, and weight-loss compliance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Each exercise session lasts for 60 to 90 minutes and consists of 5-10 minutes of warm-up and cool-down activity; up to 30 minutes of aerobic exercise using a variety of modalities (e.g., walking laps on a track, cycle ergometry, treadmills, stair climbers); and 15-20 minutes of upper and lower body resistance exercises using Thera-Bands. An exercise physiologist creates an individualized plan</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab+Weight Loss (WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meeting with Dietitian</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants have one meeting with a dietitian, usually within the first 2 weeks of the program, to discuss dietary concerns and address issues noted in the dietary assessment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab+Weight Loss (WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Group education classes conducted by an exercise physiologist and/or dietitian are designed to provide support and general information on healthy lifestyle behaviors. Topics include risk factor control, diabetes, hypertension, lipids, medications, aerobic exercise, strength training and flexibility, weight control, reading food nutrition labels, eating out, holiday eating, intimacy, stress, relaxation, cardiac symptoms, and cardiac interventions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab+Weight Loss (WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise Compliance</intervention_name>
    <description>Multiple behavioral management strategies to create a positive exercise environment and promote adherence and retention will be utilized. These include promptly contacting participants who miss a session, scheduling makeup sessions, and offering individual counseling sessions to discuss strategies to promote attendance and limit obstacles to participation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab+Weight Loss (WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Calorie-Restricted Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Diet plans will provide a caloric deficit of 500 kcals per day. The lowest calorie level permitted will be 1,100 kcals for women and 1,200 kcals for men. The calorie distribution goal will be 15-20% from protein, &lt;30% from fat, and 45-60% from carbohydrates. Participants will consume 2 meal replacements per day (Premier Protein shakes and bars); provided by the study)), along with one meal composed of traditional foods (500-750 kcals, low in fat, high in vegetables), and 1-3 snacks as needed (e.g., cereal bar, fruit, or vegetable, providing 100-150 kcals each). For the meal, patients will follow a weekly menu plan and recipes provided by the study. The food plan will be tailored to individual preferences and energy needs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab+Weight Loss (WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral Modification</intervention_name>
    <description>During months 1-3, participants will attend weekly individual behavioral counseling sessions with the study registered dietitian (RD); individual sessions will be held twice per month during months 4-6. The sessions will focus on self-monitoring, portion control, mindful eating, coping with negative thoughts, eating at regular times, and stress management. The RD will review individual progress, solve problems, answer questions, and set weight loss goals. At the end of the 6-month weight loss intervention, the RD will meet with participants to devise a weight maintenance strategy, including sample meal plans.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab+Weight Loss (WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Weight-Loss Compliance</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be asked to record their food and beverage intake in daily logs which will be reviewed weekly by the RD to verify compliance to the diet. Body weight will be measured weekly to ensure that participants are losing weight at an appropriate rate. If a participant is not meeting weight loss goals, energy intake will be modified accordingly to produce the desired rate of weight loss.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehab+Weight Loss (WL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  documented CHD defined as recent hospitalization for MI/heart attack coronary artery
             bypass grafting (CABG) or percutaneous coronary intervention (i.e., angioplasty,
             stent)

          -  age = 50-80 years

          -  overweight or obese based on an elevated BMI (≥25 kg/m2)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  body weight &gt;300 lbs

          -  congestive heart failure

          -  ejection fraction &lt;35%

          -  advanced kidney disease (GFR &lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m2, on dialysis, or dialysis anticipated
             within 6 months)

          -  cognitive impairment (Montreal Cognitive Assessment [MoCA] score &lt;26)

          -  major depression (Patient Health Questionnaire [PHQ-9] ≥20)

          -  uncontrolled diabetes (hemoglobin A1c &gt;11%)

          -  severe pulmonary disease (i.e., oxygen-dependent)

          -  significant impairment from a prior stroke or other neurologic disease or injury

          -  high risk for non-adherence (i.e., unwilling or unable to comply with study
             requirements)

          -  current participation in physical therapy or another weight loss study

          -  current or recent use of weight loss medications (e.g., orlistat)

          -  pregnant or pre-menopausal women

          -  peanut allergy

          -  milk allergy/lactose intolerance
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tina Brinkley, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tina Brinkley, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>336-713-8534</phone>
    <email>tbrinkle@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kimberly Kennedy</last_name>
    <phone>336-713-8567</phone>
    <email>kkennedy@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tina Brinkley, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>336-713-8534</phone>
      <email>tbrinkle@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kimberly Kennedy</last_name>
      <phone>336-713-8567</phone>
      <email>kkennedy@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Denise Houston, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fang-Chi Hsu, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Barbara Nicklas, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Killian Robinson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cardiac</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehab</keyword>
  <keyword>Diet</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Obese</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

