<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03420651</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-4459</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03420651</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Peak Expiratory Flow Rate for Emergency Department Management of Acute Asthma Exacerbation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Peak Expiratory Flow Rate (PEFR) for Emergency Department Management of Acute Asthma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Minneapolis Medical Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Minneapolis Medical Research Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients presenting to the emergency department with acute asthma exacerbation will be
      assigned to peak-expiratory flow rate (PEFR) guided management and non-PEFR guided
      management.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It is common practice to use peak-expiratory flow rate (PEFR) as an indicator of severity in
      patients that present with acute asthma exacerbation. There is, however, little data
      supporting this practice.

      A recent Canadian 20 site prospective observational cohort study of 805 ED patients with
      acute asthma exacerbation concluded PEFR was not useful in predicting need for
      hospitalization or relapse following discharge.

      As this was a cohort observational study, the conclusions that can be drawn are limited by
      the lack of randomization and control; it is necessary to conduct a randomized controlled
      trial to quantify how much time is expended caring for these patients, and gather safety
      data.

      This is important because no studies have quantified differences in resource utilization
      based on PEFR-guided management compared to non-PEFR-guided management. It is possible
      physicians following PEFR-guided management use comparatively more resources, such as
      nebulizer treatments and hospitalization, in order to treat low PEFR values in patients they
      would have otherwise discharged based on clinical judgement alone. If outcomes are not
      affected by non-PEFR-guided management, it may reduce resource utilization to avoid using
      PEFR-guided management.

      The investigators seek to determine if PEFR-based management and non-PEFR-based management
      perform similarly in guiding ED management of acute asthma exacerbations. Specifically, they
      seek to determine if the proportion of patients with no or mild asthma symptoms at 150
      minutes after enrollment arrival is similar in the two groups.

      At 150 minutes, it is expected that approximately 80% of patients will have no or mild asthma
      symptoms in both groups. When comparing the proportion of patients between the two groups, a
      confidence interval less than 20% wide (10% on either side of the point estimate) is desired.
      Therefore, goal enrollment is 110 patients per group.

      This study will only include patients who are discharged from the ED. Patients who are
      enrolled and then eventually admitted to the hospital will be tabulated but excluded from the
      analysis.

      Statistical analysis will compare the difference in the proportion of patients who achieve
      the primary outcome between groups, with the associated 95% confidence interval. Secondary
      outcomes will be presented descriptively; depending on the final distribution of the data,
      the investigators will present the means or medians of the data with the associated
      difference in mean/median with the associated 95% confidence intervals
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>When patients are randomized to the non-peak flow guided therapy, physicians are blinded to the peak flow values</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adequate control of asthma symptoms within 150 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>150 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients reporting no or mild asthma symptoms at 150 minutes after enrollment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization during index encounter</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of hospitalization in both groups directly from initial ED encounter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ED Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time elapsed from when the patient is roomed until the time the MD places discharge order, by review of the Electronic Medical record by a blinded abstractor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of nebulized treatments with short-acting beta antagonists (SABA)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
    <description>This is defined as the number of nebulized treatments received in the emergency department during the encounter, by review of the Electronic Medical record by a blinded abstractor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse following discharge within 72 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient will be assessed via chart review and telephone follow up to see if they visited an ED or urgent care for asthma symptoms during the 72 hour time frame. Rates of relapse will be compared between the two treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">220</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PEFR Guided Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Peak Expiratory Flow Rate (PEFR) Patients in this group will perform PEFR testing every 30 minutes and this data along with the National Asthma Prevention and Education Program guidelines will be considered by primary ED medical providers in the management of this group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-PEFR Guided Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard Clinical Judgement Patients in this group will receive management based on primary medical provider's clinical judgement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peak Expiratory Flow Rate (PEFR)</intervention_name>
    <description>PEFR values and the National Asthma Prevention and Education Program guidelines will be used by providers in the management of these patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PEFR Guided Management</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Clinical Judgement</intervention_name>
    <description>Providers will use physical exam and standard clinical judgement to guide management.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-PEFR Guided Management</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Presumed diagnosis of asthma, requiring at least 2 nebulized albuterol treatments

          -  Presenting with acute asthma exacerbation defined as acute or subacute episodes of
             progressively worsening shortness of breath, cough, wheezing, and chest tightness, or
             some combination of these symptoms

          -  Start of enrollment process must occur within 15 minutes of being roomed in the ED

          -  Working phone number and willingness to be contacted at least 72 hours following
             encounter

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prisoner or in custody

          -  Pregnant

          -  Known diagnosis of COPD

          -  Co-morbid medical conditions that patient is seeking treatment for concurrently

          -  Non-English speaking

          -  Unable to provide informed consent

          -  In the resuscitation bay or on non-invasive positive pressure ventilation (NPPV)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Audrey Hendrickson</last_name>
    <phone>612-873-7448</phone>
    <email>audrey.hendrickson@hcmed.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hennepin County Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55415</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Audrey Hendrickson</last_name>
      <phone>612-873-7448</phone>
      <email>audrey.hendrickson@hcmed.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hennepin County Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55415</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Audrey Hendrickson</last_name>
      <phone>612-873-9528</phone>
      <email>audreyh@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Minneapolis Medical Research Foundation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brian Driver</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Clinical Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

