<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03422380</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>07-0584</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1K23DK078913</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03422380</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Energy Expenditure and Weight Loss Maintenance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Energy Expenditure in Subjects Successful at Weight Loss Maintenance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity is reaching epidemic proportions and threatens both health and quality of life of
      people around the world. While many individuals succeed at short term weight loss, weight
      loss maintenance is the greatest barrier to successful treatment of obesity. High levels of
      physical activity are consistently associated with success in weight loss maintenance. The
      major goal of this proposal is to understand how and why high levels of physical activity are
      critical for long term maintenance of weight loss. This project takes advantage of the
      National Weight Control Registry (NWCR), which follows over 6000 individuals who have
      maintained a weight loss of ≥30 pounds for ≥1 year. Understanding how individuals successful
      at weight loss maintenance achieve energy balance will provide important insight into
      strategies to help more people sustain a weight loss.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants were recruited in three groups: weight loss maintainers (WLM: maintaining ≥13.6
      kg weight loss for ≥1 year), normal weight controls (NC: Body Mass Index (BMI) matched to
      current BMI of WLM), and controls with overweight/obesity (Overweight Controls (OC): BMI
      matched to pre-weight loss maximum BMI of WLM). The investigators hypothesize that total
      daily energy expenditure (TDEE) in WLM is similar to OC but is significantly higher then NC.
      High levels of volitional physical activity may compensate for the reduction in energy
      expenditure (&quot;energy gap&quot;) that is the expected result of weight loss. This allows WLM to
      maintain a high level of &quot;energy flux&quot;, which may facilitate optimal body weight regulation
      over time. The investigators will use doubly labeled water to compare TDEE in WLM and both NC
      and OC. The investigators will also compare individual components of TDEE including resting
      energy expenditure (REE), thermic effect of food (TEF), physical activity energy expenditure
      (PAEE), and physical activity level (PAL) between groups. The investigators also hypothesize
      that REE in WLM is similar to controls of both types under free living conditions, but will
      decrease following a period of physical inactivity and be significantly less than controls.
      Studies in rodents have consistently shown evidence of an increase in metabolic efficiency in
      the reduced obese state manifested by a lower than predicted REE. Studies in humans have
      shown mixed results, however few studies have controlled for habitual level of physical
      activity. Recent evidence suggests REE is greater in adults who perform regular exercise than
      their sedentary peers; this difference can be attributed in part to greater tonic sympathetic
      nervous system stimulation of REE that occurs in habitually exercising adults. The
      investigators believe there is an increase in metabolic efficiency in the reduced obese state
      manifested by a lower than predicted REE, and that high levels of physical activity function
      to &quot;mask&quot; or &quot;correct&quot; this metabolic efficiency. The investigators will compare REE under
      free living conditions and during an experimentally imposed period of reduced energy flux
      (restricted physical activity matched by an equivalent reduction in energy intake) in WLM and
      controls.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Daily Energy Expenditure (TDEE)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 8 days</time_frame>
    <description>After a 12-hour overnight fast, participants provided a baseline urine sample on day 1. Participants were then administered an oral dose of doubly labeled water (DLW) containing 1.8g 10% 18O/kg total body water (TBW) and 0.12 g/kg TBW of 99.9% deuterium. TBW was estimated as 73% of FFM from DXA. The dosing cup was rinsed twice with 30 mL of water and the rinsing dose consumed. Exact time of dosing was recorded. Additional urine samples were collected after a 4hr and 5hr post-dose equilibrium period and then again at the same times on day 8. TDEE over days 1-8 was determined using a single DLW dose and the two-point method according to Schoeller and colleagues.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity Energy Expenditure (PAEE)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 8 days</time_frame>
    <description>PAEE was calculated as TDEE - TEF - REE. In addition, because the energy cost of PA is proportional to body weight for a given intensity and duration, PAEE was also calculated as relative to body weight (kg).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resting Energy Expenditure (REE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 8 over a 1 week period</time_frame>
    <description>REE was measured using standard indirect calorimetry (Truemax 2400, ParvoMedics, Salt Lake City, UT) with the ventilated hood technique. Study participants arrived at 7am after a 12-hour overnight fast. Participants rested supine, awake, and lightly clothed in a thermoneutral (68-74 ˚F), dimly lit, quite room for 30 minutes. Respiratory gas exchange was measured for 15 minutes, using the last 10 minutes to average REE. Tests were examined for validity to confirm a) average RQ was 0.7-0.9, and b) average Metabolic Equivalents (METs) &lt;1.10. If the averaged data fell outside of these ranges, the test was considered invalid and excluded from the analysis. REE was collected on days 1 and 8 of the free-living monitoring period, and averaged to produce a single value for REE (intraclass correlation coefficient = 0.96).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thermic Effect of Food (TEF)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 8 days</time_frame>
    <description>The thermic effect of food (TEF) was calculated as 10% of TDEE.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity Level (PAL)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 8 days</time_frame>
    <description>PAL was calculated as TDEE/REE.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity Patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>At 8 days</time_frame>
    <description>PA patterns were assessed using the activPALTM activity monitor (PAL Technologies, Glasgow, Scotland). The activPALTM is a small (23x43x5 mm) and lightweight (10 grams) device that uses accelerometer-derived information about thigh position to estimate time spent sitting/lying, standing, and stepping. The device is attached to the anterior thigh and is waterproofed by wrapping it in a nitrile sleeve, allowing for 24-hour measurement. Participants were asked to wear the device continuously for seven days.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Weight Change, Body</condition>
  <condition>Weight Loss</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Weight Loss Maintainers (WLM)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals maintaining ≥13.6 kg (30 lb) weight loss for ≥1 year</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Weight Controls (NC)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals with normal weight whose BMI was matched to the current BMI of the WLM. NC had to be weight stable and not maintaining a weight loss of ≥13.6kg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls with Overweight/Obesity (OC)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals with overweight/obesity whose BMI was matched to the pre-weight loss maximum BMI of WLM. OC had to be weight stable and not maintaining a weight loss of ≥13.6kg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The proposed study design is aimed at collecting additional data on previously enrolled
        adult study subjects in the NWCR, which does not include children. The NWCR contains
        approximately 70% women and 30% men. We anticipate studying equal numbers of men and women
        in this study. Minorities comprise approximately 7% of total subjects in the NWCR. In the
        proposed studies, there will be no exclusions for racial or ethnic background.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men or women

          -  Age 18-65

          -  Weight stable (&lt;10 lb fluctuation in body weight over previous 6 months) or

          -  NWCR subjects successful at weight loss maintenance (maintaining a loss of ≥ 30 pounds
             for at least 2 years)

          -  Non-Reduced Weight Matched Controls: Individuals matched to NWCR subjects' current
             body weight. These individuals will be normal weight (BMI 18-25, BMI up to 27 allowed
             in men with waist circumference &lt; 40 cm), and have no history of overweight or obesity
             (BMI &gt;25) and will not be maintaining a weight loss ≥ 30 pounds.

          -  Non-Reduced Obese Controls: Individuals matched to NWCR subjects' maximum pre-weight
             loss body weight. These individuals will be overweight or obese (BMI ≥ 26-45).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diabetes

          -  Uncontrolled HTN (&gt;160/100)

          -  History of cardiac disease: CHF or angina, atrial fibrillation or ventricular
             tachycardia, or significant abnormality on resting EKG

          -  Symptoms suggestive of cardiovascular disease: chest pain, shortness of breath at rest
             or with mild exertion, dizziness, syncope.

          -  History of neurological disease: stroke, TIA or seizure disorder

          -  Current treatment for cancer (except skin)

          -  Severe pulmonary, liver or kidney disease

          -  Untreated thyroid disorder

          -  Severe arthritis or other musculoskeletal disorder

          -  Alcohol or drug abuse

          -  Active psychiatric illness

          -  Positive response to PAR-Q indicating requirement for monitored physical activity

          -  Other serious medical condition as determined by the investigator which would limit
             physical activity or require monitored activity.

          -  Pregnant and lactating women, and women actively trying to become pregnant
             (post-menopausal women on a stable dose of HRT and pre-menopausal women on a stable
             OCP regimen will be allowed to participate)

          -  Smoking within the past 6 months

          -  Subjects using prescription or over the counter medication which may affect RMR
             including beta blockers, stimulants such as Ritalin and appetite suppressants.

          -  Subjects who have undergone bariatric surgery or who are currently maintaining their
             weight loss with prescription weight loss drugs or supplements.

          -  Severe claustrophobia

          -  Moderate or high levels of physical activity at the workplace and unable to reduce
             workplace activity, work from home or take time off from work to participate in Study
             2.

          -  We will exclude controls if they are weight reduced (maintaining a weight loss of ≥ 30
             pounds).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Victoria Catenacci, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of CO</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>energy expenditure</keyword>
  <keyword>adaptive thermogenesis</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolic adaptation</keyword>
  <keyword>weight loss maintenance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Body Weight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Body Weight Changes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

