<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03429335</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Just TRAC It!</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03429335</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Just TRAC It! Transitioning Responsibly to Adult Care Using Smart Phone Technology</brief_title>
  <official_title>Just TRAC It! Transitioning Responsibly to Adult Care Using Smart Phone Technology</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Just TRAC It! study (Transitioning Responsibly to Adult Care using smart phone
      technology) is a randomized controlled trial designed to evaluate the impact of using smart
      phone technology in combination with the nurse led transition intervention, versus the
      current standard of care (nurse led transition intervention including MyHealth Passport), on
      preparing adolescents with chronic cardiac disease to successfully transition from pediatric
      to adult cardiology care. &quot;Just TRAC it!&quot; is a mobile-health intervention designed to teach
      youth to manage their health using existing functions on their mobile devices. We propose to
      conduct a nurse-led intervention that encourages adolescents to use &quot;Just TRAC it!&quot; while
      addressing the healthcare transition needs of 16-18 year olds.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Many adolescents and young adults living with chronic health conditions lack knowledge about
      their medical condition and confidence communicating with health care providers. Despite
      various positions statements on transition by the Canadian Pediatric Society, the American
      Academy of Pediatrics and the American Heart Association, there is limited evidence on the
      impact and effectiveness of transition interventions. Due to the convenience and
      accessibility of technology, adolescents embrace technology-based interventions to aid in
      their disease management and to improve their transition experience. However, there is a
      paucity of evidence-based apps in contrast to countless existing apps that are not
      evidence-based, which act as a barrier to physicians prescribing them. There is a pressing
      need for credible evidence on the effectiveness and value of health apps in improving
      self-management skills in adolescents.

      Instead of redesigning a mobile app, the Just TRAC It! encourages youth to use existing
      functions on their personal phones to track their health information. This information is
      easily retrievable when visiting health care providers and can help youth take ownership in
      managing their own health. This free option, using the technology already on most phones, can
      be used for any patient population or disease category. The use of Just TRAC It! allows youth
      to electronically document all medical information that would previously be printed on their
      MyHealth Passport, but may offer additional functionality in terms of learning to manage
      their health. Further investigation is warranted to evaluate the effectiveness of Just TRAC
      It! on improving patient knowledge, self-management skills, and transition readiness.

      The Stollery Children's Hospital is an international leader in pediatric to adult cardiology
      transition research, with two randomized clinical trials completed (CHAPTER 1 Trial, Mackie
      et al, Heart 2014 and CHAPTER 2 Trial, Mackie et al, BMC Cardiovascular 2016) and a 3rd in
      progress. The Just Trac It! Trial is an extension of our prior work. The results of the
      CHAPTER 1 Trial inform the current standard of care for transition interventions currently
      offered to all 16-18 year olds in our program who have had prior cardiac surgery, and this
      standard of care is the &quot;usual care&quot; (control) group for the Just Trac It! Study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be randomized individually in permuted blocks with randomly varying sizes of 2 and 4, and allocation ratio 1:1 for intervention and control groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in transition readiness measured by the TRANSITION-Q Questionnaire score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This 14-item instrument, developed at McMaster University, is written at a grade 4.4 level and takes about 3 minutes to complete.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in transition readiness measured by the TRANSITION-Q Questionnaire score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This 14-item instrument, developed at McMaster University, is written at a grade 4.4 level and takes about 3 minutes to complete.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of use and perceived helpfulness of intervention measured by Just TRAC It! Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire was developed for the purpose of this study to ascertain perceived helpfulness and frequency of use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of use and perceived helpfulness of intervention measured by Just TRAC It! Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire was developed for the purpose of this study to ascertain perceived helpfulness and frequency of use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart; Surgery, Heart, Functional Disturbance as Result</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Teaching session &amp; Just TRAC It</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Youth will attend a single one-on-one teaching session with a cardiology nurse (RN) the same day as their pediatric cardiology clinic visit. The RN will also explain &quot;Just TRAC It!&quot; and help the youth to enter their health information into their phone.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Teaching session &amp; MyHealth Passport</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Youth will attend a single one-on-one teaching session with a cardiology nurse (RN) the same day as their pediatric cardiology clinic visit. The RN will help youth complete and print out a &quot;MyHealth Passport&quot; to track their medical information.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Teaching session</intervention_name>
    <description>The cardiology nurse (RN) will have an hour long one-on-one teaching session prior to their pediatric cardiology clinic visit. The RN will go over the youth's cardiac history including the chronic heart disease diagnoses, names and dates of cardiac surgical procedures and cardiac catheterizations, and current cardiac medications and doses. She will also discuss transitioning from pediatric to adult care and healthy lifestyle choices.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Teaching session &amp; Just TRAC It</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Teaching session &amp; MyHealth Passport</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Just TRAC It!</intervention_name>
    <description>Just TRAC It! (Transitioning Responsibly to Adult Care) is a mobile health intervention that encourages youth to use existing functions on their personal phones to track their health information. The use of Just TRAC It! allows youth to electronically document all medical information that would previously be printed on their MyHealth Passport, but may offer additional functionality in terms of learning to manage their health.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Teaching session &amp; Just TRAC It</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MyHealth Passport</intervention_name>
    <description>MyHealth Passport is a customized, wallet-size card that includes the youth's important medical information. The RN will help the youth create a MyHealth Passport online, and print out the card for them.
The same educational intervention will be completed by cardiology nurse using a MyHealth Passport to track their medical information instead of the electronic &quot;Just TRAC It!&quot;</description>
    <arm_group_label>Teaching session &amp; MyHealth Passport</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  16-18 year olds with moderate or complex CHD, or acquired heart disease requiring
             surgery (e.g., rheumatic heart disease, prior endocarditis, prior valve replacement,
             Marfan's syndrome) who are followed at the Stollery Children's Hospital.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  less than grade 6 level of reading and comprehension based on parent report

          -  heart transplantation, as this results in distinct health challenges

          -  does not have a personal mobile device, as this is required for the Just TRAC It!
             intervention
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew S Mackie, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew S Mackie, MD</last_name>
    <phone>17804078361</phone>
    <email>Andrew.Mackie@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Angela X Han, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(780) 952-4085</phone>
    <email>axhan@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stollery Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew S Mackie, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(780)407-8361</phone>
      <email>Andrew.Mackie@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://moodle.univ-lille2.fr/pluginfile.php/128248/mod_resource/content/0/patients%20apps%20for%20improved%20healthcare%20IMS.pdf</url>
    <description>Patient Apps for Improved Healthcare: From Novelty to Mainstream.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bcchildrens.ca/our-services/support-services/transition-to-adult-care/just-trac-it</url>
    <description>British Columbia Children's Hospital. Just TRAC it!</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.sickkids.ca/myhealthpassport/</url>
    <description>The Hospital for Sick Children. MyHealth Passport.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell F, Biggs K, Aldiss SK, O'Neill PM, Clowes M, McDonagh J, While A, Gibson F. Transition of care for adolescents from paediatric services to adult health services. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2016 Apr 29;4:CD009794. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD009794.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27128768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Deyk K, Pelgrims E, Troost E, Goossens E, Budts W, Gewillig M, Moons P. Adolescents' understanding of their congenital heart disease on transfer to adult-focused care. Am J Cardiol. 2010 Dec 15;106(12):1803-7. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2010.08.020. Epub 2010 Nov 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21126624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kantoch MJ, Collins-Nakai RL, Medwid S, Ungstad E, Taylor DA. Adult patients' knowledge about their congenital heart disease. Can J Cardiol. 1997 Jul;13(7):641-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9251576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dore A, de Guise P, Mercier LA. Transition of care to adult congenital heart centres: what do patients know about their heart condition? Can J Cardiol. 2002 Feb;18(2):141-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11875583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clarizia NA, Chahal N, Manlhiot C, Kilburn J, Redington AN, McCrindle BW. Transition to adult health care for adolescents and young adults with congenital heart disease: perspectives of the patient, parent and health care provider. Can J Cardiol. 2009 Sep;25(9):e317-22.</citation>
    <PMID>19746251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moons P, Pinxten S, Dedroog D, Van Deyk K, Gewillig M, Hilderson D, Budts W. Expectations and experiences of adolescents with congenital heart disease on being transferred from pediatric cardiology to an adult congenital heart disease program. J Adolesc Health. 2009 Apr;44(4):316-22. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2008.11.007. Epub 2009 Feb 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19306789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Transition to adult care for youth with special health care needs. Paediatr Child Health. 2007 Nov;12(9):785-93. English, French.</citation>
    <PMID>19030468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Academy of Pediatrics; American Academy of Family Physicians; American College of Physicians-American Society of Internal Medicine. A consensus statement on health care transitions for young adults with special health care needs. Pediatrics. 2002 Dec;110(6 Pt 2):1304-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12456949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sable C, Foster E, Uzark K, Bjornsen K, Canobbio MM, Connolly HM, Graham TP, Gurvitz MZ, Kovacs A, Meadows AK, Reid GJ, Reiss JG, Rosenbaum KN, Sagerman PJ, Saidi A, Schonberg R, Shah S, Tong E, Williams RG; American Heart Association Congenital Heart Defects Committee of the Council on Cardiovascular Disease in the Young, Council on Cardiovascular Nursing, Council on Clinical Cardiology, and Council on Peripheral Vascular Disease. Best practices in managing transition to adulthood for adolescents with congenital heart disease: the transition process and medical and psychosocial issues: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2011 Apr 5;123(13):1454-85. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0b013e3182107c56. Epub 2011 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>21357825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mackie AS, Islam S, Magill-Evans J, Rankin KN, Robert C, Schuh M, Nicholas D, Vonder Muhll I, McCrindle BW, Yasui Y, Rempel GR. Healthcare transition for youth with heart disease: a clinical trial. Heart. 2014 Jul;100(14):1113-8. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2014-305748. Epub 2014 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24842870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang JS, Gottschalk M, Pian M, Dillon L, Barajas D, Bartholomew LK. Transition to adult care: systematic assessment of adolescents with chronic illnesses and their medical teams. J Pediatr. 2011 Dec;159(6):994-8.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2011.05.038. Epub 2011 Jul 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21784450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trawley S, Browne JL, Hagger VL, Hendrieckx C, Holmes-Truscott E, Pouwer F, Skinner TC, Speight J. The Use of Mobile Applications Among Adolescents with Type 1 Diabetes: Results from Diabetes MILES Youth-Australia. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2016 Dec;18(12):813-819. Epub 2016 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>27788032</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geryk LL, Roberts CA, Sage AJ, Coyne-Beasley T, Sleath BL, Carpenter DM. Parent and Clinician Preferences for an Asthma App to Promote Adolescent Self-Management: A Formative Study. JMIR Res Protoc. 2016 Dec 6;5(4):e229.</citation>
    <PMID>27923777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crosby LE, Ware RE, Goldstein A, Walton A, Joffe NE, Vogel C, Britto MT. Development and evaluation of iManage: A self-management app co-designed by adolescents with sickle cell disease. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2017 Jan;64(1):139-145. doi: 10.1002/pbc.26177. Epub 2016 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>27574031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Majeed-Ariss R, Baildam E, Campbell M, Chieng A, Fallon D, Hall A, McDonagh JE, Stones SR, Thomson W, Swallow V. Apps and Adolescents: A Systematic Review of Adolescents' Use of Mobile Phone and Tablet Apps That Support Personal Management of Their Chronic or Long-Term Physical Conditions. J Med Internet Res. 2015 Dec 23;17(12):e287. doi: 10.2196/jmir.5043. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26701961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Misra S, Lewis TL, Aungst TD. Medical application use and the need for further research and assessment for clinical practice: creation and integration of standards for best practice to alleviate poor application design. JAMA Dermatol. 2013 Jun;149(6):661-2. doi: 10.1001/jamadermatol.2013.606.</citation>
    <PMID>23783150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang JS, Terrones L, Tompane T, Dillon L, Pian M, Gottschalk M, Norman GJ, Bartholomew LK. Preparing adolescents with chronic disease for transition to adult care: a technology program. Pediatrics. 2014 Jun;133(6):e1639-46. doi: 10.1542/peds.2013-2830. Epub 2014 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24843066</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klassen AF, Grant C, Barr R, Brill H, Kraus de Camargo O, Ronen GM, Samaan MC, Mondal T, Cano SJ, Schlatman A, Tsangaris E, Athale U, Wickert N, Gorter JW. Development and validation of a generic scale for use in transition programmes to measure self-management skills in adolescents with chronic health conditions: the TRANSITION-Q. Child Care Health Dev. 2015 Jul;41(4):547-58. doi: 10.1111/cch.12207. Epub 2014 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>25351414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boutron I, Moher D, Altman DG, Schulz KF, Ravaud P; CONSORT Group. Methods and processes of the CONSORT Group: example of an extension for trials assessing nonpharmacologic treatments. Ann Intern Med. 2008 Feb 19;148(4):W60-6.</citation>
    <PMID>18283201</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrew Mackie</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Transition</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Smart phone</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pathologic Processes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

