<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03420456</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017P002231</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03420456</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcranial Pulse Near-Infrared Light in Generalized Anxiety Disorder: a Placebo-Controlled Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>Lighten-GAD</acronym>
  <official_title>Transcranial Pulse Near-Infrared Light in Generalized Anxiety Disorder: a Placebo-Controlled Study (Lighten-GAD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cerebral Sciences LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Transcranial Light Therapy involves non-invasive and invisible beams of light that increase
      energy metabolism in the brain. Transcranial light therapy has been found to promote brain
      metabolism which may help people with anxiety. The research team proposes a novel approach to
      treating anxiety by using transcranial light therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see if using Transcranial Light Therapy (TLT), also called
      near- infrared light, helps improve symptoms of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD). Subjects
      will be randomized at a 1:2 ratio into 2 groups: pulse light (TLT) and sham. The sham group
      will be randomized after 8 weeks at a 1:1 ratio in to TLT and sham.

      The study involves 1 screening visit which may last up to 3 hours, 16 weekly study visits,
      and one follow-up visit. There are 2 in-office treatment visits, during which a clinician
      applies transcranial light therapy to the participant's head for about 30 minutes. The other
      study visits involve assessments with a study clinician. The participants will administer the
      treatment once daily at home during the 16-week treatment period.

      If a participant qualifies for the study, the study team assigns the participant by chance to
      receive either active transcranial light therapy or sham transcranial light therapy
      treatment. During sham transcranial light therapy visits, the transcranial light therapy
      device will not produce near infrared waves (e.g., light energy that cannot penetrate the
      skin and cranium). Participants have more than an equal chance of being assigned to the
      active transcranial light therapy or the sham transcranial light therapy over the course of
      the study. Neither the participant, nor the clinician, nor any research staff other than the
      study statistician will know which study group the participant belongs.

      Participants are randomized a second time after 8-weeks in the study. If the participant were
      in the sham group the first 8-weeks, that participant may receive the active transcranial
      light therapy treatment after re-randomization. If the participant were already in the active
      transcranial light therapy group during the first 8-weeks the participant continues receiving
      the active treatment. All in all, participants have a 2 in 3 chance of receiving the active
      transcranial light therapy treatment at some point during the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 26, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 25, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 25, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>2-phase sequential parallel design</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>All subjects and investigators (except the study statistician) will be blind to treatment sequence assignment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Structured Interview Guide for the Hamilton Anxiety Scale (SIGH-A)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks - Sequential-parallel comparison design</time_frame>
    <description>This instrument is completed by the clinician based on his/her assessment of the patient's anxiety symptoms, using a structured interview, specific instructions, and defined anchor points. Answers to the questions are rated on a scale of 0-4, with higher scores indicating more severe pathology. Scores range between 0 to 56; &lt;17 indicates mild severity, 18-24 mild-to-moderate severity, and 25-30 moderate to severe.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impressions - Severity and Improvement (CGI-S, CGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks - Sequential-parallel comparison design</time_frame>
    <description>These two instruments are scored 1-7 by the clinician based on assessment of the subject's overall clinical status. They measure, based on history and scores on other instruments: (a) symptom severity (CGI-S) and (b) clinical improvement (CGI-I).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Generalized Anxiety Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transcranial Light Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Transcranial light therapy penetrates the skin and brain using light energy and the light energy may activate under-stimulated brain regions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Transcranial Light Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the sham group, the transcranial light therapy device uses nonpenetrating light emitting diode light energy. The sham controls for which participants improve from the actual transcranial light therapy treatment and which participants improve during the study for reasons other than the therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial Light Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Transcranial light therapy penetrates the skin and brain using light energy; this makes transcranial light therapy noninvasive. Transcranial light therapy may activate under-stimulated brain regions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transcranial Light Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Transcranial Light Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Low Level Laser-Light Therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>Photobiomodulation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Transcranial Light Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The same device used for the actual transcranial light therapy is used as the sham device; The device, when set to sham, will mimic the actual transcranial light therapy; however, when set to sham the device does not emit skin and cranium penetrating light emitting diode light energy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Transcranial Light Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects age at screening will be between 18 and 70 years old (inclusive).

          -  Diagnosis of generalized anxiety disorder (MINI) - primary disorder

          -  CGI-S ≥4 or higher, i.e., &quot;moderately anxious&quot;

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must use a double-barrier method for birth control
             (e.g. condoms plus spermicide) if sexually active.

          -  Subject Informed Consent obtained in writing in compliance with local regulations
             prior to enrollment into this study.

          -  The subject is willing to participate in this study for at least 16 weeks.

          -  Subjects will need to be on stable dose(s) of anti-anxiety treatments (if taking any)
             for at least six weeks prior to enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The subject is pregnant or lactating.

          -  Structured psychotherapy focused on treating the subject's anxiety (i.e. CBT) and
             other alternative interventions for anxiety are permitted if started at least 8 weeks
             prior to the screening visit.

          -  Substance dependence or abuse in the past 3 months.

          -  History of a psychotic disorder or psychotic episode (current psychotic episode per
             MINI assessment).

          -  Bipolar affective disorder (per MINI assessment).

          -  Unstable medical illness, defined as any medical illness which is not well-controlled
             with standard-of-care medications (e.g., insulin for diabetes mellitus, HCTZ for
             hypertension).

          -  Active suicidal or homicidal ideation (both intention and plan are present), as
             determined by C-SSRS screening.

          -  Cognitive impairment (MOCA&lt;21)

          -  The subject has a significant skin condition (i.e., hemangioma, scleroderma,
             psoriasis, rash, open wound or tattoo) on the subject's scalp that is found to be in
             proximity to any of the procedure sites.

          -  The subject has an implant of any kind in the head (e.g. stent, clipped aneurysm,
             embolised AVM, implantable shunt - Hakim valve).

          -  Any use of light-activated drugs (photodynamic therapy) within 14 days prior to study
             enrollment (in US: Visudine (verteporfin) - for age related macular degeneration;
             Aminolevulinic Acid- for actinic keratoses; Photofrin (porfimer sodium) - for
             esophageal cancer, non-small cell lung cancer; Levulan Kerastick (aminolevulinic acid
             HCl) - for actinic keratosis; 5-aminolevulinic acid (ALA)- for non-melanoma skin
             cancer)

          -  Recent history of stroke (90 days).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paolo Cassano, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Anxiety and Traumatic Stress Disorders</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Samantha Hellberg, BA</last_name>
    <phone>(617) 724-0666</phone>
    <email>shellberg@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah Wieman, BA</last_name>
    <phone>617-726-3508</phone>
    <email>swieman@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital- Center for Anxiety and Traumatic Stress Disorders</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Samantha Hellberg, BA</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-0666</phone>
      <email>shellberg@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sarah Wieman, BA</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-3508</phone>
      <email>swieman@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paolo Cassano, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paolo Cassano</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Personally unidentifiable information will be sent to Dr. Anastasia Ivanova, a privately contracted biostatistician form Chapel Hill North Carolina, for consultation on analyses. All information sent to Dr. Ivanova uses acrostics in place of personally identifiable information.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

