<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02073123</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NLG2103</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02073123</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of IDO Inhibitor in Combination With Checkpoint Inhibitors for Adult Patients With Metastatic Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Study of the Concomitant Administration of Indoximod Plus Immune Checkpoint Inhibitors for Adult Patients With Advanced or Metastatic Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NewLink Genetics Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NewLink Genetics Corporation</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the preliminary efficacy of the established dose of indoximod in combination with
      immune checkpoint inhibition as measured by the best overall response rate (ORR) (complete
      response (CR) + partial response (PR))across both standard of care agents administered
      sequentially in patients with unresectable stage III or stage IV melanoma
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of melanoma is increasing. Based upon data obtained between 2004 and 2006, the
      lifetime probability of developing melanoma in the United States is estimated to be 1 in 37
      for men and 1 in 56 for women. In the United States, melanoma is the fifth leading cancer in
      men and the seventh in women. Locally confined, fully-resectable disease may be curable with
      current therapy; but Stage IV metastatic disease (or relapsed/recurrent disease) is highly
      refractory to therapy. Thus, experimental clinical trials provide an accepted treatment
      option for metastatic or relapsed/refractory melanoma.

      The current study is designed as a prospective trial to evaluate the combination of indoximod
      and checkpoint inhibitors in adult patients with metastatic melanoma. Ipilimumab,
      pembrolizumab and nivolumab will be used at the recommended approved doses for this
      indication.

      The current trial will be done in two phases: a Phase 1b dose escalation of indoximod in
      combination with ipilimumab, starting at half the recommended single-agent dose, to establish
      the recommended Phase 2 dose for the combination.

      This will be followed by a three arm expansion study testing a fixed dose of indoximod (at
      the recommended Phase 2 dose) combined with standard-dose ipilimumab, pembrolizumab or
      nivolumab.

      Treatment will be administered on an outpatient basis. No investigational or commercial
      cancer directed agents or therapies other than those described below may be administered.

      Safety assessment will follow the guidelines provided in the National Cancer Institute Common
      Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI-CTCAE) Version.4.03.

      Patients will be followed both clinically and radiographically starting 12 weeks after
      initiation of treatment then every 8 weeks for tumor evaluation. Post-treatment scans will be
      compared to the baseline scan and responses will be assessed based using mWHO and immune
      related response criteria (irRC) described by Wolchok et al. (Wolchok et al., 2009).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Incidence of Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>17 months</time_frame>
    <description>Phase 1 component:
Evaluate the safety (adverse events - type, incidence, severity, duration, causality and treatment intervention) of the combination of indoximod and ipilimumab when given concomitantly.
The safety and tolerability ipilimumab followed by Indoximod will be assessed by listing the overall incidence of AEs. The AEs will be summarized and classified by body system and by treatment group. The type, incidence, severity, and causality of each AE, the duration of the event, and any required treatment interventions will be tabulated. Physical examination results will be presented in the patient data listings. The DLT will be listed per dose level and treatment along with overall frequencies. The data from the expansion part (Phase II) will be used for this part of safety and tolerability assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2 Dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>22 months</time_frame>
    <description>Phase 1 component:
To determine the recommended Phase 2 dose of indoximod in combination with ipilimumab in patients with unresectable melanoma.
A minimum of nine patients will be treated depending on DLT. Each dose will be administered to a cohort of 3 patients. If 0 out of 3 or less than 2 out of 6 patients experienced a DLT at any given dose level, the dose escalation will proceed to the next dose level. The MTD is generally the largest dose level at which at most 1 out of 6 patients experiences a DLT. IF DLT is not reached at the highest dose level (1200mg twice daily), no further escalation will proceed and this dose level will be declared the recommended Phase II dose</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>22 months</time_frame>
    <description>Phase 2 component:
To evaluate the preliminary efficacy of the established dose of indoximod in combination with immune checkpoint inhibition as measured by the best overall response rate in patients with unresectable Stage III or Stage IV melanoma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>22 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse event profile of ipilimumab and indoximod in patients with unresectable stage III or Stage IV melanoma participating in phase II portion of the study will be listed, summarized classified by body system. The type, incidence, severity, and causality of each AE, the duration of the event, and any required treatment interventions will be tabulated. Physical examination results will be presented in the patient data listings. The data from the expansion part (Phase II) will be used for this part of safety and tolerability assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>b) To evaluate the overall survival (OS) of patients with unresectable stage III or Stage IV melanoma receiving ipilimumab and indoximod. OS, defined as the time between the first dose of study therapy and death (subjects who have not died will be censored at the most recent last-known-alive date), will also be analyzed. The OS rate along with its 95% confidence interval will be presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanisms of activity/resistance to IDO/CTLA-4 inhibitor therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The mechanisms of activity/resistance to IDO/CTLA-4 inhibitor therapy will be demonstrated through correlative studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>22 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>22 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Ipilimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Indoximod will be administered at 1200mg BID by mouth.
Ipilimumab administered intravenously at 3 mg/kg every three weeks for a total of four doses.
Indoximod and ipilimumab will be dosed concurrently. Indoximod will be dosed twice daily on all days of each 21 day cycles (segment 1). Ipilimumab will be dosed on the 1st day of each 21 day cycle for the first 4 cycles. Indoximod dosing will continue after all 4 doses of ipilimumab are administered (segment 2, 28-day cycles).
Patients will continue until they experience disease progression or limiting toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Indoximod will be administered at 1200mg BID by mouth.
Pembrolizumab administered intravenously at 2 mg/kg every three weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Indoximod will be administered at 1200mg BID by mouth.
Nivolumab administered intravenously at 3 mg/kg every four weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indoximod</intervention_name>
    <description>Initial dose of 600mg BID by mouth with escalation planned to 1200mg BID by mouth
Dose escalation:
If 0 of the 3 subjects forming the first cohort experience RLT, 1200mg BID cohort will be enrolled
If 1 of the 3 subjects in any cohort experiences a RLT, then enrollment into that cohort will increase to a total of 6 subjects
If &gt; 1 of the 3-6 subjects experience a RLT, then the MTD has been exceeded and further enrollment into the cohort will cease
If &gt;1 subject at 600mg BID experiences a RLT, the dose will be de-escalated to 400mg BID. If &gt;1 subject at this level experiences a RLT, one additional de-escalation to 200mg BID is allowed
Dosing cycles are 21 days in length during the combination immunotherapy component (first 4 cycles) and 28 days during indoximod monotherapy. Patients will continue until they experience disease progression or limiting toxicity
Phase 2 Treatment Plan (Cohort 2) Will receive fixed dose of indoximod determined in phase 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Ipilimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>1-methyl-D-tryptophan</other_name>
    <other_name>D-1MT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Ipilimumab administered intravenously at 3 mg/kg every three weeks for a total of four doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Ipilimumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YERVOY</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-010</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-101</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Nivolumab administered intravenously at 3 mg/kg every three weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Pembrolizumab administered intravenously at 2 mg/kg every three weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indoximod + Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Unresectable Stage III or Stage IV melanoma.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease, defined as lesions that can be accurately
             measure in in 2 perpendicular diameters with at least one diameter &gt; 20mm and the
             other &gt;10mm on conventional CT or MRI or 10mm x 10 mm by spiral CT.

          -  No systemic treatment in the previous 28 days.

          -  Age ≥18 years. Because no dosing or adverse event data are currently available on the
             use of ipilimumab or indoximod in patients &lt;18 years of age, children are excluded
             from this study.

          -  ECOG performance status ≤2 (Karnofsky ≥60% )

          -  Patient has adequate bone marrow and organ function as defined by the following
             laboratory values :

          -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) ≥ 1.0 x 109/L

          -  Platelets ≥ 100 x 109/L

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

          -  INR ≤ 2 x ULN

          -  Potassium, calcium, magnesium ≤ Grade 1 per CTCAE

          -  Serum Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

          -  Serum Bilirubin, amylase and lipase ≤ 1.5 x ULN (in patients with known Gilbert
             Syndrome, total bilirubin ≤ 3 x ULN, with direct bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN)

          -  AST and ALT ≤ 3 x ULN (or ≤ 5.0 x ULN if hepatic metastases are present)

          -  Serum Albumin ≥ 3 g/dL

          -  Patients must have normal pituitary function as defined below:

          -  free T4, TSH within normal institutional limits

          -  ACTH within normal institutional limits

          -  Patients with known brain metastases will only be eligible after their tumors have
             been treated with definitive resection and/or radiotherapy and they are neurologically
             stable for at least 1 month off steroids.

          -  The effects of indoximod on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason
             and because indoximod may affect maternal immune tolerance of the fetus, sexually
             active women of child-bearing potential must agree to use two forms of contraception
             (hormonal and barrier method of birth control or abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for the duration of study participation. Use of contraception or abstinence should
             continue for a minimum of 1 month after completion of the study. Should a woman become
             pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study, she should
             discontinue the study drug and inform her treating physician immediately. A pregnancy
             test is required prior to study enrollment and monthly while on treatment with
             indoximod for all women of child-bearing potential. Also men should be discouraged
             from fathering children while on treatment.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had molecular targeted therapy (including vemurafenib) or
             radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to entering the study or those who have not
             recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          -  Patients who have had prior therapy with immune checkpoint inhibition or or indoximod
             are excluded from the trial. Pre-treatment with other immune modulators is allowed in
             the phase 1 component of the study only. For the Phase II component, patients are
             excluded if they have had prior therapy with or immune-stimulating agents including
             interleukin-2, interferons, CTLA-4 or PD1 antagonists, CD40 or CD137 agonist, or
             cancer therapeutic vaccines in any prior line for metastatic disease. Interferons used
             in the adjuvant setting are allowed (Phase 1 or 2 component).

          -  Patients with known active, uncontrolled brain metastases should be excluded from this
             clinical trial.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to ipilimumab or tryptophan containing substances. This would include
             L-tryptophan or 5-hydroxy-tryptophan supplements. Also patients with a history of
             known hypersensitivity reactions to mouse or humanized monoclonal antibodies are
             excluded.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection (especially toxoplasmosis, which could potentially be worsened by indoximod
             (Divanovic et al., 2012)), symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina
             pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because indoximod is an immunoregulatory
             agent with the potential for abortifacient effects due to fetal rejection by the
             maternal immune system. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse
             events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the mother with indoximod,
             breastfeeding should be discontinued if the mother is treated with indoximod.

          -  Known HIV-positive patients and those with other acquired/inherited immunodeficiencies
             are ineligible due the possibility of affecting the response to indoximod, and the
             higher risk of active opportunistic infections.

          -  Any other cancer, unless the patient has been disease-free for ≥5 years (except
             treated and cured basal-cell or squamous-cell skin cancer, superficial bladder cancer,
             or treated carcinoma in situ of the cervix, breast, or bladder and treated localized
             prostate cancer with undetectable PSA for 2 years).

          -  Patients with laboratory evidence of pancreatitis are excluded.

          -  Patients with autoimmune disease (e.g., psoriasis, extensive atopic dermatitis,
             asthma, IBD, M.S., uveitis, vasculitis), chronic inflammatory condition, or any
             condition requiring concurrent use of any systemic immunosuppressants or steroids for
             any reason are excluded from the study. Patients with isolated vitiligo remain
             eligible. Any patient with an allo-transplant of any kind would be excluded as well,
             including xenograft heart valve. Mild, intermittent asthma requiring only occasional
             beta-agonist inhaler use or mild localized eczema will not be excluded.

          -  Chronic use of immune-suppressive drugs (ie, systemic corticosteroids used in the
             management of cancer or non-cancer related illnesses, eg, COPD).

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Vahanian, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>NewLink Genetics Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgia Regents University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robin Dobbins</last_name>
      <phone>706-721-2154</phone>
      <email>rdobbins@gru.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Samir Khleif, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Iowa Hospital and Clinics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teena Davis-Vandaele</last_name>
      <phone>319-467-5834</phone>
      <email>teena-vandaele@uiowa.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yousef Zakharia, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Renee Bradshaw</last_name>
      <phone>507-284-2041</phone>
      <email>Bradshaw.Renee@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert McWilliams, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New Mexico Cancer Center Alliance</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Oliva Reynolds</last_name>
      <phone>505-925-0370</phone>
      <email>oreynolds@salud.unm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Montaser Shaheen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Hershey Cancer Institue</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Becky Miller, BSN, RN, OCN</last_name>
      <phone>717-531-1003</phone>
      <email>rmiller13@hmc.psu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Drabick, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huntsman Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacqueline Richards</last_name>
      <phone>801-587-4433</phone>
      <email>jacqueline.richards@hci.utah.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kenneth Grossman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.newlinkgenetics.com</url>
    <description>Study Sponsor Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 27, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Stage III melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Stage IV melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>unresectable</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tryptophan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

