<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02078544</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013/00705</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02078544</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrated Molecular Analysis of Cancer in Gynaecologic Oncology (IMAC-GO)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University Hospital, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University Hospital, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to identify biomarkers and potentially actionable mutations/
      activated molecular pathways and evaluate the impact of molecular profiling information on
      patients with gynaecological cancer.

      The hypothesis of the study are:

        -  Analysis of gynaecological tumour samples will allow us to identify novel and/or
           actionable molecular changes that may drive therapeutic strategies for the management of
           these cancers.

        -  Molecular profiling will improve the outcome of novel targeted-agent treatment in
           clinical trials

        -  Molecular profiling of paired samples (primary/recurrent and primary/metastatic) will
           provide new insights into mechanisms underlying drug resistance and metastasis in
           gynaecological cancers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Advances in our understanding of cancer biology has led to a rapid expansion of molecularly
      targeted therapeutics in pre-clinical and clinical development over the last decade. The
      systematic sequencing of cancer genomes has revealed that individual tumours frequently
      harbor multiple &quot;driver&quot; somatic mutations that confer growth advantage and positive
      selection. Importantly, many of the altered proteins resulting from the mutations identified
      by these studies are in fact actionable, i.e. &quot;druggable&quot;, targets. Hence, evaluating drug
      efficacy in tumours selected by a combination of histopathology and molecular analysis has
      the potential to result in a greater therapeutic gain. The premises behind personalised
      cancer medicine include: i) genetic aberrations exist in human malignancies; ii) a subset of
      these aberrations frequently exist across multiple tumour types and have functional relevance
      as drivers for oncogenesis and tumour progression; iii) the molecular effects of these
      genetic aberrations are potentially actionable targets; and iv) there are medicinal compounds
      that can safely and effectively modulate such targets in patients with these tumours. The key
      challenge to optimising this personalised approach to cancer therapy is to ensure that
      patients with tumours harbouring specific molecular/ genetic aberrations are specifically
      matched to a particular drug or combination of drugs. In this respect, molecular analysis of
      tumours to identify somatic mutations and/or other genetic aberrations are examples of
      enrichment strategies to assist in matching patients to drugs or treatments that have gained
      increasing interest in the oncology communityGenetic heterogeneity in gynaecological cancer
      underpins the observed variations in patient outcomes. Hence, the ability to characterise the
      unique genetic features of each patient's tumour will be a critical step to identifying the
      optimal therapeutic strategy for the individual.It is anticipated that once a validated
      process for molecular profiling is fully established at NUHS, this will eventually be
      integrated into patient care at a much earlier stage. The spectrum and development of
      molecularly-targeted agents is rapidly expanding, and it is increasingly likely that the
      future of cancer management will require the molecular and histological subtype of one's
      tumour to be defined in order to decide on the most appropriate treatment strategy. By
      initiating this first step towards the development of a well-validated, cohesive, streamlined
      and efficient process for molecular profiling, the eventual aim will be to obtain formal
      accreditation so that cancer physicians at NUHS/NCIS, NCC and KKH will be able to
      unequivocally use the data for patient care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in biomarkers and potentially actionable mutations/ activated molecular pathways and evaluate the impact of molecular profiling information on patients with gynaecological cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>It is anticipated that once a validated process for molecular profiling is fully established at NUHS, this will eventually be integrated into patient care at a much earlier stage. The spectrum and development of molecularly-targeted agents is rapidly expanding, and it is increasingly likely that the future of cancer management will require the molecular and histological subtype of one's tumour to be defined in order to decide on the most appropriate treatment strategy. By initiating this first step towards the development of a well-validated, cohesive, streamlined and efficient process for molecular profiling, the eventual aim will be to obtain formal accreditation so that cancer physicians at NUHS/NCIS, NCC and KKH will be able to unequivocally use the data for patient care.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">700</enrollment>
  <condition>Gynaecologic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gynaecological cancer</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Integrated Molecular Analysis</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Gynaecological cancer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      I. Tumour samples from patients with a diagnosis of gynaecological cancer from year 1995 to
      31 July 2013 will be obtained from the pathology archives and tissue repository.

      II. Blood, tumour and ascitic and pleural fluid samples will be prospectively collected.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients treated with gynaecological cancers at National University Hospital.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with histological confirmation of gynaecological cancers who are candidates
             for systemic therapy, including molecular-targeted therapy/ biomarker-driven clinical
             trials.

          2. Patients must be &gt;= 21 years old.

          3. All patients must have signed and dated an informed consent form.

          4. All patients must have sufficient tumour tissue for molecular profiling.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Boon Cher Goh, MBBS, MRCP</last_name>
    <phone>(65) 6779 5555</phone>
    <email>boon_cher_goh@nuhs.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>119074</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Boon Cher Goh, MBBS, MRCP</last_name>
      <phone>(65) 6779 5555</phone>
      <email>boon_cher_goh@nuhs.edu.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Boon Cher Goh, MBBS, MRCP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kola I, Landis J. Can the pharmaceutical industry reduce attrition rates? Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2004 Aug;3(8):711-5. doi: 10.1038/nrd1470. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15286737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart DJ, Kurzrock R. Cancer: the road to Amiens. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Jan 20;27(3):328-33. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.18.9621. Epub 2008 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>19064964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National University Hospital, Singapore</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Haematology-Oncology</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Goh Boon Cher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer in Gynaecologic Oncology</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

