<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02594332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-001868-19</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02594332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Mepolizumab Compared to Placebo on Airway Physiology in Patients With Eosinophilic Asthma: MEMORY Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>MEMORY</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Mono-center Study to Evaluate the Effects of Mepolizumab on Airway Physiology in Patients With Eosinophilic Asthma: the MEMORY Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the MEMORY trial is to compare the effects of mepolizumab with Placebo on
      airway physiology in patients with eosinophilic asthma
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Asthma with eosinophilic inflammation in the airways and/or blood eosinophilia is associated
      with clinical severity including the risk of exacerbations and relevant comorbidities (e.g.
      nasal polyposis). Interleukin-5 (IL-5) is a cytokine essential for eosinophil trafficking and
      survival. Clinical trials of blocking IL-5 with anti-IL-5 antibodies (mepolizumab and
      reslizumab) in patients with uncontrolled eosinophilic asthma resulted in an improvement in
      exacerbation rate and oral corticosteroid use. In some studies with mepolizumab and
      reslizumab there was a beneficial effect on lung function (FEV1). In addition, many patients
      described a profound impact on asthma symptoms and quality of life in personal reports which
      is not uniformly reflected in clinical trials.

      The MEMORY trial is the first to primarily evaluate the effect of mepolizumab treatment on
      pulmonary function in patients with severe eosinophilic asthma. Importantly, using spirometry
      and bodyplethysmography will allow to evaluate additional parameters beyond FEV1 that more
      closely mirror the pathophysiological changes and functional aspects of airflow limitation in
      asthma in real life, e.g. airway resistance, hyperinflation and diffusion capacity. The
      proposed trial will answer the important questions: if, and if so, which parameters of airway
      (patho-) physiology as assessed by bodyplethysmography best reflect clinical response to
      mepolizumab therapy in patients with severe eosinophilic asthma. In addition, the time course
      to clinical response will be assessed. Equally important, there is only a loose correlation
      between FEV1 and parameters of asthma control and asthma-related quality of life. This is why
      another new and important aspect of this trial is to carefully monitor asthma control and
      asthma quality in life in correlation with lung function changes beyond FEV1. Finally, it is
      tempting to speculate that the proposed trial will contribute to the question how to best
      define clinical response to mepolizumab.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    recruitment problems
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 17, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 22, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 22, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator FVC at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</measure>
    <time_frame>week 24 and time of response</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator forced vital capacity (FVC) at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator FEV1 at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</measure>
    <time_frame>week 24 and time of response</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator RV at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</measure>
    <time_frame>week 24 and time of response</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator residual volume (RV) at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator TLC at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</measure>
    <time_frame>week 24 and time of response</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator total lung capacity (TLC) at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator airway resistance at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</measure>
    <time_frame>week 24 and time of response</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator airway resistance at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator IC at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</measure>
    <time_frame>week 24 and time of response</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator inspiratory capacity (IC) at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator CO diffusion capacity at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</measure>
    <time_frame>week 24 and time of response</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator CO diffusion capacity at visit 10 (week 24) and at time of response</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator forced vital capacity (FVC) over the 48-week treatment period at prespecified timepoints (1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) over the 48-week treatment period at prespecified timepoints (1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator residual volume (RV) over the 48-week treatment period at prespecified timepoints (1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator total lung capacity (TLC) over the 48-week treatment period at prespecified timepoints (1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator airway resistance over the 48-week treatment period at prespecified timepoints (1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator inspiratory capacity (IC) over the 48-week treatment period at prespecified timepoints (1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in pre- and post-bronchodilator CO diffusion capacity over the 48-week treatment period at prespecified timepoints (1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise tolerance in a subgroup of patients: Mean change from baseline in exercise endurance time</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change from baseline in exercise endurance time during a sub-maximal constant-load cycle ergometry test after 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise tolerance in a subgroup of patients: Mean change from baseline in inspiratory capacity (IC)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change from baseline in inspiratory capacity (IC) at rest and at peak during sub-maximal constant-load cycle ergometry test after 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise tolerance in a subgroup of patients: Mean change from baseline in exertional dyspnea and leg discomfort (Borg CR10 Scale®)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change from baseline in exertional dyspnea and leg discomfort (Borg CR10 Scale®) during sub-maximal constant-load cycle ergometry test after 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: sence of smell</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: sense of taste</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: lung volume</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: CO Diffusion capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: FEV1 reversibility</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: exhaled NO (eNO)</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: blood eosinophils</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: eosinophilic cationic Protein (ECP)</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to clinical response and time to change of baseline parameters of clinical Response: blood periostin</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in Asthma Control Questionnaire (ACQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire (AQLQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in St. George´s Respiratory Questionnaire (SQRG)</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in Dyspnoe Index (BDI/TDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in fatique</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in number of days off school/work over the 48-week treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first clinically significant exacerbation requiring oral or systemic corticosteroids, hospitalization, and/or emergency department (ED) visits</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of clinically significant exacerbations</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first exacerbation requiring hospitalization or emergency department (ED) visit</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of exacerbations requiring hospitalization (including intubation and admittance to an intensive care unit (ICU)) or ED visits</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GETE rating by physician and patient at time of response and over the 52-week treatment period at pre-specified timepoints (1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in proportion of patients with nasal polyps, chronic sinusitis and loss of smell and taste</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical response to mepolizumab in relation to asthma parameters which potentially predict clinical response</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical response to mepolizumab in relation to asthma parameters which potentially predict clinical response (age at onset and duration of asthma, prior asthma medication, presence of nasal polyps, sense of smell and taste, allergic sensitization (skin prick test, total and specific IgE against aeroallergens and Staph. aureus enterotoxin), reversibility of airflow obstruction, eNO, blood eosinophils, eosinophilic cationic protein (ECP), blood periostin, ANA, ANCA, ECP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Routine safety assessment (AE and SAE reporting, withdrawals, pregnancy, hematological and clinical chemistry parameters, ECG and vital signs (pulse rate and systolic and diastolic blood pressure))</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Routine safety assessments are incorporated throughout and/or at the end of treatment period including AE and SAE reporting, withdrawals, pregnancy, hematological and clinical chemistry parameters, ECG and vital signs (pulse rate and systolic and diastolic blood pressure).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>100 mg SC every 4 weeks for 13 injections</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amount of Placebo corresponding to mepolizumab dose SC every 4 weeks for 13 injections</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mepolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg SC every 4 weeks for 13 injections</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must be able to give written informed consent prior to participation in the
             study, which will include the ability to comply with the requirements and restrictions
             listed in the consent form.

          2. Male or female patients at least 18 years

          3. Physician-diagnosis of asthma and evidence of asthma as documented by either
             reversibility of airflow obstruction (FEV1 ≥ 12% or 200 ml) demonstrated at visit 1 or
             visit 2 .

          4. ICS dose must be ≥ 1000 μg/day BDP or equivalent daily with or without maintenance
             oral corticosteroids.

          5. Treatment in the past 12 months with an additional controller medication for at least
             3 successive months, e.g., long-acting beta-2-agonist (LABA), leukotriene receptor
             antagonist (LTRA), or theophylline.

          6. Persistent airflow obstruction as indicated by a pre-bronchodilator FEV1 &lt; 80%
             predicted recorded at Visit 1 or &lt; 90% for patients on oral corticosteroids.

          7. An elevated peripheral blood eosinophil level of ≥ 300/µL that is related to asthma or
             ≥ 150/µL in patients treated with oral corticosteroids as maintenance therapy
             demonstrated at visit 1 or in the previous 12 months

          8. Confirmed history of two or more exacerbations requiring treatment with systemic
             corticosteroids (intramuscular, intravenous, or oral), in the 12 months prior to visit
             1, despite the use of high-dose inhaled corticosteroids. For patients receiving
             maintenance corticosteroids, the corticosteroid treatment for the exacerbations must
             have been a two-fold increase or greater in the dose.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current smokers or former smokers with a smoking history of ≥ 10 pack years (number of
             pack years = (number of cigarettes per day / 20) x number of years smoked). Patients
             who have not smoked for ≥ 6 months before visit 1 and have &lt; 10 pack years can be
             included into the study.

          2. Presence of a clinically important lung condition other than asthma. This includes
             current infection, bronchiectasis, pulmonary fibrosis, bronchopulmonary aspergillosis,
             or diagnoses of emphysema or chronic bronchitis (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
             other than asthma) or a history of lung cancer.

          3. Patients who have received omalizumab [Xolair] within 130 days of Visit 1.

          4. Patients who have received any biological to treat inflammatory disease within 5
             half-lives of visit 1
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephanie Korn, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin der Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz, Pneumologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <zip>55131</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>PD Dr. Stephanie Korn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>eosinophilic asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>mepolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Eosinophilia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

