<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02592304</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SvG2-4-13-07</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02592304</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preoperative Assessment of Mesorectal Lymph Nodes by Dual Energy CT. PUMK-DECT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preoperative Assessment of Mesorectal Lymph Nodes by Dual Energy CT. PUMK-DECT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Odense University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Odense University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endpoints subproject 1: To develop a reproducible method for the detection of lymph nodes by
      DECT in operation specimens from rectal resection for cancer. sub project 2: Primary
      endpoint: To evaluate the sensitivity and specificity for malignant lymph nodes in vitro RC
      specimens compared with histopathology. Secondary endpoint: To assess DECT as imaging tool
      for the diagnosis of malignant lymph nodes at RC. Histopathology will be used as
      reference.Subproject 3: Primary endpoint: To compare the sensitivity, specificity, positive-
      and negative predictive values, accuracy of DECT and standard MRI. Secondary: To evaluate the
      value of the gold standard for the use of imaging methods for the description of the lymph
      node, validated by histopathology. Secondary: to determine the value of tumor diagnostics
      using DECT.subproject 4: To assess the value of DECT as imaging tool for diagnosing response
      to chemo radiotherapy of malignant lymph nodes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background Long-term survival for patients with cancer of the rectum (RC) is through the last
      20 years dramatically improved from about 30% to 65% . Overall focus on disease with the
      creation of multidisciplinary teams, national quality databases certification of surgeons,
      etc. have contributed to the development especially in the last 10-15 years . The
      introduction of pre-operative Oncology, known as neoadjuvant treatment increased the survival
      rate by up to 10% in certain patient series. However, the prognosis remains poor for advanced
      cases, qua risk of metastasis and local cancer relapse.

      Surgical treatment remains the cornerstone of curative treatment of RC. Total mesorectal
      excision (TME) includes resection of both the tumor and the surrounding mesorectal fat. TME
      is currently used as the gold standard for surgical treatment of RC. The use of TME has
      reduced local relapse rate to less than 10%.

      TME surgery combined with preoperative chemotherapy and radiation therapy if the cancer is in
      an advanced stage (T3), and often with high-dose radiotherapy and chemotherapy in the most
      advanced cases of T-stage 4.

      Complications of TME are present in more than 40% of patients. Most often in the form of
      wound dehiscence, infection, sexual dysfunction, bowel disorders and the necessity of a
      stoma. More than 50% of patients have permanently reduced quality of life.

      Minimally invasive therapies (trans-anal endoscopic microsurgery (TEM)) for the curative
      treatment of early rectal cancers, is well-validated. The complication rate is low, and above
      all, the operative mortality of less than 1% even in the elderly and patients with
      comorbidities, opposed to 10% at standard surgery. The use of TEM surgery early in the rectum
      cancers in selected patients will thus be able to reduce the risk of complications and
      improve the overall long-term survival. Even though the disease-specific survival is reduced
      due to a less radical procedure. The Danish screening program for colorectal cancer will
      result in a significant increase in the detection of early cancers.

      Thus, over the past 10-15 years, there is developed a complex treatment algorithm with
      tailored surgery, in combination with oncological treatment if necessary. The full benefits
      of the available treatment options require that you pre-treatment, stage classify the disease
      so the patient can be allocated to the proper treatment. The tumor extent of ingrowth into
      the different layers in the rectum (T-stage) can now be carried out with great certainty
      preoperatively.

      Patients with tumor stage T1 may be candidates for TEM surgery because only 10% of these
      patients have metastases to the lymph nodes. Cancers of the stage T2 may be candidates for
      TEM if they have increased operative mortality risk. A local resection of the cancer is of
      course undesirable, in the lymph node metastases as they are not included in the resection.
      Distant metastases can with certainty be detected with CT and MRI scans. Preoperative
      assessment of lymph node involvement is difficult and uncertain for daring to use it to
      allocate candidates for local resection.

      The indication for TEM treatment of rectal cancers can potentially be extended if you could
      allocate patients independent of tumor stage - based on lymph node stage.

      The detection of disease spread to the lymph nodes has a decisive impact on the choice of
      treatment modality. Moreover the impact on prognosis and local recurrence.

        1. Local resection performed only for N0.

        2. The number of involved lymph nodes has a prognostic value for the outcome of surgery for
           RC.

        3. Detection of tumor cells in the lymph nodes at the mesorectal fascia (which forms
           circumferential resection margin CRM) increases the risk of recurrence. Patients must
           have neoadjuvant oncological treatment.

        4. Lymph nodes located outside the mesorectal fascia may require extended lymphadenectomy,
           to achieve a good oncological outcome and avoid relapse.

      Today, magnetic resonance scan (MRI) and trans rectal ultrasound (TRUS) is used as the gold
      standard in the imaging staging of RC. Studies have demonstrated high specificity for the
      assessment of T stage and CRM using the preoperative MRI. Comparative high specificity is
      obtained in the intermediate hands with TRUS.

      In contrast to T stage and CRM classification, the MR and TRUS have shown poor results
      compared to N-staging of RC. Even worse results arise for the use of conventional Computed
      Tomography Scan (CT) for lymph node diagnostics, with a median sensitivity of 80% (from 62.5
      to 91.9%) and median specificity of 77.8% (50- 87.9%).

      Research should be directed towards improvement of lymph node diagnostics by RC, in order to
      take full advantage of the differentiated treatments.

      Dual Energy Computed Tomography (DECT) is an imaging modality, which in recent years has
      gained a foothold in the diagnosis of several types of micro-lesions. DECT provides
      information on a tissue reaction when it is affected by different energy levels. This gives
      you information about its composition, based on the known K-edge value of different
      substances. K-edge is defined by the maximum visual attenuation of a substance in a DECT scan
      when it is affected by a certain amount of energy. The energy required to achieve a given
      k-edge depends on the individual substances atomic size, and therefore increases with the
      atomic mass.

      The technique is known from, for example, kidney stones diagnosis, pancreatic cancer staging,
      vascular anomalies such as classification of aortic aneurysms, detection of coronary plaques
      etc.

      A study from 2013 by Zalai Pan et al investigated the association between histologically
      confirmed gastric cancer, and the discovery of metastatic lymph nodes by DECT. Ninety-six
      patients were included. Two groups of radiologists were blinded to the endoscopic and
      histological findings. Lymph nodes of 6 mm were included in the N-staging. They found a
      sensitivity of 85.4% for N0, 84.4% N1, 91.7% N2. Furthermore, it showed a significant
      difference in the uptake of iodine (from the iodine-containing contrast) with the K-edge
      value of 33.20 keV, in malignant and non-malignant lymph nodes.

      Thus, there is the hope of both iodine and Gadolinium found in X-ray contrast agent, is
      absorbed in cancer tissues, and gives a recognizable signal in dual energy CT scanning.

      . Hypotheses

        1. It is possible to develop a standardized method for DECT scanning of the rectum
           specimens, removed during surgery.

        2. Metastatic lymph nodes suspected by DECT can be verified histopathological.

        3. DECT can increase the sensitivity and specificity of the diagnosis of lymph node
           compared to other imaging modalities.

        4. The effect of chemo-radiotherapy to the lymph nodes can be detected by DECT

      Study Design The study is a prospective observational study, based on patients with newly
      diagnosed rectum cancer at the Surgical Department A, Odense University Hospital.

      Patients will automatically be divided into 3 groups according to the preoperative
      stratification, in a group which will refer to the direct operation either TEM (group 1) or
      TME (GROUP2) after the preoperative imaging staging, and a group of 3 which will undergo two
      imaging phases, before and after the radio or chemo-radiotherapy before surgery.

      Methods Subproject 1: In Vitro DECT scan of rectal specimens. Subproject 1 scan without
      contrast

      Part 1 procedure: 3 patients with visible lymph nodes in the perirectal fat tissue by MRI are
      selected.

      Scenario 1 - after TME the specimens will be transported to the pathological institute for
      the preparation of 3mm. thick sections from the distal to the proximal resection rim.

        -  The product is placed in an aluminum lattice.

        -  All cuts of 3 mm gets numbered and photographed.

        -  The ex-vivo specimen scan is done; this is done in three different ways to determine the
           ideal technique.

             1. specimen is scanned between 2 gel plates

             2. specimens is scanned in the air

             3. specimens is scanned in flooded container

        -  All sections of 3 mm which is photographed and numbered, gets coupled with its DECT-scan
           image.

        -  The specimens are placed in formalin, and the same scans will be made 24 hours later.
           This is to compare the effect of formalin on the DECT scans of specimens.

        -  The ideal technique for the in vitro DECT scan of specimens will be determined.

      The scan with contrast

      Second part procedure: Nine patients with visible lymph nodes in the perirectal fat tissue by
      MRI will be selected.

        -  At the preparing meeting with the patients in KA (surgical day center, Svendborg), the
           patients will receive information about the study, provided written material, and
           consent will be obtained.

        -  questions in time from the information in KA, to participation in the study to time of
           surgery, may be directed to the investigator. The investigator is present at the time of
           surgery, and can take questions from the patient.

        -  Upon written consent from the patients the following procedure will be completed:

             1. 5 min. before the default central ligating of a. mesenteric inf. three patients
                will receive iv, iodine-containing contrast media, Omnipaque 350 mg iodine / ml, a
                total of 10 ml.

      For 3pt: intra venous Gadovist (Gadobutrol) 1.0 mmol / ml total 0.1 mmol / kg For 3pt: using
      rectoscope and a needle 5 ml of 1 mmol / ml Gadovist will be administered, for examination of
      the sentinel node.

      2. After TME the specimens are prepared and DECT scanned according to the ideal technique
      found by part-1 procedure.

      3. All lymph nodes, designated normal or pathological by DECT scan will be analyzed by a
      pathologist, who is blinded to the scan results. The lymph nodes will be assessed under the
      gold standard for pathological assessment of these (38). In this process it is possible to
      remove the lymph node for histopathological validation, as they are numbered according to
      photograph and scan images.

      4. Pathologist fills in Annex 2 5. Investigator assesses DECT scan pictures, together with
      the radiologist. 6. Investigator fills in Annex 1

      Subproject 2: assess the sensitivity and specificity of benign / malignant differentiation in
      DECT scanning of in Vitro rectal specimens.

        -  All included patients under the standardized preoperative imaging staging, by written
           consent, will get an additional DECT scan of the pelvis, either with Gadovist 1.0 mmol /
           ml, 0.1 mg / kg iv, or after administration of standard CT contrast Omnipaque. DECT
           scans can be performed in the same scanner and at the same session as the conventional
           CT of the thorax and abdomen. Images should result in ongoing 3mm thick sections of the
           pelvis, perpendicular to the rectum wall, from the anorectal transition to promontory
           level.

        -  Conventional CT scan of the thorax and abdomen, and MRI of the rectum will be used as
           usual, for the stratification of patients to appropriate treatment cf. Figure 1

        -  Endoscopist informs about the study and provides written material for signature when the
           detection of a rectal cancer is made.

        -  Questions from patients about participation in the study during the period between
           endoscopy and scanning can be directed to the investigator. The investigator is present
           at the time of the planned preoperative imaging staging, and accept any questions from
           the patient.

        -  Written acceptance delivered to the investigator in the preoperative imaging staging. A
           Copy of the acceptance will be provided the radiologist.

        -  Item 2-6 from subproject 1 second procedural element is repeated.

      Subproject 3: Best protocol during subproject 2, compared with standard MRI of malignant
      lymph nodes in the mesorectum in patients who have not received neoadjuvant therapy.

        -  As mentioned above, the aim is the inclusion of a total of 100 pts. With RC. After the
           1-year inclusion period analyzed the scanning images. All the preoperative in vivo
           images is reviewed by dedicated radiologists, with a particular focus on lymph node
           detection. Morphological criterions as used in MRI is used to determine whether a lymph
           node is malignant or not (39), both in the preoperative MR and DECT scanning.

        -  Radiologists are blinded to the results of the preoperative MRI staging and the
           histopathological results.

        -  Only patients who did not receive neoadjuvant therapy will be included in the subproject
           3, radiologist fills in Annex 1.

        -  Investigator compares in vivo scan results.

        -  Investigator compares in vivo scanning results with in vitro scan results and pathology
           results. The results are calculated as N0, N1 or N2

      Subproject 4: Evaluate DECT ability to follow changes in lymph node status of malignancy
      after adjuvant chemo-radiotherapy.

        -  Patients who have received adjuvant chemo-radiotherapy will be included.

        -  Following the same procedure as subproject 2 the patients are scanned a second time
           after adjuvant chemo-radiotherapy.

        -  The rescans are described according to the description procedure in subproject 3.

        -  Annex 1 is filled in.

        -  Annex 1 from before and after adjuvant radio chemotherapy will be compared.

      Statistics and data analysis

      Prerequisites for patient collection, for in Vitro DECT scanning after the administration of
      Gadovist as a contrast agent:

      Median figures for the diagnosis of lymph nodes on MRI in patients with RC are as follows:

        -  70% of patients with RC have no visible lymph nodes.

        -  15% of patients with RC have visibly benign lymph nodes.

        -  15% of patients with RC have visibly malignant lymph nodes (40). 5 shows an in average 5
           lymph nodes are seen per patient.

      A sample size analysis showed that a number of visible nodes 150 in total were needed to
      achieve a sensitivity of 70% (95% CI 56% -80%). Knowing that 5 Iymph nodes are seen in
      average per patient would necessitate a population of 100 pts. Included. (15% of 100) x5
      Iymph nodes= 75 visible benign Iymph nodes + (15% of 100) x5 Iymph nodes = 75 visible
      malignant lymph nodes.

      Total number of Iymph nodes = 150

      Ethical considerations The project must is approved by the research ethics committees in the
      Region of Southern Denmark and by the Data Inspectorate in Odense university hospital
      /Svendborg.

      First contact with the patient before inclusion in the project will take place on the day
      when, after having endoscopic examination, found a malignant tumor in the rectum. The patient
      will then be informed about the project by one of the doctors of the department, in an
      uninterrupted interview rooms designed for the information of patients and their relatives.
      Written information will be disclosed.

      Patients will have a minimum of 3 days of reflection before accepting participation in the
      project.

      When the patient accepts the participation in the project it will only be medically relevant
      information that will be obtained in the patient's chart. This will include age, gender,
      pregnancy, other diseases, allergies and information on details of the patient's cancer.

      DECT scan is a painless procedure that can be done in line with the preoperative scans.
      Disregarding the known risks of administering the contrast agent in the form of anaphylactic
      reactions, patients are not exposed to medical risk. Using gadolinum based contrast agents
      are suspected to be contributing to nephrogenic systemic fibrosis (NSF), but there is no case
      of this by the recent report of Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use (CHMP) in
      2007. Allergic reactions to iodinated contrast agents are described with a frequency of 0.2%,
      most commonly in the form of hives. Serious adverse reactions, as anaphylactic shock is
      described with a frequency of 0.01%.

      Patients in sub-project 1 are under the administration of contrast agent preoperatively under
      close surveillance by the anesthesiologists, and any possible allergic reaction could be
      treated immediately.

      Included patients will be exposed to increased radiological radiation, equivalent to 1-10 mSv
      and therefore only one additional CT scan of the abdomen.

      The selected specimens will be treated in exactly the same way as it is legally described in
      that matter. The investigator will, in the usual pathological preparation of the specimens,
      photograph the specimens and categorize them in the project gradient time. After completing
      the project, the picture material will be made anonymous.

      It should be emphasized that the results of the experiments related to the scans will not to
      have a therapeutic impact.

      Perspective In the event that the study shows that DECT enhances the quality of the imaging
      staging of patients with RC, the consequences will be substantial. If the accuracy of lymph
      node positive for RC reaches 90%, a local resection would be possible for the 10% of the
      lymph nodes positive T1 tumors. Furthermore you may be able to offer local resection for the
      75% of T2 and T3 early cancers that have not spread, and who otherwise meet the criterions
      for local resection. With secure node diagnostics, the surgical oncological treatment will
      improve in terms of prognosis and the rate of local relapse. Furthermore, one with better
      lymph node diagnostics one can avoid unnecessary neoadjuvant chemo-radiotherapy to the
      previous false-positive patients. They are between 25 and 50%.

      Medical oncology one will be able to assess the effect of chemotherapy on RC patients, with
      the possibility of optimizing the oncological treatment.

      Opportunities for practical implementation: We have access to dual-CT and contrast. The
      feasibility study is completed.

      Study design problems:

      There is a risk of categorizing some of the lymph nodes seen on the preoperative DECT scan as
      false positive, if they are not found in the in-vitro scans, due to the effect of radiation
      therapy. However this is a fact for both MRI and DECT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the detection of lymph nodes by DECT in specimens from rectal resection for cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measurments will be done in Hounsfield units, effective z-value and iodine, water and gadolinium concentrations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>sensitivity and specificity for the detection of malignant lymph nodes in vitro RC specimens compared with histopathology</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measurments will be done in Hounsfield units, effective z-value and iodine, water and gadolinium concentrations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>sensitivity, specificity, positive- ognegative predictive values, accuracy of DECT and standard MRI.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measurments will be done in Hounsfield units, effective z-value and iodine, water and gadolinium concentrations. Histopathological proved malignant lymph nodes will be compared to histopathological proved benign lymph nodes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DECT as imaging tool for diagnosing response to chemo radiotherapy of malignant lymph nodes, and tumors.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Rectal Cancer Regression Grade (RCRG) according to the three levels RCRG 1-3. RCRG 1: the tumour is either sterilised or only microscopic foci of adenocarcinoma remain; RCRG 2: marked fibrosis, but with macroscopic tumour still present; and RCRG 3: little or no fibrosis in the presence of abundant macroscopic tumour , based on measurments of Hounsfield units, effective z-value and iodine, water and gadolinium concentrations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dual energy ct</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dual energy computed tomography</intervention_name>
    <description>one extra scanning with a dual energy ct.</description>
    <arm_group_label>dual energy ct</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - All patients with an endoscopic suspected rectal cancer.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic kidney failure

          -  pregnancy

          -  rectal cancer recurrence

          -  known contrast allergies
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Issam al-Najami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Svendborg</city>
        <state>Southern Denmark</state>
        <zip>5700</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Issam al-najami, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+4524608398</phone>
      <email>issam.al-najami@rsyd.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 30, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 29, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 29, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 30, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Odense University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Issam al-Najami</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

