<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02599961</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UX007G-CL202</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-000389-69</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02599961</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Assess the Long Term Safety and Efficacy of UX007 in Subjects With Glucose Type 1 DS</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Extension Study to Assess the Long-term Safety and Efficacy of UX007 in Subjects With Glucose Transporter Type 1 Deficiency Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ultragenyx Pharmaceutical Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ultragenyx Pharmaceutical Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      UX007G-CL202 is an open-label, single-arm, multi center extension study to assess the
      long-term safety and efficacy of UX007 in Glut 1 DS. The study will enroll up to 40
      pediatric, adolescent and adult Glut 1 DS subjects who have completed the UX007G-CL201 study
      or participated in qualified ISTs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A Phase 2 study (UX007G-CL-201) is currently ongoing to assess safety and efficacy of UX007
      in reducing the frequency of seizures in Glut 1 DS patients. ISTs and other treatment
      programs are also evaluating UX007 as a treatment for Glut 1 DS.

      This open label long term safety and efficacy study (UX007G-CL202) will provide an
      opportunity for Glut 1 DS patients to be treated with UX007 for up to 3 years (or until
      market approval) under a single standardized protocol for maintenance therapy and consistent
      safety monitoring. The study is designed to obtain long-term safety information and evaluate
      maintenance of efficacy in a pediatric and adult Glut 1 DS population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of AEs and SAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of Adverse Events and Serious Adverse Events assessed as related to study drug</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maintenance of reduction in seizure frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long term Efficacy of UX007</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Long term efficacy in measures of neurological function and development delay using the Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long term Efficacy of UX007</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Long term efficacy in measures of neurological function and development delay using the Columbia Neurological Score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maintenance of UX007 treatment effect on gross motor function and movement disorders using the 6 Minute Walk Test</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maintenance of UX007 treatment effect on gross motor function and movement disorders using Paroxymal Exertional Dyskinesia (PED)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continued impact of UX007 treatment on clinical status and health related quality of life using the Clinical Global Impression Scales</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continued impact of UX007 treatment on clinical status and health related quality of life using the Short Form Health Surveys</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continued impact of UX007 treatment on clinical status and health related quality of life using thePediatric Evaluations of Disability Inventory Computer Adaptive Test (PEDI-CAT)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Glucose Transporter Type 1 Deficiency Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>UX007 (Triheptanoin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a single arm, open label study. All subjects will be on active treatment; no reference therapy or placebo will be administered.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>UX007</intervention_name>
    <description>UX007 is a liquid intended for oral (PO) administration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>UX007 (Triheptanoin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Triheptanoin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Glut 1 DS confirmed by cerebrospinal fluid glucose concentration.
             erythrocyte 3-O-methyl-D-glucose uptake assay, or SLC2A1 molecular genetic testing
             (Information obtained from Medical Records)

          -  Males and females aged at least 1 year old at the time of informed consent

          -  Completion of UX007G-CL201 study (NCT - 01993186). Glut1 DS patients who received
             UX007/triheptanoin treatment as apart of clinical studies, ISTs or expanded
             access/compassionate use treatment programs may be eligible at the discretion of the
             Sponsor

          -  Provide written informed consent or verbal assent (if possible) with written informed
             consent by a legally authorized representative after the nature of the study has been
             explained, and prior to any research related procedures

          -  Must, in the opinion of the investigator, be willing and able to complete all aspects
             of the study, and comply with accurate completion of the seizure diary

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test at
             Baseline and be willing to have additional pregnancy tests during the study. Females
             considered not of childbearing potential include those who have not experienced
             menarche, are post-menopausal (defined as having no mensus for at least 12 months
             without an alternative medical cause), or are permanently sterile due to total
             hysterectomy, bilateral salpingectomy, or bilateral oophorectomy.

          -  Participants of child-bearing potential or fertile males with partners of
             child-bearing potential who are sexually active must consent to use a highly-effective
             method of contraception as determined by the investigator from the period following
             the signing of the informed consent through 30 days after last dose of study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any known hypersensitivity to triheptanoin, that in the judgement of the investigator,
             places the subject at an increased risk for adverse effects

          -  History of, or current suicidal ideation, behavior and/or attempts

          -  Pregnant and/or breast feeding an infant

          -  Unwilling or unable to discontinue use of prohibited medication (barbiturates,
             pancreatic lipase inhibitors) or other substance that may confound study objectives.
             Use of up to 3 concomitant AEDs is allowed, provided dose has been stable at least 14
             days prior to Baseline

          -  Use of any Investigational Product, drug or supplement (other than UX007) within 30
             days prior to Baseline, or at any time during the study

          -  Has a condition of such severity and acuity, in the opinion of the investigator, that
             it warrants immediate surgical intervention or other treatment

          -  Has a concurrent disease or condition, or laboratory abnormality that, in the view of
             the investigator, places the subject at high risk of poor treatment compliance or of
             not completing the study, or would interfere with study participation or introduce
             additional safety concerns
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melanie M Brandabur, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ultragenyx Pharmaceutical Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Colorado - University of Colorado, Denver, School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33155</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cook Children's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Worth</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>76104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seattle Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Melbourne Brain Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Sant Joan De Deu</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08950</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Newcastle upon Tyne Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle upon Tyne</city>
        <zip>NE7 7DN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ultragenyx.com/</url>
    <description>Company Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glut 1 DS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carbohydrate Metabolism, Inborn Errors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

