<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02595645</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GENESIS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02595645</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GENESIS: Genetic Biopsy for Prediction of Surveillance Intervals After Endoscopic Resection of Colonic Polyps</brief_title>
  <acronym>GENESIS</acronym>
  <official_title>GENESIS: Genetic Biopsy for Prediction of Surveillance Intervals After Endoscopic Resection of Colonic Polyps</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Ulm</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Technische Universität München</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Specialized Medical Office for Gastroenterology Dornstadt</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>QIAGEN Gaithersburg, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Ulm</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer ist the 2nd most leading cancer among men and women in germany. Screening
      colonoscopy has the potential to detect premalignant lesions. By endoscopical resection of
      these lesions, colorectal cancers could be avoided. The decision for surveillance is made
      according to patients medical history, amount and histological characteristics of the
      resected polyps. Molecular guided decisions are still missing. Thus, further tools and
      mechanisms, beyond but in addition to endoscopy and histopathological, are strongly required
      to reduce such interval carcinomas and get a better and deeper inside into molecular
      alterations which occurs in premalignant lesions in the colon and describe risk populations
      which might benefit from shorter surveillance strategies by colonoscopy. Therefore GENESIS
      will enroll 100 patients, which underwent screening colonoscopy with polyp ectomy. All
      biopsies were stored and processed without formalin in special boxes (PaxGene by Qiagen®).
      After microdissection of polyp tissue and isolation of DNA targeted next generation
      sequencing of 38 cancer-related genes followed by bioinformatics and systems biology
      analyses. The sequencing results were correlated to the endoscopical and histopathological
      findings. In parallel we are collecting EDTA-blood samples for analysis of circulating
      cell-free DNA (cfDNA) to investigate the potential of liquid biopsies in premalignant
      colorectal lesions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer ist the 2nd most leading cancer among men and women in germany. Screening
      colonoscopy is provided for all people over 55 years in germany to detect and remove
      precancerous lesions (polyps) and thereby prevent the occurence of colorectal cancers.
      According to the result of screening colonoscopy and histopathological examination of the
      removed polyps the next examination will be planned. But so called interval carcinomas were
      observed with increasing incidence. Thus, further tools and mechanisms, beyond but in
      addition to endoscopy and histopathology, are strongly required to reduce such interval
      carcinomas and get a better and deeper inside into molecular alterations which occurs in
      premalignant lesions in the colon and describe risk populations which might benefit from
      shorter surveillance strategies by colonoscopy. Therefore we will enroll 100 patients, which
      underwent screening colonoscopy with polyp ectomy. Each polyp, provided for endoscopical
      removal, well be biopsied and stored separately. In each case, diagnosis is ensured. Per
      patient a maximum of 6 biopsies (from 6 different polyps) is intended. All biopsies were
      stored and processed without formalin in special boxes (PaxGene by Qiagen®). After
      microdissection of polyp tissue and isolation of DNA targeted next generation sequencing of
      38 genes (ACVR1B, DCC, MIER3, SLC9A9, AKT1, DMD, MLH1, SMAD2, APC, EP300, MSH2, SMAD4, ATM,
      ERBB2, MSH3, TCERG1, ATP6V0D2, FBXW7, MSH6, TCF7L2, BAX, FZD3, MYO1B, TGFBR2, BRAF, GPC6,
      NRAS, TP53, CASP8, KRAS, PIK3CA, WBSCR17, CDC27, MAP2K4, PIK3R1, CTNNB1, MAP7, PTPN12)
      followed by bioinformatics and systems biology analyses. The sequencing results were
      correlated to the endoscopical and histopathological findings. In parallel we are collecting
      EDTA-blood samples for analysis of circulating cell-free DNA (cfDNA). NGS targeted sequencing
      of these 38 genes should also be performed on cfDNA level to investigate the potential of
      liquid biopsies in premalignant colorectal lesions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic landscape of colonic polyps based on NGS-analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Are we able to describe risk populations based on clinical, histopathological and sequencing data which might bring a benefit for these cohort for shorter surveillance strategies by colonoscopy? What are the similarities in the altered genes, what are the differences? Are we able to define common signaling hubs?</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">101</enrollment>
  <condition>Colonic Polyps</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Polypectomy and NGS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients which underwent screening colonoscopy and fulfilling the inclusion criteria are eligible. Polyps were biopsied and underwent histopathological and genetic analyses</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Polypectomy and NGS</intervention_name>
    <description>NGS of 38 cancer-related genes, systems biological analyses, correlation genetics to pathology and clinical data</description>
    <arm_group_label>Polypectomy and NGS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  written informed consent

          -  indication of screening colonoscopy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  chronic inflammatory bowl disease

          -  known colorectal cancer (except curative treated colorectal cancers more than 5 years
             ago)

          -  disagreement in participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander G. Meining, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Ulm, Internal Medicine I, Interventional and experimental endoscopy (InExEn)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University Graz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <state>Steiermark</state>
        <zip>8036</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Specialized Medical Office for Gastroenterology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dornstadt</city>
        <state>Baden-Württemberg</state>
        <zip>89160</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Ulm, Internal Medicine I, Interventional and Experimental Endoscopy (InExEn)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <state>Baden-Württemberg</state>
        <zip>89081</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Technical University Munich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Munich</city>
        <state>Bavaria</state>
        <zip>81675</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Ulm</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thomas Seufferlein</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. Alexander Meining</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>colorectal adenoma</keyword>
  <keyword>colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>next generation sequencing</keyword>
  <keyword>liquid biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>screening colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>surveillance strategies</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polyps</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colonic Polyps</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

