<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02598869</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00011584</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02598869</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Posterior Subtenon Versus Intravitreal Injection of Triamcinolone Acetonide for Treatment of Uveitic Cystoid Macular Edema</brief_title>
  <official_title>Posterior Subtenon Versus Intravitreal Injection of Triamcinolone Acetonide for Treatment of Uveitic Cystoid Macular Edema (CME)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Health and Science University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Macular edema is the most common sight threatening complication of uveitis which can lead to
      permanent loss of central vision. Triamcinolone acetonide ( the study drug)injection for
      treatment of cystoid macular edema(CME) is well established. The purpose of this study is to
      compare the safety and efficacy of injecting the study drug inside the eye(intravitreal
      injection) and behind the eye(subtenon injection)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is randomized interventional non inferiority study that will enroll 30 adults aged
      18 or older with the diagnosis of cystoid macular edema secondary to non-infectious uveitis.
      Potential subjects will be recruited from the retina and uveitis clinics at the Casey Eye
      Institute, Oregon health and science University(OHSU). Potential recruits will be asked to
      sign and date the informed consent and a copy will be given to subject prior to any study
      procedure. Subjects will have a screening visit before the injection procedure so that the
      study doctor can decide if they meet the criteria to be in the study. This study requires 6
      visits to the clinic and will take 6 months to complete. During the screening visit, medical/
      surgical/ ocular history and will be collected from the subject and medical records.
      Laboratory tests will be performed to rule out infectious uveitis if the subject has not
      already had infectious types of uveitis ruled out since the time of diagnosis of uveitis.
      Urine collection for pregnancy test for females of childbearing potential will be done.
      Examination of subjects will include measurement of visual acuity, examination of the front
      and back part of the eye, measurement of the eye pressure . A scan of the retina will be
      obtained by spectral domain optical coherence tomography (SD-OCT). During the injection
      visit, history, examination, and pregnancy tests will be repeated in addition to receiving
      the injection. Subjects will be randomized to either injecting the study drug by intravitreal
      or subtenon routes. Examination after injection will be performed to rule out immediate
      complications. Then subjects will have 4 follow-up visits (2 weeks, 1 month, 3 months and 6
      months). During each visit, subjects will be asked about adverse events, concomitant
      medications, how their eyes feel in addition to obtaining a clinical examination and OCT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in best corrected visual acuity( BCVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1,3 and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Best corrected visual acuity will be assessed using the Snellen chart</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in central macular thickness in micrometers</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1,3 and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>A spectral domain optical coherence tomography device will be used to capture central macular thickness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of eyes that develop side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1,3 and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Uveitis</condition>
  <condition>Cystoid Macular Edema</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intravitreal triamcinolone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects will receive intravitreal injection of 2mg /0.05 ml of preservative free triamcinolone acetonide ( otherwise known as triesence)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>posterior subtenon triamcinolone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects will receive posterior subtenon injection of 40mg /1 ml of preserved triamcinolone acetonide ( otherwise known as kenalog)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Triamcinolone Acetonide</intervention_name>
    <description>injection of triamcinolone acetonide</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intravitreal triamcinolone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>posterior subtenon triamcinolone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>triesence</other_name>
    <other_name>kenalog</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or non-pregnant female at least 18 years of age at the time of consent

          -  One or both eyes having CME associated with non-infectious uveitis

          -  Subject has the ability to understand and sign the Informed Consent Form

          -  Subject is willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan,
             laboratory tests, and other study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy to triamcinolone acetonide

          -  History of any type of non-infectious uveitis without macular edema

          -  Vitreous hemorrhage

          -  Uveitis with infectious etiology

          -  CME due to non-uveitis causes

          -  Previous viral retinitis or uveitis

          -  Toxoplasmosis scar in study eye or scar related to viral retinitis

          -  Media opacity interfering with optical coherence tomography (OCT) or evaluation of the
             retina and vitreous

          -  Patient may not have had prior treatment for CME within the past 3 months including
             anti-VEGF (vascular endothelial growth factor), periocular or intravitreal steroid

          -  Pregnant or nursing women; females of childbearing potential who are unwilling or
             unable to use an acceptable method of contraception

          -  Subjects unwilling to comply with the study protocol or who are likely to be lost to
             follow-up within 6 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guex-Crosier Y. The pathogenesis and clinical presentation of macular edema in inflammatory diseases. Doc Ophthalmol. 1999;97(3-4):297-309. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10896343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sivaprasad S, McCluskey P, Lightman S. Intravitreal steroids in the management of macular oedema. Acta Ophthalmol Scand. 2006 Dec;84(6):722-33. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17083528</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leder HA, Jabs DA, Galor A, Dunn JP, Thorne JE. Periocular triamcinolone acetonide injections for cystoid macular edema complicating noninfectious uveitis. Am J Ophthalmol. 2011 Sep;152(3):441-448.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.ajo.2011.02.009. Epub 2011 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21652023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 6, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Phoebe Lin, MD,PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant professor of Ophthalmology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Triamcinolone acetonide</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Edema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Edema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone hexacetonide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone Acetonide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone diacetate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

