<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02596763</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014_45</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-002977-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02596763</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phone-based Safety Monitoring of Baclofen Prescriptions for Alcohol Use Disorder</brief_title>
  <acronym>BACLOPHONE</acronym>
  <official_title>Phone-based Safety Monitoring of the First Year of Baclofen Treatment for Alcohol Use Disorder: the BACLOPHONE Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Lille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Région Nord-Pas de Calais, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Groupement Interrégional de Recherche Clinique et d'Innovation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Lille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      BACLOPHONE is a prospective multicenter cohort study, conducted in two nearby French regions
      (Hauts-de-France and Normandie). BACLOPHONE consists of the monthly phone-based monitoring of
      792 patients during their first year of baclofen prescription for alcohol use disorder.

      The main objective of the study is to determine the rate of patients who stop baclofen due to
      an adverse event (AE) in the first year of treatment.The BACLOPHONE study also aims to
      determine which types of AEs and serious AEs are actually liable to baclofen, and which other
      types are more likely the consequence of confounding factors, e.g., concomitant alcohol,
      psychotropic medications or substance uses, and comorbidities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Inclusions are performed by any previously-labeled baclofen-prescribing physician in the
      Hauts-de-France or Normandie French regions.

      INITIAL ASSESSMENT PHONE CALLS

      In the 15 days following the inclusion, participants will receive two successive phone calls.
      The first call will be performed by a physician investigator of the study who will:
      re-explain the principles of the study to patients, check the absence of non-inclusion
      criteria, and note the medical history, date of baclofen initiation and current dose,
      undergoing medications and current doses, occurrence of AEs since the initiation of baclofen,
      birthdate, weight, and height. The physician will also check whether specific safety elements
      important with regards to the baclofen treatment are noticeable in the patient: history of
      seizures, suicide, and other concurrent substance use. The second phone call is performed by
      a clinical research associate (CRA) who will check the absence of non-inclusion criteria, and
      collects the 30 last-days reported alcohol use according to alcohol timeline follow-back
      (A-TLFB) method, date of initiation and current dose of baclofen, severity alcohol dependence
      questionnaire (SADQ), alcohol use disorder identification test (AUDIT), and A-B
      neuropsychological assessment schedule (ABNAS) which scores the current level of sedation in
      patients with psychotropic drugs.

      FOLLOW-UP PHONE CALLS

      During the subsequent one-year follow-up, two types of phone interviews are performed: 1)
      Monthly Standardized Interviews (MSI). MSIs consist in collecting the previous-month daily
      use of alcohol using the A-TLFB, the daily dose of baclofen across the previous month, the
      current ABNAS sedation score, any change in any associated medication, any change in any
      substance use, and any AE reported by the patient. No predefined list of AEs is used, as the
      investigator only asks the patient if he/she has noticed or experienced any unexpected
      symptoms of health issues since the last call. The daily dose distribution of baclofen, i.e.,
      hours and doses of baclofen intakes, are also systematically investigated in the patient. The
      average subjective level of craving for alcohol is self-scored by the patient using a 0-10
      verbal rating scale (i.e., 0 for no craving at all, to 10 for the most severe possible
      craving). The daily hours of maximum craving is also noted.

      2) Semi-standardized Pharmacovigilance Interviews (SPI) which are unscheduled, and are
      performed in the case of an AE reported by the patient to the CRA, or in the case of a direct
      phone call to the pharmacovigilance center by the patient or their baclofen prescriber, with
      the aim to report an AE. Data collected are: current baclofen dose and recent changes in
      baclofen dosing, recent and current drinking patterns, associated medications, type of AE,
      'serious' feature of the AE according to the definition of the Food and Drugs Administration,
      onset date and occurrence conditions. Patients can be secondarily re-contacted to assess the
      final outcome of the AE, and to determine the causality score of baclofen regarding the AE,
      using both the French causality method and the Naranjo's algorithm if applicable.

      DELAYED PHONE CALL IN THE CASE OF BACLOFEN CESSATION

      If baclofen is stopped for any reason during the year following the initiation, a last phone
      interview will be conducted by the CRA 3 months after baclofen cessation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Discontinuation of baclofen because of an AE</measure>
    <time_frame>First year of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The link between AE and the discontinuation of baclofen will be defined by the results of the analysis of the pharmacovigilance team. the one-year probability (with it 95% confidence interval) of baclofen discontinuation due to the occurrence of an AE will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Drop-outs, death, or baclofen discontinuation for other reasons than an AE will be treated as censoring events. A sensitivity analysis treating death or baclofen discontinuation for other reasons than an AE as competing risk will be performed using the approach of Kalbfleisch and Prentice.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of the different types of AEs and SAEs occuring on baclofen</measure>
    <time_frame>First year of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The AEs will be identified and reported by the &quot;Monthly Standardized CRA Phone Interviews&quot; and by the &quot;Unscheduled pharmacovigilance Phone Interviews&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between the occurrence of the first sedative AE and alcohol and baclofen dosing</measure>
    <time_frame>First year of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether there is an association between the occurrence of baclofen-related sedation and the concurrent doses of baclofen, alcohol and psychoactive drugs. , bivariate and multivariate time-varying Cox's regression models will be used to assess the impact of doses of baclofen and alcohol on occurrence of first sedative AE by using available exposition measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Causality of baclofen in the occurrence each AE</measure>
    <time_frame>First year of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the causality of baclofen in the occurrence of each AE, using the French method for assessing causality, and the Naranjo's algorithm (if applicable). For each AE, the determined causality of baclofen will thus be &quot;doubtful&quot;, &quot;possible&quot;, &quot;probable&quot;, and &quot;definite&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients whose prescription meets the official prescription requirements of the Temporary Recommendation for Use (TRU)</measure>
    <time_frame>First year of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>This proportion of patients will be calculated from data collected during &quot;Monthly Standardized CRA Phone Interviews&quot;, based on whether the patient has received the official TRU document which should systematically be given together with the prescription</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">792</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Baclofen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient with current alcohol use disorder included by any baclofen prescriber located in the French region of Nord - Pas-de-Calais - Picardie.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Baclofen</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient receiving an off-label baclofen treatment for alcohol use disorder for less than 1 month.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Baclofen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Agonist of GABA B receptors</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18 or more and under 80 years

          -  Receiving an off-label baclofen treatment for alcohol use disorder for less than 15
             days

          -  Mentally and physically able to participate in telephone interviews

          -  Reachable by phone

          -  Living in the Hauts-de-France or Normandie French regions

          -  Beneficiary of a health insurance plan

          -  Informed and signed consent before the beginning of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Baclofen prescriber not registered as investigator or not previously labeled for
             receiving consent, or not located in the regions of Hauts-de-France or Normandie

          -  Patient with ICD-10 criteria for other substance dependence (except tobacco) in the
             past three months.

          -  Patient not reachable by phone or unable to correctly understand the French language

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renaud JARDRI, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHRU de Lille</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Benjamin ROLLAND, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <email>benjamin.rolland@chru-lille.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Abbeville</city>
        <zip>80100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maroussia WILQUIN, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centres de Soins, d'Accompagnement et de Prévention en Addictologie (CSAPA) Le Cèdre Bleu</name>
      <address>
        <city>Armentières</city>
        <zip>59280</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie-Christine BLANQUARD, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arras</city>
        <zip>62000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dominique LEJEUNE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Aide aux Toxicomanes (SATO-Picardie)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beauvais</city>
        <zip>60000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean-Jacques PIK, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boulogne</city>
        <zip>62200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Frédéric TEISSIERE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Caen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caen</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>François VABRET, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicolas CABE, MD</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Carvin</city>
        <zip>62220</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hugo FAVRE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont</city>
        <zip>60600</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sophie VELASTEGUI, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dunkerque</city>
        <zip>59300</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cécile RICHEZ, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ham</city>
        <zip>80400</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michel SOCHALA, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hazebrouck</city>
        <zip>59190</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lucie MOLMY, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lens</city>
        <zip>62300</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christelle DUBOCAGE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Etablissement Public de Santé Mentale (EPSM)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Véronique VOSGIEN, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roubaix</city>
        <zip>59100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurent URSO, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Rouen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexandre BAGUET, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Pol sur Ternoise</city>
        <zip>62130</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dominique LEJEUNE, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-Amand-les-Eaux</city>
        <zip>59230</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charles LESCUT, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tourcoing</city>
        <zip>59200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laure SPINOSI, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valenciennes</city>
        <zip>59300</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexandre BONORD, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Off-label prescription</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcoholism</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacovigilance</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacoepidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Baclofen</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

