<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02597764</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H14-03205</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02597764</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diaphragmatic Breathing as an Adjunctive Therapy in the Management of Children With Bladder and Bowel Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of Diaphragmatic Breathing (DB) in the Management of Bladder and Bowel Disorders in Children: A Pilot Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Urination is a result of a complex neuro-muscular coordination which involves the action and
      arrangement of different parts of nervous systems as well as the muscular structure of the
      lower part of the urinary system. When there is an abnormal pattern in bladder and bowel
      habits without any known neuronal lesions, the condition is called bladder and bowel disorder
      (BBD). The symptoms can range from the feeling of rushing to the toilet, urinary accidents to
      urinating much less than expected during the day.

      The standard treatment for most cases of BBD starts with Standard Urotherapy (SU) which is a
      beneficial basic and harmless form of treatment widely used for all children with BBD. SU
      involves explaining of the problem to the children and their parents by the doctors and
      educating them on proper voiding mechanisms, sitting, and standing positions as well as how
      and when to void.

      The purpose of this study is to explore the possibility of testing the additive effectiveness
      of Diaphragmatic Breathing exercise (DB) as an alternative and harmless additional treatment
      to SU in children with BBD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with resolved incontinence at the end of the trial in each group (SU+DB vs. SU only).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of withdrawals during the treatment period.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of children adhering to the diaphragmatic breathing schedule that is given to them.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured by the information obtained from the mobile application used during the study period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment acceptability of the proposed intervention (diaphragmatic breathing).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be reported based on the participants and their parents' response to the Treatment Acceptability Questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in High Frequency (HF) variation of HRV from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured using state-of-the-art machine for recording heart rate variability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Power from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be calculated from the measurements obtained from state-of-the-art machine for recording heart rate variability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in heart rate from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pre-ejection Period (PEP) from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured using state-of-the-art machine for recording heart rate variability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in BBD score from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be reported based on participants' response to a validated 5-point Likert scale questionnaire for diagnosing BBD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pediatric Incontinence Questionnaire (PinQ) scores from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in average urinary flow rate (a uroflowmetry parameter) from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Average urinary flow rate will be measured using top-notch equipment for measuring uroflowmetry parameters. Average urinary flow rate will be reported in mL/sec.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in peak urinary flow rate (a uroflowmetry parameter) from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Peak urinary flow rate will be measured using top-notch equipment for measuring uroflowmetry parameters. Peak urinary flow rate will be reported in mL/sec.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in post-void residual volume from baseline to end of treatment period for both study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A hand-held ultrasound device will be used for the measurement of the post-void residual volume.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder and Bowel Disorder, Pediatric</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Urotherapy (SU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard Urotherapy (SU): A non-invasive therapy combining cognitive, behavioral and physical therapy. The study team will explain the problem to the children and their parents and educate them on the following: proper voiding mechanics, sitting, standing positions, how and when to void, techniques on relaxing pelvic floor muscles, and avoiding straining. An assessment of bowel habits will be done and their diet and drinking/voiding habits will be modified to maintain proper hydration with timed voiding. Voiding diaries will be provided for the assessment of the bladder and bowel habits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Urotherapy (SU) + Diaphragmatic Beathing (DB)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard Urotherapy (SU) with the addition of Diaphragmatic Breathing (DB):
A non-invasive breathing technique that is performed by a marked expansion of the abdomen (contracting diaphragm) rather than chest cavity during inspiration and tightening of the stomach muscles during expiration. Participants will lie on their back on a flat surface. Head is supported with a pillow and knees are bent forward supported by another pillow. Participants will place one hand on chest and the other on the abdomen, then start inhalation by moving their abdomen out against their hand, breathing in through their nose while keeping their chest and the other hand as still as possible. During expiration, the participants will tighten their abdominal muscles by forcing them inward and breathe out through pursed lips while keeping the hand on the chest as still as possible. Participants will be asked to perform this exercise for 10 minutes 3 times daily for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diaphragmatic Breathing</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Urotherapy (SU) + Diaphragmatic Beathing (DB)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Urotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Urotherapy (SU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Urotherapy (SU) + Diaphragmatic Beathing (DB)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Children with bladder and bowel disorders (BBD) will be diagnosed by the attending
        pediatric urologists via a combination of thorough clinical history, physical examination,
        BBD Questionnaire, uroflowmetric evaluation, and voiding and stool diary.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known anatomic or neurological lower urinary tract abnormalities such as posterior
             urethral valve, urethral obstruction or stricture, ectopic ureters, congenital
             abnormalities of the spinal cord, or any previous surgery of the lower urinary tract.

          2. Current use of medication or treatments which affects bladder or ANS function. These
             include anti-cholinergics, anti-psychotics, anti-depressants, and neuromodulators.

          3. Any conditions or disorders that would affect the cardiovascular system or the
             activity of the ANS.

          4. Serious pulmonary issues or diaphragmatic problems that would interfere with the
             practice of diaphragmatic breathing technique.

          5. Psychological/behavioral abnormalities severe enough to prevent the cooperation of the
             child with the study coordinator or the urologist.

          6. Inability to provide consent.

          7. Inability to speak and/or understand in English.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kourosh Afshar, MD, MHSc, FAAP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mir Sohail Fazeli, MD, PhD(c)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Paul Collet, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BC Children's and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6H 3N1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 27, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 5, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kourosh Afshar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Study Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diaphragmatic breathing (DB)</keyword>
  <keyword>Bladder and bowel disorders (BBD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Autonomic nervous system (ANS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart rate variability (HRV)</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep breathing</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized controlled trial (RCT)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

