<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02591758</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-1919</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02591758</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Novel Vitality Indices Derived From the Hexoskin in Patients Affected With Angina Undergoing Coronary Revascularization or Medical Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>NOVA-SKIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Novel Vitality Indices Derived From the Hexoskin in Patients Affected With Angina Undergoing Coronary Revascularization or Medical Therapy (NOVA-SKIN Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Montreal Heart Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Montreal Heart Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The first and foremost manifestation of ischemic heart disease (IHD) is angina. At a global
      level, patients with chronic angina are at risk of poor vital status and deconditioning.
      Medical therapy and coronary revascularization using coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) or
      percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) can effectively relieve angina . In spite of all the
      available treatment options, the assessment of angina remains a challenge. Angina has a
      cyclical pattern and will naturally worsen and improve as days go by. Likewise, angina can be
      significantly biased by the placebo effect. Clinically angina is most frequently quantified
      with the Canadian Cardiovascular Society (CCS) classes system. In research protocols, angina
      is often quantified with health-related quality of life questionnaires and diaries. None of
      the tool available accounts for an important phenomenon called ischemic threshold adaptation,
      which could be defined as a limitation of their activity level under the ischemic level,
      which will translate into fewer angina episodes and a seemingly stable condition. Better
      clinical assessment tools that take into consideration the ischemic threshold adaption are
      needed.

      Despite increased interest in wearable biometrics clothing in medicine, no prospective study
      has documented their utility to assess angina and to monitor the rehabilitation in cardiac
      patients. The Hexoskin™ is a biometric vest that can collect physiological data from
      individuals in their natural daily living environment. Currently, the use of biometric
      clothing is confined to a niche exploited exclusively by health enthusiasts, athletes or
      astronauts. As we enter this new age of virtual healthcare, tools like wearable biometrics
      could represent a giant leap forward in assisting healthcare professionals and patients. This
      will translate a better assessment of their health status, will allow physicians to target
      the right treatment strategy, ultimately improving case-selection and outcomes.

      Our objective is to prospectively validate the wearable biometrics clothing Hexoskin™ against
      established standards used to assess chronic stable angina. In addition, the investigators
      want to derive a novel vitality index from the data generated by this device that will
      subsequently be used to propose a new angina classification system that will account for
      ischemic threshold adaptation. Moreover, the investigators want to evaluate the safety and
      efficacy of Hexoskin monitor patients undergoing home-based cardiac rehabilitation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the Hexoskin measures : Correlation between the heart rate as determined by the Hexoskin with the reference data provided by the Holter monitoring.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months to three months</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate (R-R) variability, Average heart rate, Maximum ST-segment depression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the vitality index with angina class as assessed by the CCS Class</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the vitality index with quality of life using the WHO-QoL</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in the vitality index compared with changes quality-of-life as measured by the World Health Organization QoL questionnaire (WHO-QoL);</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the vitality index with Anxiety using the GAD-7</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in the vitality index compared with changes of anxiety as measured by the General Anxiety Disorder Scale - 7 .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the vitality index with quality of life using the SF-36</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in the vitality index compared with changes quality-of-life as measured by the Short-Form 36 (SF-36).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the vitality index with Anxiety using the ASI-3</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in the vitality index compared with changes of anxiety as measured by the Anxiety Sensitivity Index (ASI-3)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Responsiveness to the revascularisation procedure or medical treatment : Correlation between changes in vitality index as measured by the Hexoskin and the CCS class.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Responsiveness to the revascularisation procedure or medical treatment : Correlation between changes in heart rate as measured by the Hexoskin and treadmill stress test.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the vitality index with angina class as assessed by the Seattle Angina Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validation of the Hexoskin measures : Correlation between the arrhythmias as determined by the Hexoskin with the reference data provided by the Holter monitoring.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major adverse cardiac events (MACE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>Mortality, re-infarction, revascularization procedure, ventricular arrhythmias and re-hospitalisation for angina.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety outcomes of the Hexoskin (Allergies, Intolerance)</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>Allergies, Intolerance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resource utilisation : Any overnight hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>Rehospitalisation: Any overnight stay at the hospital.
Coronary care unit admission: Any overnight stay at the coronary care unit.
Intensive care unit admission: Any overnight stay at the intensive care unit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical contact (Number of phone calls or unplanned clinic or emergency visit to the physician per patient)</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>Any phone call or unplanned clinic visit to a physician.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Remote signal transmission integrity</measure>
    <time_frame>Two to three months</time_frame>
    <description>o Defined as the number of seconds the Hexoskin does not transmit any interpretable data divided by the total time the Hexoskin has been worn.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Stable Angina</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stable Angina with coronary angiogram</arm_group_label>
    <description>This study aims to correlate the biometric data collected and derived from the Hexoskin with the standard physiological assessment, in patients referred for coronary angiography for limiting angina. Afterwards, the clinician will decide of the best treatment strategy for the patient: coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) or percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) or no revascularization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hexoskin Vest</intervention_name>
    <description>The Hexoskin vest will be used at home to monitor the patient before and after the coronary angiography, during a treadmill test and during a home cardiac rehabilitation program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stable Angina with coronary angiogram</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cardiac rehabilitation program</intervention_name>
    <description>A 6 sessions home cardiac rehabilitation program will be prescribed to the patient 2 to 4 weeks after the coronary angiogram. Those sessions will take place under Hexoskin surveillance. One session will take place at our specialized institution and six sessions will take place at home over the time span of two to three weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stable Angina with coronary angiogram</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anxiety assessment as determined by the GAD-7</intervention_name>
    <description>Anxiety assessment using the General Anxiety Disorder (GAD-7) scale, at the end of the study, to see if the Hexoskin relieved the anxiety patients can feel at home when exercising after a percutaneous coronary intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stable Angina with coronary angiogram</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Angina assessment with the angina diary, the SAQ and the SF-36</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Stable Angina with coronary angiogram</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Angina assessment with the angina diary, the Seattle Angina Questionnaire (SAQ) and the Short Form 36 (SF-36)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise stress test</intervention_name>
    <description>Using the RAMP protocol before and after the coronary intervention, under Hexoskin surveillance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stable Angina with coronary angiogram</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Holter monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>24-hour Holter monitoring before and after the coronary angiogram with simultaneous Hexoskin reading.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stable Angina with coronary angiogram</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Thirty (30) subjects who meet all of the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion
        criteria and who successfully wear the Hexoskin vest in the run-in will be eligible to
        study participation. Subjects will be recruited as outpatient, from the specialized angina
        clinic at the Montreal Heart Institute (MHI) or as an inpatient, after screening by the
        research team.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent form

          2. Patient 18 years of age

          3. History of coronary artery disease that consists of a well-documented medical history
             (over 3 months prior to the enrolment) of myocardial infarction or significant
             coronary artery disease with non-invasive angiographic confirmation.

          4. Symptoms that support the diagnosis of chronic angina and/or a history of an abnormal
             exercise response limited by angina and/or electrocardiograph (ECG) changes.

          5. All-comers with stable or unstable moderate-to-severe angina pectoris (Canadian
             Cardiovascular Class [CCS] II-III or IV subsequently medically stabilized (minimum 7
             days) despite guideline directed medical therapy due to a reversible myocardial
             ischemia deemed sufficiently severe to justify a coronary angiography.

          6. Patient can be treated percutaneously, surgically or medically.

          7. Willing to undertake a cardiac rehabilitation program at home

          8. Patient understands the nature of the device and is able to wear the Hexoskin for 24h
             Patient is willing to comply with specified follow-up evaluation and can be contacted
             by telephone.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Recent (&lt;1 week) acute coronary syndrome

          2. Decompensated congestive heart failure (CHF) or hospitalization due to CHF during the
             3 months prior to screening.

          3. Severe valvular disease

          4. High-risk criteria demonstrated on the treadmill stress test (Appendix D5)

          5. With contraindications to, unable to, or with other co-morbidities that may prevent or
             interfere with the ability to perform treadmill stress test (including but not limited
             to : pulmonary hypertension, functionally limiting chronic obstructive pulmonary
             disease (COPD), history of pulmonary tuberculosis, prior hospitalization for acute
             exacerbation of chronic lung disease, home oxygen use, chronic oral steroid therapy
             that can limit exercise capacity, functionally limiting peripheral artery disease.

          6. Patients for whom an home-based cardiac rehabilitation is contraindicated or not
             possible

          7. Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 40% or patients with defibrillator or
             cardiac resynchronisation pacemaker.

          8. Severe left ventricular (LV) hypertrophy (defined as septal wall thickness at
             echocardiography of more than &gt; 13 mm)

          9. Congenital cardiac defects, severe uncontrolled hypertension (seated systolic blood
             pressure &gt; 180 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure &gt; 110 mm Hg), severe anemia, suspected
             or known dissecting aortic aneurysm, acute myocarditis or pericarditis,
             thrombophlebitis or pulmonary embolism.

         10. Presence of electrocardiographic or other abnormalities/factors that could interfere
             with exercise electrocardiograph interpretation or may lead to a false positive stress
             test (See appendix B for more details)

         11. Clinically significant arrhythmias, rapid atrial fibrillation (&gt; 110 beats per minute
             at rest) or atrioventricular conduction block greater than first degree.

         12. Planned need for concomitant cardiac surgery, such as valve surgery.

         13. Refusal or an inability to perform cardiac rehabilitation.

         14. Moribund patients, or patients with comorbidities limiting life expectancy &lt; 1 year.

         15. Any contra-indications to the treadmill stress test (See Appendix D6)

         16. Mental condition (psychiatric or organ cerebral disease) rendering the subject unable
             to understand the nature, scope and possible consequences of the trial or mental
             retardation or language barrier such that the patient is unable to give informed
             consent.

         17. Potential for non-compliance towards the requirements in the study protocol and/or
             follow-up visits

         18. Any other conditions that, in the opinion of the investigator, are likely to prevent
             compliance with the study protocol or pose a safety concern if the subject
             participates in the study.

         19. Currently enrolled in another investigational device or drug trial that has not
             completed the primary endpoint or that clinically interferes with the current study
             endpoints.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Jolicoeur Jolicoeur, MD, M.Sc., MHS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Montreal Heart Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marc Jolicoeur, MD, M.Sc., MHS</last_name>
    <phone>514-376-3330</phone>
    <phone_ext>3685</phone_ext>
    <email>marc.jolicoeur@icm-mhi.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Luc Harvey, RN</last_name>
    <phone>514-376-3330</phone>
    <phone_ext>2776</phone_ext>
    <email>luc.harvey@icm-mhi.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montreal Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H1T 1C8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc Jolicoeur, MD, M.Sc., MHS</last_name>
      <phone>514-376-3330</phone>
      <email>marc.jolicoeur@icm-mhi.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marie-Gabrielle Lessard, RN, B.Sc.</last_name>
      <phone>514-376-3330 ext. 2094/2598</phone>
      <email>marie-gabrielle.lessard@icm-mhi.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Avram, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 30, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Montreal Heart Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marc Jolicoeur</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hexo-Skin</keyword>
  <keyword>Hexoskin</keyword>
  <keyword>NOVA-SKIN</keyword>
  <keyword>angina</keyword>
  <keyword>biometric vest</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Angina Pectoris</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angina, Stable</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

