<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02599090</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2008-0059 Phase II</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01617</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02599090</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Sorafenib With Radiation and Temozolomide in Newly Diagnosed Glioblastoma or Gliosarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Portion of Multi Phase Study of Sorafenib With Radiation and Temozolomide in Newly Diagnosed Glioblastoma or Gliosarcoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find the highest tolerable dose of sorafenib
      that can be given in combination with temozolomide. The safety of this combination will also
      be studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Study Drugs:

      Sorafenib is designed to stop the cell growth and to block the formation of new blood vessels
      (the tubes that carry blood around the body), which are involved in the growth and
      development of tumors.

      Temozolomide is designed to kill cancer cells by damaging DNA (the genetic material of
      cells). The damaged DNA may cause tumor cell death.

      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be assigned to 1 of 4
      groups based on when you joined this study. You will remain in the same group for the entire
      study. In this study, the dose of the study drugs is different from group to group, and the
      doses are also different during and after radiation. During radiation, the study drugs and
      doses are as follows:

        -  If you are in Group 1, you will take temozolomide.

        -  If you are in Groups 2 or 3, you will take temozolomide and the lower dose of sorafenib.

        -  If you are in Group 4, you will take temozolomide and the higher dose of sorafenib.

        -  During radiation, all the groups will take the same dose of temozolomide.

      After Radiation:

        -  If you are in Groups 1 or 2, you will take the higher dose of temozolomide on a shorter
           cycle and the higher dose of sorafenib.

        -  If you are in Group 3, you will take the lower dose of temozolomide on a longer cycle
           and the lower dose of sorafenib.

        -  If you are in Group 4, you will take the lower dose of temozolomide on a longer cycle
           and the higher dose of sorafenib.

      The amount of study drugs you receive may change if you experience side effects. If at any
      time you experience any intolerable side effects, tell the study doctor right away.

      Study Drug Administration:

      During Radiation:

      As a part of standard of care, you will receive radiation therapy Monday-Friday for a total
      of 30 radiation treatments (about 6 weeks).

      Every day while you are receiving radiation, you will take the temozolomide by mouth once a
      day (up to a maximum of 7 weeks). On Monday-Friday, you will take temozolomide 1 hour before
      radiation therapy. On Saturday and Sunday, you will take temozolomide in the morning.

      You should swallow temozolomide whole, one right after the other, without chewing them. If
      you vomit while taking temozolomide, you cannot take more capsules before the next scheduled
      dose. They should be taken on an empty stomach (at least 1 hour before and 2 hours after
      eating) with 1 cup (about 8 oz.) of water.

      Every day while you are receiving radiation, you will take sorafenib by mouth 2 times a day
      (in the morning and evening) (up to a maximum of 7 weeks). You should take sorafenib without
      food (1 hour before or 2 hours after eating), with at least 1 cup (8 oz.) of water. If you
      are in Group 1, you will not take sorafenib.

      After Radiation:

      You will not take the study drug(s) for about 4 weeks after the radiation therapy ends.

      After 4 weeks:

        -  If you are in Group 1 or 2, on Days 1-5 of every 28-day study cycle, you will take
           temozolomide by mouth once a day.

        -  If you are in Group 3 or 4, on Days 1-21 of every cycle, you will take temozolomide by
           mouth once a day.

      Every day of each cycle, all groups will take sorafenib by mouth 2 times (in the morning and
      evening).

      Study Visits:

      During Radiation:

      Once a week while you are receiving radiation therapy, you will be asked about any drugs you
      may be taking and if you have experienced any side effects. Your blood pressure will be
      measured. Blood (about 3-4 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      After Radiation:

      About 3-4 weeks after the end of radiation therapy, you will have a MRI scan to check the
      status of the disease.

      On Day 1 of every cycle, the following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  You will have a performance status evaluation.

        -  You will be asked about any drugs you may be taking and if you have experienced any side
           effects.

        -  Blood (about 3-4 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      On Days 7, 14, and 21 of Cycle 1 and on Days 7 and 14 (or 21) of Cycles 2 and beyond, blood
      (about 3-4 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      On Day 1 of every other cycle (Cycles 3, 5, 7, and so on), you will have a MRI scan to check
      the status of the disease.

      Every week of Cycle 1, your blood pressure will be measured.

      Length of Study:

      You will be on study for about 15 months total. You will be taken off study early if the
      disease gets worse or you experience intolerable side effects.

      End-of-Study Visit:

      After you go off study, you will have an end-of-study visit. At this visit, the following
      tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vital signs.

        -  You will be have a performance status evaluation.

        -  You will be asked about any drugs you may be taking and if you have experienced any side
           effects.

        -  You will have a neurological exam.

        -  You will have a MRI scan to check the status of the disease.

        -  Blood (about 3 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      This is an investigational study. Temozolomide is FDA approved and commercially available for
      the treatment of brain tumors. Sorafenib is FDA approved and commercially available for the
      treatment of kidney cancer, but it is experimental for use in brain tumors. In addition, the
      combination of temozolomide and Sorafenib is experimental for use in brain tumors. At this
      time, the combination is only being used in research.

      Up to 51 participants will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Multi phase study did not progress to Phase II. Phase I registered as NCT00734526.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>December 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>15 Months or till progressive disease, severe toxicity or death.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Gliosarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Temozolomide + Radiation, Followed by Higher Dose Temozolomide in a Shorter Cycle
Temozolomide 75mg/m^2 daily during radiation therapy, and 150mg/m^2 in the first cycle of adjuvant therapy. Dose Level 1 will receive sorafenib in the adjuvant phase (following radiation therapy) at the dose of 400mg BID in combination with standard dose temozolomide 150-200 mg/m^2 two days out of 28 day cycle. Radiotherapy 2.0 Grey (Gy)/day given daily 5 days per week for total of 60.0 Gy over 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Temozolomide + Lower Dose Sorafenib + Radiation, Followed by Higher Dose Temozolomide in a Shorter Cycle + Higher Dose Sorafenib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Temozolomide + Lower Dose Sorafenib + Radiation, Followed by Lower Dose Temozolomide in a Longer Cycle + Lower Dose Sorafenib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Temozolomide + Higher Dose Sorafenib + Radiation, Followed by Lower Dose Temozolomide in a Longer Cycle + Higher Dose Sorafenib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Groups 1 &amp; 2: 75 mg/m^2 Once Daily by Mouth During Radiation; 4 Weeks after Completion of Radiation, 150-200 mg/m^2 Once Daily by Mouth Days 1-5 of 1st 28-Day Cycle, then 75 mg/m^2 Once Daily by Mouth Days 1-5 for Subsequent 28-Day Cycles.
Groups 3 &amp; 4: 75 mg/m^2 Once Daily by Mouth During Radiation; 4 Weeks after Completion of Radiation, 75-100 mg/m^2 Once Daily by Mouth Days 1-21 every 28-Day Cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Total of 60 Gy delivered over 30 Days (approximately 6 weeks).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Radiotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>XRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sorafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Group 1: 4 Weeks after Completion of Radiation, 400 mg Twice Daily by Mouth.
Group 2: 200 mg Twice Daily by Mouth during Radiation; 4 Weeks after Completion of Radiation, 400 mg Twice Daily by Mouth.
Group 3: 200 mg Twice Daily by Mouth during Radiation; 4 Weeks after Completion of Radiation, 200 mg Twice Daily by Mouth.
Group 4: 400 mg Twice Daily by Mouth during Radiation; 4 Weeks after Completion of Radiation, 400 mg Twice Daily by Mouth.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Level 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BAY43-9006</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histopathologically proven diagnosis of glioblastoma. Since gliosarcoma is a variant
             of glioblastoma, gliosarcoma is also an eligible diagnosis.

          2. Patients must have at least 1 block of tumor tissue available for submission to the
             central pathologist for analysis of gene expression status by QRT-PCR; there must be
             at least 1 cm^2 of tumor from the block when cut on a slide: fresh frozen tumor tissue
             acquisition is also encouraged, but not required. Unstained slide submission without a
             block submission is not acceptable for study entry.

          3. Diagnosis must be established by open biopsy or tumor resection. Patients who have
             only had a stereotactic biopsy are not eligible..

          4. The tumor must have a supratentorial component.

          5. Patients must have recovered from the effects of surgery, postoperative infection, and
             other complications before study registration.

          6. All patients must sign an informed consent indicating that they are aware of the
             investigational nature of this study.

          7. A diagnostic contrast-enhanced MRI or CT scan (if MRI is contraindicated) of the brain
             must be performed postoperatively in the period between surgery and initiation of
             radiation therapy.

          8. Therapy must begin &lt;/=5 weeks after the most recent brain tumor surgery.

          9. History/physical examination within 14 days prior to study registration.

         10. Neurologic examination within 14 days prior to study registration.

         11. Documentation of steroid doses within 14 days prior to study registration and stable
             or decreasing steroid dose within 5 days prior to registration.

         12. Karnofsky performance status of &gt;/= 60.

         13. Age &gt;/= 18 years.

         14. Patients with well-controlled hypertension are eligible (systolic blood pressure of
             &lt;/= 140 mgHg or diastolic pressure &lt;/= 90 mgHg).

         15. Complete blood count (CBC)/differential obtained within 14 days prior to study
             registration, with adequate bone marrow function as defined below: Absolute neutrophil
             count (ANC) &gt;/= 1500 cells/mm^3; Platelets &gt;/= 100,000 cells/mm^3;Hemoglobin &gt;/= 10
             g/dl.

         16. Adequate renal function, as defined below: Serum creatinine &lt;/= 1.7 mg/dl within 14
             days prior to study registration

         17. Adequate hepatic function, as defined below: Bilirubin &lt;/= 2.0 mg/dl within 14 days
             prior to study registration; ALT &lt;/= 2 x upper limit of normal range (ULN) within 14
             days prior to study registration; AST &lt;/= 2 x ULN range within 14 days prior to study
             registration

         18. Fasting cholesterol &lt; 300 mg/dL (9.0 mmol/L) and fasting triglycerides &lt; 2.5 times ULN

         19. International normalized ratio (INR) &lt; 1.5 or a PT/PTT within normal limits for
             patients not on anti-coagulation treatment

         20. Patients receiving anti-coagulation treatment with an agent such as warfarin or low
             molecular weight heparin may be allowed to participate with the following criteria:
             For patients on prophylactic anticoagulation therapy (low-dose warfarin): INR level &lt;
             1.5; Patients on prophylactic dose or full dose low molecular weight heparins are
             eligible provided that the patient has no active bleeding or pathological condition
             that carries a high risk of bleeding;

         21. (20. continued) Patients on full-dose anticoagulants (e.g., warfarin) are eligible
             provided that both of the following criteria are met: (a) Patient has an in-range INR
             (usually between 2-3) on a stable dose or oral anticoagulant or on a stable dose of
             low molecular weight heparin. (b) Patient has no active bleeding or pathological
             condition that carries a high risk of bleeding.

         22. If the patient's mental status precludes his/her giving informed consent, written
             informed consent may be given by the responsible family member.

         23. For females of child-bearing potential, negative serum pregnancy test within 72 hours
             prior to starting temozolomide

         24. Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (barrier method of birth control) prior to study entry and for the duration of study
             participation. Men should use adequate birth control for at least six months after the
             last administration of sorafenib or temozolomide.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior invasive malignancy (except for non-melanomatous skin cancer) unless disease
             free for &gt;/= 3 years.

          2. Recurrent or multifocal malignant gliomas

          3. Metastases detected below the tentorium or beyond the cranial vault.

          4. Prior chemotherapy or radiosensitizers for cancers of the head and neck region; note
             that prior chemotherapy for a different cancer is allowable.

          5. Prior use of Gliadel wafers or any other intratumoral or intracavitary treatment are
             not permitted.

          6. Prior radiotherapy to the head or neck (except for T1 glottic cancer), resulting in
             overlap of radiation fields.

          7. Severe, active co-morbidity, defined as follows: Cardiac disease - Congestive heart
             failure &gt; class II New York Heart Association (NYHA). Patients must not have unstable
             angina (anginal symptoms at rest) or new onset angina (began within the last 3 months)
             or myocardial infarction within the past 6 months; Cardiac ventricular arrhythmias
             requiring anti-arrhythmic therapy; Acute bacterial or fungal infection requiring
             intravenous antibiotics at the time of registration; Chronic Hepatitis B or C
             infection;

          8. (7. continued) Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease exacerbation or other respiratory
             illness requiring hospitalization or precluding study therapy at the time of
             registration; Hepatic insufficiency resulting in clinical jaundice and/or coagulation
             defects;

          9. (7. continued) Known history or symptoms and laboratory results consistent with
             Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) based upon current CDC definition (note,
             however, that HIV testing is not required for entry into this protocol. The need to
             exclude patients with AIDS from this protocol is necessary because the treatments
             involved in this protocol may be significantly immunosuppressive); Major medical
             illnesses or psychiatric impairments that in the investigator's opinion will prevent
             administration or completion of protocol therapy;

         10. (7. continued) Active connective tissue disorders, such as lupus or scleroderma, that
             in the opinion of the treating physician may put the patient at high risk for
             radiation toxicity; Arterial thrombotic or embolic events such as a cerebrovascular
             accident including transient ischemic attacks within the past 6 months; Pulmonary
             hemorrhage/bleeding event &gt; Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Effects (CTCAE) Grade
             2 within 4 weeks of first dose of study drug;

         11. (7. continued) Any other hemorrhage/bleeding event &gt; CTCAE Grade 3 within 4 weeks of
             first dose of study drug; Serious non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture; Evidence
             or history of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy

         12. Uncontrolled hypertension defined as systolic blood pressure &gt; 140 mmHg or diastolic
             pressure &gt; 90 mmHg, despite optimal medical management.

         13. Major surgery, open biopsy or significant traumatic injury within 4 weeks of first
             study drug.

         14. Use of St. John's Wort or rifampin (rifampicin).

         15. Pregnancy or women of childbearing potential and men who are sexually active and not
             willing/able to use medically acceptable forms of contraception; this exclusion is
             necessary because the treatment involved in this study may be significantly
             teratogenic.

         16. No tissue provided for histopathologic review and QRT-PCR analysis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vinay K. Puduvalli, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 6, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Sorafenib</keyword>
  <keyword>Temozolomide</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>XRT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gliosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

