<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00494143</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A4372-R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00494143</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metabolic Cost Savings for Transtibial Amputees Wearing the Controlled Energy Storage and Return (CESR) Foot</brief_title>
  <official_title>Metabolic Cost Savings for Transtibial Amputees Walking With the CESR Foot</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine if below-knee amputees will walk with better efficiency wearing a CESR foot
      which stores energy at heel strike and releases energy releases energy during push-off.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Amputees work harder and have greater oxygen cost during ambulation compared to those without
      limb loss. Therefore, amputees generally walk slower and tire more easily than intact
      individuals. The loss of the ankle as a propulsive and supportive joint requires the amputee
      to perform extra muscular work with the hip, trunk and contralateral limb during ambulation.
      This increased muscular activity consumes additional metabolic energy and means that amputees
      have to work harder to walk at the same speed as intact individuals. For some amputees, this
      extra effort is simply not possible, and their loss of functional ambulation leads to a
      progressive spiral of disuse, reduced capacity and more disuse. Conversely, greater mobility
      can lead to greater activity and even more successful return to the workplace. The health
      consequences for amputees who do not maintain functional ambulation is multifactorial and
      costly, not only in terms of dollars for the institutions committed to their care, but also
      for the individuals themselves in terms of decreased quality of life, increased disability
      and pain. Recent developments have resulted in the design of a novel prosthetic foot that
      uses the energy from compressive forces during heel contact, stores it throughout midstance
      and releases it at an optimal instant during push-off in late stance. This unique design,
      with Controlled Energy Storage and Release (CESR) developed by a team at the University of
      Michigan, Ann Arbor has been shown to reduce the metabolic cost penalty of prosthetic
      ambulation (i.e. the increased cost over normal walking) by 50% compared to a standard SACH
      foot, but as yet only intact individuals wearing an aircast boot equipped with the prosthetic
      feet have been studied. It is likely that the increased energy savings will also be observed
      in transtibial amputees. Young, active amputees will soon be entering the VA system following
      operations in Iraq and Afghanistan, and the energy improvements may benefit this new VA
      patient population. The CESR foot may also provide substantial metabolic cost savings to
      older less active amputees currently in the VA system. By improving gait efficiency amputees
      will be better able to keep up with the demands of functional ambulation, remain more active
      and postpone many of the debilitating consequences of limited mobility. Therefore we propose
      to first refine the design of the CESR foot focusing on the energy storage and energy release
      mechanisms of the CESR foot. Several spring characteristics may prove optimal for certain
      subjects depending upon weight and walking characteristics. This will be an iterative
      optimization process with power generation and absorption characteristics of the CESR foot
      evaluated using computerized gait analysis and the lessons used for further refinement. The
      second phase will involve a three week wear-testing trial to determine if any improvement in
      gait economy, reduction in fatigue, improvement in comfort, or increase in the amount of
      daily walking can be achieved. A validated questionnaire will be utilized to determine each
      amputee's comfort and fatigue during a three week trial in their conventional foot and with
      the CESR foot. Step counts will be performed on each individual over the entire 3 week period
      with both the conventional foot and with the CESR foot. We will collect full body gait
      kinematics (motion) and kinetics (forces) using our Vicon 612 system, and metabolic
      measurements using our VmaxST to calculate oxygen cost for 24 transtibial amputees while
      walking with the CESR foot and their conventional foot. This will permit the calculation of
      the energy storage and release of the foot by inverse dynamics and calculate the net effect
      upon metabolic energy cost savings during ambulation at several speeds. If the CESR foot is
      successful in amputee gait these domains, our next step will be to perform a multi-center
      study with other VA motion laboratories, and eventually collaborate with Ohio Willow Wood, a
      prominent prosthetic manufacturer who has expressed an interest in bringing the CESR foot to
      market.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolic Oxygen Consumption During Ambulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects were oriented to the testing protocol and each prosthetic foot on average 5 days prior to data collection and a acclimatization period of 5-10 minutes with each prosthetic foot prior to data collection</time_frame>
    <description>VO2 was collected at rest and while walking at a controlled walking speed of 1.14 meters/second for 10 minutes until they reached a steady state for 3 minutes. This was repeated for each foot condition. VO2 at the steady state was recorded in ml/min and were subsequently converted to calories and and then to Watts. The data were then corrected for body weight by dividing by weight in Kg. The gross VO2 in Watts/Kg during walking were then adjusted to net VO2 in Watts/kg by subtracting the resting metabolic rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prosthetic Foot Push Off Peak Power</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects were oriented to the testing protocol and each prosthetic foot on average 5 days prior to data collection and a acclimatization period of 5-10 minutes with each prosthetic foot prior to data collection</time_frame>
    <description>The biomechanical measurement of the power generated by the prosthetic foot during the push off component of stance phase. The peak power output during the push off component of stance phase was calculated in Joules. It was subsequently standardized for body weight in Kgs. The final units were therefore Joules/Kg.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Intact Knee Loading</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects were oriented to the testing protocol and each prosthetic foot on average 5 days prior to data collection and a acclimatization period of 5-10 minutes with each prosthetic foot prior to data collection</time_frame>
    <description>The biomechanical measure of the first peak of the knee external adduction moment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Transtibial Amputation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Prosthetic foot</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A conventional prosthetic foot that has limited energy storage and return capabilities. It is standardized and used by all subjects in the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prescribed Prosthetic foot</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>the Prosthetic foot that the subject had prescribed for them by their clinical providers and was worn prior to study initiation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CESR foot</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the experimental CESR, controlled energy storage prosthetic foot</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CESR Prosthetic Foot</intervention_name>
    <description>a novel prosthetic foot that is designed to store energy and release it at a predetermined time in the gait cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>CESR foot</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>typical prosthetic foot</intervention_name>
    <description>patients will wear the prosthetic foot that they were prescribed by the care providers in the clinical team</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Prosthetic foot</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>standardized prosthetic foot</intervention_name>
    <description>a standard foot that has had weights applied to match the mass of the CESR foot</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prescribed Prosthetic foot</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Transtibial Amputees &gt; 1 year walking with prosthesis

          -  Non-amputee control subjects

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Additional musculoskeletal pathology

          -  Cognitive limitation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph M. Czernieki, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Puget Sound Health Care System, Seattle</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Puget Sound Health Care System, Seattle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Segal AD, Zelik KE, Klute GK, Morgenroth DC, Hahn ME, Orendurff MS, Adamczyk PG, Collins SH, Kuo AD, Czerniecki JM. The effects of a controlled energy storage and return prototype prosthetic foot on transtibial amputee ambulation. Hum Mov Sci. 2012 Aug;31(4):918-31. doi: 10.1016/j.humov.2011.08.005. Epub 2011 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22100728</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Morgenroth DC, Segal AD, Zelik KE, Czerniecki JM, Klute GK, Adamczyk PG, Orendurff MS, Hahn ME, Collins SH, Kuo AD. The effect of prosthetic foot push-off on mechanical loading associated with knee osteoarthritis in lower extremity amputees. Gait Posture. 2011 Oct;34(4):502-7. doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2011.07.001. Epub 2011 Jul 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21803584</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zelik KE, Collins SH, Adamczyk PG, Segal AD, Klute GK, Morgenroth DC, Hahn ME, Orendurff MS, Czerniecki JM, Kuo AD. Systematic variation of prosthetic foot spring affects center-of-mass mechanics and metabolic cost during walking. IEEE Trans Neural Syst Rehabil Eng. 2011 Aug;19(4):411-9. doi: 10.1109/TNSRE.2011.2159018. Epub 2011 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21708509</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 28, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 29, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>August 30, 2013</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2014</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2014</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Amputee</keyword>
  <keyword>Economy</keyword>
  <keyword>Efficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Foot</keyword>
  <keyword>Gait</keyword>
  <keyword>Kinematics</keyword>
  <keyword>Kinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Prosthesis</keyword>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>subjects were recruited through bulletin board ads and through a local VA amputee clinic. Subjects were included if between the ages of 18 and 80 years, had used a prosthesis for grtr than 2 years, wore the prosthesis grtr than 8 hours per day, did not ambulate with u/e aids and had no falls in the prior 6 mo or known neuro or msk deficits.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Subjects were provided with suitable acclimatization prior to testing with their initial randomized prosthetic foot type.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Conventional, Prescribed, CESR</title>
          <description>this is a randomized arm where the sequence of prosthetic use was their conventional foot, followed by prescribed foot, followed by the CESR foot</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Conventional, CESR, Prescribed</title>
          <description>The randomized sequence of prosthetic use in this arm was Conventional foot, followed by CESR foot, followed by Prescribed.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P3">
          <title>Prescribed, CESR, Conventional</title>
          <description>The randomized sequence of this arm was the Prescribed prosthetic foot, followed by the CESR foot followed by the Conventional prosthetic foot</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P4">
          <title>Prescribed, Conventional, CESR</title>
          <description>This arm included individuals who were randomized to the sequence, Prescribed prosthetic foot, conventional foot, CESR foot</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P5">
          <title>CESR, Prescribed, Conventional</title>
          <description>This arm included the individuals who were randomized to the prosthetic foot sequence, CESR foot followed by Prescribed foot, followed by Conventional foot.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P6">
          <title>CESR, Conventional, Prescribed</title>
          <description>The individuals in this group were randomized to the prosthetic foot sequence, CESR foot, Conventional foot followed by Prescribed prosthetic foot.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P4" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P5" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P6" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>CESR, Prescribed, Conventional</title>
          <description>all subjects were randomized to each of the three interventions</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="7"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="52.3" spread="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>stature</title>
          <description>height</description>
          <units>meters</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1.85" spread=".05"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Body Weight</title>
          <units>kilograms</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="80.9" spread="9.9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Metabolic Oxygen Consumption During Ambulation</title>
        <description>VO2 was collected at rest and while walking at a controlled walking speed of 1.14 meters/second for 10 minutes until they reached a steady state for 3 minutes. This was repeated for each foot condition. VO2 at the steady state was recorded in ml/min and were subsequently converted to calories and and then to Watts. The data were then corrected for body weight by dividing by weight in Kg. The gross VO2 in Watts/Kg during walking were then adjusted to net VO2 in Watts/kg by subtracting the resting metabolic rate.</description>
        <time_frame>Subjects were oriented to the testing protocol and each prosthetic foot on average 5 days prior to data collection and a acclimatization period of 5-10 minutes with each prosthetic foot prior to data collection</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>CESR Experimental Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>the CESR, controlled energy storage prosthetic foot
CESR Prosthetic Foot : a novel prosthetic foot that is designed to store energy and release it at a predetermined time in the gait cycle</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Conventional Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>subjects wearing the conventional prosthetic foot</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Prescribed Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>subjects wearing the prescribed prosthetic foot</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Metabolic Oxygen Consumption During Ambulation</title>
          <description>VO2 was collected at rest and while walking at a controlled walking speed of 1.14 meters/second for 10 minutes until they reached a steady state for 3 minutes. This was repeated for each foot condition. VO2 at the steady state was recorded in ml/min and were subsequently converted to calories and and then to Watts. The data were then corrected for body weight by dividing by weight in Kg. The gross VO2 in Watts/Kg during walking were then adjusted to net VO2 in Watts/kg by subtracting the resting metabolic rate.</description>
          <units>Watts per kilogram</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.45" spread="0.59"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3.13" spread="0.33"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="2.97" spread="0.23"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Prosthetic Foot Push Off Peak Power</title>
        <description>The biomechanical measurement of the power generated by the prosthetic foot during the push off component of stance phase. The peak power output during the push off component of stance phase was calculated in Joules. It was subsequently standardized for body weight in Kgs. The final units were therefore Joules/Kg.</description>
        <time_frame>Subjects were oriented to the testing protocol and each prosthetic foot on average 5 days prior to data collection and a acclimatization period of 5-10 minutes with each prosthetic foot prior to data collection</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>CESR Experimental Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>the CESR, controlled energy storage prosthetic foot
CESR Prosthetic Foot : a novel prosthetic foot that is designed to store energy and release it at a predetermined time in the gait cycle</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Conventional Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>results with the conventional prosthetic foot</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Prescribed Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>results with prescribed prosthetic foot</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Prosthetic Foot Push Off Peak Power</title>
          <description>The biomechanical measurement of the power generated by the prosthetic foot during the push off component of stance phase. The peak power output during the push off component of stance phase was calculated in Joules. It was subsequently standardized for body weight in Kgs. The final units were therefore Joules/Kg.</description>
          <units>joules per kilogram</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.27" spread="0.04"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.11" spread="0.03"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="0.15" spread="0.04"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Peak Intact Knee Loading</title>
        <description>The biomechanical measure of the first peak of the knee external adduction moment</description>
        <time_frame>Subjects were oriented to the testing protocol and each prosthetic foot on average 5 days prior to data collection and a acclimatization period of 5-10 minutes with each prosthetic foot prior to data collection</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>CESR Experimental Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>the CESR, controlled energy storage prosthetic foot
CESR Prosthetic Foot : a novel prosthetic foot that is designed to store energy and release it at a predetermined time in the gait cycle</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Conventional Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>results while wearing the conventional prosthetic foot</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Prescribed Prosthetic Foot</title>
            <description>results while wearing the prescribed prosthetic foot</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Peak Intact Knee Loading</title>
          <description>The biomechanical measure of the first peak of the knee external adduction moment</description>
          <units>newton meters per kilogram</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.451" spread="0.144"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.608" spread="0.169"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="0.509" spread="0.132"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Arm 3 CESR Prosthetic Foot</title>
          <description>subjects randomized to the CESR prosthetic foot</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Arm 1 Conventional Prosthetic Foot</title>
          <description>subjects randomized to the conventional prosthetic foot</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E3">
          <title>Arm 2 Prescribed Prosthetic Foot</title>
          <description>subjects randomized to the prescribed prosthetic foot</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Acclimatization to a prosthetic foot type can alter the measured performance. In this study, subjects were most experienced using their prescribed foot. The CESR foot was also only available in one foot size which can affect gait characteristics.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Joseph Czerniecki</name_or_title>
      <organization>VA Puget Sound Health Care System</organization>
      <phone>206 277 5188</phone>
      <email>joseph.czerniecki@va.gov</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

