<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00492193</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01-07-14</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14CL401</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00492193</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Post-Op Recovery After Partial Large Bowel Resection</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Observational, Multi-center Study Assessing Early Post-Operative Recovery Following Laparoscopic Partial Large Bowel Resection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cubist Pharmaceuticals LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this trial is to gather information on the postoperative recovery time and
      hospital length of stay experienced by patients having laparoscopic surgeries. This trial
      will also collect data on daily surgical pain and pain medication and how it relates to
      recovery after surgery. In addition, the investigators will collect data on the use of pain
      medication and laxatives in patients following laparoscopic large bowel resection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Laparoscopic surgery was initially performed by surgeons in France in 1987 and was introduced
      in the United States in 1988. This minimally invasive procedure was performed for
      cholecystectomy, and is now the standard of care in the treatment of gallbladder disease.
      Recent advances in laparoscopic surgery and its success in cholecystectomy have permitted the
      procedure to be used for treating a variety of diseases and for diagnosing and staging.

      Minimally invasive laparoscopic surgery has advantages over conventional open surgery,
      including smaller incisions, earlier gastrointestinal (GI) recovery, shorter hospital stays,
      less pain, and fewer complications. In recent years evidence is accumulating for some
      operations that laparoscopic procedures produce outcomes that are comparable to those
      produced by routine open surgery and may actually surpass others.

      Whereas laparoscopic surgery has been successful and well accepted for various abdominal and
      pelvic surgeries, its use in the area of colorectal surgery has progressed at a slower rate.
      There are challenges impacting the wider use of laparoscopic bowel resection (LBR). These
      include the technical difficulty associated with the size of the colon, the need for complete
      immobilization of the bowel and the need for a watertight, non-leaking anastomosis. In
      addition, the equipment is expensive and surgeons require specialized training.

      Results from studies in colon cancer now indicate that LBR reduces perioperative morbidity,
      and decreases hospital stay with comparable cancer-related survival as compared to open
      colectomy. The use of LBR in short-term outcomes is increasing because clinical trial data
      have demonstrated superiority of LBR, particularly in short-term outcomes over conventional
      open surgery.

      Gastrointestinal recovery and related patient outcomes during the early postoperative period
      following open segmental colon resection have been extensively evaluated in previous
      randomized, controlled, multicenter trials. Current data in laparoscopic colectomy have been
      collected from retrospective, single center clinical trials which lacked standardized
      definitions and endpoints. Therefore, this prospective, multicenter study in LBR is being
      undertaken to determine how this surgical technique impacts GI recovery and related outcomes
      relative to the open laparotomy.

      The primary objective of this study is to assess the clinical course of gastrointestinal (GI)
      recovery and hospital length of stay in subjects undergoing laparoscopic partial large bowel
      resection. The secondary objective is to assess the immediate post discharge clinical course
      of subjects undergoing laparoscopic bowel resection with respect to opioid-induced GI
      effects, daily surgical pain, opioid consumption and laxative use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to upper and lower GI recovery and post-operative hospital length of stay.</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome or end points were time to upper and lower GI recovery (GI-2: tolerance of solid food and bowel movement) and post-operative hospital length of stay.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative ileus related mobidity.</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary outcome or endpoints are postoperative ileus(POI) related morbidity (postoperative nasogastric tub insertion or investigator-assisted POI resulting in prolonged hospital stay or readmission), conversion rate, and protocol-defined prolonged POI (GI-2&gt;5 postoperative days.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">139</enrollment>
  <condition>Diverticulitis</condition>
  <condition>Colon Polyps</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Colorectal Surgery clinic population
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be male or female at least 18 years of age

          -  be scheduled for laparoscopic (SL or HAL) partial large bowel resection with primary
             anastomosis.

          -  have an American Society of Anesthesiologists Physical Status Score of P1 to P3
             (Appendix C.1 of the full protocol).

          -  are scheduled to receive postoperative pain management primarily with opioid analgesia
             via intravenous (IV) patient-controlled analgesia (PCA)

          -  are scheduled to have the NG tube removed on the morning of POD 1

          -  are able to read, write, and fully understand the language of the study diary

          -  be able to understand the study procedure, agrees to participate in the study program,
             and voluntarily provides informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  be scheduled for a total colectomy, ileal pouch-anal anastomosis, colostomy,
             ileostomy, right HAL colectomy or have a history of total colectomy, gastric bypass,
             previous bowel resection or short bowel syndrome.

          -  has a complete bowel obstruction

          -  has taken therapeutic doses of opioids for 7 consecutive days immediately before
             surgery.

          -  has participated in a clinical trial with alvimopan or has taken alvimopan in the past
             30 days.

          -  has a diagnosed history of alcoholism or drug addiction (eg, opioids or other drugs of
             abuse) within 1 year of the surgery date (Day 0).

          -  has a diagnosed history of constipation, pelvic floor disorder, or GI disorders known
             to affect bowel function (eg, chronic diarrhea)

          -  has a history of laxative dependence or daily use (ie, hyperosmotics, mineral oil,
             saline, stimulants, bulking agents, suppositories, lubricants, enemas, or any other
             natural products that promote bowel motility or cleansing)

          -  has, as determined by the investigator or the sponsor's medical monitor, a history or
             clinical manifestations of significant renal, hepatic, cardiovascular, GI, metabolic
             disorders or mental conditions (e.g., depression, psychosis) that might confound the
             results of the study or pose additional risk to the subject.

          -  has participated in another investigational drug or medical device study within the
             last 30 days or will be enrolled in another investigational drug or medical device
             study or any study in which active patient participation is required outside normal
             hospital data collection during the course of this study.

          -  is unwilling or unable to complete the study diary.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Conor P. Delaney, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospitals of Cleveland/ Institute for Surgical Innovation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals of Cleveland Case Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Delaney CP, Marcello PW, Sonoda T, Wise P, Bauer J, Techner L. Gastrointestinal recovery after laparoscopic colectomy: results of a prospective, observational, multicenter study. Surg Endosc. 2010 Mar;24(3):653-61. doi: 10.1007/s00464-009-0652-7. Epub 2009 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>19688390</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Conor Delaney, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hand assist laparoscopic partial large bowel resection</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopic partial large bowel resection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diverticulitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

