<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00493467</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2005-0512</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-01569</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00493467</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zevalin (Ibritumomab Tiuxetan) for Early Stage Indolent Lymphomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Zevalin for the Treatment of Early-Stage Indolent Lymphomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biogen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CTI BioPharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find out if giving (Rituxan) rituximab with
      90Y (ibritumomab tiuxetan) (90 Y Zevalin®) may be effective in treating low-grade lymphoma.
      The safety of this combination treatment will also be studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      90 Y Zevalin and rituximab are both designed to attach to lymphoma cells, causing them to
      die.

      Before you can start treatment on this study, you will have &quot;screening tests.&quot; These tests
      will help the doctor decide if you are eligible to take part in this study. You will have a
      physical exam. Blood (about 2 to 3 teaspoons) and urine will be collected for routine tests.
      You will have a chest x-ray and computerized tomography (CT) scans of the neck, chest,
      abdomen (stomach area), and pelvis.

      A PET scan is also recommended. A PET (Positron Emission Tomography) scan is a medical
      technique that monitors the activity in the brain and other organs by tracking the movement
      of a special radioactive solution through the body. The radioactive solution is either
      inhaled as a mist or injected into a vein. The radioactive solution is usually made from
      simple sugar that has radioactive particles attached to it. After the solution is injected
      into a vein or inhaled, the PET scanner takes pictures of the radioactive solution as it
      moves through the body and collects in various organs. By watching how the solution travels
      through the body and studying where the solution collects, researchers can learn the extent
      of disease in certain organs in the body.

      You will have an electrocardiogram (ECG -- a test that measures the electrical activity of
      the heart). You will have a bone marrow aspirate and biopsy performed. To collect a bone
      marrow aspirate and biopsy, an area of the hip or chest bone is numbed with anesthetic, and a
      small amount of bone marrow and bone is withdrawn through a large needle. Women who are able
      to have children must have a negative blood or urine pregnancy test.

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be given diphenhydramine
      (Benadryl) by vein and you will take acetaminophen (Tylenol) by mouth before each dose of
      rituximab. This is done to help decrease the risk of developing side effects of rituximab.
      You will then receive 1 dose of rituximab by vein over about 4-6 hours on Day 1 of treatment.
      After treatment with rituximab, you will then be given 111 In Zevalin (this is a radioactive
      agent that binds to rituximab to help with imaging exams), by vein over about 10 minutes.
      This is so researchers can use a special camera to see where the drug is in your body.

      You will have imaging performed (on a camera, like an x-ray) on either Day 2 or 3. On Day 8
      (7 days after the first dose of rituximab) you will receive a second dose of rituximab. You
      will also be given Benadryl, Tylenol, and 90Y Zevalin in the same manner as on Day 1.

      If you experience intolerable side effects while on this study, you may be removed from this
      study. Your treatment on the study will end on Day 8.

      You will return for follow-up tests for 4 years. Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn
      weekly for the first 3 months. Blood (about 2 tablespoons each time) will also be drawn at
      month 6 and 9 of the first year, and every 6 months in the second, third, and fourth years.
      You may also have CT scans, PET scans (which are recommended), x-rays, and bone marrow
      biopsies and aspirates performed, if your doctor thinks they are necessary.

      Your participation on this study will end in about 4 years.

      This is an investigational study. 90 Y Zevalin and rituximab are FDA approved and
      commercially available. Their use in this study is investigational. Up to 36 patients will
      take part in this multicenter study. Up to 36 patients will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluation following completion of 12 weeks of treatment and performed by CT scan or MRI.</time_frame>
    <description>ORR defined as the percentage of number of complete response or partial response in total number of patients treated using International Working Group (IWG) revised response criteria for Malignant Lymphoma. The treatment period is defined as 12 weeks from the 90Y Zevalin infusion. Overall response to therapy is evaluated after three months using radiographic and clinical parameters to assess response.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">31</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zevalin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ibritumomab Tiuxetan (Zevalin) + Rituximab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibritumomab Tiuxetan (Zevalin)</intervention_name>
    <description>111In Zevalin (5 mCi of ^111In, 1.6 mg of Ibritumomab Tiuxetan) Intravenously Over 10 minutes on Day 1.
90Y Zevalin 0.3 or 0.4 mCi/kg Intravenously Over 10 minutes on Day 8.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zevalin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ibritumomab</other_name>
    <other_name>Zevalin</other_name>
    <other_name>IDEC-Y2B8</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>250 mg/m^2 Intravenously Over 4-6 Hours On Days 1 and 8.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zevalin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. New diagnosis of low-grade indolent lymphomas Stage I-II. Patients with multiple skin
             lesions will be eligible provided that the skin is the only site of involvement.

          2. Histology includes Indolent cluster of differentiation antigen 20 (CD20)+ lymphomas
             including: Follicular lymphoma, Extranodal marginal lymphoma of MALT type, Nodal
             Marginal zone B-cell lymphoma (+/- monocytoid cells), and Splenic marginal B-cell
             lymphoma (+/- villous lymphocytes).

          3. Signed Informed Consent.

          4. Age &gt;/= 18 years.

          5. Pre-study Zubrod performance status of 0, 1, or 2.

          6. Acceptable hematologic status within two weeks prior to patient registration,
             including: absolute neutrophil count ([segmented neutrophils + bands] x total WBC) &gt;/=
             1, 500/mm^3, total lymphocyte count &lt;/= 5,000/mm^3 and platelet counts &gt;/=
             100,000/mm^3.

          7. Female patients who are not pregnant or lactating.

          8. Men and women of reproductive potential who are following accepted birth control
             methods (as determined by the treating physician, however abstinence is not an
             acceptable method).

          9. Patients determined to have &lt; 25% bone marrow involvement with lymphoma within six
             weeks of registration (define measurement of a bone marrow aspirate or biopsy).

         10. Patient should have at least one lesion measuring &gt;/= 1.5 cm in a single dimension.
             Measurable cutaneous lesions are allowed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of central nervous system (CNS) lymphoma.

          2. Patients with HIV or AIDS-related lymphoma.

          3. Patients with pleural effusion.

          4. Patients with abnormal liver function: total bilirubin &gt; 2.0 mg/dL.

          5. Patients with abnormal renal function: serum creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL.

          6. Patients who have received prior external beam radiation therapy to &gt; 25% of active
             bone marrow (involved field or regional).

          7. Impaired bone marrow reserve as indicated by &lt; 15% bone marrow cellularity

          8. Serious nonmalignant disease or infection which, in the opinion of the investigator
             and/or the sponsor, would compromise other protocol objectives.

          9. Major surgery, other than diagnostic surgery, within four weeks.

         10. Evidence of transformation in the latest biopsy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Felipe Samaniego, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 17, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 17, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Indolent Lymphomas</keyword>
  <keyword>Ibritumomab Tiuxetan</keyword>
  <keyword>Zevalin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 20, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>May 25, 2016</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

