<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00496314</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-20-06</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00496314</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physician's Comfort Level and Satisfaction Study With The e2TM Collector Compared to the Spatula/CytoBrush Technique</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Study Assessing Physician's Comfort Level and Satisfaction When Using The e2TM Cervical Cell Collector Compared to the Standard Spatula/CytoBrush Technique</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>CytoCore, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>CytoCore, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A study which assesses the physician's comfort level and satisfaction when using the e2TM
      Collector compared to the Spatula/SytoBrush technique.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Terminated for lack of resources to complete.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician comfort level and satisfaction when using the e2TM Collector compared to the standard spatula/cytobrush.</measure>
    <time_frame>Each physician will be surveyed after first and last use of the e2TM collector as well as three more times spaced at near regular intervals in between.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Cell Collection</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>e2TM Cervical Cell Collector</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Every Physician who will participate in the two CytoCore prospective studies assessing
             the safety and efficacy of the e2TM Collector

          -  Each physician will have used the Collector 15 - 25 times

          -  Each physician will have signed the Consent form prior to using the Collector for the
             first time.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None (commensurate with the above inclusion conditions.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jay Pinkerton, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital CASE Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muñoz N, Bosch FX, de Sanjosé S, Herrero R, Castellsagué X, Shah KV, Snijders PJ, Meijer CJ; International Agency for Research on Cancer Multicenter Cervical Cancer Study Group. Epidemiologic classification of human papillomavirus types associated with cervical cancer. N Engl J Med. 2003 Feb 6;348(6):518-27.</citation>
    <PMID>12571259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sankaranarayanan R, Budukh AM, Rajkumar R. Effective screening programmes for cervical cancer in low- and middle-income developing countries. Bull World Health Organ. 2001;79(10):954-62. Epub 2001 Nov 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11693978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Umland B, Waterman R, Wiese W, Duban S, Mennin S, Kaufman A. Learning from a rural physician program in China. Acad Med. 1992 May;67(5):307-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1575861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holowaty P, Miller AB, Rohan T, To T. RESPONSE: re: natural history of dysplasia of the uterine cervix . J Natl Cancer Inst. 1999 Aug 18;91(16):1420A-1421.</citation>
    <PMID>10451450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solomon D, Davey D, Kurman R, Moriarty A, O'Connor D, Prey M, Raab S, Sherman M, Wilbur D, Wright T Jr, Young N; Forum Group Members; Bethesda 2001 Workshop. The 2001 Bethesda System: terminology for reporting results of cervical cytology. JAMA. 2002 Apr 24;287(16):2114-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11966386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nanda K, McCrory DC, Myers ER, Bastian LA, Hasselblad V, Hickey JD, Matchar DB. Accuracy of the Papanicolaou test in screening for and follow-up of cervical cytologic abnormalities: a systematic review. Ann Intern Med. 2000 May 16;132(10):810-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10819705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fahey MT, Irwig L, Macaskill P. Meta-analysis of Pap test accuracy. Am J Epidemiol. 1995 Apr 1;141(7):680-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7702044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clavel C, Masure M, Bory JP, Putaud I, Mangeonjean C, Lorenzato M, Nazeyrollas P, Gabriel R, Quereux C, Birembaut P. Human papillomavirus testing in primary screening for the detection of high-grade cervical lesions: a study of 7932 women. Br J Cancer. 2001 Jun 15;84(12):1616-23.</citation>
    <PMID>11401314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Willis BH, Barton P, Pearmain P, Bryan S, Hyde C. Cervical screening programmes: can automation help? Evidence from systematic reviews, an economic analysis and a simulation modelling exercise applied to the UK. Health Technol Assess. 2005 Mar;9(13):1-207, iii. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15774236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buntinx F, Brouwers M. Relation between sampling device and detection of abnormality in cervical smears: a meta-analysis of randomised and quasi-randomised studies. BMJ. 1996 Nov 23;313(7068):1285-90.</citation>
    <PMID>8942687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin-Hirsch P, Lilford R, Jarvis G, Kitchener HC. Efficacy of cervical-smear collection devices: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet. 1999 Nov 20;354(9192):1763-70. Erratum in: Lancet 2000 Jan 29;355(9201):414.</citation>
    <PMID>10577637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin-Hirsch P, Jarvis G, Kitchener H, Lilford R. Collection devices for obtaining cervical cytology samples. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2000;(2):CD001036. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2000;(3):CD001036.</citation>
    <PMID>10796736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Selvaggi SM, Guidos BJ. Specimen adequacy and the ThinPrep Pap Test: the endocervical component. Diagn Cytopathol. 2000 Jul;23(1):23-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10907927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marchand L, Mundt M, Klein G, Agarwal SC. Optimal collection technique and devices for a quality pap smear. WMJ. 2005 Aug;104(6):51-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16218317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koss LG. Evolution in cervical pathology and cytology: a historical perspective. Eur J Gynaecol Oncol. 2000;21(6):550-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11214608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 17, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

