<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00492089</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2009-00256</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2009-00256</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000553135</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2006-0890</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>7955</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM62202</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00492089</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bevacizumab in Reducing CNS Side Effects in Patients Who Have Undergone Radiation Therapy to the Brain for Primary Brain Tumor, Meningioma, or Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II Trial of Bevacizumab to Control Brain Radiation Damage</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bevacizumab may reduce CNS side effects caused by radiation therapy. This randomized phase II
      trial is studying how well bevacizumab works in reducing CNS side effects in patients who
      have undergone radiation therapy to the brain for primary brain tumor, meningioma, or head
      and neck cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      I. Determine to what extent bevacizumab can reduce active radiation toxicity to the CNS in
      patients who have undergone cranial irradiation for primary brain neoplasm, meningioma, or
      head and neck cancer.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine to what extent this drug can reduce dexamethasone dependence in these patients.

      II. Determine to what extent this drug can improve neurologic function in these patients.

      III. Determine to what extent this drug can improve quality of life of these patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a randomized, placebo-controlled, crossover, double-blind study. Patients
      are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive bevacizumab IV over 30-90 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 3
      weeks for up to 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM II: Patients receive placebo IV over 30-90 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 3
      weeks for up to 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Patients in arm II who have failed to respond to treatment at 6 or 12 weeks may cross over to
      arm I and receive 2 courses of bevacizumab as in arm I. Patients in arm I (including
      crossover patients) who have responded to treatment may receive 2 additional courses of
      bevacizumab.

      Patients undergo MRI after courses 2 and 4.

      Quality of life and neurologic function are assessed at baseline, periodically during study
      treatment, and at 12 and 24 weeks after completion of study treatment.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed at 12 and 24 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Response ( &gt; 25% Reduction in T2 Flair) From Baseline to Evaluation at 6 Weeks Post Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) from baseline to evaluation at 6 weeks for participants where MRI changes are based on the size of edema (T2 FLAIR) and Gd-contrast enhancement (lesion diameter and perfusion/dynamic). A 25% reduction in T2 flair volume constitutes a response for study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Anaplastic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Anaplastic Ependymoma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Anaplastic Meningioma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Anaplastic Oligodendroglioma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Brain Stem Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Central Nervous System Germ Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Adult Choroid Plexus Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Adult Diffuse Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Ependymoma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Grade II Meningioma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Grade III Meningioma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Malignant Hemangiopericytoma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Mixed Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Oligodendroglioma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Papillary Meningioma</condition>
  <condition>Adult Pineocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Meningeal Melanocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Radiation Toxicity</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adenoid Cystic Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Brain Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Basal Cell Carcinoma of the Lip</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Esthesioneuroblastoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Inverted Papilloma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Lymphoepithelioma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Lymphoepithelioma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Midline Lethal Granuloma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mucoepidermoid Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Salivary Gland Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Hypopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Adenoid Cystic Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Basal Cell Carcinoma of the Lip</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Esthesioneuroblastoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Inverted Papilloma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Lymphoepithelioma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Lymphoepithelioma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Midline Lethal Granuloma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Mucoepidermoid Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Salivary Gland Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Hypopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Adenoid Cystic Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Basal Cell Carcinoma of the Lip</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Esthesioneuroblastoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Inverted Papilloma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Lymphoepithelioma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Midline Lethal Granuloma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Mucoepidermoid Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Salivary Gland Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Hypopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adenoid Cystic Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Basal Cell Carcinoma of the Lip</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Esthesioneuroblastoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Inverted Papilloma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Lymphoepithelioma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Lymphoepithelioma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Midline Lethal Granuloma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Mucoepidermoid Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Salivary Gland Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Hypopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Lip and Oral Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Nasopharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Oropharynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Paranasal Sinus and Nasal Cavity</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Verrucous Carcinoma of the Larynx</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Verrucous Carcinoma of the Oral Cavity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive bevacizumab IV over 30-90 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for up to 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive placebo IV over 30-90 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for up to 2 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-VEGF humanized monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>anti-VEGF monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>Avastin</other_name>
    <other_name>rhuMAb VEGF</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PLCB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>magnetic resonance imaging</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MRI</other_name>
    <other_name>NMR imaging</other_name>
    <other_name>NMRI</other_name>
    <other_name>nuclear magnetic resonance imaging</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality-of-life assessment</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>quality of life assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  No evidence of bleeding diathesis or coagulopathy

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception during and for &gt;= 2 months after
             completion of study therapy

          -  No diarrhea &gt;= grade 1

          -  Histologically confirmed primary brain neoplasm, meningioma, or head and neck cancer
             [WHO grade 2 or 3 disease--no WHO grade 4 primary brain neoplasms (i.e., glioblastoma
             or gliosarcoma)]

          -  Patients with head and neck cancer must not have any of the following:

               -  Evidence of metastatic disease

               -  Evidence of tumor invasion to major vessels (e.g., the carotid)

               -  History of bleeding related to tumor or radiotherapy during or after completion
                  of radiotherapy

          -  Must have undergone cranial irradiation

          -  Must have radiographic evidence to support the diagnosis of radiation necrosis and/or
             surgical biopsy evidence of necrosis without tumor within the past 2 months

          -  Must have evidence of progressive neurologic signs or symptoms appropriate to the
             location of the radiation necrosis

          -  No abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or intra-abdominal abscess within
             the past 28 days

          -  No significant traumatic injury within the past 28 days

          -  No evidence of active CNS hemorrhage

          -  Karnofsky performance status 60-100%

          -  No clinically significant cardiovascular disease, including any of the following:

               -  Inadequately controlled hypertension (i.e., systolic BP &gt; 140 mm Hg and/or
                  diastolic BP &gt; 90 mm Hg despite antihypertensive medication)

               -  Large vessel cerebrovascular accident within the past 6 months

               -  Myocardial infarction or unstable angina within the past 6 months

          -  No clinically significant cardiovascular disease, including any of the following:

               -  NYHA class II-IV congestive heart failure

               -  Serious or inadequately controlled cardiac arrhythmia

               -  Significant vascular disease (e.g., aortic aneurysm or history of aortic
                  dissection)

               -  Clinically significant peripheral vascular disease

          -  At least 6 months since prior radiotherapy

          -  Platelet count &gt; 75,000/mm^3

          -  Granulocyte count &gt; 1,500/mm^3

          -  Creatinine &lt; 1.0 times ULN

          -  AST &lt; 2.5 times ULN

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Prior chemotherapy for tumor allowed

          -  Prior tyrosine kinase inhibitors of VEGF receptor (VEGFR) allowed

          -  More than 28 days since prior and no concurrent major surgical procedure or open
             biopsy

          -  Concurrent dexamethasone allowed provided patient is on a stable dose for &gt;= 1 week
             prior to study entry

          -  Concurrent full-dose anticoagulants (e.g., warfarin) with PT INR &gt; 1.5 allowed
             provided the following criteria are met:

               -  In-range INR (usually between 2 and 3) and patient is on a stable dose of oral
                  anticoagulant for 1 week or on a stable dose of low molecular weight heparin

               -  No active bleeding or pathological condition that carries a high risk of bleeding

          -  Concurrent full-dose anticoagulants (e.g., warfarin) with PT INR &gt; 1.5 allowed
             provided the following criteria are met: No evidence of serious or nonhealing wound,
             ulcer, or bone fracture

          -  No concurrent chemotherapy or tyrosine kinase inhibitors of VEGFR

          -  No prior bevacizumab

          -  More than 7 days since prior core biopsy

          -  History of seizures allowed provided the patient is receiving anticonvulsant therapy

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9.0 g/dL

          -  Bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  No other concurrent investigational agents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monica Loghin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>June 15, 2012</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2013</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">June 14, 2013</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 9, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Germ Cell and Embryonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Laryngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Verrucous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Basal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ependymoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nasopharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Salivary Gland Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oligodendroglioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Meningioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paranasal Sinus Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papilloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Adenoid Cystic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Mucoepidermoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Granuloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esthesioneuroblastoma, Olfactory</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papilloma, Inverted</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Choroid Plexus Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemangiopericytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pinealoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Recruitment Period: June 20, 2007 to December 07, 2009. All recruitment done at The University of Texas (UT) MD Anderson Cancer Center.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Of the 15 patients enrolled, four participants were excluded from the study.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Arm A: Bevacizumab</title>
          <description>Bevacizumab 7.5 mg/m^2 intravenous (IV) every 3 weeks.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Crossover Arm B: Placebo First, Then Bevacizumab</title>
          <description>Placebo IV every 3 weeks for two courses, crossover at 6 weeks to receive Bevacizumab 7.5 mg/m^2 IV as in Arm A.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>First Intervention (6 Weeks)</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
        <period>
          <title>Second Intervention (6 Weeks)</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Arm A: Bevacizumab</title>
          <description>Bevacizumab 7.5 mg/m^2 intravenous (IV) every 3 weeks</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Crossover Arm B: Placebo First, Then Bevacizumab</title>
          <description>Placebo IV every 3 weeks for two courses, crossover at 6 weeks to receive Bevacizumab 7.5 mg/m^2 IV as in Arm A</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="5"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="6"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="11"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="43" lower_limit="39" upper_limit="59"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="47" lower_limit="39" upper_limit="70"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="47" lower_limit="39" upper_limit="70"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants With Response ( &gt; 25% Reduction in T2 Flair) From Baseline to Evaluation at 6 Weeks Post Treatment</title>
        <description>Change in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) from baseline to evaluation at 6 weeks for participants where MRI changes are based on the size of edema (T2 FLAIR) and Gd-contrast enhancement (lesion diameter and perfusion/dynamic). A 25% reduction in T2 flair volume constitutes a response for study.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline to 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Analysis was conducted per protocol. The participants in the Crossover Arm were evaluated after receiving the Bevacizumab treatment as described in the arm description.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Arm A: Bevacizumab</title>
            <description>Bevacizumab 7.5 mg/m^2 intravenous (IV) every 3 weeks</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Crossover Arm B: Placebo Then Bevacizumab</title>
            <description>Placebo IV every 3 weeks for two courses, crossover at 6 weeks to receive Bevacizumab 7.5 mg/m^2 IV as in Arm A</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants With Response ( &gt; 25% Reduction in T2 Flair) From Baseline to Evaluation at 6 Weeks Post Treatment</title>
          <description>Change in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) from baseline to evaluation at 6 weeks for participants where MRI changes are based on the size of edema (T2 FLAIR) and Gd-contrast enhancement (lesion diameter and perfusion/dynamic). A 25% reduction in T2 flair volume constitutes a response for study.</description>
          <population>Analysis was conducted per protocol. The participants in the Crossover Arm were evaluated after receiving the Bevacizumab treatment as described in the arm description.</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="6"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>2 years and 9 months</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Bevacizumab</title>
          <description>Bevacizumab 7.5 mg/m^2 intravenous (IV) every 3 weeks</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>First Intervention Placebo IV (only) every 3 weeks for two courses</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>CTCAE (3.0)</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dysphagia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Seizure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Vascular disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>CTCAE (3.0)</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombocytopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypertension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Hepatobiliary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Elevated alanine aminotransferase (ALT)</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="11"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="6"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>The only disclosure restriction on the PI is that the sponsor can review results communications prior to public release and can embargo communications regarding trial results for a period that is less than or equal to 60 days. The sponsor cannot require changes to the communication and cannot extend the embargo.</restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Monica Loghin, MD / Assistant Professor</name_or_title>
      <organization>The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</organization>
      <phone>K Hunter, RN 713-745-5769</phone>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

