<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01116947</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LABioMed 13892-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01116947</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fosrenol for Enhancing Dietary Protein Intake in Hypoalbuminemic Dialysis Patients (FrEDI) Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>FrEDI</acronym>
  <official_title>Fosrenol for Enhancing Dietary Protein Intake in Hypoalbuminemic Dialysis Patients (FrEDI) Study: An Investigator Initiated Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Los Angeles Biomedical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>DaVita Dialysis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shire</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Los Angeles Biomedical Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Protein-energy wasting, as reflected by a serum albumin &lt;4.0 g/dL, is very common in
      maintenance hemodialysis (MHD) patients and associated with poor clinical outcomes including
      high death rates. Hyperphosphatemia, reflected by serum phosphorus level &gt;5.5 mg/dL, is also
      common disorder and associated with increased death risk in the same population. The
      traditional dietary intervention to control hyperphosphatemia is to restrict protein intake.
      This, however, may worsen protein-energy wasting as recently showed in large epidemiologic
      data, which indicated that the best survival was observed in MHD patients with increased
      protein intake while serum phosphorus could be controlled. We hypothesize that the provision
      of high protein diet will be possible if a potent phosphorus binder (Fosreonl™) will be
      prescribed simultaneously. Hence, we propose to conduct a randomized controlled trial in 110
      hypoalbuminemic (albumin &lt;4.0 mg/dL) MHD patients in several DaVita dialysis facilities in
      Los Angeles South Bay area. After 1:1 randomization, we will provide the participating
      subjects (the INTERVENTION group) with 8 weeks of high protein meals in form of prepared meal
      boxes (50 g protein, 850 Cal, and a phosphorus to protein ratio of &lt;10 mg/gm) during each
      hemodialysis treatment, along with 0.5 to 1.5 g Fosrenol, to be titrated if necessary; as
      well as dietary counselling to maintain a high dietary protein intake at home (with same or
      similar binder regimen) for 8 weeks and to avoid food items with high phosphorus based
      additives. Meals will be prepared at Harbor-UCLA GCRC Bio-nutrition Department. We have
      reviewed and tested the feasibility of meal preparation and distribution system and the
      related logistics. The CONTROL group will also receive meal boxes but the meal contains low
      Calorie (&lt;50 Cal) and almost zero protein (&lt;1 g) diet (such as salads) during each
      hemodialysis treatment. These patients will continue their pre-existing phosphorus control
      regimens. As outcome variables, we will examine change in serum albumin over the 8 weeks of
      intervention. We will also examine changes in dietary protein and serum phosphorus in the 2
      groups after 8 weeks of intervention. Quality of life and patient satisfaction will also be
      examined before and towards the end of the intervention phase. Given our ongoing 2-year study
      with a similar operation known as the AIONID Study and given DaVita dieticians''
      collaboration and support, we anticipate successful recruitment, retention and data analyses
      within 8 to 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE:

      Based on the hypothesis that the efficacy and potency of Fosrenol enables increasing dietary
      protein intake and provision of meals during dialysis treatment for improving nutritional
      status in malnourished dialysis patients with a low serum albumin (&lt;4.0 g/dL) while serum
      phosphorus can be effectively controlled with the target range of 3.5 to 5.5 mg/dL.

      STUDY PROCEDURE:

        1. In all subjects: Recommend adequate dietary protein intake to achieve or maintain an
           nPCR (nPNA) above 1.0 g/kg/day for 2 months. Encourage aggressive increase in protein
           intake while avoiding high phos/protein ratio esp. higher intake of egg whites, meat,
           fish, poultries, legumes, etc. via counseling by renal dietician (RD) and/or study
           staff.

        2. Both groups will receive free meal boxes during the first 60 min of HD treatment for 8
           weeks (24 meals during 24 HD treatment sessions). Cases will receive high protein meals
           (~50 gm, with phos/protein ratio &lt;10 mg//gm), whereas controls will receive salad with
           almost no protein.

        3. In CASES (n=55): Switch binder simultaneously to (or start) Fosrenol 500 mg to 1,500 per
           meal/snack, according to the meal size at different times of the day. Recommend crushing
           the pills using the pill-crusher that will be provided to subjects, and recommend
           placing or sprinkling Fosrenol pieces on the food. Titrate the dose every 2 weeks
           according to serum phosphorus.

        4. In CONTROLLS (n=55): Continue the same binder (other than Fosrenol). In All subjects:
           Titrate the binder as indicated to control serum phosphorus &lt;5.5 mg/dL.

      SAFETY ENDPOINTS:

        1. Routine safety measures for food ingestion and binder administration

        2. Bi-weekly measures of minerals and monthly measures of PTH

      STATISTICAL METHODS:

      The t test, the chi square test, and the Mann-Whitney rank sum test to compare the baseline
      characteristics of intervention and control participants in serum albumin and other measures.
      To simplify presentation of results, some Likert scale responses will be dichotomized. The
      corresponding P values will be based on the complete ordinal scales used by participants to
      respond to questions quality of life, satisfaction, and food intake and about how often they
      eat meals from specific fast-food restaurants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1. Change in serum albumin by +0.2 g/dl or higher over 2 months, i.e., from baseline (Month 0) to Month 2 (main outcome measure)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2. Percentage of serum phosphorus between 3.5 and 5.5 mg/dL</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3. Change in nPCR (nPNA) by +0.1 g/kg/day</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>4. Change in protein intake via food frequency questionnaire x 2 (baseline vs. after 2 months)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5. Change in post-dialysis dry weight</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6. Changes in calcium, PTH, and alkaline phosphatase</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>7. Patients satisfaction and quality of life (KDQOL36)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>8. RD and MD satisfaction per questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>9. Change in other nutritional or inflammatory markers (CRP, TIBC, MIS, SGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">108</enrollment>
  <condition>End-Stage Renal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1. Treatment Arm (CASES) will receive high protein meals during thrice weekly hemodialysis in-center (each meal includes ~50 g of protein, ~850 Cal, and phos/protein ratio &lt;10 mg/g) PLUS dietary counseling to continue similar high protein intake with low phosphorus to protein ratio and to avoid foods with high preservative content. Fosrenol 1.0 to 1.5 g per meal will be prescribed (use of pill crusher will be recommended) and will be titrated based on bi-weekly phosphorus levels.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm (CONTROLS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2. Control Arm (CONTROLS) will receive salad boxes in-center (no protein, low calorie) and routine dietary counseling and will continue pre-existing phosphorus binder regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meals during hemodialysis accompanied by lanthanum carbonate to control phosphorus</intervention_name>
    <description>Based on the hypothesis that the efficacy and potency of Fosrenol enables increasing dietary protein intake and provision of meals during dialysis treatment for improving nutritional status in malnourished dialysis patients with a low serum albumin (&lt;4.0 g/dL) while serum phosphorus can be effectively controlled with the target range of 3.5 to 5.5 mg/dL</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm (CONTROLS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Prevalent hypoalbuminemic hemodialysis patients with a serum albumin &lt;4.0 g/dL and
             capable of oral food intake

          2. Adult (18-85 years) hemodialysis patients for 3 months or longer, capable of eating
             food independently

          3. Protein energy wasting as evident by serum albumin &lt;4.0 g/dL

          4. Not receiving Fosrenol for the past 2 weeks

             Exclusion Criteria:

          5. Not willing to sign the written consent form

          6. Any condition that can interfere with increasing dietary protein intake, e.g.
             inability to eat or to maintain ingested food (OK to be on vitamin D agents including
             paricalcitol, calcitriol, doxercalciferol, ergocalciferol and cholecalciferol; or
             cinacalcet)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kamyar Kalantar-Zadeh, MD, MPH, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.NIEDstudy.org</url>
    <description>NIED Study Website (including Harold Simmons Center's related studies: NIED, AIONID, FREDI, etc)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kovesdy CP, Anderson JE, Kalantar-Zadeh K. Outcomes associated with serum phosphorus level in males with non-dialysis dependent chronic kidney disease. Clin Nephrol. 2010 Apr;73(4):268-75.</citation>
    <PMID>20353734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noori N, Kalantar-Zadeh K, Kovesdy CP, Bross R, Benner D, Kopple JD. Association of dietary phosphorus intake and phosphorus to protein ratio with mortality in hemodialysis patients. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2010 Apr;5(4):683-92. doi: 10.2215/CJN.08601209. Epub 2010 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>20185606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalantar-Zadeh K, Gutekunst L, Mehrotra R, Kovesdy CP, Bross R, Shinaberger CS, Noori N, Hirschberg R, Benner D, Nissenson AR, Kopple JD. Understanding sources of dietary phosphorus in the treatment of patients with chronic kidney disease. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2010 Mar;5(3):519-30. doi: 10.2215/CJN.06080809. Epub 2010 Jan 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20093346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shinaberger CS, Greenland S, Kopple JD, Van Wyck D, Mehrotra R, Kovesdy CP, Kalantar-Zadeh K. Is controlling phosphorus by decreasing dietary protein intake beneficial or harmful in persons with chronic kidney disease? Am J Clin Nutr. 2008 Dec;88(6):1511-8. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.2008.26665.</citation>
    <PMID>19064510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noori N, Sims JJ, Kopple JD, Shah A, Colman S, Shinaberger CS, Bross R, Mehrotra R, Kovesdy CP, Kalantar-Zadeh K. Organic and inorganic dietary phosphorus and its management in chronic kidney disease. Iran J Kidney Dis. 2010 Apr;4(2):89-100.</citation>
    <PMID>20404416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kovesdy CP, Kalantar-Zadeh K. Bone and mineral disorders in pre-dialysis CKD. Int Urol Nephrol. 2008;40(2):427-40. doi: 10.1007/s11255-008-9346-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18368510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalantar-Zadeh K, Kuwae N, Regidor DL, Kovesdy CP, Kilpatrick RD, Shinaberger CS, McAllister CJ, Budoff MJ, Salusky IB, Kopple JD. Survival predictability of time-varying indicators of bone disease in maintenance hemodialysis patients. Kidney Int. 2006 Aug;70(4):771-80. Epub 2006 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>16820797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shinaberger CS, Kilpatrick RD, Regidor DL, McAllister CJ, Greenland S, Kopple JD, Kalantar-Zadeh K. Longitudinal associations between dietary protein intake and survival in hemodialysis patients. Am J Kidney Dis. 2006 Jul;48(1):37-49.</citation>
    <PMID>16797385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehrotra R, Martin KJ, Fishbane S, Sprague SM, Zeig S, Anger M; Fosrenol Overview Research Evaluation Study for Early Experience Study Group. Higher strength lanthanum carbonate provides serum phosphorus control with a low tablet burden and is preferred by patients and physicians: a multicenter study. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2008 Sep;3(5):1437-45. doi: 10.2215/CJN.04741107. Epub 2008 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>18579668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 29, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Los Angeles Biomedical Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>kamyar kalantar-zadeh, md phd mph</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of medicine, pediatrics and epidemiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypoalbuminemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperphosphatemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Phosphorus</keyword>
  <keyword>Protein</keyword>
  <keyword>CKD</keyword>
  <keyword>Dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Meals</keyword>
  <keyword>Lanthanum</keyword>
  <keyword>End-Stage Renal Disease (ESRD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Dietary Protein Intake (DPI)</keyword>
  <keyword>Dietary Phosphorus Binding (DPB)</keyword>
  <keyword>Protein-Energy Wasting (PEW)</keyword>
  <keyword>Sources of Dietary Phosphorus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

