<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01112527</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-468</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>WS573383</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01112527</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT01036477</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PF-00299804 in Adult Patients With Relapsed/Recurrent Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Phase 2 Trial of Orally Administered PF-00299804 in Adult Patients With Relapsed/Recurrent Glioblastoma (GBM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Henry Ford Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There are three arms to this study (A, B and C) The purpose of this research study during Arm
      A is to see how much of PF-00299804 gets into the brain tumor. For many brain tumors, one
      reason that chemotherapy drugs might not be effective is that the drug may not be able to get
      into the brain tumor and kill the cancer cells. We will determine how much PF-00299804 gets
      into the brain tumor by obtaining a sample of the tumor from the surgery that the participant
      already has scheduled. The purpose of this research study during Arm B and C, is to determine
      how well PF-00299804 works in killing cancer cells. PF-00299804 works by binding to specific
      proteins found on the surface of some cancer cells that promote a growth signal. Blocking
      this signal from reaching its target on the cancer cells may slow or stop the cancer from
      growing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ARM A:

        -  Each treatment cycle lasts four weeks (28 days). There are no breaks from taking
           PF-00299804 between treatment cycles. Participants will take PF-00299804 once a day for
           a total of 7 to 9 days before surgery. They will then stop taking PF-00299804 until they
           have recovered from surgery.

        -  Once they have recovered from surgery, they will continue to take PF-00299804 once a day
           until their disease worsens, they experience side effects or they decide to stop study
           treatment.

        -  The following tests and procedures will be performed at the time intervals specified:
           Research blood tests (Day 1 of study drug administration, day of surgery, day 1 of all
           cycles after surgery, day 14 of the first cycle after surgery); tissue samples (day of
           surgery); physical and neuro exams (day 1 of all cycles after surgery); skin exam (day 1
           of all cycles after surgery and day 14 of the first cycle after surgery).

        -  An assessment of the tumor by CT or MRI scan will be made within 24 hours after surgery.
           Another assessment by CT or MRI scan will be made at the end of cycle 2 and then at the
           end of every even numbered cycle thereafter.

      ARM B &amp; C:

        -  Each treatment cycle lasts four weeks (28 days). There are no breaks from taking
           PF-00299804 between treatment cycles. Participants will take PF-00299804 orally once a
           day until their disease worsens, they experience any side effect, or if they decide to
           stop study treatment.

        -  Participants will come into the clinic on Day 1 and Day 14 of Cycle 1, and then on Day 1
           of all subsequent cycles for some of the following tests and procedures: research blood
           tests, physical and neuro exams, skin exam, urine test and Patient Reported Outcomes
           questionnaire.

        -  An assessment of the participants tumor by CT scan or MRI scans will be done at the end
           of Cycle 2, 4 and then every other cycle thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess progression-free survival at six months in patients with recurrent GBM and EGFR amplification in archival tumor material who are treated with continuous daily dosing of PF-00299804 (Arm B)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability of PF-00299804 to cross the blood-brain barrier</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the ability of PF-00299804 to cross the blood-brain barrier in GBM patients who are candidates for surgical re-section in Arm A.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the safety and tolearbility of orally administered PF-00299804 on a continuous dosing schedule in patients with recurrent GBM.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-tumor response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess anti-tumor response in patients in Arm B</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>GBM</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma Multiforme</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with Glioblastoma that has returned or grown after chemotherapy or radiation treatment and who will be having a standard operation to remove the tumor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with glioblastoma at first recurrence who are not surgical candidates and who have not had prior anti-VEGF therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with glioblastoma who are not surgical candidates and who are at first recurrence from a therapeutic regimen containing bevacizumab.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PF-00299804</intervention_name>
    <description>Taken orally once a day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of a recurrent primary WHO grade IV malignant
             glioma (glioblastoma). Patients with recurrent disease whose diagnostic pathology
             confirmed glioblastoma will not need re-biopsy. Patients with prior low-grade glioma
             or anaplastic glioma are eligible if histologic assessment demonstrates transformation
             to GBM.

          -  Evidence of EGFR gene amplification by fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) in
             archival tumor material.

          -  Patients must have at least 15 unstained slides or 1 tissue block (frozen or paraffin
             embedded) available from a prior biopsy or surgery.

          -  For Arm A: patients must be at first recurrence of GBM, must not have had previous
             anti-VEGF therapy, and must be candidates for surgical partial or gross-total
             resection.

          -  For Arm B: patients must be at first recurrence of GBM and must not have had prior
             anti-VEGF therapy.

          -  For Arm C: patients may have had an unlimited number of prior therapies for GBM,
             however must be at first recurrence from a therapeutic regimen containing bevacizumab

          -  Progressive disease on contrast-enhanced brain CT or MRI as defined by McDonald
             Criteria, or have documented recurrent glioblastoma on diagnostic biopsy.

          -  Prior to enrollment, there must be an interval of at least 2 weeks between prior
             surgical resection (1 week for intracranial biopsy) and adequate wound healing.

          -  Interval of at least 12 weeks from prior radiotherapy unless there is either: a)
             histopathologic confirmation of recurrent tumor, or b) new enhancement on MRI outside
             of XRT treatment field.

          -  Patients must have sufficient time to recover from prior therapy.

          -  Karnofsky Performance Score 70% or greater

          -  Adequate hematologic and liver function as outlined in the protocol

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             prior to study entry and for the duration of study participation and for at least 3
             months thereafter.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of extra-cranial metastatic disease

          -  Participants may not be receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Prior investigational therapy with an agent that is known or proposed to be active by
             action on any component of the EGFR tyrosine kinase, IGF1R, mTor, orc-MET pathways

          -  Patients who have been previously treated with an anti-VEGF agent will be excluded
             from Arm A and Arm B.

          -  Patients must not have received prior Gliadel wafers

          -  For participants in Arm A, if the diagnostic pathology of the biopsy specimen is not
             consistent with recurrent glioblastoma, then the participant must be taken off study
             and be replaced with another participant that meets the inclusion criteria and is
             eligible for surgical resection.

          -  Any surgery (not including minor diagnostic procedures such as lymph node biopsy)
             within 2 weeks of baseline disease assessments; or not fully recovered from any side
             effects of previous procedures.

          -  Any clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities, which may impair intake,
             transit or absorption of the study drug.

          -  Any psychiatric or cognitive disorder that would limit the understanding or rendering
             of informed consent and/or compromise compliance with the requirements of this
             protocol

          -  Patients with known interstitial lung disease

          -  Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease

          -  Any patient with a history of significant cardiovascular disease, even if currently
             controlled, or who has signs or symptoms suggesting impaired left ventricular function
             in the judgment of the investigator must have a screening left ventricular ejection
             fraction evaluation by ECHO or MUGA. Patients with LVEF measurements below local
             institutional lower limit of normal or less then 50% will not be eligible.

          -  Individuals with a history of a different malignancy are ineligible except for the
             circumstances outlined in the protocol

          -  Patients who have had prior stereotactic radiotherapy, convection enhanced delivery or
             brachytherapy as gliosis/scarring from these modalities may limit delivery

          -  Patients will not be eligible if they present with leptomeningeal dissemination

          -  Pregnant women

          -  HIV-positive individuals on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to PF-00299804

          -  Other severe acute or chronic medical condition, uncontrolled intercurrent illness or
             laboratory abnormality that may increase the risk associated with trial participation
             or investigation product administration or may interfere with the interpretation of
             trial results and, in the judgment of the investigator, would make the patient
             inappropriate for entry into this trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tracy T. Batchelor, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henry Ford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 27, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 27, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 28, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>October 27, 2016</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 2016</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2016</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tracy T. Batchelor, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PF-00299804</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

