<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01116674</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00045186</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21DK081847</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CIH Registry</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01116674</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Critical Illness Hyperglycemia and Glycemic Control Registry</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pediatric Critical Illness Hyperglycemia and Glycemic Control Registry: A Project to Assist in the Improved Understanding of Hyperglycemia and Glycemic Control in Pediatric Critical Illness.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective in this project is to assemble a consortium of pediatric critical care centers
      of varying size, acuity, and composition to evaluate our glycemic control protocol on at
      least 250 children with hyperglycemia in different critical care units.

      ***This Study is supported by an R21 Grant (MRR) from the National Institute of Diabetes and
      Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Many studies over the past decade have demonstrated that clinical outcomes can be improved in
      critically ill adults by aggressive management of hyperglycemic with insulin infusions (Van
      Den Berghe 2001, Van Den Berghe 2006, Krinsey 2004, Treggari 2008, Scalea, 2007, Lang 2007).
      Yet, in some of these studies and other recent trials (i.e. Glucontrol (Preiser, 2009) VISEP
      (Brunkhorst, 2008) and (NICE-SUGAR, 2009)), have highlighted the potential and real risks of
      glycemic control (namely iatrogenic hypoglycemia) and questioned how effectively glucose can
      be controlled in critical illness. One reason for the suboptimal glycemic control witnessed
      in some trials may be not rigorously refined and validated. Even as such, many medical
      oversight committees (including the Institutes of Healthcare Improvement, the American
      Diabetes Association, and Society of Critical Care Medicine, among others) continue to
      recommend regular and aggressive glycemic control in critically ill patients. Although not
      specifically included nor excluded from such recommendations, most pediatric intensivists
      have not incorporated glycemic control into regular practice primarily due to concerns of
      therapy induced hyperglycemia - although there are reports of protocols that appear to be
      effective at controlling BG levels with low rates of hypoglycemia (Preissig et al 2008,
      Verhoeven et al 2009).

      Our group at Emory University and Children's' Healthcare of Atlanta has taken a progressive,
      yet methodical, approach to better understand the implications of hyperglycemia and its
      treatment in critically ill and injured children. Practitioners at our facility developed a
      pediatric-specific protocol to identify and treat hyperglycemia in critically ill children.
      We have instituted this approach as standard care in our facility and have experience with
      managing several hundred children with hyperglycemia. Our approach to glycemic management has
      very promising safety and efficacy profiles, even when compared to the most stringent and
      successful glycemic control protocols used in adults. We published the first experience in
      pediatric glycemic control in pediatric in 2008 (Preissig et al PCCM 2008) and have used our
      experience to identify specific risk factors for developing hypoglycemia (Preissig et al
      JPed, 2009).

      The goal of this proposal is to assist our step-wise approach in investigating hyperglycemia
      in critically ill children by externally validating our glycemic control protocol via
      multi-center evaluation. In doing so, we will also be developing the infrastructure and a
      tested intervention that can be leveraged for future studies of hyperglycemia in pediatric
      critical illness, including a multi-center outcome trial. The specific hypothesis for this
      project is that our protocol is safe and efficient at identifying and managing hyperglycemia
      in critically ill or injured children in pediatric ICUs regardless of ICU size, acuity,
      model, staffing makeup, or clinical focus.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify and manage hyperglycemia in pediatric intensive care unit</measure>
    <time_frame>5-2012</time_frame>
    <description>Determine safety (ie hypoglycemia) and effectiveness (ie ability to establish/maintain glycemic control) of our pedatric-specific approach to control critical illness hyperglycemia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Consortium of centers practiced at glycemic control in pediatric intensive care unit.</measure>
    <time_frame>5-2012</time_frame>
    <description>To develop a consortium of centers that will be practiced at glycemic control who may be able to participate in a future multi-center trial in glycemic control. To use the experience of other centers to refine a generalizable protocol to successfully and safely control hyperglycemia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">206</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoglycemia Hyperglycemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glycemic Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>Critically ill children at participating centers who require select vital organ support measure (i.e. mechanical ventilation, vasopressor, or continuous renal replacement therapy) will have routine blood glucose (BG) screening initiated (i.e. at least q 12 hours). If a patient has a BG reading of &gt; 140 mg/dL, a repeat BG will be obtained in 1-2 hours. If this second BG is &gt; 140 mg/dL the patient will be diagnosed with critical illness hyperglycemia and an insulin infusion will be started and BG will be maintained between 80-140 using a pediatric specific developed and tested algorithm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Childern upto 18 or 21 years old admitted to pedaitric intensive care units who are ar risk
        for deleveloping critical illness hyperglycemia.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Critically ill children requiring mechanical ventilation, vasopressor/inotropes,
             continuous renal replacement therapy or other criteria, will have glycemic screening
             initiated. (Such are the risk factors that have been demonstrated to assist in the
             identification of critically children who will develop hyperglycemia (Preissig et al.,
             JPeds., 2009)

          -  Admission to the pediatric medical/surgical or pediatric cardiac intensive care unit

          -  Require mechanical ventilation (endotracheal or via tracheotomy) and/or
             vasopressors/inotropic infusions (including dopamine, dobutamine, norepinephrine,
             epinephrine, vasopressin, or milrinone)

          -  Patient or family member available to discuss informed consent criteria and provide
             informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with type I diabetes mellitus presenting to the ICU in diabetic ketoacidosis
             (DKA)

          -  Preexisting conditions in which there is impaired glycogen stores or counter
             regulatory response (i.e. inborn error of metabolism, fulminant hepatic failure)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark R Rigby, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University and Children's Healthcare of Atlanta at Egleston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cathering M Preissig, MD (Co-I)</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Medical Center of Central Georgia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin O Maher, MD (Co-I)</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University and Children's Healthcare of Atlanta at Egleston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel C Keeton, BA (Coordinator)</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta at Egleston and Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeryl Huckaby, RRT (Coordinator)</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta at Egleston and Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta at Egleston - Pediatric Cardiac Intensive Care Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta at Egleston - Pediatric Intensive Care Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Center of Central Georgia - Pediatric Intensive Care Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Macon</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>31201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Preissig CM, Rigby MR, Maher KO. Glycemic control for postoperative pediatric cardiac patients. Pediatr Cardiol. 2009 Nov;30(8):1098-104. doi: 10.1007/s00246-009-9512-4. Epub 2009 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>19705188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Preissig CM, Rigby MR. Pediatric critical illness hyperglycemia: risk factors associated with development and severity of hyperglycemia in critically ill children. J Pediatr. 2009 Nov;155(5):734-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2009.05.007. Epub 2009 Jul 22.</citation>
    <PMID>19628220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Preissig CM, Rigby MR. A disparity between physician attitudes and practice regarding hyperglycemia in pediatric intensive care units in the United States: a survey on actual practice habits. Crit Care. 2010;14(1):R11. doi: 10.1186/cc8865. Epub 2010 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20128893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Preissig CM, Hansen I, Roerig PL, Rigby MR. A protocolized approach to identify and manage hyperglycemia in a pediatric critical care unit. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2008 Nov;9(6):581-8. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e31818d36cb.</citation>
    <PMID>18838924</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intensive critical care, glycemic control, hypoglycemia, hyperglycemia , insulin treatment, intensive care outcomes, pediatrics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypoglycemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperglycemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

