<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01114191</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>M11-306</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01114191</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Assess the Effect of Ketoconazole on the Pharmacokinetics of Linifanib (ABT-869)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ph I Study to Assess the Effect of Ketoconazole on the Pharmacokinetics of Linifanib (ABT-869)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abbott</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abbott</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 1, open-label study designed to determine the interaction of ketoconazole
      with ABT-869.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to explore the drug interaction between ketoconazole and ABT-869 to
      determine the potential effect of ketoconazole on the metabolism of ABT-869. ABT-869 will be
      taken alone or in combination with ketoconazole. The safety of a single dose administration
      of ABT-869 when administered alone and in combination with ketoconazole will be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate the effect of ketoconazole on the pharmacokinetics of ABT-869 in subjects with advanced or metastatic solid tumors.</measure>
    <time_frame>Different timepoints on Days 1-12</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples for the PK of ABT-869 and ketoconazole will be collected at designated time points throughout the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Adverse Events - The number of participants with adverse events will be reported as a measure of Safety.</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse event monitoring, lab tests assessments, physical exam and vital signs will be evaluated throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ABT-869</intervention_name>
    <description>2.5mg [5 mg days 1, 8 and 12. 17.5 mg on days 13 and after]</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>linifanib, ABT-869</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ketoconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>400 mg days 6-11</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Male or female and age is &gt;= 18 years.

          2. Must have a histologically or cytologically confirmed non-hematologic malignancy.

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Score of 0-2.

          4. Must have adequate bone marrow, renal and hepatic function as follows:

               -  Bone Marrow: Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,500/mm3; Platelets &gt;=
                  100,000/mm3 ; Hemoglobin &gt;= 9.0 g/dL

               -  Renal function: serum creatinine &lt;= 2.0 mg/dL;

               -  Hepatic function: AST and ALT &lt;= 1.5 x ULN unless liver metastases are present,
                  then AST and ALT &lt;= 5.0 x ULN; bilirubin &lt;= 1.5 mg/dL

          5. Must have PTT &lt;= 1.5 x ULN and/or INR &lt;= 1.5.

          6. Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception (one
             of the following listed below) prior to study entry, for the duration of study
             participation and up to 90 days following completion of therapy. Women of childbearing
             potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test within 7 days prior to initiation
             of treatment and/or post menopausal women must be amenorrheic for at least 12 months
             to be considered of non-childbearing potential.

               -  Total abstinence from sexual intercourse (minimum one complete menstrual cycle);

               -  Vasectomized male subjects or vasectomized partner of female subjects;

               -  Hormonal contraceptives (oral, parenteral or transdermal) for at least 3 months
                  prior to study drug administration; if the subject is currently using a hormonal
                  contraceptive, she should also use a barrier method during this study and for 1
                  month after study completion;

               -  Intrauterine device (IUD);

               -  Double barrier method (condoms, contraceptive sponge, diaphragm or vaginal ring
                  with spermicidal jellies or creams);

               -  Additionally, male subjects (including those who are vasectomized) whose partners
                  are pregnant or might be pregnant must agree to use condoms for the duration of
                  the study and for 90 days following completion of therapy.

          7. Is capable of understanding and complying with parameters as outlined in the protocol
             and able to sign the informed consent, approved by an Independent Ethic Committee
             (IEC)/Institutional Review Board (IRB) prior to the initiation of any screening or
             study-specific procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Has received anti-cancer therapy including investigational agents, cytotoxic
             chemotherapy, radiation therapy or biologic therapy within 21 days or within a period
             defined by 5 half lives, whichever is shorter, prior to study drug administration. In
             addition subject has not recovered to less than or equal to Grade 1 clinically
             significant adverse effects/toxicities of the previous therapy.

          2. Has undergone major surgery within 21 days of Study Day 1.

          3. Has untreated brain or meningeal metastases. Subjects with treated brain metastases
             that are radiographically or clinically stable (for at least 4 weeks after therapy)
             and who have no evidence of cavitation or hemorrhage in the brain lesion, are eligible
             provided that they are asymptomatic and do not require corticosteroids (must have
             discontinued steroids at least 1 week prior to Study Day 1).

          4. Has a central thoracic tumor lesion as defined by location involving or abutting the
             hilar structures. The presence of central nodal disease is allowed.

          5. Female subjects who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          6. Has received potential inhibitors of the metabolism of linifanib within 21 days prior
             to initial study drug administration. Such drugs include CYP3A inhibitors e.g.,
             triazole, itraconazole, ketoconazole, fluconazole, grapefruit juice, verapamil,
             diltiazem, aprepitant, clarithromycin and erythromycin; CYP1A2 inhibitors e.g.,
             fluvoxamine, ciprofloxacin, mexiletine, propafenone and zileuton; CYP2C19 inhibitors
             e.g., omeprazole; CYP2C8 substrates e.g., repaglinide, paclitaxel and rosiglitazone
             and CYP3A inducers e.g., rifampin and carbamazepine.

          7. Has proteinuria defined by the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria
             for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) Grade &gt; 1 at baseline as measured by a urine dipstick
             (2+ or greater) and confirmed by a 24 hour urine collection (&gt; 1 g/24 hrs). Subjects
             may be re-screened if proteinuria is shown to be controlled with or without
             intervention.

          8. Currently exhibits symptomatic or persistent, uncontrolled hypertension defined as
             diastolic blood pressure (BP) &gt; 100 mmHg; or systolic blood pressure (BP) &gt; 150 mmHg.
             Subjects may be re-screened if BP is shown to be controlled with or without
             intervention.

          9. Clinically significant uncontrolled condition(s) including but not limited to:

               -  Active uncontrolled infection

               -  Class III or IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart Association
                  functional classification system

               -  Unstable angina pectoris or cardiac arrhythmia

               -  Myocardial infarction within last 6 months

               -  History of adrenal insufficiency

               -  History of cerebral vascular accident within last 6 months

               -  Active ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease, celiac disease or any other
                  conditions that interfere with absorption

               -  History of autoimmune disease with kidney involvement

               -  History of overt bleeding (&gt; 30 mL bleeding/episode) within 3 months of study
                  drug administration

               -  Psychiatric illness/social situation that would limit compliance with study
                  requirements

               -  Any medical condition, which in the opinion of the study investigator places the
                  subject at an unacceptably high risk for toxicities

         10. Is receiving combination anti-retroviral therapy for human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV).

         11. Has consumed grapefruit or grapefruit products within 21 days prior to initial study
             drug administration.

         12. Has a documented left ventricular (LV) ejection fraction &lt; 50%.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark D McKee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Abbott</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 35784</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site Reference ID/Investigator# 36527</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <zip>03756-0001</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 26, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Mark McKee, MD, Medical Director, Oncology</name_title>
    <organization>Abbott</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketoconazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

