<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01116063</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COPDVEN 2009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01116063</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Inhaled Iloprost for Disproportionate Pulmonary Hypertension in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</brief_title>
  <acronym>COPDVEN</acronym>
  <official_title>Inhaled Iloprost for Disproportionate Pulmonary Hypertension in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carmel Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Carmel Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pulmonary hypertension is frequently present in COPD and it is generally limited to a mild
      increase in mean pulmonary artery pressure. However some COPD patients are characterized by
      higher levels of mPAP at rest, fulfilling the definition of moderate or severe PH
      disproportionate PH .

      In these patients the elevated pulmonary pressures adversely affect the prognosis.At the
      present time the evidence for the the use of specific pulmonary vasodilators in the
      management of these patients are scarce and cannot be recommended.the aim of this study is to
      evaluate the medium term efficacy and safety of the inhaled prostacyclin stable analog,
      iloprost in patients with COPD and moderate to severe pulmonary hypertension
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While pulmonary hypertension is frequently present in COPD, particularly in the presence of
      hypoxemia, it is generally limited to a mild increase in mean pulmonary artery pressure in
      the face of a normal cardiac output.

      Apart from this classical and widely observed profile of PH with modestly elevated mPAP, some
      COPD patients are characterized by higher levels of mPAP at rest, fulfilling the definition
      of moderate or severe PH . This kind of PH may be observed in patients presenting with a
      severe obstructive disease, but sometimes contrasts with a mild or moderate obstruction. In
      the latter case, the term disproportionate PH has been proposed, but it can be extended to
      describe all COPD patients with moderate to- severe PH.

      Therefore, it is possible that in some patients with COPD, pulmonary hypertension contributes
      to the clinical picture because of right ventricular output limitation and is responsible for
      the poor prognosis of these patients, which is similar to that in primary pulmonary arterial
      hypertension.

      The exact incidence of clinically significant pulmonary hypertension, defined as pulmonary
      hypertension that contributes to symptomatology and prognosis, is difficult to estimate in
      COPD. A prevalence of 5.8%- 13.5% in patients seems reasonable which would suggest an
      incidence of 1-3/10,000, which is 100 times the incidence of idiopathic pulmonary arterial
      hypertension.

      These patients are characterized by marked effort dyspnea , profound hypoxemia, hypocapnia,
      moderate airway obstruction and a very low DLCO.

      PH in COPD was an independent prognostic factor. Indeed, patients with similar airflow
      limitation had lower life expectancy when PH was resent. Patients with PH had a significantly
      lower survival rate at 5 yrs compared with patients without PH (33 versus 66%). Pathologic
      studies that stemmed from long-term oxygen trials pointed to the fact that pulmonary vascular
      remodeling in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is more than just medial
      hypertrophy from long-lasting hypoxic vasoconstriction. In these patients, all vessel wall
      layers appear to be involved, with intimal changes actually being the most prominent. Major
      remodeling of all pulmonary arterial vessel layers explains why pulmonary hypertension in
      COPD is often not,or minimally, reversible by supplemental oxygen, acutely or chronically.
      The pathobiology of pulmonary artery remodeling in advanced COPD remains incompletely
      explored. There are data supporting an endothelium-derived vasoconstrictor-dilator imbalance,
      mainly from a decreased endothelial nitric oxide expression. Plasma levels of ET-1 are
      increased both in patients with severe COPD and there is evidence that ETA and ETB receptor
      expression is increased in the pulmonary arteries of patients with COPD.

      The major unmet medical need is the absence of a simple drug therapy that relieves the
      breathlessness or muscle fatigue, reduces pulmonary vascular resistance and the overloaded
      right ventricles that severely limits exercise tolerance in COPD and affects survival.

      The only validated therapeutic approach of the 'common' PH in COPD patients is long-term
      oxygen therapy. A large variety of vasodilators has been tested in numerous studies both
      after short- and medium-term administration. The early enthusiasm vanished subsequently for
      several reasons: modesty of the vasodilator effect, inability for some drugs to sustain the
      acute benefit, no specificity of the vasodilator effect with concomitant systemic
      vasodilatation, deleterious effect on gas exchange due to a diminution of the
      ventilation/perfusion ratio and no demonstration of a survival benefit. At the present time
      vasodilators cannot be recommended in the management of COPD.

      Treatments of PAH have shown a dramatic change in the past few years. Synthetic prostacyclin
      (epoprostenol), prostacyclin analogues, endothelin-1 receptor antagonists and
      phosphodiesterase-5 inhibitors are in use in group I PAH with improve clinical outcome.

      Based on analogy to primary pulmonary hypertension, a specific interventions aiming at the
      restoration of endothelial vasoconstrictor- dilator imbalance could be undertaken.

      Selective pulmonary vasodilatation by inhalation of the vasorelaxant agent is an appealing
      concept to circumvent some of the hazards inherent in systemic vasodilator therapy in COPD
      patients with PH. Treatment of these patients with aerosolization of iloprost may reduce
      pulmonary vascular resistance , increases cardiac output while conserving
      ventilation-perfusion matching and and shunt preventing worsening of arterial hypoxia and
      wasting of the small ventilatory reserve of these patients.

      In order to resolve these uncertainties we suggest evaluating the effectiveness of an inhaled
      iloprost in COPD patients with moderate to severe pulmonary hypertension. This evaluation
      would include monitoring and measurement of all the relevant cardio-respiratory variables as
      set out in detail below.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary vascular resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 minutes walking test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Borg dyspnea score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NT-BNP</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial blood gases</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm open label</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will receive the study drugs and will be evaluated</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inhaled iloprost</intervention_name>
    <description>Inhalation Initial: 2.5 mcg/dose; if tolerated, increase to 5 mcg/dose; administer 6 times daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm open label</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brand name - Ventavis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient with COPD and increased SPAP &gt;55 on echocardiogram will be screened for the
             study.

          2. Patients with normal wedge pressure ( [PCWP] ≤ 15 mm Hg), mean PAP ≥ 35 mm Hg and a
             pulmonary vascular resistance (PVR- 3.0 wood unit)on right heart catheterization.

          3. Diagnosis of COPD according to GOLD guidelines

          4. The patient can read, understand and sign the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1. Other identified cause for pulmonary hypertension
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yochai Adir, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Pulmoanry Division, Carmel Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yochai aDIR, MD</last_name>
    <phone>972-4-8250517</phone>
    <email>yochaiad@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pulmoanry Division, Carmel Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yochai Adir, MD</last_name>
      <phone>972-4-8250517</phone>
      <email>yochaiad@clalit.org.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yochai Adir, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 4, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 4, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Yochai Adir, Director pulmonary hypertesnion service</name_title>
    <organization>Pulmonary divison Carmel Medical Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>COPD, Pulmonary hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Iloprost</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

