<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01117415</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-07-40</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>09-07-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01117415</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cost Effectiveness Analysis of Cholecystectomy, Projected Long Term Outcomes and Complications Evaluation</brief_title>
  <acronym>NOTES</acronym>
  <official_title>Cost Effectiveness Analysis of Transgastric Cholecystectomy, Transvaginal Cholecystectomy, and Laparoscopic Cholecystectomy: Projected Long Term Outcomes and Complications Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Participation in this research study does not involve any procedures. Health preference will
      be ascertained through standard techniques including time-tradeoff, standard gamble, and
      rating scale to assess risks regarding potential complications specific to NOTES (Natural
      Orifice Translumenal Endoscopic Surgery)gallbladder removal.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The enticement of scarless surgery has created an unprecedented wave of enthusiasm and
      collaboration amongst surgeons, gastroenterologists, industry, and the lay public. However,
      major hurdles remain between current minimally invasive practices and the ultimate goal of
      safe, effective Natural Orifice Translumenal Endoscopic Surgery (NOTES). In an ideal world,
      these procedures should incur equivalent (or less) morbidity than current laparoscopic
      approaches and offer benefits of incisionless surgery. This idealism has been quickly
      tempered by the potential to create new and devastating complications with only minimal
      potential benefit to the patient. Several critical questions need to be answered. What
      probability of complication(s) are to be accepted? How will the potential benefits of NOTES
      be weighed against these new complications? What factors unique to NOTES will contribute to
      its cost effectiveness? The proposed study seeks to answer these questions before they occur.
      These results will give clinicians and investigators the necessary information with which to
      compare outcomes of NOTES and potentially alter techniques for safer, more effective
      interventions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare cost effectiveness data at one year postoperative</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>One year cost effectiveness data comparing transgastric cholecystectomy, transvaginal cholecystectomy, and laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Costs from two national databases: the State Ambulatory Surgery Database (SASD) and the NIS. The main outcome measure for this study will be cost per quality adjusted life year (QALY). Markov modeling techniques for model patient experiences for each of the procedures analyzed. Monte Carlo simulation will be used to calculate cost per QALY over a one year time span with determination of the incremental cost effectiveness ratio.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analyze the important factor that contributes to cost effectiveness at one year post operative.</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>Extensive sensitivity analyses of how individual factors (e.g. probability of gastric leak in transgastric cholecystectomy) impact cost effectiveness. Factors are varied over a clinically plausible range and their impact on cost effectiveness determined. One way and two way sensitivity analyses allow alterations of one or two factors simultaneously. Multiway sensitivity analysis using Monte Carlo simulation will be used to vary several variables simultaneously and to determine impact on cost effectiveness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">37</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholelithiasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gall Bladder Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <description>Who have symptomatic cholelithiasis and wish to undergo laparoscopic cholecystectomy for treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The participants will be recruited from the University Hospitals Case Medical Center
        Department of Surgery. The patient population in this study for the visual analog scale
        measurement, standard gamble questionnaire, and time trade-off questionnaire will be
        candidates of either sex, 18 years old or above, who have symptomatic cholelithiasis and
        wish to undergo laparoscopic cholecystectomy for treatment. The patients will be asked to
        participate in the study after evaluation by either the principal investigator,
        co-investigators, or study coordinator. The investigator will discuss the study with the
        patient and the study coordinator will participate in reviewing details and questions
        regarding the study if necessary. Patients will be recruited until 40 participants are
        enrolled.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Candidate of either sex

          -  18 years old or above

          -  Have symptomatic cholelithiasis

          -  Wish to undergo laparoscopic cholecystectomy for treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Benjamin K. Poulose, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals Case Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeffrey Marks, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gall Bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholecystectomy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholelithiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholecystolithiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gallstones</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

