<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01119014</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TEAprotocolversion5-11 03 2010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2009-016715-38</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01119014</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tolerance and Effect of Antipsychotics in Children and Adolescents With Psychosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>TEA</acronym>
  <official_title>Tolerance and Effect of Antipsychotics in Children and Adolescents With Psychosis- An Investigator-initiated, Phase IV, Randomised Double-blind Multi-centre Trial of the Benefits and Harms of Aripiprazole Versus Quetiapine in Children and Adolescents With Psychosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Anne Katrine Pagsberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Psychiatric Centre for Children and Adolescents in Bispebjerg, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Psychiatric Centre Copenhagen, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Copenhagen Trial Unit, Center for Clinical Intervention Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Research Institute for Biological Psychiatry, Sct. Hans Hospital, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Capital Region Pharmacy, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Research Council for Health and Disease, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Allocated inheritance from Elizabeth Stevn and Niels Rindom, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AP Moeller Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tryg Fonden, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Copenhagen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The benefits and harms of antipsychotics are relatively well studied in adults. However,
      there is a lack of scientifically valid studies regarding the benefits and harms of
      antipsychotics in children and adolescents with psychosis.

      The main objective of the TEA trial is to compare the efficacy and adverse reactions of two
      antipsychotics (quetiapine versus aripiprazole) in children and adolescents between 12-17
      years of age with psychotic symptoms on psychopathology, cognitive deficits, and daily
      functioning. Furthermore, the trial will focus on adverse reaction profiles of the two
      antipsychotics as well as early predictors of later sustained clinical effects of these
      antipsychotics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A sex and age matched healthy control group will be included to form a reference group for
      cognitive and somatic measures. The healthy controls will not receive any trial medication.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychopathology: improvement on PANSS positive scale (PANSS 'Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale')</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychopathology</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Psychopathology (other PANSS scales, DIPI, SGI-S, CGI-I,and GAPD).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cognition and functioning (BACS Global Score, SCoRS-DK, Schizophrenia Cognition Rating Scale, BRIEF)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse reactions (UKU side effect scale, AIMS, SAS, BARS, and other adverse events)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Suicidal ideation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Suicidal ideation (K-SADS-PL, specific questions for depressive disorders (current)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic and antipsychotic laboratory tests</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Genetic variants affecting metabolism of antipsychotics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prognostic factors</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Prognostic factors (DUP, and PAS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Life (measured with Kidscreen)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stigmatization</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Qualitative interviews</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Psychosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aripirazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Quetiapine prolong</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aripiprazole</intervention_name>
    <description>pill, 2,5-20 mg/day, maximum 16 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aripirazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quetiapine</intervention_name>
    <description>pill, 50-600mg/day, maximum 16 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quetiapine prolong</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients - Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis: Children and adolescents with a non-organic and non-drug-induced psychosis,
             meeting the criteria for ICD-10 diagnoses: F20, F22-F29 and F30.2, F31.2 F31.5, F32.3
             and F33.3. This is verified with a semi-structured psychopathological interview using
             K-SADS-PL (Kaufmann 1997) four weeks after inclusion into the trial.

          -  Psychopathology: Children and adolescents with psychotic symptoms, scoring ≥ 4 on at
             least one of the following PANSS items: P1 (delusions), P2 (conceptual
             disorganisation), P3 (hallucinations), P5 (grandiosity), P6
             (suspiciousness/persecution) or G9 (unusual thought content); and a total PANSS score
             &gt; 60. The treating physician has decided to prescribe an antipsychotic compound.

          -  Age: 12-17 years (both inclusive).

          -  Sex: Both sexes are included.

          -  Previous treatment: Patients must be antipsychotic-naïve. The maximum accepted
             previous treatment with antipsychotic compounds is two weeks cumulatively, and during
             the two weeks prior to inclusion no continuous treatment and a maximum of four dosages
             in total can have been received.

          -  Somatic illness: No somatic contraindication to planned medication, documented by
             standard somatic examination

          -  Written informed consent.

        Patients - Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Compulsory treatment: Patients that are compulsorily hospitalised against their will
             are excluded. If their status changes to voluntary hospitalisation, patients can be
             included. If the patient is already included in the trial and is briefly detained,
             confined, or subjected to other forceful treatment according to the Danish Psychiatric
             Care Act ('Psykiatriloven'), both the patient and parents have to agree to remain in
             the trial if exclusion is to be avoided. Compulsory treatment in the form of, e.g.,
             brief forced immobilisation or single instances of forced medication, are not causes
             for exclusion.

          -  Diagnoses: Patients with drug-induced or organic psychosis, severe chronic somatic
             illness, or a history of severe head-trauma are not included. Patients that do not
             have psychotic symptoms but are prescribed antipsychotic treatment on the indication
             of, e.g., severe behavioural problems or tics are not included.

          -  Pregnancy: Pregnant or lactating patients are not included (a pregnancy test is
             undertaken at inclusion). Female participants, that are sexually active, must use safe
             contraception throughout the trial period (see section 6.4)

          -  Substance abuse: People with severe alcohol or drug abuse are not included. Possible
             abuse is monitored both by interviewing participants and by taking a urine sample at
             inclusion and at 4, 12 and 52 weeks follow-up (if there is suspicion of substance
             abuse), testing for the presence of cocaine, amphetamine, cannabis, opiates,
             metamfetamine (inclusive for extacy), and benzodiazepines. When severe abuse is
             suspected during the trial, an ad hoc urine sample is taken. Brief periods of large
             alcohol/cannabis intake are not a cause of exclusion from the trial; however,
             cognitive and other examinations are not carried out while patients are under the
             influence of drugs or alcohol.

          -  Aggravation: Patients may be excluded if there is a significant worsening of clinical
             state during the course of the trial (i.e., increases of 30% or more from baseline on
             the PANSS total score).

          -  Allergy and intolerance: Patients with allergy towards the investigational drugs, or
             is lactose intolerant are not included.

          -  Lack of informed consent.

        Healthy volunteers - Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Matching: Healthy controls (n=100) are included, in the way that they are matched to
             the first 100 patients included in the study (i.e., corresponding to the number of
             patients required in each treatment group). They will be matched according to:

               -  age;

               -  sex; and

               -  socioeconomic status (based on a combination of parental education and income,
                  according to criteria from the National Institute of Public Health (earlier
                  Danish Institute of Clinical Epidemiology, DIKE)).

          -  Informed consent.

        Healthy volunteers - Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Psychopathology: People with a previous psychotic disorder (ICD 10, F20-F29 and F30.2,
             F31.2, F31.5, F32.3 and F33.3) or current psychiatric disorder (multiaxial axis 1) are
             not included. This is verified by diagnostic screening using K-SADS-PL at eligibility
             assessment before inclusion into the study of healthy controls. The presence of
             psychotic psychiatric diagnoses in first-degree relatives is also a cause for
             exclusion.

          -  Somatic illnesses: People with severe chronic somatic illness or a history of severe
             head-trauma are not included.

          -  Intelligence: People with known mild mental retardation (i.e., IQ between 50-70) prior
             to inclusion are excluded; however, if mild mental retardation is found during the
             study, participants are not excluded, since they must be considered a marginal part of
             the normal distribution. People with moderate to severe mental retardation (i.e., IQ &lt;
             50) are excluded.

          -  Substance abuse: People with severe alcohol- or drug abuse are excluded. Possible
             abuse is monitored both by interviewing participants and by taking a urine sample at
             inclusion and at 4, 12 and 52 weeks follow-up (if there is suspicion of substance
             abuse), testing for the presence of cocaine, amphetamine, cannabis, opiates,
             metamfetamine (inclusive for extacy) and benzodiazepines. Brief periods of large
             alcohol/cannabis intake are not a cause of exclusion from the study; however,
             cognitive and other examinations are not carried out while participants are under the
             influence.

          -  Lack of informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne Katrine Pagsberg, MD, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bispebjerg Centre for Child and Adolescent Psychiatry. University of Copenhagen.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pia Jeppesen, MD, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Glostrup Centre for Child and Adolescent Psychiatry. University of Copenhagen.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maj-Britt Lauritsen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hillerød Centre for Child and Adolescent Psychiatry.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Per Hove-Thomsen, Professor, MD, D.M.Sci.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Psychiatric Hospital for Children and Adolescents, Aarhus University Hospital.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marlene Briciet Lauritsen, MD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Child- and Adolescent Psychiatric Department, Aalborg.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Niels Bilenberg, Professor, MD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Department, University of Southern Denmark, Odense</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Werge, Professor, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Research Institute for Biological Psychiatry, Sct. Hans Hospital, Roskilde.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anders Fink-Jensen, MD, professor, DMSci.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Psychiatric Centre Copenhagen. University of Copenhagen.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jesper Pedersen, MD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Psychiatric Hospital for Children and Adolescent; Region Zeeland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aalborg Psychiatric Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aalborg</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychiatric Centre Copenhagen, Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bispebjerg Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2400</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Glostrup Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glostrup</city>
        <zip>2600</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hillerød Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hillerød</city>
        <zip>3400</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Odense University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense</city>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychiatric Hospital for Children and Adolescents, Aarhus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Risskov</city>
        <zip>8240</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Department, Region Zealand</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roskilde</city>
        <zip>4000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychiatric Centre Sct. Hans</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roskilde</city>
        <zip>4000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 3, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Copenhagen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anne Katrine Pagsberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD., PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Aripiprazole</keyword>
  <keyword>Quetiapine</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Child</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antipsychotic Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aripiprazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Quetiapine Fumarate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

