<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03224494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6021016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03224494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Bowel Sensitivity Threshold in IBS Patients Versus in Healthy Controls Using the Novel Rapid Barostat Bag</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Visceral Bowel Sensitivity Threshold in Irritable Bowel Syndrome Patients Versus in Healthy Controls Using the Novel Rapid Barostat Bag</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Queen's University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Queen's University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND &amp; AIMS: Bowel hypersensitivity (lower threshold for discomfort in response to
      distention of a balloon in the rectum compared to healthy controls) is a key documented
      feature in Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS) mechanistic studies. The use of the barostat
      catheter to assess bowel hypersensitivity has been well documented in research settings, but
      it's use is time consuming which makes it unpractical for routine clinical practice (test
      time up to 60 minutes). The Rapid Barostat Bag is a novel device used to obtain a rapid and
      simple assessment of the rectal function, which has received approval for use by Health
      Canada. Although its safety and use has been validated in healthy controls, RBB use has never
      been reported in a cohort of IBS patients. The aim of this study is to 1) evaluate bowel
      sensitivity in IBS patients, compared with healthy controls and 2) determine whether the
      sensory threshold predicts response to standard of care interventions such as diet or
      medications.

      METHODS: This is a prospective controlled study. All participants will undergo RBB testing
      and will answer a questionnaire related to bowel symptoms (IBS-SSS - IBS Severity Scoring
      System) and a questionnaire related to anxiety/depression (HADS - Hospital and Anxiety and
      Depression Scale).

      HYPOTHESIS: The investigators hypothesize that IBS patients will display lower bowel
      sensitivity thresholds than healthy controls, using the RBB device. Furthermore, we predict
      that those with a low sensory threshold (i.e. visceral hypersensitivity) are most likely to
      respond to interventions that decrease bowel distention (e.g. low FODMAP diet) or the
      medication linaclotide that is reported to decrease pain signaling.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      IBS is a clinical entity characterized by abdominal pain and altered bowel movements. About
      20% of the western population is affected by IBS. Abnormal perception of visceral stimuli
      plays a paramount role in the pathogenesis of IBS related abdominal pain. Moreover,
      sensitization (modulation of intracellular mechanisms leading to exaggerated action potential
      discharge in response to a given stimulus) of nociceptive dorsal root ganglia (DRG) neurons
      by tissue mediators is a fundamental mechanism underlying abnormal pain signaling. Clinical
      management of IBS has consisted primarily of symptomatic management of the altered bowel
      movement pattern. Although these can also afford improvement in abdominal pain,
      pharmacotherapy directly targeting bowel hypersensitivity are limited. Tri-cyclic
      antidepressants have been used in small doses in selected IBS patients who have not responded
      to first line therapy, but anti-cholinergic side effects have limited their use. The low
      FODMAP diet is well described therapeutic intervention which also targets bowel
      hypersensitivity, and about 70% of patients respond to this intervention. However, predictors
      of response to the various IBS therapies are lacking, and treatment decisions are often made
      on a &quot;trial and error&quot; fashion.

      Assessment of bowel sensitivity has been reported using a barostat (an elastic balloon
      inflated manually by a syringe until rectal sensations are reported). Unfortunately, barostat
      device use has not been practical because considerable time is required to carry out the
      studies (up to 60 min). As such, barostat studies have been used mainly in research settings.

      The rapid barostat bag (RBB) is a novel handheld barostat device. It is quick and simple to
      use, and its polyethylene bag provides superior volume measurements than the elastic balloons
      currently in use. This test could ultimately provide a bedside measure in the clinic of
      patients and identify those who are hypersensitive and thus more likely to respond to
      therapies targeting this sensory disorder. Data on validation of the RBB method against the
      standard barostat system has been published, using healthy volunteers. However, no studies
      evaluating the use of the RBB to assess bowel visceral sensitivity have been published to
      date.

      Thus, there are 2 aims to this study:

      Aim 1. To evaluate bowel sensitivity in IBS patients, compared with healthy controls.

      Aim 2. To determine whether sensory thresholds measured in clinic at the time of the initial
      physical examination correlate with standard of care interventions, such as a low FODMAP diet
      or medication such as linaclotide.

      This new knowledge will afford the opportunity to gain new insights into the bowel
      hypersensitivity which characterizes IBS. The overall goal of this study will be to assess if
      IBS-mediated bowel hypersensitivity as assessed by the RBB can serve as predictor of response
      to IBS pharmacotherapy.

      Both healthy controls (n= 100) and IBS patients (n=100) will undergo anorectal studies using
      a Rapid barostat bag catheter. To test for stability of the response over time, IBS patients
      will be given the option of returning in one month time so these studies can be repeated.
      These studies will measure rectal perception to balloon inflation. The investigators will
      correlate the changes to IBS symptoms using the IBS severity scoring system questionnaire
      (IBS-SSS). The questionnaire will be administered twice for IBS patients who have consented
      to return for a second study visit, at each of the two RBB studies. The patients will also
      complete a validated anxiety and depression questionnaire (HAD scale). The symptom
      questionnaires will also be administered to the healthy controls, to prove that they indeed
      do not have symptoms of IBS. The Rapid Barostat Bag (Mui Scientific, Mississauga) will be
      used for these studies. It has been approved for clinical use by Health Canada. It is a
      computer driven volume displacement device. The device measures pressures and volumes
      (sampling rate 1-2mL/second) and is connected to a device that monitors sensations as 0= no
      pain,1=sensation, 2=urge, 3=discomfort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bowel sensory threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>A second visit to record sensory threshold a second time may be obtained up to 52 weeks after the first visit.</time_frame>
    <description>Sensory thresholds are obtained via rapid barostat bag measurements, and are expressed in millilitres.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IBS-SSS Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At first visit, and during a second visit. A second visit may be obtained up to 52 weeks after the first visit.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a validated symptom questionnaire pertaining to irritable bowel syndrome symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HADS scale questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At first visit, and during a second visit. A second visit may be obtained up to 52 weeks after the first visit.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a validated questionnaire pertaining to psychological parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Visceral Hypersensitivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IBS Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients 18 years or older with a diagnosis of irritable bowel symptom, as per Rome IV criteria. The diagnosis is established by the patient's gastroenterologist. Please see inclusion and exclusion section for more details.
They will undergo Rapid Barostat Bag testing, and they will answer the IBS severity scoring system questionnaire (IBS-SSS) and HAD scale questionnaire.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients 18 years of age without IBS or other colo-rectal symptoms or pathology seen for other issues in the general GI clinic.
They will undergo Rapid Barostat Bag testing, and they will answer the IBS severity scoring system questionnaire (IBS-SSS) and HAD scale questionnaire.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rapid Barostat Bag</intervention_name>
    <description>Both healthy controls (n= 100) and IBS patients (n=100) will undergo anorectal studies using a Rapid barostat bag catheter.</description>
    <arm_group_label>IBS Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IBS severity scoring system questionnaire (IBS-SSS)</intervention_name>
    <description>We will correlate the changes to IBS symptoms using the IBS severity scoring system questionnaire (IBS-SSS). The questionnaire will be administered twice for IBS patients who have consented to return for a second study visit, at each of the two RBB studies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>IBS Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HAD scale questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>It is a validated anxiety and depression questionnaire</description>
    <arm_group_label>IBS Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients diagnosed with IBS by their treating gastroenterologist, according to the
             Rome IV criteria. According to Rome IV criteria, IBS is defined as:

             recurrent abdominal pain, on average, at least one day per week in the last three
             months, associated with 2 or more of the following:

               1. pain is related to defecation

               2. associated with a change in stool frequency

               3. associated with a change in stool form.

          2. Irritable Bowel syndrome patients will be recruited from the GI motility clinic and
             general GI clinic at Hotel Dieu Hospital.

          3. Healthy controls will be recruited from the GI clinics. These are patients coming for
             evaluation for non-colonic symptoms such as colon screening, gastroesophageal reflux
             disease, or liver disease.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. patients under the age of 18;

          2. a recent change in IBS treatment regimen or patients taking analgesics, which may
             affect bowel sensitivity (this includes the FODMAP diet)

          3. pregnant patients, as there may be a small risk of inducing labor with the barostat
             probe

          4. patients who have had previous colorectal surgery as it may bowel sensitivity

          5. healthy controls who are experiencing bowel symptoms

          6. known significant anorectal pathology (eg. fistulae, abscess, stricture, etc)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Vanner, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Queen's University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stephen Vanner, MD</last_name>
    <phone>613-544-3400</phone>
    <phone_ext>2332</phone_ext>
    <email>vanners@hdh.kari.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Celine Morissette</last_name>
    <phone>613-544-3400</phone>
    <phone_ext>2479</phone_ext>
    <email>morissc@hdh.kari.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kingston Health Sciences Centre - HDH site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L5G2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Pichora, CEO</last_name>
      <phone>613-548-2341</phone>
      <email>KHSCCEO@hdh.kari.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vic Sahai, HDHRI Director</last_name>
      <phone>613-544-3400</phone>
      <phone_ext>3642</phone_ext>
      <email>sahaiv@hdh.kari.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sauter M, Heinrich H, Fox M, Misselwitz B, Halama M, Schwizer W, Fried M, Fruehauf H. Toward more accurate measurements of anorectal motor and sensory function in routine clinical practice: validation of high-resolution anorectal manometry and Rapid Barostat Bag measurements of rectal function. Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2014 May;26(5):685-95. doi: 10.1111/nmo.12317. Epub 2014 Feb 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24517865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Halmos EP, Power VA, Shepherd SJ, Gibson PR, Muir JG. A diet low in FODMAPs reduces symptoms of irritable bowel syndrome. Gastroenterology. 2014 Jan;146(1):67-75.e5. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2013.09.046. Epub 2013 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24076059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Queen's University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Stephen Vanner</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There will be no sharing of individual participation data with other researchers</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

