<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03228459</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>The ILERVAS project</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03228459</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The ILERVAS Project: Assessing the Prevalence of Subclinical Vascular Disease and Hidden Kidney Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>ILERVAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Intervention Study to Assess the Prevalence of Subclinical Vascular Disease and Hidden Kidney Disease and Its Impact on Morbidity and Mortality: The ILERVAS Project</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut de Recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Diputació de Lleida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundació Renal Jaume Arnó</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Unit of Detection and Treatment of Atherothrombotic diseases (UDETMA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lleida Primary health care</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut de Recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background and Objectives: Chronic kidney disease (CKD) and atherosclerosis are 2
      interrelated diseases that increase the risk of cardiovascular morbidity and mortality. The
      objectives of the ILERVAS project are: (1) to determine the prevalence of subclinical
      arterial disease and hidden kidney disease; (2) to assess the impact of early diagnosis of
      both diseases on cardiovascular morbidity and mortality and also on the progression of CKD;
      (3) to have a platform with clinical data, vascular imaging and biological samples to define
      a personalized cardiovascular risk profile.

      Methods: Randomized intervention study. From 2015 to 2017, 14,600 people (7,300 in the
      intervention group and 7,300 in the control group) aged between 45 and 70 years without a
      previous history of cardiovascular disease and with at least one cardiovascular risk factor
      will be randomly selected from the primary health care centers across the province of Lleida,
      Spain. A team of experts will travel around in a mobile unit to carry out the following
      baseline tests on the intervention group: artery ultrasound (carotid, femoral, transcranial
      and abdominal aorta), ankle-brachial index, spirometry, determination of advanced glycation
      end products, atrial fibrillation screening, dried blood spot and urine spot tests.
      Additionally, blood and urine samples will be collected and stored in the biobank to identify
      new biomarkers using omics studies. Participants will be followed up until 2027 to assess
      whether the intervention group has any changes on medical treatments and lifestyle changes.
      In addition, the incidence of cardiovascular events will be compared between the intervention
      and control groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study design and population: a randomized interventional study with 2 arms that will include
      14,600 individuals with at least one CV risk factor, registered in Primary care in the
      province of Lleida, between January 2015 and December 2017, who will subsequently be followed
      up until January 2027. The ILERVAS study data will be available on www.elbusdelasalut.cat/.

      Source of information and instruments for data collection: sociodemographic variables (age,
      sex and race), medical history of comorbidities and medical treatments will be collected from
      the electronic Primary Care medical history (e-CAP). The Mobile Unit (MU) has the equipment
      to perform all explorations of the study. In addition, variables such as physical exercise
      (International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ), diet (PREDIMED), and daytime
      somnolence (Berlin questionnaire and the Epworth somnolence scale) will be collected.

      Participant selection: from a total of 410,246 people with an open history in the e-CAP (on
      October 24, 2014), the study population that meets the inclusion criteria will be identified.
      Of these, a total of 14,600 people (7300 in the intervention group and 7300 in the control
      group) will be selected through simple randomization without replacement, within clusters
      defined by basic healthcare area, primary care (PC) center or doctor's office, in accordance
      with the total number of people who may be visited in the MU during one year period. The
      participants of the selected intervention group will be informed of the study objectives and
      the diagnostic tests to be performed by means of a personalized letter with an appointment
      day and time. Prior to the inclusion in the study they must sign the informed consent form.
      The study protocol has been approved by the Hospital Universitari Arnau de Vilanova (Lleida)
      Ethics Committee. One month before the MU reaches each population, 2 investigators
      responsible for the project will travel to explain the project to healthcare workers and
      administrators of the different healthcare basic areas; and to help with the interpretation
      of the results of the examinations and recommendations that will be included in the ILERVAS
      final report in the electronic medical history of each patient which are based on clinical
      practice guidelines.

      Follow-up period: as this is an asymptomatic population with a low-moderate CV risk, a
      minimum 10-year follow-up period has been established to observe the onset of CV events.
      Initially the cohort will be followed up from January 2015 to December 2027. The follow-up
      period may be lengthened, given that all data will be recorded in the e-CAP. The population
      selected will be monitored every six months to collect changes in medical history.

      Cardiovascular events and CKD progression: the onset of a CV event will be recorded according
      to the 10th version of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases (ICD-10),
      which includes: angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, transient ischemic attack,
      cerebrovascular accident, heart failure, arrhythmia, peripheral artery disease, aortic
      aneurysm, revascularization and angioplasty of any artery region. Likewise, the patient's
      cause of death, whether of CV origin (myocardial infarction, arrhythmia, heart failure,
      cerebrovascular accident, aortic aneurysm, mesenteric infarction or sudden death) or of
      non-CV origin (infections, cancers, accident or kidney disease) will be recorded. The
      information sources used to identify CV events will be: review of medical records (through
      the e-CAP) and consultation of the Catalonia mortality registry. CKD progression is defined
      as a doubling of creatinine or entry into renal replacement therapy, and will also be
      collected through the e-CAP.

      Clinical and Biochemical data: the following variables will be recorded: weight, height,
      waist circumference and neck circumference, body mass index in kg/m2, hours of fasting,
      systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure and pulse pressure (mmHg). Blood pressure
      will be measured 3 times (Omron 6®) at 2-min intervals and the mean of the last 2 will be
      collected. Dried capillary blood testing (fingertip puncture) will be used to determine
      creatinine, uric acid and total cholesterol, using the Reflotrons® Plus system (Roche). In
      cases in which total cholesterol is greater than 200 mg/dl, the complete lipid profile (HDL
      cholesterol, LDL cholesterol and triglycerides) will be determined using Cobas B 101® system,
      Roche. Non-HDL cholesterol levels, glycated hemoglobin (Cobas B 101 system, Roche), the
      CKD-EPI glomerular filtration rate will be determined as well. Albuminuria and
      albumin/creatinine ratio will be determined in urine sample from spontaneous micturition
      collected in the MU using Clinitek Microalbumin 2 Reagent Strips and a Siemens Clinitek
      Status® analyzer.

      Artery ultrasound: the examination and reading will be performed by 2 nurses specialized in
      vascular imaging diagnostics, following a standardized protocol with the patient in supine
      decubitus. The VIVID I version BT12 ultrasound system (GE Healthcare) will be used. The
      system has a 12L-RS/4-13 MHz linear probe (carotid and femoral arteries), a 4C-RS/1.5-6 MHz
      convex probe (abdominal aorta) and a 3SRS/ 1.5-2.5 MHz sector probe (transcranial). It also
      has a module for measuring intima-media thickness and pulsed Doppler ultrasound to assess
      hemodynamic abnormalities in the case that atheromatous plaques are present, and also to
      analyze the intracranial circulation. The DICOM network connectivity system will be used to
      record the results and ultrasound images online in the e-CAP.

      Carotid arteries: a total of 8 vascular regions will be analyzed (common carotid, bifurcation
      or bulb, internal carotid and external carotid), with the patient in supine decubitus and the
      head turned 45º towards the opposite side in the examination. The transversal examination
      will be started with a 2D longitudinal seccion of the common carotid up to the bifurcation.
      At this level, color Doppler will be used to distinguish the external carotid from the
      internal carotid and then examine both carotids simultaneously. The presence of an
      atheromatous plaque will be identified as an intima-media thickness with a height greater
      than 1.5 mm. In case of presence of plaque, the degree of stenosis (&lt;50%, 50-70% or 70-99%)
      will be quantified by color and pulsed Doppler and the peak systolic velocity (PSV in cm/s),
      peak diastolic velocity (PDV cm/s) and ratio (between common carotid and the location of the
      stenosis) will be determined to assess the degree of hemodynamic repercussion.

      Femoral arteries: with the patient in supine decubitus, the presence of plaque will be
      examined in the common femoral artery (1 cm proximal to the bifurcation) and the superficial
      femoral artery on both sides. The plaque definition follows the same previous criteria.

      Abdominal aorta: the aim is early diagnosis of aortic aneurysm in men age 60 and older. With
      the patient in supine decubitus, the abdominal aorta will be examined in the midline of the
      abdomen from the base of the sternum until the bifurcation the iliac arteries. In an axial
      section, at the points where a greater diameter is observed, 2 images of the aorta will be
      captured, and 2 measurements will be made (anterior-posterior and lateral-lateral). An aortic
      aneurysm will be considered to be present when the diameter is greater than 3 cm.

      Transcranial ultrasound: the arteries of the Willis circle and their branches will be
      insonated through the transtemporal and transforaminal acoustic windows. The Doppler spectrum
      of each intracranial artery will be determined using the colour-coded signal. Flow direction,
      peak systolic velocity, mean flow velocity and diastolic flow velocity will be established.
      The intracranial carotid artery, the medial cerebral artery in the M1 and M2 segments, the
      anterior cerebral artery (segment A1) and the posterior cerebral artery in segments P1 and P2
      will be studied through the transtemporal acoustic window. The V4 segment of the vertebral
      arteries and the basilar artery will be studied through the transforaminal acoustic window.
      In each patient, the number, location and severity of stenosis will be recorded.
      Baumgartner's criteria will be used to establish the severity of the stenosis based on peak
      systolic wave velocity (moderate to serious stenosis, if it is ≥155/ 220 cm/s for the medial
      cerebral artery, ≤120/≥155 cm/s for the anterior cerebral artery, ≥100/≥145 cm/s for the
      posterior cerebral artery and the basilar artery, and ≥90/≥120 cm/s for the vertebral
      artery).

      Ankle-brachial index: a continuous Doppler (Hadecco ES100X MiniDop®), sphygmomanometer and
      blood pressure cuffs (Riester minimus III®) will be used. Systolic blood pressure will be
      measured in the brachial artery, posterior tibial artery and dorsalis pedis artery in both
      limbs. The ratios between tibial and pedal systolic blood pressure in each leg and the higher
      brachial blood pressure will be calculated. The final value for each limb will be the lower
      value of those obtained between tibial and pedal blood pressure. An ankle-brachial index
      value &lt;0.9 will be considered to be suggestive of stenosis; a value &lt;0.7 will be considered
      to be stenosis and a value ≥1.4 will be considered to be suggestive of arterial rigidity.

      Spirometry: it will measure forced vital capacity (FVC); forced expiratory volume in one
      second (FEV1); the ratio between FEV1 and FVC and the lower limit of normality, as a
      percentage.

      Determination of advanced glycation end products: they will be measured using skin
      autofluorescence (SAF) in the forearm with the AGE Reader system® (Diagnoptics, the
      Netherlands). SAF is measured using spectrophotometry which is calculated as the relationship
      of the intensity of reflected light compared to refracted light. The result obtained will be
      divided into 4 CV risk groups, taking into account age and sex.

      Atrial fibrillation screening: The presence of atrial fibrillation will be assessed with the
      SRA device® (EVINA Health Solutions) for one hour in the MU.

      Biobank: drawing of blood samples from a peripheral vein of the hand or forearm to obtain
      serum, plasma, DNA and RNA will be collected. Samples will be prepared in aliquots following
      a standardized protocol, and sent frozen (dry ice) to a centralized biobank (IRBLleida
      Biobank, Spain) for processing and storage for subsequent studies. Moreover, urine samples
      will be frozen and stored in the IRBLleida biobank for subsequent studies.

      Statistical analysis: descriptive analysis will include absolute and relative frequencies for
      the qualitative variables, means and standard deviations for the continuous variables that
      follow a normal distribution, and median and interquartile range in the cases that do not
      follow a normal distribution. Their distribution will be analyzed with the chi-squared test,
      in the case of qualitative variables, and Student's t test or ANOVA for quantitative
      variables with a normal distribution, or, failing this, non-parametric Mann-Whitney U or
      Kruskal-Wallis tests will be used for those without a normal distribution. The correlation
      between quantitative variables will be analyzed using Pearson's or Spearman's test, depending
      on the distribution. The existence of collinearity between 2 variables will be analyzed to
      enter the variable that better predicts the result variable in the multivariate model.
      Multivariate analysis will be performed using logistic regression if the dependent variable
      is qualitative or linear regression if it is quantitative. Beta regression coefficients, odds
      ratios (ORs) and their respective 95% confidence intervals will be estimated as measures of
      association. In the longitudinal study, the incidence of CV morbidity and mortality and
      mortality due to any cause will be analyzed, based on the diagnostic tests used in the MU and
      the biomarkers studied using Cox regression. Statistical significance will be set at a p
      value &lt; 0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A randomized interventional study with 2 arms that will include 14,600 individuals with at least one CV risk factor, registered in Primary care in the province of Lleida, between January 2015 and December 2017, who will subsequently be followed up until December 2027.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of the intervention on cardiovascular events and mortality in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>The onset of a cardiovascular event will be recorded according to the tenth version of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases (ICD-10). Cardiovascular events and mortality in the intervention group will be compared to the control group during a during a 10-year follow-up period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of subclinical atherosclerosis in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of subclinical atherosclerosis will be evaluated in the intervention group. The presence of an atheromatous plaque will be identified as an intima-media thickness higher than 1.5 mm. The degree of stenosis (&lt;50%, 50-70% or 70-99%) will be quantified by colour and pulsed Doppler. In addition, the systolic velocity peak (SVP in cm/s), diastolic velocity peak (DVP cm/s) will be quantified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of hidden chronic kidney disease in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of hidden chronic kidney disease will be assessed with a urine spot test that determines the albumin/creatinine ratio (ACR). Values lower than 30 mg/g are normal; 30-300 mg/g indicate microalbuminuria; and values higher than 300 indicate macroalbuminuria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of pre-diabetes and undiagnosed diabetes in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of glycated hemoglobin (Hb A1c) will be determined with a Cobas b 101® machine (Roche). Values lower than 5.7% are normal; 5.7-6.5% indicate pre-diabetes; and ≥ 6.5% indicate diabetes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of advanced glycation end-products (AGEs) with atheromatous disease in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The relationship between the AGES and the presence of atheromatous plaques will be evaluated quantifying the skin autofluorescence (SAF). SAF will be analyzed with the AGE reader™ device (DiagnOptics Technologies, Groningen, The Netherlands). Values are expressed in arbitrary units and calibrated according to manufacturer's instructions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of adherence to the Mediterranean diet with atheromatous disease in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence to the Mediterranean diet will be evaluated with the diet survey adapted from the PREDIMED study. This survey has been previously validated in the Spanish population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of new early lipidomic biomarkers of atherosclerosis in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be analyzed to describe new lipid biomarkers associated with the presence of atheromatous plaque.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of physical exercise with atheromatous disease in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Physical exercise will be evaluated with the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ). The association between physical exercise and the presence on atheromatous plaque will be evaluated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of atrial fibrillation in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of atrial fibrillation is assessed with stroke risk analysis device (SRA, EVINA Health Solutions).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of spirometry alterations and atheromatous plaque in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometry will measure forced vital capacity (FVC); forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1); the ratio between FEV1 and FVC and the lower limit of normality, as a percentage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes induced by the report generated in the Mobile Unit in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The mobile Unit generates a personal report with results and recommendations. This report will be sent to the Primary Care doctor. The impact of this report will be evaluated as changes in medical treatment (new prescriptions or adjustment in previous prescriptions).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of advanced glycation end-products (AGEs) and cardiovascular events in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>The relationship between the AGES and cardiovascular events will be evaluated quantifying the skin autofluorescence (SAF). SAF will be analyzed with the AGE reader™ device (DiagnOptics Technologies, Groningen, The Netherlands). Values are expressed in arbitrary units and calibrated according to manufacturer's instructions. The onset of a cardiovascular event will be recorded according to the tenth version of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases (ICD-10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of adherence to the Mediterranean diet and cardiovascular events in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence to the Mediterranean diet will be evaluated with the diet survey adapted from the PREDIMED study. This survey has been previously validated in the Spanish population. The onset of a cardiovascular event will be recorded according to the tenth version of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases (ICD-10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of physical exercise and cardiovascular events in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Physical exercise will be evaluated with the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ). The association between physical exercise and cardiovascular events will be evaluated. The onset of a cardiovascular event will be recorded according to the tenth version of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases (ICD-10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of new early lipidomic biomarkers of cardiovascular events in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be analyzed to describe new lipid biomarkers associated with cardiovascular events. The onset of a cardiovascular event will be recorded according to the tenth version of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases (ICD-10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of spirometry alterations and cardiovascular events in a low/moderate cardiovascular risk population</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Spirometry will measure forced vital capacity (FVC); forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1); the ratio between FEV1 and FVC and the lower limit of normality, as a percentage. The onset of a cardiovascular event will be recorded according to the tenth version of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases (ICD-10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14600</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Subclinical Disease and/or Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Early Diagnosis</condition>
  <condition>Ultrasound</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the MU, besides clinical data collection, dried blood spot and urine spot tests, patients will be evaluated with artery ultrasound (carotid, femoral, transcranial and abdominal aorta), ankle-brachial index, spirometry, determination of advanced glycation end products and atrial fibrillation screening. Additionally, blood and urine samples will be collected and stored in the biobank to identify new biomarkers using omic studies. Finally, a report with the exploration results and recommendations based on the current guidelines will be uploaded to the e-CAP history for the Primary care evaluation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be evaluated in primary care units only according to their cardiovascular risk scores.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical data collection</intervention_name>
    <description>Sociodemographic variables (age, sex and race), medical history of comorbidities and medical treatments will be collected from the electronic Primary Care medical history (e-CAP). The following variables will be recorded in the MU: weight, height, waist circumference and neck circumference, body mass index in kg/m2, hours of fasting, systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure and pulse pressure (mmHg). Blood pressure will be measured 3 times (Omron 6) at 2-min intervals and the mean of the last 2 will be collected. In addition, variables related to physical exercise (International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ)), diet (adapted from the PREDIMED study), and variables daytime somnolence (the Berlin Questionnaire and the Epworth somnolence scale).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dried blood spot</intervention_name>
    <description>Dried capillary blood testing creatinine, uric acid and total cholesterol (Reflotrons® Plus system, Roche). Determination of the complete lipid profile in cases in which total cholesterol is greater than 200 mg/dl: HDL cholesterol (mg/dl), LDL cholesterol (mg/dl) and triglycerides (mg/dl) (Cobas B 101® system, Roche). Calculation of non-HDL cholesterol levels. Glycated haemoglobin will be analysed with the Cobas B 101 system,Roche. The CKD-EPI glomerular filtration rate will be determined.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Urine spot tests</intervention_name>
    <description>A urine sample from spontaneous micturition will be collected and analyzed using Clinitek Microalbumin 2 Reagent Strips and a Siemens Clinitek Status® analyzer. It will be determined albuminuria (mg/l) and albumin/creatinine ratio (mg/g).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Artery ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>Carotid and femoral artery ultrasound for atheroma plaque diagnosis. Abdominal aorta ultrasound for early diagnosis of aortic aneurism. Transcranial ultrasound for cerebral arterial blood flow alterations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ankle-brachial index</intervention_name>
    <description>Systolic blood pressure measurement in the brachial artery, posterior tibial artery and dorsalis pedis artery in both limbs. The ratios between tibial and pedal systolic blood pressure in each leg and the higher brachial blood pressure will be calculated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Spirometry</intervention_name>
    <description>Spirometry will be used to assess lung capacity. It will be performed by the same nurse who will measure forced vital capacity (FVC); forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1); the ratio between FEV1 and FVC and the lower limit of normality, as a percentage.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Determination of advanced glycation end products</intervention_name>
    <description>These will be measured using skin autofluorescence (SAF) in the forearm with the AGE Reader® system (Diagnoptics, the Netherlands). SAF is measured using spectrophotometry which is calculated as the relationship of the intensity of reflected light compared to refracted light.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atrial fibrillation screening</intervention_name>
    <description>The presence of atrial fibrillation is assessed with a device (SRA, EVINA Health Solutions) during one hour in the mobile unit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biobank</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood samples from a peripheral vein of the hand or forearm to obtain serum, plasma, DNA and RNA will be collected. These samples will be prepared in aliquots following a standardized protocol, and sent frozen (dry ice) to a centralized biobank (IRBLleida Biobank, Spain) for processing and storage for subsequent studies of CV, inflammatory and mineral-metabolism biomarkers and genetic polymorphisms. Urine samples will be frozen and stored in a biobank for subsequent study of biomarkers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exploration results and recommendations</intervention_name>
    <description>A report with exploration results and recommendations based on the current guidelines will be uploaded to the e-CAP history for the Primary care evaluation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women (50-70 years) and men ( 45-65 years) with at least one cardiovascular risk
             factor (hypertension, dyslipidemia, obesity (BMI&gt;30Kg/m2), current smoking habit or
             former smoker in less than 10 years, first-degree family history of early
             cardiovascular disease).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior medical history of cardiovascular disease.

          -  Diabetes.

          -  Glomerular filtration rate (CKD-EPI) &lt; 60 ml/min(1.73m2).

          -  Active neoplasm or acute disease.

          -  A life expectancy shorter than 18 months.

          -  Pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elvira Fernandez Guiráldez</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institut de Recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Àngels Betriu Bars</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Institut de Recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jose Manuel Valdivielso Revilla</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut de Recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcelino Bermúdez López</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut de Recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Arroyo Rueda</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut de Recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Àngels Betriu Bars</last_name>
    <phone>0034973702481</phone>
    <phone_ext>2481</phone_ext>
    <email>abetriu@irblleida.cat</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jose Manuel Valdivielso Revilla</last_name>
    <phone>0034973703650</phone>
    <phone_ext>3650</phone_ext>
    <email>valdivielso@medicina.udl.cat</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Primary Care centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lleida</city>
        <zip>25007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cristina Farrás Salles</last_name>
      <phone>0034661343421</phone>
      <email>cfarras.lleida.ics@gencat.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marcelino Bermudez Lopez</last_name>
      <phone>0034973702482</phone>
      <phone_ext>2482</phone_ext>
      <email>mbermudez@irblleida.cat</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut de recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lleida</city>
        <zip>25198</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Àngels Betriu Bars</last_name>
      <phone>0034973702481</phone>
      <phone_ext>2481</phone_ext>
      <email>abetriu@irblleida.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jose Manuel Valdivielso Revilla</last_name>
      <phone>0034973703560</phone>
      <phone_ext>3560</phone_ext>
      <email>valdivielso@medicina.udl.cat</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ferran Barbé Illa</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manuel Portero Otín</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francisco Purroy Garcia</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Albert Lecube Torelló</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.elbusdelasalut.cat/</url>
    <description>Study website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Betriu À, Farràs C, Abajo M, Martinez-Alonso M, Arroyo D, Barbé F, Buti M, Lecube A, Portero M, Purroy F, Torres G, Valdivielso JM, Fernández E. Randomised intervention study to assess the prevalence of subclinical vascular disease and hidden kidney disease and its impact on morbidity and mortality: The ILERVAS project. Nefrologia. 2016 Jul-Aug;36(4):389-96. doi: 10.1016/j.nefro.2016.02.008. Epub 2016 Apr 1. English, Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>27044887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 25, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Institut de Recerca Biomèdica de Lleida</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elvira Fernández Girálde</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>IRBLleida's Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kidney Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Subclinical Disease and/or Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung capacity</keyword>
  <keyword>Early diagnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced glycation end products</keyword>
  <keyword>Atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Arterial ultrasound</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

