<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03222895</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>W17_069</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03222895</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Distribution of Lymph Node Metastases in Esophageal Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>TIGER</acronym>
  <official_title>Distribution of Lymph Node Metastases in Esophageal Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Lymph node status is an important prognostic parameter in esophageal carcinoma
      and an independent predictor of survival. Distribution of metastatic lymph nodes may vary
      with tumor location, tumor histology, tumor invasion depth and neoadjuvant therapy. Surgical
      strategy depends on the distribution pattern of nodal metastases but consensus on the extent
      of lymphadenectomy differs worldwide. Especially for adenocarcinoma the distribution of lymph
      node metastases has not yet been described in large series. Aim of the present study is to
      evaluate the distribution of lymph node metastases in esophageal carcinoma specimens
      following transthoracic esophagectomy with at least a 2-field lymphadenectomy.

      Methods: The TIGER-study is a multinational observational cohort study with 58 participating
      centers. All patients with a resectable esophageal or gastro-esophageal junction carcinoma in
      whom a transthoracic esophagectomy with a 2- or 3-field lymphadenectomy is performed in
      participating centers will be included. All lymph node stations will be excised and
      separately sent for pathological examination. Cluster analysis will be performed to identify
      patterns of metastases in relation to tumor location, tumor histology, tumor invasion depth
      and neoadjuvant therapy.

      Conclusion: TIGER will provide a roadmap of the location of lymph node metastases in relation
      to tumor histology, tumor location, invasion depth, number of lymph nodes and lymph node
      metastases, pre-operative diagnostics, neo-adjuvant therapy and survival. Patient-tailored
      treatment can be developed on the basis of these results, such as the the optimal radiation
      field and extent of lymphadenectomy based on the primary tumor characteristics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective:

      Aim of the TIGER study is to evaluate the distribution of lymph node metastases in esophageal
      carcinoma specimens following transthoracic esophagectomy with at least 2-field
      lymphadenectomy.

      Secondary Objective(s):

        -  Accuracy of preoperative diagnostics (especially EUS and PET-CT) and added value of EBUS
           (endobronchial ultrasonography) to existing staging with EUS (endoscopic
           ultrasonography)/PET-CT

        -  Prognostic value of different lymph node stations

        -  Three- and 5-year overall and disease free survival

        -  Distribution pattern of recurrence or metastases

        -  Number of harvested lymph nodes in patients who are treated with and without
           neo-adjuvant chemoradiotherapy

        -  Frequency of skip nodal metastases

        -  Ratio of nodal metastases inside and outside the radiation field o Lymph node metastases
           will be defined as inside or outside the radiation field nodes.

      Study design:

      TIGER is a multinational observational cohort study. The duration of the study will
      approximately be 7,5 years (6 months preparation, 2 years inclusion, 5 years follow-up).
      There are 58 participating centers distributed over 18 countries (11 Dutch hospitals, 1
      Swedish hospital, 1 Finnish hospital, 2 Belgian hospitals, 3 German hospital, 1 Swiss
      hospital, 1 French hospital, 5 Italian hospitals, 2 Spanish hospitals, 8 British hospitals, 2
      Irish Hospitals, 7 Japanese hospitals, 1 Hong Kong hospital, 1 Chinese hospital, 3 Indian
      hospitals, 7 American hospitals, 1 Canadian hospital and 1 Brazilian hospital).

      Sample size calculation:

      In 2012, the incidence of esophageal cancer was 456,000 new cases worldwide.44 Only a small
      percentage of patients with esophageal cancer present with curable disease at time of
      diagnosis. We aim to include all patients with resectable disease in 58 centers in a 2 year
      time period. We aim to include 5000 patients. This number suffices for (i) descriptive
      purposes and (ii) clustering of metastases diffusion profiles into meaningful subgroups
      within predefined strata (patients with adenocarcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma, with and
      without neoadjuvant therapy, different tumor heights and invasion depths, and following a 2-
      or 3-field lymphadenectomy).

      Study procedures:

      Patients will not undergo any additional procedures for the study. This is an observational
      study only. Patients will be treated according to national guidelines.

      Follow-up:

      Patients will be followed up for 5 years after the operation according to national
      guidelines. Follow-up will be scheduled every three months the first year, every six months
      the second until the fourth year and once yearly until the fifth year. Investigations are
      performed according to national guidelines. In the Netherlands, these are performed on
      indication of patients' complaints.

      Progress tracking:

      A progress reports will be composed every 6 months. Progress includes: the numbers of
      subjects included and numbers of subjects that have completed the study in relation to the
      estimated included subjects at that point of time, problems and bottlenecks found during the
      past 6 months and their solution and amendments that have been made. The progress tracking
      report will be send to the local PIs every 6 months during the patient inclusion period.

      Statistical analysis:

      Primary study parameter(s):

      Numbers and percentages of resected lymph nodes and lymph node metastases will be given per
      lymph node station. Tumor location and invasion depth will be categorized. Patients with
      adenocarcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma and patients with and without neoadjuvant therapy
      will be analyzed separately. Also patients following a 2- or 3-field lymphadenectomy will be
      analyzed separately.

      Secondary study parameter(s) :

      The sensitivity, specificity, and positive and negative predictive values of EUS and PET-CT
      will be reported. Perioperative morbidity and mortality will be summarized descriptively. For
      each patient group mentioned in 5.4, explorative cluster analyses will be done to identify
      subgroups of patients with different patterns of lymph nodes metastases, tumor locations and
      invasion depths. Potentially relevant other characteristics at the time of surgery like age,
      gender, tumor differentiation, vaso-invasive growth will be included in the analysis. No
      restrictions will be applied to the number of clusters in each analysis, but the ratio of the
      largest cluster size to the smallest cluster size should preferably not exceed the value of 3
      and/or the smallest cluster size should be minimally 30 patients. Characteristics introducing
      patient outliers will be excluded and one should further be able to attribute meaning to the
      resulting cluster profiles. Clusters that show the phenomenon of skip metastases will be
      noted. The resulting clusters will be evaluated for the diffusion pattern of future
      metastases during follow-up (descriptive analysis), the number of future metastases during
      follow-up (Poisson regression or generalized estimation equation, whichever appropriate), for
      3- and 5-year overall and disease free survival (Kaplan-Meier survival analysis).
      Multivariate analysis will be performed using the Cox hazard regression method. The
      univariate analysis, including all baseline parameters, will serve as the basis for the
      multivariate Cox hazard regression model. Variables showing association (p &lt; 0.10) with
      survival in univariate analysis will be included in the multivariate analysis. Age and sex
      will be included in all multivariate analyses. Results are presented as hazard ratio with
      exact 95% confidence interval (95% CI). After 5-years of follow-up the efficacy index will be
      determined (incidence of metastases to an area (%) x 5-year overall survival rate (%)). A
      log-rank test, Mann-Whitney U test, or χ2-test will be used as indicated to compare groups. A
      value of p &lt; 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. Statistical analysis will be
      performed with SPSS 21.0 software (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). No formal power analysis or
      sample size calculation will be performed, but the 5,000 inclusions will suffice for an
      exploratory study.

      Other study parameters:

      Baseline characteristics will be presented in a baseline table. Clinical and pathology data
      will be presented in separate tables.

      Study population:

      Central data management is organized via the secured TIGER database that can be found on
      TIGERstudy.net. Patient inclusion and data registration of these patients will be done by the
      participating local PI, surgeon or fellow for the center they are representing on the TIGER
      website. The local PI is responsible for the inclusion and data registration of all eligible
      patients in his or her center.

      All patients with resectable esophageal carcinoma undergoing transthoracic esophageal
      resection are eligible for inclusion.

      Patients will be treated according to national guidelines and may be neo-adjuvantly treated
      with chemotherapy or chemoradiation. An esophagectomy with a 2- or 3-stage lymphadenectomy
      will be performed followed by a gastric tube or colonic interposition for reconstruction. All
      lymph node stations will be excised and separately sent for pathological examination. Initial
      microscopic evaluation will be performed by standard H&amp;E staining. In case of suspicion of
      micro-metastasis or isolated tumor cells in the lymph node, or in case of suspicion of
      residual tumor cells in patients with extensive response to neoadjuvant therapy, additional
      keratin stains will be performed. For the TIGER-study a new lymph node classification is
      designed, and lymph nodes will be recorded according to that classification system. Patients
      will be followed-up for 5 years after the operation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Distribution of lymph node metastases</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The distribution of lymph node metastases in esophageal and esophago-gastric junction carcinoma specimens following transthoracic esophagectomy with at least 2-field lymphadenectomy in relation to tumor histology, tumor location, invasion depth, number of lymph nodes and lymph node metastases, pre-operative diagnostics, neo-adjuvant therapy and (disease free) survival.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy of preoperative diagnostics</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Accuracy of preoperative diagnostics (especially EUS and PET-CT) and added value of EBUS to existing staging with EUS/PET-CT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prognostic value of different lymph node stations</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Prognostic value of different lymph node stations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distribution pattern of recurrence or metastases</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Distribution pattern of recurrence or metastases, In-field- or out-field nodal recurrence in case of neo-adjuvant chemoradiation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of harvested lymph nodes in patients who are treated with and without neo-adjuvant chemoradiotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of harvested lymph nodes in patients who are treated with and without neo-adjuvant chemoradiotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Skip nodal metastases</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of the phenomenon skip nodal metastases</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio of nodal metastases inside and outside the radiation field</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Ratio of nodal metastases inside and outside the radiation field</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3- and 5-year overall and disease free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>3- and 5-year overall and disease free survival in relation to the lymph node distribution pattern</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Lymph Node Metastases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TIGER study cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>This is the entire patient cohort. Alle patients with resectable esophageal cancer undergoing a transthoracic esophagectomy with at least a 2-field lymphadenectomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients with esophageal cancer who will undergo a transthoracic esophagectomy with a
        2- or 3 field lymphadenectomy for esophageal cancer in one of the participating centers
        during the inclusion period.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary squamous cell or adenocarcinoma of the esophagus or esophago-gastric junction

          -  Surgically resectable (cT1-4a, N0-3, M0)

          -  Adequate physical condition to undergo transthoracic surgery (ASA 1-3)

          -  Transthoracic esophagectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous thoracic or abdominal (upper GI) surgery disturbing lymph drainage of the
             esophagus and stomach

          -  Patients with in situ carcinoma or high grade dysplasia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suzanne S Gisbertz, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark I van Berge Henegouwen, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eliza RC Hagens, BSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Suzanne S Gisbertz, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31205669111</phone>
    <email>s.s.gisbertz@amc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eliza RC Hagens, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>+31613460431</phone>
    <email>e.r.hagens@amc.uva.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>S.S. Gisbertz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Upper GI Surgeon</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Esophageal Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymph node metastases</keyword>
  <keyword>Esophagectomy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

