<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03224338</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DTG-01-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03224338</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dolutegravir Plus 2 NRTIs, in Treatment-Naïve HIV-2 Infected Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Multicenter, Single-Arm, Open-Label Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Triple Therapy With Dolutegravir Plus 2 NRTIs, in Treatment-Naïve HIV-2 Infected Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Blueclinical, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Blueclinical, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multicenter, single-arm, open-label clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy, the safety and
      the tolerability of 50 mg dolutegravir once daily (q.d.) given in combination with 2 NRTIs
      backbone in HIV-2 positive, treatment-naïve subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects who fulfill all inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria, after giving
      informed consent, will be eligible for participation in this study. At the Visit 2 (Day1)
      subjects will receive the study medication and instructions for its administration.
      Thereafter, subjects will return to the investigational site at week 4, 12, 24, 36 and 48,
      for efficacy and safety assessments.

      Subjects who meet the virologic failure criteria will return to the investigational site
      approximately one week later to repeat viral RNA testing (Virologic Failure Confirmation
      visit). If virologic failure is confirmed and the viral load meets the criteria for
      resistance testing, viral resistance testing will then be performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 5, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy analysis- treatment efficacy, as measured by the &quot;overall treatment success defined as proportion of patients with &quot;global success&quot; at week 48.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of DTG in combination with two NRTIs [ABC/3TC or TDF/FTC] in the treatment of HIV-2 treatment-naïve subjects, as measured by the proportion of subjects achieving a plasma viral load of &lt;40 copies/mL and/or by the change from baseline in CD4 cell count and in CD4/CD8 ratio at Week 48. Global success&quot; is a composite variable defined as a plasma HIV-2 RNA viral load &lt;40 copies/mL and a delta of CD4 depending on the initial CD4 count (CD4 delta &gt;+100 cells/mm3 for initial CD4s ≤ 500 cells/mm3; or CD4delta &gt; +50 cells/mm3 for initial CD4s &gt; 500 cells/mm3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study treatment immunological effect</measure>
    <time_frame>12, 24 and 48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the study treatment immunological effect, as measured by the change from baseline in CD4 cell count and the CD4/CD8 ratio at Week 48.
as measured by the change from baseline in CD4 cell count and the CD4/CD8 ratio at Week 48. Change from Baseline in CD4 Cell Count and CD4/CD8 ratio Change from baseline in CD4 cell count and the CD4/CD8 ratio will be estimated at each time point with CD4 and CD8 cell count collection with a key interest at Week 12, 24 and 48.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study treatment immunological effect</measure>
    <time_frame>12, 24 and 48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Proportions of subjects achieving HIV-2 RNA &lt; 40 copies/mL. The proportions of subjects achieving HIV-2 RNA &lt;40 copies/mL will be estimated at Week 12, 24 and 48.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of the study treatment, as assessed by review of the accumulated safety data.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks or rebounder at least one week apart afte rinitial response</time_frame>
    <description>The following clinical and laboratory adverse experiences will be summarized:
Subjects with at least one adverse experience. Subjects with at least one drug related adverse experience. Subjects with at least one serious adverse experience. Subjects with at least one serious and drug related adverse experience, Subjects who discontinued study therapy due to an adverse experience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Antiretroviral activity</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The exploratory objective of this study is to evaluate the antiretroviral activity of DTG in combination with two NRTIs [ABC/3TC or TDF/FTC] against HIV-2, as measured by the Time to Virologic Response (TVR)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Antiretroviral activity</measure>
    <time_frame>48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The exploratory objective of this study is to evaluate the antiretroviral activity of DTG in combination with two NRTIs [ABC/3TC or TDF/FTC] against HIV-2, as measured by the Time to Loss Of Virologic Response (TLOVR).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV II Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>: Dolutegravir (DTG)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dolutegravir 50 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Dolutegravir will be used in combination with 2 nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs). The NRTIs used in combination with DTG will be abacavir (ABC) plus lamivudine (3TC) or tenofovir (TDF) plus emtricitabine (FTC), which is in line with the current standard of care. The combination ABC/3TC/DTG will be preferential except in case of hepatitis B co-infection or in case the subject has a positive HLA-B*5701 allele screening assessment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>: Dolutegravir (DTG)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A subject is eligible for the study if he/she fulfills all of the following inclusion
             criteria:

               1. Able to understand and willing to comply with all the requirements of the study,
                  as confirmed by giving voluntary written informed consent for participation.

               2. Male or female gender.

               3. Age ≥ 18 years on the day of signing the informed consent.

               4. HIV-2 positive as determined by a positive result in the respective assay.

               5. CD4 count ≤500 cells/mm3 (in case of undetectable baseline HIV-2 viral load);
                  and/or classified as B- or C-stage, by the HIV disease staging and classification
                  system of Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC); and/or have
                  detectable viral load irrespective of CD4 count; and/or have other medical
                  conditions / co-morbidities in which treatment is considered, according to
                  European AIDS Clinical Society (EACS) and national guidelines;

               6. Naïve to ART including investigational antiretroviral agents .

               7. Considered clinically stable with no signs or symptoms of active infection, at
                  the time of entry into the study (i.e., clinical status and all chronic
                  medications should be unchanged for at least 2 weeks prior to the start of
                  treatment in this study), in the opinion of the investigator.

               8. If woman or man with reproductive potential, agrees to adopt one of the following
                  effective contraceptive methods throughout the study:

                    1. True abstinence, if this is in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle
                       of the subject [Period abstinence (e.g., abstinence only on certain calendar
                       days, abstinence only during ovulation period, use of symptothermal method,
                       use of post-ovulation methods) and withdrawal are not acceptable methods of
                       contraception].

                    2. Use of an acceptable method of birth control throughout the study (either by
                       subject or subject's partner). Acceptable methods of birth control are: oral
                       contraceptive, intrauterine device (IUD), diaphragm with spermicide,
                       contraceptive sponge, condom, vasectomy. All forms of hormonal contraception
                       are acceptable. However, the investigator should consult local prescribing
                       information for guidance on the use of hormonal contraceptives with
                       background ART as some antiretrovirals have clinically significant drug
                       interactions with these products.

        NOTE: A subject who is not of reproductive potential , is not sexually active, whose
        current partner(s) is/are not of reproductive potential, or whose sexual activity is
        exclusively homosexual is eligible without requiring the use of contraception. However, use
        of barrier methods of contraception is strongly encouraged to reduce the risk of HIV-2
        transmission during sexual contact.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A subject is not eligible for the trial if he/she fulfills any of the following
             exclusion criteria:

               1. History or presence of allergy to the study drugs or their components.

               2. HIV-1 infection or HIV-1/HIV-2 dual infection.

               3. History or current evidence of any condition, therapy, laboratory abnormality or
                  other circumstance that might confound the results of the study, or interfere
                  with the subject's participation for the full duration of the study, such that it
                  is not in the best interest of the subject to participate.

               4. Documented or known resistance to DTG and/or NRTIs.

               5. Treatment with systemic immunosuppressive therapy or immune modulators within 30
                  days prior to treatment in this study or is anticipated to need them during the
                  course of the study.

                  NOTE: &quot;Short courses&quot; of corticosteroids (e.g., as for asthma exacerbation) will
                  be allowed. &quot;Short courses&quot; mean a use of corticosteroids for less than 7 days.

               6. Requiring or is anticipated to require any of the prohibited medications while in
                  the study (dofetilide, inducers of CYP3A4, including phenobarbital, phenytoin,
                  carbamazepine and rifampicin).

                  NOTE: Subjects must discontinue phenobarbital, phenytoin, carbamazepine, and
                  rifampicin at least 14 days prior to the treatment phase of the study.

               7. Current (active) diagnosis of tuberculosis.

               8. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≥5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), or ALT
                  ≥3xULN and bilirubin ≥1.5xULN (with &gt;35% direct bilirubin).

               9. Moderate to severe hepatic impairment (Class B or greater) as determined by
                  Child-Pugh classification .

              10. If subject eligible to receive Tivicay®: Unstable liver disease (as defined by
                  the presence of ascites, encephalopathy, coagulopathy, hypoalbuminemia,
                  esophageal or gastric varices, or persistent jaundice), cirrhosis, known biliary
                  abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic
                  gallstones).

              11. Estimated creatinine clearance &lt;50 mL/min at time of screening, based on
                  Cockcroft-Gault equation .

              12. Current (active) diagnosis of acute hepatitis due to any cause. NOTE: Subjects
                  with chronic hepatitis B and C may enter the study as long as they fulfil all
                  entry criteria, have stable liver function tests, and have no significant
                  impairment of hepatic synthetic function (significant impairment of hepatic
                  synthetic function is defined as a serum albumin &lt;2.8 g/dL in the absence of
                  another explanation for the abnormal laboratory value) at the time of enrollment.

              13. Under treatment for a viral infection other than HIV-2, such as hepatitis B, with
                  an agent that may be active against HIV-2, including but not limited to 3TC, TDF
                  or entecavir, unless the treatment with these agents occurred prior to the
                  diagnosis of HIV.

              14. Anticipated need for Hepatitis C virus (HCV) therapy with interferon and/or
                  ribavirin during the study.

              15. Positive HLA-B*5701 allele screening assessment and is also not eligible for
                  treatment with the other acceptable NRTIs (TDF/FTC).

              16. Significant suicidality risk, according to the investigator's judgment. NOTE:
                  Recent history of suicidal behavior and/or suicidal ideation may be considered as
                  evidence of serious suicide risk.

              17. Participation in a study with an investigational compound/device within 30 days
                  of signing informed consent or anticipates participating in such a study
                  involving an investigational compound/device during the course of this study.

              18. If woman, she is pregnant, breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive at any time
                  during the study.

              19. If woman, she is expecting to donate eggs at any time during the study.

              20. If man, expecting to donate sperm at any time during the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luis Almeida, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+351 220 995 159</phone>
    <email>regulatory@blueclinical.pt</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Hospitalar de Lisboa Central Hospital Curry Cabral</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisboa</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fernando Maltez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Hospitalar de Lisboa Ocidental Hospital de Egas Moniz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisboa</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kamal Mansinho, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Hospitalar Lisboa Norte Hospital de Santa Maria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisboa</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nuno Janeiro, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Beatriz Ângelo Loures</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisboa</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paulo Rodrigues, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Garcia de Orta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisboa</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nuno Marques, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Professor Doutor Fernando Fonseca Amadora</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisboa</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patricia Pacheco, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Portugal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dolutegravir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

