<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03224195</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>213682</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03224195</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Experience of Acute Rehabilitation After Hip Fracture</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patient Experience of Acute Rehabilitation After Hip Fracture</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to explore the patient experience of acute rehabilitation after hip
      fracture surgery. We also aim to identify patient perceived barriers to rehabilitation and
      recovery after hip fracture surgery. More specifically, the objectives of this study are to:

        1. describe the rehabilitation experience of patients who underwent hip fracture surgery
           with respect to the frequency, intensity, type, and timing of rehabilitation and

        2. identify patient perceived barriers to rehabilitation and recovery related to the
           patient, their injury and their health care.

      The results of this qualitative study will inform a future feasibility cluster randomised
      controlled trial aimed at optimising acute rehabilitation after hip fracture surgery. The
      findings will help to strengthen the patient and carergiver centred approach when developing
      the intervention to optimise rehabilitation and potentially improve outcomes after hip
      fracture surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each year, UK hospitals admit 75,000 older men and women with fracture of the hip. The injury
      has been dubbed the &quot;hip attack&quot;, due to its clinical severity and adverse consequences. In
      fact, hip fracture is one of the most detrimental events in an older adult's life. Even with
      treatment, 30% of patients die within a year.Among survivors, 25% never walk again, and 22%
      transition from independent living to long-term care. Further, up to one third of patients
      develop new-onset depressive symptoms post fracture. Many fear admission to a nursing home,
      in fact a recent study noted that 80% would rather be dead.

      Most hip fractures are treated surgically with the goals of reducing pain and re-establishing
      mobility. Allied health professionals develop rehabilitation interventions targeting the
      frequency, intensity, type and timing of rehabilitation to improve survival, recovery and
      quality of life after hip fracture surgery. Evaluation of these interventions rarely offer
      insight into the patient and caregiver experience. This insight is essential to determine
      feasibility, acceptability, and ultimately adherence to a new rehabilitation intervention.

      As an example, clinicians and researchers suggest the timing of mobilisation will reduce
      complications and improve recovery after hip fracture surgery, particularly among older
      patients. The evidence to support these claims is inconsistent. Further, there is limited
      understanding of the patient experience of early mobilisation after hip fracture surgery.
      Indeed, for some patients the experience may be improved with a delay to first mobilisation.

      To maximise adherence, it is important to also gauge patient's perceptions of perceived
      barriers to rehabilitation and recovery after hip fracture surgery. These barriers may
      present in the form of patient characteristics such as motivation. Alternatively, they may
      present in the form of injury characteristics such as perceived injury severity. Lastly,
      patient's may perceive healthcare barriers to rehabilitation such as perceived benefit.

      DESIGN AND METHODS Design Qualitative study. Semi-structured interview The research assistant
      will first collect participant demographics - age, sex, previous functional status, previous
      place of residence - home or long-term care.

      Participants will then complete a semi-structured face-to-face interview delivered by a
      research assistant. The interview will be on an interview topic guide comprised of 3 core
      topics related to our aims. The questions are flexible, open-ended and broad, while focused
      on the topic to elicit rich responses from participants. The interviews will explore the
      experiences of patients who underwent rehabilitation after hip fracture surgery. Each
      semi-structured interview will last 30-45 minutes and will be recorded with an audio
      recorder. The research assistant will take reflective field notes to assist interpretation of
      the interview data.

      Data preparation Participant demographics (age, sex, previous functional status, previous
      place of residence - home or long-term-care) and field notes will be entered into a Microsoft
      Excel Spreadsheet on a secure controlled access server at Kings College London on the same
      day as the interview by the research assistant. This server is accessible only to staff at
      Kings College London. The data will be password-protected and accessible only to the research
      team.

      Recording of semi-structured interviews will be downloaded onto the secure server on the same
      day as the interview by the research assistant. Recordings will then be permanently deleted
      from the voice recorder. Interviews will be transcribed verbatim into Microsoft Word
      documents on the server by the research assistant. Transcripts will then be checked by a
      Kings College London supervisor, de-identified (by removal of names/locations) and uploaded
      into the NVivo software. On completion of the transcription the audio recordings will be
      deleted permanently from the server.

      The spreadsheet and transcriptions will be archived on the secure controlled access server
      for 3 years to allow for analysis, journal submission, response to reviewer's comments, and
      publication.

      Analysis The resulting data will be open coded and thematically analysed using a constant
      comparative approach with the software package NVivo. Analysis will take place iteratively
      throughout the project with ongoing coding completed to identify themes and subthemes as they
      emerge. This will entail the identification of common themes in the data through the reading
      and re-reading of transcripts first for a descriptive and then an analytic account. Matrices
      will be used to compare the occurrence of themes across participants.

      Upon writing materials for publication, anonymized quotations from the data set will be used
      to support and illustrate the emergent themes.

      Setting George Perkins Ward (trauma orthopaedics), St Thomas's Hospital. The interview will
      take place in a confidential, private room on the Ward.

      Sample size We will recruit 20 participants. We based the sample size on qualitative analysis
      sample size recommendations. Further, a recent Canadian qualitative study on patient
      perspective to guide recovery reached data saturation with no new themes emerging after 19
      interviews.

      Sample technique We will use purposeful-criterion sampling to recruit participants. The first
      20 patients/caregivers admitted to George Perkins Ward, St Thomas's Hospital who meet
      inclusion and exclusion criteria and give informed consent to participate will be included.
      We chose criterion sampling as we have a predetermined criterion of importance (i.e. adults
      (and their caregivers) who sustained hip fractures).

      Identification of potential participants A member of the clinical team will identify
      potential participants at the daily multidisciplinary team handover on George Perkins ward,
      Guy's and St. Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust. During handover, each patient case is discussed
      including admitting diagnosis, surgery, Abbreviated Mental Test Score (AMTS), functional
      status, caregiver involvement, and any communication difficulties.

      A member of the research team not involved in direct clinical care will be notified by the
      clinical team of potential participants on attendance at George Perkins Ward. The member of
      the research team not involved in direct clinical care will then complete the recruitment and
      consent process.

      Recruitment and Consent We will adopt a previous published recruitment strategy developed by
      the Warwick Hip Trauma Evaluation. As part of usual care patients are assessed for capacity
      to consent using the 10-item AMTS preoperatively. A score below 8 suggests cognitive
      impairment.

      Those with a score of 8 or more will be approached in hospital after their hip fracture
      surgery. They (and their caregiver) will be provided with an information sheet and given the
      opportunity to ask questions. At least 24 hours later they will be given the opportunity to
      ask any additional questions, and if they wish to take part, to provide written consent.
      Caregivers who participate will also sign a consent form.

      On approach, potential participants and their caregiver will be invited to take part in the
      study. They will be provided with an information sheet and given the opportunity to ask
      questions. At least 24 hours later they will be given the opportunity to ask any additional
      questions, and if they wish to take part, will sign an agreement form and we will aim to
      interview a caregiver as well as the patient (patient/carer dyad). Caregivers who participate
      will also sign a consent form.

      If the participant declines to participate, we will record the reason offered.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>patient perspective of acute rehabilitation following hip fracture</measure>
    <time_frame>interviews over 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>nil outcome measure- semi-structured interview</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Hip Fractures</condition>
  <condition>Fracture of Hip</condition>
  <condition>Fractured Hip</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients aged 65 and over who have been admitted for surgical management of hip fracture
        who were mobile prior to fracture and do not have cognitive impairment
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Adult who underwent surgery after admission to St. Thomas's Hospital with hip
             fracture.

               -  Admission during the 9 weeks beginning July 2, 2017.

               -  Mobile (with/without aid) before fracture.

               -  Informed consent.

               -  English speaking.

               -  Aged ≥ 60.

               -  Abbreviated Mental Test Score ≥ 8/10.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  • Adults who do not undergo surgery after admission to St. Thomas's Hospital with hip
             fracture.

               -  Admissions outside the 9 weeks beginning July 2, 2017.

               -  Not mobile before fracture.

               -  Aged&lt; 60.

               -  Not English speaking.

               -  AMTS &lt; 8/10.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>patient perspective</keyword>
  <keyword>semi-structured interview</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

