<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03221946</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PMVIDS&amp;RC/IEC/OMR/PR 0051-15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03221946</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Comparative Evaluation of Diclofenac Sodium Transdermal Patch, Oral Diclofenac Sodium With Intramuscular Injections of Diclofenac Sodium in Patients Suffering From Oral Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparative Evaluation of Diclofenac Sodium Transdermal Patch, Oral Diclofenac Sodium With Intramuscular Injections of Diclofenac Sodium in Patients Suffering From Oral Pain: A Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Panineeya Mahavidyalaya Institute of Dental Sciences &amp; Research Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Panineeya Mahavidyalaya Institute of Dental Sciences &amp; Research Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Newer drug delivery systems such as transdermal patches using pain relieving or modifying
      agents emerged as mainstream treatment protocol for management of pain on the outpatient
      basis. The administration of Diclofenac 100 mg in transdermal patch in the patients having
      dental pain due to periapical/periodontal infections was evaluated.

      Methods: 90 Patients of either gender, between 18 to 80 years were divided into 3 groups
      (Group A- oral medication, Group B- transdermal patch, Group C - intra muscular group).
      Patients at the dental department with pain from periapical/periodontal pathologies were
      explained about the procedure of analgesia. With written consent, 100 mg diclofenac sodium
      transdermal patches were prescribed to patients who opted their use in pain control for 2
      consecutive days. A Visual Analog Scale was provided for all patients assessing the pain
      intensity during the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Transdermal Patches ensure simple, painless procedure of drug usage even in patients with
      needle phobia. they are on par with sustainable plasma levels comparable with that of oral
      medication. With the local drug delivery method, hepatic first pass metabolism is bypassed.
      Offering increased flexibility in placing and removing the transdermal patch better patient
      compliance is achieved.

      This study was carried out comparing the efficacy of analgesia, occurrence of side effects
      from the drugs employed and patient compliance during the drug usage with diclofenac sodium
      trans dermal patch 100 mg, oral supplementation of diclofenac sodium 50 mg given as twice
      daily medication and intra muscular administration of 75 mg diclofenac sodium once daily for
      two days in patients having dental pain due to periapical or periodontal pathology.

      Material and Methods

      A total sample of 90 subjects of either gender, between 18 to 80 years attending Department
      of Oral Medicine &amp; Radiology with dental pain and who were willing to be part of the study
      were included and divided randomly into 3 groups based on their preference and priority of
      the route of administration of the drug. As this was a pilot study, a sample size of 90 was
      chosen according to recommendations by Isaac and Michael, W. B

      The study was cleared by ethical clearance committee with necessary approvals. the subjects
      were informed thoroughly about the study and could withdraw from the study at their choice
      when there is no relief of pain with the medication.

      The groups included in the study were:

      Group A which included 30 patients of either gender who were prescribed tablet Diclofenac
      sodium 50 mg orally twice daily for 2 days which is the preferred adult dose for dental pain
      disorders

      Group B which included 30 patients who were prescribed Diclofenac sodium 100mg transdermal
      patch to equate the oral dosage of 50mg that is given twice daily once daily for 2 days (
      SPARSH PHARMA). It is a transparent patch that gave sustained release of the drug for 24
      hours at the local site applied. A total number of 2 patches were given to each patient one
      per day. The patches were applied at an hairless area on the left or right shoulders which
      were subsequently replaced the next day to another area of application in order to avoid
      contact dermatitis in the area of application.

      Group C which included 30 patients of either gender who were given intra muscular injection
      of 75mg which was the nearest available dosage to 100mg availability in India at deltoid or
      gluteus muscle once daily for 2 days using sterile and aseptic precautions.

      All the subjects were prescribed necessary antibiotics for reduction in peri apical
      /periodontal infections. The rescue medication tablet chosen was Paracetamol 325 mg, if any
      of the patients opted for further medication for pain relief. Also, a visual analog scale was
      provided to all the subjects during their presentation to the hospital for 2 consecutive days
      for treatment. the scales were obtained in all the subjects individually assessing the
      intensity of pain after the medication intake during the study period. Team of six doctors
      evaluated the patients in the study. 2 physicians were assigned the task of data collection
      from the study participants and assigning them into the group chosen by the patients
      themselves. 2 physicians had evaluated the patients VAS scores clinically and administered
      the necessary medication to the patients and rest of the doctors had evaluated the patients
      at each visit, making a note of inter observer variability. The enquiry of following adverse
      effects were noted from all 3 groups.

      Group A: Rash, Itch, Gastritis

      Group B: Rash at the delivery site, adherence of patch

      Group C: Pain at injection site, Nerve palsy, Hypersensitivity reactions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 31, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 15, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>3 arms with 3 groups of 30 patients each evaluated for diclofenac sodium oral tablets, transdermal patch and injection of same drug for dental pain disorders</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Perception scale</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of pain on Visual Analog scale scores in all three groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient compliance - Self reported daily catalog</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Self reported by patients themselves on their compliance with oral medication, transdermal patch and intra muscular injection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Orofacial Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diclofenac sodium oral</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group A which included 30 patients of either gender. Dosage drug: Diclofenac sodium Dosage form: Oral medication Frequency: twice daily Dose: 50mg Duration: 2 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>diclofenac sodium patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group B which included 30 patients who were prescribed Drug: Diclofenac sodium Dose: 100mg Drug form: transdermal patch to equate the oral dosage of 50mg Duration: for 2 days Frequency: Once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diclofenac sodium injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group C which included 30 patients of either gender Drug: diclofenac sodium intra muscular injections Dose: 75mg which was the nearest available dosage to 100 mg availability in India Frequency: once daily Duration: for 2 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diclofenac Sodium</intervention_name>
    <description>tablet of 50mg,</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diclofenac sodium oral</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Voveran</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diclofenac sodium</intervention_name>
    <description>Transdermal patch 100 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>diclofenac sodium patch</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sparsh</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diclofenac</intervention_name>
    <description>intra muscular injection 100mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diclofenac sodium injection</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>dicloran</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with oral and dental pain due to pulp and periapical pathology

          -  patients not allergic to any form of medications in terms of NSAIDs.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unwilling and unconscious patients

          -  patients with cellulitis and spreading oral infections

          -  patients allergic to non steroidal anti inflammatory agents

          -  patients with kidney and liver diseases

          -  patients with blood disorders
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Panineeya Institute of Dental Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyderabad</city>
        <state>Telangana</state>
        <zip>500060</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Panineeya Mahavidyalaya Institute of Dental Sciences &amp; Research Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>NALLAN CHAITANYA</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Facial Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diclofenac</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

