<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03223623</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>170126</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>17-N-0126</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03223623</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pathophysiology of Dystonia and Complex Regional Pain Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigations of Pathophysiology of Dystonia and Complex Regional Pain Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Little is known about the problems in brain function in focal hand dystonia (FHD) or complex
      regional pain syndrome (CRPS) dystonia. It is unclear why some CRPS patients develop dystonia
      but others do not. Researchers want to learn which area of the brain is involved in CRPS
      dystonia compared with FHD.

      Objectives:

      To understand why people with CRPS develop dystonia, and if these reasons are different in
      people with FHD.

      Eligibility:

      Adults ages 18 - 70 with CRPS dystonia OR with CRPS without dystonia OR with FHD and Healthy
      volunteers of similar age.

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with physical exam, neurological exam, and medical history.
      They may give a urine sample and will answer questions.

      Participants can have 4 - 5 outpatient visits or stay at the clinical center for
      approximately 5-6 days.

      Participants will have MRI scans. They will lie on a table that slides in and out of a
      scanner that takes pictures of their brain. They will do small tasks or be asked to imagine
      things during the scanning.

      Participants will have transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) sessions for a few hours, with
      breaks. A brief electrical current passing through a well insulated wire coil on the scalp
      creates a magnetic pulse. This affects brain activity. Participants may do small tasks during
      TMS.

      Participants will have the electrical activity of their muscles measured during TMS sessions.
      Small sticky pads will be attached to their hands and arms.

      Participants ability to feel 2 separate stimuli as different will be tested by using a weak
      electrical shock to their fingers. They will also be asked to feel small plastic domes with
      ridges, that may cause discomfort.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      The current exploratory study aims at detailed evaluation of pathophysiology of Complex
      Regional Pain Syndrome (CRPS) dystonia compared to Focal Hand Dystonia (FHD) with focus on
      the involvement of the parietal area.

      Study population:

      The study will enroll patients with Focal Hand Dystonia (FHD), CRPS dystonia, CRPS without
      dystonia and Healthy Volunteers (HVs).

      Design:

      Prospective study using MRI and Physiology experiments using EMG and TMS based protocols to
      evaluate the differences between the groups.

      Outcome measures:

      The evaluation using fMRI will be performed under 3 conditions; 1. Rest 2. Voluntary activity
      3. Motor imagery task.

      Outcome measures (fMRI based):

        -  We will explore the differences in BOLD signal in the parietal lobe, in CRPS dystonia
           compared to FHD, in the different conditions. We will look for changes in the BOLD
           signal in the parietal sensorimotor integration area.

        -  We will further explore the differential activation in CRPS dystonia vs CRPS without
           dystonia to identify any specific features inherent to patients with CRPS dystonia
           compared to CRPS alone.

      The Physiology experiments aim to explore abnormalities and differences in the baseline motor
      cortical excitability between the groups and evaluated the influence of continuous Theta
      Burst Stimulation (cTBS) on these measures. We will study the influence of cTBS on the
      phenomenon Cortical Silent Period ( cSP) in CRPS dystonia and FHD.

      We will also be studying the baseline Spatial and Temporal Discrimination (SDTs and TDTs),
      which are measures of sensory surround inhibition. TDT and SDT abnormalities have been noted
      to be endophenotypic of dystonia, however the comparative characteristics between FHD and
      CRPS dystonia are not known.

      Physiology outcomes:

        -  Baseline differential influences of PMv and IPL on motor cortical excitability and
           changes after cTBS of dIPL.

        -  Baseline cortical Silent Period (cSP) in the involved and uninvolved limb in FHD and
           CRPS dystonia and the influence of cTBS on cSP between the groups in the involved limb.

        -  The TDTs/ SDTs in both the involved and uninvolved limbs in FHD and CRPS dystonia
           compared to HVs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 12, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation using fMRI will be performed under 3 conditions; 1. Rest 2. Voluntary activity 3. Motor imagery task.</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TMS outcomes (continuous): differential influences of PMv and IPL on motor cortical excitability, changes after cTBS of dIPL, changes in the SI measures post TBS in FHD.</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Dystonia</condition>
  <condition>Complex Regional Pain Syndromes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Focal Hand Dystonia (FHD)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Focal Hand Dystonia (FHD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CRPS dystonia</arm_group_label>
    <description>CRPS dystonia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CRPS without dystoni</arm_group_label>
    <description>CRPS without dystonia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy Volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will enroll patients with Focal Hand Dystonia (FHD), CRPS dystonia, CRPS without
        dystonia and Healthy Volunteers (HVs).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age between 18 - 70 years.

          -  Able to give informed consent.

          -  Able to comply with all study procedures.

          -  Subjects must be willing to abstain from alcohol for at least 48 hours prior to the
             study.

          -  Adult patients with an established diagnosis of focal hand dystonia.

          -  Healthy volunteers will be healthy subjects without neurological or psychiatric
             disorders established by history and physical/neurological examination.

          -  Adult CRPS patients, diagnosed based on the Budapest Clinical diagnostic criteria by
             an experienced Neurologist, with the presence of dystonia involving at least one hand.

          -  Adult CRPS patients, diagnosed based on the Budapest Clinical diagnostic criteria by
             an experienced Neurologist, without the presence of dystonia in any limbs.

          -  Patients receiving botulinum toxin injections will be evaluated after 3 months since
             their last injection.

          -  All participants must be able to obtain an MRI (No contraindications per MRI safety
             checklist) which will be part of the initial evaluation.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Self-reported consumption of &gt;14 alcoholic drinks/week for a man and &gt;7 alcoholic
             drinks/week for a woman.

          -  Patients on daily chronic opioid or benzodiazepine use.

          -  Patients treated with anticholinergics, who are not willing and/or unable to withhold
             taking them for 1 week prior and for the duration of the study participation.

          -  Patients taking opioids and/or benzodiazepines on an as needed basis, who are not
             willing and/or unable to withhold taking them for 1 week or time interval equivalent
             to 5 half-lives (whichever is shorter) prior to study participation and for the days
             during study participation.

          -  Abnormal findings on neurological examination, except diagnosis of interest (FHD, CRPS
             with/without dystonia in patients.

          -  History of or current brain tumor, stroke, head trauma with loss of consciousness,
             epilepsy or seizures.

          -  Past or present medical history of (a) neurological disorders, such as stroke,
             movement disorders (other than dystonia in the patient group), ataxias, myopathies,
             myasthenia gravis, demyelinating diseases, alcoholism, drug dependence; (B)
             ventricular arrhythmias, renal and hepatic insufficiency, vascular headache, or
             carcinoid syndrome.

          -  Subjects with Baclofen pumps and/or neuro stimulators for pain.

          -  Current episode of major depression or any major psychiatric illness. Note: SSRI use
             is not exclusionary.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women. Aside from history obtained at the screening,
             pregnancy status in women with childbearing potential is also established by urine
             pregnancy testing no more than 24 hours before each MRI and TMS sessions.

          -  Subjects who have contraindications to MRI:

               -  You have metal in your body which would make having an MRI scan unsafe, such as
                  pacemakers, stimulators, pumps, aneurysm clips, metallic prostheses, artificial
                  heart valves, cochlear implants or shrapnel fragments, or if you were a welder or
                  metal worker, since you may small metal fragments in the eye.

               -  You are uncomfortable in small closed spaces (you have claustrophobia) so that
                  you would feel uncomfortable in the MRI machine.

               -  You are not able to lie comfortably on your back for approximately 2 hours.

          -  Subjects who have contra-indications for TMS

               -  You have a pacemaker, implanted pump, stimulator, cochlear implant or metal
                  objects inside the eye or skull.

               -  You have hearing loss.

               -  You are pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shabbir Hussain I Merchant, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elaine P Considine, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-8518</phone>
    <email>considinee@ninds.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2017-N-0126.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harden RN, Bruehl S, Stanton-Hicks M, Wilson PR. Proposed new diagnostic criteria for complex regional pain syndrome. Pain Med. 2007 May-Jun;8(4):326-31.</citation>
    <PMID>17610454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwartzman RJ, Kerrigan J. The movement disorder of reflex sympathetic dystrophy. Neurology. 1990 Jan;40(1):57-61.</citation>
    <PMID>2296383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 8, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Complex Regional Pain Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>CRPS</keyword>
  <keyword>Dystonia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Somatoform Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Complex Regional Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Reflex Sympathetic Dystrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

