<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01929967</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB-P00007001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01929967</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Defining Immunodeficiency in Heterotaxy Syndrome: Pilot Study Data</brief_title>
  <official_title>Defining Immunodeficiency in Heterotaxy Syndrome: Pilot Study Data</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Litron Laboratories</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim with this study is to investigate the mechanisms of immune deficiency
      in patients with heterotaxy syndrome through the use of novel biomarkers and a prospective
      questionnaire survey documenting the burden of infectious sequelae following enrollment. It
      is known that patients with under-active spleens (functional asplenia or hyposplenia)
      secondary to other (non-cardiac) conditions such as Sickle Cell Disease or Inflammatory Bowel
      Disease have a characteristic paucity of a B cell sub-class known as IgM memory B cell. This
      specific sub-class of B cell normally matures in the spleen and in those with an improperly
      functioning spleen a significant deficiency of this B cell class is seen on flow cytometry.

      Similarly, these same patients are noted to have increased amounts of 'junk' DNA / nuclear
      remnant in their red cells. This is seen on microscopy as a dark particle inside the red cell
      and is termed a Howell Jolly Body (normally less than 2% of red cells have these dark
      particles present). Part of a functioning spleen's normal task is to rid the blood of red
      cells that contain nuclear remnants and an under-active spleen gets behind on this task with
      a build-up of Howell Jolly Bodies in red cells present in the bloodstream. Flow cytometry can
      very quickly and accurately quantify Howell Jolly Bodies as well as IgM memory B cells from a
      small (~1.5cc) sample of blood. Normal IgM memory B cell ranges are known for healthy
      children from infancy onwards allowing interpretation of results against normative data
      ranges.

      The investigators aim to enroll 10 patients in this pilot study who have a diagnosis of
      heterotaxy syndrome (both asplenia and polysplenia) and to prospectively follow them after
      obtaining the initial biomarker sample. The family will be contacted once every two weeks for
      a period of 12 weeks and asked a series of simple questions taking approximately 5 minutes on
      any recent infectious sequelae or symptoms. The questions will elucidate history of minor
      illness such as low-grade fever or cough to more significant events such as admission for
      in-patient antibiotic therapy of bacterial sepsis. Ultimately, with this pilot study, the
      investigators hope to obtain sufficient data to support funding applications for a larger,
      multi-center trial that will allow us to develop biomarker thresholds for future risk of
      sepsis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Howell Jolly Body quantification</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of recruitment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>IgM Memory B Cell quantification</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of recruitment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Results of phone questionnaire of parents documenting infectious symptoms and sequelae</measure>
    <time_frame>Once every 2 weeks for 12 weeks following enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Heterotaxy Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heterotaxy syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with a diagnosis of heterotaxy syndrome, as objectively defined by visceral heterotaxy (malrotation, interrupted inferior vena cava) with either documented polysplenia or asplenia by radiological imaging</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with a diagnosis of heterotaxy syndrome from inpatient and outpatient Cardiology
        settings at Boston Children's Hospital
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of heterotaxy syndrome, as objectively defined by visceral heterotaxy
             (malrotation, interrupted inferior vena cava) with either documented polysplenia or
             asplenia by radiological imaging.

          -  0-12 years old.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other known immunodeficiency or hyposplenic states (22q11, hypogammaglobulinemia,
             sickle hemoglobinopathy, liver cirrhosis or portal hypertension, organ
             transplantation, Fanconi syndrome, HIV or AIDS, chronic corticosteroid use, cancer,
             chemotherapy or other immunomodulating drug exposure, Addison's disease or
             pan-hypopituitarism, surgical splenectomy).

          -  Red blood cell transfusion within the last 90 days as the donated red blood cells may
             interfere with calculation of the subject's Howell Jolly Body count. Patient
             enrollment will be deferred until 90 days has elapsed, assuming other eligibility
             requirements are met.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Terence Prendiville, MB BCh BAO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 26, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 26, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Terence Prendiville</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Pediatric Cardiology Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heterotaxy syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Asplenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Polysplenia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heterotaxy Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

