<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01924169</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-0371</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-01058</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01924169</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lenalidomide as Immune Adjuvant in Patient's With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study of Immune-adjuvant Effect of Lenalidomide in Patients With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia and Hypogammaglobulinemia and Impaired Response to Vaccinations - RV-CL-CLL-PI-002544</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if lenalidomide can increase the level
      of immunoglobulins (parts of the blood that may help to improve the immune system's function)
      and/or will improve the protective effect of the flu and pneumonia vaccines in patients with
      CLL.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will take lenalidomide by
      mouth on Monday, Wednesday and Friday for 3 months.

      In order to participate in this study you must register into and follow the requirements of
      the Revlimid REMS™ program of Celgene Corporation. This program provides education and
      counseling on the risks of fetal exposure, blood clots and reduced blood counts. You will be
      required to receive counseling every 28 days during treatment with lenalidomide, follow the
      pregnancy testing and birth control requirements of the program that are appropriate for you
      and take telephone surveys regarding your compliance with the program.

      Depending on how you respond to the drug, after 3 months, you will either:

      °Take lenalidomide every Monday, Wednesday and Friday on a 3 months on/3 months off schedule.
      You will then repeat this process for up to 2 years.

      or

      °Take lenalidomide every day for an extra 3 months. If you respond well, you will take
      lenalidomide every day for 3 months, then for the next 3 months stop the drug. You will then
      repeat this process for up to 2 years.

      You should swallow the lenalidomide capsules whole with water. Do not open, crush, or break
      the lenalidomide capsules. If you touch a broken lenalidomide capsule, wash the area of your
      body with soap and water.

      If you miss a dose of lenalidomide, and it has been less than 12 hours since your regular
      dose time, take it as soon as you remember. If it has been more than 12 hours, just skip your
      missed dose. Do not take 2 doses at the same time. If you take too much lenalidomide or
      overdose, call your healthcare provider right away. If you vomit after any dose, do not take
      another dose.

      You will also receive a vaccine for the flu (Trivalent or Fluzone) 1 time a year. If you have
      not received one in the last 5 years, you will receive a vaccine for pneumonia (Pneumovax)
      between months 6 and 21. You will receive these vaccines as an injection under the skin.

      Study Visits:

      Before the first dose of study drug:

      °Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn to test cytokines (proteins that may affect the
      immune system) and to test your immune system.

      If you are able to become pregnant, 1 time a week for the first 4 weeks and then every 28
      days while on treatment, you will have a blood (about 1 teaspoon) or urine pregnancy test.

      While you are taking lenalidomide, blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests
      every 2-4 weeks.

      At 3 months (+/- 3 weeks):

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

      Before the flu vaccine, blood (about 1 teaspoons) will be drawn for antibody testing.
      Antibodies are created by the immune system and may attack foreign cells or substances, such
      as the study drug.

      At 4 weeks (+/- 2 weeks) and 3 months (+/- 3 weeks) after the vaccine, blood (about 2
      teaspoons) will be drawn for antibody testing, cytokine testing, and to test your immune
      system.

      Length of Study:

      You will take the study drug for up to 2 years. You will no longer be able to take the study
      drug if the disease gets worse, if intolerable side effects occur, or if you are unable to
      follow study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after the follow-up visits.

      End of Study:

      °Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for antibody testing and cytokine testing.

      This is an investigational study. Lenalidomide is FDA approved and commercially available for
      the treatment of multiple myeloma, myelodysplastic syndrome and mantle cell lymphoma. The use
      of this to help prevent infections by improving immunoglobulin levels and its use in
      combination with the flu and pneumonia vaccine is investigational.

      Up to 35 patients will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow Accrual
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 24, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 21, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 21, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>IgG Response</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>IgG response defined as having improvement in IgG level by at least 25% at 6 months, compared to baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seroconversion Response</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks after flu vaccine administered</time_frame>
    <description>Study considered positive in regard to the secondary endpoints if seroconversion is observed in 60% or more of the subjects for at least one of the vaccinations given.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematologic Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lenalidomide administered at the dose of 5 mg/day on Monday, Wednesday and Friday for 3 months. If Immunoglobulin G (IgG) levels improve by at least 25% of baseline, lenalidomide administration continued for 3 months on, and 3 months off for 2 years. If IgG levels do not improve, frequency of lenalidomide increased to 5 mg/day for additional 3 months and if response is achieved, lenalidomide continued at 5mg/day 3 month on/3 month off for a total of 2 years. Seasonal influenza vaccination (Trivalent Influenza Vaccine, Fluzone High Dose) administered yearly, during the fall/winter season and pneumococcal immunization (Pneumococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine, Pneumovax) administered once between month 6 and month 21.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg/day by mouth on Monday, Wednesday and Friday for 3 months. Process repeated for up to 2 years.
If IgG levels do not improve, frequency of lenalidomide increased to 5 mg/day by mouth for additional 3 months and if response is achieved, lenalidomide continued at 5mg/day 3 month on/3 month off for a total of 2 years.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-5013</other_name>
    <other_name>Revlimid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Influenza Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered as injection yearly, during the fall/winter season.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TIV</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pneumovax Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered by injection once between month 6 and month 21. Patients, who have received the Pneumovax vaccine within last 5 years, will not receive Pneumovax vaccination.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pneumonia vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) patients with IgG less than 500 mg/dl with/without
             symptoms who are either untreated or previously treated, regardless of response, at
             least 6 months from prior therapy (including mAb)..

          2. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)/World Health Organization (WHO) performance
             status of 0-2.

          3. Adequate renal functions as indicated by serum creatinine equal to or less than 2
             mg/dl.

          4. Adequate hepatic function indicated as total bilirubin equal to or less than 2 mg/dl
             and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) equal to or less than two times the upper limit of
             normal.

          5. Disease free of prior malignancies for 3 years with exception of currently treated
             basal cell, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma &quot;in situ&quot; of the cervix
             or breast. Patients with malignancies with indolent behavior such as prostate cancer
             treated with radiation or surgery can be enrolled in the study as long as they have a
             reasonable expectation to have been cured with the treatment modality received.

          6. Females of childbearing potential (FCBP). A female of childbearing potential is a
             sexually mature woman who: 1) has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral
             oophorectomy; or 2) has not been naturally postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive
             months (i.e., has not had menses at any time in preceding 24 consecutive months)&gt;

          7. FCBP must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least
             50 mlU/mL within 10-14 days prior to and again within 24 hours of starting
             lenalidomide from heterosexual intercourse or begin two acceptable methods of birth
             control, one highly effective method and one additional effective method at the same
             time, at least 28 days before she starts taking lenalidomide.

          8. FCBP must also agree to ongoing pregnancy testing (weekly for the first four weeks and
             then every 28 days while on therapy and at discontinuation of treatment).

          9. Men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with a FCBP even if they
             have had a successful vasectomy. All patients must be counseled at a minimum of every
             28 days about pregnancy precautions and risks of fetal exposure.

         10. Patients must be 18 years of age or older.

         11. All study participants must be registered into the mandatory Revlimid REMS® program,
             and be willing and able to comply with the requirements of the REMS® program.

         12. Females of reproductive potential must adhere to the scheduled pregnancy testing as
             required in the Revlimid REMS® program. Able to take aspirin (81 or 325 mg) daily as
             prophylactic anticoagulation (patients intolerant to ASA may use warfarin or low
             molecular weight heparin).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known sensitivity to lenalidomide or other thalidomide derivatives.

          2. History of Guillain-Barre within 6 weeks of previous influenza vaccination.

          3. Patient on steroid therapy.

          4. Documented prolymphocytic leukemia (prolymphocytes more than 55% in the blood) or
             Richter's transformation.

          5. Known positivity for HIV or active hepatitis B or C.

          6. Pregnant or breast feeding females.

          7. History of tuberculosis treated within the last five years or recent exposure to
             tuberculosis.

          8. Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality or psychiatric illness that
             places the subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study.

          9. Patients with a recent history of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) or pulmonary embolus
             (PE), in six months prior to enrollment are not eligible for this study.

         10. Subjects who have currently active hepatic or biliary disease (with the exception of
             patients with Gilbert's syndrome).

         11. Patients with severe allergic reaction (e.g., anaphylaxis) after previous dose of any
             influenza vaccine or to a vaccine component, including egg protein.

         12. Moderate or severe acute illness with or without fever.

         13. Use of any other experimental drug or therapy within 28 days of baseline.

         14. Concurrent use of other anti-cancer agents or treatments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alessandra Ferrajoli, MD,BS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 13, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 13, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 16, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>February 9, 2018</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2018</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hematologic Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypogammaglobulinemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Impaired Response to Vaccinations</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunoglobulins</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune system's function</keyword>
  <keyword>Lenalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>CC-5013</keyword>
  <keyword>Revlimid</keyword>
  <keyword>Flu vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>TIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Pneumonia vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Agammaglobulinemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heptavalent Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adjuvants, Immunologic</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>November 2014 through May 2016. All of the participants were recruited at The University of Texas (UT) MD Anderson Cancer Center.</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Lenalidomide</title>
          <description>Lenalidomide administered at the dose of 5 mg/day three times a day for three months. If IgG levels improve by at least 25% of baseline, lenalidomide administration continued for 3 months on, and 3 months off for 2 years. If Immunoglobulin G (IgG) levels do not improve, frequency of lenalidomide increased to 5 mg/day for additional 3 months and if response is achieved, lenalidomide continued at 5mg/day 3 month on/3 month off for a total of 2 years.
Seasonal influenza vaccination (Trivalent Influenza Vaccine, Fluzone High Dose) administered yearly, during the fall/winter season and pneumococcal immunization (Pneumococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine, Pneumovax) administered once between month 6 and month 21.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Lenalidomide</title>
          <description>Lenalidomide administered at the dose of 5 mg/day three times a day for three months. If IgG levels improve by at least 25% of baseline, lenalidomide administration continued for 3 months on, and 3 months off for 2 years. If IgG levels do not improve, frequency of lenalidomide increased to 5 mg/day for additional 3 months and if response is achieved, lenalidomide continued at 5mg/day 3 month on/3 month off for a total of 2 years.
Seasonal influenza vaccination (Trivalent Influenza Vaccine, Fluzone High Dose) administered yearly, during the fall/winter season and pneumococcal immunization (Pneumococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine, Pneumovax) administered once between month 6 and month 21.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="3"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="65" lower_limit="48" upper_limit="68"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Ethnicity (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>More than one race</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>IgG Response</title>
        <description>IgG response defined as having improvement in IgG level by at least 25% at 6 months, compared to baseline.</description>
        <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Lenalidomide</title>
            <description>Lenalidomide administered at the dose of 5 mg/day three times a day for three months. If IgG levels improve by at least 25% of baseline, lenalidomide administration continued for 3 months on, and 3 months off for 2 years. If IgG levels do not improve, frequency of lenalidomide increased to 5 mg/day for additional 3 months and if response is achieved, lenalidomide continued at 5mg/day 3 month on/3 month off for a total of 2 years.
Seasonal influenza vaccination (Trivalent Influenza Vaccine, Fluzone High Dose) administered yearly, during the fall/winter season and pneumococcal immunization (Pneumococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine, Pneumovax) administered once between month 6 and month 21.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>IgG Response</title>
          <description>IgG response defined as having improvement in IgG level by at least 25% at 6 months, compared to baseline.</description>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="3"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Seroconversion Response</title>
        <description>Study considered positive in regard to the secondary endpoints if seroconversion is observed in 60% or more of the subjects for at least one of the vaccinations given.</description>
        <time_frame>4 weeks after flu vaccine administered</time_frame>
        <population>The first three participants did not remain on study long enough to undergo immunizations.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Lenalidomide</title>
            <description>Lenalidomide administered at the dose of 5 mg/day three times a day for three months. If IgG levels improve by at least 25% of baseline, lenalidomide administration continued for 3 months on, and 3 months off for 2 years. If IgG levels do not improve, frequency of lenalidomide increased to 5 mg/day for additional 3 months and if response is achieved, lenalidomide continued at 5mg/day 3 month on/3 month off for a total of 2 years.
Seasonal influenza vaccination (Trivalent Influenza Vaccine, Fluzone High Dose) administered yearly, during the fall/winter season and pneumococcal immunization (Pneumococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine, Pneumovax) administered once between month 6 and month 21.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Seroconversion Response</title>
          <description>Study considered positive in regard to the secondary endpoints if seroconversion is observed in 60% or more of the subjects for at least one of the vaccinations given.</description>
          <population>The first three participants did not remain on study long enough to undergo immunizations.</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Adverse events reported during each treatment course monthly</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Lenalidomide</title>
          <description>Lenalidomide administered at the dose of 5 mg/day three times a day for three months. If IgG levels improve by at least 25% of baseline, lenalidomide administration continued for 3 months on, and 3 months off for 2 years. If IgG levels do not improve, frequency of lenalidomide increased to 5 mg/day for additional 3 months and if response is achieved, lenalidomide continued at 5mg/day 3 month on/3 month off for a total of 2 years.
Seasonal influenza vaccination (Trivalent Influenza Vaccine, Fluzone High Dose) administered yearly, during the fall/winter season and pneumococcal immunization (Pneumococcal Polysaccharide Vaccine, Pneumovax) administered once between month 6 and month 21.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>CTCAE (4.0)</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Chest Pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vomiting</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>CTCAE (4.0)</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Constipation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue/Malaise</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>insomnia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>rash</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Alessandra Ferrajoli, MD/Professor</name_or_title>
      <organization>The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</organization>
      <phone>713-792-7734</phone>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

