<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01927770</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130171</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-HG-0171</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01927770</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Consent Forms for Whole Exome and Whole Genome Sequencing</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Trial of Consent Interventions for NIH Whole Exome and Whole Genome Sequencing Studies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      The purpose of this study is to investigate the process of consenting participants to whole
      exome/genome sequencing and its outcomes. It is unknown how best to consent people to this
      new technology. NO GENOME SEQUENCING IS OFFERED AS PART OF THIS STUDY. This protocol is a
      companion to other NIH studies that involve genomic sequencing. Participants must be enrolled
      in a parent NIH study that is collaborating on this consent study to be eligible. Currently
      this involves only one NIH study.

      Objectives:

      - To learn the best way to help participants understand sequencing, so they can decide
      whether to join studies that use it.

      Eligibility:

        -  Adults at least 18 years old who are enrolled in a National Institutes of Health (NIH)
           study that uses WES/WGS.

        -  Adults at least 18 years old whose children are enrolled in an NIH study that uses
           WES/WGS.

      Design:

        -  Participants will take part in the study either in person or over the phone.

        -  Participants will review two sequencing consent forms with a genetic counselor.

        -  Before and after meeting with the counselor, participants will answer several questions
           about sequencing. Each questionnaire will take about 15 minutes.

        -  Six weeks later, participants will answer questions about sequencing. This will take
           about 15 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Consent to participant in studies that include whole exome and whole genome sequencing
      (WES/WGS) studies and to receive results present challenges to achieving informed consent due
      to the scope, depth and uncertainty of the information. NIH Intramural studies increasingly
      involve WES/WGS to identify elusive primary variants. This umbrella protocol aims to compare
      an evidence-based consent for WES/WGS to a standard consent in

      collaboration with ongoing and future NIH studies. An equivocal hypothesis will be tested to

      evaluate whether informed choice and perceptions of uncertainty differ between two consent

      groups. A mixed-methods design is proposed that starts with a qualitative mental-model pilot

      study to revise an expert opinion consent intervention by integrating lay-person response

      preferences. Following development of this evidence-based intervention, a randomized
      twofactor design will be used for a quantitative survey study conducted in conjunction with a

      number of NIH studies conducting WES/WGS to test for differences between two consent

      models. A descriptive analysis of the audiotaped consent process will also be conducted to

      assess differences in the content or extent of the process, and related outcomes of
      satisfaction and decisional conflict will also be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 20, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 10, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 10, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Informed Choice</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">212</enrollment>
  <condition>Whole Genome Sequencing</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Eligible adults (greater than or equal to 18 years of age) consenting to enroll in an NIH
        study that includes WES/WGS. Parents of eligible children (&lt;18 years of age) consenting to
        enroll their child(ren) in an NIH study that includes WES/WGS. Participants must be
        cognitively able to consent and fluent in written and spoken English.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Children (&lt;18 years of age). Non-English speaking participants (until the study has evolved
        to be able to use translations of the interventions into Spanish).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie Sapp</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-HG-0171.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ayuso C, Millán JM, Mancheño M, Dal-Ré R. Informed consent for whole-genome sequencing studies in the clinical setting. Proposed recommendations on essential content and process. Eur J Hum Genet. 2013 Oct;21(10):1054-9. doi: 10.1038/ejhg.2012.297. Epub 2013 Jan 16.</citation>
    <PMID>23321621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biesecker LG, Mullikin JC, Facio FM, Turner C, Cherukuri PF, Blakesley RW, Bouffard GG, Chines PS, Cruz P, Hansen NF, Teer JK, Maskeri B, Young AC; NISC Comparative Sequencing Program, Manolio TA, Wilson AF, Finkel T, Hwang P, Arai A, Remaley AT, Sachdev V, Shamburek R, Cannon RO, Green ED. The ClinSeq Project: piloting large-scale genome sequencing for research in genomic medicine. Genome Res. 2009 Sep;19(9):1665-74. doi: 10.1101/gr.092841.109. Epub 2009 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19602640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dormandy E, Michie S, Hooper R, Marteau TM. Low uptake of prenatal screening for Down syndrome in minority ethnic groups and socially deprived groups: a reflection of women's attitudes or a failure to facilitate informed choices? Int J Epidemiol. 2005 Apr;34(2):346-52. Epub 2005 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>15737971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 23, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Whole Genome Sequencing</keyword>
  <keyword>Informed Choice</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

