<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01920477</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>116910</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01920477</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Ofatumumab in Treatment of Pemphigus Vulgaris</brief_title>
  <official_title>OPV116910: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel-Group Study to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Ofatumumab Injection for Subcutaneous Use in Subjects With Pemphigus Vulgaris</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pemphigus vulgaris (PV) is a rare, chronic, debilitating, and potentially life-threatening
      autoimmune disorder that is characterized by mucocutaneous blisters. Ofatumumab is a novel
      monoclonal antibody (mAb) that specifically binds to the human CD20 antigen, which is
      expressed only in B lymphocytes.

      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy, tolerability, and safety of ofatumumab
      injection for subcutaneous use (ofatumumab SC) 20 milligrams (mg) administered once in every
      4 weeks, (with an additional 20 mg loading dose [i.e. 40 mg total] at both Week 0 and Week 4)
      in subjects with PV. It is anticipated that with sustained B-cell depletion in the presence
      of ofatumumab SC, and the resultant reduction of pathogenic anti Dsg (desmoglein)
      autoantibodies in PV, that clinical remission of the disease will result.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 13, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 11, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 11, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to sustained remission on minimal steroid therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time from randomization to the time of the subject's initial reduction of prednisone/prednisolone dose to &lt;=10 mg/day and maintained a dose &lt;=10 mg/day with no new or nonhealing (established) lesions for &gt;=8 weeks and maintained the status until Week 60 will be assessed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of remission on minimal steroid therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Sum of all periods of absence of new or nonhealing (established) lesions while on an oral prednisone/prednisolone dose of &lt;=10 mg/day up to Week 60 will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects achieving remission on minimal steroid therapy at Week 60</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 60</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of subjects achieving absence of new or nonhealing (established) lesions while on an oral prednisone/prednisolone dose of &lt;=10 mg/day at Week 60 will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to remission while on minimal steroid therapy by Week 60.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time from randomization to the time of the subject's initial reduction of prednisone/prednisolone dose to &lt;=10 mg/day and maintained dose at &lt;=10 mg/day with no new or nonhealing (established) lesions for &gt;=8 weeks by Week 60 will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to remission off steroid therapy by Week 60</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time from randomization to the time of the subjects initial reduction of all steroids for &gt;=8 weeks with an absence of new or nonhealing (established) lesions by Week 60 will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects achieving remission while off steroid therapy by Week 60</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of subjects with initial reduction of all steroids for &gt;=8 weeks with an absence of new or nonhealing (established) lesions by Week 60 will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days a subject maintained minimal steroid therapy by Week 60.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days a subject maintained minimal steroid therapy (an oral prednisone/prednisolone dose of ≤10 mg/day in the absence of new or nonhealing lesions) by Week 60.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to initial flare/relapse by Week 60</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time from randomization to the time of appearance of &gt;=3 new lesions within 1 month that did not heal spontaneously within 1 week, or to the time when there was an extension of lesions that were present at the randomization by Week 60 will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects with no flare/relapse by Week 60</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of subjects achieving absence of new or nonhealing (established) lesions while on an oral prednisone/prednisolone dose of &lt;=10 mg/day and did not subsequently have a appearance of &gt;=3 new lesions within 1 month that did not heal spontaneously within 1 week, or to the time when there was an extension of lesions that were present at the randomization by Week 60 will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative dose of corticosteroids</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Exposure to corticosteroids over a period of 60 weeks will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in B-lymphocyte counts in peripheral blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change from Baseline in B-lymphocyte counts in peripheral blood at prespecified time points (Day 0 and every four weeks till Week 60) and at the time of any opportunistic infection will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to repletion of CD19+ B-cells to either &gt;=Baseline level or &gt;=Lower Limit of Normal (LLN) , whichever</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time to repletion of CD19+ B-cells to either &gt;=Baseline level (observation at Week 0) or &gt;=LLN (110 cell/mcgL), whichever is lower will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of population pharmacokinetics (PK) of ofatumumab</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma (trough) concentrations of ofatumumab, Exposure-response relationship, PK parameters include: Maximum concentration (Cmax); time to maximum concentration (tmax); and area under the time-concentration curve (AUC).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity of ofatumumab</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Immunogenicity will be assessed by the incidence, titer, and type of human anti-human antibody (HAHA) immune response</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of ofatumumab assessed by Adverse events (AEs).</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>AEs assessment include: Frequency and severity of AE, AE relationship to IP, frequency and severity of SAE, AE of special interest, Frequency and severity of infections, Percentage of subject withdrawals due to treatment-related AEs, AEs leading to permanent discontinuation of study drug, Postinjection systemic reactions, Injection site reactions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs include: pulse rate, temperature, systolic and diastolic blood pressure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in laboratory parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory parameters include: hematology, clinical chemistry, and urinalysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of demographic factors, including Baseline covariates on PK parameters of ofatumumab as data permits.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Demographic factors such as age, race, and sex.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of Vital signs of Clinical Concern</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs of Clinical Concern are a subset based on pre-defined levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Pemphigus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subject will receive subcutaneous administration of ofatumumab 20 mg once every 4 weeks through Week 56, with an additional 20 mg dose (that is 40mg total) at both Week 0 and Week 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subject will receive subcutaneous administration of matching placebo of ofatumumab once every 4 weeks through Week 56, with an additional dose at both Week 0 and Week 4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ofatumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Ofatumumab (human monoclonal antibody) will be provided in prefilled glass syringes containing 0.4 milliliters (mL) (20 mg) of concentration 50 mg/mL drug product</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo to match the active doses will consist of prefilled glass syringes containing 0.4 mL of normal saline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  Adults (18 through 70 years of age) with clinically-documented diagnosis of PV for &gt;2
             months and &lt;10 years.

          -  History of biopsy consistent with PV (Hematoxylin and Eosin staining and direct
             immunofluorescence). If no history, a biopsy may be performed during the Screening
             Period.

          -  At least 1 previous episode of a failed steroid taper (ie, disease flare/relapse) at a
             prednisone/prednisolone dose &gt;10 mg/day. The following criteria must have been met as
             evidence of disease severity at the time of the failed steroid taper: a) A Pemphigus
             Severity of Clinical Disease score of moderate (2) or severe (3) (may be
             historical/retrospective assessment). b) Required a treatment change at the time of
             the failed steroid taper of at least one of the following: i) A steroid increase to
             &gt;=20 mg/day OR ii) The addition of immunosuppressive/immunomodulatory agent/treatment
             OR iii) A dose increase of immunosuppressive/immunomodulatory agent/treatment

          -  Screening anti-Dsg antibodies consistent with a diagnosis of PV (ie, elevated antiDsg3
             antibodies).

          -  Has initiated and received a stable dose of prednisone/prednisolone from a minimum of
             20 mg/day (example: 0.25 mg/kg/day for an 80 kg person) up to a maximum of 120 mg/day
             or 1.5 mg/kg/day (whichever is higher) for &gt;=2 weeks prior to randomization.

          -  Has exhibited PV disease control, defined as no new lesions for &gt;=2 weeks.

          -  A female subject is eligible to enter the study if she: Is of non-child bearing
             potential, who is either surgically sterile (bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral
             oophorectomy, or post-hysterectomy) or is postmenopausal without menses for &gt;2 years.
             Women who are &lt;2 years postmenopausal are required to have menopausal status confirmed
             by follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and estradiol levels at the screening
             evaluation. If FSH and estradiol levels do not provide confirmation of menopause,
             subject will be considered to be of childbearing potential; Is of childbearing
             potential, defined as a woman who has functional ovaries, ducts, and a uterus with no
             documented impairment that would cause sterility. This includes women with
             oligomenorrhea (even severe), women who are perimenopausal, and women who have just
             begun to menstruate. Subject must have a negative serum pregnancy test at screening
             and must agree to the consistent and correct use of acceptable methods of
             contraception during heterosexual intercourse, beginning when the subject provides
             informed consent and lasting until 12 months after last dose of investigational
             product.

        Acceptable methods of contraception are limited to the oral contraceptives (either combined
        or progesterone only), injectable progesterone, levonorgestrel implants, estrogenic vaginal
        ring, percutaneous contraceptive patches, intrauterine device or intrauterine system with a
        documented failure rate of &lt;1% per year, male partner sterilization (vasectomy with
        documentation of azoospermia) prior to the female subject's entry into the study; this male
        must be the subject's sole partner, double barrier method (condom and an occlusive cap
        [diaphragm or cervical/vault caps] with a vaginal spermicidal agent
        [foam/gel/film/cream/suppository]) and complete abstinence from heterosexual intercourse,
        For Japan subjects, in the list of acceptable methods of contraception, the following
        methods are not applicable in Japan: oral contraceptives with progestogen alone, injectable
        progesterone, levonorgestrel implants, estrogenic vaginal ring, percutaneous contraceptive
        patches, vaginal spermicidal foam, gel, film, and cream French subjects: In France, a
        subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study only if either affiliated to or a
        beneficiary of a social security category.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of pemphigus foliaceus, paraneoplastic pemphigus, or other autoimmune
             blistering disease (other than pemphigus vulgaris).

          -  Past or current history of hypersensitivity to components of the investigational
             product or medically significant adverse effects (including allergic reactions) from
             cetirizine (or antihistamine equivalent) or paracetamol/acetaminophen.

          -  Prior treatment with rituximab without achieving disease control within 6 months of
             initiating rituximab dosing.

          -  Prior treatment with with any of the following within the specified periods: any time:
             ofatumumab, total body irradiation, bone marrow transplantation, anti-CD4 ; within 2
             weeks: systemic steroids (except for prednisone/prednisolone) ; within 6 weeks: live
             vaccine ; within 8 weeks: azathioprine, cyclosporine, dapsone, mycophenolate,
             methotrexate and tacrolimus; within 6 months:cladribine, cyclophosphamide,
             plasmapheresis, immunoabsorption or immunoglobulin therapy, alemtuzumab, mitoxantrone;
             and within 18 months: Rituximab or other drugs affecting the number and function of
             B-cells- Confirmed progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML), or neurological
             findings potentially consistent with PML

          -  Evidence or history of clinically significant infection including: Chronic or ongoing
             active infectious disease requiring long term systemic treatment, including, but not
             limited to, chronic renal infection, chronic chest infection with bronchiectasis, or
             active hepatitis C; Positive test for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg). For HBsAg
             negative, but hepatitis B core antibody (anti-HBc/HBcAb positive (regardless of
             hepatitis B surface antibody [HbsAb] status), an HBV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) test
             will be performed and the subject will be excluded if results are positive; Consult
             with a physician experienced in the care and management of subjects with hepatitis B
             to manage/treat subjects who are anti-HBc positive; History of positive serology for
             human immunodeficiency virus; Previous serious opportunistic or atypical infections;
             Prior history, or suspicion, of tuberculosis (TB);

        For Japan: Evidence or history of clinically significant infection or medical condition
        including: Pneumocystis pneumonia or interstitial pneumonia (based on results of screening
        posterior-anterior chest X-ray, KL-6, and beta-D glucan). Order these tests from a local
        laboratory during screening and as part of a work-up for a subject with signs or symptoms
        of potential concern during the study; Based on the Japanese Guideline for Hepatitis B, for
        subjects who are HBsAg negative, anti-HBc (HBcAb) negative, but HBsAb positive, an HBV DNA
        test will be performed and the subject will be excluded from the study if results are
        positive; If any of the following criteria for TB screening are met:Past medical history
        for latent or active TB before screening; Sign(s) or symptom(s) suggestive of active TB in
        medical history on examination; Recent close contact with a patient with active TB;
        Positive interferon-gamma release assay or tuberculin skin test within 1 month before the
        first dose of study treatment; Chest x-ray, taken within 3 months before first dose of
        study treatment, shows evidence indicating currently active or previous TB.

        For South Korea: Evidence or history of clinically significant infection including: For
        subjects who are HBsAg negative, anti-HBc (HBcAb) negative, but HBsAb positive, an HBV DNA
        test will be performed and the subject will be excluded from the study if results are
        positive; If any of the following criteria for TB screening are met: Past medical history
        for latent or active TB before screening, Sign(s) or symptom(s) suggestive of active TB in
        medical history on examination; Recent close contact with a patient with active TB;
        Positive interferon-gamma release assay or tuberculin skin test within 1 month before the
        first dose of study treatment; Chest x-ray, taken within 3 months before first dose of
        study treatment, shows evidence indicating currently active or previous TB.

          -  Past or current malignancy, except for cervical carcinoma Stage 1B or less,
             noninvasive basal cell and squamous cell skin carcinoma and cancer diagnoses with a
             duration of complete response (remission) &gt;5 years

          -  Significant concurrent, uncontrolled medical condition that could affect the subject's
             safety, impair the subject's reliable participation in the study, impair the
             evaluation of endpoints, or necessitate the use of medication not allowed by the
             protocol. This includes subjects who require any systemic steroid treatment for a
             concurrent medical condition (other than pemphigus vulgaris).

          -  White blood cells (WBC) &lt;3.8 GI/L (&lt;3800/mm^3), neutrophils &lt;2 GI/L (&lt;2000/mm^3),
             platelets &lt;130 GI/L (130,000/mm^3), circulating IgG, IgA, or IgM levels &lt;10% of the
             LLN and requiring treatment in the opinion of the investigator, alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;2.0 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), aspartate
             aminotransferase (AST) &gt;2.0 X ULN, alkaline phosphatase (ALP) &gt;1.5 X ULN, bilirubin
             &gt;1.5 X ULN (except in cases of isolated predominantly indirect hyperbilirubinemia due
             to Gilbert's syndrome).

          -  Use of an investigational drug or other experimental therapy within 4 weeks, 5
             pharmacokinetic half-lives, or the duration of biological effect (whichever is longer)
             prior to Screening.

          -  Electrocardiogram (ECG) showing a clinically significant abnormality or showing a QTc
             interval ≥450 msec (≥480 msec for subjects with a bundle branch block) (ECG to be
             obtained during Screening/prior to receiving the first dose of study drug).

          -  Woman who is breastfeeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84132</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kogarah</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2217</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brisbane</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4102</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3002</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3004</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3050</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zagreb</city>
        <zip>10000</zip>
        <country>Croatia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Limoges cedex</city>
        <zip>87042</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille cedex 5</city>
        <zip>13385</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac Cedex</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reims</city>
        <zip>51092</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <zip>76031</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Larissa</city>
        <zip>41 110</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessalonica</city>
        <zip>54643</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>56429</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ramat-Gan</city>
        <zip>52621</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <zip>64239</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <state>Lazio</state>
        <zip>00167</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>Lombardia</state>
        <zip>20122</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Florence</city>
        <zip>50129</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hokkaido</city>
        <zip>060-8648</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kurume-shi</city>
        <zip>830-0011</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Okayama</city>
        <zip>700-8558</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>160-8582</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>135720</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Warszawa</city>
        <zip>02-008</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wroclaw</city>
        <zip>50-368</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucharest</city>
        <zip>11461</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cluj-Napoca</city>
        <zip>400006</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iasi</city>
        <zip>700401</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sibiu</city>
        <zip>550245</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Petersburg</city>
        <zip>194044</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dnipropetrovsk</city>
        <zip>49074</zip>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Croatia</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Greece</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 3, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 12, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pemphigus</keyword>
  <keyword>(MAB)</keyword>
  <keyword>autoimmune disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>human CD20 antigen</keyword>
  <keyword>subcutaneous</keyword>
  <keyword>Pemphigus vulgaris</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase 3</keyword>
  <keyword>monoclonal antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>ofatumumab</keyword>
  <keyword>PV</keyword>
  <keyword>rare disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pemphigus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ofatumumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Novartis is committed to sharing with qualified external researchers, access to patient-level data and supporting clinical documents from eligible studies. These requests are reviewed and approved by an independent review panel on the basis of scientific merit. All data provided is anonymized to respect the privacy of patients who have participated in the trial in line with applicable laws and regulations.
This trial data availability is according to the criteria and process described on www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

