<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01920490</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IDOR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01920490</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blame Rebalance fMRI Feedback Proof-of-concept</brief_title>
  <acronym>GUIMRINFB1</acronym>
  <official_title>Rebalancing Blame Using fMRI Neurofeedback: a Double-blind Controlled Clinical Proof-of-concept Trial in Remitted Major Depressive Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>D'Or Institute for Research and Education</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>D'Or Institute for Research and Education</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators have shown that decoupling of brain networks when feeling guilty is the
      first potential functional neuroimaging biomarker of risk of major depression. It remains
      detectable on remission of symptoms (Green et al., 2012). Decoupling of neural networks was
      found while people felt guilty during functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) relative
      to feeling indignation. Guilt-selective brain decoupling is therefore an excellent target for
      interventions to reduce the largely increased risk of recurrent episodes in people who have
      had one episode but are currently remitted. To our knowledge, however, there is no
      proof-of-concept study showing that self-blame-selective decoupling on fMRI can be detected
      and fed back to the participants after a short temporal delay in a real-time fMRI setting and
      whether coupling can be increased through neurofeedback training. This project aims at
      developing the first fMRI neurofeedback system to treat self-blame-selective neural
      decoupling and to test its feasibility in people with major depressive disorder currently
      remitted from symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific aim 1: Demonstrate that anterior temporal lobe (ATL)-septal/subgenual cingulate
      (SCSR) coupling for guilt can be increased through one session of neurofeedback in the group
      seeing visual feedback based on increasing correlations during the guilt condition compared
      with the group seeing visual feedback based on keeping correlations at the same level during
      the guilt condition.

      Specific aim 2: Demonstrate that this increase in coupling is selective for guilt relative to
      indignation.

      Specific aim 3: Demonstrate that mood is not negatively affected by neurofeedback.

      Specific aim 4: Explore whether this short intervention decreases self-hate on the
      Interpersonal Guilt Questionnaire (Portuguese translation) and increases self-esteem on the
      Rosenberg scale (both show significant correlations with SCSR-ATL coupling across major
      depressive disorder and control groups in our Manchester study), or if these measures are not
      available, decreases negative affect on the Positive and Negative Affect Scale.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in correlation between anterior temporal and subgenual frontal fMRI signal for guilt relative to indignation</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline after one session of fMRI neurofeedback training</time_frame>
    <description>Correlations are computed by using average signal in the most highly activated voxels within a priori regions of interest in the right superior anterior temporal and septal/subgenual cingulate region. The same a priori regions are also used to provide neurofeedback.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after one session of fMRI neurofeedback training</time_frame>
    <description>This is an outcome measure to ensure the safety of our intervention, we expect that one session of fMRI neurofeedback will not lead to a significant increase in Beck Depression Inventory scores when comparing scores after and before the training session.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interpersonal Guilt Questionnaire - Self-hate subscale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after one session of fMRI neurofeedback training</time_frame>
    <description>This is an exploratory outcome measure to determine whether there is a detectable effect on self-blaming emotions after one session of fMRI neurofeedback. This is not our primary aim in that this study is primarily designed to determine feasibility and safety rather than efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline after one session of fMRI neurofeedback</time_frame>
    <description>This is an exploratory outcome measure to determine whether there is a detectable effect on global self-esteem after one session of fMRI neurofeedback. This is not our primary aim in that this study is primarily designed to determine feasibility and safety rather than efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GUILT-INCREASE-CORRELATION</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will receive visual feedback that reinforces increasing the correlation in fMRI signal between the right superior anterior temporal and septal-subgenual regions during the retrieval of predefined guilt-related autobiographical episodes. During the indignation condition, visual feedback will reinforce stabilization of the preceding degree of correlation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GUILT-STABILIZE-CORRELATION</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will receive visual feedback that reinforces stabilization of the preceding degree of correlation in fMRI signal between the right superior anterior temporal and septal-subgenual regions during the retrieval of predefined guilt-related autobiographical episodes. During the indignation condition, visual feedback will also reinforce stabilization of the preceding degree of correlation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GUILT-INCREASE-CORRELATION</intervention_name>
    <description>This uses a novel software &quot;FRIEND&quot; created at IDOR in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. The software is used on a regular clinical fMRI scanner</description>
    <arm_group_label>GUILT-INCREASE-CORRELATION</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GUILT-STABILIZE-CORRELATION</intervention_name>
    <description>This uses a novel software &quot;FRIEND&quot; created at IDOR in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. The software is used on a regular clinical fMRI scanner</description>
    <arm_group_label>GUILT-STABILIZE-CORRELATION</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  past major depressive episode according to Diagnostic Statistical Manual (DSMIV) for
             at least 2 months, currently not fulfilling criteria for depression and remitted from
             symptoms for at least 2 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  suicidal thoughts

          -  other current DSM-IV axis-I disorders

          -  a history of atypical major depressive episodes (DSM-IV)

          -  Global Assessment of Functioning scores below 80 as a sign of incomplete remission or
             co-morbidity

          -  &gt;2 points on the suicidality item of the Hamilton Depression Scale

          -  prior criminal convictions

          -  history of violent behavior towards persons as determined by clinical interview

          -  positive past or current screening question for irritability on the mood disorders
             module

          -  antisocial personality as determined on personality interview using DSM-IV criteria

          -  borderline personality disorder as determined on personality interview using DSM-IV
             criteria according to the personality interview

          -  current self-harming behaviors
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jorge Moll, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>D'Or Institute for Research and Education</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roland Zahn, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>D'Or Institute for Research and Education</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paulo Mattos, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>D'Or Institute for Research and Education</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ricardo de Oliveira-Souza, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>D'Or Institute for Research and Education</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leonardo F Fontenelle, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto de Psiquiatria da Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto de Psiquiatria da Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rio de Janeiro</city>
        <zip>22290-140</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green S, Lambon Ralph MA, Moll J, Deakin JF, Zahn R. Guilt-selective functional disconnection of anterior temporal and subgenual cortices in major depressive disorder. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2012 Oct;69(10):1014-21.</citation>
    <PMID>22638494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 12, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 23, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

