<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02655315</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015_22</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-003679-31</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Grant agreement No 633190</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HP751</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02655315</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Conservative Iron Chelation as a Disease-modifying Strategy in Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>FAIRPARKII</acronym>
  <official_title>Conservative Iron Chelation as a Disease-modifying Strategy in Parkinson's Disease. European Multicentre, Parallel-group, Placebo-controlled, Randomized Clinical Trial of Deferiprone&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Lille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Commission</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ApoPharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Lille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effect of iron chelation as a therapeutic strategy to slow the
      progression of Parkinson's disease. Half of participants will receive the deferiprone to 15
      mg / kg twice daily morning and evening (30mg / kg per day), while the other half will
      receive a placebo. The treatment lasts nine months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is the new concept of &quot;conservative iron chelation&quot;. We recently demonstrated (for the
      first time) the feasibility, efficacy and acceptability of the conservative iron chelation
      approach in pilot translational studies in Parkinson's disease with a prototype drug:
      deferiprone (1,2-dimethyl-3-hydroxypyridin-4-one) (in the FAIR-PARK-I project led by the
      applicant and funded by French Ministry of Health). The only available
      blood-brain-barrier-permeable iron chelator deferiprone is approved for treating systemic
      iron overload in transfused patients with thalassemia. Deferiprone has been on the European
      Union market since 1999, with a favourable risk/benefit balance at dose of 75 to 100
      mg/kg/day. The investigators shall adopt a repositioning strategy by using deferiprone at a
      lower dose of 30 mg/kg/day in this new indication for local iron overload in Parkinson's
      disease. Deferiprone will be the first-in-class drug for this novel therapeutic strategy. On
      the basis of the preclinical and clinical data from (FAIR-PARK-I), the present (FAIR-PARK-II)
      project should constitute a model for future cytoprotection strategies in neurodegenerative
      diseases; if deferiprone treatment is associated with significant slower disease progression,
      it would be the first non-dopaminergic drug to have a proven disease-modifying effect in
      Parkinson's disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Global effect (symptomatic and disease modifying effects) on motor and non motor handicap</measure>
    <time_frame>at 36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the change in the total Movement Disorders Society-Unified Parkinson Disease Rating Scale score between baseline and 36 weeks (i.e. the end of the placebo-controlled phase for analysis of both disease-modifying and symptomatic effects)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-modifying effect on motor and non motor handicap</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It will be measured as the changes in the overall Movement Disorders Society-Unified Parkinson Disease Rating Scale score between baseline and week 40 (i.e. the end of the one-month post-treatment monitoring period), to analyse the disease-modifying effect without bias from the symptomatic effect of ongoing deferiprone treatment) on the study population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of the motor symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 12, 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The effect of the motor symptoms will be analysed as the change in the subscale part III of the Movement Disorders Society-Unified Parkinson Disease Rating Scale score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life and autonomy by PDQ-39 score</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It will be analyzed as the change in the Parkinson's Disease Quality of Life (PDQ-39, via a 39-item self-questionnaire)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life and autonomy by Clinical Global Impression score</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the Clinical Global Impression scored by the examiner and the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health economics assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>will be performed via a specific questionnaire provides a simple descriptive profile and a single index value for health status</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EQ-5D questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the questionnaire provides a simple descriptive profile and a single index value for health status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>All the safety concerns will be listed in a table with the number of patients, the type the severity and the time of occurrence for
adverse events
neutropenia (weekly complete blood count)
agranulocytosis (weekly complete blood count)
anemia (weekly complete blood count)
iron metabolism abnormalities (haemoglobin, serum iron, ferritinemia, transferrin, total binding capacity, transferrin saturation coefficient, 24-hour urine iron).
Standard biological abnormalities (fasting glucose, urea, creatinine, aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and (for all sexually active, fertile females) urine pregnancy tests.
Abnormal physical examination (including vital signs, bodyweight, electrocardiogram and blood pressure)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on overall cognitive status</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 12, 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the score in the Montreal Cognitive Assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on gait disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 12, 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Stand Walk Sit test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on daily living</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 12, 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The effect on daily living will be analysed as the change in the subscale part II (activities of daily living) of the Movement Disorders Society-Unified Parkinson Disease Rating Scale score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on non-motor symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 12, 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The effect on non motor symptoms will be analysed as the change in the subscale part I (cognition and behavior) of the Movement Disorders Society-Unified Parkinson Disease Rating Scale score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lack of occurrence of motor fluctuations</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, at 12, 36 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The lack of occurrence of motor fluctuations will be analysed on the subscale part IV of the Movement Disorders Society-Unified Parkinson Disease Rating Scale score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">338</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DEFERIPRONE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half of participants will receive the deferiprone (DFP) to 15 mg / kg twice daily morning and evening (30mg / kg per day).The treatment lasts nine months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PLACEBO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half of participants will receive the placebo twice daily morning and evening. The treatment lasts nine months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deferiprone</intervention_name>
    <description>15 mg / kg twice daily morning and evening (30mg / kg per day).The treatment lasts nine months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DEFERIPRONE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>active drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>the placebo twice daily morning and evening. The treatment lasts nine months</description>
    <arm_group_label>PLACEBO</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>harmless pill</other_name>
    <other_name>inactive drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients

          2. Parkinson's disease diagnosed according United Kingdom Parkinson's disease Society
             Brain Bank Clinical Diagnostic Criteria and based on the presence of at least two of
             the three cardinal features of the disease (rest tremor, bradykinesia and rigidity).
             If rest tremor is not present, subjects must have unilateral onset of symptoms.

          3. Treatment-naïve, i.e. the best population for assessing a disease-modifying effect
             without the interaction of dopaminergic treatment (no dopaminergic agonists, L-dopa,
             anticholinergics, monoamine oxidase B inhibitors (e.g. rasagiline) or deep brain
             stimulation).

          4. Patients covered by a Health Insurance System in countries where required by law

          5. Written informed consent dated and signed prior to the beginning of any procedures
             related to the clinical trial

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Disease duration greater than 18 months.

          2. Patients with high frequency of comorbidity or vital risks that may reasonably impair
             life expectancy

          3. Subject with handicap required dopaminergic treatment at the inclusion and therefore
             likely not to bear 9 months without symptomatic treatment

          4. Hoehn and Yahr stage 3 or more.

          5. Significant cognitive impairment (a Mini Mental State Examination score &lt;24 or an
             equivalent impairment on a similar scale) or dementia diagnosed in accordance with the
             Movement Disorders Society criteria (Emre et al., 2007).

          6. Atypical or secondary parkinsonism (supranuclear palsy, multisystem atrophy, etc.) or
             anomalies on MRI suggestive of vascular involvement or significant cortical or
             subcortical atrophy (i.e. atypical for Parkinson's Disease).

          7. Progressing axis I psychiatric disorders (psychosis, hallucinations, substance
             addiction, bipolar disorder, or severe depression), in accordance with the Diagnostic
             and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders.

          8. Subjects undergoing brain stimulation.

          9. Positive Human Immunodepression Virus serology.

         10. Hypersensitivity to deferiprone.

         11. Patients with agranulocytosis or with a history of agranulocytosis.

         12. Patients taking a treatment at risk of agranulocytosis (clozapine,
             Closaril®/Leponex®).

         13. Patients with anaemia (regardless of the latter's aetiology) or a history of another
             haematological disease. Haemochromatosis is not an exclusion criterion.

         14. Pregnant or breastfeeding women or women of childbearing potential not taking highly
             effective contraception.

         15. Kidney or liver failure.

         16. Other serious diseases.

         17. Inability to provide informed consent.

         18. Participation in another clinical trial with investigational medicinal product within
             3 months prior to inclusion in the study

         19. Patient who has suffered mild or moderate depressive episode and isn't in remission
             and on a stable medication for at least 8 weeks

         20. Patient &gt; 130k

        Exclusion criteria for the biomarker study and the ancillary study (i) Magnetic Resonance
        Imaging:

          -  Subjects for whom Magnetic Resonance Imaging is contraindicated (metal objects in the
             body, severe claustrophobia, pacemaker, incompatible surgical material).

          -  Very severe rest tremor, which could induce Magnetic Resonance Imaging artefacts.

        (ii) Lumbar puncture:

          -  Blood coagulation disorders, antiplatelet drugs or anticoagulants.

          -  Intracranial hypertension. (iii) Contraindications to nitrous oxide:

          -  Ventilation with Fraction of inspired Oxygen &gt;50%, emphysema or pneumothorax

          -  Altered states of consciousness, non-cooperative patient (need to stop the nitrous
             oxide)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Devos, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Lille</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Devos, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <email>david.devos@chru-lille.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Pauline Guyon, Project Manager</last_name>
    <email>pauline.guyon@chru-lille.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Universitat Innsbruck</name>
      <address>
        <city>Innsbruck</city>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Werner Poewe, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univerzita Karlova V Praze</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prague</city>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Evzen Ruzicka, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charles University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha</city>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Evzen Ruzicka, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Pellegrin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wassilios Meissner, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Wertheimer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bron</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stéphane Thobois, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Montpied</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont-Ferrand</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frank Durif, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Salengro, CHRU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU la TIMONE</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexandre Eusebio, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AP-HP, Hôpital Pitié-Salpêtrière</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Christophe Corvol, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Strasbourg, Hôpital de Hautepierre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Strasbourg</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christine Tranchant, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chu Purpan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olivier Rascol, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital, Saarland University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Homburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stefanie Behnke, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Christian-albrechts universität zu kiel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kiel</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniela Berg, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinik und Poliklinik für Neurologie der Universitätsmedizin Rostock</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostock</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Uwe Walter, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Acadamic central center, Amsterdam</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rob De Bie, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboud university medical center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bart Post, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Hospitalar e universitario de Coimbra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Coimbra</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cristina Januario, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Hospitalar do Alto Ave</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guimarães</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miguel Gago, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Hospitalar Lisboa Norte</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lisbon</city>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joaquim Ferreira, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clinic Universitari de Barcelona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eduard Tolosa, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Bellvitge</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matilde Calopa, MD,Phd</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jaime Kulisevsky, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cambridge University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Worth, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Glasgow</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Terminated</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Newcastle University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Burn, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Czechia</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Portugal</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://fairpark2.eu/</url>
    <description>Website for informations on the Fairpark2 study</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson</keyword>
  <keyword>Deferiprone</keyword>
  <keyword>Chelation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Deferiprone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

