<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02652364</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015/2423</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02652364</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Strong Ion Gap as Prognostic Indicator for Adult Patients Admitted With Shock to the Intensive Care Units</brief_title>
  <official_title>Strong Ion Gap as Prognostic Indicator for Adult Patients Admitted With Shock to the Intensive Care Units</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Singapore General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Changi General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Singapore General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates if strong ion gap on admission or 24 hours after admission to critical
      care unit can predict 28 day outcome in patients admitted with shock due to any cause
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Metabolic acidosis is frequently found in patients with shock. Traditional methods of
      evaluating acid-base status can underestimate and even miss complex acid-base disorders
      particularly in the setting of hypoalbuminemia, hypo/hypernatraemia and hypo/hyperchloraemia
      .An alternative approach to acid-base balance, based on chemical and physical principles, and
      was proposed by Peter Stewart more than 30 years ago. Later in 1992 Figge and Fencl modified
      the strong ion difference, which corresponds with the net charge balance of all strong ions
      present in a given solution (the ''Fencl-Stewart'' approach). The strong ion gap (SIG) which
      corresponds with the difference between the apparent strong ion difference and the effective
      strong ion difference was proposed by Kellum. Compared to the Fencl- Stewart approach SIG has
      more accuracy and bedside practicality.

      As the SIG is calculated from all known charged components of blood, it is considered the
      gold standard for the quantification of unmeasured anions. In contrast, the traditional anion
      gap calculation only factors in sodium, potassium, chloride and bicarbonate. In healthy
      humans, the SIG equals zero. In critically ill patients, a high SIG, defined as &gt;2mEq/L,
      indicates the accumulation of unmeasured anions in blood as a cause of acidosis. The
      unmeasured anions include lactate, ketoacids, uraemic acids and toxins like ethylene glycol
      and methanol. Studies found that a higher SIG on admission to intensive care unit is
      associated with poorer outcomes, and has a role in prediction of outcome in septic patients.
      However this finding is not consistent.

      In addition it was found that there is a significant difference in the threshold for SIG
      value associated with higher mortality. The abnormal SIG value in American studies are
      described around 5 mEq/l . However studies from Europe and Australia reported higher values
      in the range of 8-13 mEq/l. It is speculated that this difference is due to exogenous sources
      of unmeasured ions from gelatin based intravenous fluids used for resuscitation.
      Interestingly studies using gelatine- based fluids also failed to show a correlation between
      SIG and mortality. SIG values have not been published in critically ill Asian adult patients
      admitted to the Intensive Care Units (ICU) as yet. We aim to find the SIG for these patients
      in the hope that it will be useful for predicting outcome. Our hypothesis is that SIG is an
      independent predictor of outcomes in adult patient with shock.

      We propose to conduct this prospective observational study in the surgical and medical ICUs
      of 2 hospitals in Singapore. (Singapore General Hospital and Changi General Hospital) We aim
      to enrol 112 of you admitted to the ICU with shock of any etiology. Shock is defined as
      persistence of arterial hypotension despite adequate volume resuscitation. Hypotension is
      defined as systolic pressure &lt;90mmHg, Mean arterial pressure (MAP)&lt;70 mmHg or drop in SBP &gt;40
      mmHg from baseline. 30ml/kg of fluid is considered as the threshold for adequate volume
      resuscitation.

      The methodology of this observational study was approved by Sing health Institutional review
      Board, Singapore. We will include you if you have persistent hypotension despite adequate
      fluid resuscitation as defined above or if you require vasopressors or inotropes to maintain
      MAP above 65mmHg on admission.

      We will exclude the conditions with acid base disturbance which are not amenable to using
      standard supportive care such as pre-existing chronic kidney disease stage 3 and above (
      defined as estimated GFR&lt;60 ml/min/1.73m2 ) and chronic liver failure.

      Blood samples will be taken from indwelling intra-arterial catheters on admission and 24
      hours after admission. Blood samples will be analyzed in the respective hospital laboratory
      for Arterial Blood Gas(ABG) analysis, electrolytes albumin and lactate levels in order to
      calculate the SIG.

      All of you included in the study will be managed by the same group of critical care physician
      in accordance with pre-existing protocols in both ICUs to ensure that there will not be any
      major discrepancies among patients in terms of organ support and therapy. Haemodynamic
      support will be applied to reverse the hypotension and to correct peripheral perfusion
      abnormalities after optimal resuscitation. IV noradrenaline is the vasopressor of first
      choice followed by vasopressin and adrenaline.

      Data collection-

      Fluid resuscitation before ICU admission, SOFA and APACHE II score 24 hours after the
      admission, requirement for vasopressors, mechanical ventilation renal replacement
      therapy(RRT) ,duration of ICU stay, number of ventilator days, duration of vasopressor
      support, number of vasopressors used and the duration of RRT, 28 day outcome will be
      collected.

      Calculation of SIG-

      SIG will be calculated according to the following formulae;

        1. SIG= SIDapp - SIDeff

           (SIDapp -Strong ion difference apparent; SIDeff - Strong ion difference effective)

        2. SIDapp = ( Na++K++Ca2++Mg2+) - (Cl-+Lactate-)

           ( all concentrations in mEq/l)

        3. SIDeff = 2.46 x 10-8 x Pco2/ 10-pH + [albumin] x ( 0.123xpH - 0.631) +[PO43-] x
           (0.309xpH -0.469)

      (PCO2 is measured in mm Hg, albumin in g/L, and phosphate in mmol/L)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of ICU stay</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>number of days patient spent in ICU</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Shock</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patient with any form of shock on admission to ICU defined by those who require
        vasopressors or inotropes to maintain MAP &gt; 65mmHg on admission
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with any form of shock on admission to ICU

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  CKD stage 3 and above (GFR&gt; 60)

          -  Chronic liver failure( Child`s B grade and above)

          -  Patients who were already recruited for this study

          -  Patients expected to die within next 48 hrs upon admission
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Thangavelautham Suhitharan, MBBS,MMed</last_name>
    <phone>+6596499944</phone>
    <email>tsuhitharan@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Singapore General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169608</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thangavelautham Suhitharan</last_name>
      <phone>+6596499944</phone>
      <email>tsuhitharan@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mecher C, Rackow EC, Astiz ME, Weil MH. Unaccounted for anion in metabolic acidosis during severe sepsis in humans. Crit Care Med. 1991 May;19(5):705-11.</citation>
    <PMID>2026034</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Figge J, Mydosh T, Fencl V. Serum proteins and acid-base equilibria: a follow-up. J Lab Clin Med. 1992 Nov;120(5):713-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1431499</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Figge J, Jabor A, Kazda A, Fencl V. Anion gap and hypoalbuminemia. Crit Care Med. 1998 Nov;26(11):1807-10.</citation>
    <PMID>9824071</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stewart PA. Modern quantitative acid-base chemistry. Can J Physiol Pharmacol. 1983 Dec;61(12):1444-61.</citation>
    <PMID>6423247</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kellum JA, Kramer DJ, Pinsky MR. Strong ion gap: a methodology for exploring unexplained anions. J Crit Care. 1995 Jun;10(2):51-5.</citation>
    <PMID>7647842</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gunnerson KJ. Clinical review: the meaning of acid-base abnormalities in the intensive care unit part I - epidemiology. Crit Care. 2005 Oct 5;9(5):508-16. Epub 2005 Aug 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16277740</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kellum JA. Closing the gap on unmeasured anions. Crit Care. 2003 Jun;7(3):219-20. Epub 2003 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>12793870</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rutherford EJ, Morris JA Jr, Reed GW, Hall KS. Base deficit stratifies mortality and determines therapy. J Trauma. 1992 Sep;33(3):417-23.</citation>
    <PMID>1404512</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Smith I, Kumar P, Molloy S, Rhodes A, Newman PJ, Grounds RM, Bennett ED. Base excess and lactate as prognostic indicators for patients admitted to intensive care. Intensive Care Med. 2001 Jan;27(1):74-83.</citation>
    <PMID>11280677</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Balasubramanyan N, Havens PL, Hoffman GM. Unmeasured anions identified by the Fencl-Stewart method predict mortality better than base excess, anion gap, and lactate in patients in the pediatric intensive care unit. Crit Care Med. 1999 Aug;27(8):1577-81.</citation>
    <PMID>10470767</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kaplan LJ, Kellum JA. Initial pH, base deficit, lactate, anion gap, strong ion difference, and strong ion gap predict outcome from major vascular injury. Crit Care Med. 2004 May;32(5):1120-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15190960</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Funk GC, Doberer D, Sterz F, Richling N, Kneidinger N, Lindner G, Schneeweiss B, Eisenburger P. The strong ion gap and outcome after cardiac arrest in patients treated with therapeutic hypothermia: a retrospective study. Intensive Care Med. 2009 Feb;35(2):232-9. doi: 10.1007/s00134-008-1315-1. Epub 2008 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18853143</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Noritomi DT, Soriano FG, Kellum JA, Cappi SB, Biselli PJ, Libório AB, Park M. Metabolic acidosis in patients with severe sepsis and septic shock: a longitudinal quantitative study. Crit Care Med. 2009 Oct;37(10):2733-9.</citation>
    <PMID>19885998</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cusack RJ, Rhodes A, Lochhead P, Jordan B, Perry S, Ball JA, Grounds RM, Bennett ED. The strong ion gap does not have prognostic value in critically ill patients in a mixed medical/surgical adult ICU. Intensive Care Med. 2002 Jul;28(7):864-9. Epub 2002 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>12122523</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rocktaeschel J, Morimatsu H, Uchino S, Bellomo R. Unmeasured anions in critically ill patients: can they predict mortality? Crit Care Med. 2003 Aug;31(8):2131-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12973170</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hayhoe M, Bellomo R, Liu G, McNicol L, Buxton B. The aetiology and pathogenesis of cardiopulmonary bypass-associated metabolic acidosis using polygeline pump prime. Intensive Care Med. 1999 Jul;25(7):680-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10470571</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gunnerson KJ, Srisawat N, Kellum JA. Is there a difference between strong ion gap in healthy volunteers and intensive care unit patients? J Crit Care. 2010 Sep;25(3):520-4. doi: 10.1016/j.jcrc.2009.11.001. Epub 2009 Nov 25.</citation>
    <PMID>19942401</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Singapore General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Suhitharan Thangavelautham</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Resident, Department of Anaesthesia</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Shock</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

