<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02652676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5150418</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02652676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reversible Pulmonary Artery Banding as Simplified Management of End-stage Dilated Left Ventriculopathy in Early Life</brief_title>
  <official_title>Reversible Pulmonary Artery Banding as Simplified Management of End-stage Dilated Left Ventriculopathy in Early Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Loma Linda University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Loma Linda University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to: 1) Remodel and restore left ventricular geometry and
      function. 2) Avoid the need for mechanical circulatory support (MCS) and/or cardiac
      transplantation (CT). 3) Confirm the outcomes of a pilot study completed in Germany and
      reported in The Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation in May 2013.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study infant will undergo cardiac catheterization and myocardial biopsy before pulmonary
      artery banding and at appropriate intervals during follow-up surveillance by the
      interventional cardiologist. Patients will be &quot;listed&quot; for heart transplantation, and rPAB
      will be applied in lieu of mechanical circulatory support or as an alternative to already
      existing mechanical circulatory support, in the form of extracorporeal mechanical oxygen
      (ECMO). Myocardial biopsies will be flash frozen for storage and eventual probing for cell
      type (mature or stem) as part of a separate study.

      The addition of afterload rPAB to a normal-functioning right ventricle (in the setting of
      end-stage dilated cardiomyopathy) shifts the inter-ventricular septum toward the midline,
      thus significantly improving left ventricular geometry and function. It permits the infant or
      young child to operate from a much improved position on Starling's curve with gradual
      resolution of congestive heart failure and the potential for lethal ventricular dysrhythmia.
      An abundance of progenitor myocytes known to exist within the myocardium of this patient age
      group may then contribute to &quot;permanent&quot; left ventricular restoration.

      A sternotomy incision is used for application of the rPAB. The band is tightened under
      echocardiographic control until the inter-ventricular septum becomes a midline structure.
      Myocardial function is augmented with inotropic and vasodilator agents. These agents are
      weaned off gradually over a period of 2-4 weeks. The infant is separated from mechanical
      ventilation within the first post-rPAB week, and enteric feeding is resumed. The infant is
      discharged on oral medications, and is kept under frequent clinical surveillance.

      As the infant grows, the rPAB becomes relatively more obstructive to right ventricular
      outflow. Based on a finding of increasing right ventricular dilation, onset or worsening
      tricuspid valve regurgitation, or a gradual late increase in plasma B-type natriuretic
      peptide (BNP) levels, the band may be loosened in stages as a balloon catheter-based
      procedure. Band enlargement may be accomplished in stages, ultimately opting for a mild
      residual right ventricle-main pulmonary artery pressure gradient of 15-30 mmHg.

      The infants' short- and long-term surveillance will include clinical examination, height,
      weight, cardiac catheterization, electrocardiogram, echocardiogram, chest x-ray, and plasma
      BNP levels.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical Success</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>positive surgical outcome, the survival of the patient, the lack of a need for mechanical circulatory support or heart transplant, and improved left ventricular function</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All Cause Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistent Heart Failure</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute on Chronic Systolic Congestive Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Reversible Pulmonary Artery Banding</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The addition of afterload Reversible Pulmonary Artery Banding to a normal-functioning right ventricle (in the setting of end-stage dilated cardiomyopathy) shifts the inter-ventricular septum toward the midline, thus significantly improving left ventricular geometry and function. It permits the infant or young child to operate from a much improved position on Starling's curve with gradual resolution of congestive heart failure and the potential for lethal ventricular dysrhythmia. An abundance of progenitor myocytes known to exist within the myocardium of this patient age group may then contribute to &quot;permanent&quot; left ventricular restoration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reversible Pulmonary Artery Banding</intervention_name>
    <description>A sternotomy incision is used for application of the rPAB. Tightening is under echocardiographic control until the inter-ventricular septum becomes a midline structure. Myocardial function is augmented with inotropic and vasodilator agents that are weaned after 2-4 weeks. The infant is separated from mechanical ventilation within the first week, and enteric feeding is resumed. The infant is discharged on oral medications, with follow-ups. Band enlargement is in stages as a balloon catheter-based procedure if a finding of increasing right ventricular dilation, onset or worsening tricuspid valve regurgitation, or a gradual late increase in plasma B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) levels, opting for a mild residual right ventricle-main pulmonary artery pressure gradient of 15-30 mmHg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Reversible Pulmonary Artery Banding</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>rPAB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GORE-TEX DualMesh EMERGE PLUS Biomaterial</intervention_name>
    <description>The study is being conducted to evaluate the procedure, not the materials being used. The study uses the patch as materials to create the band around the pulmonary artery which is currently done routinely off label. The patch is approved as a cardiovascular patch. FDA 501(k) K032168.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Reversible Pulmonary Artery Banding</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gortex Cardiovascular Patch</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 0-4 years

          2. Isolated, idiopathic left-ventricular end-stage dilated cardiomyopathy or a Left
             Ventricular End-Diastolic Diameter (LVEDD) Z-score &gt; 4.5; Ejection Fraction (EF) &lt; 30%

          3. Acceptable candidate for mechanical circulatory support and/or cardiac transplantation

          4. Preserved right-ventricular function

          5. Clinical functional status IV (hospitalized)

          6. Parental consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Biventricular end-stage dilated cardiomyopathy

          2. Proven or suspected myocarditis

          3. Concomitant structural (congenital) heart disease

          4. Moderate-severe tricuspid valve regurgitation

          5. Pulmonary hypertension out of proportion with left-ventricular end-stage
             cardiomyopathy

          6. Hereditary disease associated with bi-ventricular dysfunction

          7. Age greater than 4 years

          8. No parental consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>4 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leonard Bailey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Loma Linda University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leonard Bailey, MD</last_name>
    <phone>909-558-3110</phone>
    <email>llbailey@llu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vanessa Ayer Miller, MS</last_name>
    <phone>9095584355</phone>
    <email>vayermiller@llu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Loma Linda University Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loma Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92354</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leonard L Bailey, MD</last_name>
      <phone>909-558-3110</phone>
      <email>llbailey@llu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vanessa Ayer Miller, MS</last_name>
      <phone>909-558-4355</phone>
      <email>vayermiller@llu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arbustini E, Weidemann F, Hall JL. Left ventricular noncompaction: a distinct cardiomyopathy or a trait shared by different cardiac diseases? J Am Coll Cardiol. 2014 Oct 28;64(17):1840-50. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2014.08.030. Epub 2014 Oct 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25443708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bailey LL. Back to the future! Bold new indication for pulmonary artery banding. J Heart Lung Transplant. 2013 May;32(5):482-3. doi: 10.1016/j.healun.2013.03.001.</citation>
    <PMID>23570740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brancaccio G, Amodeo A, Ricci Z, Morelli S, Gagliardi MG, Iacobelli R, Michielon G, Picardo S, Parisi F, Pongiglione G, Di Donato RM. Mechanical assist device as a bridge to heart transplantation in children less than 10 kilograms. Ann Thorac Surg. 2010 Jul;90(1):58-62. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2010.03.056.</citation>
    <PMID>20609748</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Everett BM, Berger JS, Manson JE, Ridker PM, Cook NR. B-type natriuretic peptides improve cardiovascular disease risk prediction in a cohort of women. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2014 Oct 28;64(17):1789-97. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2014.04.089. Epub 2014 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25443700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Julious SA. Two-sided confidence intervals for the single proportion: comparison of seven methods by Robert G. Newcombe, Statistics in Medicine 1998; 17:857-872. Stat Med. 2005 Nov 15;24(21):3383-4.</citation>
    <PMID>16206245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miyamoto SD, Karimpour-Fard A, Peterson V, Auerbach SR, Stenmark KR, Stauffer BL, Sucharov CC. Circulating microRNA as a biomarker for recovery in pediatric dilated cardiomyopathy. J Heart Lung Transplant. 2015 May;34(5):724-33. doi: 10.1016/j.healun.2015.01.979. Epub 2015 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25840506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ross RD. The Ross classification for heart failure in children after 25 years: a review and an age-stratified revision. Pediatr Cardiol. 2012 Dec;33(8):1295-300. doi: 10.1007/s00246-012-0306-8. Epub 2012 Apr 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22476605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schranz D, Veldman A, Bartram U, Michel-Behnke I, Bauer J, Akintürk H. Pulmonary artery banding for idiopathic dilative cardiomyopathy: a novel therapeutic strategy using an old surgical procedure. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2007 Sep;134(3):796-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17723838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schranz D, Rupp S, Müller M, Schmidt D, Bauer A, Valeske K, Michel-Behnke I, Jux C, Apitz C, Thul J, Hsu D, Akintürk H. Pulmonary artery banding in infants and young children with left ventricular dilated cardiomyopathy: a novel therapeutic strategy before heart transplantation. J Heart Lung Transplant. 2013 May;32(5):475-81. doi: 10.1016/j.healun.2013.01.988. Epub 2013 Feb 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23410738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Loma Linda University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Leonard Bailey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infant Cardiac Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>End-stage Idiopathic Dilated Cardiomyopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Mechanical Circulatory Device</keyword>
  <keyword>End Stage Dilated Left Ventriculopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute-on-Chronic Left Ventricular Failure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure, Systolic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

