<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02655276</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Classroom FR03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02655276</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sublingual Glycine vs. Placebo on Attentional Difficulties and Hyperactivity in Prepuberal Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Sublingual Microencapsulated Glycine on Attentional Difficulties and Hyperactivity in Prepuberal Children - A Placebo-controlled, Double-blind, Randomized, Cross-over Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eberhard Schulz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biotiki</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Freiburg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to investigate effects on attentional performance and motoric activity
      of 100 mg microencapsulated glycine (Bidicin® from Biotiki®) compared to placebo after
      treatment with t.i.d. sublingual doses over 3 weeks each.

      The primary objective of the study is to determine the effects on attentional performance and
      motoric activity of 100 mg microencapsulated Glycine (Bidicin® from Biotiki® ) compared to
      placebo after treatment with t.i.d. sublingual doses over 3 weeks each in children with low
      attentional performance and high motoric activity.

      A number of 30 prepuberal boys and girls aged 6 - 14 years with low attentional performance
      and high motoric activity will be enrolled in this study. The prepuberal status will be
      determined by Tanner stages ≤ 3.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Trial Design:

      This study has a double-blind, randomized, two-period, cross-over design. The study
      population will be randomized equally to the sequence 1 (first 3 weeks microencapsulated
      Glycine, second 3 weeks placebo) or sequence 2 (first 3 weeks placebo, second 3 weeks
      microencapsulated Glycine). Study Agent/Placebo - Dosage and Route of Administration:

      Study Agent/Placebo will first be dispensed at Visit 2 (day 0). Treatment assignments will be
      made in accordance with the randomization. At each visit (Visit 2 and Visit 3), subjects will
      receive two blisters for the 3 following weeks. Only qualified personnel may dispense study
      Agent/Placebo.

      Investigational and reference treatment:

      100 mg microencapsulated Glycine (Bidicin® from Biotiki® ) Placebo from Biotiki®

      Study design:

      This study will employ a double blind, randomized, placebo-controlled cross-over design.
      SKAMP raters and teachers will be blinded concerning the study Agent/Placebo.

      Planned Study Time Schedule:

      The study ends 10 weeks after enrollment of the last patient (total study end). Study
      duration for each patient is between 7 and 10 weeks (from inclusion) until the last visit
      (close-out visit).

      Statistics:

      Sample size calculation is based on the primary endpoint &quot;mean of the SKAMP Combined score
      over all time points in the classroom setting&quot;. The study should have sufficient power to
      detect a difference between treatments if a moderate effect size (corresponding to Cohen's
      d=0.5) were present in parallel-group study in two independent patient groups. Assuming a
      correlation between measurements in the same patient of 0.6, this translates into an effect
      size of 0.56 in a cross-over trial comparing within patient measurements. With this effect
      size, 27 patients have to be included in the study, to achieve a power of 0.8 at a two-sided
      significance level of alpha=0.05. To account for a small number of drop-outs, 30 patients
      have to be randomized.

      Data analysis: The trial will be analyzed according to the intention-to-treat principle.
      Efficacy measures will be evaluated by linear mixed models for repeated measurements.

      Safety analyses will be performed for subjects who received at least one dose of
      microencapsulated Glycine/ placebo. Incidences of adverse events and of serious adverse
      events will be calculated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SKAMP-Combined rating scale in the classroom setting</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>SKAMP-Combined rating performed at 25 minutes before and 0:50 h, 1,55 h, 2:50 h, 4:05 h, 5:50 h, 7:40 h and 8:35 h after first microencapsulated Glycine/ placebo intake in a laboratory classroom setting after a 3 week treatment period. The primary efficacy endpoint is the mean of the SKAMP-Combined score over all time points in the classroom setting.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SKAMP-Attention subscale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>SKAMP- Attention subscale rating performed at 25 minutes before and 0:50 h, 1,55 h, 2:50 h, 4:05 h, 5:50 h, 7:40 h and 8:35 h after first microencapsulated Glycine/ placebo intake in a laboratory classroom setting after a 3 week treatment period. The secondary efficacy endpoint is the mean of the SKAMP- Attention subscale score over all time points in the classroom setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>SKAMP-Deportment subscale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>SKAMP- Deportment subscale rating performed at 25 minutes before and 0:50 h, 1,55 h, 2:50 h, 4:05 h, 5:50 h, 7:40 h and 8:35 h after first microencapsulated Glycine/ placebo intake in a laboratory classroom setting after a 3 week treatment period. The secondary efficacy endpoint is the mean of the SKAMP- Deportment subscale score over all time points in the classroom setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The assessment of the child behaviour scale (CBCL) is performed by the primary caregivers due to the last week before the visit of a classroom. The CBCL global score and the CBCL subscores are used for evaluation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life scores</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The instrument provides a QoL total score and several domains of QoL regarding family, school, peers, interests, physical and mental health, and also the impact of the respective disorder. These scores are used for evaluation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual-Analogue-Scale of perceived parental stress</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The value of the visual-analogue-scale of perceived parental stress is used for evaluation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Saliva cortisol levels</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>In this study, saliva cortisol samples are collected for determination of the cortisol awakening response (CAR) as well as before and after the supposedly stressful situation of the classroom math test. For the CAR, cortisol will be measured on three consecutive days before Visit 2, 3 and 4 at awakening, 30 minutes after awakening and before bedtime.
For assessment of cortisol levels under acute stress, cortisol samples will be taken before and after classroom III of Visit 2, as well as before and after classroom III and VI of Visits 3 and 4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ADHD-Rating scale-IV</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The ADHD Rating Scale-IV is a reliable and easy-to-administer instrument both for diagnosing ADHD in children and adolescents and for assessing treatment response. Containing 18 items, the scale is linked directly to DSM-IV diagnostic criteria for ADHD.
Outcome Measure are the summed total score for &quot;Inattention, Hyperactivity and Impulsivity&quot; and the sub-scores for &quot;Inattention&quot; and for &quot;Hyperactivity and Impulsivity&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events that are related or not related to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse events no matter how intense will be observed by the investigator until resolved or until they can be sufficiently medical explained. All AEs must be described by diagnosis or symptoms, duration, frequency, severity, an assessment of its cause, its relationship to the study Glycine or placebo, whether it influenced the course of the study Glycine or placebo, whether it required specific therapy and its outcome.
All documented AEs will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Motor Activity</condition>
  <condition>Attention Deficit</condition>
  <condition>Stress, Psychological</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>100 mg microencapsulated Glycine and then Placebo tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>100 mg microencapsulated Glycine (Bidicin® from Biotiki® ) t.i.d. for the first three weeks and then Placebo t.i.d. from Biotiki® for the second three weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo tablets and then 100 mg microencapsulated Glycine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo t.i.d. from Biotiki® for the first three weeks and then 100 mg microencapsulated Glycine (Bidicin® from Biotiki® ) t.i.d. for the second three weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>microencapsulated Glycine</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg microencapsulated Glycine (Bidicin® from Biotiki® ) t.i.d.</description>
    <arm_group_label>100 mg microencapsulated Glycine and then Placebo tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo tablets and then 100 mg microencapsulated Glycine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo tablets</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo t.i.d. from Biotiki® in a crossover-design.</description>
    <arm_group_label>100 mg microencapsulated Glycine and then Placebo tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo tablets and then 100 mg microencapsulated Glycine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who meet all of the following inclusion criteria will be eligible for enrollment
        in the study:

          1. Male and female subjects aged 6-14 years with Tanner stages 0 to 3 and attentional
             and/or hyperactivity problems.

          2. Subjects with parents or a legal guardian, who will give written informed consent for
             the child to participate in the study. Additionally, assent to participate must be
             obtained from all children entering the study if the child is able to judge the
             nature, the meaning and the significance of the trial. Assent will be documented by
             the child´s signature on the consent form.

          3. Health Status: Subjects must not have clinically significant diseases or clinically
             significant abnormal laboratory values as assessed during medical history and physical
             exam.

          4. Subjects meeting minimum intelligence requirements: In the opinion of the investigator
             the subject must generally be functioning at age-appropriate levels academically,
             which should take into account any prior cognitive or academic testing (basic
             knowledge of reading, writing and calculating).

          5. Subject has an ADHD-RS-IV total score ≥18.

          6. Subjects already receiving behavioral therapies for HKS/ADHD or oppositional defiant
             disorder may continue to do sor during the course of the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. subjects with psychiatric disorders requiring current pharmacological treatment (e.g.
             major depression, psychosis)

          2. Subjects with psychiatric or somatic conditions that may contraindicate the trial or
             confound efficacy or safety assessments.

          3. Subjects with a history of drug abuse or current use of recreational drugs.

          4. History of hypersensitivity to microencapsulated Glycine or placebo.

          5. Subjects who are judged by the investigator as likely to be non-compliant with study
             procedures.

          6. Use of any investigational drugs at the time of enrollment, or within 30 days or 5
             half-lives of enrollment, whichever is longer.

          7. History of malignancy of any organ system, treated or untreated, within the past 5
             years whether or not there is evidence of local recurrence or metastases, with the
             exception of localized basal cell carcinoma of the skin.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eberhard Schulz, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Freiburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freiburg</city>
        <state>Baden-Württemberg</state>
        <zip>79104</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Freiburg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eberhard Schulz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>microencapsulated glycine</keyword>
  <keyword>attentional performance</keyword>
  <keyword>motoric activity</keyword>
  <keyword>hyperactivity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glycine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

