<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02659280</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MinneapolisMRF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02659280</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using &quot;Store and Forward&quot; Tele-health as an Adjunct to Traditional Outpatient or Home Health Physical Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>TELE</acronym>
  <official_title>Using &quot;Store and Forward&quot; Tele-health as an Adjunct to Traditional Outpatient or Home Health Physical Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Minneapolis Medical Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hennepin County Medical Center, Minneapolis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medtronic</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Minneapolis Medical Research Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will take about 3-16 months. Participants will be inpatients in the Hennepin
      Health System that are transitioning into outpatient or home health Physical Therapy or
      current outpatient patients. Investigators will assess 24 participants for eligibility based
      on the study's inclusion criteria. If eligible, Investigators will attain informed consent
      and provide instruction on how to use a coaching app, Hudl Technique, and enter data in the
      Apple Health Kit (all participants will be gifted an iPad mini 4, cover and Hudl Technique
      app). Baseline Body Mass Index (BMI) will be taken and entered in the Apple Health Kit.
      Randomization (1:1) will occur by an outside statistician. 12 patients will be allotted to
      the control group (receive traditional Outpatient PT and have access to the Apple Health Kit
      and Hudl Technique with the gifted iPad). 12 patients will be the variable group (receive
      traditional Outpatient PT, have access to the Apple Health Kit and Hudl Technique with the
      gifted iPad, and have an adjunct Home Exercise Program which will be administered via
      tele-health &quot;store and forward&quot; technology 1x/wk). There will be an 8 week assessment in
      which investigators plan to measure 1) satisfaction with PT (via survey) 2) Home Exercise
      Program (HEP) compliance (via survey) 3) incidents of ED visits or hospital admissions 4) BMI
      (via patient report with option to put it in the Apple Health Kit). There will be a 24 week
      assessment in which investigators will measure the same 4 measurements. Investigators plan on
      performing this protocol for an additional 24 participants in late 2016/early 2017 (48
      participants in total). Unfortunately, this will be a non-blinded (assessor, therapist and
      participant) study due to the nature of the intervention and how investigators received the
      funding. Casey Byron will be the Principal Investigator. Investigators would like the
      statistician to be blinded to group allocation until completion of the study (roughly
      3/11/2017).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hennepin Health System (HHS) will determine participant's eligibility in the pilot project if
      a participant meets the following stipulations; 1) The prospective participant must be an
      Hennepin Health Services outpatient or home health Physical Therapy (PT) patient. 2) The
      prospective participant's primary PT and Primary Investigator must determine that the
      participant has adequate motor control to participate in a HEP (home exercise program) on
      their own. 3) The prospective participant's primary PT and Primary Investigator must
      determine that the prospective participant has adequate cognitive ability to use electronic
      assistive technology (iPad Mini 4). The prospective participant will need to live greater
      than 100 miles from Minneapolis and/or needs to have financial hardship (as designated by
      being on Medical Assistance, Emergency Medical Assistance, Hennepin Care, Medicaid, Medical
      Assistance Cost Plan, Wavered services or have no health insurance).

      Note: The prospective participant may receive home health or outpatient PT at another
      facility other than Hennepin Health System (HHS), if they are from greater than 100 miles
      from Minneapolis (but the participant's care will need to be tied to a HHS admission).

      The tele-health will be administered in the following manner;

        1. The participant's primary PT will determine the appropriateness for this adjunct therapy
           and contact the tele-therapist/Primary Investigator, Casey Byron, MPT.

        2. Casey Byron, MPT will perform a chart review and interview the participant to determine
           if they meet eligibility requirements.

        3. Participant will sign the pilot program contract agreement, informed consent agreement
           and terms and conditions for the Hudl Technique app. The participant will be given
           information on how to operate the iPad Mini 4, how to use the Hudl Technique app and be
           given information on what to do if problems occur.

        4. The participant's primary PT will discuss the home exercise program (HEP) that they wish
           for the participant to perform with the tele-therapist.

        5. The tele-therapist will formulate an audio/video clip through Hudl Technique of the HEP
           and send it to the participant.

        6. The participant will record their performance of the HEP using the Hudl Technique app,
           iPad Mini 4 and iPad Mini 4 tripod and send their audio/video clip back to the
           tele-therapist.

        7. The video clip will be analyzed by the tele-therapist. Hudl Technique tools such as slow
           motion video, comparing two videos side by side, measuring angles, highlighting points
           of emphasis, and an audio voice over will be used to formulate a critiqued video clip.

        8. The critiqued video clip will be sent back to the participant.

        9. The participant will view the critiqued video clip and await the next video. ***There
           will be a maximum of 1 HEP per week.***

       10. The tele-health PT and participant's primary PT will correspond for updates to
           participant's HEP.

       11. The critiqued video clip will be &quot;deleted&quot; from the tele-therapists Hudl Technique
           account (HHS will not store any video clips that we generate).

      Study Parameters to be Measured:

      Participants will need to agree to data analytics of their electronic medical record (EMR).
      We will need access to information like payer source, diagnoses, address, and past and future
      emergency department and inpatient visits to the hospital. This will be performed through EMR
      review here at HHS and a survey for participants living greater than 100 miles from
      Minneapolis. The Hudl Technique app and a survey will allow for measurement of adherence to
      HEP. Participant's satisfaction with tele-health will be measured via survey (Modified
      Patient Satisfaction with Outpatient Physical Therapy Scale)1. Participants would be
      encouraged to allow the use of the Apple Health Kit. Participants would be encouraged to
      enter data in the Apple Health Kit, on a regular basis. This IOS/Apple program would allow
      for the measurement of changes that occur to a participant's body measurements (height,
      weight, and body mass index) with this adjunct therapy. The participant's use of the Apple
      Health Kit would be voluntary. Body weight measurements would also be assessed via survey.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 16, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 10, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 24, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved compliance with Physical Therapy Home Exercise Program</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will have statistically significant improvement in the frequency of performing their Home Exercise Program (HEP). This will be measured via survey with the modified Patient Satisfaction for Outpatient Physical Therapy Survey.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home Health or Outpatient Physical therapy services (a minimum of 1x/week).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adjunct Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home Health or Outpatient Physical therapy services (a minimum of 1x/week) with an adjunct Home Exercise Program given up to 1x/wk via &quot;Store and Forward&quot; tele-health through the Hudl Technique app.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adjunct Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;Store and Forward&quot; Tele-heath</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adjunct Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of Care Outpatient Physical Therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hennepin Health System (HHS) will determine participant's eligibility in the pilot
             project if a participant meets the following stipulations

          -  The prospective participant must be an HHS outpatient or home health Physical Therapy
             (PT) patient.

          -  The prospective participant's primary PT must determine that the participant has
             adequate motor control to participate in a HEP (home exercise program) on their own.

          -  The prospective participant has adequate cognitive ability to use electronic assistive
             technology (iPad Mini

          -  The prospective participant will need to live greater than 100 miles from Minneapolis
             and/or needs to have financial hardship (as designated by being on Medical Assistance,
             Emergency Medical Assistance, Hennepin Care, Medicaid, Medical Assistance Cost Plan,
             Wavered services or have no health insurance).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any participant less than the age of 18 years of age. Any participant who is pregnant
             or has reason to beleive they are pregnant,
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hennepin County Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55415</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beattie PF, Pinto MB, Nelson MK, Nelson R. Patient satisfaction with outpatient physical therapy: instrument validation. Phys Ther. 2002 Jun;82(6):557-65. Erratum in: Phys Ther 2002 Aug;82(8):827.</citation>
    <PMID>12036397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 15, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>telerehabilitation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

