<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02652611</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HP-00063838</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02652611</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sacroiliac (SI) Screws: The Effect of SI Screw Removal on Patient-Reported Pain and Functional Outcomes</brief_title>
  <acronym>SIS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Sacroiliac (SI) Screw Removal on Patient-Reported Pain and Functional Outcomes After Open or Closed Reduction and Internal Fixation of Pelvic Fractures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Maryland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic pain following surgical stabilization of a pelvic fracture is very prominent and can
      have a major affect on a patient's quality of life. Persistent pain after radiographic
      evidence of fracture union commonly leads to implant removal. But, the routine removal of
      orthopaedic fixation devices after fracture healing remains an issue of debate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Many surgeons remember patients whose intractable, hardly explainable local symptoms and
      complaints of pain resolved quickly after a hardware-removal procedure. However, implant
      removal requires a second surgical procedure in scarred tissue, poses a risk for nerve
      damage, infection and re-fractures, and is not a guarantee of pain relief.

      Rates of implant removal vary based on anatomic location and implant selection. Many studies
      have introduced and assessed the outcomes of hardware removal in the ankle, tibia and femur.
      But, there is currently no controlled trial that assesses the benefits and harms of
      sacroiliac (SI) screw removal in pelvic fracture patients.

      Reports in literature are not consistent concerning the incidence of painful hardware and the
      outcome and pain relief after hardware removal. There is conflicting evidence that removing
      hardware decreases acute pain in ankle, tibia, and femur fractures but there is a need to
      explore the effect of SI screw removal in pelvic fracture patients. The investigators propose
      to prospectively randomize patients with a pelvic fracture requiring the use of SI screws for
      stabilization to removal versus non-removal of SI screws and track which group has less pain
      and need for narcotic pain medications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain as measured by using the arithmetic mean of the four pain visual analog scale severity items on the patient-reported Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post initial SI screw stabilization</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Narcotic use as measured by the patient's medical record during follow-up clinic appointments</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post initial SI screw stabilization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Work productivity and impairment as measured by the WPAI:SHP questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post initial SI screw stabilization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life as measured by the SF-12 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post initial SI screw stabilization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pelvic specific function as measured by the Majeed Pelvic Score questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post initial SI screw stabilization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>General function as measured by the SMFA questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post initial SI screw stabilization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical-related complications as measured by the patient's medical record during follow-up clinic appointments</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months post initial SI screw stabilization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Sacroiliac Joint</condition>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Pelvis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Screw Removal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients enrolled in the SI screw removal treatment group will undergo the surgery 5-9 months after the initial SI screw stabilization surgery. The surgeon will remove all screws that he/she is able and feels is appropriate for the patient. The patient will mobilize as per the surgeon's instructions and x-rays will be taken at follow-up clinic appointments as per standard of care to determine if the injury continues healing properly. If additional surgery is required or other complications arise, this will be recorded within the study follow-up forms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-screw Removal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients enrolled in the Non-SI screw removal treatment group will not undergo surgical intervention to for removal of their SI screws. remove all screws that he/she is able and feels is appropriate for the patient. The patient will mobilize as per the surgeon's instructions and x-rays will be taken at follow-up clinic appointments as per standard of care to determine if the injury continues healing properly. If complications arise and/or the patient requires screw removal surgery, crossover will be allowed and recorded within study follow0up forms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SI Screw Removal Surgery</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Screw Removal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-screw removal treatment (non-operative management)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Non-screw Removal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient is between 18 and 80 years of age, inclusive

          -  The patient has a pelvic fracture that required SI screw stabilization

          -  The patient has reached skeletal maturity

          -  The patient's pelvic fracture was the result of trauma (includes polytraumatized
             patients)

          -  The patient is English-speaking

          -  The patient's pelvic fracture was initially treated at Shock Trauma

          -  The patient is currently experiencing pain associated with his/her pelvic fracture

          -  The patient's surgeon agrees to randomization (the patient is amendable to either SI
             screw removal or non-screw removal treatment)

          -  The patient is able to be randomized between 4 and 8 months post-SI screw
             stabilization surgery at an orthopaedic follow-up appointment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient is non-ambulatory due to an associated spinal cord injury

          -  The patient was non-ambulatory pre-injury

          -  The patient is currently pregnant

          -  The patient is enrolled in another study that does not allow co-enrollment

          -  The patient is likely to have severe problems with maintaining follow-up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcus Sciadini, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gerard Slobogean, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marcus Sciadini, MD</last_name>
    <phone>410-328-5435</phone>
    <email>msciadini@umoa.umm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Joshua Rudnicki</last_name>
    <phone>410-706-1604</phone>
    <email>jrudnicki@umoa.umm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland, Shock Trauma Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joshua Rudnicki</last_name>
      <phone>410-706-1604</phone>
      <email>jrudnicki@umoa.umm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marcus Sciadini, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-328-5435</phone>
      <email>msciadini@umoa.umm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcus Sciadini</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerard Slobogean</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert O'Toole</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobsen S, Honnens de Lichtenberg M, Jensen CM, Tørholm C. Removal of internal fixation--the effect on patients' complaints: a study of 66 cases of removal of internal fixation after malleolar fractures. Foot Ankle Int. 1994 Apr;15(4):170-1.</citation>
    <PMID>7951948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown OL, Dirschl DR, Obremskey WT. Incidence of hardware-related pain and its effect on functional outcomes after open reduction and internal fixation of ankle fractures. J Orthop Trauma. 2001 May;15(4):271-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11371792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dodenhoff RM, Dainton JN, Hutchins PM. Proximal thigh pain after femoral nailing. Causes and treatment. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1997 Sep;79(5):738-41.</citation>
    <PMID>9331026</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keating JF, Orfaly R, O'Brien PJ. Knee pain after tibial nailing. J Orthop Trauma. 1997 Jan;11(1):10-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8990026</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Court-Brown CM, Gustilo T, Shaw AD. Knee pain after intramedullary tibial nailing: its incidence, etiology, and outcome. J Orthop Trauma. 1997 Feb-Mar;11(2):103-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9057144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Busam ML, Esther RJ, Obremskey WT. Hardware removal: indications and expectations. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2006 Feb;14(2):113-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16467186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerbershagen HJ, Dagtekin O, Isenberg J, Martens N, Ozgür E, Krep H, Sabatowski R, Petzke F. Chronic pain and disability after pelvic and acetabular fractures--assessment with the Mainz Pain Staging System. J Trauma. 2010 Jul;69(1):128-36. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e3181bbd703.</citation>
    <PMID>20093984</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meyhoff CS, Thomsen CH, Rasmussen LS, Nielsen PR. High incidence of chronic pain following surgery for pelvic fracture. Clin J Pain. 2006 Feb;22(2):167-72.</citation>
    <PMID>16428951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pohlemann T, Tscherne H, Baumgärtel F, Egbers HJ, Euler E, Maurer F, Fell M, Mayr E, Quirini WW, Schlickewei W, Weinberg A. [Pelvic fractures: epidemiology, therapy and long-term outcome. Overview of the multicenter study of the Pelvis Study Group]. Unfallchirurg. 1996 Mar;99(3):160-7. German.</citation>
    <PMID>8685720</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanson B, van der Werken C, Stengel D. Surgeons' beliefs and perceptions about removal of orthopaedic implants. BMC Musculoskelet Disord. 2008 May 24;9:73. doi: 10.1186/1471-2474-9-73.</citation>
    <PMID>18501014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toms AD, Morgan-Jones RL, Spencer-Jones R. Intramedullary femoral nailing: removing the nail improves subjective outcome. Injury. 2002 Apr;33(3):247-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12084641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams AA, Witten DM, Duester R, Chou LB. The benefits of implant removal from the foot and ankle. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2012 Jul 18;94(14):1316-20. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.J.01756.</citation>
    <PMID>22810403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Maryland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marcus Sciadini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor in Orthopaedics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Screw Removal vs. Non-screw removal</keyword>
  <keyword>Complications</keyword>
  <keyword>SI Screw Stabilization</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

