<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02651805</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MIE-Palliative</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02651805</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mechanical Insufflator-exsufflator to Control Mucus Hypersecretion in Patients in Palliative Care - A Feasibility Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mechanical Insufflator-exsufflator to Manage Respiratory Secretion in Patients in Palliative Care - A Feasibility Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Estadual Américo Brasiliense</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Philips Respironics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with advanced chronic diseases may suffer with respiratory secretion and available
      therapies to control this condition are uncomfortable or little effective in palliative care
      patients. Therefore, alternative therapies should be tested, assessing clinically relevant
      outcomes in palliative care, such as comfort during therapy and the number of interventions
      required in a day. Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation is an option that presents
      advantages, since it can be used in patients with minimum cooperation and is non-invasive,
      which may lead to higher comfort during therapy.

      The aim of the study is to verify the feasibility of a clinical trial comparing the effects
      of Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation with usual care in hospitalized palliative care
      patients that are suffering with respiratory secretion. Patients allocation will follow a
      &quot;fast-track allocation design&quot;, in which included patients will be randomized in two groups:

        1. Receive Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation therapy in the moment that is assigned to
           this group;

        2. will receive 24h of usual care and after that will be allowed to choose between usual
           care or Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation Therapy.

      The assessments will be: Time from the first intervention until the need of a following
      intervention, discomfort due therapy, discomfort due respiratory secretion, palliative
      outcome scale, number of adverse events and number of interventions during 24h period. The
      primary outcome is to verify the feasibility of developing a future larger clinical trial to
      assess the effects of the use of Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation to control respiratory
      secretions in patients in palliative care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Investigators will conduct a feasibility study for a future fast track randomized trial,
      which will be carried out in the Américo Brasiliense State Hospital and conducted by the
      Spirometry and Respiratory Physiotherapy Laboratory from the Federal University of São
      Carlos, Brazil.

      The concept of feasibility is defined as &quot;capable of being done or carried out&quot; and studies
      which aim is to verify the feasibility intends to verify if a larger clinical trial would
      have a acceptable probability of success in proving the efficacy of an intervention 24. The
      importance of feasibility studies has been discussed since health research resources are
      frequently wasted in large clinical trials with interventions with small impact, studies with
      insufficient power, or even using measures and outcomes that do not reflect the expected
      changes caused by the interventions. Furthermore, these studies are essential when dealing
      with populations that usually lead to an increased chance of losing the follow-up or a high
      number of missing data, such as palliative care.

      Both groups will receive the therapy with the mechanical insufflators-exsufflator, however,
      the Mechanical insufflation-exsufflation group will receive it as in a fast track way, while
      the usual care, will receive the usual care for more 24 hours, and then they will receive one
      session of Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation. After this 24 hours period, the patients
      will be asked what therapy they would like to receive each time they need help to deal with
      hypersecretion until the end of the hospitalization, or until the physician responsible for
      the patient consider the hypersecretion was controlled.

      The allocation through fast track has been used due to ethical reasons, in order to maintain
      the randomized and controlled aspects of the research, and yet provide the opportunity to all
      patients to be benefited of the new intervention before the end of the study. Furthermore, an
      increase in the acceptability and retention of the participants is expected, since they are
      going to receive the new therapy in some moment of the study, which may be during or after
      the follow-up 28. The cross-over design was not chosen, since the wash-out period necessary
      to this model of study might lead to a period without treatment for vulnerable patients, with
      expected short life time.

      Usual Care The patients will receive the treatment according to the hospital protocol to deal
      with hypersecretive patients (suctioning that can be preceded by respiratory physiotherapy
      and nebulisation). A trained member of the nurse staff or a physiotherapist will be
      responsible for providing the therapy. A member of the research team will collect in the
      patients' records all the therapies provided by the staff to control hypersecretions.

      Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation The settings used in the Mechanical
      Insufflator-Exsufflator will be the same of a previous study, where were used: six assisted
      cough cycles with pressures of 40 to -40cmH2O; the inspiratory time of 3s; the expiratory
      time 4s and a pause between cycles of 4s. The patients will be instructed to cough alongside
      the exsufflation phase, with exception of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease patients
      which will be instructed to exhale slowly. An oral-nasal mask will be used as interface, but
      in patients with tracheotomy, the device will be connected to it.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Study Feasibility assessed by verifying the recruitment rates, acceptability of the patients and hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>Through the completion of the study, up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>The feasibility of the study will be the primary outcome, and it will be assessed by verifying the recruitment rates, acceptability of the patients and hospital, and if the assessments were suitable to the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (Safety and Tolerability)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed in the period between the start of the intervention until 30min after the end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by the number of times an event with change in physiological parameters occurred during the intervention (Heart Rate&gt;150bpm or &lt;50bpm; Systolic Blood Pressure&gt;200mmHg or &lt;80mmHg; decrease of 5% or higher in the pulse oxymetry; hemoptysis).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect size of Palliative Outcome Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after the inclusion and in the final assessment (24 hours after the inclusion).</time_frame>
    <description>This is a quality of life multidimensional scale in patients in palliative care. With this scale, we intend to see the effects of the therapy over the general perceived health of the patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect size of discomfort due to the hypersecretion</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately before the first intervention and ten minutes after the first intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using a numeric scale (0-10). This assessment will be conducted in order to evaluate how much the hypersecretion bothers the patient, and if the therapy is capable of changing this perception of discomfort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect size of discomfort due to the therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Ten minutes after the first intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using a numeric scale (0-10), this assessment will provide information to the decision of the viability the therapy in palliative care, since uncomfortable therapies are often discouraged since usually they may not cure the cause of the problem.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect size of time until the next intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>In the end of the 24 hours period.</time_frame>
    <description>The moment immediately after the first intervention until the time a new intervention is required. It will be verified in the patient's records. The therapies to control hypersecretions may lead to discomfort due to the stimulation of the cough and the change in the respiratory pattern, a therapy with a more lasting effect may be preferable, since it can provide a longer period without the discomfort of another intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect size of number of interventions during 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>In the end of the 24 hours period</time_frame>
    <description>The number of interventions will be verified in the patient's records. Therapies that may lead to a lasting effect, can be performed less times during a day, this reflects in a longer period of comfort, and smaller health expenses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients using pharmacological agents to control respiratory secretions</measure>
    <time_frame>In the completion of the study, an average of one year</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's chart will be revised to verify the percentage of patients that received pharmacological interventions to control respiratory secretions, prescribed by the hospital team.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Palliative Care</condition>
  <condition>Mucus Hypersecretion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive usual care except suctioning or cough augmentation techniques+Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive the usual care provided by the hospital, all interventions to control respiratory secretion will be verified in patient chart</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation</intervention_name>
    <description>Mechanical Insufflator-Exsufflator (MI-E): 6 assisted cough with expiratory pressure of -40cmH2O and inspiratory pressure defined by the therapist as the maximum pressure defined as comfortable; inspiratory time 3s and expiratory time 4s, using a manual cycle. Patients will be instructed to cough during exsufflation phase, with exception of Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease patients which will be instructed to exhale slowly. An oral-nasal mask will be used as interface, but in patients with tracheotomy, the device will be connected to it. A trained physiotherapist will conduct the therapy. During the night and weekends, patients will not start this therapy, however, if they have already started the therapy in MI-E group, or if they have already finished the period of follow-up they will be able to request this therapy, which will be provided by hospital staff . The equipment (Cough Assist®, Respironics, Phillips), will be available in the ward for the interventions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mechanical Insufflation-Exsufflation Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cough Assist (Philips Respironics)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients will receive the treatment according to the hospital protocol to deal with hypersecretive patients (suctioning that can be preceded by respiratory physiotherapy and nebulisation). A trained member of the nurse staff or a physiotherapist will be responsible for providing the therapy. A member of the research team will collect in the patients' records all the therapies provided by the staff to control hypersecretions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Prognosis:

               -  Less than one year assessed by the responsible physician, with a negative answer
                  of the to the &quot;surprise question&quot; - Would you be surprised if this patient died
                  in the following year?

               -  Higher than 3 months, assessed by the same physician

          -  Patients with problems to deal with secretions, which could be one or both of the
             following problems:

               -  Hypersecretion

               -  Cough inefficiency (peak cough flow &lt;250L/min)

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status Scale higher or equal to 30%;

          -  Ability to give written informed consent or presence of a person who is responsable
             for the patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with conditions considered as contra-indication for the use of Mechanical
             Insufflator-Exsufflator:

               -  Bullous emphysema history

               -  Known susceptibility for pneumothorax or pneumo-mediastinum

               -  Known to have had any recent barotrauma.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Juliano F Arcuri, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+55 16 33518343</phone>
    <email>julianoarcuri@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Valéria AP Di Lorenzo, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+55 16 33518343</phone>
    <email>vallorenzo@ufscar.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Estadual Américo Brasiliense</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Carlos</city>
        <state>São Paulo</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Juliano F Arcuri, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+55 16 33518343</phone>
      <email>julianoarcuri@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach JR. Mechanical insufflation-exsufflation. Comparison of peak expiratory flows with manually assisted and unassisted coughing techniques. Chest. 1993 Nov;104(5):1553-62.</citation>
    <PMID>8222823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach JR. Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis: prolongation of life by noninvasive respiratory AIDS. Chest. 2002 Jul;122(1):92-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12114343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Juliano Ferreira Arcuri</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD Student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Palliative Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory Secretion</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

