<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02656550</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>015-158</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02656550</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Uterine Transplantation and Pregnancy Induction in Women Affected by Absolute Uterine Infertility</brief_title>
  <official_title>Uterine Transplantation and Pregnancy Induction in Women Affected by Absolute Uterine Factor Infertility</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to investigate the treatment of absolute uterine infertility (AUI) due to
      congenital or surgical absence of a uterus or presence of a nonfunctioning uterus. The
      investigators will follow a model based on a Swedish study to enroll 10 women with
      functioning ovaries and successfully transplant the uterus from either a living or cadaveric
      donor, with the goal of live birth after transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION

      Absolute Uterine Factor Infertility (AUI) is due to congenital or surgical absence of a
      uterus or presence of a nonfunctional uterus. Until 2014 the only option for women affected
      by Absolute Uterine Factor Infertility (AUI) was adoption or surrogate motherhood.

      Primary Objective

        -  Successful living or deceased donor uterine transplants resulting in live birth.

        -  Pregnancy rate via in vitro fertilization.

      BACKGROUND

      In 1991 the National Transplantation Pregnancy Registry (NTPR) was established to study the
      outcomes of female transplant recipients. In 2010 the NTPR had collected data on 2000
      pregnancy outcomes. The NTRP database includes data not just on the pregnancy but on
      follow-up of both parents and their offspring. The first reported case of pregnancy after
      transplant was reported in 1958.

      In 2011 25,787 solid organ transplant recipients (kidney, liver, pancreas, small bowel, heart
      &amp; lung) of which:

        -  9662 were women

        -  3505 were of childbearing age

        -  765 were less than 17 years old and could potentially become pregnant later in life.

      One of the benefits of receiving a kidney, liver, pancreas, small bowel, heart or lung
      transplant is the underlying disease that caused the subject to have a transplant is gone,
      therefore fertility returns. Pregnancy after transplant is increasingly common. This has led
      to an accumulation of data and knowledge on how to best manage this subject population. These
      pregnancies are still considered high-risk. Successful pregnancy outcomes are a result of
      transplant and obstetrics teams working closely together.

      The American Society of Transplantation (AST) recommends for solid organs that pregnancy is
      allowable if there has been: no rejection within the past year, there is adequate and stable
      graft function, no acute infections that may impact fetal growth and well-being and
      maintenance immunosuppression is at stable dosing. Both the NTPR and AST advise waiting one
      year until after transplant before conceiving. This one year wait time is associated with
      better maternal and neonatal outcomes and fewer obstetric complications.Based on the long
      term data from the NPTR on transplant recipient's pregnancy outcomes and the relative safety
      of immunosuppressive medications a new area of transplant is being developed. Uterine
      transplant may provide an additional option for women with absolute uterine infertility
      (AUI).

      Pre-clinical research into uterine transplant has been going on for more than a decade. There
      have been several studies demonstrating the feasibility of Uterine Transplantation in
      animals, both primates and non-primates. In the last year human trials have started in
      Europe.

      RATIONALE

      In Great Britain an estimated 12000 women of childbearing age are affected by AUI. In the US
      the number of women affected by AUI may be in the millions considering that 9 million women
      of reproductive age have had a hysterectomy.

      Congenital absence of the Uterus has been reported in 1/5000 women and in 2005 over 12000
      women in reproductive age,15 years to 44 years have been diagnosed with congenital absence of
      the Uterus.

      In the US, 1000 hysterectomies are performed immediately post-partum for every 1 million
      births.

      It is estimated that 62 million women in the United States are in the reproductive age and
      about 15.4% may have absolute AUI, and about 7 million women may have lost their uterus to
      benign causes or obstetric complications. Although the statistics may offer different
      interpretation it seems evident that thousands of women in the United States may be
      interested in considering Uterine Transplantation as their best option to have children.

      Previous Subject Experience

      There were two reported attempts at uterine transplantation at other institutions, one of
      which was able to carry two pregnancies but not at term. However, the University of
      Gothenburg reported the first clinical trial of Uterine Transplantation as nouvelle treatment
      for AUI.

      In this report 9 living donors and 9 recipients underwent donor hysterectomies and recipient
      uterine transplantation. Seven out of the 9 had viable uteri at the time of the report with 1
      recipient losing the transplanted uterus to an infection and the other one to a vascular
      complication. One donor suffered a surgical grade IIIb complication, an ureterovaginal
      fistula, and was successfully treated.

      This early report was followed by a subsequent one where the 7 recipients showed regular
      menses and 5 out of the seven recipient suffered mild rejection episodes that were all
      successfully treated.

      The feasibility of Uterine Transplantation as a cure to AUI was finally demonstrated by the
      first live birth after uterus transplantation.

      The surgeries have been described by the Gothenburg University Group consist of a total
      abdominal hysterectomy and upper vaginectomy with preservation of the major feeding arteries
      and veins to the uterus of the donor and the implantation of the uterus in the pelvis of the
      recipient. Vascular anastomosis is achieved between the two major arteries and veins of the
      uterus, extending to the external iliac vessels of the recipient using transplant
      microvascular techniques. Finally the vaginal rim of the transplanted uterus is anastomosed
      to the recipient's vaginal vault.

      The procedure can be performed also with a uterus obtained from a deceased donor. The
      hysterectomy in the deceased donor will proceed as described above. The advantage will be
      obtaining the vascular pedicle attached to segments of the iliac artery and vein which will
      make the implantation in the recipient technically easier. The preservation solution will not
      change and the ischemia time will be kept under 6 hours.

      2. STUDY DESIGN This is a prospective study to treat absolute uterine infertility (AUI)
      through uterine transplantation resulting in live birth.

      There will be five distinct clinical stages in the study after inclusion/exclusion met
      criteria &amp; subject consented: Pre-transplant/Screening, Transplant/Recovery, embryo
      transfer/Pregnancy, Delivery/Explant, Follow up.

      Number of Clinical Sites and Subjects This trial will be conducted at the Annette C. and
      Harold C. Simmons Transplant Institute, Baylor University Medical Center in Dallas, TX. A
      total of 10 female (biologically) subjects will receive a uterine transplant. Subjects can
      either receive a uterus from a living donor or a cadaveric donor. Living donors will be
      consented per the living donor research protocol. Uterus recovery from cadaveric donors will
      follow UNOS guidelines.

      SUBJECT PARTICIPATION and STUDY DURATION

      All subjects will be followed for a 5 year period post-transplant. Continued follow up
      depends upon the subject status:

        -  Subjects who received a uterine transplant resulting in live birth then and have the
           uterus removed will be followed for 12 months post explant.

        -  Subjects who received a uterine transplant resulting in live birth and desire another
           pregnancy will be followed through the second pregnancy resulting in live birth for 12
           months post explant.

        -  Subjects who have the uterus explanted due to infection, rejection or unable to maintain
           pregnancy will be followed for 12 months post explant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 11, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of successful live births after uterine transplant and IVF.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Full term birth by cesarean section.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Absolute Uterine Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Uterine Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will undergo uterine transplantation after IVF. Donor uterus will be from either a living donor or cadaveric.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Uterine Transplant</intervention_name>
    <description>Transplant of a uterus from either a living donor or a deceased donor.,</description>
    <arm_group_label>Uterine Transplant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Thymoglobulin</other_name>
    <other_name>Mycophenolate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women diagnosed with Absolute Uterine Infertility (AUI) and intact native ovaries.

          2. Women of childbearing age 20-35.

          3. Human papillomarvius negative or received vaccination for human papillomarvius virus
             (HPV). Subjects with a history of HPV in the past must show a negative history since
             and test negative at screening.

          4. A subject who is negative for Gonorrhea, Chlamydia and Syphilis.

          5. A subject with the history of Herpes (HSV-2) with no current symptoms. Subject may
             require preventative maintenance per study doctor discretion.

          6. Subjects have received counseling regarding infertility alternatives to uterine
             transplant such as adoption or surrogate pregnancy.

          7. Willing to undergo in-vitro fertilization and medically cleared for in-vitro
             fertilization.

          8. Evaluated by a fertility specialist and determined to have good ovarian reproductive
             potential and ability to carry fetus to term.

          9. Must have the ability to fund, either through third party coverage or through other
             their own personal financing, any expenses associated with assisted reproduction
             services provided to them.

         10. Meets physiological recipient criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject with Diabetes Mellitus Type I and II by medical history or elevated hemoglobin
             A1c blood test.

          2. Subject has known hypersensitivity to Tacrolimus, Thymoglobulin or CellCept.

          3. Subject with existing hypertension, per investigator's discretion.

          4. Subject who has a history of solid organ or bone marrow transplant.

          5. Subject who has history of cancer in last five years.

          6. Subject with a body mass index &gt;30.

          7. Subject with an active infection.

          8. Subject who is seropositive for HIV, HBV, HCV

          9. Subject with technical obstacles as per anatomical malformations, which pose a high
             surgical risk in the judgment of the investigator.

         10. Subject unwilling or unable to comply with study requirements.

         11. Subject unable to undergo in-vitro fertilization or not cleared for transplant.

         12. Subject who has smoked within the last 12 months.

         13. Subject who has alcohol or drug abuse within 12 months of screening.

         14. Subject with any pre-existing clinical or medical conditions that would pose the
             subject at an increased risk, as per the investigator's discretion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Giuliano Testa, MD</last_name>
    <phone>214-880-2050</phone>
    <email>Giuliano.Testa@BSWHealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristin P Wallis, BSN, RNC-OB</last_name>
    <phone>214-818-7703</phone>
    <email>kristin.wallis@BSWHealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giuliano Testa, MD FACS MBA</last_name>
      <phone>214-820-2050</phone>
      <email>Giuliano.Testa@BSWHealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Wallis P Kristin, BSN, RNC-OB</last_name>
      <phone>214-818-7703</phone>
      <email>Kristin.Wallis@BSWHealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brännström M. Uterus transplantation. Curr Opin Organ Transplant. 2015 Dec;20(6):621-8. doi: 10.1097/MOT.0000000000000246. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26536423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brännström M, Johannesson L, Dahm-Kähler P, Enskog A, Mölne J, Kvarnström N, Diaz-Garcia C, Hanafy A, Lundmark C, Marcickiewicz J, Gäbel M, Groth K, Akouri R, Eklind S, Holgersson J, Tzakis A, Olausson M. First clinical uterus transplantation trial: a six-month report. Fertil Steril. 2014 May;101(5):1228-36. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2014.02.024. Epub 2014 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24582522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johannesson L, Kvarnström N, Mölne J, Dahm-Kähler P, Enskog A, Diaz-Garcia C, Olausson M, Brännström M. Uterus transplantation trial: 1-year outcome. Fertil Steril. 2015 Jan;103(1):199-204. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2014.09.024. Epub 2014 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>25439846</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brännström M, Johannesson L, Bokström H, Kvarnström N, Mölne J, Dahm-Kähler P, Enskog A, Milenkovic M, Ekberg J, Diaz-Garcia C, Gäbel M, Hanafy A, Hagberg H, Olausson M, Nilsson L. Livebirth after uterus transplantation. Lancet. 2015 Feb 14;385(9968):607-616. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61728-1. Epub 2014 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25301505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Louden, K. (2009). Pregnancy After Transplantation: Improving Outcomes Through Counseling, Closed Management, and Research. Nephrology Times, 2(2), 11-13</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mann, W., Goff, B., Falk, S. et. al (2015). Radical Hysterectomy. UpToDate, 3303 (9).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mukherjee, S. &amp; Shapiro, R, et. al. (2011). Transplantation and Pregnancy. Kidney, 716, 1097.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Uterine Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>AUI</keyword>
  <keyword>Rokitansky Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thymoglobulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

