<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01653041</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRAD001ABR26T</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01653041</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Certican (Everolimus) for Recipients of Kidney From HLA-identical Living Donors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Certican (Everolimus) for Recipients of Kidney From HLA-identical Living Donors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital do Rim e Hipertensão</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital do Rim e Hipertensão</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recipients from living donors kidneys HLA-identical were lower risk for acute rejection,
      graft loss or death. There is no clear definition of what is ideal immunosuppressive regimen
      for this population.

      Everolimus (EVR) was associated with lower incidence of viral infections and also the lowest
      incidence of neoplasms. Furthermore, immunosuppressive regimens based everolimus allow the
      reduction or elimination of calcineurin inhibitors reducing cardiovascular risks associated
      with chronic use of these agents. Moreover, the use of EVR is associated with increased
      incidence of proteinuria, which associated mechanism has not been fully elucidated. Knowing
      that proteinuria may be the first indication of recurrence of the underlying renal disease,
      detailed information about the patient's medical history and histological analysis of the
      graft may contribute with additional knowledge in this area.

      The aim of this prospective, open, single arm study that will be performed only in the
      Hospital do Rim e Hipertensão, is investigating the outcomes of kidney transplantation in
      recipients of HLA identical living donor, receiving an everolimus-based immunosuppressive
      regimen. This will include 100 recipients of first or second kidney transplant from a living
      donor HLA identical to the Kidney and Hypertension Hospital, which will be followed by a
      period of 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy compound outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of treatment failure, defined as the first occurrence of biopsy confirmed acute rejection, graft loss, death, or treatment discontinuation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>acute rejection, allograft and patient survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Acute rejection Type of acute rejection: clinical acute rejection; biopsy confirmed acute rejection; Timing of acute rejection; Severity of acute rejection, based on Banff 2007 classification; Treatment modality: steroids; polyclonal antibodies; change in immunosuppressive regimen Outcome: resolved; partially resolved; graft loss Allograft Renal function measured by creatinine and calculated creatinine clearance (MDRD formula); proteinuria including microalbuminuria and urinary protein- creatinine ratio; histology at month 12, including optic, fluorescence and electronic microscopy; graft loss, including incidence and cause.
Patient Cardiovascular safety: blood pressure; glucose metabolism; lipids profile;Infections: site of infection, microorganism and treatment; everolimus related adverse reaction: event, time of transplant and outcome; malignancies: type, time of transplant and outcome; death, including incidence and causes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory evaluations</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>At some study visits will be obtained blood and urine samples for exploratory analyzes on immune tolerance, biomarkers such as CD30 and FOXP3 and genetic polymorphism of enzymes and transporters targets of immunosuppressants used. For crossmatch cell will be used cells derived from peripheral blood of the donor as a stimulus to cells in vitro receptor.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplantation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Everolimus</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult candidates of first or repeat kidney transplant HLA identical living donors;

          2. Patient who signed the informed consent form to participate in this study;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients were excluded if they had been receiving immunosuppressive therapy before
             transplantation;

          2. Patients who received an investigational medication within the past 12 months;

          3. Patients with suspected or known to have an infection or were seropositive for
             hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), antibody against hepatitis B core antigen
             (anti-HBcAg), hepatitis C virus (HCV), or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV);

          4. Patient who had had cancer (except nonmelanoma skin cancer) within the previous 2
             years.

          5. Pregnant women, nursing mothers, and women of childbearing potential who were not
             using condoms or oral contraceptives were excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital do Rim e Hipertensão</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <zip>04038-002</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 30, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital do Rim e Hipertensão</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Helio Tedesco Silva Junior</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>immunosuppression, identical HLA, kidney transplantation, everolimus</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

