<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01653483</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>116213</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01653483</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Aura Adolescent PK Study GSK2829332</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Repeat Dose, 2-period Incomplete Block Crossover Safety and Pharmacokinetic Study of Umeclidinium in Adolescent Asthma Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, repeat dose, 2-period, incomplete
      block, crossover, safety and pharmacokinetic (PK) study to evaluate 3 once-daily doses of
      umeclidinium (GSK573719; UMEC) in adolescent asthma subjects aged 12 through 17 years,) who
      are currently using asthma medications that do not contain inhaled corticosteroids (non-ICS).
      The objectives are to investigate safety and tolerability, and PK after a 7-day (+2) repeat
      once-daily dose of UMEC (15.6, 62.5, and 250 mcg) in asthmatic adolescent subjects. Safety
      endpoints will include reported adverse events, vital signs, ECGs, clinical laboratory tests,
      and rescue albuterol use. The PK endpoints will include serial PK (plasma and urine)
      concentrations and derived parameters.

      Twenty four subjects will be randomized to participate in the study for up to 7 weeks
      (including: an initial screening visit, a 7 to 14-day run-in, and 2 treatment periods each of
      7 (+2) day duration, with a washout period of 7-14 days between treatment periods). There
      will be a Follow-up Visit approximately one week after the end of the second treatment
      period. Subjects will refrain from using rescue medication for 4 hours prior to any clinic
      visits, unless for emergency.

      During each treatment period, study medication will be taken once in the morning until the
      morning of Day 7 (+2 days) when subjects will return to the clinic for study assessments and
      take the last dose of study medication. On Day 7 (+2), subjects will remain in the clinic
      overnight for serial assessments (ECG, and PK plasma and urine samples over the 24-hours).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, repeat dose, 2-period, incomplete
      block, crossover, safety and pharmacokinetic (PK) study to evaluate 3 once-daily doses of
      umeclidinium (UMEC) in adolescent asthma subjects aged 12 through 17 years,) who are
      currently using asthma medications that do not contain inhaled corticosteroids (non-ICS). The
      objectives are to investigate safety and tolerability, and PK after a 7-day (+2) repeat
      once-daily dose of UMEC (15.6, 62.5, and 250 mcg) in asthmatic adolescent subjects. Safety
      endpoints will include reported adverse events, vital signs, ECGs, clinical laboratory tests,
      and rescue albuterol use. The PK endpoints will include serial PK (plasma and urine)
      concentrations and derived parameters.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    FDA advised that study is no longer required
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject safety as measured by serial ECGs and vital signs measured on Days 7 of each treatment period and the number (and frequency) of subjects who experience adverse events after repeat doses of GSK573719</measure>
    <time_frame>Through the expected 7 day duration for each of 2 treatment periods.</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of safety and tolerability, including: reported adverse events, clinical laboratory measurements, vital signs (heart rate and blood pressure), and electrocardiographic (ECG) parameters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject safety as measured by ECGs and vital signs measures on Day 1 of each treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>Through the expected 6 hour duration of in clinic stay</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of safety and tolerability, including: vital signs (heart rate and blood pressure), and electrocardiographic (ECG) parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters such as Cmax, AUC, half-life, Tmax of GSK573719 after repeat dosing.</measure>
    <time_frame>predose, 5, 15 and 30 minutes and, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 24, hours on Day 7 of dosing</time_frame>
    <description>To characterise the PK profile of repeat doses of GSK573719 in adolescent asthmatic subjects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GSK573719</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigational treatment - Swedish Orange Coloured, opaque hard gelatin capsule</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GSK573719 matched-placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK573719</intervention_name>
    <description>Novel Dry-Powder Inhaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK573719 matched-placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>umeclidinium</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK573719matched-placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Novel Dry-Powder Inhaler</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK573719</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Demographic Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed consent: At least one parent/guardian has signed and dated the written
             informed consent prior to admission to the study. This will be accompanied by informed
             assent from the subject for children aged 12 through 17 years.

          -  Type of Subject: Outpatients. However subjects will remain in the clinic overnight at
             the end of each treatment period for serial safety and PK blood and urine assessments
             over a 24-hour period.

          -  Age: subjects aged 12 through 17 years (inclusive) at Visit 1 (a subject may not
             participate if the subject's 18th birthday would occur during the conduct of the
             study). Note: The study population will include an adequate representation of subjects
             throughout the ages of 12 to 17 years with at least 4 subjects 12 or 13 years of age
             and no more than 4 subjects 16 or 17 years of age.

          -  Weight: Subjects must weigh at least 32kg.

          -  Male or Eligible Female. Eligible being defined as of non-childbearing potential or
             childbearing potential using an acceptable method of birth control consistently and
             correctly. Note: To be eligible for entry into the study, females of childbearing
             potential must commit to consistent and correct use of an acceptable method of birth
             control, as defined below: Females of childbearing potential who are not sexually
             active must commit to complete abstinence from intercourse throughout the clinical
             trial and for a period after the trial to account for elimination of the drug (minimum
             of 6 days); Male partner who is sterile prior to the female subject's entry into the
             study and is the sole sexual partner for that female subject; Implants of
             levonorgestrel or etonogestrel; Injectable progestogen; Oral contraceptive (either
             combined or progestogen alone); Estrogenic vaginal ring; Percutaneous contraceptive
             patches; Any intrauterine device (IUD) with a documented failure rate of less than 1%
             per year; Male condom combined with a vaginal spermicide (foam, gel, film, cream, or
             suppository); Male condom combined with a female diaphragm, either with or without a
             vaginal spermicide (foam, gel, film, cream, or suppository); Contraceptive transdermal
             patch, Ortho Evra (if the subject is less than 198 pounds [90kg]); Female subjects
             should not be enrolled if they are pregnant or lactating or if they plan to become
             pregnant during the time of study participation. A serum pregnancy test is required of
             all females and will be performed at the initial screening visit (Visit 1). In
             addition, a urine pregnancy test will be performed as in the Table of Time and Events.

          -  Understand protocol requirements: The subject and parent/guardian are able to
             understand and comply with protocol requirements, instructions, and protocol stated
             restrictions. The parent or guardian must have the ability to read, write, and record
             diary information collected throughout the study. The parent or guardian must have the
             ability to manage study drug administration.

        Asthma-Related Diagnostic Inclusion Criteria

          -  Diagnosis: diagnosis of asthma as defined by the National Institutes of Health [NIH,
             2007] at least 6 months prior to Visit 1.

          -  Severity of Disease: A best pre-bronchodilator AM FEV1 of greater than and equal to
             80% of the predicted normal value at the Visit 1 (screening) visit. Percent predicted
             normal values will be based upon: NHANES III (Hankinson, 1999) for the primary
             race/ethnicity of the subject (e.g Mexican-American, African-American/African
             heritage, Caucasian); Multiethnic spirometric assessments (Hankinson, 2010) for the
             primary race/ethnicity of the subject (e.g Asian).

          -  Current Anti-Asthma Therapy: Subjects must demonstrate a need for use of a
             non-corticosteroid medication as shown by having or received a prescription for either
             of the following for greater than and equal to 12 weeks preceding Visit 1 (and with no
             ICS used for at least 12 weeks prior to screening): a non-corticosteroid controller
             (e.g., theophylline, cromolyn, nedocromil, leukotriene modifiers [e.g. montelukast,
             zafirlukast], etc.), with or without SABA; a SABA bronchodilator such as albuterol.

          -  Short-Acting Beta2-Agonists (SABAs): All subjects must be able to replace their
             current SABA treatment with albuterol aerosol inhaler at Visit 1, as needed, for the
             duration of the study. Subjects must be judged capable of withholding albuterol for at
             least 4 hours prior to study visits.

        Demographic Exclusion Criteria

          -  Tobacco Use: A subject may not have used inhaled tobacco products (i.e., cigarettes,
             cigars, or pipe tobacco) or have historical use of tobacco products. Includes, urinary
             cotinine or CO breath test levels at screening that is indicative of smoking or
             history or regular use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products within 6 months
             prior to screening.

          -  Previous Use of Study Drug or Investigational Products: Previous use of UMEC excludes
             a subject or the subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an
             investigational product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day
             in the current study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological
             effect of the investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Compliance: A subject will not be eligible if he/she or his/her parent or legal
             guardian has any infirmity, disability, disease, or geographical location which seems
             likely (in the opinion of the investigator) to impair compliance with any aspect of
             this study protocol, including visit schedule and completion of the daily diaries.

          -  Alcohol or substance abuse: Subjects with any history of alcohol use or substance
             abuse prior to screening, or use of, at any time during the study.

          -  Viral Hepatitis: A positive Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C
             antibody pre-study or at Visit 1.

          -  Wards of State: Children who are wards of the state or government.

          -  Affiliation with Investigator's Site: A subject will not be eligible for this study if
             he/she is an immediate family member of the participating investigator,
             sub-investigator, study coordinator, or employee of the participating investigator.

          -  Pregnancy: Pregnant females as determined by positive serum hCG test at screening or
             prior to dosing.

          -  Lactation: Lactating females.

        Asthma-Related Exclusion Criteria

          -  History of Life-threatening asthma: Defined for this protocol as an asthma episode
             that required intubation and/or was associated with hypercapnea requiring non-invasive
             ventilator support, respiratory arrest, hypoxic seizures or asthma-related syncopal
             episode(s).

          -  Asthma Exacerbation: A subject must not have a history of a severe asthma exacerbation
             within 12 weeks prior to Visit 1. A severe asthma exacerbation is defined as
             deterioration of asthma requiring the use of systemic corticosteroids (oral, or
             injection) for at least 3 days or an inpatient hospitalization or emergency department
             visit due to asthma that required systemic corticosteroids.

          -  Signs or symptoms of unstable asthma: Defined as: During the 7 days immediately
             preceding a visit, at least 3 days in which greater than and equal to 12
             inhalations/day of albuterol/salbutamol were used; or A symptom score of greater than
             and equal to 4 on at least 3 consecutive days during the previous 7 days (defined as
             the subject experiencing symptoms for most of the day which affected normal daily
             activities); or at the discretion of the Investigator

          -  Respiratory Infection expected to affect the subject's ability to participate in the
             study: Within 4 weeks prior to Visit 1 a subject has had a culture-documented or
             suspected bacterial or viral infection of the upper or lower respiratory tract, sinus
             or middle ear that is not resolved and has led to a change in asthma management or, in
             the opinion of the Investigator, is expected to affect the subject's asthma status or
             the subject's ability to participate in the study.

          -  Concurrent Respiratory Disease: A subject must not have current evidence of pneumonia,
             pneumothorax, atelectasis, pulmonary fibrotic disease, bronchopulmonary dysplasia,
             chronic bronchitis, emphysema, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, or other
             respiratory abnormalities other than asthma.

          -  Diseases Preventing Use of Anticholinergics: Diagnosis of narrow-angle glaucoma, or
             bladder neck obstruction that in the opinion of the study investigator or GSK medical
             monitor would pose a safety risk with use of an inhaled anticholinergic.

          -  Other Concurrent Diseases/Abnormalities: A subject must not have any clinically
             significant, uncontrolled condition or disease state that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would put the safety of the patient at risk through study participation
             if the condition/disease exacerbated during the study. The investigator is encouraged
             to contact the study medical monitor if further clarification is warranted.

        Safety Exclusion Criteria

          -  Liver Function: ALT greater than and equal to 2xULN; alkaline phosphatase and
             bilirubin greater than and equal to 1.5xULN (isolated bilirubin less than 1.5xULN is
             acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin less than 35%).

          -  Average QTcF greater than 450 msec.

          -  Allergies: Drug Allergy - Any adverse reaction including immediate or delayed
             hypersensitivity to any beta-agonist, or sympathomimetic drug. Known or suspected
             sensitivity to the constituents of the NDPI (i.e., lactose).

          -  Previous Clinical Trials: Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12
             months prior to the first dosing day.

          -  Concomitant Medication or Treatments: Administration of prescription or
             over-the-counter medication that would significantly affect the course of asthma, or
             interact with study drug, such as:: Medication: Mucolytics such as acetylcysteine;
             beta -blocker eye drops ( e.g. use in glaucoma symptoms treatment) or systemic
             beta-adrenergic blocking agents; No use within the following time interval before
             Visit 1: 12 weeks. Medication: Inhaled short-acting beta2-agonists (rescue use
             albuterol is permitted during the study); No use within the following time interval
             before Visit 1: 4 hours (including all study visits). Medication: Short acting
             anticholinergics; No use within the following time interval before Visit 1: 6 hours.
             Medication: Long and short acting oral beta2-agonists; No use within the following
             time interval before Visit 1: 24 hours. Medication: Long acting anticholinergics or
             antimuscarinics; No use within the following time interval before Visit 1: 14 days.
             Medication: Systemic, depot, or oral corticosteroids; No use within the following time
             interval before Visit 1: 4 weeks. Medication: Inhaled corticosteroids (ICS); No use
             within the following time interval before Visit 1: 12 weeks. Medication: Inhaled
             long-acting beta2-agonists (e.g. salmeterol, formoterol, indacaterol) including
             long-acting beta2-agonists combined with an ICS (e.g. Advair, seretide); No use within
             the following time interval before Visit 1: 4 weeks. Medication: Immunosuppressive
             medications (e.g., methotrexate, gold, or dapsone) including immunomodulators
             (Immunotherapy for the treatment of allergies is allowed during the study provided it
             was initiated at least 4 weeks prior to Visit 1 and the subject remains in the
             maintenance phase throughout the study); No use within the following time interval
             before Visit 1: 12 weeks. Medication: Monoclonal antibody: Anti-IgE, or any other
             monoclonal antibody, for any reason (e.g., omalizumab); No use within the following
             time interval before Visit 1: 5 months. Medication: Strong and moderate pgp inhibitors
             (e.g. dronedarone,ritonavir, indinavir, quinidine, valspodar, elacridar (GF120918); No
             use within the following time interval before Visit 1: 4 weeks. Medication: Strong and
             moderate CYP2D6 inhibitors (bupropion, fluoxetine, paroxetine, quinidine, ecstasy,
             terbinafine, cinacalcet, ritonavir, tipranavir, moclobemide, duloxetine, dronedarone);
             No use within the following time interval before Visit 1: 4 weeks. Medication: Any
             other investigational drug; No use within the following time interval before Visit 1:
             30 days or within 5 drug half-lives of the investigational drug (whichever is longer)
             - Liver Disease: Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or
             biliary abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic
             gallstones).

          -  Bundle branch block: Subjects with right or left bundle branch block.

          -  Blood Volume: Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or
             blood products in excess of 500mL within a 56-day period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 23, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 31, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 12, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Umeclidinium</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

