<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01651741</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>911029-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01651741</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Seaweeds Combined With Probiotics on Intestinal Function of Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Seaweeds Combined With Probiotics on Intestinal Function of Healthy Subjects: a Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Waiting-list Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Korea Institute of Planning &amp; Evalution for Technology of Food, Agriculture, Forestry &amp; Fisherie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Korea Institute of Planning &amp; Evalution for Technology of Food, Agriculture, Forestry &amp; Fisherie</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aims of this study are to investigate the effect of seaweeds which is one of the main
      ingredients of Korean traditional food 'Kimchi' and probiotics on intestinal function of
      healthy subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Kimchi is one of the the typical and main foods in Korea. Seaweed is one of the important
      ingredient of Kimchi and has been known to have antiinflammatory, anticoagulant and
      antiadhesive effects. As seaweeds are fermented in order to make Kimchi, it can encourage
      beneficial probiotics to grow and lead to preventing digestive problems such as constipation
      and diarrhea.

      In this trial, we are going to investigate the effect of combination of seaweeds and
      probiotics on intestinal function of healthy subject by evaluating intestinal microbiota. The
      trial is a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled, 2-arm study. Forty patients with
      normal intestinal condition will be randomly assigned to one of the 2 groups consisting of
      Seaweed with real probiotics or Seaweed with placebo probiotics. The assigned treatments will
      last for 4 weeks and the follow-up period will be 2 weeks.

      Four weeks of administration of seaweeds and probiotics is expected to increase the amount of
      beneficial microbiota and reduce that of harmful microbiota in intestine. we will also use
      questionnaires such as K-GSRS (Korean Gastrointestinal symptom rating scale), WHOQOL (The
      World Health Organization Quality of Life) - BREF and Assessment of bowel function scores
      (frequency, consistency, ease of passage - based on Bristol stool scale) to assess the change
      of digestive symptoms and the quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of intestinal microflora (7 strains of Lactic acid bacteria)</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1(0week), Visit 2(4week)</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the changes of intestinal microbes before and after experiment, feces should be collected.
The feces will be analyzed by the method of DGGE (denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis - PCR of DNA).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily assessment of bowel function scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1(0week), Visit 2(4week), Visit 3(6week)</time_frame>
    <description>The patients should write diaries of stool's frequency, consistency and ease of passage
Frequency (number of defecation in a day)
Consistency (judged by Bristol scale)
Ease of passage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>KGSRS (Korean gastrointestinal symptom rating scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1(0week), Visit 2(4week), Visit 3(6week)</time_frame>
    <description>GSRS(Gastrointestinal symptom rating scale) is composed of 15 questions associated with various digestive problems such as abdominal pain, gastrointestinal reflux, indigestion, diarrhea and constipation.
KGSRS, the Korean version of GSRS, reflects the language and sociocultural environment of Korea. The reliability and validity was confirm by Gwan et al.,2008.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>WHOQOL (The World Health Organization Quality of Life) - BREF</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1(0week), Visit 2(4week), Visit 3(6week)</time_frame>
    <description>WHOQOL - BREF consists of 4 categories and 26 questions assessing various types of quality of life such as physical, psychological, social relationships and environment function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Seaweed and Duolac7S</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Seaweed: Real Seaweed granule, Duolac7S: Real probiotics</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Seaweed and Duolac7S-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Seaweed: Real Seaweed granule, Duolac7S-P: Placebo probiotics</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Seaweed and Duolac7S</intervention_name>
    <description>Seaweed and probiotics is composed of seaweed and Duolac7S.
Seaweed:
Form: brown granule
Dosage and frequency: 1 pack (3 g), 2 packs per day (30 min after morning, and evening meal)
Duration: 4 weeks of treatment period
Duolac7S:
The probiotics, Duolac7S, consist of 7 bacteria.
Ingredients: Lactobacillus acidophilus, L. plantarum, L. rhamnosus, Bifidobacterium breve, B. lactis, B. longum, Streptococcus thermophilus.
Dosage and frequency: 1 capsule (5✕1,000,000,000 bacteria/capsule [7✕100,000,000 viable cells/strain]), 2 capsules per day (30 min after morning and evening meal)
Duration: 4 weeks of treatment period</description>
    <arm_group_label>Seaweed and Duolac7S</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Seaweed and probiotics</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Seaweed and Duolac7S-P</intervention_name>
    <description>Seaweed and probiotics is composed of seaweed and Duolac7S-P(Placebo Duolac7S).
Seaweed:
Form: brown granule
Dosage and frequency: 1 pack (3 g), 2 packs per day (30 min after morning, and evening meal)
Duration: 4 weeks of treatment period
Duolac7S-P:
Duolac7S placebo has the same form, color and flavor as experimental intervention (Duolac7S). The dosage, frequency and duration is also the same as experimental intervention (Duolac7S).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Seaweed and Duolac7S-P</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Seaweed and placebo probiotics</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age of 18 - 75, with a elementary-school diploma or higher, must be literate

          2. One who does not have any diseases or clinical symptoms related to digestive system

          3. One whose every question of KGSRS is under 3 points

          4. One who agree on not taking other therapies during the trial

          5. During the past 5 yrs, no history of organic lesion proven by colonoscopy

          6. One who agree on consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have abdominal operation in the past (exception: appendectomy, caesarean
             section, tubal ligation, laparoscopic cholecystectomy, hysterectomy and abdominal wall
             hernia repair)

          2. Patients who have history of serious diseases (cholangitis, pancreatitis, enteritis,
             ulcer, bleeding, cancer, etc.)

          3. Before participating clinical trial, one who took over-the-count medication affecting
             GI motility

          4. One who took antibiotics, herbal medicine or probiotics within 2 wks before
             participating the trial

          5. Pregnant woman

          6. One who disagree on the consent form
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jae-Woo Park, KMD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, College of Oriental Medicine, Kyung Hee University, 1 Hoegi-dong, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul 130-701, Republic of Korea</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyung Hee University Hospital at Gangdong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <state>Gangdong-gu</state>
        <zip>134-727</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.khnmc.or.kr/</url>
    <description>This is the URL of the site in which the clinical trial will be conducted.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 27, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 20, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 20, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kyunghee University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jae-Woo Park</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intestinal Microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>Probiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Seaweed</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Subject</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

