<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01659944</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GZGD04112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01659944</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Effect of Eliglustat on the Pharmacokinetics, Safety and Tolerability of Metoprolol in Healthy Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-site, Open-label, Fixed-sequence Phase 1 Study Evaluating the Effect of Eliglustat (Genz-112638) on the Pharmacokinetics, Safety and Tolerability of Metoprolol in Healthy Adult Subjects.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective is to determine the effect of repeated oral doses of eliglustat 150 mg
      twice daily (BID) on the pharmacokinetics (PK) of orally administered metoprolol 50 mg in
      healthy adults.

      The secondary objective is to assess the safety and tolerability of a single oral dose of
      metoprolol 50 mg when administered alone and in combination with repeated oral doses of
      eliglustat 150 mg BID in healthy adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Metoprolol area under the plasma concentration time curve from time zero to the last evaluable concentration (AUC0-last)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7; predose and up to 48 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Metoprolol area under the plasma concentration time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity (AUC0-∞)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7; Predose and up to 48 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) for metoprolol</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7; Predose and up to 48 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to maximum plasma concentration (Tmax) for metoprolol</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7; Predose and up to 48 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal elimination half-life (T1/2) for metoprolol</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7; Predose and up to 48 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trough plasma concentration of eliglustat</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3, Day 4, Day 5, Day 6, Day 7 and Day 8.</time_frame>
    <description>Eliglustat plasma concentration observed just prior to administration during repeated dosing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) of eliglustat</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7, up to 12 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to maximum plasma concentration (Tmax) of eliglustat</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7; up to 12 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eliglustat area under the plasma concentration time curve during the dosing interval (AUC0-τ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7; up to 12 hours after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through to Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metoprolol alone then eliglustat + metoprolol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In Period 1 all participants will receive a single oral dose of metoprolol 50 mg on Day 1. In Period 2, participants will receive repeat oral doses of eliglustat 150 mg twice a day from Day 3 to Day 8 and a single oral dose of metoprolol 50 mg on Day 7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eliglustat</intervention_name>
    <description>Capsules for oral administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metoprolol alone then eliglustat + metoprolol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Genz-112638</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metoprolol</intervention_name>
    <description>Tablets for oral administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metoprolol alone then eliglustat + metoprolol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lopressor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject is willing and able to provide signed informed consent.

          2. The male or female subject is in good general health and between 18 and 40 years of
             age, inclusive.

          3. The subject has a body weight of 50 to 100 kg (110 to 220 lb) with a body mass index
             (BMI) ≤32 kg/m2 at screening.

          4. The subject's physical examination, laboratory, vital sign, and electrocardiogram
             (ECG) test results are within normal limits at screening and Day -1 or, if abnormal,
             are not considered clinically significant in the opinion of the Investigator.

          5. The subject has been a non-smoker for at least 6 months prior to the time of providing
             informed consent, and is willing and able to abstain from smoking (and use of other
             forms of nicotine) until completion of the safety follow-up visit.

          6. The subject has not used drugs of abuse for at least 6 months prior to Day -1 and is
             willing and able to abstain from using drugs of abuse until completion of the safety
             follow-up visit.

          7. The subject is willing and able to abstain from alcohol for 48 hours prior to the
             first dose of study drug until completion of the safety follow-up visit.

          8. The subject is willing and able to abstain from grapefruit, grapefruit juice or any
             other grapefruit-containing products for 72 hours prior to the first dose of study
             drug until completion of the safety follow-up visit.

          9. The subject is willing and able to maintain a normal-fiber diet (i.e., to abstain from
             excess fiber-rich foods) for 72 hours prior to the first dose of study drug until
             completion of the safety follow-up visit.

         10. Female subjects of childbearing potential must have a documented negative pregnancy
             test at screening, Day -1 and prior to dosing on Day 7 and be willing to use a
             medically accepted form of contraception (as defined in the protocol) from screening
             until 30 days after the last dose of study drug. A woman of childbearing potential is
             defined as any female who has not been amenorrheic for at least 2 years or has not
             undergone a hysterectomy or surgical sterilization.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject is classified as a cytochrome P450 2D6 (CYP2D6) poor metabolizer (or an
             indeterminate metabolizer with neither allele known to be active) based on results of
             CYP2D6 genotyping performed at screening. (Note: Prior CYP2D6 genotyping results may
             be used for the purpose of determining study eligibility if a copy of the laboratory
             report is available and the genotyping results can be interpreted with the same
             classification system used by the study reference laboratory.)

          2. The subject has a digestive disorder, including malabsorption, gastroenteritis,
             pancreatitis, gastroesophageal reflux disease, inflammatory bowel disease (including
             Crohn's disease), or any other digestive disorder which, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, may affect oral bioavailability (e.g., clinically significant
             constipation, diverticulitis, or irritable bowel syndrome).

          3. The subject has had a gastrointestinal (GI) surgical procedure that might affect drug
             transit time, (e.g., cholecystectomy, GI bypass surgery, partial or total gastrectomy,
             or small bowel resection).

          4. The subject has any of the following: Clinically significant coronary artery disease
             including history of myocardial infarction or ongoing signs or symptoms consistent
             with cardiac ischemia or heart failure; clinically significant arrhythmias or
             conduction defect such as 2nd or 3rd degree atrioventricular (AV) block, a PR interval
             ≥200 msec, complete bundle branch block, prolonged QTc interval (e.g., repeated
             demonstration of a QTc interval ≥430 msec for male subjects and ≥450 msec for female
             subjects), sustained ventricular tachycardia, heart rate &lt;55 beats/min, or systolic
             blood pressure &lt;110 mmHg.

          5. The subject has a clinically significant organic disease, including cardiovascular,
             renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, pulmonary, neurologic, endocrine, metabolic, or
             psychiatric disease, or other medical condition, serious intercurrent illness, or
             extenuating circumstance that, in the opinion of the Investigator, precludes
             participation in the trial.

          6. The subject has a disease, clinical finding, or any contraindication that would
             prohibit the use of metoprolol in a phase 1 study (i.e., risk of disease exacerbation
             outweighs benefit). Examples of these are clinical findings of glucose intolerance,
             poor arterial peripheral circulation or bronchospastic disease including asthma.

          7. The subject has a history of fainting, postural lightheadedness, or any other postural
             symptoms.

          8. The subject has received any prescription or non-prescription medication (with the
             exception of nonprescription-strength ibuprofen and acetaminophen, topical
             non-steroidal preparations, and topical hydrocortisone (up to 1% strength)) or dietary
             or herbal or fiber supplement within 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer)
             prior to the first dose of study drug without the approval of both the Investigator
             and Sponsor.

          9. The subject has received an immunization within 30 days of providing informed consent.

         10. The subject has received an investigational product within 30 days prior to the first
             dose of study drug or plans to receive any other investigational product at any time
             during the course of this study.

         11. The subject has a history of drug allergies that are clinically significant in the
             opinion of the Investigator (e.g., significant rash or hives).

         12. The subject has a screening laboratory test result above the upper limit of normal for
             any of the following liver function tests: aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT), gamma glutamyltransferase (GGT), and total bilirubin.

         13. The subject tests positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody, hepatitis
             C antibody, or hepatitis B surface antigen at screening.

         14. The subject tests positive for urine drugs of abuse, urine alcohol, or urine cotinine
             at screening.

         15. The subject donated blood or blood products within 30 days prior to providing informed
             consent.

         16. The subject's schedule or travel plans prevent the completion of all required visits.

         17. The subject is scheduled for inpatient hospitalization, including elective surgery
             (inpatient or outpatient), during the study.

         18. The subject has a history of cancer, with the exception of basal cell carcinoma.

         19. The female subject of childbearing potential is pregnant or lactating.

         20. The subject, in the opinion of the Investigator, is unable to adhere to the
             requirements of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Monitor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug-drug interaction</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metoprolol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eliglustat</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

