<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01658527</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EORTC-1211-GUCG-IG</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-002122-67</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01658527</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TAK-700 in Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Randomized Comparative Trial of TAK-700 (Orteronel) Versus Bicalutamide in Metastatic Prostate Cancer Patients Failing 1st Line Treatment With LHRH Agonists or Surgical Castration.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer - EORTC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer - EORTC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this randomized phase II open label trial is to determine the anti-tumor
      activity of TAK-700 (Orteronel) as compared to bicalutamide in terms of clinical
      progression-free survival in prostate cancer patients who failed 1st line treatment with LHRH
      (luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone) agonists or surgical castration.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Pharmaceutical company has terminated orteronel (TAK-700) development for Prostate Cancer
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint of the trial is clinical progression free survival.</measure>
    <description>The primary endpoint of the trial is clinical progression free survival. In this protocol, it is defined according to the recommendations of the &quot;Prostate-Cancer clinical trials Working Group 2&quot; and referred to as the &quot;PCWG2&quot; for the setting &quot;delay/prevent&quot; progression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RECIST (Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors) response in patients presenting with measurable disease</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to PSA (Prostate specific antigen) progression and PSA change from baseline</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 4.03</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain (when an SAE (Serious Adverse Event)) or pain requiring initiation of narcotic analgesia</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Skeletal related events, including requirement to initiate chemotherapy, radiotherapy, cord compression or requirement for surgery to the bone</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Orteronel, 300 mg twice daily</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bicalutamide 50 mg per day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Orteronel</intervention_name>
    <description>Tak-700 will be administered until disease progression, diagnosis of a second malignancy, patient refusal to continue the treatment, excessive toxicity precluding further therapy according to protocol and /or according to the responsible physician.
Upon progression, patient may stay on study medication until the initiation of a new therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Orteronel, 300 mg twice daily</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TAK 700</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bicalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Bicalutamide will be given at the standard daily dose of 50 mg PO (per os). Bicalutamide will be maintained until disease progression diagnosis of a second malignancy, patient refusal to continue the treatment, excessive toxicity precluding further therapy according to protocol and /or according to the responsible physician.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bicalutamide 50 mg per day</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of prostate adenocarcinoma

          -  Metastatic disease in bone or other lesions documented by imaging. Abnormal 99mTc-bone
             scan imaging must be confirmed by Computed Tomography (CT) Scan or Magnetic resonance
             Imaging (MRI)

          -  Progressive disease following 1st line androgen deprivation therapy with LHRH
             (luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone) Agonists or surgical castration.
             Recommendations of Prostate Cancer Working Group 2 (PCWG2)

          -  WHO (World health organization) performance status ≤ 2

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 12 weeks

          -  Adequate bone marrow function (Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) 1500/μL; platelets
             100,000/μL)

          -  Castrate serum levels of testosterone (&lt; 50 ng/dL)

          -  Adequate renal function: calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 40 mL/minute

          -  Adequate hepatic function:

               -  Bilirubin: total bilirubin 1.5 Upper limit of Normal (ULN)

               -  Asparate aminotransferase (AST) and/or Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 x ULN
                  in the absence of liver metastases or ≤ 5 x ULN if liver metastases are present

          -  Patients of reproductive potential should use adequate birth control measures, as
             defined by the investigator, during the study treatment period and for at least 4
             months following the last study treatment. A highly effective method of birth control
             is defined as those that result in low failure rate (i.e. less than 1% per year) when
             used consistently and correctly

          -  Before patient registration/randomization, written informed consent must be given
             according to ICH/GCP (International conference on Harmonization-Good Clinical
             Practices), and national/local regulations

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Cardiac function:

               -  Screening calculated ejection fraction (Multi Gated Acquisition Scan (MUGA) scan,
                  or by echocardiogram) must be ≥ 50%

               -  No history of myocardial infarction, unstable symptomatic ischemic heart disease,
                  ongoing arrhythmias of Grade &gt; 2 thromboembolic events (e.g., deep vein
                  thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, or symptomatic cerebrovascular events), or any
                  other cardiac condition (e.g., pericardial effusion restrictive cardiomyopathy)
                  within 6 months prior to first dose of study drug

               -  Chronic stable atrial fibrillation on stable anticoagulant therapy is allowed

               -  Absence of New York Heart Association Class III or IV heart failure

               -  Absence of Electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities of: Q-wave infarction, unless
                  identified 6 or more months prior to screening and QTc interval &gt; 470 msec

               -  No uncontrolled hypertension despite appropriate medical therapy defined as blood
                  pressure &gt;160/90 mmHg at 2 separate measurements no more than 60 minutes apart
                  during the Screening visit

          -  Prior radiotherapy but only for lymph nodes is allowed

          -  Prior or concomitant therapy:

               -  No intake of narcotic analgesia for bone pain

               -  No prior treatment with non-steroidal antiandrogens, within 6 months prior to
                  randomization

               -  No anticancer therapy or treatment with another investigational agent within the
                  last 4 weeks prior to randomization

               -  No prior therapy with TAK-700, ketoconazole, abiraterone, aminoglutethimide or
                  MDV3100

               -  Patients taking bisphosphonates or denosumab are eligible if they have received a
                  stable dose for 4 weeks or more prior to randomization. (These treatments may
                  then be continued on study)

          -  No known hypersensitivity to compounds related to TAK-700 or to TAK-700 excipients
             (refer to Investigator's brochure)

          -  No known gastrointestinal (GI) disease or GI procedure that could interfere with the
             GI absorption or tolerance of TAK-700, including difficulty swallowing tablets

          -  No prior history of adrenal insufficiency

          -  No prior history of malignancies other than prostate adenocarcinoma (except for basal
             cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin), or the patient has been free of
             malignancy for a period of 3 years prior to first dose of study drug

          -  No known active chronic hepatitis B or C, life-threatening illness unrelated to
             cancer, or any serious medical or psychiatric illness that could, in the
             investigator's opinion, potentially interfere with participation in this study

          -  No drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Absence of any psychological, familial, sociological or geographical condition
             potentially hampering compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule; those
             conditions should be discussed with the patient before registration in the trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cora Sternberg</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>San Camillo Forlanini Hospitals, Rome, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bertrand Tombal</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Cliniques Universitaires de St Luc, Brussels, Belgium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Onze Lieve Vrouw Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aals</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cliniques Universitaires Saint-Luc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AZ Groeninge Kortrijk - Campus Vercruysselaan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kortrijck</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Dinant Godinne - UCL Namur</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yvoir</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 2, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 10, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>prostate cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bicalutamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

