<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02725918</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTONG1510</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02725918</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pemetrexed vs Pemetrexed Plus Cisplatin in Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor(EGFR)-Mutant NSCLC Patients After First Line EGFR Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors (TKIs) Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase II Study of Pemetrexed Alone vs Pemetrexed Plus Cisplatin in Patients With EGFR Mutation-positive Advanced NSCLC After First Line EGFR-TKIs Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guangdong Association of Clinical Trials</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guangdong Association of Clinical Trials</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective, multi-center, open-label, randomized, and controlled phase II
      clinical trial. The investigators hope to figure out the better chemotherapy regimen for the
      post-EGFR-TKI failure setting. The primary objective of this trial is to compare
      progression-free survival without grade 4 (G4PFS) toxicities between pemetrexed-cisplatin and
      single-agent pemetrexed treatment arms.

      The trial will include stage IIIB/IV EGFR mutation positive NSCLC patients who got disease
      progression after front-line EGFR TKI treatment.Eligible patients will be randomized to 2
      arms. Patients in arm A will receive 4 cycles of cisplatin (75 mg/m2, d1) and pemetrexed (500
      mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks, those without disease progression (PD) and being tolerable judged
      by investigator will continue single-agent pemetrexed (500 mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks as
      maintenance until progression or intolerable toxicities. Patients in arm B will receive
      pemetrexed (500 mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks until PD or intolerable toxicities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective, multi-center, open-label, randomized, and controlled phase II
      clinical trial.

      The trial will include stage IIIB/IV EGFR activating mutation positive NSCLC patients who got
      disease progression after frontline EGFR-TKI treatment. Clinical staging is determined
      according to the routine protocol, which includes enhanced chest CT scans, abdominal
      ultrasonography or CT scans, brain MRI or CT, and bone scintigraphy. Positron emission
      tomography (PET)/CT scan is optional. Measurement of acquired resistance to EGFR-TKIs is
      based on Jackman criteria.

      Eligible patients will be randomized to 2 arms. Patients in arm A will receive 4 cycles of
      cisplatin (75 mg/m2, d1) and pemetrexed (500 mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks, those without disease
      progression (PD) and being tolerable judged by investigator will continue single-agent
      pemetrexed (500 mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks as maintenance until progression or intolerable
      toxicities. Patients in arm B will receive pemetrexed (500 mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks until PD
      or intolerable toxicities. All patients will be administrated with vitamin B12 and folic acid
      supplement (vitamin B12 1mg intramuscular injection at least 7 days prior to the first dose
      of pemetrexed and repeated approximately every 9 weeks during pemetrexed treatment till 22
      days after the last dose of pemetrexed; folic acid 0.5 mg orally administered once daily from
      at least 7 days prior to the first dose of pemetrexed till 22 days after the last dose of
      pemetrexed).

      Efficacy data will be analyzed by intention-to-treat (ITT) population using all randomized
      patients, and safety data will be evaluated using CTCAE v4.0 criteria for patients who
      received ≥ 1 dose of study treatment. If the criteria for drug administration (absolute
      neutrophil count ≥1500/μl, platelets ≥100 000/μl, creatinine clearance ≥45 ml/min, no grade
      ≥3 nonhematologic toxicity [except for alopecia]) were not met, drug administration have to
      be delayed to allow sufficient time for recovery. If a delay of more than 42 days due to
      toxicity was necessary, the patient will be discontinued from the study. Dose adjustments
      according to hematologic toxicity at the start of a subsequent cycle of the therapy will be
      based on platelet and neutrophil nadir counts from the preceding cycle. Granulocyte
      colony-stimulating factor is allowed to use for neutropenia event. Patients will be
      discontinued from study treatment for the following reasons: disease progression;
      unacceptable toxicities; patient's refusal to continue.

      Radiological examinations (according to the RECIST 1.1 criteria) at baseline will be repeated
      for tumor response evaluation following every two cycles of chemotherapy. Patients will be
      followed up to 30 days after the last dose of study chemotherapy, and then every 3 months.

      Blood samples [8ml with ehylene diamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA) as anticoagulant each time]
      will be collected at the time of baseline, tumor response evaluation every 2 cycles, and
      disease progression. Blood samples at baseline and disease progression are mandatory to be
      provided. Tumor samples collection at the time of baseline and/or disease progression is
      strongly recommended but not mandatory for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival without grade 4 (G4PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization to the earliest occurrence of the first of grade 4 adverse events (AEs), disease progression, or death from any cause, regardless of whether or not the event leads to discontinuation,assessed up to 4 months.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization to the first date of documented objective progression disease or of death from any cause,assessed up to 6 months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization to the date of death from any cause,assessed up to 12 months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomization to date of objective disease progression,assessed up to 6 months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pem mono</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in arm B will receive pemetrexed (500 mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks until PD or intolerable toxicities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pem+Cis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in arm A will receive 4 cycles of cisplatin (75 mg/m2, d1) and pemetrexed (500 mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks, those without disease progression (PD) and being tolerable judged by investigator will continue single-agent pemetrexed (500 mg/m2, d1) every 3 weeks as maintenance until progression or intolerable toxicities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pemetrexed</intervention_name>
    <description>500 mg/m2,iv,d1,q3w,until PD</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pem mono</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pem+Cis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alimta，pemetrexed disodium</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>75 mg/m2,iv,d1,q3w,×4 cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pem+Cis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DDP，platinol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Informed consent must be signed.

          2. Age of ≥18 and &lt; 75 years old.

          3. Performance status (PS) 0 - 2 on the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Scale.

          4. Histologically confirmed stage IIIB/IV advanced NSCLC harboring activating EGFR
             mutation.

          5. Chemotherapy-naïve for advanced disease.

          6. Acquired resistance is measured according to the Jackman criteria. Achieved complete
             remission (CR)/partial remission (PR)≥4 months or stable disease (SD)＞6 months with
             first-line EGFR TKIs (Gefitinib or Erlotinib or Icotinib) for advanced NSCLC.

          7. Disease progression(RECIST) ＜4 weeks prior to study randomization.

          8. Adequate organ function including the following:

               -  Bone marrow: absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1.5 x 109/L, platelets ≥100 x 109/L
                  hemoglobin ≥9 g/dL.

               -  Hepatic: total bilirubin ≤1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), liver
                  transaminases: aspartate transaminase (AST or SGOT) and alanine transaminase (ALT
                  or SGPT) ≤2.5 times ULN. AST and ALT ≤ 5 x ULN may be included only if Patient
                  has liver metastasis.

               -  Renal: calculated creatinine clearance ≥45 mL/min (using the standard
                  Cockcroft-Gault formula).

          9. Patients have resolution to &lt;Grade 2 by the CTCAE (Version 4.0), of all clinically
             significant toxic effects of prior anti-cancer therapy (with the exception of rash and
             alopecia).

         10. Patients with stable central nervous system (CNS) metastasis successfully treated with
             local therapy, or with asymptomatic CNS metastasis are eligible. Treated stable CNS
             metastases are allowed; the patient must be stable after radiotherapy for ≥2 weeks and
             off of corticosteroids for ≥1 week.

         11. At least one measurable lesion as defined by RECIST 1.1 criteria.

         12. Previous palliative radiation therapy is allowed, but limited in &lt;25% of the bone
             marrow and must not have included whole pelvis radiation. Patients must have recovered
             from the toxic effects of the treatment prior to study enrollment (except for
             alopecia). Prior radiotherapy must be completed one month before study entry.
             Radiotherapy should not be administered to target lesions selected for this study,
             unless progression of the selected target lesions within the radiation portal is
             documented.

         13. Estimated life expectancy of at least 8 weeks.

         14. For women: must be surgically sterile, postmenopausal, or compliant with a highly
             effective contraceptive method during and for 3 months after the treatment period;
             must not be pregnant and must not be lactating; negative pregnancy test is required
             for women of childbearing potential. Postmenopausal women must have been amenorrhoeic
             for at least 12 months to be considered of non-childbearing potential. For men: must
             be surgically sterile or compliant with a highly effective contraceptive method during
             and for 3 months after the treatment period.

         15. Patient compliance and geographic proximity that allow adequate follow-up. Willingness
             to provide blood samples for EGFR mutation test at baseline and disease progression.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient got disease relapsed within 12 months after post-operative adjuvant
             chemotherapy, thereafter got failure from subsequent EGFR-TKI treatment cannot be
             enrolled.

          2. History of another malignancy within the last 5 years except cured carcinoma in-situ
             of uterine cervix, cured basal cell carcinoma of skin and superficial bladder tumors
             [Ta, Tis &amp; T1].

          3. Any unstable systemic disease (including active infection, hepatic, renal or metabolic
             disease) or serious concomitant disorders that will compromise the safety of the
             patient, or compromise the patient's ability to complete the study, at the discretion
             of the investigator.

          4. Significant cardiovascular event: congestive heart failure &gt;New York Heart Association
             (NYHA) class 2; unstable angina, active coronary artery disease (myocardial infarction
             more than 1 year prior to study entry is allowed); serious cardiac arrhythmia
             requiring anti-arrythmic therapy ( beta blockers or digoxin are permitted) or
             uncontrolled hypertension.

          5. History of significant neurological or mental disorder, including seizures or
             dementia.

          6. Incision from operation has not healed before the start of study treatment (Small
             incision for biopsy is eligible.)

          7. Presence of clinically uncontrollable third-space fluid collections, for example,
             ascites or pleural effusions that cannot be controlled by drainage or other procedures
             prior to study entry.

          8. Inability or unwillingness to interrupt aspirin or other non-steroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) from 2 days before to 2 days after administration of
             pemetrexed. If a patient is taking an NSAID (including Cox-2 inhibitors) or salicylate
             with a long half-life (e.g. naproxen, piroxicam, diflusinal, nabumetone, rofecoxib, or
             celecoxib), it should not be taken from 5 days before to 2 days after the
             administration of pemetrexed.

          9. Inability or unwillingness to take folic acid, vitamin B12 supplementation, or
             dexamethasone.

         10. Inability to comply with protocol or study procedures.

         11. Concurrent use of any other anti-tumor therapy during study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zeng Z, Yan HH, Zhang XC, Zhong WZ, He YY, Guan JL, Niu FY, Xie Z, Huang YS, Xu CR, Dong S, Wu YL. Reduced chemotherapy sensitivity in EGFR-mutant lung cancer patient with frontline EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor. Lung Cancer. 2014 Nov;86(2):219-24. doi: 10.1016/j.lungcan.2014.09.008. Epub 2014 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25263853</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tseng JS, Yang TY, Chen KC, Hsu KH, Yu CJ, Liao WY, Tsai CR, Tsai MH, Yu SL, Su KY, Chen JJ, Chen HY, Chang GC. Prior EGFR tyrosine-kinase inhibitor therapy did not influence the efficacy of subsequent pemetrexed plus platinum in advanced chemonaïve patients with EGFR-mutant lung adenocarcinoma. Onco Targets Ther. 2014 May 23;7:799-805. doi: 10.2147/OTT.S62639. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24920920</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yang JJ, Chen HJ, Yan HH, Zhang XC, Zhou Q, Su J, Wang Z, Xu CR, Huang YS, Wang BC, Yang XN, Zhong WZ, Nie Q, Liao RQ, Jiang BY, Dong S, Wu YL. Clinical modes of EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor failure and subsequent management in advanced non-small cell lung cancer. Lung Cancer. 2013 Jan;79(1):33-9. doi: 10.1016/j.lungcan.2012.09.016. Epub 2012 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>23079155</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zinner RG, Obasaju CK, Spigel DR, Weaver RW, Beck JT, Waterhouse DM, Modiano MR, Hrinczenko B, Nikolinakos PG, Liu J, Koustenis AG, Winfree KB, Melemed SA, Guba SC, Ortuzar WI, Desaiah D, Treat JA, Govindan R, Ross HJ. PRONOUNCE: randomized, open-label, phase III study of first-line pemetrexed + carboplatin followed by maintenance pemetrexed versus paclitaxel + carboplatin + bevacizumab followed by maintenance bevacizumab in patients ith advanced nonsquamous non-small-cell lung cancer. J Thorac Oncol. 2015 Jan;10(1):134-42. doi: 10.1097/JTO.0000000000000366.</citation>
    <PMID>25371077</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NSCLC</keyword>
  <keyword>EGFR-TKI failure</keyword>
  <keyword>chemotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

