<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02726464</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H16-00328</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02726464</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing the Characteristics of Platelet Rich Plasma in Sports Medicine</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRiSM</acronym>
  <official_title>Testing the Characteristics of Platelet Rich Plasma in Sports Medicine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>LightIntegra Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational study that evaluates the characteristics of Platelet Rich Plasma
      used in the therapy and treatment of musculoskeletal injuries and degenerative joint
      diseases.

      A sample of the PRP will be tested for platelet and microparticle content using dynamic light
      scattering to determine if there is a relationship between the composition and the treatment
      outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An observational study that evaluates the characteristics of Platelet Rich Plasma used in the
      therapy and treatment of musculoskeletal and degenerative joint conditions.

      Patients enrolled in this study have already been assessed by the Principal Investigator and
      are schedule to receive treatment with Platelet Rich Plasma. Prior to the treatment patients
      will be asked to consent in the study where the composition of the PRP is to be evaluated.
      Consenting patients that meet inclusion/exclusion criteria will complete a pain score
      self-assessment prior to treatment.

      An autologous preparation of PRP sample will be made from the subject's whole blood. The
      subject will receive the PRP treatment and an excess portion of the PRP preparation will be
      tested for composition and the relative concentration of the constituents.

      The sample of the PRP will be tested using Dynamic Light Scattering (ThromboLUX System) to
      measure the constituents in PRP preparations prior to injection. PRP and whole blood (at
      physician's discretion) will be analyzed on a hematology analyzer.

      The testing work-flow does not alter the subject's standard of care. The physician will be
      blinded to the analytical results during the enrolment, treatment and patient follow-up phase
      of the study. Analytical results are not used in patient management decisions.

      Patient's response to the PRP treatment will be assessed at 3 and 6 weeks post injection. At
      these times, the clinical outcome of the treatment will be measured using a patient self
      -assessment (post-treatment pain scores).

      This study will test the hypothesis that PRP characteristics, such as platelet and
      microparticle content and composition can be predictive clinical outcome for PRP treatments.

      The clinical outcome will be evaluated by patient pre- and post-pain score assessment. This
      study aims to review clinical outcomes and compare these results against ThromboLUX and other
      test results. If the predictive value of platelet composition testing can be demonstrated,
      additional studies may be considered.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pre- and post- pain score at 3 and 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 weeks after injection</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective of the study is to test the hypothesis that the constituents in platelet-rich plasma (PRP) preparations, such as platelet and microparticle content and composition, can be correlated to the clinical outcome for PRP treatments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The impact of microparticle content on pain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 weeks after injection</time_frame>
    <description>The study will ascertain the capability of ThromboLUX microparticle assay results to correlate with the clinical outcome for PRP treatments when evaluated by patient pre- and post-pain score assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of platelet count to ThromboLUX results</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 weeks after injection</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of PRP platelet count to clinical outcome and ThromboLUX data outputs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The use of dynamic light scattering (ThromboLUX) as a patient screening tool</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 weeks after injection</time_frame>
    <description>To verify the performance of the ThromboLUX instrument in a clinical setting by reviewing size and composition of constituents in PRP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Musculoskeletal Pain</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will consist of adults have been selected to receive platelet-rich
        plasma (PRP) injections as a treatment for musculoskeletal or degenerative joint conditions
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Are willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the study

          -  Have a diagnosed injury/condition requiring PRP injection: patients with acute or
             chronic musculoskeletal injury, tendinopathy, or mild to moderate osteoarthritis of
             the knee

          -  Are otherwise healthy

          -  Agree to pre-treatment fasting (4 hours prior to treatment)

          -  Agree to disclose medications taken in the last 2 weeks

          -  Able (in the Investigators opinion) and willing to comply with all study requirements

          -  Able to attend an on-site visit or provide information on your current status
             electronically, 3 and 6 weeks following the PRP injection

          -  Have not previously received a PRP injection for your current injury

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide informed consent

          -  Have any blood borne disease, currently or in the past

          -  Have a systemic inflammatory disease, skin or joint infection, bleeding disorders, or
             compromised immune function

          -  Have a known platelet abnormality or hematological disorder

          -  Are not able or willing to share with the study team any medications taken in the last
             two weeks.

          -  Taking anti-inflammatory medications or medications that interfere with clotting

          -  Are female and are pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Have inadequate venous access for drawing blood

          -  Have any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, may either put the participants at risk because of participation in the
             study, or may influence the result of the study, or the patients ability to
             participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Don McKenzie, MD, PhD, LLD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Leung, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>LightIntegra Technology Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allan McGavin Sports Medicine Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6T1Z3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Platelet-rich Plasma</keyword>
  <keyword>Cell-Derived Microparticles</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain Management</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Platelets</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapeutics</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>ThromboLUX</keyword>
  <keyword>Dynamic Light Scattering</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Musculoskeletal Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>Patient Brochure</doc_type>
      <doc_url>http://www.lightintegra.com/prism-study</doc_url>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

