<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02722109</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VEK52217</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02722109</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dual Energy CT: A New Method for Better Dose Calculation in Proton Beam Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>(DUAL)</acronym>
  <official_title>Dual Energy CT: A New Method for Better Dose Calculation in Proton Beam Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Aarhus University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Researchers want to compare proton stopping ratios, used for proton beam therapy planning,
      calculated based on single energy CT and dual energy CT images; with the intension of improve
      upon the proton range determination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The main goal of this study is to compare proton stopping ratios, used for proton beam
      therapy planning, calculated based on single energy CT and dual energy CT images.

      The calculation methods for proton stopping power ratios differs for the two types of CT
      images, and researchers want to investigate if the proton stopping power ratio can be
      estimated more accurately by using dual energy CT. A more accurate stopping power ratio
      calculation gives a more accurate proton range determination in the patient tissue, which
      again will lead to a better knowledge of the dose distribution in the patient undergoing
      cancer treatment with proton beam irradiation.

      Knowing the accurate dose distribution allows for an uncertainty margin reduction around the
      tumor, which will result in less normal tissue being irradiated and thereby the risk of side
      effects is reduced without risking an under-dosage of the tumor.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Not enough patients signed up
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stopping power ratio differences</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>For each patient the stopping power will be calculated based on both single and dual energy CT. The treatment of the patient will not be affected in any way of this study, the patient will receive the same treatment whether or not the patient volunteers to participate in this study. And the outcome of the calculations performed in this study will have no influence for the patient.
The calculations of the stopping power differences for each patient will as far as possible be done right after acquisition of the CT images, but the exact time point is not important. We will set as a deadline that the calculation for each patient is done within 2 months of acquisition of the CT images of the patient.
The entire study will be finished within 2 years, and the results will be tried published in a peer-reviewed journal.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>No intervention will be done</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        -  Patients with a identified tumor referred to curativ intended external beam
             radiotherapy

          -  Patients, for who are scheduled for a control CT scan during their treatment course

          -  Patients above 18 years of age

          -  Participation will take place on a voluntary basis It is estimated that annually
             around 1,000 patients will meet the above inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cancer patients who are scheduled for a control CT scan

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under 18 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cai Grau, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Aarhus University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engelsman M, Schwarz M, Dong L. Physics controversies in proton therapy. Semin Radiat Oncol. 2013 Apr;23(2):88-96. doi: 10.1016/j.semradonc.2012.11.003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23473685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knopf AC, Lomax A. In vivo proton range verification: a review. Phys Med Biol. 2013 Aug 7;58(15):R131-60. doi: 10.1088/0031-9155/58/15/R131. Epub 2013 Jul 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23863203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson TR. Dual-energy CT: general principles. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2012 Nov;199(5 Suppl):S3-8. doi: 10.2214/AJR.12.9116.</citation>
    <PMID>23097165</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hünemohr N, Krauss B, Tremmel C, Ackermann B, Jäkel O, Greilich S. Experimental verification of ion stopping power prediction from dual energy CT data in tissue surrogates. Phys Med Biol. 2014 Jan 6;59(1):83-96. doi: 10.1088/0031-9155/59/1/83. Epub 2013 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24334601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bourque AE, Carrier JF, Bouchard H. A stoichiometric calibration method for dual energy computed tomography. Phys Med Biol. 2014 Apr 21;59(8):2059-88. doi: 10.1088/0031-9155/59/8/2059. Epub 2014 Apr 2. Erratum in: Phys Med Biol. 2014 Sep 21;59(18):5611-2.</citation>
    <PMID>24694786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hall EJ. Henry S. Kaplan Distinguished Scientist Award 2003. The crooked shall be made straight; dose-response relationships for carcinogenesis. Int J Radiat Biol. 2004 May;80(5):327-37. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15223765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Paganetti H. Range uncertainties in proton therapy and the role of Monte Carlo simulations. Phys Med Biol. 2012 Jun 7;57(11):R99-117. doi: 10.1088/0031-9155/57/11/R99. Epub 2012 May 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22571913</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hudobivnik N, Schwarz F, Johnson T, Agolli L, Dedes G, Tessonnier T, Verhaegen F, Thieke C, Belka C, Sommer WH, Parodi K, Landry G. Comparison of proton therapy treatment planning for head tumors with a pencil beam algorithm on dual and single energy CT images. Med Phys. 2016 Jan;43(1):495. doi: 10.1118/1.4939106.</citation>
    <PMID>26745942</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hansen DC, Seco J, Sørensen TS, Petersen JB, Wildberger JE, Verhaegen F, Landry G. A simulation study on proton computed tomography (CT) stopping power accuracy using dual energy CT scans as benchmark. Acta Oncol. 2015;54(9):1638-42. doi: 10.3109/0284186X.2015.1061212. Epub 2015 Jul 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26219959</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yang M, Virshup G, Clayton J, Zhu XR, Mohan R, Dong L. Theoretical variance analysis of single- and dual-energy computed tomography methods for calculating proton stopping power ratios of biological tissues. Phys Med Biol. 2010 Mar 7;55(5):1343-62. doi: 10.1088/0031-9155/55/5/006. Epub 2010 Feb 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20145291</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schneider U, Pedroni E, Lomax A. The calibration of CT Hounsfield units for radiotherapy treatment planning. Phys Med Biol. 1996 Jan;41(1):111-24.</citation>
    <PMID>8685250</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Aarhus University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vicki Trier Taasti</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.Sc., PhD student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to share data with other centers</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

