<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02721212</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Habilita-Armeo-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U0074917/11110</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02721212</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of a New Technology to Functional Recovery Upper Limb in Post Stroke Patients.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of a New Technology to Functional Recovery Upper Limb in Post Stroke Patients: a Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Habilita S.p.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Habilita S.p.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      54 inpatients participants were randomly divided into two groups (experimental and
      conventional). Individual of experimental group were treated according to an established
      protocol for ARMEO Spring (30 minutes/session with &quot;Armeo Spring&quot; and 30 minutes/session with
      conventional treatment 5 days/week for 6 weeks). The conventional treatment consists of
      passive and active assisted mobilization of the upper limbs, traditional training based on
      the Bobath concept. Inpatients of control group were treated with conventional treatment with
      training session of 60 minutes 5 days/week for 6 weeks. All patients were evaluated by a
      blinded observer using the outcomes tests at enrollment (T0), after the treatment (T1) and at
      follow up 6 weeks later (T2). We assessed the impact on functional recovery (Functional
      Independence Measure - FIM scale), strength (ARM Motricity Index-MI), spasticity (Modified
      Ashworth Scale-MAS) and pain (Numeric Rating Pain Scale -NRPS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Authors conducted a double blind randomized controlled trial. Informed consent was obtained
      from all participants and procedures were conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki.
      The protocol (N° U0074917/11110) was approved by the Local Ethical Committee of Bergamo,
      Italy. A number of clinical trials have shown significant advances in upper limb recovery
      with the use of different sensory - motor techniques, including intensive repetitive
      movement, constraint-induced movement therapy, functional electrical stimulation treatment,
      the use of robot-assisted therapy in association with virtual reality. Robot-assisted virtual
      reality intervention has been shown more effective than conventional interventions and
      achieved more improvement in upper limb function, however the effect size reported by recent
      reviews was small and this datum is always reported as a cost-benefit ratio to challenge the
      use of virtual reality technology in rehabilitation. Robot aided rehabilitation is
      increasingly used in stroke rehabilitation, with a broad spectrum of applied technology from
      motor to non-motor aided systems, posing the problem to match the clinical need of the
      patient with the proper device. In the immediate post stroke period the motor recovery
      usually do not allow the use of non-motored robot device while the use of motored robot aid
      after months can be too delayed to obtain some valuable clinical results. The wide range of
      available devices are certainly a richness in the clinical possibility but also a critical
      factor in selecting a suitable technology tailored for the clinical feature of the patient at
      the actual state of the art. This can affect the comparison and interpretation of the
      literature so far published. Virtual reality therapy recreates favorable conditions to motor
      learning. Functional recovery is achieved through use-dependent cortical reorganization. The
      time/intensity of its application is therefore a pivotal point in this learning process. Its
      duration is not standardized and can varies from 3-4 to 20 hours of total treatment making
      results accordingly variable, adding further bias in data interpretation. A prerequisite to
      gain the best results is patients selection and early application when is possible.All these
      factors, have been ascribed as possible causes of small effect size reported in recent
      literature in comparing robot-aided virtual reality rehabilitation versus traditional
      rehabilitation alone.In a group of patients with hemiparesis following stroke, we compared
      the efficacy of a neurorehabilitation program consist of combination of non-motor
      robot-assisted therapy with virtual reality (Armeo®Spring) to conventional therapy with the
      primary aim to verify if the punctual application of what suggested by the single papers is
      able to improve differences of the efficacy between treatments and, therefore, creating a
      better effect size. And, as a secondary arm, if it is possible to improve the clinical
      picture also in post-acute stroke patients and as a secondary aim, if motor selection and
      intensive treatments can improve the small effect size reported by the literature.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Functional Independence Measure - FIM</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline (T0) to 6 weeks (T1) and 12 weeks (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>All patients were evaluated by a blinded observer using the outcomes tests at enrollment (T0), after the treatment (T1) and at follow up 6 weeks later (T2). Investigators assessed the impact on functional recovery (Functional Independence Measure - FIM scale).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in strength (ARM Motricity Index-MI)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline (T0) to 6 weeks (T1) and 12 weeks (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>All patients were evaluated by a blinded observer using the outcomes tests at enrollment (T0), after the treatment (T1) and at follow up 6 weeks later (T2). Investigators assessed the impact on strength (ARM Motricity Index-MI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in spasticity (Modified Ashworth Scale-MAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline (T0) to 6 weeks (T1) and 12 weeks (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>All patients were evaluated by a blinded observer using the outcomes tests at enrollment (T0), after the treatment (T1) and at follow up 6 weeks later (T2). Investigators assessed the impact on spasticity (Modified Ashworth Scale-MAS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain (Numeric Rating Pain Scale -NRPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline (T0) to 6 weeks (T1) and 12 weeks (T2)</time_frame>
    <description>All patients were evaluated by a blinded observer using the outcomes tests at enrollment (T0), after the treatment (T1) and at follow up 6 weeks later (T2). Investigators assessed the impact on pain (Numeric Rating Pain Scale -NRPS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Armeo Spring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients of experimental group were treated according to an established protocol for ARMEO Spring. In the first session the device was adjusted for patients arms. The physiotherapist controlled functional space of upper limb movement and correct position of working station.
Each training session consisted of two parts with 30 minutes per session with &quot;Armeo Spring&quot; and 30 minutes per session with conventional treatment 5 days per week, for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The conventional treatment, under control of physiotherapist, consists of passive and active assisted mobilization of the upper limbs traditional training based on the Bobath concept (neuromuscular facilitation, postural control and proprioception exercises, verticalization and gait training).
Each training session consisted of 60 minutes with conventional treatment 5 days per week, for 6 weeks in a control group.
The conventional session in the experimental group lasted 30 minutes with the same techniques and methods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Armeo Spring</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients of experimental group were treated according to an established protocol for ARMEO Spring. In the first session the device was adjusted for patients arms. The physiotherapist controlled functional space of upper limb movement and correct position of working station.
Each training session consisted of two parts with 30 minutes per session with &quot;Armeo Spring&quot; and 30 minutes per session with conventional treatment 5 days per week, for 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Armeo Spring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>The conventional treatment, under control of physiotherapist, consists of passive and active assisted mobilization of the upper limbs traditional training based on the Bobath concept (neuromuscular facilitation, postural control and proprioception exercises, verticalization and gait training).
Each training session consisted of 60 minutes with conventional treatment 5 days per week, for 6 weeks in a control group.
The conventional session in the experimental group lasted 30 minutes with the same techniques and methods.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The clinical diagnosis of stroke

          -  post stroke hemiparesis

          -  maximum six months from stroke

          -  stability of the clinical picture at the time of roll-in

          -  minimum level of upper arm motility (&gt;2) movement against gravity

          -  trunk control and ability to maintain sitting position for at least 120 minutes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hemiplegia of other aetiology ( neurodegenerative, neoplastic)

          -  Presence of articular ankyloses, spasms and/or severe muscle spasticity with complete
             loss of movement in any of the three major joints

          -  Instability of upper limb bone (not consolidated fractures)

          -  Presence of cognitive impairment (MMSE&lt;=21) and/or psychiatric disease

          -  Concomitant disease that could prevent the rehabilitation program (respiratory
             failure, heart failure, osteomyelitis, thrombophlebitis and other clinical condition
             that are against rehabilitation treatment)

          -  Ulcer sores that can contraindicate the use to ARMEO Spring

          -  Ashworth &gt; 3 (for each of the three upper limb joints)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giovanni Taveggia, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Habilita S.p.A.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roberto Casale, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Habilita S.p.A.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lorena Salvi, Vice Coord.</last_name>
    <phone>+39035918</phone>
    <phone_ext>293</phone_ext>
    <email>salvi.lorena@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Chiara Mulè, Coordinator</last_name>
    <phone>+39035918</phone>
    <phone_ext>293</phone_ext>
    <email>chiaramule@habilita.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Habilita, Sarnico's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sarnico</city>
        <state>Bergamo</state>
        <zip>24067</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giovanni Taveggia, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+39035918</phone>
      <phone_ext>293</phone_ext>
      <email>giovannitaveggia@habilitasarnico.it</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chiara Mulè, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stefania Fogliaresi, PT</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lorena Salvi, PT</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alberto Borboni, PhD, Eng</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roberto Casale, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Giovanni Taveggia, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kernan WN, Ovbiagele B, Kittner SJ; Secondary Prevention Guideline Writing Group. Response to letter regarding article, &quot;Guidelines for the prevention of stroke in patients with stroke and transient ischemic attack: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association&quot;. Stroke. 2015 Apr;46(4):e87-9. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.115.008661. Epub 2015 Mar 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25744519</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kernan WN, Ovbiagele B, Black HR, Bravata DM, Chimowitz MI, Ezekowitz MD, Fang MC, Fisher M, Furie KL, Heck DV, Johnston SC, Kasner SE, Kittner SJ, Mitchell PH, Rich MW, Richardson D, Schwamm LH, Wilson JA; American Heart Association Stroke Council, Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing, Council on Clinical Cardiology, and Council on Peripheral Vascular Disease. Guidelines for the prevention of stroke in patients with stroke and transient ischemic attack: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2014 Jul;45(7):2160-236. doi: 10.1161/STR.0000000000000024. Epub 2014 May 1. Erratum in: Stroke. 2015 Feb;46(2):e54.</citation>
    <PMID>24788967</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Colomer C, Baldoví A, Torromé S, Navarro MD, Moliner B, Ferri J, Noé E. Efficacy of Armeo® Spring during the chronic phase of stroke. Study in mild to moderate cases of hemiparesis. Neurologia. 2013 Jun;28(5):261-7. doi: 10.1016/j.nrl.2012.04.017. Epub 2012 Jun 23. English, Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>22727271</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Boian R, Sharma A, Han C, Merians A, Burdea G, Adamovich S, Recce M, Tremaine M, Poizner H. Virtual reality-based post-stroke hand rehabilitation. Stud Health Technol Inform. 2002;85:64-70.</citation>
    <PMID>15458061</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brokaw EB, Murray T, Nef T, Lum PS. Retraining of interjoint arm coordination after stroke using robot-assisted time-independent functional training. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2011;48(4):299-316.</citation>
    <PMID>21674385</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bütefisch C, Hummelsheim H, Denzler P, Mauritz KH. Repetitive training of isolated movements improves the outcome of motor rehabilitation of the centrally paretic hand. J Neurol Sci. 1995 May;130(1):59-68.</citation>
    <PMID>7650532</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wolf SL, Winstein CJ, Miller JP, Taub E, Uswatte G, Morris D, Giuliani C, Light KE, Nichols-Larsen D; EXCITE Investigators. Effect of constraint-induced movement therapy on upper extremity function 3 to 9 months after stroke: the EXCITE randomized clinical trial. JAMA. 2006 Nov 1;296(17):2095-104.</citation>
    <PMID>17077374</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Knutson JS, Hisel TZ, Harley MY, Chae J. A novel functional electrical stimulation treatment for recovery of hand function in hemiplegia: 12-week pilot study. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2009 Jan;23(1):17-25. doi: 10.1177/1545968308317577. Epub 2008 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>18812432</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Basteris A, Nijenhuis SM, Stienen AH, Buurke JH, Prange GB, Amirabdollahian F. Training modalities in robot-mediated upper limb rehabilitation in stroke: a framework for classification based on a systematic review. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2014 Jul 10;11:111. doi: 10.1186/1743-0003-11-111. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25012864</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Laver KE, George S, Thomas S, Deutsch JE, Crotty M. Virtual reality for stroke rehabilitation. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015 Feb 12;(2):CD008349. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD008349.pub3. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2017 Nov 20;11:CD008349.</citation>
    <PMID>25927099</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tesio L, Granger CV, Perucca L, Franchignoni FP, Battaglia MA, Russell CF. The FIM instrument in the United States and Italy: a comparative study. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2002 Mar;81(3):168-76.</citation>
    <PMID>11989512</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fasoli SE, Krebs HI, Stein J, Frontera WR, Hughes R, Hogan N. Robotic therapy for chronic motor impairments after stroke: Follow-up results. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2004 Jul;85(7):1106-11.</citation>
    <PMID>15241758</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kim YJ, Ku J, Cho S, Kim HJ, Cho YK, Lim T, Kang YJ. Facilitation of corticospinal excitability by virtual reality exercise following anodal transcranial direct current stimulation in healthy volunteers and subacute stroke subjects. J Neuroeng Rehabil. 2014 Aug 18;11:124. doi: 10.1186/1743-0003-11-124.</citation>
    <PMID>25135003</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Teasell RW, Murie Fernandez M, McIntyre A, Mehta S. Rethinking the continuum of stroke rehabilitation. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2014 Apr;95(4):595-6. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2013.11.014. Epub 2014 Feb 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24529594</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lum PS, Burgar CG, Shor PC, Majmundar M, Van der Loos M. Robot-assisted movement training compared with conventional therapy techniques for the rehabilitation of upper-limb motor function after stroke. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2002 Jul;83(7):952-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12098155</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Demain S, Burridge J, Ellis-Hill C, Hughes AM, Yardley L, Tedesco-Triccas L, Swain I. Assistive technologies after stroke: self-management or fending for yourself? A focus group study. BMC Health Serv Res. 2013 Aug 22;13:334. doi: 10.1186/1472-6963-13-334.</citation>
    <PMID>23968362</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kwakkel G, Kollen B, Lindeman E. Understanding the pattern of functional recovery after stroke: facts and theories. Restor Neurol Neurosci. 2004;22(3-5):281-99. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15502272</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ridding MC, Brouwer B, Miles TS, Pitcher JB, Thompson PD. Changes in muscle responses to stimulation of the motor cortex induced by peripheral nerve stimulation in human subjects. Exp Brain Res. 2000 Mar;131(1):135-43.</citation>
    <PMID>10759179</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rossini PM, Dal Forno G. Neuronal post-stroke plasticity in the adult. Restor Neurol Neurosci. 2004;22(3-5):193-206. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15502265</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nudo RJ. Postinfarct cortical plasticity and behavioral recovery. Stroke. 2007 Feb;38(2 Suppl):840-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17261749</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Villafañe JH, Valdes K, Anselmi F, Pirali C, Negrini S. The diagnostic accuracy of five tests for diagnosing partial-thickness tears of the supraspinatus tendon: A cohort study. J Hand Ther. 2015 Jul-Sep;28(3):247-51; quiz 252. doi: 10.1016/j.jht.2015.01.011. Epub 2015 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>26003014</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Prange GB, Jannink MJ, Groothuis-Oudshoorn CG, Hermens HJ, Ijzerman MJ. Systematic review of the effect of robot-aided therapy on recovery of the hemiparetic arm after stroke. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2006 Mar-Apr;43(2):171-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16847784</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lotze M, Braun C, Birbaumer N, Anders S, Cohen LG. Motor learning elicited by voluntary drive. Brain. 2003 Apr;126(Pt 4):866-72.</citation>
    <PMID>12615644</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Takahashi CD, Der-Yeghiaian L, Le V, Motiwala RR, Cramer SC. Robot-based hand motor therapy after stroke. Brain. 2008 Feb;131(Pt 2):425-37. Epub 2007 Dec 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18156154</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kaelin-Lang A, Luft AR, Sawaki L, Burstein AH, Sohn YH, Cohen LG. Modulation of human corticomotor excitability by somatosensory input. J Physiol. 2002 Apr 15;540(Pt 2):623-33.</citation>
    <PMID>11956348</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Villafañe JH, Silva GB, Chiarotto A, Ragusa OL. Botulinum toxin type A combined with neurodynamic mobilization for upper limb spasticity after stroke: a case report. J Chiropr Med. 2012 Sep;11(3):186-91. doi: 10.1016/j.jcm.2012.05.009.</citation>
    <PMID>23449315</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Posteraro F, Mazzoleni S, Aliboni S, Cesqui B, Battaglia A, Dario P, Micera S. Robot-mediated therapy for paretic upper limb of chronic patients following neurological injury. J Rehabil Med. 2009 Nov;41(12):976-80. doi: 10.2340/16501977-0403.</citation>
    <PMID>19841827</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Daviet JC, Bonan I, Caire JM, Colle F, Damamme L, Froger J, Leblond C, Leger A, Muller F, Simon O, Thiebaut M, Yelnik A. Therapeutic patient education for stroke survivors: Non-pharmacological management. A literature review. Ann Phys Rehabil Med. 2012 Dec;55(9-10):641-56. doi: 10.1016/j.rehab.2012.08.011. Epub 2012 Sep 7. Review. English, French.</citation>
    <PMID>23000090</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Masiero S, Celia A, Rosati G, Armani M. Robotic-assisted rehabilitation of the upper limb after acute stroke. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2007 Feb;88(2):142-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17270510</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Invernizzi M, Negrini S, Carda S, Lanzotti L, Cisari C, Baricich A. The value of adding mirror therapy for upper limb motor recovery of subacute stroke patients: a randomized controlled trial. Eur J Phys Rehabil Med. 2013 Jun;49(3):311-7. Epub 2013 Mar 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23480975</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hess G. Synaptic plasticity of local connections in rat motor cortex. Acta Neurobiol Exp (Wars). 2004;64(2):271-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15366258</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jang SH, You SH, Hallett M, Cho YW, Park CM, Cho SH, Lee HY, Kim TH. Cortical reorganization and associated functional motor recovery after virtual reality in patients with chronic stroke: an experimenter-blind preliminary study. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2005 Nov;86(11):2218-23.</citation>
    <PMID>16271575</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>You SH, Jang SH, Kim YH, Hallett M, Ahn SH, Kwon YH, Kim JH, Lee MY. Virtual reality-induced cortical reorganization and associated locomotor recovery in chronic stroke: an experimenter-blind randomized study. Stroke. 2005 Jun;36(6):1166-71. Epub 2005 May 12. Erratum in: Stroke. 2005 Jul;36(7):1625.</citation>
    <PMID>15890990</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Habilita S.p.A.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Giovanni Taveggia</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Robotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Upper Limb Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

