<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02722330</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CBAS5619</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02722330</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Cochlear Baha 5 SuperPower Sound Processor on the Baha Attract System</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Audiological Outcomes and Subjective Benefits of Cochlear Baha® 5 SuperPower Sound Processor on the Baha® Attract™ System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cochlear Bone Anchored Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cochlear Bone Anchored Solutions</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this clinical investigation is to evaluate objective and subjective hearing
      performance with the Cochlear Baha 5 SuperPower Sound Processor on the Baha Attract System,
      compared to the unaided hearing performance. Comparison of audiological test results with the
      same sound processor on a Baha Softband will also be performed. Short term safety parameters
      will be collected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Cochlear Baha bone conduction hearing implant offers two alternative ways to transmit
      vibrations from the external sound processor to the osseointegrated implant: The Baha Connect
      System uses a skin-penetrating abutment and allows direct bone conduction. The Baha Attract
      System uses a magnetic connection through intact skin. Magnetic bone conduction hearing
      implants have the advantage over skin-penetrating systems of eliminating the daily cleaning
      of the site and are perceived as a more cosmetically appealing by some subjects. With modern
      sound processor technology, it is possible to obtain good sound transmission despite the soft
      tissue attenuation that is inherent to magnetic bone conduction hearing implants. Clinical
      investigations have shown that the Baha Attract System, when used in combination with
      existing head-worn sound processors within the Premium (e.g. BP100, Baha 4 Sound Processors)
      and Power (BP110 Sound processor) segments, provides good hearing outcomes in subjects with
      conductive and mild mixed hearing loss.

      The Cochlear Baha 5 SuperPower Sound Processor is the first head-worn sound processor within
      the Super Power segment and has a fitting range of 65 dBHL. It is CE marked and is intended
      for subjects with mixed hearing loss or single-sided sensorineural deafness (SSD). It can be
      used with the Baha Connect and Baha Attract Systems and with a Baha Softband. When used in
      combination with the Baha Attract System, it will be able to compensate for a larger
      sensorineural component than the current Premium and Power sound processors and, hence, will
      allow more subjects to benefit from the Baha Attract System. The combination Baha Attract
      System with Baha 5 SuperPower Sound Processor is the most powerful non-skin penetrating bone
      conduction hearing implant solution available today.

      The Baha 5 SuperPower Sound Processor includes discreet design, advanced signal processing
      and improved connectivity to external sound sources. The new sound processor supports
      Cochlear's 2.4 GHz wireless protocol and is programmable with a new version of the Baha 5
      Fitting Software.

      The aim of this clinical investigation is to evaluate objective and subjective hearing
      performance with the Cochlear Baha 5 SuperPower Sound Processor on the Baha Attract System,
      compared to the unaided hearing performance. Comparison of audiological test results with the
      same sound processor on a Baha Softband will also be performed. Short term safety parameters
      will be collected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance PTA4 from the unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Audiometry; free field thresholds. Pure tone average PTA4 [Mean of 0.5, 1, 2 and 4 kHz]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of the self-reported assessments of hearing outcome APHAB from the unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Abbreviated Profile of Hearing Aid Benefit (APHAB)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of the self-reported assessments of hearing outcome SSQ-12 from the unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Speech, Spatial and Qualities of Hearing Scale (SSQ-12)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance PTA4 from the unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Audiometry; free field thresholds. Pure tone average PTA4 [Mean of 0.5, 1, 2 and 4 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field tresholds per frequency from unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Audiometry; free field thresholds per frequency[0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0, 4.0, 6.0 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field tresholds per frequency from unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Audiometry; free field thresholds per frequency[0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0, 4.0, 6.0 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field - adaptive speech recognition in noise from unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Free field; - Adaptive speech recognition in noise</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field - adaptive speech recognition in noise from unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Free field; - Adaptive speech recognition in noise</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field - speech recognition in quiet from the unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Free field; - Speech recognition in quiet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field - speech recognition in quiet from the unaided hearing situation at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system, aided at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Free field; - Speech recognition in quiet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance PTA4 from the situation with the same sound processor on a Baha soft band at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Audiometry; free field thresholds. Pure tone average PTA4 [Mean of 0.5, 1, 2 and 4 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance PTA4 from the situation with the same sound processor on a Baha soft band at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Audiometry; free field thresholds. Pure tone average PTA4 [Mean of 0.5, 1, 2 and 4 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field tresholds per frequency from the situation with same sound processor on a Baha softband with the Investigational device on the attract system at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Audiometry; Free field thresholds per frequency[0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0, 4.0, 6.0 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field tresholds per frequency from the same sound processor on a Baha softband with the Investigational device on the attract system at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Audiometry; Free field thresholds per frequency[0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0, 4.0, 6.0 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance BC Direct tresholds per frequency from the situation with the sound processor on a Baha softband at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system tresholds at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>BC Direct thresholds per frequency [0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0, 4.0, 6.0 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance BC Direct tresholds per frequency from the situation with the sound processor on a Baha softband at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system tresholds at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>BC Direct thresholds per frequency [0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0, 4.0, 6.0 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance BC Direct PTA4 from the situation with the same sound processor on a Baha softband at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>BC Direct PTA4 [Mean of 0.5, 1, 2 and 4 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance BC Direct PTA4 from the situation with the same sound processor on a Baha softband at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>BC Direct PTA4 [Mean of 0.5, 1, 2 and 4 kHz]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field - adaptive speech recognition in noise from the situation with the same sound processor on a Baha softband at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Free field - Adaptive speech recognition in noise</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field - adaptive speech recognition in noise from the situation with the same sound processor on a Baha softband at pre-operation with the Investigational device on the attract system at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Free field - Adaptive speech recognition in noise</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field - speech recognition in quiet from the situation with the same sound processor on a Baha Softband with the Investigational device on the attract system at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Free field - Speech recognition in quiet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of hearing performance free field - speech recognition in quiet from the situation with the same sound processor on a Baha Softband with the Investigational device on the attract system at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Free field - Speech recognition in quiet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sound processor magnet selection at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Information about sound processor magnet selection, type of SP magnet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sound processor magnet selection at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Information about sound processor magnet selection, type of SP magnet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sound processor magnet selection at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Information about sound processor magnet selection, type of SP magnet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily use of sound processor (Average daily use during the last week)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Average daily use during the last week</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events related to the treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of adverse events related to the treatment during the 12 weeks treatment period</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Single Sided Sensorineural Deafness</condition>
  <condition>Mixed Hearing Loss, Unilateral</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Baha 5 SuperPower on Baha Attract System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The device involves the following parts:
The sound processor unit, an actuator unit and a cable, the Sound Processor Magnet (SP Magnet) of the Baha Attract System, the BIM400 Baha Implant Magnet that is fixated to the BI300 Implant, a snap coupling.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Baha 5 SuperPower on Baha Attract System</intervention_name>
    <description>The Investigational device involves the following parts: the sound processor unit, an actuator unit and a cable that connects the sound processor and actuator units. The actuator unit is attached to the Sound Processor Magnet (SP Magnet) of the Baha Attract System which is pulled towards the BIM400 Baha Implant Magnet that is fixated to the BI300 Implant. The actuator unit can also be connected to the Baha Softband via a snap coupling.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Baha 5 SuperPower on Baha Attract System</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult subjects ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Mixed hearing loss in the ear to be implanted. Bone conduction thresholds with pure
             tone average (PTA4, Mean of 0.5, 1, 2 and 4kHz) of 30-55 dBHL or

          -  Single-sided sensorineural deafness: Bone conduction thresholds with a pure tone
             average [PTA4, Mean of 0.5, 1, 2 and 4 kHz] of lower or 30 dBHL in the best ear.
             Subjects who have, for some reason, experienced no or limited benefit from other sound
             processors when tested on a Baha Softband.

          -  Subjects suitable for surgery according to the recommended surgical procedure for
             Cochlear Baha 5 SuperPower with no previous implant on the side to be investigated.

          -  Signed inform consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject scheduled for simultaneous bilateral implant surgery. The investigation is
             limited to subjects with unilateral use of the Investigational device (however,
             bilateral hearing loss is not an exclusion criterion).

          -  Suitable implant position for the BI300 Implant (4 mm or 3 mm) not found during
             surgery due to insufficient bone quality and/or bone thickness

          -  Less than 3 mm soft tissue thickness at the planned implant site. (Intra-operative
             exclusion criteria judged by the surgeon at Visit 1 or Visit 2 according to local
             practice).

          -  Subjects that have received radiation therapy at the same side of the skull where the
             Investigational device will be positioned.

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes as judged by the investigator.

          -  Condition that could jeopardise osseointegration and/or wound healing (e.g.
             osteoporosis, psoriasis and long-term systemic use of corticosteroids) or condition
             that may have an impact on the outcome of the investigation as judged by the
             investigator.

          -  Unable to follow investigational procedures, e.g. to complete quality of life scales.

          -  Participation in another clinical investigation with pharmaceutical and/or device.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jaydip Ray, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Hallamshire Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>César Orús, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital de Sant Pau</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Van de Heyning, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Antwerp</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jesper Schmidt, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Odense University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Antwerp University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antwerp</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Odense University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense</city>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Sant Pau</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Hallamshire Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 30, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deafness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss, Mixed Conductive-Sensorineural</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss, Unilateral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hearing Loss, Sensorineural</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>February 1, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

