<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02725749</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>USaoPauloGH1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02725749</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low Level Laser Therapy Associated With Exercise in Subacromial Impingement Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Low Level Laser Therapy Associated With Exercise in Subacromial Impingement Syndrome: a Randomized, Double-blind Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: The objective was to compare low level laser therapy (LLLT) therapy versus low
      LLLT therapy in combination with an exercise or exercise only on pain, range of motion (ROM),
      functionality, and activity limitation in patients with subacromial impact syndrome.

      Design: Randomized and placebo-controlled clinical trial.

      Setting: The setting for the study was the Municipal Clinic of Barueri, São Paulo, Brazil.

      Participants: 60 patients with subacromial impact syndrome were randomly assigned in three
      groups.

      Interventions: Group I, experimental (n=21) treated with low level laser therapy and
      exercises; Group II, experimental (n=21) treated with exercises; and Group III, experimental
      (n=18) treated with low level laser therapy. Laser used were GaAs (904 nm, 60 mW), in
      continuous emission. The participants received application of laser three times or week for
      eight weeks, on 9 shoulder points (3 Joules/point) per session.

      Main outcome measures: Visual Analogic Scale (VAS) score, Shoulder Pain and Disability Index
      (SPADI), goniometer, Modified-University of California at Los Angeles Shoulder Rating Scale
      (UCLA), recorded before and after treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the groups that received low level laser therapy (LLLT), energy was irradiated over three
      insertion points in the supraspinatus muscle region, three points on the bursa subacromial,
      and three points along the bicipital groove, at 3 Joules per point. Total dose per shoulder
      was 27 Joules per treatment, using a previously calibrated Irradia Class 3B (Stockholm,
      Sweden). Pen's semiconductor consisted of gallium arsenide with a wavelength of 904 nm,
      frequency of 700 Hz, average potency of 60 mW, peak potency of 20 W, pulse duration of 4.3
      ms, and 50 seconds per point (0.5cm2 area). The parameters followed the recommendation of the
      World Association of Laser Therapy for subacromial impact syndrome.

      The participants received application of laser three times or week for eight weeks.

      The groups treated with exercise followed the same training program. Isotonic strengthening
      exercises were performed for the scapular pivot, scapula stabilizer, and humeral propellant
      muscle groups. Three sets of 15 repetitions of each isotonic strengthening exercise were
      performed. The isometric exercises were performed in ten sets of ten seconds each. Analytical
      stretching of each muscle group was performed at the beginning of the session for 30 seconds.

      The participants performed the exercises three times a week for eight weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain assessed using a VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Pain was assessed using a VAS consisting of a 10cm ruler (without numbers), ranging from &quot;no pain&quot; on the left side to &quot;unbearable pain&quot; on the right side. The patients were instructed to mark their level of pain on the ruler.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Range of motion assessed with a universal goniometer (Aesculap)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Range of motion was assessed with a universal goniometer (Aesculap) used to measure shoulder flexion and extension according to the methods described by Marques et al. (2011).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functionality measured using the Modified-University of California at Los Angeles Shoulder Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Functionality was measured using the Modified-University of California at Los Angeles Shoulder Rating Scale, which consists of five domains—pain, function, range of motion, muscle strength, and patient satisfaction—and a possible total of 35 points, with higher scores indicating better results</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life assessed with the Shoulder Pain and Disability Index (SPADI)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life was assessed with the Shoulder Pain and Disability Index (SPADI). This questionnaire, which is specific to the shoulder joint, assesses pain and disability. The SPADI consists of 13 items distributed in the areas of pain (five items) and function (eight items), with each item scored on a numerical scale from 0 to 10 points. The final score of the questionnaire and the score of each domain are converted into percentages ranging from 0 to 100%, with higher scores indicating worse shoulder conditions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Subacromial Impingement Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laser and Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laser</intervention_name>
    <description>Laser used were GaAs (904 nm, 60 mW), in continuous emission. The participants received application of laser three times or week for eight weeks, on 9 shoulder points (3 Joules/point) per session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Laser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EXE</intervention_name>
    <description>Isotonic strengthening exercises were performed for the scapular pivot, scapula stabilizer, and humeral propellant muscle groups. Three sets of 15 repetitions of each isotonic strengthening exercise were performed. The isometric exercises were performed in ten sets of ten seconds each. Analytical stretching of each muscle group was performed at the beginning of the session for 30 seconds.
The participants performed the exercises three times a week for eight weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Exercise</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laser + EXE</intervention_name>
    <description>Laser used were GaAs (904 nm, 60 mW), in continuous emission. The participants received application of laser three times or week for eight weeks, on 9 shoulder points (3 Joules/point) per session.
Isotonic strengthening exercises were performed for the scapular pivot, scapula stabilizer, and humeral propellant muscle groups. Three sets of 15 repetitions of each isotonic strengthening exercise were performed. The isometric exercises were performed in ten sets of ten seconds each. Analytical stretching of each muscle group was performed at the beginning of the session for 30 seconds.
The participants performed the exercises three times a week for eight weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Laser and Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Laser and Exercise</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of subacromial impact syndrome

          -  Age range: 30-75 years

          -  Both genders

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  cancer,

          -  diabetes,

          -  symptomatic shoulder osteoarthritis,

          -  surgery or previous fractures in the humeral head of the shoulder,

          -  history of acute trauma, calcification of the articular rotator tendon,

          -  total tendon rupture,

          -  cervical myofascial syndrome,

          -  radicular pain,

          -  inflammatory rheumatic disease,

          -  neurological disorders,

          -  depressive syndrome

          -  use of antidepressants,

          -  use of anti-inflammatory medications

          -  use anxiolytics
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 21, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 5, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Raquel A. Casarotto</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PHD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>shoulder</keyword>
  <keyword>low level laser therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>exercises</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rotator Cuff Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shoulder Impingement Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

