<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02720198</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00064983</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02720198</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Levomilnacipran ER vs. Adjunctive Quetiapine for Adults With Inadequate Relief With SSRIs in MDD</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Rater-blinded Trial Comparing Efficacy and Tolerability and Changes in Neurocognition and Apathy of a Switch to Levomilnacipran Extended Release (ER) Versus Adjunctive Quetiapine for Patients Who Have Shown Inadequate Relief With Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors (SSRIs) in Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Forest Laboratories</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institute for Advanced Medical Research, Alpharetta, GA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study's primary objective is to compare the efficacy and tolerability of switching
      patients with inadequate relief on generic SSRIs to levomilnacipran versus adding a new
      treatment (quetiapine) to the participants' existing treatment with people diagnosed with
      depression (major depression disorder).

      The secondary objective is to examine the response and remission rates following the switch
      from a generic SSRI to levomilnacipran ER and augmentation with quetiapine along with
      examining changes in neurocognitive and apathy measures after the switch.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 23, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>A ten-item diagnostic questionnaire which use to measure the severity of depressive episodes in patients with mood disorders. Total scores will range from 0 to 60.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Response rate will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Remission Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Remission rate will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neurocognition by changes in Scores on Reyes Verbal Learning Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Number of words correctly recalled by the respondent is recorded. 1 point for each word correctly recalled. Total score range of 0-40</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neurocognition by changes in Scores on Clinical Global Impression Scale- Severity (CGI-S)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>CGI-S a 7 point scale that requires the clinician to assess how much the patient's illness has improved or worsened relative to a baseline state at the beginning of the intervention. Total score range of 0-7.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neurocognition by changes in Scores on Clinical Global Impression Scale- Severity (CGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>CGI-I a 7 point scale that requires the clinician to assess how much the patient's illness has improved or worsened relative to a baseline state at the beginning of the intervention. Total score range of 0-7.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in scores on Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale (HAM-A) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire used by clinicians to rate the severity of a patient's anxiety. Total score range of 0-48.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in scores on Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>A self-reported brief scale to assess impairment of work/school, social life and family and home. Total score range of 0-30.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neurocognition by changes in scores on Scores on Digit symbol substitution test (DSST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Total score range of 0-89.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in scores on Apathy Evaluation Scale (AES).</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Self-Administered assessment measuring lack of motivation not attributable to diminished level of consciousness, cognitive impairment, or emotional distress. Total scores range from 0-54.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neurocognition by changes in scores on Improvement (CGI-I) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline - Week 8</time_frame>
    <description>CGI-I is a 7 point scale that requires the clinician to assess how much the patient's illness has improved or worsened relative to a baseline state at the beginning of the intervention. Total score range of 0-7.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Levomilnacipran</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Quetiapine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Quetiapine will be added in addition to current antidepressant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levomilnacipran</intervention_name>
    <description>treating major depression. A flexible dose regime of levomilnacipran ER 20-120 mg/d mg per day starting at 20 mg/d on Days 1-2, increasing to 40 mg/d on Days 3-7 in week 1, then flexibly dosed between 40 mg/d -120 mg/d during weeks 2 through 8</description>
    <arm_group_label>Levomilnacipran</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fetzima</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quetiapine</intervention_name>
    <description>Quetiapine will be started at 50 mg/d on Day 1-2, increasing to 150 mg/d on Days 3-7 in Week 1 and then flexibly dosed between 150-300 mg/d during Weeks 1 through 8 along with their current antidepressant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quetiapine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Seroquel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-65 years inclusive

          -  Current diagnosis of MDD based on DSM-IV criteria

          -  Able to understand study rules and procedures and willing to sign written informed
             consent for study participation

          -  Inadequate response to antidepressants: having a score of ≥14 on the 17-item Hamilton
             Anxiety Scale (HAMD) and not having a ≥ 50% reduction in HAMD or CGI-S scores from
             baseline after a retrospective confirmation of an adequate trial of a single
             antidepressant (defined as a minimum 6-week trial of acceptable therapeutic dose
             (daily dose ≥ 40 mg of fluoxetine, 40 mg of paroxetine, 20 mg of citalopram, 10 mg of
             escitalopram, 37.5 mg of paroxetine CR, 150 mg of sertraline, 100 mg of fluvoxamine).

          -  If female, nonpregnant/nonlactating status

          -  Duration of current MDD ≥ 4 weeks and &lt; 24 months

          -  Not more than 2 treatment failures of adequate antidepressant trials for current
             episode of MDD

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has previously participated in a levomilnacipran ER or quetiapine XR or quetiapine
             clinical study in previous 12 months

        Has 1 or more the following:

          -  Current or past history of: manic or hypomanic episode, schizophrenia or any other
             psychotic disorder defined in the DSM- 5

          -  Diagnosis of alcohol or other substance use disorder (except nicotine and caffeine) as
             defined in the DSM-5 that has not been in sustained full remission for at least 6
             months prior to screening (participant must also have negative urine drug screen prior
             to baseline).

          -  Presence or history of a clinically significant neurological disorder (including
             epilepsy)

          -  Poorly controlled Hypertension or Diabetes

          -  uncontrolled narrow-angle glaucoma

          -  hypersensitivity to levomilnacipran, milnacipran , quetiapine or quetiapine XR

          -  Neurodegenerative disorder.

          -  Has a thyroid stimulating hormone value outside the normal range at the Screening
             Visit that is deemed clinically significant by the investigator.

          -  Has clinically significant abnormal vital signs as determined by the investigator.

          -  Has a clinical significant abnormal electrocardiogram.

          -  Has screening laboratory values greater than 2.5 times the upper or lower limits of
             normal range or judged to be clinically significant

          -  Has a disease or takes medication that, in the opinion of the investigator, could
             interfere with the assessments of safety, tolerability, or efficacy or prevent the
             individual from completing the study.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential not on adequate contraception methods in the
             opinion of the investigator

             o If the female is childbearing, she must agree to use appropriate contraceptive
             measures for the duration of the study and for one month afterwards. Medically
             acceptable contraceptives include: (1) surgical sterilization (such as tubal ligation
             of hysterectomy), (2) approved hormonal contraceptives (such as birth control pills,
             patches, implants, or injections), (3) barrier methods (such as condom or diaphragm)
             used with a spermicide, or (4) an intrauterine device (IUD). Contraceptive measures
             such as Plan B ™, sold for emergency use after unprotected sex, are not acceptable
             methods for routine use. If the female does become pregnant during this study she must
             inform the study physician immediately.

          -  Has a significant risk of suicide according to Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale
             (CSSRS) or in the clinical judgment of the investigator

          -  History of suicide attempt in the previous 12 months

          -  MDD with postpartum onset, psychotic features or seasonal features

          -  Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAM-A) baseline score ≥ 24

          -  Failure of ≥ 3 adequate trials of different antidepressants for the current episode of
             MDD

          -  ≥ 3 episodes major depression in previous 12 months or ≥ 8 lifetime episodes of MDD

          -  Current or previous use of an atypical or typical antipsychotic agent for augmentation
             of major depression or treatment of psychotic depression, mania psychosis, or
             agitation. Previous use of antipsychotics for insomnia will be permitted.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashwin A Patkar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke Universtiy Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Josephine E Lee, BA</last_name>
    <phone>919-681-0613</phone>
    <email>josephine.white@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute for Advanced Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alpharetta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30005</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brandon W Lenfest, CCRC</last_name>
      <phone>770-817-9200</phone>
      <email>crc4@iamresearch.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Angelo Sambunaris, MD</last_name>
      <phone>770-817-9200</phone>
      <email>a.sambunaris@iamresearch.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Angelo Sambunaris, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 25, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Quetiapine Fumarate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Milnacipran</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Serotonin Uptake Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

