<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02725879</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PEDIATRIC ENDOCRINOLOGY</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02725879</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>FGF-21 Levels and RMR in Children and Adolescents With Hashimoto's Thyroiditis (THYROMETABOL)</brief_title>
  <acronym>THYROMETABOL</acronym>
  <official_title>Association of Serum Fibroblast Growth Factor 21 (FGF-21) Levels With Resting Metabolic Rate (RMR), in Children and Adolescents With Hashimoto's Thyroiditis.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aristotle University Of Thessaloniki</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Aristotle University Of Thessaloniki</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Thyroid hormone (TH) and fibroblast growth factor 21 (FGF-21) are reported to share common
      metabolic pathways and underlying mechanisms in terms of energy balance, thus affecting both
      thermogenesis and resting metabolic rate (RMR). Although FGF-21 levels has been studied in
      children and adolescents regarding obesity, body composition and insulin resistance, data in
      children and adolescents diagnosed with Hashimoto's thyroiditis are lacking. Therefore, the
      purpose of this study is to measure the RMR in children and adolescents diagnosed with
      clinical hypothyroidism due to thyroiditis Hashimoto just before starting levothyroxine
      treatment and after six months achieving an euthyroid state, and to detect any association
      between serum FGF-21 levels and RMR.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with hypothyroidism due to Hashimoto thyroiditis (HT) will receive standard
      treatment with levothyroxine by their attending physician in order to achieve an euthyroid
      status. Free T4 level is expected to be displayed within normal range (10-16 mg/dl) after the
      first few months of levothyroxine administration, and TSH level is expected to be less than
      5mU / ml after 3-4 months. Participants will be re-examined in 6 months after the initiation
      of substitution pharmacotherapy with levothyroxine. Similarly, a control group consisted by
      healthy children and adolescents matched for age and gender will be re-examined after a 6-
      month interval from the initial measurements.

      From all participants detailed medical history will be recorded and following parameters will
      be measured and calculated: Age and pubertal stage according Tanner, height, body weight,
      Body Mass Index (BMI),waist circumference, hip circumference, Mid Arm Circumference (MAC),
      skinfolds measurement (using a Harpenden skinfold caliper), in order to estimate the
      percentage (%) body fat. Measurement of RMR, with a portable device applying indirect
      calorimetry (Fitmate Cosmed, Italy) The blood samples will be collected and centrifuged
      immediately after the RMR measurement. Following parameters will be tested in serum: FGF-21
      (measured by ELISA method), TSH, F-T3, F-T4, TPOAb, TgAb, Fasting Glucose, Insulin, TChol,
      TG, HDL, LDL, AST, ALT, γGT (applying automatic chemical analyzers and analogues reagents
      that already exist at the Hospital).

      Additionally, a 3-day food dairy (two weekdays and one weekend day) will be completed by the
      participants and/or their caregivers just a week before the measurement of the RMR and the
      blood sampling.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of FGF-21 serum levels in children and adolescents with Hashimoto's clinical hypothyroidism.</measure>
    <time_frame>1year</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of FGF-21 serum levels before and after 6 month period with levothyroxine treatment in children and adolescents with Hashimoto's clinical hypothyroidism.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of RMR in children and adolescents with Hashimoto's clinical hypothyroidism.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of RMR before and after 6 month period with levothyroxine treatment in children and adolescents with Hashimoto's clinical hypothyroidism.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Comparisons between initial and after 6 months levothyroxine treatment of FGF-21 serum levels and RMR.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison between the patient's group initial FGF-21 serum levels and RMR before and after levothyroxine treatment. Similar comparison will be done in the control group. Furthermore, a final comparison between patients and controls will be held.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Thyroiditis Hashimoto</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HASIMOTO's PATIENTS (HT)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children and Adolescents diagnosed with Hashimoto's clinical hypothyroidism.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONTROL GROUP (C)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy individuals matched for gender and age</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Serum samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Children and Adolescents of Greek origin who attend the Pediatric Endocrinology Outpatient
        Unit of 4th Department of Pediatrics,Medical School,Aristotle University of Thessaloniki
        for testing thyroid autoimmunity, as well as healthy controls.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For patients

          -  Subjects 5 to 18 years old.

          -  First diagnosis of hypothyroidism due to Hashimoto's thyroiditis (high levels of serum
             antithyroid autoantibodies (antiTPO, anti-TgAb).

        For Controls:

          -  Healthy individuals 5 to 18 years old.

          -  BMI for age between 15th and 85th percentile (z-score between -1 and +1).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        For patients

          -  Presence of euthyroidsm, subclinical hypothyroidism, hyperthyroidism.

          -  Pre-existing medical treatment for clinical hypothyroidism.

          -  Taking other medications (eg growth hormone, corticosteroids) in the last 3 months.

          -  Taking food supplements (eg omega-3 fatty acids, amino acids) in the last 3 months.

          -  Concomitant endocrine, metabolic, degenerative and / or chronic diseases other than
             obesity (eg diabetes, hyper / hypo-cortisolemia, cardiovascular diseases, kidney
             diseases, myasthenia, neurological diseases, psychiatric disorders eg anorexia
             nervosa, cancer, anemia, celiac disease, chromosomal abnormalities eg syndrome Turner,
             Down, etc).

          -  Participation in any daily organized physical activity (sport), more than 1 hour per
             day.

          -  Presence of menstrual disorders in adolescent girls.

          -  Having any kind of nutrition/dietary intervention (eg weight loss diet, hypocaloric,
             ketogenic, low-protein diet), in the last 6 months.

        For Controls:

          -  Presence of any form of thyroid disease.

          -  Presence of any endocrine, metabolic, degenerative and / or chronic disease (eg
             diabetes, hyper/ hypo-cortisolemia, obesity, metabolic syndrome, cardiovascular
             diseases, kidney diseases, myasthenia, neurological diseases, psychiatric disorders eg
             anorexia nervosa, cancer, anemia, celiac disease, chromosomal abnormalities eg
             syndrome Turner, Down, etc).

          -  Taking any medication (eg growth hormone, corticosteroids) in the last 3 months.

          -  Taking food supplements (eg omega-3 fatty acids, amino acids) in the last 3 months.

          -  Participation in any daily organized physical activity (sport), more than 1 hour per
             day. Presence of menstrual disorders in adolescent girls.

          -  Having any kind of nutrition/dietary intervention (eg weight loss diet, hypocaloric,
             ketogenic, low-protein diet), in the last 6 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Assimina Galli-Tsinopoulou, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Unit of Pediatric Endocrinology, Diabetes and Metabolism-4th Department of Pediatrics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Assimina Galli-Tsinopoulou, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>2310991537</phone>
    <phone_ext>+30</phone_ext>
    <email>agalli@auth.gr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unit of Pediatric Endocrinology, Diabetes and Metabolism-4th Department of Pediatrics, Medical School of Aristotle University of Thessaloniki</name>
      <address>
        <city>Thessaloniki</city>
        <zip>56403</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Assimina Galli-Tsinopoulou, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>2310991537</phone>
      <phone_ext>+30</phone_ext>
      <email>agalli@auth.gr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pavlos Drongitis, RD,MSc</last_name>
      <phone>2310991537</phone>
      <phone_ext>+30</phone_ext>
      <email>droggpaul@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Assimina Galli-Tsinopoulou, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pavlos Drongitis, RD,MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eleni Papaconstantinou, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dalia Malkova, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adams AC, Astapova I, Fisher FM, Badman MK, Kurgansky KE, Flier JS, Hollenberg AN, Maratos-Flier E. Thyroid hormone regulates hepatic expression of fibroblast growth factor 21 in a PPARalpha-dependent manner. J Biol Chem. 2010 May 7;285(19):14078-82. doi: 10.1074/jbc.C110.107375. Epub 2010 Mar 17.</citation>
    <PMID>20236931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Astrup A, Buemann B, Toubro S, Ranneries C, Raben A. Low resting metabolic rate in subjects predisposed to obesity: a role for thyroid status. Am J Clin Nutr. 1996 Jun;63(6):879-83.</citation>
    <PMID>8644681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barbesino G, Chiovato L. The genetics of Hashimoto's disease. Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am. 2000 Jun;29(2):357-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10874534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coskun T, Bina HA, Schneider MA, Dunbar JD, Hu CC, Chen Y, Moller DE, Kharitonenkov A. Fibroblast growth factor 21 corrects obesity in mice. Endocrinology. 2008 Dec;149(12):6018-27. doi: 10.1210/en.2008-0816. Epub 2008 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18687777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dayan CM, Daniels GH. Chronic autoimmune thyroiditis. N Engl J Med. 1996 Jul 11;335(2):99-107. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8649497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dostálová I, Kaválková P, Haluzíková D, Lacinová Z, Mráz M, Papezová H, Haluzík M. Plasma concentrations of fibroblast growth factors 19 and 21 in patients with anorexia nervosa. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2008 Sep;93(9):3627-32. doi: 10.1210/jc.2008-0746. Epub 2008 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>18559909</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Griffiths M, Payne PR, Stunkard AJ, Rivers JP, Cox M. Metabolic rate and physical development in children at risk of obesity. Lancet. 1990 Jul 14;336(8707):76-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1975323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanks LJ, Casazza K, Ashraf AP, Wallace S, Gutiérrez OM. Fibroblast growth factor-21, body composition, and insulin resistance in pre-pubertal and early pubertal males and females. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2015 Apr;82(4):550-6. doi: 10.1111/cen.12552. Epub 2014 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>25039824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iglesias P, Selgas R, Romero S, Díez JJ. Biological role, clinical significance, and therapeutic possibilities of the recently discovered metabolic hormone fibroblastic growth factor 21. Eur J Endocrinol. 2012 Sep;167(3):301-9. doi: 10.1530/EJE-12-0357. Epub 2012 Jun 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22740503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim KH, Lee MS. FGF21 as a Stress Hormone: The Roles of FGF21 in Stress Adaptation and the Treatment of Metabolic Diseases. Diabetes Metab J. 2014 Aug;38(4):245-51. doi: 10.4093/dmj.2014.38.4.245. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25215270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee P, Linderman JD, Smith S, Brychta RJ, Wang J, Idelson C, Perron RM, Werner CD, Phan GQ, Kammula US, Kebebew E, Pacak K, Chen KY, Celi FS. Irisin and FGF21 are cold-induced endocrine activators of brown fat function in humans. Cell Metab. 2014 Feb 4;19(2):302-9. doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2013.12.017.</citation>
    <PMID>24506871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee Y, Park YJ, Ahn HY, Lim JA, Park KU, Choi SH, Park DJ, Oh BC, Jang HC, Yi KH. Plasma FGF21 levels are increased in patients with hypothyroidism independently of lipid profile. Endocr J. 2013;60(8):977-83. Epub 2013 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23759753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mai K, Schwarz F, Bobbert T, Andres J, Assmann A, Pfeiffer AF, Spranger J. Relation between fibroblast growth factor-21, adiposity, metabolism, and weight reduction. Metabolism. 2011 Feb;60(2):306-11. doi: 10.1016/j.metabol.2010.02.016. Epub 2010 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20362303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAninch EA, Bianco AC. Thyroid hormone signaling in energy homeostasis and energy metabolism. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2014 Apr;1311:77-87. doi: 10.1111/nyas.12374. Epub 2014 Feb 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24697152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mraz M, Bartlova M, Lacinova Z, Michalsky D, Kasalicky M, Haluzikova D, Matoulek M, Dostalova I, Humenanska V, Haluzik M. Serum concentrations and tissue expression of a novel endocrine regulator fibroblast growth factor-21 in patients with type 2 diabetes and obesity. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2009 Sep;71(3):369-75. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2265.2008.03502.x. Epub 2008 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19702724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Müller TD, Tschöp MH. Play down protein to play up metabolism? J Clin Invest. 2014 Sep;124(9):3691-3. doi: 10.1172/JCI77508. Epub 2014 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25133420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nakamura MT, Yudell BE, Loor JJ. Regulation of energy metabolism by long-chain fatty acids. Prog Lipid Res. 2014 Jan;53:124-44. doi: 10.1016/j.plipres.2013.12.001. Epub 2013 Dec 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24362249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pyrżak B, Demkow U, Kucharska AM. Brown Adipose Tissue and Browning Agents: Irisin and FGF21 in the Development of Obesity in Children and Adolescents. Adv Exp Med Biol. 2015;866:25-34. doi: 10.1007/5584_2015_149. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26022904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Santini F, Marzullo P, Rotondi M, Ceccarini G, Pagano L, Ippolito S, Chiovato L, Biondi B. Mechanisms in endocrinology: the crosstalk between thyroid gland and adipose tissue: signal integration in health and disease. Eur J Endocrinol. 2014 Oct;171(4):R137-52. doi: 10.1530/EJE-14-0067. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25214234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skarpa V, Kousta E, Tertipi A, Anyfandakis K, Vakaki M, Dolianiti M, Fotinou A, Papathanasiou A. Epidemiological characteristics of children with autoimmune thyroid disease. Hormones (Athens). 2011 Jul-Sep;10(3):207-14.</citation>
    <PMID>22001131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vaidya B, Kendall-Taylor P, Pearce SH. The genetics of autoimmune thyroid disease. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2002 Dec;87(12):5385-97. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12466323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woelnerhanssen B, Peterli R, Steinert RE, Peters T, Borbély Y, Beglinger C. Effects of postbariatric surgery weight loss on adipokines and metabolic parameters: comparison of laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass and laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy--a prospective randomized trial. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2011 Sep-Oct;7(5):561-8. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2011.01.044. Epub 2011 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21429816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu J, Lloyd DJ, Hale C, Stanislaus S, Chen M, Sivits G, Vonderfecht S, Hecht R, Li YS, Lindberg RA, Chen JL, Jung DY, Zhang Z, Ko HJ, Kim JK, Véniant MM. Fibroblast growth factor 21 reverses hepatic steatosis, increases energy expenditure, and improves insulin sensitivity in diet-induced obese mice. Diabetes. 2009 Jan;58(1):250-9. doi: 10.2337/db08-0392. Epub 2008 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18840786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang A, Sieglaff DH, York JP, Suh JH, Ayers SD, Winnier GE, Kharitonenkov A, Pin C, Zhang P, Webb P, Xia X. Thyroid hormone receptor regulates most genes independently of fibroblast growth factor 21 in liver. J Endocrinol. 2015 Mar;224(3):289-301. doi: 10.1530/JOE-14-0440. Epub 2014 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25501997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Aristotle University Of Thessaloniki</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Assimina Galli-Tsinopoulou</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thyroiditis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hashimoto Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

