<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02724969</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO16020007</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5R00NR015106</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02724969</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Mobile, Semi-automated Text Message-based Intervention to Prevent Perceived Low or Insufficient Milk Supply</brief_title>
  <acronym>MILK</acronym>
  <official_title>A Mobile, Semi-automated Text Message-based Intervention to Prevent Perceived Low or Insufficient Milk Supply</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this pilot randomized trial is to determine the effectiveness, feasibility,
      and acceptability of a mobile, semi-automated text message-based intervention (MILK) to
      prevent perceived low or insufficient milk supply (PIM) among mothers without prior
      breastfeeding experience. PIM is the leading cause of premature breastfeeding cessation, and
      prior work shows that it is often rooted in low breastfeeding self-efficacy and
      misconceptions about lactation physiology and trajectory. The MILK intervention is designed
      to address PIM, as well as other common breastfeeding problems via semi-automated text
      messages of prenatal and postpartum breastfeeding education and support. Messages are
      time-sensitive (e.g., specific to gestational age, time since delivery) and based on the
      Breastfeeding Self-Efficacy (Social Cognitive) Theory; they are also modeled from pilot work
      that investigated how first-time mothers view, manage and describe breastfeeding problems.
      Messages were vetted with clinical lactation experts, as well as pregnant and postpartum
      women with no other children.

      The MILK intervention will be trialed against a control intervention group, who will receive
      general perinatal education through the national Text4Baby system. The investigators will
      recruit approximately 186 healthy, pregnant women at 13-25 weeks gestation from Magee Women's
      Hospital clinics and outpatient sites. Women will be randomized via computer-generated simple
      randomization to the experimental or control intervention. Both groups will receive text
      messages 3-5 times per week from week 25 of pregnancy through week 8 postpartum. Measured
      outcomes of interest will include perceived breast milk supply, breastfeeding confidence,
      maternal anxiety, breastfeeding exclusivity, and breastfeeding duration. Data will be
      collected at baseline (13-25 gestational weeks), 34-36 gestational weeks, and at 1, 2, 4, and
      8 weeks postpartum via online survey or telephone call. To assess the potential longer-term
      impact of the intervention, breastfeeding continuation and exclusivity will be reassessed via
      telephone at 6 months postpartum. Between group and group x time differences in outcome
      measures will be examined graphically and via linear mixed modeling. To inform modifications
      to MILK, telephone interviews will be conducted with a subset of participants in each group
      to assess and compare intervention use, burdens and challenges, and suggested alterations (8
      weeks).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the MILK Trial is to examine and compare the effectiveness, feasibility, and
      acceptability of a semi-automated, text-based, theory-driven intervention (&quot;MILK&quot;
      intervention) to prevent perceived insufficient milk and its potential inter-related
      sequelae, including maternal anxiety and early breastfeeding cessation, among mothers without
      breastfeeding experience who intend to exclusively or nearly exclusively breastfeed.
      Specifically, the investigators will:

        1. Determine the effect of the MILK intervention on perceived insufficient milk supply
           (PIM) and related maternal psychological and behavioral sequelae.

           Compared to the control intervention group (&quot;Text4Baby&quot;), the investigators hypothesize
           that MILK participants will have a perception of greater breast milk volume/supply,
           higher self-reported breastfeeding confidence, lower anxiety scores, and longer duration
           of exclusive breastfeeding.

        2. Assess the feasibility of a semi-automated text-based PIM intervention (MILK) for
           mothers.

      The investigators will compare characteristics of women who are and who are not eligible for,
      chose to participate in, and complete this randomized pilot intervention study. The
      investigators will also conduct post-study individual interviews with mothers to determine
      how the interventions were used and perceived (e.g., burden, challenges).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 9, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Lactation consultant providing assistance has no knowledge of group assignment. Statistician completing final analysis of data will be blinded to group assignment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perception of milk supply</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed via the H &amp; H Lactation Scale (21-item Likert scale)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breastfeeding self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>assessed via 14-item Breastfeeding Self-Efficacy Scale (Likert scale)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed via Likert scale (8-item combined Emotional Distress-Anxiety scale and Perceived Stress Scale)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breastfeeding continuation</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>whether mom is doing any breastfeeding; assessed via questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breastfeeding exclusivity</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>whether mom is feeding 100% breast milk; assessed via questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">186</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Feeding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MILK intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive the MILK text message intervention, which consists of semi-automated text messages sent to women's cellular phones 3-5 times per week beginning Week 25 of pregnancy, through 8 weeks postpartum, specific to breastfeeding support and prevention of perceived insufficient milk supply.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Text4Baby control intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive the Text4Baby text message intervention, which consists of automated texts sent to women's cellular phones 3-5 times per week from Week 25 of pregnancy through the postpartum period from the national Text4Baby system. Messages provide general prenatal and postpartum support, including breastfeeding.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MILK or Text4Baby text message intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>MILK text message intervention encompasses prenatal and postpartum breastfeeding support and education text messages. Text4Baby text message intervention encompasses prenatal and postpartum text messages about pregnancy, infant care, and postpartum issues.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MILK intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Text4Baby control intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Pregnant women who:

          1. are ≥ 18 years;

          2. are between 13-25 gestational weeks;

          3. have no prior breastfeeding experience or other living biological children;

          4. have a personal cell phone with internet access and an unlimited text message plan;
             and

          5. intend to exclusively, or nearly exclusively breastfeed (&lt;2 ounces of artificial milk
             per day) for at least 2 months postpartum; (6) plan to deliver their infant at MWH.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Maternal, fetal, or neonatal conditions or complications with the potential to
             physiologically compromise breastfeeding or milk supply (e.g., history of breast
             reduction surgery, infant cardiac defects, postpartum infant ventilator dependence);

          2. current gestation of ≥ 1 fetus;

          3. contraindications to breastfeeding as specified by the American Academy of Pediatrics
             (e.g., HIV+ status).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jill Demirci, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Melissa Glasser, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>412-622-4370</phone>
    <email>mlg130@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jill Demirci, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>412-648-9236</phone>
    <email>jvr5@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15261</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Glasser, Phd</last_name>
      <phone>412-622-4370</phone>
      <email>mlg130@pitt.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jill Demirci, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 31, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jill R. Demirci, PhD, RN, IBCLC</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>text messaging</keyword>
  <keyword>short message service</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

