<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03269227</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRST163.01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03269227</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Accelerated Hypofractionated Radiotherapy in the Treatment of Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma</brief_title>
  <acronym>MesoRT</acronym>
  <official_title>Accelerated Hypofractionated Radiotherapy in the Treatment of Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituto Scientifico Romagnolo per lo Studio e la cura dei Tumori</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Scientifico Romagnolo per lo Studio e la cura dei Tumori</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a monocentric prospective study of radiotherapy using accelerated hypofractionation
      with Tomotherapy in Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma (MPM) patients after pleurectomy /
      decortication (P / D) or biopsy.

      The treatment will be delivered using Tomotherapy, that allows to adopt dose accelerated
      hypofraction criteria. Treatment duration is 5 consecutive days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The role of radiation therapy remains to be defined in unresected MPM or after P/D. For the
      latter, local control remains the primary objective but radiotherapy (RT) is a challenge
      because of the risk of pneumonia in the intact lung. There are no specific clinical data to
      support the use of adjuvant radiation therapy after P/D or definitive radiation therapy after
      biopsy-based diagnosis for patients not amenable to surgery.

      However, recent publications on Intensity Modulated Radiotherapy (IMRT) and conventional
      fractionation after P/D or biopsy have shown the feasibility and acceptable toxicity profile
      of the treatment.

      The investigators submitted a retrospective analysis of accelerated hypofractionated
      Intensity modulated arc therapy (IMAT) using TomoTherapy in MPM following P/D or diagnostic
      biopsy. In the investigators experience of MPM, treatment of the intact lung with pleural
      IMAT using helical Tomotherapy is a safe and feasible option with an acceptable lung toxicity
      profile. The results obtained in terms of toxicity were encouraging. In fact, the
      investigators only observed one case of G3 pneumonia, and the patient in question is still
      alive and off oxygen therapy. Patient compliance with this short-course treatment was also
      very good.

      Overall, the investigators found that accelerated hypofractionation with IMAT was feasible at
      the dose delivered and had an acceptable toxicity profile. So the investigators want to
      propose this protocol for treatment of MPM in intact lung to improve local control.

      In patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma who underwent pleurectomy / decortications
      (P/D) or only diagnostic biopsy, it is difficult to deliver a tumoricidal dose of radiation
      to the pleura due to the presence of the ipsilateral lung. In recent years, the investigators
      have implemented a technique for irradiation of the pleura in intact lung, using accelerated
      hypofractionation with Tomotherapy in an attempt to reduce as far as possible, the dose to
      the ipsilateral lung. The aim of the treatment was palliation. The investigators analyzed the
      data of 36 patients with MPM, with a long follow-up without recording death cases related to
      radiation treatment or radiation pneumonitis grade 4.

      In view of these data, the aim of this study is to increase the dose of treatment in patients
      suffering from MPM after P/D or biopsy.

      The study will evaluate the feasibility of the treatment through the study of pulmonary acute
      and late toxicity; The treatment will be delivered using Tomotherapy that allows to adopt
      dose accelerated hypofraction criteria. Treatment duration is 5 consecutive days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 14, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events [Safety and Tolerability]</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Acute and late toxicity evaluation by Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.03, performing strumental tests (CT scan, spirometry) to evaluate adverse events including pulmonary toxicity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>time from randomization until death for any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>the assessment of disease control rate (DCR) defined as proportion of patients with complete response (CR), partial response (PR) and stable disease (SD) for patients with evaluable disease using the Modified RECIST criteria for assessment of response in malignant pleural mesotelioma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time to progessione (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>calculation of time to progression (TTP) for patients without evidence of disease or with not evaluable disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Accelerated hypofractionation with Tomotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tomotherapy Treatment Planning System (TPS) will be used for treatment plannings.
Patient' set-up daily control through Tomo-image (CT megavoltage) immediately before each sitting of all the patients.
Prescription dose to the target: 30 Gy in 5 daily fraction (at the reference isodose 60-70%) with an internal increasing inhomogenous dose of up to 37.5 Gy-40 Gy for Gross Tumor Volume (GTV).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Accelerated hypofractionation with Tomotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Tomotherapy TPS will be used for treatment plannings. Patient' set-up daily control through Tomo-image (CT megavoltage) immediately before each sitting of all the patients.
Prescription doses:
Prescription dose to the target: 30 Gy in 5 daily fraction (at the reference isodose 60-70%) with an internal increasing inhomogenous dose of up to 37.5 Gy-40 Gy for GTV.
Steroids (methylprednisolone 4 mg daily) should be used from day 1 of radiotherapy to day + 30 after the end of the treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Accelerated hypofractionation with Tomotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed MPM

          2. Karnofsky Performance status scale 70-100 (see Appendix B)

          3. Male or female, Aged &gt;= 18 and ≤ 85 years

          4. Life expectancy greater than 6 months

          5. All clinical and pathological stage with the exclusion of contralateral mediastinum
             involvement (N3) and M1

          6. Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  leukocytes &gt;3,000/microL

               -  absolute neutrophil count &gt;1,500/microL

               -  platelets &gt;100,000/microL

               -  aspartate transaminase(AST)/alanine transaminase (ALT) &lt;2.5 X institutional upper
                  limit of normal

               -  creatinine within normal institutional limits

               -  glycemia &lt; 100 mg/dl

          7. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

          8. Forced expiratory volume in the 1st second(FEV1) ≥ 50

          9. Patients after biopsy must have measurable disease defined as at least one lesion that
             can be accurately measured according to modified RECIST criteria; for resected
             patients no more than 3 months are allowed for RT start.

         10. Written informed consent signed and dated before starting study procedure.

         11. Female participants of child bearing potential and male participants whose partner is
             of child bearing potential must be willing to ensure that they or their partner use
             effective contraception during the study and for 4 months thereafter.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous thorax radiotherapy

          2. Chemotherapy is allowed but completed 3 weeks before RT starts

          3. Participation in another clinical trial with any investigational agents within 30 days
             prior to study screening.

          4. Patients with M1 have to be excluded to this study

          5. FEV1 &lt; 50

          6. Age &gt;85 years old

          7. Respiratory needing oxygen therapy

          8. Interstitial pneumopathy

          9. Active pneumonitis

         10. Fissural disease

         11. Contralateral mediastinum involvement (N3) and M1

         12. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elisabetta Parisi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Istituto Scientifico Romagnolo per lo Studio e la Cura dei Tumori, Via Maroncelli 40, 47014 Meldola, ITALY</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Oriana Nanni</last_name>
    <phone>+39 0543 739266</phone>
    <email>oriana.nanni@irst.emr.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SC Radiotherapy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Meldola</city>
        <zip>47014</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elisabetta Parisi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0543 7391100</phone>
      <email>elisabetta.parisi@irst.emr.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 29, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Tomotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypofractionation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mesothelioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

