<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03260205</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SPD489-347</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03260205</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy Study in Preschool Children Aged 4-5 Years With Attention-deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Randomized, Double-blind, Multicenter, Parallel-group, Placebo-controlled, Fixed-Dose Safety and Efficacy Study of SPD489 Compared With Placebo in Preschool Children Aged 4-5 Years With Attention-deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shire</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shire</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if an investigational treatment is effective in
      improving the total score on the ADHD-RS-IV Preschool Version in children 4-5 years old
      diagnosed with ADHD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 6, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 7, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 7, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Clinician-Administered Attention-deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Rating Scale-IV (ADHD-RS-IV) Preschool Version Total Score at Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>ADHD-RS-IV Preschool Version was adapted from the ADHD Rating Scale-IV and provides examples appropriate for the developmental level of preschool children. The ADHD-RS-IV Preschool Version is an 18-item questionnaire that requires the respondent to rate the frequency of occurrence of ADHD symptoms as defined by Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition-Text Revision (DSM-IV-TR) criteria. Each item is scored on a 4-point scale ranging from 0 (never or rarely) to 3 (very often) with total scores ranging from 0-54. The 18 items may be grouped into 2 subscales: hyperactivity/impulsivity (even numbered items 2-18) and inattentiveness (odd numbered items 1-17).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression- Global Improvement (CGI-I) Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>CGI-I provides an overall assessment of global symptom improvement. It is a 7-point scale ranging from 1 (very much improved) to 7 (very much worse).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response Relationship in Preschool Children with Attention-deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Dose response relationship will be evaluated by using the ADHD-RS Preschool Version Total Score. ADHD-RS-IV Preschool Version was adapted from the ADHD Rating Scale-IV and provides examples appropriate for the developmental level of preschool children. The ADHD-RS-IV Preschool Version is an 18-item questionnaire that requires the respondent to rate the frequency of occurrence of ADHD symptoms as defined by Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition-Text Revision (DSM-IV-TR) criteria. Each item is scored on a 4-point scale ranging from 0 (never or rarely) to 3 (very often) with total scores ranging from 0-54. The 18 items may be grouped into 2 subscales: hyperactivity/impulsivity (even numbered items 2-18) and inattentiveness (odd numbered items 1-17).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study treatment up to 10 days after the last dose of investigational drug</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event (AE) is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a pharmaceutical product and that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment. TEAEs are defined as AEs that start or deteriorate on or after the date of the first dose of investigational product and no later than 3 days following the last dose of investigational product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Vital Sign Abnormalities Reported as Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study treatment up to 10 days after the last dose of investigational drug</time_frame>
    <description>Vital sign assessments will include blood pressure, pulse and respiratory rate. Vital sign abnormalities are recorded and reported as AE. An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a pharmaceutical product and that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of Height</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study treatment, Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Height should be measured in inches or centimeters without shoes with the participant standing on a flat surface and with chin parallel to the floor..</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of Body Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study treatment up to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Weight should be measured in pounds or kilograms without shoes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Clinical Laboratory Abnormalities Reported as Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study treatment up to 10 days after the last dose of investigational drug</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical laboratory evaluations include biochemistry and endocrinology, hematology, and urinalysis. Clinical laboratory abnormalities will be recorded and reported as AE. An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a pharmaceutical product and that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Electrocardiogram (ECG) Abnormalities Reported as Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study treatment up to 10 days after the last dose of investigational drug</time_frame>
    <description>12-lead ECG will be recorded and measured with the participant in rested supine position for 5 minutes. ECG abnormalities will be recorded and reported as AE. An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a pharmaceutical product and that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Children's Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ) is a parent report questionnaire designed to screen for the most common sleep problems in children, and consists of 33 items for scoring and several extra items intended to provide administrators with other potentially useful information about respondents. The instrument evaluates the child's sleep based on behavior within 8 different subscales: bedtime resistance, sleep-onset delay, sleep duration, sleep anxiety, night wakings, parasomnias, sleep-disordered breathing, and daytime sleepiness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of study treatment up to Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) is a semi-structured interview that captures the occurrence, severity, and frequency of suicide-related thoughts and behaviors during the assessment period. The interview includes definitions and suggested questions to solicit the type of information needed to determine if a suicide-related thought or behavior occurred. The C-SSRS contains 2 required items pertaining to suicidal ideation, 4 required items pertaining to suicidal behavior, and 1 required item pertaining to non-suicidal but self-injurious behavior. In situations where there is a positive response to the screening questions, there are 8 additional suicidal ideation items and 4 additional suicidal behavior items which are completed. Thus, there is a maximum of 19 items to be completed. The assessment is done by the nature of the responses, not by a numbered scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">195</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participant will receive placebo matching to SPD489 (Lisdexamfetamine dimesylate) capsule for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SPD489 (Lisdexamfetamine dimesylate)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be randomized to receive SPD489 capsule in a 5:5:5:5:6 ratio to SPD489 5, 10, 20, 30 milligram (mg) orally once daily for 6 weeks. Dosing will begin with the lowest strength of SPD489 (5 mg), and will be titrated until the randomly assigned fixed-dose is reached.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo matching to SPD489 (Lisdexamfetamine dimesylate) capsule for 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SPD489 (Lisdexamfetamine dimesylate)</intervention_name>
    <description>SPD489 capsule in a 5:5:5:5:6 ratio to 5, 10, 20, 30 mg orally once daily for 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SPD489 (Lisdexamfetamine dimesylate)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SPD489</intervention_name>
    <description>SPD489</description>
    <arm_group_label>SPD489 (Lisdexamfetamine dimesylate)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is a male or female aged 4-5 years inclusive at the time of consent

          -  Participant's parent(s) or legally authorized representative (LAR) must provide
             signature of informed consent, and there must be documentation of assent (if
             applicable) by the participant before completing any study related procedures.

          -  Participant and parent(s)/LAR are willing and able to comply with all of the testing
             and requirements defined in the protocol, including oversight of morning dosing.

          -  Participant must meet DSM-IV-TR criteria for a primary diagnosis of ADHD (any
             sub-type).

          -  Participant has an ADHD-RS-IV Preschool Version Total Score at the baseline visit
             (Visit 0) greater than or equal to 28 for boys, and greater than or equal to 24 for
             girls.

          -  Participant has a Clinical Global Impressions - Severity of Illness (CGI-S) score
             greater than or equal to 4 at the baseline visit (Visit 0).

          -  Participant has a Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test standard score of greater than or
             equal to 70 at the screening visit (Visit -1).

          -  Participant has undergone an adequate course of non-pharmacological treatment or has a
             severe enough condition to consider enrollment without undergoing prior
             non-pharmacological treatment.

          -  Participant has participated in a structured group activity (e.g, preschool, sports,
             Sunday school) so as to assess symptoms and impairment in a setting outside the home.

          -  Participant has lived with the same parent(s) or guardian for greater than or equal to
             6 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is required to or anticipates the need to take any prohibited medications
             or medications that have central nervous system (CNS) effects or have an effect on
             performance. Stable use of bronchodilator inhalers is not exclusionary.

          -  Participant has taken another investigational product or has taken part in a clinical
             study within 30 days prior to the screening visit (Visit -1).

          -  Participant is well-controlled on his/her current ADHD medication with acceptable
             tolerability.

          -  Participant has a concurrent chronic or acute illness, disability, or other condition
             that might confound the results of safety assessments or may increase risk to the
             participant..

          -  Participant has glaucoma.

          -  Participant has failed to fully respond to an adequate course of amphetamine therapy.

          -  Participant has a documented allergy, hypersensitivity, or intolerance to amphetamine
             or to any excipients in the investigational product.

          -  Participant has a known family history of sudden cardiac death or ventricular
             arrhythmia.

          -  Participant has a blood pressure measurement greater than or equal to 95th percentile
             for age, sex, and height at the screening visit (Visit -1) or the baseline visit
             (Visit 0) or history of moderate or severe hypertension.

          -  Participant has a known history of symptomatic cardiovascular disease, unexplained
             syncope, exertional chest pain,advanced arteriosclerosis, structural cardiac
             abnormality, cardiomyopathy, serious heart rhythm abnormalities, coronary artery
             disease, or other serious cardiac problems.

          -  Participant has any clinically significant clinical laboratory abnormalities at the
             screening visit (Visit -1) or electrocardiogram (ECG) at screening visit (Visit-1) or
             baseline visit (Visit 0) based on investigator judgment.

          -  Participant has current abnormal thyroid function, defined as abnormal thyroid
             stimulating hormone (TSH) and thyroxine (T4) at the screening visit (Visit -1).
             Treatment with a stable dose of thyroid medication for at least 3 months is permitted.

          -  Participant has a current, controlled (requiring medication or therapy) or
             uncontrolled, co-morbid psychiatric disorder including but not limited to any of the
             below co-morbid Axis I disorders and Axis II disorders:

             i. post-traumatic stress disorder or adjustment disorder ii. bipolar illness,
             psychosis, or a family history of these disorders iii. pervasive developmental
             disorder iv. obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) v. psychosis/schizophrenia vi. a
             serious tic disorder, or a family history of Tourette's disorder vii. Participant is
             currently considered a suicide risk in the opinion of the investigator, has previously
             made a suicide attempt, or has a prior history of, or is currently demonstrating
             active suicidal ideation.

        viii. a history of physical, sexual, or emotional abuse ix. any other disorder or agitated
        state that in the opinion of the investigator, contraindicates SPD489 or lisdexamfetamine
        dimesylate treatment or confound efficacy or safety assessments.

          -  Participant has initiated behavioral therapy within 1 month of the baseline visit
             (Visit 0). Participant may not initiate behavioral therapy during the study.

          -  Participant has a height less than equal to (&lt;=) 5th percentile for age and sex at the
             screening visit (Visit -1).

          -  Participant has a weight &lt;= 5th percentile for age and sex at the screening visit
             (Visit -1).

          -  Participant lives with anyone who currently abuses stimulants or cocaine.

          -  Participant has a history of seizures (other than infantile febrile seizures).

          -  Participant is taking any medication that is excluded per the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shire Physician</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shire</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shire Contact</last_name>
    <phone>+1 866 842 5335</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTransparency@shire.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harmonex, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dothan</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>36303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Barbara A Baldwin</last_name>
      <phone>334-836-2000</phone>
      <email>bbaldwin@harmonex.us</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nelson Handal-Thome</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Preferred Research Partners, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sun Valley Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Imperial</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92251</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alliance for Wellness d/b/a Alliance for Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Long Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90807</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrea Hilliard</last_name>
      <phone>562-548-8500</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Zarate Rowell</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asclepes Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Panorama City</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91402</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychiatric Centers at San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Avail Clinical Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>DeLand</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32720</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarkis Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Neuroscience Solutions, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32256</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Valerie Arnold</last_name>
      <phone>901-843-1045</phone>
      <email>varnold@cnshealthcare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nadita Joshi-Jones</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Research Group of Central Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange City</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32763</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Megan McMahon</last_name>
      <phone>386-775-7627</phone>
      <email>mmcmahon@mrgcf.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adly Thebaud</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Neuroscience Solutions</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia Brown</last_name>
      <phone>407-425-5100</phone>
      <phone_ext>204</phone_ext>
      <email>pbrown@cnshealthcare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Molpus Robert</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>APG Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida Department Of Psychiatry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33613</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>iResearch Atlanta LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lake Charles Clinical Trials</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lake Charles</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70629</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kennedy Krieger Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rochester Center for Behavioral Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester Hills</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48306</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Neurophysiology Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sterling Heights</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48314</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Premier Psychiatric Reseach Institute, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lincoln</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68526</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelly Espenschade</last_name>
      <phone>402-817-2235</phone>
      <email>kespenschade@premierpsych.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Walter Dufffy</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Psychiatry and Behavioral Medicine, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89128</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals Case Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacqui Lingler</last_name>
      <email>Jacqui.lingler@uhhospitals.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nora McNamara</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Associates of Fairfield, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fairfield</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45014</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IPS Research Company</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hossein Dabiri</last_name>
      <phone>405-235-8188</phone>
      <email>hdabiri@ipsresearch.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Louise Thurman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oklahoma Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Chastain</last_name>
      <phone>405-753-4994</phone>
      <email>sarah@rivusinstintitue.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M. Lane Peyton</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Paradigm Research Professionals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cutting Edge Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73120</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michelle Vernon</last_name>
      <phone>405-603-8068</phone>
      <phone_ext>3201</phone_ext>
      <email>mvernon@cuttingedgeresearch.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Willis Holloway</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cyn3rgy Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gresham</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rainbow Research Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barnwell</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29812</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan P. Moskow</last_name>
      <phone>803-541-7920</phone>
      <email>susan.moskow@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Abraham Moskow</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carolina Clinical Trials, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Coastal Carolina Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mount Pleasant</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29464</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robin Swinks</last_name>
      <email>rswinks@coastalcarolina.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Robbins</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Neuroscience Solutions, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38119</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jason Bain</last_name>
      <email>jbain@cnshealthcare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Valerie Arnold</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Neuroscience Solutions</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38119</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Valerie Arnold</last_name>
      <phone>901-843-1945</phone>
      <email>varnold@cnshealthcare.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Valerie Arnold</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BioBehavioral Research of Austin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78759</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bayou City Research Limited</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Red Oak Psychiatry Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77090</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Road Runner Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Family Psychiatry of the Woodlands</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Woodlands</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77381</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Research Partners, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Petersburg</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23805</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwest Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bellevue</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leslie Gills</last_name>
      <phone>425-453-0404</phone>
      <email>lgills@nwcrc.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arifula Khan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>SPD489</keyword>
  <keyword>Lisdexamfetamine dimesylate</keyword>
  <keyword>ADHD</keyword>
  <keyword>hyperactivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurobehavioral disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lisdexamfetamine Dimesylate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

