<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03267758</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO27955</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03267758</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Probiotic Supplementation on Endothelial Function II</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Probiotic Supplementation on Endothelial Function II</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Researchers at MCW have discovered a new pathway that links the type of bacteria present in
      the intestines to the severity of heart attacks. This discovery of a relationship between
      intestinal bacteria, bacterial metabolites, and severity of heart attacks means that for the
      first time, the investigators may be able to determine a person's probability of having a
      heart attack via non-conventional risk factors. This may provide opportunities for novel
      diagnostic tests as well as a potential for therapeutic intervention. The link between gut
      microbiota and the severity of heart attacks may also lead to novel therapeutic approaches
      (probiotics, non-absorbable antibiotics) to prevent heart attacks from happening. The studies
      proposed will test the hypothesis that altered intestinal microbiota are mechanistically
      linked to the pathogenesis of cardiovascular disease. The investigator's objective is to
      determine whether inflammatory markers in the blood are decreased and endothelial cell
      function improved by a probiotic in patients with established coronary artery disease.
      Furthermore, the investigators wish to elucidate a mechanism by which the gut microbiota
      regulates serum inflammatory markers.

        1. Specific Aim 1 will determine the impact of a probiotic on circulating leptin and TMAO
           levels, conventional risk factors for cardiovascular disease and diabetes (total
           cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, oxidized LDL, triglycerides, C-reactive protein, serum
           amyloid A, fibrinogen and adiponectin, glucose-dependent- insulinotropic polypeptide
           (GIP), glucagon-like-peptide (GLP-1), glucagon, insulin), and their relationship to the
           intestinal microbiota (15 representative microbial groups) as non conventional risk
           factors. Several blood samples will be collected to measure biomarkers. Participants
           will provide periodic stool samples in order to measure gut bacterial biodiversity.
           Lastly, endothelial cell function (flow mediated dilation) will be measured in order to
           assess blood vessel function.

        2. Specific Aim 2 will determine the impact of a probiotic on metabolites derived from the
           intestinal microbiota as candidates for non-conventional risk factors of cardiovascular
           disease. The relationship between metabolites derived from the intestinal microbiota,
           endothelial cell function and risk factors for cardiovascular disease identified in
           Specific Aim 1 will be correlated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recently, a direct link between intestinal microbiota, dietary phosphatidylcholine, and
      promotion of cardiovascular disease has been elegantly demonstrated. In this study, broad
      spectrum antibiotics were employed to disrupt the intestinal microbiota, and metabolomic
      analysis identified 3 metabolites of phosphatidylcholine, including TMAO, linked to
      atherosclerosis. However, the impact of intestinal dysbiosis on the heart and its
      susceptibility to injury from ischemia/reperfusion has not been known until now.

      Novel work has demonstrated a mechanistic link between changes in the intestinal microbiota
      and severity of myocardial infarction. Treatment of Dahl S rats with the commercially
      available probiotic bacterium Lactobacillus plantarum 299v, and a non-absorbed antibiotic
      vancomycin to alter abundance of multiple microbiota reduced circulating leptin levels,
      reduced myocardial infarct size, and improved recovery of post-ischemic mechanical function.
      Pretreatment with leptin abolished cardioprotection by the probiotic and the antibiotic.

      These findings also show the reach of the intestinal microbiota extends far beyond local
      effects to remote organ systems such as the heart and provide support for the metabolomic
      studies to be conducted in Specific Aim 2. The prior discovery of a relationship between
      intestinal microbiota, their metabolites and myocardial infarction provides opportunities for
      novel therapeutic approaches (probiotics, non-absorbable antibiotics and/or microbial
      metabolites) for the treatment and prevention of cardiovascular disease.

      Prior studies indicate an important role of leptin in signaling between the intestinal
      microbiota and the heart. Supplementation of the diet with active cultures of Lactobacillus
      plantarum 299v leads to significant reductions in fibrinogen and LDL-cholesterol, and leptin
      concentrations in smokers. These clinical studies demonstrate that a probiotic is capable of
      decreasing risk factors for cardiovascular disease. Note that neither leptin nor TMAO levels,
      per se, are recognized cardiovascular risk factor. This is currently an area with enormous
      potential for gaining new mechanistic insight and may lead to a therapeutic product or
      clinical use.

      Impaired endothelial function is recognized as an early and modulating process in the
      pathogenesis of atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. Endothelial function is easily
      measurable by non-invasive means and endothelial dysfunction measured non-invasively
      independently predicts future cardiovascular risk in patients both with and without
      clinically apparent cardiovascular disease. Conduit vessel endothelial function in humans is
      commonly quantified by measurement of flow-mediated dilation (FMD) in the brachial artery,
      which represents the endothelium-dependent relaxation of a conduit artery - typically the
      brachial artery - due to an increased blood flow. FMD correlates with impaired
      endothelium-dependent relaxation in the coronary arteries and is a commonly recognized
      &quot;barometer&quot; of cardiovascular risk. Taken together, these data suggest brachial FMD is an
      ideal surrogate marker of cardiovascular risk to monitor the effects of Lactobacillus
      plantarum 299v as proposed in this work.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in baseline flow mediated dilation (FMD) at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and week 6</time_frame>
    <description>This is a measurement of endothelial function in the brachial artery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Goodbelly First</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm will consume 1 serving of lactobacillus plantarum 299v daily for first 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation First</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm will be without lactobacillus plantarum 299v daily for first 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Goodbelly first</intervention_name>
    <description>Consumption of 1 serving of Goodbelly probiotic daily for 6 weeks. This will be followed by an observation period for 6 weeks during which the subjects will not consume Goodbelly.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Goodbelly First</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Goodbelly</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>observation first</intervention_name>
    <description>Observation for the first 6 weeks during which time the subjects will not consume Goodbelly. During weeks 6-12 of the study, following the observation period, the subjects will consume Goodbelly for 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Observation First</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 40-75 years old

          -  History of known coronary artery disease (by either history of myocardial infarction,
             angiogram demonstrative &gt;=50% stenosis in at least 1 major epicardial coronary artery,
             or a previous stress test that showed evidence of ischemia that has not been revealed
             to be a false positive test by angiography)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unstable angina or myocardial infarction by history, ECG, and/or enzymatic criteria
             within 1 month of enrollment.

          -  LV dysfunction as defined by an LV ejection fraction documented as &lt; 45% within 1 year
             of enrollment by an echocardiogram, MRI, or nuclear imaging.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension with a blood pressure greater than 170/100 mmHg at the
             screening visit.

          -  Known history of chronic renal insufficiency, liver dysfunction, or cancer besides
             non-melanoma skin carcinomas or localized prostate cancer requiring systemic treatment
             within five years of enrollment.

          -  Known history of cognitive impairment or inability to follow study procedures

          -  Patient with an implanted defibrillator or permanent pacemaker on which the potential
             participant is known to rely upon for greater than 50% of ventricular depolarizations.

          -  Patients who received probiotics, prebiotics, and antibiotics in the last 12 weeks.

          -  Patients with dosing changes of vasoactive medications and HMG-CoA reductase
             inhibitors in the 6 weeks prior to enrollment.

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Widlansky, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Widlansky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>414-456-6737</phone>
    <email>mwidlans@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael E Widlansky</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lam V, Su J, Koprowski S, Hsu A, Tweddell JS, Rafiee P, Gross GJ, Salzman NH, Baker JE. Intestinal microbiota determine severity of myocardial infarction in rats. FASEB J. 2012 Apr;26(4):1727-35. doi: 10.1096/fj.11-197921. Epub 2012 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22247331</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naruszewicz M, Johansson ML, Zapolska-Downar D, Bukowska H. Effect of Lactobacillus plantarum 299v on cardiovascular disease risk factors in smokers. Am J Clin Nutr. 2002 Dec;76(6):1249-55.</citation>
    <PMID>12450890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Widlansky ME, Gokce N, Keaney JF Jr, Vita JA. The clinical implications of endothelial dysfunction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 Oct 1;42(7):1149-60. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14522472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corretti MC, Anderson TJ, Benjamin EJ, Celermajer D, Charbonneau F, Creager MA, Deanfield J, Drexler H, Gerhard-Herman M, Herrington D, Vallance P, Vita J, Vogel R; International Brachial Artery Reactivity Task Force. Guidelines for the ultrasound assessment of endothelial-dependent flow-mediated vasodilation of the brachial artery: a report of the International Brachial Artery Reactivity Task Force. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2002 Jan 16;39(2):257-65. Erratum in: J Am Coll Cardiol 2002 Mar 20;39(6):1082.</citation>
    <PMID>11788217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Celermajer DS, Sorensen KE, Gooch VM, Spiegelhalter DJ, Miller OI, Sullivan ID, Lloyd JK, Deanfield JE. Non-invasive detection of endothelial dysfunction in children and adults at risk of atherosclerosis. Lancet. 1992 Nov 7;340(8828):1111-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1359209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thijssen DH, Black MA, Pyke KE, Padilla J, Atkinson G, Harris RA, Parker B, Widlansky ME, Tschakovsky ME, Green DJ. Assessment of flow-mediated dilation in humans: a methodological and physiological guideline. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2011 Jan;300(1):H2-12. doi: 10.1152/ajpheart.00471.2010. Epub 2010 Oct 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20952670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takase B, Uehata A, Akima T, Nagai T, Nishioka T, Hamabe A, Satomura K, Ohsuzu F, Kurita A. Endothelium-dependent flow-mediated vasodilation in coronary and brachial arteries in suspected coronary artery disease. Am J Cardiol. 1998 Dec 15;82(12):1535-9, A7-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9874063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vita JA, Keaney JF Jr. Endothelial function: a barometer for cardiovascular risk? Circulation. 2002 Aug 6;106(6):640-2.</citation>
    <PMID>12163419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tang WH, Wang Z, Levison BS, Koeth RA, Britt EB, Fu X, Wu Y, Hazen SL. Intestinal microbial metabolism of phosphatidylcholine and cardiovascular risk. N Engl J Med. 2013 Apr 25;368(17):1575-84. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1109400.</citation>
    <PMID>23614584</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 10, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 29, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 30, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael E. Widlansky</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

