<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03262714</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>53834516.0.0000.5347</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03262714</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Dancing on Cardiovascular and Functional Risk Factors in Older Women.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Dancing and Walking on Cardiovascular Risk Factors and Functional Capacity in Older Women: a Randomized Controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this randomized controlled trial is to investigate the effects of a dance
      intervention on cardiovascular risk factors and functional capacity of older women, comparing
      dancing to a walking exercise intervention and to an active control condition (stretching).
      The participants will include women between 60 and 80 years old, with body mass index
      inferior to 35 Kg /m2. The main outcome of this study is the peak oxygen consumption
      (VO2peak). The secondary outcomes are cardiovascular risk associated factors (C-reactive
      protein, TNF-alpha, lipid profile, etc) and functional performance (muscle strength and
      power, balance, gate ability, etc). The experimental design will include 3 parts: 1)
      Pre-intervention assessments: medical evaluation, fasting blood exams, maximum exercise test,
      assessments of body composition, balance, gate ability, muscular strength and power. 2)
      Period of interventions: patients will be randomized to one of the three following groups:
      dance, walking or stretching. The duration of the interventions will be 8 weeks, including 3
      sessions per week for dance and walking, and once a week for the stretching group. Each
      session will last 60 min. 3) Post-intervention assessments: the same protocols of testing as
      pre-intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aging process is characterized by reductions of lean mass simultaneously to increases in
      visceral adipose tissue. Metabolically, this is related to insulin resistance and higher risk
      to develop cardiovascular diseases. Functionally, loss of strength and cardiorespiratory
      fitness may lead to early muscle fatigue onset, which may limit the performance of daily
      activities, and eventually lead to loss of independence with aging. Dancing has been used as
      a form of exercise to improve functional and metabolic outcomes during aging. However, the
      field lacks of randomized controlled trials (RCT) evaluating metabolic outcomes related to
      dance interventions, as well as comparisons of dancing with other types of exercise on
      functional performance and metabolic health of older adults. Therefore, the goal of this
      randomized controlled trial is to investigate the effects of a dance intervention on
      cardiovascular risk factors and functional capacity of older women, comparing dancing to a
      walking exercise intervention and to an active control condition (stretching). Additionally,
      we aim to investigate the acute cardiorespiratory responses of a dance session. The
      participants will include women between 60 and 80 years old, with body mass index inferior to
      35 Kg /m2 and independent for performing daily activities. They should not be engaged in any
      type of regular physical activity in the past 6 months. Exclusion criteria will include type
      2 diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular complications and neurodegenerative diseases. The main
      outcome of this study is the peak oxygen consumption (VO2peak), as it has been associated
      with both, cardiovascular risk and functional performance in aging individuals. The secondary
      outcomes are: (1) cardiovascular risk associated factors: C-reactive protein, TNF-alpha,
      triglycerides, total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, fasting glucose and
      insulin, and homeostatic model assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR). (2) Functional
      performance: muscle strength and power, balance, gate ability and muscle quality. The
      experimental design will include 3 parts: 1) Pre-intervention assessments: medical
      evaluation, fasting blood exams, maximum exercise test, assessments of body composition,
      balance, gate ability, muscular strength and power. 2) Period of interventions: patients will
      be randomized in blocks (randomization.com), in accordance to their VO2peak , to one of the
      three following groups: dance, walking or control. The duration of the dance and walking
      interventions will be 8 weeks, including 3 sessions per week, each lasting 60 min. Dance
      classes will be performed in group in a dance studio, including a variety of rhythms such as
      salsa, jazz and aerobics. Walking sessions will be performed individually or in groups of two
      people, in a treadmill, at the gym. The control group will have 60min stretching classes once
      a week, also for 8 weeks. 3) Post-intervention assessments: the same protocols of testing of
      the pre-interventions assessments will be repeated. All the assessments and interventions
      will be held at the Laboratory of Research in Exercise (LAPEX-UFRGS).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Peak Oxygen Consumption (VO2peak)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum capacity of oxygen consumption measured during an incremental exercise test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in C-reactive protein (CRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiovascular risk marker. It will be analyzed in plasma, using ELISA specific kits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-alpha)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Inflammatory marker. It will be analyzed in plasma, using ELISA specific kits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid profile marker. It will be analyzed in plasma, by enzymatic colorimetric method, using an automatic analyzer (ROCHE, Cobas C111, Switzerland).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid profile marker. It will be analyzed in plasma, by enzymatic colorimetric method, using an automatic analyzer (ROCHE, Cobas C111, Switzerland).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in LDL-Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid profile marker. Estimation of the LDL concentration will be calculate using the formula of Friedewald.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HDL-Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Lipid profile marker. It will be analyzed in plasma, by enzymatic colorimetric method, using an automatic analyzer (ROCHE, Cobas C111, Switzerland).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Fasting Glycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Glycaemic profile marker. It will be analyzed in plasma, by enzymatic colorimetric method, using an automatic analyzer (ROCHE, Cobas C111, Switzerland).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Fasting Insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Glycaemic profile marker. It will be measured in plasma, usin a high sensitivity enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HOMA-IR</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Glycaemic profile marker. Homeostatic model of insulin resistance. It will be calculated according to the following formula: fasting insulin (microU/L) x fasting glucose (nmol/L)/22.5.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Muscle Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Isometric peak torque of the knee extensors will be measured using an isokinetic dynamometer (Cybex Norm, EUA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Muscle Power</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Lower body muscle power will be measured by the performance of the counter movement jump in a force platform.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Muscle Quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Echo intensity of the quadriceps will be analyzed by ultrasound images.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Static Balance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Static balance will be measured by a single leg support balance test, performed with both legs, with the eyes open and closed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Dynamic Balance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic balance will be measured by the Time to Up ang Go (TUG) test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Gate ability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Gate ability will be measured in a 10m track, picking up objects and passing over obstacles.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measurements of body weight will be measured in a digital scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Waist Circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measurements of waist circumference will be performed with a measuring tape.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Percentage of Body Fat</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measurements of skinfolds will be taken to calculate the percentage of body fat.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sit and Stand ability</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The ability to sit and stand in a chair 5 times, as fast as possible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Fall Risk</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The risk of fall will be measured by the performance in the TUG test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Fear of Falling</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The fear of falling will be analyzed by the Falls Efficacy Scale-International Brazil (FES-I-Brazil).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life will be analyzed by the questionary WHOQOL (World Health Organization Quality of Life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Risk Factor</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dancing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Elderly women randomized to the dance intervention programme.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Walking</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Elderly women randomized to the walking intervention programme.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Elderly women randomized to the stretching intervention programme.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dance</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized to the dance group will take part in a dance intervention programme for 8 weeks, including 3 sessions per week, each lasting 60 min. Dance classes will be performed in group in a dance studio, including a variety of rhythms such as salsa, jazz and aerobics. The dance session wil include a warm up of 15 min (posture, join mobility and dance technique), a main part of 40 min (learning of specific choreographies and practice of moves across the floor), and a cool down of 5 min (muscle stretching and relaxation).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dancing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Walking</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized to the walking group will take part in a walking intervention programme for 8 weeks, including 3 sessions per week, each lasting 60 min. The walking session will include a warm up of 10 min (posture and join mobility), a main part of 40 min (walking on a treadmill with a heart rate corresponding to 60% of VO2peak), and a cool down of 10 min (muscle stretching and relaxation).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Walking</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stretching</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomized to the control group will take part in stretching classes, once a week, each lasting 60 min, also for 8 weeks. Stretching exercises for large muscle groups will be performed standing or in a match, holding the positions for a maximum of 10 s. There will be no music playing during the session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women between 60 and 80 years old

          -  BMI inferior to 35 kg/m2

          -  Independent for performing daily activities (OARS scale)

          -  Not engaged in any type of regular exercise programme for the past 6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 2 diabetes mellitus, dyslipidemia, cardiovascular diseases or other
             non-controlled metabolic disorders

          -  Chronic diseases such as fibromyalgia, cancer or neurodegenerative disorders

          -  Bone, joints or muscle problems that could impair exercise performance

          -  Not being able to perform the effort test in the first assessment session, abnormal
             electrocardiogram, or any other condition identified by the physician of the study
             that limit the engagement in an exercise training programme.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alvaro Reischak-Oliveira, PhD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Josianne Rodrigues-Krause, MSc.</last_name>
    <phone>5551 999101821</phone>
    <email>rodrigues.krause@ufrgs.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alvaro Reischak-Oliveira, PhD.</last_name>
    <phone>55-51-3308-5862</phone>
    <email>alvaro.oliveira@ufrgs.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>Rio Grande do Sul</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Josianne Rodrigues-Krause, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>55-51-999101821</phone>
      <email>rodrigues.krause@ufrgs.br</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alvaro Reischak-Oliveira, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>55-51-3308-5862</phone>
      <email>alvaro.oliveira@ufrgs.br</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Josianne Rodrigues-Krause, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 8, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 25, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alvaro Reischak-Oliveira</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor Alvaro Reischak-Oliveira</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dance, walking, cardiovascular risk, functional capacity.</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

