<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02251743</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013H0417</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH100144-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02251743</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Double-Blind 2-Site Randomized Clinical Trial of Neurofeedback for ADHD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Double-Blind 2-Site Randomized Clinical Trial of Neurofeedback for ADHD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of North Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Additional treatments with long-term benefit for attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder
      (ADHD) are needed; one of the more promising is neurofeedback (EEG biofeedback), which has
      several randomized controlled trials showing significant benefit, but which are inconclusive
      because they were not double-blinded; the benefit could have been nonspecific (placebo
      response). Because of neurofeedback's labor-intensive cost (1 treatment costing as much as a
      month's medication), It is important to know how much specific benefit it yields. This 2-
      site placebo-controlled double-blind randomized clinical trial is the first to test for a
      specific benefit of neurofeedback with adequate power, the first designed and implemented
      collaboratively by experts in neurofeedback, ADHD, and clinical trials, the first to
      rigorously monitor quality not only of treatment, but also of placebo and blinding, and the
      first to follow up for 2 years to examine enduring effect; the results, whether positive or
      negative, will provide evidence for clinical practice and public policy regarding ADHD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Current established, evidence-based treatments for attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder
      (ADHD) are incompletely effective and not universally acceptable, and appear to wane in
      effect over time despite significant immediate benefit. E.g., FDA-approved medication, which
      shows large acute benefit, leaves a third of children only partially treated even when
      combined with behavioral treatment, and has not been demonstrated effective beyond 2 years.
      Additional treatments are needed that are effective with persisting benefit, preferably
      related to a biomarker predicting treatment response. A good candidate is
      electroencephalographic (EEG) biofeedback, called neurofeedback (NF). It is based on 1)
      observations that patients with ADHD often have excessive theta band (4-8 Hz) quantitative
      EEG power, low beta band (13-21 Hz) power, and excessive theta beta ratio (TBR), and 2)
      theoretical application of operant conditioning to correct this EEG imbalance. Metaanalysis
      of 6 randomized clinical trials found a large benefit for inattentive symptoms and medium
      benefit for hyperactive-impulsive symptoms. Unfortunately, none of these were blinded. Three
      of 4 small blinded studies found no advantage for NF over sham, but used suboptimal NF,
      leaving the situation inconclusive. Because of the expense and time required by NF, there is
      a public health need to determine whether it has a specific effect beyond the obvious
      nonspecific benefit of doing a focused activity several times a week with a
      friendly,encouraging adult who reinforces for attending to the task. Experts in NF, ADHD,
      clinical trials, statistics, and data management have joined to design a double-blind
      sham-controlled randomized clinical trial to answer several pressing scientific and clinical
      questions in a way that will be credible to all. At each of 2 sites (1 university &amp; 1 NF
      clinic) 70 children (total N=140) age 7 through 10 with rigorously diagnosed moderate to
      severe ADHD and TBR&gt;5 will be randomized in a 3:2 ratio to active TBR downtraining by NF vs.
      a sham training of equal duration, intensity, and appearance. To keep both participants and
      study staff blind, the sham will utilize pre-recorded EEGs with the participant's artifacts
      superimposed. The sham will be programmed into the equipment via internet by an off-site
      statistician-guided person who has no contact with participants. Treatment fidelity will be
      trained and monitored by 2 acknowledged NF leaders in a manner that protects blinding.
      Multi-domain assessments at baseline, mid-treatment, treatment end, and follow-ups at 6
      months, 1 year, and 2 years will include parent and teacher ratings of symptoms &amp; impairment,
      neuropsychological tests,clinician ratings, and quantitative EEG as well as tests of blinding
      and of sham inertness. Hypotheses include that NF will improve parent- and teacher-rated
      inattentive symptoms (primary outcome) and other outcomes more than sham,that benefit will
      persist for 2 years after training, that initial TBR will moderate treatment response, and
      that change in TBR will mediate response. Research Domain Criteria and EEG brain changes will
      be explored, including relationship of TBR to clinical symptoms, executive-function
      impairment, and sleep.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Scores of Teacher and Parent Rated Inattentive Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure will be scores on teacher and parent rated inattentive symptoms on the Conners-3.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neurofeedback treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intended treatment is downtraining of theta power and uptraining of beta power for 38 treatments of active NF.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham neurofeedback treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to sham and their trainers will be fed EEG data from pre-recorded files (recorded during live clinical NF) rather than from the participant's live signal. In order to prevent unblinding of experienced NF trainers/technicians, artifacts from the participant's EMG and EOG are blended into the pre-recorded EEG so that the trainer controlling the feedback cannot differentiate between live and simulated data. To insure trainer/technician blindness, the pre-recorded EEG will be 38 consecutive EEGs from the same age-matched clinical case so that EEGs of the sham group will also show &quot;training progress&quot; over successive sessions, like real NF.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurofeedback treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Each session, the child participates in 5 training tasks. Each task lasts 5 minutes at the beginning and gradually increases to 9 minutes per task over the course of the neurofeedback as the child's attention span improves. We record four results for each of the 5 tasks:
The number of half-second periods that they met the reward parameters (i.e. theta mV below threshold; beta mV above threshold)
Average voltage of theta waves
Average voltage of beta
Average ratio of theta to beta power (TBR)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neurofeedback treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham neurofeedback treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Boys and girls age 7 to 10

          -  IQ&gt;80

          -  diagnosed DSM-5 ADHD inattentive presentation or combined presentation

          -  an item mean ≥1.5 sd above norms on a 0-3 metric both on parent ratings of either
             DSM-IV inattentive symptoms or all 18 ADHD symptoms and on teacher ratings of either
             inattentive symptoms or all 18 ADHD symptoms

          -  an eyes-open QEEG with theta-beta power ratio &gt;4.5 at Cz or Fz

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  comorbid disorder requiring psychoactive medication other than FDA-approved ADHD
             medication

          -  a medical disorder requiring systemic chronic medication with confounding psychoactive
             effects

          -  sleep apnea

          -  restless legs syndrome

          -  IQ &lt;80

          -  plans to move requiring school change during the next 3 months

          -  plans to start other ADHD treatment in the next 3 months

          -  antipsychotic agent in the 6 months prior to baseline assessment

          -  fluoxetine in the 4 weeks prior to baseline

          -  other psychiatric medication in the two weeks prior to baseline

             -&gt;5 previous NF treatments

          -  Vitamin D deficiency will be a temporary exclusion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>L. Eugene Arnold, MD, MEd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Ohio State University Nisonger Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roger deBeus, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina at Asheville</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>L Eugene Arnold, MD, MEd</last_name>
    <phone>614-685-6708</phone>
    <email>L.Arnold@osumc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Study Website</last_name>
    <phone>www.icanstudy.org</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Asheville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Asheville</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28804</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roger deBeus, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>828-333-5359</phone>
      <email>rdebeus@unca.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roger deBeus, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University Nisonger Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>L. Eugene Arnold, M.D., M.Ed.</last_name>
      <phone>614-685-6708</phone>
      <email>L.Arnold@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jill Hollway, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>614-688-3848</phone>
      <email>Jill.Hollway@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>L Eugene Arnold, M.D., M.Ed.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jill A Hollway, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Justin A Barterian, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 29, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>L. Eugene Arnold</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor Emeritus of Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ADHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>neurofeedback</keyword>
  <keyword>EEG</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

