<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02251353</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IMET</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02251353</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intervention to Hepatic and Pulmonary Metastasis in Breast Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMET</acronym>
  <official_title>Intervention to Hepatic and Pulmonary Metastasis in Breast Cancer Patients: Prospective, Observational, Multi-institutional Registration Study - IMET</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federation of Breast Diseases Societies</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federation of Breast Diseases Societies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The number of intervention performed for metastatic breast cancer has dramatically increased
      over the past 2 decades. Hepatectomy and pulmonary resection for stage IV colorectal cancer
      is now considered the standard of care for resectable patients with isolated hepatic and/or
      pulmonary disease and acceptable performance status. However, the indications for resection /
      intervention of breast cancer origin metastases are not as clearly defined. The aim of this
      study to focus on emerging data for the intervention (resection and/or radiofrequency
      ablation (RFA), transcatheter arterial chemoembolization (TACE), cyberKnife stereotactic
      radiosurgery) of breast cancer metastatic disease to the lung and liver, with a focus on
      indications for resection / intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose Despite breast cancer being the most common cancer in women in the developed world,
      only a minority of patients (&lt; 10%) has stage IV disease at diagnosis (1). In addition,
      20-30% of patients with early breast cancer will experience distant metastatic relapse (2).
      Due to advances in available multimodality therapies and a better understanding of tumor
      biology, survival of stage IV patients is constantly improving (3-5).

      Clinically, oligometastatic breast cancer is characterized by solitary/few detectable
      lesions, usually limited to single organs, in which local therapy with curative intent could
      impact survival. This population of 'potentially curable' stage IV disease is estimated to be
      1-10% of newly diagnosed patients with metastatic breast cancer (5). A multimodal approach is
      endorsed for these selected patients (5,6). The identification of patients with truly
      oligometastatic disease is challenging. Most published series refer to an era before modern
      imaging (i.e. positron emission tomography-computed tomography), and thus many patients were
      probably understaged, potentially leading to underestimation of the global effect of an
      aggressive local management.

      Patients with oligometastatic disease can be divided into 3 cohorts (7,8): 1) patients who
      present with oligometastases; 2) patients with residual oligometastases after systemic
      therapy; and 3) those with relapsed oligometastases after curative locoregional therapy.
      These different groups have possibly distinct prognoses, and may need differential
      approaches.

      Several series have reported on lung and liver metastases resection in oligometastatic breast
      cancer and most data are from small series of patients collected over many years. The largest
      dataset comes from the International Registry of Lung Metastases and presents results of lung
      metastasectomy in 467 breast cancer patients (9). Complete resection was possible in 84% of
      patients and led to a median survival of 37 months (5-year OS = 38%, 10-year OS = 22%).
      Identified prognostic factors for lung resection include disease-free interval and number of
      metastases (disease-free interval &gt;36 months and solitary metastases being the most
      favorable), ER status, size of metastases, completeness of resection, and use of anatomical
      resection (as opposite to wedge resection) (9-19). Obviously, the reported data refer to a
      subset of patients who were selected for favorable prognostic factors, and any comparison
      with surgically untreated patients is threatened by serious biases.

      Pulmonary resection in metastatic breast cancer patients, apart from its potential
      therapeutic value, is also an important diagnostic tool, especially in patients with a
      suspected first recurrence, allowing for differential diagnosis with second primary lung
      cancers and benign lesions (19,20). The proportion of lesions proved not to be breast cancer
      metastases in various series ranges from 7% to 66% (9,14,18,21). As the morbidity and
      mortality of pulmonary resection has decreased substantially over the last decades, this
      potentially beneficial procedure can be discussed in a selected group of patients (9,19,21).

      Surgery to remove liver metastases is an accepted treatment modality in patients with
      colorectal cancer (22). Its role in breast cancer is, however, much less recognized. Liver is
      a common metastatic breast cancer site, but only 5% of patients have isolated liver
      involvement. In various series of hepatic resection for breast cancer metastases, the
      reported median survival ranged from 14.5 to 63 months and the 5-year survival from 14% to
      61%, in general, comparing well with nonsurgically treated patients. Most of the reported
      series, however, describe extremely selected patients, constituting 1% or less of metastatic
      breast cancer patients treated over the respective periods of time (22-26). As an example, in
      the one of the important series, all patients were asymptomatic and identified through
      intensive surveillance programs (27). Patients with isolated liver metastasis can potentially
      be managed with local treatments (surgery, radiofrequency ablation (RFA), transcatheter
      arterial chemoembolization (TACE), cyberKnife stereotactic radiosurgery). In contrast to
      liver colorectal metastases, local treatment for breast cancer liver metastasis is not
      considered a therapeutic option due to common involvement of additional organs; nevertheless,
      in some selected patients, local approaches have been associated with long-term survival
      (10,29,30).

      Because patients who are potentially eligible for this therapeutic strategy represent only
      1%-3% of the total metastatic breast cancer population, a large global collaboration is
      needed to confirm its impact on long-term survival or cure and to ensure adequate statistical
      power and strength of the results. Enrolled patients must have comparable clinical and
      biological characteristics, extent of staging, and frequency of monitoring to avoid selection
      biases and stage migration, which can substantially affect the outcome.

      The number of intervention performed for metastatic breast cancer has dramatically increased
      over the past 2 decades. Hepatectomy and pulmonary resection for stage IV colorectal cancer
      is now considered the standard of care for resectable patients with isolated hepatic and/or
      pulmonary disease and acceptable performance status. However, the indications for resection /
      intervention of breast cancer origin metastases are not as clearly defined. The aim of this
      study to focus on emerging data for the intervention (resection and/or radiofrequency
      ablation (RFA), transcatheter arterial chemoembolization (TACE), cyberKnife stereotactic
      radiosurgery) of breast cancer metastatic disease to the lung and liver, with a focus on
      indications for resection / intervention.

      Patient acquisition and data collection All patient should be female. All following
      demographic, clinical and tumour specific data will be collected: patient age, performance
      status according to the WHO classification at the time of first presentation to the hospital,
      stage, type and receptor status (ER, PR, HER-2) of the primary tumour, tumor load in the lung
      and/or liver (uni-or bilateral affection, number of metastases, diameter of the largest
      tumour size), chronology of the metastases (metachronous or synchronous), presence of further
      metastatic (synchronous metastases) or recurrent (metachronous) extrahepatic tumour growth
      and lymph node involvement in the mediastinal region or hepatoduodenal ligament. In addition,
      treatment-related and follow-up data will be documented: Intervention method (surgical
      resection, cryosurgery, laser-induced thermotherapy, radio-frequency ablation, ethanol
      injection, cyber-knife), median follow-up, incidence of tumour recurrence, time to
      recurrence, overall survival, and the administration of chemotherapy. Survival will be
      calculated from the date of diagnosis of the lung and/or liver metastases.

      Definitions Lung and/or liver metastases will be defined as metachronous if the interval
      between resection of the primary tumour and first diagnosis of metastases is longer than 3
      months. General physical condition of study patients will be measured by the performance
      status according to the WHO classification.

      Prior and during the treatment, all patients will be undergone evaluation with complete
      medical history, physical examination, baseline blood tests, and imaging evaluations
      (positron emission tomography (PET-CT) and/or radiography, bone scintigraphy, computed
      tomography scan, magnetic resonance imaging, ultrasonography). Effects of the treatment will
      be monitoring by imaging analyses at every 3 months for lesions detected at diagnosis of lung
      and/or hepatic metastasis or every 6 months without detectable lesions before the treatment.

      R0 resection is a complete resection with no microscopic residual tumor, while R1 resection
      means a complete resection with no grossly visual tumor as defined by surgeon, but
      microscopic cancer may be left behind. R2 resection indicates a partial resection with
      grossly visible tumor left behind.

      Effects of the treatment were assessed by analyses of maximum response, according to either
      the criteria of the World Health Organization (WHO) (30) or the Response Evaluation Criteria
      in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.0 (31) since its announcement in 2004. Responses in bone
      metastases were evaluated using the methods reported by MD Anderson Cancer Center (32,33),
      with CR as clear evidence of complete bone recalcification with attainment of near-normal
      bone architecture or normalization of scan, and partial response as radio- logical evidence
      of sclerosis in lytic lesions or marked improvement of bone scan. In recent years, MRI was
      performed when available, and the imaging information was taken into account in evaluation of
      bone metastases. Responses in pleural fluids were determined as: CR for radiological
      demonstration of complete disappearance of pleural fluid, and PR for 50% or more decrease.
      For study inclusion, pathological diagnosis of the primary lesions had to be obtained,
      whereas tissue or cellular pathology of the metastatic lesions was preferred but not
      mandatory. In patients who performed surgical resection, a complete histopathological
      response will be defined as the absence of vital tumour cells. Detection of tumour necrosis
      or scar formation within the tumour tissue will be regarded as a partial pathohistological
      response.

      Ethics committee approval in Istanbul University Istanbul Medical Faculty can be obtained to
      participate for this study.

      Statistical analysis The characteristics of the patients with assessable data will be
      compared with X2 test or Wilcoxon rank-sum tests. Overall survival (OS) will be defined as
      duration from diagnosis of the metastasis to last visit or death. Progression free interval
      (PFI) will be defined as duration from diagnosis of the metastasis to the point when disease
      progression will be detected. Complete response (CR) will be achieved by a systemic therapy
      or no evidence of clinical disease (NED) after a local therapy considered relapse-free, and
      the duration between induction of relapse free status and the point of relapse detection will
      be defined as the relapse free interval (RFI); survival time after induction of relapse-free
      status without relapse will be defined as relapse free survival (RFS). Unrelated death other
      than from breast cancer will be considered as censored in evaluation of PFI and RFI. Survival
      curves will be calculated according to the Kaplan-Meier method. The log-rank test will be
      used to evaluate differences in survival between groups with intervention and
      no-intervention. A multivariate analysis will be performed by Cox regression and the
      following variables will be included: age, DFI, performance status (PS), liver metastasis,
      pulmonary metastasis, presence of other metastasis, hormone receptor status, HER2 status,
      Ki-67 status, intrinsic subtype, administration of local therapy, and chemotherapy regimens.
      Statistical significance will be defined as a p value &lt;0.05. All p values will be calculated
      for two-sided analyses. For observed survival, all deaths will be considered as events
      including patients who died from secondary causes without recurrence. Statistical analyses
      will be performed using SPSS 22.0 (SPSS, Chicago, IL) software.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time interval between diagnosis and death</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time interval between diagnosis and first date of progression of disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity due to treatment modality</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Morbidity due to treatment modality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Metastasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>lung and/or hepatic metastasis</arm_group_label>
    <description>intervention to metastasis (resection and/or radiofrequency ablation (RFA), transcatheter arterial chemoembolization (TACE), cyberKnife stereotactic radio surgery) vs no intervention (only systemic treatment)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>hepatic and/or pulmonary resection, radiofrequency ablation (RFA), transcatheter arterial chemoembolization, CyberKnife stereotactic radiosurgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>lung and/or hepatic metastasis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surgery, Chemotherapy,stereotactic radiosurgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>systemic treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Systemic therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>lung and/or hepatic metastasis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>no intervention</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Breast cancer patients: 1) who present primary tumor with lung and/or hepatic metastases;
        2) those with residual lung and/or hepatic metastases after systemic therapy; and 3) those
        with relapsed lung and/or hepatic metastases after curative locoregional therapy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Metastatic breast cancer (lung and/or hepatic metastasis) 18 years and older Antineoplastic
        treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

        No lung and/or hepatic metastasis Below 18 years No antineoplastic treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hasan Karanlik, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Istanbul University Institute of Oncology Capa Istanbul</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Atilla Soran, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Magee-Womens Hospital of UPMC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hasan Karanlik, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+905324025354</phone>
    <email>hasankaranlik@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Serdar Ozbas, MD</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul University Istanbul Medical Faculty</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vahit Ozmen, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Abdullah Igci, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mahmut Muslumanoglu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Neslihan Cabioglu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 25, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 29, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 9, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federation of Breast Diseases Societies</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Doc. Dr. Serdar Ozbas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doc Dr Hasan Karanlik</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer, intervention to metastasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

