<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02255838</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14.0689</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02255838</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a Disposable Flexible Bronchoscope, aScope III</brief_title>
  <acronym>EVAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of a Disposable Flexible Bronchoscope, (aScope III) a Randomized, Controlled, Cross-over Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Louisville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Louisville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Flexible bronchoscopes are typically reusable and therefore need high level disinfection to
      prevent inadvertent spread of microbial pathogens from patient to patient. The process of
      disinfection is time consuming and expensive. Moreover, a bronchoscope being processed may
      not be readily available for another patient. One solution to this problem was to use a
      single use disposable sheath that covers a flexible bronchoscope protecting all surfaces of
      the bronchoscope.(Colt, Beamis, Harrell, &amp; Mathur, 2000). Another way to eliminate potential
      hazards with a reusable bronchoscope is the use of a disposable bronchoscope. Such a
      disposable bronchoscope has been developed (Ambu aScope, Ambu, Glen Burnie, MD) and has been
      used successfully for intubations in manikins(Scutt et al., 2011) and patients. (Kristensen &amp;
      Fredensborg, 2013; Pujol, López, &amp; Valero, 2010; Tvede, Kristensen, &amp; Nyhus-Andreasen, 2012).
      Further advancement in the imaging and handling of this disposable flexible bronchoscope now
      allows for the purpose of bronchoscopy and broncho-alveolar lavage in critically ill patients
      with pulmonary compromise. (FDA approval: 05-11-2013 date)

      The aim of the study is to compare image clarity, suction capacity, and handling performance
      of a reusable flexible bronchoscope to the disposable flexible bronchoscope. In addition, the
      investigators intend to perform a cost analysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Description

      Patients will be monitored by standard NIBP or invasive arterial lines, ECG and oxygen
      saturation. All patients are intubated due to their respiratory insufficiency or for airway
      protection. Patients will be anesthetized for the procedure. Anesthesia will be induced with
      versed 2mg, fentanyl 100 µg and paralyzed with 0.1mg/kg vecuronium. Anesthesia will be
      maintained with propofol infusion 50-150 µg/kg/min.

      Study Procedures All patients will be under general anesthesia. Standard monitoring will be
      applied. This includes a blood pressure cuff or an arterial line, EKG and a pulse-oximeter.
      Patients will receive 2 mg/kg propofol, 1µg/kg fentanyl and 0.1mg/kg vecuronium for the
      procedure. After induction of anesthesia the FiO2 will be turned to 1.0 and a bronchoscopy
      adaptor will be interposed in the breathing circuit next to the endotracheal tube. Patients
      will be randomized to receiving either the non-disposable bronchoscope (Storz 8402 2x, El
      Segundo, CA) or the single use aScope 3 first. After randomization, bronchoscopy will be
      started with an inspection of the trachea and carina. Next the right lung bronchial tree will
      be inspected systematically beginning with the right upper lobe, following with the right
      middle lobe and finishing with the right lower lobe. All segmental bronchi will be inspected
      and cleaned by suction as deemed necessary. The bronchoscope will then be removed from the
      bronchial tree and rinsed with saline Subsequently, the bronchoscope will be re-inserted and
      advanced to the basal segmental bronchi of the right lower lobe. The tip of the bronchoscope
      will be brought into wedge position in one of the basal segments for broncho-alveolar lavage
      (BAL). A saline flush of 20 ml will be administered. The flow of saline will be observed at
      the distal tip of the bronchoscope. After 10 seconds of maintaining a wedge position, gentle
      suction will be applied to collect the lavage specimen in the collection trap. This step will
      be repeated 4 more times (total of 80ml) to obtain an adequate specimen. The same procedure
      will be repeated on the left lung using the alternate bronchoscope according to
      randomization. At the end of the procedure, a chest radiograph will be obtained to rule out
      pneumothorax.

      Measurements

      Before starting the procedure the set up time of each bronchoscope will be recorded. The
      view, image, and light of each bronchoscope will be assessed, then the inspection of the
      upper lobe segmental bronchi will be conducted. The time of lavage and suctioning until no
      more specimen can be collected will be measured. The volume of the obtained specimen will be
      measured. The specimen will be evaluated by a blinded observer after the procedure is
      completed.(clear fluids, mucous secretions, viscous secretions, pus, blood etc). The blinded
      observer will evaluate the quality and quanity of the sample for obtaining cultures.The
      blinded observer will be an attending or resident from the infectious disease department.

      The overall ease of handling will be rated directly after the procedure by the investigator.
      All bronchoscopies will be taped and view-clarity, image and light-brightness will be
      assessed by a second blinded observer. This blinder observer can be another investigator not
      present during the procedure or an internist who was not present and is part of the study
      team.

      All assessments will be performed using a VAS scale of 0 to 10 cm as shown below. The
      investigator will mark directly on the scale.

      We will only enroll patients who were admitted to a critical care unit at the University of
      Louisville and who are intubated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    scope has a new modification with an improved view that will be used when available.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The disposable aScope III bronchoscope will be compared to the re-usable bronchoscope</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>A blinded investigator will view the bronchoscopy video and evaluate. The blinded investigator will use the same criteria the investigator who did the procedure used (Un-blinded) for the evaluation. Video will not indicate which scope was used and only indicate if it is the right or left lung they are viewing. Research coordinator will keep separate a file indicating which scope was used.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of visualization between two different flexible bronchoscopes, a disposable and a reusable bronchoscope</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Visualization of the two bronchoscopes using a qualitative scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the handling of two different flexible bronchoscopes, a disposable and a reusable bronchoscope</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Handling of the two bronchoscopes using a qualitative scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of ability to suction adequatly of two different flexible bronchoscopes, a disposable and a reusable bronchoscope</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured suction time in seconds using a qualitative scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of BAL results between two different flexible bronchoscopes, a disposable and a reusable bronchoscope</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of BAL samples using a qualitative scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Atelectasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bronchoscope disposable, aScope III</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the bronchoscope will be re-inserted and advanced to the basal segmental bronchi of the right lower lobe. The tip of the bronchoscope will be brought into wedge position in one of the basal segments for broncho-alveolar lavage (BAL). A saline flush of 20 ml will be administered. The flow of saline will be observed at the distal tip of the bronchoscope. After 10 seconds of maintaining a wedge position, gentle suction will be applied to collect the lavage specimen in the collection trap. This step will be repeated 4 more times (total of 80ml) to obtain an adequate specimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bronchoscope reusable Storz 8402 2x</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>the bronchoscope will be re-inserted and advanced to the basal segmental bronchi of the right lower lobe. The tip of the bronchoscope will be brought into wedge position in one of the basal segments for broncho-alveolar lavage (BAL). A saline flush of 20 ml will be administered. The flow of saline will be observed at the distal tip of the bronchoscope. After 10 seconds of maintaining a wedge position, gentle suction will be applied to collect the lavage specimen in the collection trap. This step will be repeated 4 more times (total of 80ml) to obtain an adequate specimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bronchoscope reusable (Storz 8402 2x)</intervention_name>
    <description>Bronchoscopy and alveolar lavage</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bronchoscope reusable Storz 8402 2x</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Storz 8402 2x (Storz, El Segundo, CA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bronchoscope disposable (aScope 3)</intervention_name>
    <description>Bronchoscopy and alveolar lavage</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bronchoscope disposable, aScope III</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>aScope 3 (Ambu, Glen Burnie, MD)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult 18 years old and older

          2. Capable of giving informed consent or have an acceptable surrogate capable of giving
             legally authorized consent on the subject's behalf.

          3. Indication of a diagnostic and or therapeutic bronchoscopy as determined by the
             attending critical care physician

          4. Being cared for in the critical care units at the U of L Hospital

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1) Patient is moribund and a bronchoscopy is very unlikely to reduce impending mortality or
        can avert death
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rainer Lenhardt, MD MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Louisville School of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Louisville School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Estella A. [Analysis of 208 flexible bronchoscopies performed in an intensive care unit]. Med Intensiva. 2012 Aug-Sep;36(6):396-401. Epub 2011 Dec 20. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>22192316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Facciolongo N, Patelli M, Gasparini S, Lazzari Agli L, Salio M, Simonassi C, Del Prato B, Zanoni P. Incidence of complications in bronchoscopy. Multicentre prospective study of 20,986 bronchoscopies. Monaldi Arch Chest Dis. 2009 Mar;71(1):8-14.</citation>
    <PMID>19522159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Georgiades G, Myrianthefs P, Venetsanou K, Kythreoti A, Kyroudi A, Kittas C, Baltopoulos G. Temperature and serum proinflammatory cytokine changes in patients with NSCLC after BAL. Lung. 2003;181(1):35-47.</citation>
    <PMID>12879338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang YC, Bassett MA, Levin D, Montilla T, Ghio AJ. Acute phase reaction in healthy volunteers after bronchoscopy with lavage. Chest. 2006 Jun;129(6):1565-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16778276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ikeda S, Yanai N, Ishikawa S. Flexible bronchofiberscope. Keio J Med. 1968 Mar;17(1):1-16.</citation>
    <PMID>5674435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kreider ME, Lipson DA. Bronchoscopy for atelectasis in the ICU: a case report and review of the literature. Chest. 2003 Jul;124(1):344-50. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12853543</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristensen MS, Fredensborg BB. The disposable Ambu aScope vs. a conventional flexible videoscope for awake intubation -- a randomised study. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2013 Aug;57(7):888-95. doi: 10.1111/aas.12094. Epub 2013 Mar 15.</citation>
    <PMID>23495767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lucena CM, Martínez-Olondris P, Badia JR, Xaubet A, Ferrer M, Torres A, Agustí C. [Fiberoptic bronchoscopy in a respiratory intensive care unit]. Med Intensiva. 2012 Aug-Sep;36(6):389-95. Epub 2011 Dec 22. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>22195599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perkins GD, Chatterjie S, McAuley DF, Gao F, Thickett DR. Role of nonbronchoscopic lavage for investigating alveolar inflammation and permeability in acute respiratory distress syndrome. Crit Care Med. 2006 Jan;34(1):57-64.</citation>
    <PMID>16374157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pujol E, López AM, Valero R. Use of the Ambu(®) aScope™ in 10 patients with predicted difficult intubation. Anaesthesia. 2010 Oct;65(10):1037-40. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2044.2010.06477.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20707786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Du Rand IA, Blaikley J, Booton R, Chaudhuri N, Gupta V, Khalid S, Mandal S, Martin J, Mills J, Navani N, Rahman NM, Wrightson JM, Munavvar M; British Thoracic Society Bronchoscopy Guideline Group. Summary of the British Thoracic Society guideline for diagnostic flexible bronchoscopy in adults. Thorax. 2013 Aug;68(8):786-7. doi: 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2013-203629. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23842821</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scutt S, Clark N, Cook TM, Smith C, Christmas T, Coppel L, Crewdson K. Evaluation of a single-use intubating videoscope (Ambu aScope ™) in three airway training manikins for oral intubation, nasal intubation and intubation via three supraglottic airway devices. Anaesthesia. 2011 Apr;66(4):293-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2044.2011.06647.x. Epub 2011 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21401543</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharif-Kashani B, Shahabi P, Behzadnia N, Mohammad-Taheri Z, Mansouri D, Masjedi MR, Zargari L, Salimi Negad L. Incidence of fever and bacteriemia following flexible fiberoptic bronchoscopy: a prospective study. Acta Med Iran. 2010 Nov-Dec;48(6):385-8.</citation>
    <PMID>21287478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steinberg KP, Mitchell DR, Maunder RJ, Milberg JA, Whitcomb ME, Hudson LD. Safety of bronchoalveolar lavage in patients with adult respiratory distress syndrome. Am Rev Respir Dis. 1993 Sep;148(3):556-61.</citation>
    <PMID>8368623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsao TC, Tsai YH, Lan RS, Shieh WB, Lee CH. Treatment for collapsed lung in critically ill patients. Selective intrabronchial air insufflation using the fiberoptic bronchoscope. Chest. 1990 Feb;97(2):435-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2298070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tvede MF, Kristensen MS, Nyhus-Andreasen M. A cost analysis of reusable and disposable flexible optical scopes for intubation. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2012 May;56(5):577-84. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-6576.2012.02653.x. Epub 2012 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22338623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Um SW, Choi CM, Lee CT, Kim YW, Han SK, Shim YS, Yoo CG. Prospective analysis of clinical characteristics and risk factors of postbronchoscopy fever. Chest. 2004 Mar;125(3):945-52.</citation>
    <PMID>15006953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bellomo R, Tai E, Parkin G. Fibreoptic bronchoscopy in the critically ill: a prospective study of its diagnostic and therapeutic value. Anaesth Intensive Care. 1992 Nov;20(4):464-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1463174</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Colt HG, Beamis JJ, Harrell JH, Mathur PM. Novel flexible bronchoscope and single-use disposable-sheath endoscope system. A preliminary technology evaluation. Chest. 2000 Jul;118(1):183-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10893377</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 24, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 3, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Louisville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rainer Lenhardt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, MBA</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Atelectasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

