<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02258126</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PI13/01335</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02258126</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Exercise on Hepatic Fat in Overweight Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>EFIGRO</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Exercise on Hepatic Fat in Overweight Children; the EFIGRO Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Basque Country University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Basque Country University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the present study is to evaluate the effect of 6 months exercise
      intervention program on hepatic fat fraction in overweight children.

      Methodology: A total of 160 children, 9-11 years old, will be randomly assigned to control
      (N=80) or intervention (N=80) groups. Training sessions will include 90 minutes of exercise,
      comprising warm-up and skill development. The control group will attend a healthy lifestyle
      education program (2 days/month) and the intervention group an exercise (3 days/week) and
      healthy lifestyle education (2 days/month) combined program. Before and after the
      intervention (6 months) hepatic fat fraction, body composition, , and cardiometabolic risk
      factors will be measured. Furthermore, dietary habits and physical activity, blood pressure
      and pubertal development will be evaluated before and after the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The control group will attend a healthy lifestyle education program (2 days/month) and
      supportive therapy and behavioral advice for both children and parents to improve nutrition
      and physical activity (nutritionists and psychologists).

      The intervention group will attend an exercise (3 days/week) and healthy lifestyle education
      (2 days/month) combined program. Training sessions will include 90 minutes of exercise,
      comprising warm-up and skill development, moderate to vigorous aerobic activities,
      flexibility and strength exercises.

      Before (baseline) and after the intervention (6 months) total and abdominal adiposity, lean
      tissue mass and bone mass density (dual-X-ray-absorptiometry), abdominal visceral and hepatic
      adiposity (magnetic resonance imaging), and blood insulin, glucose, C-reactive protein,
      alanine aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase, gamma-glutamil transpeptidase and lipid
      profile will be measured. Furthermore, cardiorespiratory fitness (treadmill test) and blood
      pressure will be measured before and after the intervention. Changes (6 months - baseline) in
      dietary habits will be estimated by using two repeated 24h recalls and food frequency
      questionnaires and changes (6 months - baseline) in physical activity by accelerometry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>changes in hepatic fat</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in hepatic fat fraction measured by magnetic resonance imaging after the 6 months intervention program</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in insulin sensitivu¡ity measured by homeostasis model assessment (HOMA) after the 6 months intervention program</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in serum lipid profile</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in total, LDL- and HDL-cholesterol after the 6 months intervention program</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in liver enzymes</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in total, alanine transaminase (ALT), aspartate transaminase (AST) and gamma-GT after the 6 months intervention program</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in dietary habits</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in dietary habits estimated by 24h recall and food frequency questionnaire after the 6 months intervention program</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in physical activity estimated by accelerometry after the 6 months intervention program</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in visceral adipose tissue (MRI), abdominal and total adiposity (DEXA), lean tissue mass and bone mass (DEXA) the 6 months intervention program</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in other cardiometabolic risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in blood pressure, leptin, adiponectin, C-reactive protein (CRP) after the 6 months intervention program</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>healthy lifestyle education including healthy lifestyle education, supportive therapy and behavioral advice for both children and parents to improve nutrition and physical activity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>multidisciplinary intervention program including healthy lifestyle education, supportive therapy and behavioral advice for for both children and parents to improve nutrition and physical activity and supervised exercise.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multidisciplinary intervention program</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercise group:
The intervention program includes an education program promoting healthy dietary habits and physical activity (nutritionist), supportive therapy and behavioral advice for the family to improve nutrition and physical activity (psychologist) (2 times/month, for children and parents) and supervised exercise (3 times/week, 90 mins) program for 6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Overweight or obesity status

          -  9-11 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical conditions that hamper their participation in the exercise program

          -  Secondary obesity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>IDOIA LABAYEN, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Nutrition and Food Sciences, Faculty of Pharmacy, University of the Basque Country</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Idoia Labayen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34945014346</phone>
    <email>idoia.labayen@ehu.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Endocrinology Unit of the University Hospital of Araba (HUA)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vitoria-Gasteiz</city>
        <state>Araba</state>
        <zip>01009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ignacio Diez, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>945007000</phone>
      <email>IGNACIO.DIEZLOPEZ@sakidetza.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ainhoa Sarasúa, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>945007000</phone>
      <email>AINHOA.SARASUAMIRANDA@sakidetza.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nobili V, Manco M. Therapeutic strategies for pediatric non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: a challenge for health care providers. World J Gastroenterol. 2007 May 14;13(18):2639-41.</citation>
    <PMID>17552019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Volovelsky O, Weiss R. Fatty liver disease in obese children--relation to other metabolic risk factors. Int J Pediatr Obes. 2011 Sep;6 Suppl 1:59-64. doi: 10.3109/17477166.2011.583661.</citation>
    <PMID>21905818</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Welsh JA, Karpen S, Vos MB. Increasing prevalence of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease among United States adolescents, 1988-1994 to 2007-2010. J Pediatr. 2013 Mar;162(3):496-500.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2012.08.043. Epub 2012 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23084707</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kotronen A, Yki-Järvinen H. Fatty liver: a novel component of the metabolic syndrome. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2008 Jan;28(1):27-38. Epub 2007 Aug 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17690317</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schwimmer JB, Pardee PE, Lavine JE, Blumkin AK, Cook S. Cardiovascular risk factors and the metabolic syndrome in pediatric nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Circulation. 2008 Jul 15;118(3):277-83. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.739920. Epub 2008 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18591439</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wicklow BA, Wittmeier KD, MacIntosh AC, Sellers EA, Ryner L, Serrai H, Dean HJ, McGavock JM. Metabolic consequences of hepatic steatosis in overweight and obese adolescents. Diabetes Care. 2012 Apr;35(4):905-10. doi: 10.2337/dc11-1754. Epub 2012 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>22357180</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Akın L, Kurtoglu S, Yikilmaz A, Kendirci M, Elmalı F, Mazicioglu M. Fatty liver is a good indicator of subclinical atherosclerosis risk in obese children and adolescents regardless of liver enzyme elevation. Acta Paediatr. 2013 Mar;102(3):e107-13. doi: 10.1111/apa.12099. Epub 2012 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23190373</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Davis CL, Pollock NK, Waller JL, Allison JD, Dennis BA, Bassali R, Meléndez A, Boyle CA, Gower BA. Exercise dose and diabetes risk in overweight and obese children: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2012 Sep 19;308(11):1103-12.</citation>
    <PMID>22990269</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Escalante Y, Saavedra JM, García-Hermoso A, Domínguez AM. Improvement of the lipid profile with exercise in obese children: a systematic review. Prev Med. 2012 May;54(5):293-301. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2012.02.006. Epub 2012 Feb 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22387009</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Koot BG, van der Baan-Slootweg OH, Tamminga-Smeulders CL, Rijcken TH, Korevaar JC, van Aalderen WM, Jansen PL, Benninga MA. Lifestyle intervention for non-alcoholic fatty liver disease: prospective cohort study of its efficacy and factors related to improvement. Arch Dis Child. 2011 Jul;96(7):669-74. doi: 10.1136/adc.2010.199760. Epub 2011 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21518734</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hallsworth K, Fattakhova G, Hollingsworth KG, Thoma C, Moore S, Taylor R, Day CP, Trenell MI. Resistance exercise reduces liver fat and its mediators in non-alcoholic fatty liver disease independent of weight loss. Gut. 2011 Sep;60(9):1278-83. doi: 10.1136/gut.2011.242073. Epub 2011 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21708823</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee S, Bacha F, Hannon T, Kuk JL, Boesch C, Arslanian S. Effects of aerobic versus resistance exercise without caloric restriction on abdominal fat, intrahepatic lipid, and insulin sensitivity in obese adolescent boys: a randomized, controlled trial. Diabetes. 2012 Nov;61(11):2787-95. doi: 10.2337/db12-0214. Epub 2012 Jun 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22751691</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Oh S, Tanaka K, Warabi E, Shoda J. Exercise reduces inflammation and oxidative stress in obesity-related liver diseases. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2013 Dec;45(12):2214-22. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0b013e31829afc33.</citation>
    <PMID>23698242</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 6, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 7, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Basque Country University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>IDOIA LABAYEN</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Lecturer of Nutrition and Food Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>overweight children</keyword>
  <keyword>hepatic fat</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>nutritional education program</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiometabolic risk</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome X</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

