<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01559636</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDC-458-GID-037</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01559636</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diarrhea and Bivalent Oral Polio Vaccine Immunity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Diarrheal Disease on Bivalent Oral Polio Vaccine (bOPV) Immune Response in Infants in Nepal</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tribhuvan University, Nepal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Global eradication of poliomyelitis has proven to be elusive. Although 99% of cases have been
      eliminated since 1988, outbreaks continue to occur, and new tools are needed to accelerate
      eradication. One concern in this effort is that some populations have decreased
      immunogenicity to oral poliovirus vaccine (OPV). Past studies have shown decreased
      seroimmunity to trivalent OPV (tOPV) in children with diarrhea. In 2009, bivalent OPV (bOPV)
      was recommended for use in immunization campaigns, and will likely replace tOPV in routine
      immunization in 2016. However, the effect of diarrhea on seroconversion to bOPV has not been
      studied.

      This project evaluated the effect of diarrhea on seroconversion to bOPV among infants who
      reside in Nepal. The investigators conducted a prospective, interventional study that
      assessed immune response to bOPV among infants with and without diarrhea. Immune responses
      were compared among infants with and without diarrhea.

      This study will result in a better understanding of the factors that decrease the ability of
      some children to seroconvert to OPV and be protected from poliomyelitis infection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of infants who seroconvert or boost in antibody titers in the diarrhea arm compared to the non-diarrhea arm</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks after date of bOPV dose</time_frame>
    <description>Seropositive: antibody titer of at least 1:8 for poliovirus type 1 or 3
Seronegative: antibody titer of less than 1:8 for poliovirus type 1 or 3
Seroconversion: proportion of children who change from seronegative to seropositive to types 1 or 3, four weeks after receipt of bOPV.
Boost (increase in titer): seropositives at baseline who increase at least 4-fold in antibody titer four weeks after receipt of bOPV.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequencies of enteric infections isolated in stool among infants with diarrhea vs. infants without diarrhea</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>One stool sample will be collected from each infant the day of enrollment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of infants seropositive after receipt of 3 doses of any oral polio vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks after date of bOPV dose</time_frame>
    <description>A subset of infants who received two doses of any OPV prior to study entry, and a third dose of bOPV as part of the study, will have their seroimmunity reported. This outcome is intended as a proxy measure for seroprevalence after 3 doses of OPV, which is how the vaccine is used in routine immunization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of infants with factors associated with poor bOPV seroconversion/boosting</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks after date of bOPV dose</time_frame>
    <description>Multivariable modeling will be used to assess factors associated with poor bOPV seroconversion/boosting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">699</enrollment>
  <condition>Seroimmunity</condition>
  <condition>Diarrhea</condition>
  <condition>Polio</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diarrhea</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants with diarrhea will have blood and stool sample taken and receive zinc and ORS. They will then receive bivalent oral polio vaccine as the intervention. Four weeks later another blood sample will be drawn to measure seroconversion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-diarrhea</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infants without diarrhea will have blood and stool sample taken and receive multivitamins. They will then receive bivalent oral polio vaccine as the intervention. Four weeks later another blood sample will be drawn to measure seroconversion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bivalent oral polio vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>vaccine given during immunization campaigns</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diarrhea</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-diarrhea</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The investigators will be including Nepali infants aged at least 6 weeks and no more
             than 12 months, who have received &lt;3 doses of OPV (cumulative from routine and SIA)
             and present to outpatient clinics in participating study sites. Whenever possible, the
             child's immunization status based on the caretaker's report will be cross-checked with
             available immunization cards.

          -  Infants with diarrhea must also have:

          -  Current diarrhea, defined as three loose stools per day in the past 24 hours. This may
             include children with acute or chronic diarrhea, low grade fever, and those with
             intermittent vomiting who are able to tolerate oral fluids and do not present with
             severe dehydration on the initial visit.

          -  Non-diarrhea children also must:

          -  Present with other, non-diarrheal minor acute complaints. This can include but is not
             limited to children presenting for non-severe illnesses such as skin problems (e.g.,
             rash), conjunctivitis, and mild cough, congestion, or cold. These children should be
             diarrhea-free for at least two weeks prior to enrolment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants younger than 6 weeks or older than 12 months of age

          -  Infants who have received 3 or more cumulative doses of OPV (including both routine
             and SIAs)

          -  Infants who require hospitalization or are deemed too ill to participate by the study
             site clinician

          -  Infants with blood in the stool (as this may represent more severe cases including
             dysentery, or non-infectious severe illnesses such as intussusception)

          -  Infants who require IV medications for a severe illness (e.g., pneumonia); however,
             this does not include medications for mild or moderate illnesses, such as paracetamol,
             ORS, eye ointment, etc.

          -  Infants who have a chronic underlying illness requiring long term medications

          -  Infants who are unable to take any oral fluids by mouth, require IV hydration and
             therefore would be unable to tolerate oral medications in the study

          -  Infants whose caregivers do not consent, or are not present to give consent, to the
             study

          -  Infants who will not be able to return to the clinic to participate the full length of
             the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cristina V Cardemil, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kathmandu</city>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nepal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.polioeradication.org</url>
    <description>Global Polio Eradication Initiative</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 21, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 13, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 13, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>seroconversion</keyword>
  <keyword>oral polio vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>OPV</keyword>
  <keyword>poliomyelitis</keyword>
  <keyword>diarrhea</keyword>
  <keyword>seroimmunity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Poliomyelitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

