<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01555541</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>112525</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01555541</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Intensive Consolidation and Stem Cell Mobilization Therapy Followed by Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation in High-risk Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Intensive Consolidation and Stem Cell Mobilization Therapy With Ofatumumab, Etoposide, and High-dose Ara-C (OVA), Followed by Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation in High-risk Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>C. Babis Andreadis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical trial is to show that incorporating ofatumumab instead of rituximab
      in combination with etoposide and cytarabine (OVA) is successful in collecting autologous
      stem cells for use in an autologous stem cell transplantation (autoSCT) and to examine its
      effectiveness in eliminating residual diffuse large B-Cell Lymphoma (DLBCL) in patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with relapsed Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma (DLBCL) who are refractory to or relapse
      within 12 months of first-line rituximab-based therapy, have poor outcomes with conventional
      approaches to autologous stem cell transplantation as detailed above. The investigators
      hypothesize that the intensive mobilization strategy developed can overcome some of the
      obstacles to successful autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT) by both eliminating
      residual disease following salvage therapy and by facilitating stem cell collection. Even
      though there is clinical experience in the cooperative group setting with intensive pre-ASCT
      mobilization, it has never been prospectively validated in DLBCL and concerns exist as to its
      ability to improve outcomes with ASCT in this high-risk, and heavily pretreated group of
      patients. Furthermore, most patients in the study site's registry treated with intensive
      mobilization were rituximab-naïve and the findings may not translate in the
      rituximab-refractory population. The investigators also believe that ofatumumab, a novel
      monoclonal antibody against a distinct CD20 epitope may in fact overcome rituximab resistance
      in DLBCL patients and through more effective CDC may eliminate minimal residual disease in
      the patient and contaminating tumor cells in the stem cell graft.

      General Design

      This is a single-institution, single-arm, prospective phase II study. Patients with high-risk
      DLBCL (defined as either achieving less than complete remission (CR) to initial
      rituximab-containing therapy or relapsing within 12 months of initial therapy) will be
      enrolled on this study and will undergo staging prior to receiving intensive mobilization
      with ofatumumab, etoposide, and high-dose ara-C (OVA). Following successful stem cell
      collection, patients will proceed to standard autologous transplantation with
      cyclophosphamide, BCNU, and etoposide (CBV) preparative regimen. Response evaluation will
      occur after salvage therapy, following intensive mobilization therapy (d42), at day +90 after
      ASCT, and at 6, 12 and 24 months thereafter. Event-free, progression-free, and overall
      survival will also be assessed until 48 months. The primary study endpoint is
      mobilization-adjusted complete metabolic response rate (maCR) following OVA. Subjects who are
      not chemosensitive to salvage therapy (i.e. do not achieve a PR or CR) will be re-evaluated
      after an additional salvage regimen. If they are still not chemosensitive at this point, they
      will be withdrawn from the study and replaced.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients achieving complete response to the treatment upon successful stem cell mobilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Response evaluation will occur after salvage therapy, following intensive mobilization therapy (day 42)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to neutrophil and platelet engraftment following successful stem cell mobilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Response evaluation will occur at day +90 after ASCT, and at 6, 12 and 24 months thereafter</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival following treatment with Ofatumumab in combination with etoposide and high-dose ara-C (OVA) and subsequent autologous stem cell transplantation</measure>
    <time_frame>Response evaluation will occur at day +90 after ASCT, and at 6, 12 24, and 48 months thereafter.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma Relapsed/Refractory</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single-arm study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ofatumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>1000 mg IV days 0, 7, 14, 21</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single-arm study</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Arzerra</other_name>
    <other_name>GSK1841157</other_name>
    <other_name>HuMax-CD20</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>10 mg/Kg IV over 24 hours daily, days 1-4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single-arm study</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vespid®</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>2000 mg/m2 IV twice daily, days 1-4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single-arm study</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytosar-U®</other_name>
    <other_name>Ara-C</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine arabinoside</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of refractory or relapsed biopsy-proven CD20+ diffuse large B-cell lymphoma
             or primary mediastinal B-cell lymphoma.

          -  Age 18 years or older

          -  Refractory to or relapse following a rituximab/anthracycline first-line regimen

          -  High-risk disease as defined by one of the following:

               -  First relapse after CR within 12 months of initiation of front-line therapy

               -  Less than CR to front-line therapy

               -  sAAIPI of 1 or higher at the time of relapse

          -  Receipt of no more than three prior chemotherapy regimens. Monoclonal antibody therapy
             alone and involved field radiotherapy are not included in this number. Prior use of
             ofatumumab is allowed if there has been no disease progression following that therapy
             (i.e. ofatumumab-based salvage regimens are allowed)

          -  ECOG performance status ≤ 2.

        Eligibility to proceed to OVA

          -  Chemosensitive disease as defined by at least a partial response to salvage therapy by
             PET/CT criteria.

          -  Bone marrow with less than 15% lymphoma cells following salvage therapy. No evidence
             of myelodysplasia.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ function with serum creatinine &lt;2.0 mg/dL, total
             bilirubin ≤2X ULN, and AST ≤3X ULN.

          -  Neutrophils &gt;1,000/μL and platelets &gt;100,000/μL prior to day 0

          -  No active uncontrolled infection.

        Eligibility to proceed to CBV ASCT

          -  Patients must be out of the hospital after OVA for a minimum of 4 weeks.

          -  Adequate peripheral blood stem cell collection with CD34 cell dose ≥2 X 106 /kg
             (actual body weight).

          -  No evidence of disease progression on day 42 assessment

          -  Approved by the UCSF Bone Marrow Transplant Committee to proceed with ASCT.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Presence of disease transformation from a previously diagnosed low-grade lymphoma

          -  Progression following prior ofatumumab-based therapy

          -  Active central nervous system or meningeal involvement by lymphoma. Patients with a
             history of CNS or meningeal involvement must be in a documented remission by CSF
             evaluation and contrast MRI imaging for at least 3 months prior to study entry.

          -  Evidence of myelodysplasia on any bone marrow biopsy.

          -  Treatment with any known non-marketed drug substance or experimental therapy within 5
             terminal half-lives or 4 weeks prior to enrollment, whichever is longer, or currently
             participating in any other interventional clinical study.

          -  Other past or current malignancy. Subjects who have been free of malignancy for at
             least 3 years, or have a history of completely resected non-melanoma skin cancer, or
             successfully treated in situ carcinoma are eligible.

          -  Chronic or current infectious disease requiring systemic antibiotics, antifungal, or
             antiviral treatment such as, but not limited to, chronic renal infection, chronic
             chest infection with bronchiectasis, tuberculosis and active Hepatitis C.

          -  History of significant cerebrovascular disease in the past 6 months or ongoing event
             with active symptoms or sequelae

          -  Known HIV infection

          -  Clinically significant cardiac disease including unstable angina, acute myocardial
             infarction within six months prior to randomization, congestive heart failure (NYHA
             III-IV), and arrhythmia unless controlled by therapy, with the exception of extra
             systoles or minor conduction abnormalities.

          -  Significant concurrent, uncontrolled medical condition including, but not limited to,
             renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, endocrine, pulmonary, neurological, cerebral or
             psychiatric disease which in the opinion of the investigator may represent a risk for
             the patient.

          -  Positive serology for Hepatitis B (HB) defined as a positive test for HbsAg and a
             detectable HBV DNA viral load. If negative for HBsAg but HBcAb positive (regardless of
             HBsAb status), a HBV DNA test will be performed and if positive the subject will be
             excluded. If HBV DNA is negative, subject may be included but must undergo at least
             every 2-month HBV DNA PCR testing from the start of treatment during the treatment
             course. Prophylactic antiviral therapy may be initiated at the discretion of the
             investigator.

          -  Positive serology for hepatitis C (HC) defined as a positive test for HCAb, in which
             case reflexively perform a HCV PCR to confirm the result

          -  Pregnant or lactating women. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative
             pregnancy test at screening.

          -  Women of childbearing potential, including women whose last menstrual period was less
             than one year prior to screening, unable or unwilling to use adequate contraception
             from study start to one year after the last dose of protocol therapy. Adequate
             contraception is defined as hormonal birth control, intrauterine device, double
             barrier method or total abstinence.

          -  Male subjects unable or unwilling to use adequate contraception methods from study
             start to one year after the last dose of protocol therapy.

          -  Subjects who have received live virus vaccination within the 4 weeks prior to planned
             initiation of study treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charalambos Andreadis, MD, MSCE</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gerry Pelle-Day</last_name>
    <phone>415-476-4765</phone>
    <email>gpelle-day@cc.ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charalambos Andreadis, MD, MSCE</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 15, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>C. Babis Andreadis</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Clinical Professor, Department of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>DLBCL</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>B-cell</keyword>
  <keyword>diffuse</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ofatumumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

