<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01550276</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UVT001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01550276</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Tension-type Headache With Articulatory and Suboccipital Soft Tissue Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Tension-type Headache With Articulatory and Suboccipital Soft Tissue Therapy: a Double-blind, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Valencia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Valencia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background. Headache is one of the most common causes of consultation in primary health care
      and neurology in Europe. Cervical muscle tension can maintain a restriction of joint motion
      at the suboccipital level, facilitating the referred head pain.

      Objective. To evaluate the effectiveness of two manual therapy treatments for tension-type
      headache.

      Methods. A randomized double-blind clinical trial was conducted, for a period of 4 weeks and
      a follow-up at one month post-treatment. Eighty-four patients with tension-type headache were
      assigned to 4 groups (3 treatment groups and 1 control group). Treatments included manual
      therapy of suboccipital soft tissue inhibition, occiput-atlas-axis global manipulation, and a
      combination of both techniques. Outcome measures were: impact of headache, disability caused
      by headache, ranges of motion of the craniocervical junction, frequency and intensity of
      headache, and associated headache symptoms.

      Results. After 8 weeks, there were significant improvements in impact of headache (p=0.01),
      disability (p=0.001), and craniocervical flexion (p=0.03) for the suboccipital soft tissue
      inhibition group; in headache impact and disability (p=0.000), pain intensity (p=0.02) and
      craniocervical flexion (p=0.004) and extension (p=0.04) for the occiput-atlas-axis group; and
      in impact (p=0.002), functional disability (p=0.000), headache frequency (p=0.002) and
      intensity (p=0.001), craniocervical flexion (p=0.008) and extension (p=0.003) and associated
      headache symptoms (p=0.01) for the combined therapy group, with effect sizes from medium to
      large.

      Conclusions. Occiput-atlas-axis and combined therapy group treatments are more effective than
      suboccipital soft tissue inhibition for tension-type headache. The treatment with
      suboccipital soft tissue inhibition, despite producing less significant results, also has
      positive effects on different aspects of headache.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Firstly, an individual clinical interview was conducted to collect socio-demographic data and characteristics of headache in a one-month base period (the previous 4 weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This interview gathers information about age, sex, intensity and frequency of headache (with a Visual Analog Scale from 0 to 10), severity of pain (low, moderate, high), qualities of pain (Bilateral location of pain, Pulsating pressure, Not aggravated by physical activity, Photofobia/Phonofobia, Nausea/Vomiting, Pericranial tenderness), cranial location of pain, family history of headache, triggers, aggravating and pain-relieving factors, as well as any previous physiotherapy treatment for headache relief.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of headache on daily life(HIT-6)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It consists of 6 items each with 4 response options ranging from &quot;never&quot; (6 points) to &quot;always&quot; (13 points), and has shown high reliability in previous studies (alpha 0.87).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Headache Disability Inventory (HDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Two first items concerning the frequency and intensity of headaches and a questionnaire of 25 items assessing emotional and functional aspects with 4 possible response options, with an alpha reliability of 0.76-0.83</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Headache pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>rated daily by the patient on the 0-10 Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) (0 = no pain, 10 = most severe pain).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ranges of motion of the craniocervical junction</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>measured with the CROM-device. This instrument has demonstrated a good intra-tester reliability for the movements of cervical flexion, extension, lateral flexion and rotation (ICC &gt; 0.80) (ICC&gt;0.80). However, not having found any previous studies about its reliability for the craniocervical junction (upper cervical joint), we performed -before using this device in our study- an inter-tester reliability analysis with our two examiners and 10 patients not participating in this study, which showed a Pearson's correlation of 0.98</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Headache diary</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>During the four-week treatment period and in the follow-up phase, patients recorded on a daily basis the characteristics of headache with data regarding headache frequency and intensity, associated headache symptoms of photophobia or phonophobia, nausea or vomiting, and pericranial tenderness, completing a total of 7 weekly records.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Tension-type Headache</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Suboccipital soft tissue inhibition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The SI treatment aims to release the suboccipital muscle spasm that maintains the occiput-atlas-axis joint dysfunction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Occiput-atlas-axis global manipulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The OAA manipulation was bilaterally administered and it attempts to restore the motion dysfunction of this complex</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The combination of both treatments</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Manual Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients were assessed in the same conditions before the treatment, after the treatment (at 4 weeks), and at follow-up (after 8 weeks). Four treatment sessions (one session per week). Prior to each treatment session, the physiotherapist performed the vertebral artery test bilaterally, followed by a two-minute neck massage without lubricants and with no proven therapeutic effect, as a placebo for all study groups.
The SI treatment aims to release the suboccipital muscle spasm10 that maintains the occiput-atlas-axis joint dysfunction. This technique, which was administered for 10 minutes, uses a deep and progressive gliding pressure applied with the fingertips towards the posterior arch of atlas.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Suboccipital soft tissue inhibition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Manual Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients were assessed in the same conditions before the treatment, after the treatment (at 4 weeks), and at follow-up (after 8 weeks). Four treatment sessions (one session per week). Prior to each treatment session, the physiotherapist performed the vertebral artery test bilaterally, followed by a two-minute neck massage without lubricants and with no proven therapeutic effect, as a placebo for all study groups.
The OAA manipulation was bilaterally administered and it attempts to restore the motion dysfunction of this complex. It is a structural technique performed on a vertical line along the odontoid process of axis; neither flexion nor extension is used, and lateroflexion is minimal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Occiput-atlas-axis global manipulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Manual Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients were assessed in the same conditions before the treatment, after the treatment (at 4 weeks), and at follow-up (after 8 weeks). Four treatment sessions (one session per week). Prior to each treatment session, the physiotherapist performed the vertebral artery test bilaterally, followed by a two-minute neck massage without lubricants and with no proven therapeutic effect, as a placebo for all study groups.
The combination of both treatments aims to determine whether this combination has greater effects than the separate application of each treatment. After receiving the treatment, the subjects in the experimental groups stayed for five minutes in the supine resting position, in neutral ranges of cervical flexion, extension, lateral flexion and rotation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>The combination of both treatments</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo control</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients were assessed in the same conditions before the treatment, after the treatment (at 4 weeks), and at follow-up (after 8 weeks). Four treatment sessions (one session per week). Prior to each treatment session, the physiotherapist performed the vertebral artery test bilaterally, followed by a two-minute neck massage without lubricants and with no proven therapeutic effect, as a placebo for all study groups.
The control group received four sessions of placebo treatment, followed by ten minutes of resting position.</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 18 and 65 years, episodes of headaches lasting from 30 minutes to 7 days,
             headache having at least two of the following characteristics: *bilateral location

               -  pressing non-pulsating quality

               -  mild or moderate intensity

               -  not aggravated by routine physical activity.

          -  Participants may present photophobia or phonophobia, nausea or vomiting, pericranial
             tenderness, with evolution of more than three months, and they must be under
             pharmacological control.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with other types of headache

          -  Headache that is aggravated by head movements

          -  Metabolic disorders or musculoskeletal complaints previous neck trauma

          -  Vertigo

          -  Dizziness

          -  Arterial hypertension

          -  Advanced degenerative osteoarthritis

          -  Neck joint stiffness

          -  Signs of malignancy

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Patients with cardiac devices

          -  Patients in process of pharmacological adaptation, and excessive emotional tension
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gemma Victoria Espí López, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Physiotherapy Department. University of Valencia. Spain</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gemma V Espí López</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castien RF, van der Windt DA, Grooten A, Dekker J. Effectiveness of manual therapy for chronic tension-type headache: a pragmatic, randomised, clinical trial. Cephalalgia. 2011 Jan;31(2):133-43. doi: 10.1177/0333102410377362. Epub 2010 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20647241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 8, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 9, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 9, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Valencia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>GEMMA V ESPÍ LÓPEZ, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD, PT</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Effectiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>Tension-type headache</keyword>
  <keyword>Manual therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tension-Type Headache</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

