<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01553188</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120079</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-C-0079</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01553188</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AMG 386 and Abiraterone for Advanced Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Multicenter Study of AMG 386 and Abiraterone in Metastatic Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Advanced prostate cancer is treated with surgery or drugs that lower the levels of
           androgens (male hormones) in the body. However, some cancers become resistant to this
           treatment. These types of cancers are known as castration-resistant prostate cancers.

        -  Interfering with the growth of blood vessels that feed tumors can slow prostate cancer
           growth. AMG 386, a new anticancer drug, targets the blood vessels that feed tumors. It
           has been tested for different types of cancer, but not for prostate cancer. Researchers
           want to see if AMG 386 can slow disease progression in men with castration-resistant
           prostate cancer. AMG 386 will be given with abiraterone and prednisone, two drugs that
           are also used to treat advanced prostate cancer.

      Objectives:

      - To test the safety and effectiveness of AMG 386 with abiraterone for castration-resistant
      prostate cancer.

      Eligibility:

      - Men at least 18 years of age with castration-resistant prostate cancer.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam, medical history, and imaging
           studies. Blood and urine samples will also be collected.

        -  Participants will be separated into two groups.

        -  The first group will have AMG 386 once per week for a total of four doses during a
           28-day cycle. They will also take abiraterone once a day and prednisone twice a day,
           every day of the cycle.

        -  The second group will not have AMG 386. They will take abiraterone once a day and
           prednisone twice a day, every day of the 28-day cycle.

        -  Treatment will be monitored with frequent blood tests and imaging studies.

        -  Participants will continue to take the study drugs as long as the disease does not
           progress and there are no severe side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Inhibition of angiogenesis, either as a stand-alone approach or in combination with
           chemotherapy, has demonstrable antitumor efficacy against castration-resistant prostate
           cancer (CRPC) and there are several antiangiogenic agents that are now in clinical
           trials in this population of patients.

        -  AMG 386 is a novel peptide-Fc fusion protein. The molecule is a non-glycosylated
           homodimer engineered by fusing an IgG1 Fc domain to 4 copies of an anti-angiopoietin 2
           (Ang2) peptide. AMG 386 sequesters Ang1 and Ang2, thereby preventing their interaction
           with Tie2 and inhibiting tumor endothelial cell (EC) proliferation and tumor growth.

        -  Abiraterone acetate is a small molecule that irreversibly inhibits CYP17, a
           rate-limiting enzyme in androgen biosynthesis, to block residual androgen synthesis in
           the adrenal gland and tumor cells.

        -  Previous studies have demonstrated that in vivo alterations of testosterone levels
           regulate the expression of VEGF, FGF, and angiopoietin family members. Dual targeting of
           the androgen and angiogenic axis represents a novel approach as a potential targeted
           therapy for patients with metastatic CRPC.

      Objectives:

      -To estimate the treatment effect as measured by progression free survival (PFS) in patients
      treated with AMG 386 plus abiraterone/prednisone relative to abiraterone/prednisone alone.

      Eligibility:

      -Patients with progressive, metastatic CRPC with radiographic evidence of progression after
      primary therapy (surgery or radiotherapy) and adequate androgen deprivation therapy.

      Design:

        -  This is an open-label, randomized, phase II multicenter trial with a two-part design and
           a planned accrual of 88 patients.

        -  An initial run-in phase of AMG 386 will be conducted with 15mg/kg weekly escalating to
           30mg/kg weekly to establish the MTD. The decision on declaration of a safe and tolerable
           dose during this run-in phase will lead to the second part of the study consisting of a
           randomized comparison of abiraterone/prednisone plus AMG 386 (at the established MTD)
           vs. abiraterone/prednisone alone.

        -  AMG 386 will be administered intravenously every week, on days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of each
           28-day cycle. Abiraterone acetate will be self-administered once daily by mouth and
           prednisone will be self-administered by mouth either twice per day at 5 mg per dose or
           once per day at 10 mg per dose as the patient prefers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 8, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 20, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Disease Progression</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Disease Progression</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Patient's Death</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine whether changes occur to AR signaling status of CTCs before and after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare change in molecular markers prior to and after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlate change in genetic markers with efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostatic Neoplams</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasm, Prostate</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasm,Prostatic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Abiraterone and prednisone will be given with MTD of AMG</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Abiraterone and prednisone only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Run in</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose escalation phase to determine MTD of AMG</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMG 386</intervention_name>
    <description>AMG 386 dose will be calculated using the subject s actual body weight (Kg). Supplied in 240 mg v will be administered as an IV infusion using an intravenous infusion pump given over a 60-minute period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Run in</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abiraterone</intervention_name>
    <description>A 1,000 mg dose of abiraterone should be taken orally once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Run in</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prednisone</intervention_name>
    <description>Prednisone should be taken orally either, at 5mg twice a day for each dose or 10 mg once a day a patient s preference.</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Must have metastatic, progressive, castrate-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) with
             radiographic evidence of disease that has continued to progress radiographically or
             biochemically (rising PSA levels on successive measurements) despite adequate
             androgen-deprivation therapy. If patients had been on flutamide, disease progression
             is documented 4 weeks or more after withdrawal. For patients on bicalutamide or
             nilutamide disease progression is documented 6 or more weeks after withdrawal.
             Flutamide, nilutamide and bicalutamide disease progression requirements only apply to
             patients who have been on these drugs for at least the prior 6 months.

          -  Histopathological confirmation of prostate cancer by the Laboratory of Pathology of
             the NCI or Walter Reed National Military Medical Center prior to entering this study.
             Patients enrolled at participating sites may have histopathological confirmation at
             the enrolling centerprior to entering the study. Patients whose pathology specimens
             are no longer available may be enrolled if the patient has a clinical course that is
             consistent with prostate cancer and available documentation from an outside pathology
             laboratory of the diagnosis. All efforts should be made to have the material forwarded
             to the research team for use in correlative studies in cases where original tissue
             blocks or archival biopsy material is available.

          -  Patients must have metastatic disease, defined as at least one lesion on bone scan or
             at least one lesion that can be accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest
             diameter to be recorded for non-nodal lesions and short axis for nodal lesions) as &gt;20
             mm with conventional techniques or as &gt;10 mm with spiral CT scan, MRI, or calipers by
             clinical exam.

          -  Patients participating in the study must have mCRPC.

          -  Patients who have received docetaxel plus ADT for metastatic castrate sensitive
             prostate cancer are eligible for the study. (Patients may enroll as long as they did
             not have progressive disease while on docetaxel and are 6 months removed from
             treatment, with all treatment related toxicities resolving to at least grade 1.)

          -  Patients may not have had more than 7 days of treatment with ketoconazole by mouth in
             the past 6 months.

          -  Males greater than or eqaul to 18 years of age. Because no dosing or adverse event
             data are currently available on the use AMG 386 in combination with abiraterone in
             patients &lt;18 years of age, children are excluded from this study, but will be eligible
             for future pediatric trials.

          -  ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2 for run-in phase; ECOG less than or
             equal to 1 for randomized phase.

          -  Life expectancy of &gt; 3 months for the run in phase and &gt; 6 months for the randomized
             phase.

          -  Adequate bone marrow, hepatic, and renal function with:

               -  Leukocytes greater than or equal to 3000/mu L

               -  ANC greater than or equal to 1500/mu L

               -  Platelets greater than or equal to 100000/mu L

               -  Total bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 times institutional upper limits of
                  normal

               -  AST (SGOT)/ALT (SGPT) less than or equal to 2.5 times institutional upper limits
                  of normal

               -  PTT or aPTT less than or equal to 1.5 times ULN per institutional laboratory
                  range and INR less thanor equal to 5

               -  Creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 times institutional upper limits of normal

        OR

          -  Creatinine clearance of &gt;40 mL/min per 24 h urine collection or calculated according
             to the Cockcroft-Gault formula

             ---CrCl (mL/min) = (((140-age) times actual body weight (kg))/(72 x serum creatinine
             (mg/dL)))*(x 0.85 for females)

          -  Urinary protein less than or equal to 30 mg/dL in urinalysis or less than or equal
             to1+ on dipstick, unless quantitative protein is &lt;1000 mg in a 24h urine sample

               -  Generally well-controlled blood pressure with systolic blood pressure less than
                  or equal to 140 mmHg AND diastolic blood pressure less than or equal to 90 mmHg
                  prior to enrollment. The use of antihypertensive medications to control
                  hypertension is permitted.

               -  Must have recovered from any acute toxicity related to prior therapy, including
                  surgery. Toxicity should be less than or equal to grade 1 CTCAE version 4 or has
                  returned to baseline. Alopecia &gt;grade 1 is permitted.

               -  The effects of AMG 386 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this
                  reasonand because inhibitors of angiogenesis as well as other therapeutic agents
                  used in this trial are known to be teratogenic, men must agree to use adequate
                  contraception

        (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the
        duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant
        while her partner is participating in this study, she should inform her treating

        physician immediately. Men treated or enrolled on this protocol must agree to use adequate
        contraception prior to the study, for the duration of study participation, and 6 months
        after completion of AMG 386 administration.

        -Must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
        document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy for metastatic castration-resistant prostate
             cancer.

          -  History or presence of known central nervous system metastases.

          -  History of venous or arterial thromboembolism within 12 months prior to
             enrollment/randomization.

          -  History of clinically significant bleeding within 6 months of
             enrollment/randomization.

          -  Currently or previously treated with AMG 386, or other molecules that primarily
             inhibit the angiopoietins or Tie2 receptor.

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease within 12 months prior to
             enrollment/randomization, including myocardial infarction, unstable angina, grade 2 or
             greater peripheral vascular disease, cerebrovascular accident, transient ischemic
             attack, congestive heart failure, or arrhythmias not controlled by outpatient
             medication or placement of percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty/stent.

          -  Major surgery within 28 days prior to enrollment or still recovering from prior
             surgery.

          -  Minor surgical procedures, placement of tunneled central venous access device within 3
             days prior to randomization/enrollment.

          -  Treatment within 30 days prior to enrollment with the following: cyclosporine,
             tacrolimus, sirolimus, mycophenolate mofetil, methotrexate, azathioprine, rapamycin,
             and targeted immune modulators such as abatacept (CTLA-4-Ig), adalimumab,

        alefacept, anakinra, belatacept (LEA29Y), efalizumab, etanercept, infliximab, or rituximab.

          -  Patients who have had large field radiotherapy must wait 2 weeks prior to entering the
             study.

          -  Non-healing wound, ulcer (including gastrointestinal), or fracture.

          -  Contraindication to steroid use or history of allergic reactions attributable to the
             study compounds.

          -  History of allergic reactions to bacterially-produced proteins.

          -  Previously diagnosed with another malignancy, within the past two years with the
             exception of non-melanoma skin cancers or non-invasive bladder cancer.

          -  Patients who have not yet completed at least 28 days (30 days for prior monoclonal
             antibody therapy) since receiving other investigational drugs.

          -  Inability to absorb abiraterone after oral administration (i.e., previous major
             gastrointestinal surgery or gastrointestinal disease resulting in malabsorption).

          -  Use of ketoconazole, itraconazole, ritonavir, cyclosporine, carbamazepine, phenytoin,
             phenobarbital within 2 weeks prior to and while on study therapy.

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because of
             the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with the study agents. In addition,
             these patients are at increased risk of lethal infections when treated with
             marrow-suppressive

        therapy. Appropriate studies will be undertaken in patients receiving combination
        antiretroviral therapy when indicated.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness or infections, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrythmias, renal dysfunction, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  Have had treatment with docetaxel for the treatment of metastatic castrate-sensitive
             prostate cancer within 6 months before the first dose of study enrollment.

          -  Have had progression of prostate cancer on prior docetaxel treatment for castrate
             sensitive disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ravi A Madan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2012-C-0079.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goktas S, Crawford ED. Optimal hormonal therapy for advanced prostatic carcinoma. Semin Oncol. 1999 Apr;26(2):162-73. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10597727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gulley J, Dahut WL. Chemotherapy for prostate cancer: finally an advance! Am J Ther. 2004 Jul-Aug;11(4):288-94. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15266221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berthold DR, Sternberg CN, Tannock IF. Management of advanced prostate cancer after first-line chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Nov 10;23(32):8247-52. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16278480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 17, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 10, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 10, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anti-Angiogenesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Ang 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Ang 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Peptide-Fc fusion protein</keyword>
  <keyword>Small Molecule</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trebananib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

