<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01553214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120096</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-CC-0096</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01553214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving White Blood Cell Collection From Healthy Donors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Collection of Granulocytes by Apheresis of Healthy Donors Stimulated With Filgrastim (G-CSF) and Dexamethasone</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - White blood cells called granulocytes help the body fight infection. People who have had
      chemotherapy or bone marrow transplants may have very low numbers of these cells.
      Transfusions of these cells can help improve the body's ability to fight infection. However,
      most of the cells are located in the bone marrow or spleen, and are hard to collect from
      healthy donors. Two drugs, filgrastim and dexamethasone, can help move the cells to the
      bloodstream to be collected by apheresis. Researchers want to study the best ways to collect
      these white blood cells. They also want to monitor the effects of the injections and
      donations on the volunteer donors.

      Objectives:

      - To improve the amount and quality of granulocytes (white blood cells) collected by
      apheresis for donation.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy volunteers between 18 and 75 years of age.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Initial blood
           tests will be done to check for eligibility.

        -  Participants will donate granulocytes by apheresis a maximum of 12 times in 1 year.
           Donations will not usually be requested more often than every 4 weeks. Donors will be
           allowed to decline participation at any time.

        -  Participants will have one injection of filgrastim 12 to 24 hours before donation. They
           will also have two tablets of dexamethasone 12 hours before donation.

        -  White blood cells will be collected through apheresis. The apheresis will last about 2
           hours.

        -  Participants will be eligible to donate until they reach their 76th birthday.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bacterial and fungal infections in neutropenic patients or in patients with inherited
      disorders of neutrophil function continue to cause substantial morbidity and mortality. In
      particular, fungal infections are an increasingly important cause of death in patients
      receiving aggressive chemotherapy, in patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation (HSCT), in patients with chronic granulomatous disease, and in patients with
      bone marrow failure syndromes such as severe aplastic anemia. The strongest predictor of
      progression and death from invasive mold infection in the cancer/ HSCT setting is the
      duration of neutropenia. Any modality which increases the granulocyte count during periods of
      profound neutropenia and severe infection is thus likely to be of clinical benefit. In the
      1970-80 s, collection of granulocyte concentrates by apheresis of healthy donors stimulated
      with corticosteroids alone yielded products with an insufficient number of granulocytes to
      substantially raise the circulating counts in neutropenic patients. Transfusion of such
      components was variably associated with clinical benefit. More recently, the ability to give
      donors recombinant human granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF) in combination with
      corticosteroids (dexamethasone) dramatically increases the circulating neutrophil count prior
      to apheresis and results in the collection of granulocyte concentrates containing 2 to 6
      times as many cells as those collected using steroids alone. Transfusion of granulocyte
      concentrates collected after G-CSF and dexamethasone stimulation of the donor typically
      increases the recipient s granulocyte count by 1,000 cells/uL, and the increase in counts is
      generally sustained for 24 to 48 hours. Transfusion of daily or every other day granulocytes
      derived by apheresis of G-CSF and dexamethasone-stimulated donors has been associated in
      observational and retrospective studies with clearance of life-threatening infections in
      neutropenic patients, but a single small randomized prospective study did not demonstrate
      improved survival in neutropenic infected patients who received granulocytes. Granulocyte
      components are not recognized as a licensed blood component by the Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA), and neither G-CSF nor dexamethasone is approved by the FDA for use in
      allogeneic granulocytapheresis donors. Studies at the NIH Department of Transfusion Medicine
      (DTM) have defined the optimal timing and dose of these drugs in granulocyte donors, and
      these components have been used for clinical care since 1996. Short term adverse effects of
      G-CSF and dexamethasone, including bone pain, myalgias, headache, insomnia and fatigue, are
      well known and possible long term effects, including cataracts from serial steroid
      administration, have been described. The purpose of the current protocol is to determine the
      operational feasibility of managing a volunteer community donor granulocytapheresis program
      and to provide informed consent for the administration of filgrastim and dexamethasone to
      volunteer donors donating granulocytes by apheresis. Donor accrual and retention, immediate
      short term adverse effects of G-CSF and dexamethasone, and any long term effects, will be
      assessed in healthy subjects who will be permitted to donate granulocytes a maximum of 12
      times per year. Participants will be selected based on general blood donor eligibility
      criteria, adequacy of antecubital venous access, and interest in the program. Most subjects
      will already have experience as plateletpheresis donors. The toxicity of granulocyte
      transfusions and the survival and discharge rates of the transfusion recipients will be
      monitored, but the protocol is not designed to evaluate the efficacy of granulocyte
      transfusions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 7, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2030</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2030</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the operational feasibility and impact of managing a volunteer community donor granulocytapheresis program</measure>
    <time_frame>Annually. The feasibility of continuing the granulocyte donation program will be assessed, based on resource need and allocation, operational impact, adverse effects in donors, and survival outcomes of recipients.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To monitor the frequency and severity (symptom grade) of acute adverse effects due to a single dose of filgrastim and dexamethasone in volunteer donors</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours after last GCSF dose. The feasibility of continuing the granulocyte donation program will be assessed, based on resource need and allocation, operational impact, adverse effects in donors, and survival outcomes of recipients.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Blood Donor</condition>
  <condition>Leukocyte Transfusion</condition>
  <condition>Granulocyte Colony-Stimulation Factor</condition>
  <condition>Blood Component Removal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are no arms in this study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are no arms in this study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are no arms in this study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are no arms in this study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Filgrastim (G-CSF)</intervention_name>
    <description>Recombinant G-CSF is available from the Clinical Center pharmacy in colorless glass, single-use vials containing 480 mcg G-CSF in 1.6 mL vials (300 mcg/mL). It is formulated as a sterile, clear, colorless liquid in 10 mm sodium acetate buffer at pH 4.0. The quantitative composition (per mL) is: Recombinant human G-CSF 300 mcg Acetate 0.59 mg Mannitol 50 mg Tween 80TM 0.004% Sodium 0.035 mg Water for injection (qs ad) to 1.0 mL Storage: The intact vials of G-CSF should be stored under refrigeration (2-8 degrees Celsius). Administration: G-CSF is administered subcutaneously, with the entire contents of one 1.6 mL vial given in one injection 12 to 24 hours prior to apheresis.Stability: G-CSF in the intact vial is stable for 36 months when stored in a refrigerator at 2-8 degrees Celsius. A single brief exposure (up to 7 days) to elevated temperatures (&lt;37 degrees Celsius) does not affect the stability. G-CSF should not be frozen, and vials that have been frozen should not be used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral dexamethasone is available from the Clinical Center pharmacy as green 4 mg tablets. The tablets contain the following inactive ingredients: lactose monohydrate, magnesium stearate, starch, sucrose, FD&amp;amp;C Green No. 3, FD&amp;amp;C Yellow No. 10, and FD&amp;amp;C Yellow No. 6. They are packaged in unit-dose blister pack strips. Storage: Dexamethasone tablets should be stored at room temperature (20-25 degrees Celsius). Administration: Dexamethasone is administered as two 4-mg tablets 12 hours prior to apheresis (approximately one hour after dinner the evening prior to apheresis). Stability: Dexamethasone is stable for 36 months when stored at room temperature in an unopened blister pack.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Donors shall meet all donor eligibility criteria for allogeneic blood donors, as
             defined in the most recent editions of the AABB Standards and FDA Code of Federal
             Regulations (21CFR640). In addition, donors shall meet the following restrictions:

          -  Age greater than or equal to18 and less than or equal to 75 years

          -  If hypertension is present, must be well-controlled on medications

          -  If peptic ulcer disease has been diagnosed in the past, symptoms must be
             well-controlled on medications

          -  If cataracts have been diagnosed in the past, records from subject s ophthalmologist
             must be obtained indicating type of cataract. If PSC was diagnosed in the past,
             subject may receive G-CSF but not dexamethasone. The only exception to this is a
             history of bilateral cataract extractions due to PSC.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Information obtained from health history screen that does not meet the allogeneic
             donor eligibility criteria of the AABB Standards or the FDA CFR.

          -  Weight less than 50 kg (110 lbs)

          -  History of coronary heart disease

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic BP &gt;160, diastolic BP &gt;100)

          -  History of hepatitis or injection drug use

          -  Diabetes mellitus requiring insulin

          -  Active, symptomatic peptic ulcer disease

          -  History of iritis or episcleritis

          -  Sickle cell disease (sickle trait is acceptable). Testing for hemoglobin S is not
             required.

          -  Lithium therapy

          -  Pregnancy or nursing (breast feeding)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathleen A Cantilena, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yu Ying Yau, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-3049</phone>
    <email>yyau@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kathleen A Cantilena, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-8637</phone>
    <email>ccantilena@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-CC-0096.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wingard JR, Carter SL, Walsh TJ, Kurtzberg J, Small TN, Baden LR, Gersten ID, Mendizabal AM, Leather HL, Confer DL, Maziarz RT, Stadtmauer EA, Bolaños-Meade J, Brown J, Dipersio JF, Boeckh M, Marr KA; Blood and Marrow Transplant Clinical Trials Network. Randomized, double-blind trial of fluconazole versus voriconazole for prevention of invasive fungal infection after allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation. Blood. 2010 Dec 9;116(24):5111-8. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-02-268151. Epub 2010 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20826719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baddley JW, Andes DR, Marr KA, Kontoyiannis DP, Alexander BD, Kauffman CA, Oster RA, Anaissie EJ, Walsh TJ, Schuster MG, Wingard JR, Patterson TF, Ito JI, Williams OD, Chiller T, Pappas PG. Factors associated with mortality in transplant patients with invasive aspergillosis. Clin Infect Dis. 2010 Jun 15;50(12):1559-67. doi: 10.1086/652768.</citation>
    <PMID>20450350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stroncek DF, Yau YY, Oblitas J, Leitman SF. Administration of G--CSF plus dexamethasone produces greater granulocyte concentrate yields while causing no more donor toxicity than G--CSF alone. Transfusion. 2001 Aug;41(8):1037-44.</citation>
    <PMID>11493736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 27, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 10, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 10, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Granulocyte Transfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Granulocytapheresis</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukapheresis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytokine Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

