<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02482103</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL-RDN_REG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02482103</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Dutch National Renal Denervation Registry</brief_title>
  <acronym>NL_RDN_REG</acronym>
  <official_title>Safety, Success Rate and Long Term Consequences of Renal Denervation in Patients With Therapy Resistant Hypertension. The Dutch National Renal Denervation Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dutch Kidney Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UMC Utrecht</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a national registry of patients treated with renal denervation (RD) in the
      Netherlands.

      The aim of the study is to collect data on safety of the procedure, predictors of the blood
      pressure lowering effect, sustainability of the effect and to assess the cardiovascular event
      rate in patients treated with renal denervation.

      This is a prospective observational study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypertension is common and one of the major risk factors for cardiovascular disease.
      Therefore, it is a major societal and economic health problem. A substantial proportion
      (20-40%) of the treated hypertensive patients has sub-optimal blood pressure control despite
      the use of multiple drugs. All these patients have an increased cardio-vascular risk.
      Furthermore, the use of multiple drugs diminishes compliance to treatment, and increases the
      risk of side effects. This underscores the need for new approaches for hypertension
      management. Elevated (renal) sympathetic nerve activity contributes importantly to the
      development of hypertension and subsequent vascular risk. Deliberate disruption of
      sympathetic nerve activity (sympatholytic therapy) leads to improvement of vascular outcome
      through blood pressure dependent and blood pressure independent effects. Recently, a
      promising novel sympatholytic approach has been introduced, i.e. catheter-based renal
      denervation in a small clinical trial with resistant hypertensive patients. Many clinical
      centres have now started to perform this procedure or are in the process to start up.

      The Dutch Minister of Health has decided to allow renal denervation in patients with so
      called resistant hypertension, and &quot;conditional reimbursement&quot; is available starting Jan 1st
      2013 for a maximum of 4 years. The Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and
      Development (ZonMw) has provided us with a grant to perform a randomized trial (SYMPATHY) to
      evaluate the effect on blood pressure at 6 months after intervention. Maximum follow-up in
      this trial will be 2 years. Important limitations of this study are, firstly that that
      follow-up is limited to 2 years after renal denervation. Secondly, not all patients that
      undergo renal denervation, will participate in the abovementioned trial. The Dutch National
      Renal Denervation Registry will complement the information from the trial in several aspects.
      These deal with safety, non-responders, and sustainability.

      Objectives of the national database are to collect data that will deliver information on:

      Safety:

        1. What are the short and long term procedural related complications?

           Responders

        2. What are the predictors for the effect on blood pressure, in particular patient related
           factors and procedural related factors?

        3. Are there differences between the various renal denervation devices?

           Sustainability

        4. What is the effect on blood pressure after (3), 6, (9), 12, (18), 24, (30), 36, and 60
           months and thereafter in patients who are considered eligible based on the judgement of
           the treating physician?

        5. What is the effect on kidney function after (3), 6, (9), 12, (18), 24, (30), 36, and 60
           months and thereafter in patients who are considered eligible based on the judgement of
           the treating physician?

        6. What are the cardiovascular events rates in this population, in strata of achieved blood
           pressure level, and potentially compared with other populations.

      Methods:

      With this database a nationwide cohort is build comprising patients treated with renal
      denervation over the years, with uniform baseline data collection and uniform follow-up
      measurements in terms of safety measurements, blood pressure measurements, hospitalisations,
      cardiovascular outcomes and all-cause mortality. The data collection will occur through a
      web-based data entry application. All centers in the Netherlands that perform renal
      denervation will be asked to participate. All patients who underwent renal denervation should
      be included, irrespective of the reason and device used.

      To address the outstanding research questions specific statistical analyses plans will be
      applied.

      Conclusion:

      Our expected results are:

        1. to be able to identify patients characteristics, which are associated with a high
           probability of a favourable blood pressure response to renal denervation,

        2. to provide short-and long-term (24 -60 months) side effects of renal denervation

      Perspective:

      These results, collected in routine clinical practice in a large number of clinics in the
      Netherlands, will have a major impact on the treatment of 'resistant hypertension'. The
      safety and efficacy data will pave the way for formal cost-effectiveness analyses. The data
      have the potential to be of high relevance to decision and policy makers in the government
      and health insurances. When deemed cost-effective and safe, this approach will be widely used
      in the treatment of 'resistant hypertension' and will revolutionise the treatment of these
      patients. Furthermore, it will open ways for evaluation of other groups of patients
      characterized by a high sympathetic tone; in particular patients with less severe
      hypertension, heart failure and chronic kidney disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in blood pressure at 6 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety aspects (change in renal function)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>change in renal function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety aspects: long term kidney function</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>change in renal function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>longterm consequences: CVD events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>cardiovascular event rates</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety aspects: procedures complication</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>procedural complications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>longterm consequences: kidney function</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>change in kidney function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>longterm consequences: mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients treated with renal denervation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients treated with RD in the Netherlands. The decision to perform RD was made by the treating physician in the participating hospitals.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Renal denervation</intervention_name>
    <description>Catheter based renal nerve ablation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients treated with renal denervation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients treated with (or evaluated and refused for) renal denervation in Dutch hospitals.
        Indications for RD (by Dutch consensus) are therapy resistant hypertension defined as a
        blood pressure above treatment goal despite use of 3 or more antihypertensive agents
        preferably including a diuretic or intolerance for (additional) antihypertensives.
        Secondary hypertension is excluded beforehand.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  treated with renal denervation. The decision to perform the procedure was made by the
             treating physician in the participating hospitals

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  below age of 18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>95 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michiel L. Bots, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Julius Center for Health Sciences and Primary Care</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michiel Bots, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <email>m.l.bots@umcutrecht.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMC Utrecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michiel L. Bots, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+31(88)7559352</phone>
      <email>m.l.bots@umcutrecht.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Peter J. Blankestijn, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+31(88)7557329</phone>
      <email>p.j.blankestijn@umcutrecht.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.renal-denervation.eu</url>
    <description>description of the project on the website and ways to enrol or participate</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vink EE, Bots ML, Blankestijn PJ. Renal denervation as therapy for hypertension: potentials and unanswered questions. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2013 Dec;20(6):980-91. doi: 10.1177/2047487312473019. Epub 2012 Dec 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23610453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Verloop WL, Vink EE, Spiering W, Blankestijn PJ, Doevendans PA, Bots ML, Vonken EJ, Voskuil M, Leiner T. Effects of renal denervation on end organ damage in hypertensive patients. Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2015 May;22(5):558-67. doi: 10.1177/2047487314556003. Epub 2014 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>25326543</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vink EE, Verloop WL, Bost RB, Voskuil M, Spiering W, Vonken EJ, Bots ML, Blankestijn PJ. The blood pressure-lowering effect of renal denervation is inversely related to kidney function. J Hypertens. 2014 Oct;32(10):2045-53; discussion 2053. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0000000000000282.</citation>
    <PMID>25023158</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Verloop WL, Vink EE, Spiering W, Blankestijn PJ, Doevendans PA, Bots ML, Vonken EJ, Voskuil M. Renal denervation in multiple renal arteries. Eur J Clin Invest. 2014 Aug;44(8):728-35. doi: 10.1111/eci.12289.</citation>
    <PMID>24931208</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Verloop WL, Vink EE, Voskuil M, Vonken EJ, Rookmaaker MB, Bots ML, Doevendans PA, Blankestijn PJ, Spiering W. Eligibility for percutaneous renal denervation: the importance of a systematic screening. J Hypertens. 2013 Aug;31(8):1662-8. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0b013e328362152e.</citation>
    <PMID>23743806</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Persu A, Jin Y, Baelen M, Vink E, Verloop WL, Schmidt B, Blicher MK, Severino F, Wuerzner G, Taylor A, Pechère-Bertschi A, Jokhaji F, Fadl Elmula FE, Rosa J, Czarnecka D, Ehret G, Kahan T, Renkin J, Widimsky J Jr, Jacobs L, Spiering W, Burnier M, Mark PB, Menne J, Olsen MH, Blankestijn PJ, Kjeldsen S, Bots ML, Staessen JA; European Network Coordinating research on REnal Denervation Consortium. Eligibility for renal denervation: experience at 11 European expert centers. Hypertension. 2014 Jun;63(6):1319-25. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.114.03194. Epub 2014 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24664290</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>UMC Utrecht</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michiel L. Bots</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Epidemiology of Cardiovascular Disease</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Therapy resistant hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

