<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02482493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14/01/282 version 1.3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02482493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>All Polyethylene Versus Metal Backed Tibial Components in Knee Replacement</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomised Control Trial to Compare Clinical and Radiological Outcomes of the Press-Fit Condylar All-Polyethylene Tibial Component With Metal-Backed Tibial Component Implant, in Patients Aged 75 Years or Over</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maidstone &amp; Tunbridge Wells NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maidstone &amp; Tunbridge Wells NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Total knee arthroplasty (TKA) is one of the most commonly performed orthopaedic procedures.
      Approximately 84,000 knee replacement procedures were recorded in the UK in 2012. The main
      goal of TKA is to relieve the disabling pain of arthritic disease.

      Patient satisfaction following TKA is related to quick recovery and return to daily
      activities. This can be dependent on the design of the implant used in the knee. Improvements
      in implant design and surgical technique mean many modern designs offer implant survival
      rates beyond 10 - 15 years.

      As cost pressure increases in the NHS the unit cost of implants is now being scrutinised,
      particularly with regard to cost effectiveness. The Press-Fit Condylar (PFC) Sigma implant
      can be used with either a conventional metal backed or alternatively an all polyethylene
      tibial component (part fitted to the shin bone), the latter considerably cheaper to
      manufacture. Four small prospective randomised trials and one large regional registry study
      with long follow up support the safe use of all polyethylene tibial components in TKA. The
      investigators will therefore undertake a prospective randomised controlled trial comparing
      the results of all polyethylene tibial components with those of conventional metal backed
      tibial components in patients aged 75 or over, comparing both clinical outcome and
      radiological survivorship.

      The type of knee replacement used for each patient (metal-backed or polyethylene) will be
      chosen at random once a patient has agreed to take part in the study.

      Data will be collected by means of follow-up appointments and questionnaires and clinical
      tests both before the operation 1 year, 2 years and 5 years postoperatively. This will allow
      us to see how both types of knee replacement perform over time and if one performs better
      than the other in terms of patients movement, pain and functional activities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Summary of design and methodology.

      When a patient who is appropriate for the study is added to the waiting list for a Total Knee
      replacement they will be given (or if missed, posted) an information sheet about the study.
      This will allow patients several weeks to read the information and telephone the Orthopaedic
      research department, if they wish, with any questions they may have.

      The Patients will then come to preassessment clinic as usual. At this point the study will be
      explained again in person, the patient will be given time to ask questions and will be asked
      if they wish to consent to participating.

      If the patient consents to taking part they will complete preoperative measures and
      questionnaires There are 3 questionnaires on how the patient is functioning. 2 are completed
      by the patient and 1 with the help of the Researcher

      The questionnaires are:

      Oxford Knee Score American Knee Society Score (AKSS) Medical Outcomes Study Short Form-36
      Health Survey (MOS SF-36) All questionnaires will be performed preoperatively, 1 year, 2
      years and 5 years postoperatively.

      Six weeks postoperatively the patient will attend a follow-up clinic. This is standard for
      all patients undergoing knee replacement surgery at the Tunbridge Wells Hospital. Routine
      wound checks and postoperative care will take place and any patient's concerns dealt with. At
      this point the patient will be booked in for another routine follow up appointment 3 months
      postoperatively. No study data will be collected at these visits besides adverse events or
      lost to follow-up where appropriate.

      At one year post-operatively the patient will be asked to attend for an appointment. The knee
      will be assessed clinical and same series of clinician and patient questionnaires completed.
      A series of x-rays will also be taken to allow the position of the implant to be recorded.
      Measurements will be taken to be taken from the x-rays Similarly the patient will be invited
      to attend a further 2 appointments at 2 year and 5 years post-operatively. At these
      appointments the questionnaires will be repeated along with the x-rays.

      Should the patient wish to withdraw at any point they are free to do so and will not then be
      contacted for any subsequent appointments unless they are due routine clinical appointments .

      Any patient undergoing total knee replacement and not in the study will attend routine 6 week
      and 3 month and one year follow-up appointments, as routine but will be discharged when
      appropriate and will not be subject to long term follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>American Knee Society Score</measure>
    <time_frame>5 year outcomes</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All-polyethylene Tibial component</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sigma PFC All polyethylene Tibial component will be implanted</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metal Backed Tibial component</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sigma PFC metal-backed tibial component will be implanted</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sigma PFC</intervention_name>
    <description>patients will receive either an all polyethylene tibial component or a metal- backed component</description>
    <arm_group_label>All-polyethylene Tibial component</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Metal Backed Tibial component</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients suitable for simple cemented primary knee arthroplasty

          -  Patients presenting with osteoarthritis of the knee

          -  Patients with inflammatory arthropathy, requiring total knee arthroplasty

          -  Patients must be ambulatory at time of preoperative assessment clinic

          -  Patients must be able to understand instructions and be willing to return for follow
             up

          -  Patients aged 75 years or over at the time of surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous knee surgery (except arthroscopic / open meniscectomy)

          -  Patients with significant medical co-morbidity

          -  Disorders causing abnormal gait or significant pain

          -  Patients unable to consent

          -  Severe visual impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>75 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Gibb</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maidstone and Tunbridge Wells NHS trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Helen Samuel</last_name>
    <phone>01892 635488</phone>
    <email>h.sankey@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Trauma &amp; Orthopaedic Dept, Tunbridge Wells Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pembury</city>
        <state>Kent</state>
        <zip>TN2 4QJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helen Samuel</last_name>
      <phone>01892 635488</phone>
      <email>h.sankey@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Gibb</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Maidstone &amp; Tunbridge Wells NHS Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Helen Samuel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Mr Paul Gibb - Consultant Orthopaedic Surgeon</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

