<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02483481</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB # 15060244</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02483481</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Ultrasound Elastography to Predict Development of SOS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Ultrasound Elastography to Predict Development of Sinusoidal Obstruction Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Mercy Hospital Kansas City</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Mercy Hospital Kansas City</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Sinusoidal obstruction syndrome (SOS) is a potentially fatal hepatic veno-occlusive
      disease-affecting children following bone marrow transplantation (BMT). SOS most likely
      develops secondary to sinusoidal endothelial damage and subsequent obstruction. The disease
      can be separated into mild, moderate, and severe forms; almost all patients diagnosed with
      severe SOS will die from this disease. Children with severe SOS suffer from multi-organ
      failure with signs and symptoms of portal hypertension (ascites, varices, edema), renal and
      respiratory failure . Although these children may be few and far between, the mere severity
      of the disease process and awful prognosis factors are valid reasons for more medical
      attention. SOS is usually diagnosed via clinical criteria and, despite available prophylaxis
      and treatment, children continue to die from this devastating disease.

      Quantitative shear wave ultrasound elastography with acoustic force radiation imaging is an
      emerging technology that uses ultrasound pressure waves to provide an estimate of tissue
      stiffness. This technique is promising for pediatric imaging because it is portable, quick to
      perform, relatively low cost and involves no ionizing radiation. Acoustic force radiation
      imaging and ultrasound elastography does not have any increased risks over conventional
      ultrasound imaging.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single site prospective cohort study that will compare ultrasound elastography to
      traditional ultrasound parameters in bone marrow transplant patients who are at risk for
      development of SOS.

        -  Primary objective: compare sensitivity and specificity of traditional ultrasound
           parameters and ultrasound elastography of the liver for detecting SOS in BMT patients.

        -  Secondary objectives: 1. compare sensitivity and specificity of traditional ultrasound
           parameters and ultrasound elastography of the liver for classifying SOS in BMT patients.
           2. compare sensitivity and specificity of traditional ultrasound parameters and
           ultrasound elastography of the liver for predicting death in BMT patients with SOS
           (defined as death within 100 days of transplant).

        -  The validity and reliability of the primary and secondary measures when available. The
           validity of the measures will be determined by comparing to clinical gold standards of
           the diagnosis and classification of SOS

      Data Collection Procedures

        -  Candidates for the study will be identified by the Hematology Oncology service when they
           are admitted for bone marrow transplant.

        -  A member of the study team will consent that patient and/or their parents once the
           patient has been identified.

        -  If the patient consents to the study, an initial limited abdominal ultrasound with
           Doppler and shear wave elastography will be performed less than one month prior to bone
           marrow transplant. Demographic and clinical variables will be collected from the chart
           at the time of initial ultrasound and after date of discharge. Lab value variables will
           be collected at the time of the initial ultrasound and during all subsequent
           ultrasounds. Only lab values that have changed since the prior ultrasound will be
           recorded.

        -  Multiple shear wave elastography measurements of the liver will be obtained during any
           post-transplant clinical abdominal ultrasound Data Analyses We will perform two-sided
           t-tests and nonparametric tests for categorical and continuous data, respectively.
           Additionally, we will perform a multivariate regression to determine which variables are
           significantly correlated to death and calculate an odds ratio for each of these
           variables. If a patient is missing any imaging or clinical data, then this patient will
           be excluded from those parts of the data analysis, but the rest of their data will still
           be included in the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence or absence of SOS</measure>
    <time_frame>within 100 days of bone marrow transplant</time_frame>
    <description>clinical determination by provider</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of SOS</measure>
    <time_frame>within 100 days of bone marrow transplant</time_frame>
    <description>death as noted in medical record</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Sinusoidal Obstruction Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Complications of Bone Marrow Transplant</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>shear wave ultrasound elastography</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pediatric bone marrow transplant patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients who are admitted for BMT from the date of study approval until patient
             accrual is met.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BMT patients who do not end up undergoing transplant during that admission. BMT
             patients who do not receive any abdominal ultrasounds post transplantation BMT
             patients who do not consent to the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sherwin Chan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Mercy Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amie Robinson, BSRT(R)(MR) CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>816-302-8311</phone>
    <email>alrobinson@cmh.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sherwin Chan, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>816-234-3000</phone>
    <phone_ext>55973</phone_ext>
    <email>sschan@cmh.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Mercy Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amie Robinson, BSRT(R)(MR), CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>816-302-8311</phone>
      <email>alrobinson@cmh.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sherwin Chan, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>816-234-3000</phone>
      <email>sschan@cmh.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sherwin Chan, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Erin Opfer, DO</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mohamed Radhi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>McDonald GB, Hinds MS, Fisher LD, Schoch HG, Wolford JL, Banaji M, Hardin BJ, Shulman HM, Clift RA. Veno-occlusive disease of the liver and multiorgan failure after bone marrow transplantation: a cohort study of 355 patients. Ann Intern Med. 1993 Feb 15;118(4):255-67.</citation>
    <PMID>8420443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carreras E, Bertz H, Arcese W, Vernant JP, Tomás JF, Hagglund H, Bandini G, Esperou H, Russell J, de la Rubia J, Di Girolamo G, Demuynck H, Hartmann O, Clausen J, Ruutu T, Leblond V, Iriondo A, Bosi A, Ben-Bassat I, Koza V, Gratwohl A, Apperley JF. Incidence and outcome of hepatic veno-occlusive disease after blood or marrow transplantation: a prospective cohort study of the European Group for Blood and Marrow Transplantation. European Group for Blood and Marrow Transplantation Chronic Leukemia Working Party. Blood. 1998 Nov 15;92(10):3599-604.</citation>
    <PMID>9808553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hommeyer SC, Teefey SA, Jacobson AF, Higano CS, Bianco JA, Colacurcio CJ, McDonald GB. Venocclusive disease of the liver: prospective study of US evaluation. Radiology. 1992 Sep;184(3):683-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1509050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teefey SA, Brink JA, Borson RA, Middleton WD. Diagnosis of venoocclusive disease of the liver after bone marrow transplantation: value of duplex sonography. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 1995 Jun;164(6):1397-401.</citation>
    <PMID>7754881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>García-Criado A, Gilabert R, Salmerón JM, Nicolau C, Vilana R, Bianchi L, Buñesch L, García-Valdecasas JC, Rimola A, Brú C. Significance of and contributing factors for a high resistive index on Doppler sonography of the hepatic artery immediately after surgery: prognostic implications for liver transplant recipients. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2003 Sep;181(3):831-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12933490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nicolau C, Brú C, Carreras E, Bosch J, Bianchi L, Gilabert R, Vilana R. Sonographic diagnosis and hemodynamic correlation in veno-occlusive disease of the liver. J Ultrasound Med. 1993 Aug;12(8):437-40.</citation>
    <PMID>8411325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herbetko J, Grigg AP, Buckley AR, Phillips GL. Venoocclusive liver disease after bone marrow transplantation: findings at duplex sonography. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 1992 May;158(5):1001-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1566656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bamber J, Cosgrove D, Dietrich CF, Fromageau J, Bojunga J, Calliada F, Cantisani V, Correas JM, D'Onofrio M, Drakonaki EE, Fink M, Friedrich-Rust M, Gilja OH, Havre RF, Jenssen C, Klauser AS, Ohlinger R, Saftoiu A, Schaefer F, Sporea I, Piscaglia F. EFSUMB guidelines and recommendations on the clinical use of ultrasound elastography. Part 1: Basic principles and technology. Ultraschall Med. 2013 Apr;34(2):169-84. doi: 10.1055/s-0033-1335205. Epub 2013 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23558397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cosgrove D, Piscaglia F, Bamber J, Bojunga J, Correas JM, Gilja OH, Klauser AS, Sporea I, Calliada F, Cantisani V, D'Onofrio M, Drakonaki EE, Fink M, Friedrich-Rust M, Fromageau J, Havre RF, Jenssen C, Ohlinger R, Săftoiu A, Schaefer F, Dietrich CF; EFSUMB. EFSUMB guidelines and recommendations on the clinical use of ultrasound elastography. Part 2: Clinical applications. Ultraschall Med. 2013 Jun;34(3):238-53. doi: 10.1055/s-0033-1335375. Epub 2013 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23605169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shiina T, Nightingale KR, Palmeri ML, Hall TJ, Bamber JC, Barr RG, Castera L, Choi BI, Chou YH, Cosgrove D, Dietrich CF, Ding H, Amy D, Farrokh A, Ferraioli G, Filice C, Friedrich-Rust M, Nakashima K, Schafer F, Sporea I, Suzuki S, Wilson S, Kudo M. WFUMB guidelines and recommendations for clinical use of ultrasound elastography: Part 1: basic principles and terminology. Ultrasound Med Biol. 2015 May;41(5):1126-47. doi: 10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2015.03.009. Epub 2015 Mar 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25805059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stenzel M, Mentzel HJ. Ultrasound elastography and contrast-enhanced ultrasound in infants, children and adolescents. Eur J Radiol. 2014 Sep;83(9):1560-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ejrad.2014.06.007. Epub 2014 Jun 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25022978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferraioli G, Filice C, Castera L, Choi BI, Sporea I, Wilson SR, Cosgrove D, Dietrich CF, Amy D, Bamber JC, Barr R, Chou YH, Ding H, Farrokh A, Friedrich-Rust M, Hall TJ, Nakashima K, Nightingale KR, Palmeri ML, Schafer F, Shiina T, Suzuki S, Kudo M. WFUMB guidelines and recommendations for clinical use of ultrasound elastography: Part 3: liver. Ultrasound Med Biol. 2015 May;41(5):1161-79. doi: 10.1016/j.ultrasmedbio.2015.03.007. Epub 2015 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25800942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sugitani M, Fujita Y, Yumoto Y, Fukushima K, Takeuchi T, Shimokawa M, Kato K. A new method for measurement of placental elasticity: acoustic radiation force impulse imaging. Placenta. 2013 Nov;34(11):1009-13. doi: 10.1016/j.placenta.2013.08.014. Epub 2013 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24075540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kutty SS, Peng Q, Danford DA, Fletcher SE, Perry D, Talmon GA, Scott C, Kugler JD, Duncan KF, Quiros-Tejeira RE, Kutty S; Liver Adult-Pediatric-Congenital-Heart-Disease Dysfunction Study (LADS) Group. Increased hepatic stiffness as consequence of high hepatic afterload in the Fontan circulation: a vascular Doppler and elastography study. Hepatology. 2014 Jan;59(1):251-60. doi: 10.1002/hep.26631. Epub 2013 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23913702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leschied JR, Dillman JR, Bilhartz J, Heider A, Smith EA, Lopez MJ. Shear wave elastography helps differentiate biliary atresia from other neonatal/infantile liver diseases. Pediatr Radiol. 2015 Mar;45(3):366-75. doi: 10.1007/s00247-014-3149-z. Epub 2014 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25238807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Özmen E, Adaletli I, Kayadibi Y, Emre Ş, Kiliç F, Dervişoğlu S, Kuruğoğlu S, Şenyüz OF. The impact of share wave elastography in differentiation of hepatic hemangioma from malignant liver tumors in pediatric population. Eur J Radiol. 2014 Sep;83(9):1691-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ejrad.2014.06.002. Epub 2014 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25012068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin P, Chen M, Liu B, Wang S, Li X. Diagnostic performance of shear wave elastography in the identification of malignant thyroid nodules: a meta-analysis. Eur Radiol. 2014 Nov;24(11):2729-38. doi: 10.1007/s00330-014-3320-9. Epub 2014 Aug 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25113648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu B, Liang J, Zheng Y, Xie X, Huang G, Zhou L, Wang W, Lu M. Two-dimensional shear wave elastography as promising diagnostic tool for predicting malignant thyroid nodules: a prospective single-centre experience. Eur Radiol. 2015 Mar;25(3):624-34. doi: 10.1007/s00330-014-3455-8. Epub 2014 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25298171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lacourpaille L, Hug F, Guével A, Péréon Y, Magot A, Hogrel JY, Nordez A. Non-invasive assessment of muscle stiffness in patients with Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Muscle Nerve. 2015 Feb;51(2):284-6. doi: 10.1002/mus.24445. Epub 2014 Dec 23.</citation>
    <PMID>25187068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 29, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sinusoidal obstruction syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound elastography</keyword>
  <keyword>bone marrow transplant</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatic Veno-Occlusive Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

