<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02482753</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDM301</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02482753</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Chidamide in Combination With Exemestane in Patients With Advanced Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III Trial of Chidamide in Combination With Exemestane in Patients With Hormone Receptor-Positive Advanced Breast Cancer (ACE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chipscreen Biosciences, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chipscreen Biosciences, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was to evaluate the efficacy and safety of Chidamide in combination with
      exemestane in postmenopausal patients with hormone-receptor positive advanced breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study including two parts: (1) Part A, open-label design, 20 patients will be enrolled
      and receive 30 mg Chidamide BIW and 25 mg exemestane QD. The main object of part A is to
      evaluate the pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profile of Chidamide when in combination
      with exemestane. (2) Part B, randomized and double-blinded design, 328 patients will be
      assigned randomly in a 2:1 ratio to experiment group (30 mg Chidamide BIW + 25 mg exemestane
      QD) and control group (placebo BIW + 25 mg exemestane QD), to evaluate the efficacy and
      safety of Chidamide when in combination with exemestane in patients with locally advanced or
      metastatic estrogen receptor-positive breast cancer progressing on endocrine therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>progression-free survival (PFS), double-blinded period</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is measured from the date of randomization until progression or death, whichever is first met</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pharmacokinetic profiles of Chidamide, open-label period</measure>
    <time_frame>0,1,2,4,8,12,24,48,72 hours after the first dose of Chidamide on day 2 at induced stage (4 days in total); 0,1,2,4,8,12,24,48,72 hours post-dose on day 1 of cycle 1 at combination treatment stage</time_frame>
    <description>The pharmacokinetic parameters include Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) , Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax), time to reach Cmax (Tmax), mean concentration at steady state (Css)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pharmacokinetic profiles of exemestane, open-label period</measure>
    <time_frame>0,1,2,4,8,12,24 hours after the first dose of exemestane on day 1 at induced stage (4 days in total); 0,1,2,4,8,12,24,48,72 hours post-dose on day 1 of cycle 1 at combination treatment stage</time_frame>
    <description>The pharmacokinetic parameters include Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) , Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax), time to reach Cmax (Tmax), mean concentration at steady state (Css)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>acetylation level of histone H3, open-label period</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-dose of Chidamide on day 2 at induced stage (4 days in total); pre-dose of Chidamide on day 1 of cycle 2 at combination treatment stage</time_frame>
    <description>The acetylation level of histone H3 is assayed by enzyme-linked immuno sorbent assay (ELISA).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival, double-blinded period</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from randomization to death from any cause, assessed up to 6 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS is measured from the date of randomization until death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>duration of response (DOR), double-blinded period</measure>
    <time_frame>From the first date of response until the date of first documented progression, assessed up to 3years</time_frame>
    <description>DOR is measured from the first date when criteria for response is met until the first date when the criteria for progression is met</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>objective response rate (ORR), open-label period and double-blinded period</measure>
    <time_frame>Response is assessed once every 6 weeks, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>ORR is defined as percentage of participants with Complete Response and Partial Response, assessed by the investigators according to the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical benefit rate (CBR), open-label period and double-blinded period</measure>
    <time_frame>Response is assessed once every 6 weeks, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>ORR is defined as percentage of participants with Complete Response, Partial Response or Stable Disease ≥ 24 weeks, assessed by the investigators according to the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS, open-label period</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from the start of treatment to the earliest of documented disease progression, or death, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is measured from the start of treatment until progression or death, whichever is first met</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">365</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chidamide + exemestane, open-label</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive 30 mg Chidamide per week and 25 mg exemestane QD. Courses repeat every 4 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chidamide + exemestane, double-blinded</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive 30 mg Chidamide twice per week and 25 mg exemestane QD. Courses repeat every 4 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo + exemestane, double-blinded</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive placebo twice per week and 25 mg exemestane PO QD. Courses repeat every 4 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chidamide</intervention_name>
    <description>30 mg, administered orally twice per week (BIW)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chidamide + exemestane, open-label</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Chidamide + exemestane, double-blinded</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CS055</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>exemestane</intervention_name>
    <description>25 mg, PO daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chidamide + exemestane, open-label</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Chidamide + exemestane, double-blinded</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo + exemestane, double-blinded</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aromasin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered orally twice per week (BIW)</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo + exemestane, double-blinded</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Simulation tablet of Chidamide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 ~ 75 years old, postmenopausal women;

          2. Histological or cytological confirmation of hormone receptor-positive [estrogen
             receptor (ER) positive and progesterone receptors (PgR) positive or negative] breast
             cancer;

          3. Disease progression or recurrence after at least one endocrine therapy (either in
             advanced/metastatic setting or adjuvant setting);

          4. ≤4 prior therapies (either in advanced/metastatic setting or adjuvant setting),
             patients may have received one prior chemotherapy;

          5. The disease condition is inoperable, stage III or stage IV, at least one measurable
             lesion or simple bone metastases with no measurable lesions;

          6. Last prior therapy intervals: (a) if the last treatment was endocrine therapy, the
             interval must ≥ 2 weeks; (b) if the last treatment was chemotherapy therapy, the
             interval must ≥ 4 weeks;

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status: 0~1;

          8. Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.5×109 / L, platelet count ≥ 100×109 / L, hemoglobin ≥ 90
             g/L;

          9. Life expectancy ≥ 3 months;

         10. Have signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients have known central nervous system (CNS) metastases or a history of CNS
             metastases , or with leptomeningeal disease;

          2. Patients with human epidermal growth factor receptor-2 (Her-2) positive;

          3. Patients previously received treatment with exemestane;

          4. Patients received radiotherapy ≤ 4 weeks prior to study entry;

          5. Patients with no measurable lesion (except simple bone metastasis), such as pleural or
             pericardial effusion, ascites, et al;

          6. Patients have uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease, including:

               1. Myocardial infarction (&lt; the last 12 months)

               2. Uncontrolled angina (&lt; the last 6 months)

               3. Congestive heart failure (&lt; the last 6 months), or Left Ventricular Ejection
                  Fraction (LVEF) &lt; 50% prior to study entry

               4. History of any significant ventricular arrhythmias (e.g., ventricular
                  tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, or TdP)

               5. History of significant QT interval prolongation, or Corrected QT Interval (QTc) &gt;
                  450 ms prior to study entry

               6. History of cerebrovascular accident

               7. Symptomatic coronary heart disease requiring treatment with agents

          7. The size of fluid area detected by cardiac ultrasonography in cavum pericardium is
             ≥10mm during diastolic period;

          8. History of organ transplantation;

          9. Patients have not recovered from all clinically relevant toxicities to grade 1 due to
             prior therapies;

         10. Patients have clinical significant gastrointestinal abnormality, e.g., unable to
             swallow, chronic diarrhea, ileus, that would interfere the ingestion,transportation or
             absorption of oral agents;

         11. Active infection [Suffered from active infection of bacteria, virus, fungi,
             mycobacteria, parasites, or other infections (excluding nail bed fungal infections),
             or require intravenous antibiotic therapy, or antiviral therapy, or hospitalization
             due to any significant infection events], or persistent fever within 14 days prior to
             study entry;

         12. Patients had organ surgery &lt; 6 weeks prior to study entry;

         13. Abnormal liver function [total bilirubin &gt; 1.5×upper limit of normal (&gt; 3×upper limit
             of normal in case of Gilbert syndrome); Transaminases (ALT, AST) &gt;2.5×upper limit of
             normal (&gt;5x upper limit of normal patients with liver metastases), abnormal renal
             function (serum creatinine &gt; 1.5×upper limit of normal);

         14. Patients with prior invasive malignancies with the exception of curatively-treated
             basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or cervical carcinoma in situ,
             unless received curative treatment and with documented evidence of no recurrence in
             the past five years;

         15. Any mental or cognitive disorder, that would interfere the ability to understand the
             informed consent document or the operation and compliance of study;

         16. Patients are currently enrolled in another investigational drug study, or completed
             within 4 weeks prior to study entry, with the exception of patients only in overall
             survival follow-up;

         17. Any other condition which is inappropriate for the study in the opinion of the
             investigators.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zefei Jiang</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>307 Hospital of PLA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The 307th Hospital of Chinese people's Liberation Army</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100021</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chidamide</keyword>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>exemestane</keyword>
  <keyword>Estrogen Receptor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Exemestane</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

