<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02487823</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCMPC-BKM-IPC 2012-009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02487823</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Finding Study of BKM 120 in Combination With LH-RH Agonists and Bicalutamide in Men With Non Castrate Metastatic Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>NCMPC-BKM</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase Ib Dose Finding Study of BKM 120 in Combination With LH-RH Agonists and Bicalutamide in Men With Non Castrate Metastatic Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut Paoli-Calmettes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut Paoli-Calmettes</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the maximum-tolerated dose (MTD) of BKM120 when administered orally in
      combination with daily bicalutamide and LH-RH agonists to men with non castrate metastatic
      prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer is the second leading cause of cancer and the third cause of death in male.
      Majority of patients had local disease that is cured by local treatment. Metastases are rare
      at the time of diagnosis but may occur after failure of local treatment (SEER).

      Recommended treatment for non castrate metastatic prostate cancer (NCMPC) is castration by
      orchiectomy or medical castration by LH-RH (luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone) agonists
      alone and or combined androgen blockage with LH-RH agonists and anti androgen. Immediate
      treatment versus deferred treatment improve specific survival for advanced prostatic cancer :
      initial results of the Medical Research Council trial.

      Continuous castration is superior to intermittent one with a median survival of 49 months.
      Chemotherapy combined with castration demonstrate a survival improvement compared to
      castration alone for high volume disease defined by visceral involvement and or 4 or more
      bone metastatis with almost one apendicular metastasis. For low volume disease or non
      selected metastatic hormone sensitive prostate cancer, Docetaxel demonstrated no survival
      benefit evaluated in a recent phase III trial (Sweeney C et al abs ASCO 2014).

      However, most patients showing an initial response to hormonal therapy for advanced prostate
      cancer will progress to a castration-resistant phase of the disease with a much poorer
      prognosis. Median duration to androgen deprivation is 24 to 36 months, after patients become
      castrate resistant and docetaxel and other hormonal therapy like abiraterone and enzalutamide
      demonstrate survival improvement in castrate resistant prostate cancer.

      Despite the considerable progress made with new agents such as abiraterone acetate or MDV3100
      in metastatic castration resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC), new therapies are critical to
      improve castration sensitivity.

      Understanding the mechanisms of resistance to AR and identifying directed new therapies is a
      real challenge in this situation.

      Prostate cancer is characterized by its dependence on AR and its frequent activation of the
      Phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase (PI3K) pathway. Besides the resistance mediated by the mutation
      in the AR, among the non-steroid alternative pathways two major pathways have been associated
      with AR activation and CRPC, namely Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK and PI3K/AKT. More specifically a genomic
      profiling of human prostate cancer was recently reported where 42% of primary and 100% of the
      metastatic lesions studied had upregulated PI3K signaling mostly via loss of phosphatase
      activity such as PTEN (Phosphatase and tensin homolog) or INPP4B (inositol polyphosphate
      4-phosphatase type II).

      Dysregulation of the PI3K/PTEN pathway has also been associated with resistance to
      conventional antiandrogen therapies. Preclinical data support the potential for a reciprocal
      negative feedback between the AR and PI3K pathway.

      Development of castration resistance is multifactorel including weak antagonist binding affi
      nity to AR, up-regulation of AR co-stimulatory pathways and increased intratumoural androgen
      levels as a result of intracrine androgen, as well as partial agonists properties of
      antiandrogens when AR is overexpressed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Defect of recruitment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the maximum-tolerated dose (MTD) of BKM120 when administered orally in combination with daily bicalutamide and LH-RH agonists to men with non castrate metastatic prostate cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Patient follow-up done until progression, or until 6 months after the end of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the efficacy of daily oral BKM120 in combination with LH-RH agonists and bicalutamide in men with NCMPC as measured by the overall rate and free survival of biological or clinical progression (composite measures).</measure>
    <time_frame>Free survival of biological or clinical progression an expected average 30 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Non Castrate Metastatic Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BKM 120 (60 mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BKM120 (60 mg) in combination with LH-RH agonists and bicalutamide</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BKM 120 (80 mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BKM120 (80 mg) in combination with LH-RH agonists and bicalutamide</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BKM 120 (100 mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BKM120 (100 mg) in combination with LH-RH agonists and bicalutamide</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BKM120 in combination with LH-RH agonists (suprefact) and bicalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>BKM 120, LH-RH agonists and Bicalutamide</description>
    <arm_group_label>BKM 120 (60 mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BKM 120 (80 mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BKM 120 (100 mg)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BKM120, LH-RH agonists (suprefact) and bicalutamide (casodex)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed Informed Consent Form (ICF) prior to screening

          -  Male patients (≥ 18 years)

          -  WHO performance status ≤ 2

          -  Histologically-confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate

          -  Patients with non castrate metastatic prostate cancer, with radiological metastatic
             disease ; patients with metastatic disease is documented on a Pet-Scan to choline is
             also eligible

          -  No previous chemotherapy treatment during the metastatic disease

          -  Neoadjuvant or adjuvant androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) treatment or for rising PSA
             is permitted if the ADT have been stopped for at least one year without metastasis or
             PSA increase during this time

          -  LH-RH agonists and bicalutamide had to began ≥ 28 days before registration

          -  Minimum pre treatment PSA &gt; 5 ng/ml

          -  Patient has adequate bone marrow and organ function as defined by the following
             laboratory values:

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) ≥ 1.0 x 109/L

               -  Platelets ≥ 100 x 109/L

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

               -  INR ≤ 2

               -  Potassium, calcium, magnesium within normal limits for the institution

               -  Serum Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) within normal
                  range (or ≤ 3.0 x ULN if liver metastases are present)

               -  Serum bilirubin within normal range (or ≤ 1.5 x ULN if liver metastases are
                  present; or total bilirubin ≤ 3.0 x ULN with direct bilirubin within normal range
                  in patients with well documented Gilbert Syndrome)

               -  Fasting plasma glucose (FPG) ≤ 120 mg/dL or ≤ 6.7 mmol/L 11. Agree to use
                  effective contraception during the study and for at least 16 weeks after
                  discontinuation 12. Patient is able to swallow and retain oral medication

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients eligible for this study must not meet any of the following criteria:

          -  Patient has received previous treatment with PI3K and/or mTOR inhibitors

          -  Patient has a concurrent malignancy or has a malignancy within 3 years of study
             enrollment, (with the exception of adequately treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma
             or non-melanomatous skin cancer)

          -  ADT &gt; 3 months

          -  Patient has any of the following mood disorders as judged by the Investigator or a
             Psychiatrist, or meets the cut-off score of ≥ 12 in the PHQ-9 or a cut-off of ≥ 15 in
             the GAD-7 mood scale, respectively, or selects a positive response of '1, 2, or 3' to
             question number 9 regarding potential for suicidal thoughts ideation in the PHQ-9
             (independent of the total score of the PHQ-9):

               -  Medically documented history of or active major depressive episode, bipolar
                  disorder (I or II), obsessive-compulsive disorder, schizophrenia, a history of
                  suicidal attempt or ideation, or homicidal ideation (immediate risk of doing harm
                  to others) or patients with active severe personality disorders (defined
                  according to DSM-IV) are not eligible Note: for patients with psychotropic
                  treatments ongoing at baseline, the dose and the schedule should not be modified
                  within the previous 6 weeks prior to start of study drug

               -  ≥ CTCAE grade 3 anxiety

          -  Patient is concurrently using other approved or investigational antineoplastic agent
             Patient has received pelvic and/or para-aortic radiotherapy ≤ 28 days prior to
             enrollment in this study or has not recovered from side effects of such therapy at the
             time of initiation of screening procedures Patient has had major surgery within 28
             days prior to starting study drug or has not recovered from major side effects of the
             surgery Patient has poorly controlled diabetes mellitus (HbA1c &gt; 8 %) Patient with
             uncontrolled hypertension

        Patient has active cardiac disease including any of the following:

          -  Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) &lt; 50% as determined by Multiple Gated
             acquisition (MUGA) scan or echocardiogram (ECHO)

          -  QTc &gt; 480 msec on screening ECG (using the QTcF formula

          -  Angina pectoris that requires the use of anti-anginal medication

          -  Ventricular arrhythmias except for benign premature ventricular contractions

          -  Supraventricular and nodal arrythmias requiring a pacemaker or not controlled with
             medication

          -  Conduction abnormality requiring a pacemaker

          -  Valvular disease with documented compromise in cardiac function

          -  Symptomatic pericarditis

             - Patient has a history of cardiac dysfunction including any of the following:

          -  Myocardial infarction within the last 6 months, documented by persistent elevated
             cardiac enzymes or persistent regional wall abnormalities on assessment of LVEF
             function

          -  History of documented congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association functional
             classification III-IV)

          -  Documented cardiomyopathy

               -  Patient is currently receiving treatment with QT prolonging medication known to
                  have a risk to induce Torsades de Pointes, and the treatment cannot be
                  discontinued or switched to a different medication prior to starting study drug

               -  Patient has impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
                  significantly alter the absorption of BKM120 (e.g., ulcerative diseases,
                  uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome, or small bowel
                  resection)

               -  Patient receiving chronic treatment with steroids or another immunosuppressive
                  agent Note: Topical applications (e.g., rash), inhaled sprays (e.g., obstructive
                  airways diseases), eye drops or local injections (e.g., intra-articular) are
                  allowed. Patients with previously treated brain metastases, who are on a stable
                  low dose corticosteroids treatment (e.g., dexamethasone 2 mg/day, prednisolone 10
                  mg/day) for at least 14 days before start of study treatment, are eligible

               -  Patient has other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical condition that
                  would, in the investigator's judgment contraindicate her participation in the
                  clinical study (e.g.,chronic pancreatitis, active chronic hepatitis etc.)

               -  Patient has a history of non-compliance to medical regimen

               -  Patient is currently being treated with drugs known to be moderate and strong
                  inhibitors or inducers of isoenzyme CYP3A, and the treatment cannot be
                  discontinued or switched to a different medication prior to starting study drug.
                  Please refer to annex 9 for a list of prohibited CYP3A inhibitors and inducers
                  Note: the oral anti-diabetic drugs troglitazone and pioglitazone are CYP3A
                  inducers

               -  Patient has a known history of HIV (testing not mandatory) infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Paoli Calmettes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13009</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.institutpaolicalmettes.fr</url>
    <description>official web site of the sponsor</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bicalutamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prolactin Release-Inhibiting Factors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Buserelin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

