<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02488395</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C14-58</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IDRCB</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02488395</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Superior Colliculus Activity in Parkinson Disease: a Potential Marker?</brief_title>
  <acronym>AGIRPARK</acronym>
  <official_title>Superior Colliculus Activity in Parkinson Disease: a Potential Marker? fMRI Brain Activation in Response to Visual Stimuli.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The ultimate goal of this project is to evaluate a possible new strategy to diagnose earlier
      Parkinson's disease, using the superior colliculus as a biomarker.

      Preliminary data from the investigator's group in a rat model of Parkinson's disease suggest
      that the superior colliculus, a sensory structure, show an early deficit in visual
      processing. The investigator's data also suggests that with the evolution of the disease,
      this structure presents a neuronal re-organisation leading which causes a sensory rebound
      after the introduction of the treatment. The light responses in the superior colliculus were
      faster, bigger in amplitude and lasted longer (Rolland et al., 2012). Those results raise an
      important question about the superior colliculus functional state in Parkinson's patients. If
      this structure have a similar neuroplasticity, the investigators could hypothesize that the
      superior colliculus may also present a sensory rebound when introducing the treatment. If
      this hypothesis is true, the accelerated and amplified light responses of this structure may
      explain the difficulties felt by the patients to inhibit reflexive saccades induced by the
      appearance of unexpected visual stimuli. Indeed, the superior colliculus is involved in the
      orientation of the head and eye toward any sudden changes in our environment (Wurtz and
      Albano, 1980) and the light responses of this structure are strongly correlated with the
      speed of the saccade (Marino et al., 2012).

      Therefore, the investigators want to test if a similar deficit could be observed in the
      superior colliculus of newly diagnosed PD patients. Data will be compared to matching
      controls.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project aims at better understanding the physiopathology of Parkinson's disease and the
      effect of the administration of the classical medical treatment. The main aim of this project
      is to evaluate the possibility of an early detection using a new original strategy. The
      investigators want to demonstrate the predictive value of the superior colliculus light
      responses as an early biomarker.

      The investigators will perform functional magnetic resonance imagery (fMRI) to measure the
      BOLD light responses of the superior colliculus at different key stages of the normal medical
      follow up of Parkinson's patients by the neurologist (when diagnosed, when introducing the
      first treatment and when the treatment is stabilised).

      Two groups of participants will be tested: a) a group of de novo patients, which have just
      been diagnosed and haven't started their treatment; b) a group of matching controls.

      A first fMRI session (S1) will be performed to compare the light induced BOLD response of the
      superior colliculus between de novo patients and their matching controls. This session will
      evaluate a possible visual processing dysfunction in the superior colliculus of newly
      diagnosed patients.

      Parkinson's patients will then start their treatment and a second session (S2) will be done
      on this group shortly after the introduction of the treatment to measure its acute effect. If
      the superior colliculus of those patients presents a sensory rebound, the investigators
      should observe a bigger light-induced BOLD response after the treatment compared to before
      the treatment.

      A third session (S3) will be performed after the optimal adjustment of the treatment on motor
      symptoms which would be around six month after the start of the treatment. This adjustment is
      long and difficult, realized by the neurologist according to its effect on the motor
      symptoms. Those two last fMRI will allow the investigators to compare the effect of the
      introduction of the treatment on the motor symptoms, known to not improve correctly at this
      stage, and on non-motor symptoms (visual processing deficits in this project) from which no
      information are available to the investigators knowledge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Light responses measure in the superior colliculus</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours / session</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>de novo Parkinson's patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group includes de novo Parkinson's patients who have just been diagnosed and not started their treatment at the inclusion.
This group will perform three fMRI sessions at different crucial steps of their normal follow up with a neurologist. Their visual abilities will be tested with an ophthalmologic evaluation and their sensitivity to contrast with a visual psycho-physics test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>matching controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group includes age-matching control participants to the first Parkinson group.
This group will perform one fMRI session. Their visual abilities will be tested with an ophthalmologic evaluation and their sensitivity to contrast with a visual psycho-physics test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fMRI</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators will use a non invasive fMRI technique centred on the superior colliculus during the presentation of flickered check-boards with varying contrast (1, 3, 5 and 9 %).</description>
    <arm_group_label>de novo Parkinson's patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>matching controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ophthalmologic evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>The aim of this experiment is the evaluate the functional state of a visual structure. Therefore, with this ophthalmologic test, the investigators will control if the participant does not present major visual deficits. This examination will evaluate the visual acuity and the visual field. A funduscopic examination will also be performed to check the retina.</description>
    <arm_group_label>de novo Parkinson's patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>matching controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>visual psychophysics test</intervention_name>
    <description>This test will allow to control the sensitivity of the participant to our contrast. The participant will be asked to look at screen on which three static check-boards will be presented. The participant will have to choose the two check-boards with the closest contrast.</description>
    <arm_group_label>de novo Parkinson's patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>matching controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Groups of de novo Parkinson's patients and their age matching controls.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  De novo parkinson's patients being just diagnosed (stage 1 according to the Hoehn and
             Yahr scale: first unilateral signs with no discomfort in everyday life) without a
             current dopaminergic treatment and who have not started their anti-parkinsonian
             treatment.

          -  Both Parkinson's patients and their age matching control must not present a major
             visual pathology (mainly in the retina) which may interfere with the visual task.

          -  Signed informed and free consent.

          -  Matching controls must not present a neurological or psychiatric troubles.

          -  For the matching controls: There are no contraindication on current treatments apart
             from those to treat other neurological disease than Parkinson's disease or psychiatric
             troubles.

          -  For Parkinson's patients: There are no contraindication on current treatments apart
             from those to treat neurological troubles including anti-parkinsonian treatment, or
             psychiatric troubles.

          -  As a precaution, the investigators will check that no MRI exam has been performed
             during the week preceding our fMRI.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parkinson's patients with important tremor limiting the validity of the fMRI
             acquisition.

          -  Adult under supervision

          -  Incapacity to understand the consent explanations.

          -  Impossibility to participate to the whole experimental protocol.

          -  No affiliation to a health insurance.

          -  Consent not signed by a participant or refusal by the participant to participate to
             the experiment.

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding woman.

          -  Administrative or justice freedom restricted participant.

        Exclusion Criteria specific for MRI:

          -  Pacemaker, neurosensorial stimulator or implanted defibrillator.

          -  Presence of ocular or cerebral ferromagnetic material.

          -  Respiratory disease (i.e. asthma), cardio-vascular deficits, claustrophobia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elena Moro, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michel Dojat, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elena Moro, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33 4 76765791</phone>
    <email>emoro@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michel Dojat, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>33 4 56 52 06 01</phone>
    <email>michel.dojat@ujf-grenoble.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <state>Isere</state>
        <zip>38000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elena Moro, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <phone>334 76765791</phone>
      <email>emoro@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pierre Pellissier</last_name>
      <phone>33 4 76 76 94 59</phone>
      <email>ppelissier@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grenoble Institute of Neurosciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <state>Isere</state>
        <zip>38000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elena Moro, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <phone>33 4 76765791</phone>
      <email>emoro@chu-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michel Dojat, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>33 4 56 52 06 01</phone>
      <email>michel.dojat@ujf-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elena Moro, MD/PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michel Dojat, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Veronique Coizet, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRMAGE</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <state>Isere</state>
        <zip>38000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michel Dojat, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>33 456 52 06 01</phone>
      <email>Michel.dojat@ujf-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Veronique Coizet, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>33 456 52 06 88</phone>
      <email>veronique.coizet@ujf-grenoble.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://neurosciences.ujf-grenoble.fr/?language=en</url>
    <description>Investigation center</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Marino RA, Levy R, Boehnke S, White BJ, Itti L, Munoz DP. Linking visual response properties in the superior colliculus to saccade behavior. Eur J Neurosci. 2012 Jun;35(11):1738-52. doi: 10.1111/j.1460-9568.2012.08079.x. Epub 2012 May 28.</citation>
    <PMID>22639796</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wurtz RH, Albano JE. Visual-motor function of the primate superior colliculus. Annu Rev Neurosci. 1980;3:189-226. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6774653</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rolland M, Carcenac C, Overton PG, Savasta M, Coizet V. Enhanced visual responses in the superior colliculus and subthalamic nucleus in an animal model of Parkinson's disease. Neuroscience. 2013 Nov 12;252:277-88. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2013.07.047. Epub 2013 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>23916713</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-motor symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Visual deficits</keyword>
  <keyword>Superior colliculus</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

