<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02487277</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>144515</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02487277</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PEGPH20, Gemicitabine and Nab-Paclitaxel for Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Perioperative Stromal Depletion Strategies in Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Andrew Ko</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We will be conducting a Phase II study investigating PEGPH20 in combination with gemcitabine
      and nab-paclitaxel in patients with borderline resectable PDAC at the Helen Diller Family
      Comprehensive Cancer Center at UCSF. There are multiple definitions of borderline resectable
      PDAC including the MD Anderson definition and the criteria developed during the Consensus
      Conference sponsored by the American Hepato-Pancreato-Biliary Association, Society of
      Surgical Oncology, and Society for Surgery of the Alimentary Tract. Borderline resectable
      PDAC cases will be identified per the definition developed in the currently running
      inter-group pilot trial for borderline resectable pancreatic cancer (NCT01821612). Per this
      trial, borderline resectable PDAC is defined as &quot;presence of any one or more of the following
      on CT:

        -  An interface between the primary tumor and the superior mesenteric vein or portal vein
           (SMV-PV) measuring ≥ 180° of the circumference of the vessel wall

        -  Short-segment occlusion of the SMV-PV with normal vein above and below the level of
           obstruction that is amenable to resection and venous reconstruction

        -  Short segment interface (of any degree) between tumor and hepatic artery with normal
           artery proximal and distal to the interface that is amenable to resection and
           reconstruction.

        -  An interface between the tumor, and SMA measuring &lt; 180º of the circumference of the
           vessel wall.

      This trial will be conducted in two parts. In Part I, pre-treatment EUS-guided core biopsies
      of the pancreatic tumor, CA 19-9 levels and functional MRIs including DCE-MRI and DWI-MRI
      will be obtained for the first fifteen patients enrolled. After a 1-week run-in period with
      PEGPH20 on days 1 and 4, patients will have repeat EUS-guided core biopsies, functional MRI,
      CA 19-9 level and baseline CT chest, abdomen and pelvis. Subsequently, patients will be
      started on treatment with PEGPH20, gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel given weekly for 3 weeks,
      every 28 days. To evaluate the disease response to treatment, CA 19-9 levels will be checked
      monthly and restaging CT chest, abdomen and pelvis will be obtained every 8 weeks. If there
      is disease progression at any point in the study, patients will be taken off of study and
      alternative treatments will be offered. At the completion of 4 cycles of therapy, restaging
      CT scans will be obtained to determine resectability. If the patients are found to have
      resectable disease, an additional functional MRI will be obtained to evaluate the PDAC
      stroma. If the patients are able to have successful surgeries, tissue analyses will be
      performed on the resected pancreatic tumor. These patients will then proceed to get 2 cycles
      of adjuvant chemotherapy with gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel. If the patients are deemed to
      be surgical candidates but are found to have unresectable disease in the operating room, an
      intraoperative core biopsy of the pancreatic tumor will be obtained for tissue analyses. At
      the time of initiation of therapy with PEGPH20, patients will be started on prophylactic dose
      of enoxaparin 1 mg/kg subcutaneous daily. This will be continued throughout the study
      participation.

      In Part II, an additional 21 patients will be enrolled, and will begin neoadjuvant therapy
      with PEGPH20, gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel without the 1 week run-in of PEGPH20-only or the
      pre- and post-run-in EUS-guided biopsies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For Specific Aim 1, we will be monitoring the post-operative complication of clinically
      relevant pancreatic fistula within one week of surgery per the standard clinical guidelines
      as noted above. Common clinical presentations of pancreatic fistula include abdominal pain,
      leukocytosis and fever (temperature &gt;100.4 degrees). Diagnostic work-up of pancreatic fistula
      will be with CT abdomen with contrast, which has a sensitivity of 63% and specificity of 83%
      for detecting pancreatic fistula. The pancreatic fistulas will be categorized into grades A,
      B or C as previously reported. Our study will be investigating only clinically relevant
      pancreatic fistulas, i.e. grades B or C. Depending on the grade of pancreatic fistula,
      patients will be treated as indicated with conservative treatment options including bowel
      rest, antibiotics, somatostatin analogues and percutaneous drainage or surgical
      re-exploration. We will also track other relevant post-operative complications such as
      delayed wound healing, development of wound dehiscence or wound infection.

      The tissue analyses will include review of the immunohistochemical (IHC) stains for actin,
      hyaluronic acid staining with binding protein probe, proliferation as measured by ki-67% and
      Phospho-histone H3 (Ph-H3); cell apoptosis as evaluated by IHC stain for cleaved caspase 3
      (CC3) and Tunel. If limited tissue sample is obtained via the core biopsies, the priority of
      tissue analysis will be as follows: (1) fixed in formalin for H&amp;E and IHC (Ph-H3; CC3/Tunel;
      HA binding); (2) fixed in OCT such that IHC with difficult antibodies can be done (to
      potentially obtain mRNA or DNA). The IHC studies will be done at the UCSF Helen Diller Family
      Comprehensive Cancer Center Immunohistochemistry and Molecular Pathology Core. The tissue
      analyses of the biopsy and surgical specimens will be done by study pathologist.

      The CT and MR imaging analyses will be performed at the Abdominal Imaging at UCSF. To
      decrease the impact that metal stents may have on the functional MRI results, we will include
      only patients who have plastic stents in our study. In addition, to reduce variability in
      results, the DCE-MRI and DWI-MRI will be obtained on the same MR machine at a similar time of
      day as the baseline scan. The DCE-MRI images will be analyzed by calculating Ktrans and
      DWI-MRI images will be analyzed by calculating ADC as described elsewhere. We will scan
      patients in a torso coil on a 3T clinical MR scanner. Imaging will include MR diffusion with
      b-values of 0, 125, and 500 for estimates of perfusion and tumor, and dynamic
      contrast-enhanced MR imaging (DCE-MRI) for measurement of Ktrans, blood volume, and blood
      flow. The region of tumor will be determined by MR imaging in reference to the baseline CT
      scans. The native T1 of the pancreas and liver will be calculated from a series of four, 3D,
      spoiled gradient recalled echo (SPGR) sequences with different flip angles. The conventional
      DCE-MRI will be acquired as a 3D, fast spoiled gradient echo sequence, covering the targeted
      areas of the pancreas or liver, at a temporal resolution of 5 sec over 6 minutes after the
      administration of 0.1 mmol/kg gadobenate dimeglumine. DCE-MRI images will be post-processed
      using MIStar software (Apollo Medical Imaging, Melbourne, Australia), which allows for motion
      correction to account for any shifts in data. Datasets with artifacts will be eliminated
      before further post processing. After contrast delivery, the new T1 is calculated and is
      presumed to change with the Gd concentration such that [Gd] = (1/T1-1/T10)/R1 where R1 is
      assumed to be 4.5 sec-1 mmol/L-1 at 3T.

      Run-in Period with PEGPH20

      - Days 1, 4

      PEGPH20 3 ug/kg Dexamethasone 8mg PO 1-2 hours pre-PEGPH20 and PO 8-to-12 hours post-PEGPH20

      *Start enoxaparin 1 mg/kg subcutaneous daily on day 1 (to be continued throughout the trial)

      - On day 8 of run-in period with PEGPH20, EUS-directed core biopsy, CA 19-9, functional MRI
      and CT chest, abdomen (pancreatic protocol) and pelvis will be obtained.

      Cycle 1 and onward

      -Day 1, 8, 15

      PEGPH20 3 ug/kg + Gemcitabine 1000mg/m2 + nab-Paclitaxel 125mg/m2 Dexamethasone 8mg PO 1-2
      hours pre-PEGPH20 and PO 8-to-12 hours post-PEGPH20

        -  Gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel will be administered 2-4 hours post-PEGPH20.

        -  Neoadjuvant therapy will be four 28-day cycles with CT chest, abdomen and pelvis scans
           and CA 19-9 measurements every 8 weeks. Patients will be taken off of the study if there
           is any evidence of disease progression.

        -  After four cycles of neoadjuvant therapy, patients will be evaluated for surgical
           resection depending on the CT scan findings obtained on cycle 4, day 21.

        -  If they have resectable disease, they will have a functional MRI following the restaging
           CT scan. If patients have successful resection, they will receive 2 additional cycles of
           gemcitabine and nab-paclitaxel. If they are found to have unresectable disease in the
           operating room, an intra-operative core biopsy will be obtained.

        -  If they have unresectable disease on the restaging scans following 4 cycles of therapy,
           they will be taken off of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically Relevant Pancreatic Fistula</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic Complete Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by pathological exam of resected tumors</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CA19-9 Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor marker testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>R0 Resection Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by imaging studies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by imaging studies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Run-In</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PEGPH20: 3ug/kg on Days 1 and 4</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PEGPH20: 3ug/kg on Days 1, 8, 15 Gemcitabine: 1000mg/m^2 on Days 1, 8, 15 Nab-paclitaxel: 125mg/m^2 on Days 1, 8, 15</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PEGPH20</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Run-In</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nab-paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Greater than or equal to 18 years old

          -  Histologically confirmed pancreatic adenocarcinoma

          -  Borderline resectable disease

          -  Performance status of ECOG of 0-1

          -  Therapy naïve

          -  Evaluable disease with either:

          -  RECIST-defined measurable disease

          -  An elevated serum CA19-9 &gt;100 u/ml

          -  Adequate organ function including:

          -  Bone marrow: ANC ≥1500/mm3, platelets ≥100,000/mm3 and hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL

          -  Hepatic: Serum total bilirubin ≤1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN), ALT

          -  (SGPT) and AST (SGOT) ≤ 2.5 x ULN.

          -  Renal: Serum creatinine (sCr) ≤ 1.5 x ULN, or creatinine clearance (Ccr) ≥ 40 mL/min
             as calculated by the Modified Cockcroft-Gault formula.

          -  Peripheral neuropathy &lt; grade 2

          -  Alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2X ULN unless bone metastasis is present in the absence of
             liver metastasis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age younger than 18 years old

          -  Locally advanced or metastatic disease

          -  Known allergy to hyaluronidase

          -  Contraindications to prophylactic dose LMWH, including

          -  Patients with recent gastrointestinal bleeding

          -  History of heparin induce thrombocytopenia on LMWH

          -  Subjects with previous severe hemorrhagic events on LMWH

          -  Known contraindications to heparin including:

          -  Recent central nervous system bleed, intracranial or spinal lesion at high risk for
             bleeding

          -  Active bleeding (major): more than 2 units transfused in 24 hours

          -  Spinal anesthesia/lumbar puncture within the past month

          -  Chronic, clinically significant measurable bleeding &gt; 48 hours

          -  Severe platelet dysfunction (uremia, medications, dysplastic hematopoiesis)

          -  Recent major operation at high risk for bleeding

          -  Underlying hemorrhagic coagulopathy High risk for falls (head trauma)

          -  Presence of metal biliary stents (plastic biliary stents are not an exclusion)

          -  Known status of HIV which is not well-controlled at the time of study eligibility

          -  Untreated Hepatitis B infection

          -  Active infection or antibiotics within 48 hours prior to study

          -  Currently active second primary malignancy or history of malignancy less than 5 years
             prior to the time of study eligibility (Patients with history of skin cancers
             excluding melanoma will be eligible for participation).

          -  Serious medical comorbidities such as New York Heart Association Class III/IV cardiac
             disease, uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmias, myocardial infarction over the past 12
             months.

          -  Patients with aneurysm clips, ear implants, spinal nerve stimulators, pacemaker,
             shrapnel or any other metal in their body (contraindication for MRI scans)

          -  Known, existing uncontrolled coagulopathy. Patients who have had a venous
             thromboembolic event (e.g., pulmonary embolism or deep vein thrombosis) requiring
             anticoagulation are eligible IF: they are appropriately anticoagulated and have not
             had a Grade 2 or greater bleeding episode in the 3 weeks before Day 1.

          -  Current use of warfarin (patients will be eligible if warfarin is discontinued and
             low-molecular weight heparin is used instead).

          -  Intolerance to dexamethasone

          -  Prior history of cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack, or
             pre-existing carotid artery disease.

          -  Known pregnancy, nursing women or positive pregnancy test.

          -  Any condition that would preclude informed consent, consistent follow-up and
             compliance for the study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew Ko, MD</last_name>
    <phone>415-353-7286</phone>
    <email>Andrew.Ko@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Julie Sudduth-Klinger</last_name>
    <phone>415-353-7463</phone>
    <email>Julie.Sudduth-Klinger@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94158</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Dito, RN</last_name>
      <phone>415-353-7244</phone>
      <email>Elizabeth.Dito@ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anna Ong, RN</last_name>
      <phone>415-885-7603</phone>
      <email>Anna.Ong@ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrew Ko</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Clinical Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pancreatic</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

