<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00887367</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>106591</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00887367</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EtOH Interaction Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Investigate Potential Interactions Between GSK598809 and Ethanol in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate the possible effects of alcohol in combination with GSK598809 on
      the central nervous system in 20 healthy male and female volunteers, between 18 and 65 years
      of age.

      During 4 separate study periods subjects will receive the following treatment combinations:
      Alcohol + GSK598809, alcohol + placebo drug, placebo infusion + GSK598809, and placebo
      infusion + placebo drug. A placebo is a pill or liquid infusion which contains no drug or
      alcohol; it is a dummy version. Therefore it is administered in the same way that either the
      study drug or ethanol is depending on which placebo it is. All study drugs are administered
      in a random order and both the doctor and the participant are not aware of the treatment
      combination. However treatment combinations will be available at the end of the study or in
      case of an emergency. GSK598809 is administered orally and alcohol is administered per
      infusion. The duration of the infusion is 5 hours, during which approximately 75 grams of
      alcohol is infused, which is comparable to less than one bottle of wine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a blinded, randomised, placebo-controlled, double-dummy, four-period crossover study
      to investigate the psychomotor and cognitive effects of GSK598809 alone and in combination
      with ethanol in healthy subjects.

      A sufficient number of subjects, approximately 20 healthy (18 to 65 years) male and female
      subjects will be enrolled. Occasional smokers who are non-daily smokers may be enrolled in
      the study, but will not be permitted to smoke whilst in the unit.

      Subjects will be screened by medical history, physical examination and routine laboratory
      tests within three weeks before the start of the study. Within three weeks or on Day -1 they
      will have a training session to get familiar with the pharmacodynamic tests.

      There will be four crossover sessions. All study occasions/sessions will be performed in the
      same way. The duration of each treatment session is 5 study days. Subjects will report to the
      clinic during the evening of Day -1 in a fasted condition and will remain in the clinic for
      two overnight stays. A short study introduction will be given followed by admission
      procedures. Dinner will be served after the collection of blood samples for laboratory safety
      tests.

      On morning of study day 1, approximately 08:00hrs two intravenous cannulae (one cannula for
      blood sampling and another cannula for infusion of the ethanol/placebo) will be inserted.
      Before the start of the infusion a light breakfast will be given. The alcohol infusion will
      start in the morning, between approximately 09:30hr and 10:00hr and will take place for five
      hours, followed by a three-hour infusion-free washout period. GSK598809 or matching placebo
      will be administered orally 30 minutes after the start of the alcohol infusion. A
      standardised lunch will be given at approximately 3.5 hours post dose and dinner
      approximately 9 hours post dose.

      Subjects will be discharged after the completion of study assessments and AE review on Day 2
      and if deemed appropriate by the investigator or designee. Study Days: 3 and 4 will be
      outpatient visits for collection of pharmacokinetic samples and AE review.

      During each session, a range of central nervous system (CNS) functions will be tested
      frequently, using a validated CNS-battery, CHDR Neurocart. In addition, pharmacokinetic
      measurements will be taken for plasma levels of GSK598809 and GSK685249 (GSK598809
      metabolite). Pharmacokinetic measures will also be taken for breath alcohol and blood alcohol
      levels.

      There will be a washout period of at least five days between treatment sessions. The follow
      up visit will take place approximately 7 days post final treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 29, 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 3, 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 3, 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability: Vital sign measurement, 12 lead ECG and telemetry, safety laboratory sampling including prolactin and lipid measurements, Barnes Akathesia Scale (BAS), Simpson-Angus Scale (SAS) and Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale (AIMS).</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening: BAS, SAS and AIMS (as training only), 12 lead ECG, vital signs and clinical labs. All will be measured throughout dosing day (Day 1), day 2, 3: vital signs, day 4: vital signs, clinical labs, follow up: clinical labs, vital signs, 12 lead ECG</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics: breath ethanol concentrations, blood ethanol concentrations, main pharmacokinetic parameters of GSK598809 and its metabolite (GSK685249) AUC∞, Cmax, Tmax and t½.</measure>
    <time_frame>All will be measured throughout day 1, PK blood sampling for GSK598809 and GSK685249 will also be collected on Day 2, 3 and 4.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic: saccadic eye movements, smooth pursuit eye movements, body sway, adaptive tracking, Visual Verbal Learning Test (VVLT).</measure>
    <time_frame>Saccadic eye movement, smooth pursuit eye movements, body sway and adaptive tracking measured at set intervals between 1.5hrs pre dose to 7.5hrs post dose. VVLT administered between 0.5hrs post dose to 3.5hrs post dose.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic/biomarker endpoints: saccadic eye movements, visual analogue scales (VAS B&amp;L) according to Bond &amp; Lader, Visual Analogue Scales for 'alcohol effects' (VAS 'Alcohol Effects').</measure>
    <time_frame>Saccadic eye movements at time points as given above. VAS B&amp;L and VAS 'Alcohol Effects' at following time points: -1.5, 0.5, 1.5, 2.5, 3.5, 4.5, 5.5, 6.5, 7.5 hrs post dose.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Substance Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo to match GSK598809</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo to match GSK598809.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo to match ethanol infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Glucose solution to be given in the same way as ethanol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK598809</intervention_name>
    <description>Two 175 mg doses of GSK598809 will be given.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo to match GSK598809</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ethanol</intervention_name>
    <description>A constant ethanol level of 0.6 g·L-1 for five hours will be given to the subjects intravenously. This level shows significant CNS effects, without causing too many inadvertent events. Furthermore this level is considered safe as it is just above the legal driving limit in the Netherlands (i.e. 0.5 g·L-1) and these levels are routinely achieved during social drinking. Moreover, this level leaves enough room for CNS-impairment without compromising safety, in case of a (supra-) addictive drug-alcohol interaction.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo to match ethanol infusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Generally healthy.

          -  Occasional non-daily smokers.

          -  Willing to use appropriate contraception method.

          -  Weight more than 50 kg.

          -  BMI within the range 18 - 30 kg/m2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding female.

          -  Daily smoker.

          -  Asthma or a history of asthma.

          -  Abuse of drugs or alcohol.

          -  Psychiatric illness.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <zip>2333 CL</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.gsk-clinicalstudyregister.com/study/106591?search=study&amp;search_terms=106591#rs</url>
    <description>Results for study 106591 can be found on the GSK Clinical Study Register.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>te Beek ET, Zoethout RW, Bani MS, Andorn A, Iavarone L, Klaassen ES, Fina P, van Gerven JM. Pharmacokinetics and central nervous system effects of the novel dopamine D3 receptor antagonist GSK598809 and intravenous alcohol infusion at pseudo-steady state. J Psychopharmacol. 2012 Feb;26(2):303-14. doi: 10.1177/0269881111431750. Epub 2012 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22219221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 24, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Substance dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol dependence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

