<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00881764</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAC8756</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R34HD060741</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSF223200810036C</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SmartTots</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00881764</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PANDA (Pediatric Anesthesia &amp; NeuroDevelopment Assessment) Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Anesthesia Exposure and Neurodevelopment in Infants and Children: Pediatric Anesthesia &amp; NeuroDevelopment (PANDA) Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Office of Acquisitions and Grants Services (OAGS)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the use of anesthetic agents in infants and
      children have long term adverse effects on neurocognitive development. According to the
      National Hospital Discharge Survey, around 2.5 million children have surgical procedures
      requiring anesthesia each year in the US. Recent animal studies have suggested that the
      exposure of the immature organism to a variety of commonly used anesthetic agents may lead to
      neurobehavioral functional deficits in vivo and to neuronal apoptosis in vitro. While the
      relevance of these findings on children exposed to anesthetics remains to be determined, it
      is clearly critically important to public health that this issue is resolved quickly and
      clearly.

      Hypothesis: Exposure to anesthetic agents within the first three years of life will not
      significantly impair cognitive functions at ages 8 yr, 0 mo to 15 yr, 0 mo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of our study is to compare neurocognitive functions in sibling pairs: one of whom
      had exposure to anesthesia during surgery before 36 months of age (exposed sibling cohorts)
      and who would be from ages 8yr, 0 mo to15 yr, 0 mo at the time of the study; and the other
      who never had anesthesia or surgery less than 36 months of age, is from ages 8yr, 0mo to 15
      yr, 0 mo at the time of the study, and is within 36 months of age range from the exposed
      sibling(unexposed sibling cohort).

      Neuropsychological assessments are administered to the sibling cohorts prospectively and
      parents of the siblings will complete parental interviews/questionnaires. We assess
      individually neurocognitive, behavioral and emotional function for both exposed and unexposed
      siblings. Family function will also be evaluated. We will also obtain complete medical
      history for each participant, including significant perinatal events and social history. We
      also review medical records when appropriate.

      All testing are performed during a one day site visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in neurocognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Global cognitive function: verbal, performance and full IQ assessed by Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence (WASI). These are one unit of measure for IQ.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to visual memory and learning</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>NEPSY II (A Developmental Neuropsychological Assessment) assesses visual memory learning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to verbal memory and learning</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>California Verbal Learning Test-Children (CVLT-C) assesses verbal memory and learning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to receptive language</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>NEPSY II (A Developmental Neuropsychological Assessment) is used to assess receptive language and speeded naming.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to expressive language</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>WASI is used to assess expressive language and verbal reasoning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to working memory</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Weschler Intelligence Scale for Children (WISC-IV) is used to assess working memory, attention and executive function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to all executive function components</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Behavior Rating In Executive Function (BRIEF) is used to assess all components of executive function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to selective attention and impulsivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Continuous Performance Test-II (CPT-II) is used to assess sustained and selective attention as well as impulsivity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to cognitive flexibility aspects of executive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (DKEFS) is used to assess cognitive flexibility.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in domain-specific function related to motor and processing speed</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Grooved pegboard and Weschler Intelligence Scale for Children (WISC-IV) are used to assess motor and processing speed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Childhood Behavior Check List (CBCL) assesses emotionally reactive, anxious/depressed, somatic complaints, withdrawn, attention problems and aggressive behavior.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in adaptive behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Adaptive behavior is assessed using Adaptive Behavior Assessment Systems II (ABAS-II), which measures overall adaptive behavior and skills.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in parental relationships</measure>
    <time_frame>Varies; when the participant is 8-15 years of age</time_frame>
    <description>Parent Relationship Questionnaire (PRQ) is used to explore parents' perspectives on parent-child relationship.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">369</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognition - Other</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exposed Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children who had inguinal hernia surgery and general anesthesia before 36 months of age (n=500). These children should be ages 8 yr, 0 mo to 15 yr, 0 mo at the time of the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unexposed Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children who are siblings of the exposed children (inguinal hernia surgery and general anesthesia) and differ in age from the exposed children by less than 36 months and have no history of surgery or exposure to volatile and intravenous anesthetics or sedatives including barbiturates, benzodiazepines and chloral hydrate less than 36 months of age. These children should also be ages 8 yr, 0 mo to 15 yr, 0 mo at the time of the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inguinal hernia surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-experimental procedure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exposed Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>General anesthesia</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-experimental procedure/treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exposed Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will be a multi-center study based at Columbia University with the following
        participating centers: Boston Children's (Harvard University), Children's Hospital of
        Philadelphia (University of Pennsylvania), Monroe Carell Children's Hospital (Vanderbilt
        University), and Morgan Stanley Children's Hospital of New York (Columbia University).
        Children exposed to anesthesia prior to 36 months must be ages 8 yr, 0 mo to 15 yr, 0 mo
        and have a sibling with no history of surgery or anesthesia prior to 36 months of age.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Exposed cohort:

          1. Subjects who had inguinal hernia surgery before 36 months of age

          2. Ages 8 yr, 0 mo to 15 yr, 0 mo

          3. Gestation age greater or equal to 36 weeks

          4. Categorized as ASA I or ASA II

          5. English speaking

          6. Biologically related to the unexposed sibling

        Unexposed cohort:

          1. Sibling within 36 months of age of the exposed cohort

          2. Never had surgery or exposure to anesthesia prior to 36 months of age

          3. Ages 8 yr, 0 mo to 15 yr, 0 mo

          4. Gestation age greater or equal to 36 weeks

          5. Categorized as ASA I or ASA II

        5. English speaking 6. Biologically related to the exposed sibling

        Exclusion criteria:

        Exposed cohort:

          1. Gestational age less than 36 weeks at birth

          2. No exposure to surgery or anesthesia prior to 36 months of age

          3. Surgery/Anesthesia other than index hernia repair prior to 36 months of age

          4. Not categorized as ASA I or ASA II

          5. Not ages 8 yr, 0 mo to 15 yr, 0 mo

          6. Not English speaking

          7. Not biologically related to the unexposed sibling

        Unexposed cohort:

          1. Gestational age under 36 weeks at birth

          2. Any exposure to surgery or anesthesia prior to 36 months of age

          3. Not categorized as ASA I or ASA II

          4. Not ages 8 yr, 0 mo to 15 yr, 0 mo

          5. Not English speaking

          6. Not biologically related to the unexposed sibling
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lena S Sun, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University, 622 W. 168th St.</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ikonomidou C, Bosch F, Miksa M, Bittigau P, Vöckler J, Dikranian K, Tenkova TI, Stefovska V, Turski L, Olney JW. Blockade of NMDA receptors and apoptotic neurodegeneration in the developing brain. Science. 1999 Jan 1;283(5398):70-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9872743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anand KJ, Soriano SG. Anesthetic agents and the immature brain: are these toxic or therapeutic? Anesthesiology. 2004 Aug;101(2):527-30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15277935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anand KJ. Anesthetic neurotoxicity in newborns: should we change clinical practice? Anesthesiology. 2007 Jul;107(1):2-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17585205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olney JW, Young C, Wozniak DF, Jevtovic-Todorovic V, Ikonomidou C. Do pediatric drugs cause developing neurons to commit suicide? Trends Pharmacol Sci. 2004 Mar;25(3):135-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15019268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walden M, Carrier CT. Sleeping beauties: the impact of sedation on neonatal development. J Obstet Gynecol Neonatal Nurs. 2003 May-Jun;32(3):393-401. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12774882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mellon RD, Simone AF, Rappaport BA. Use of anesthetic agents in neonates and young children. Anesth Analg. 2007 Mar;104(3):509-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17312200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jevtovic-Todorovic V, Hartman RE, Izumi Y, Benshoff ND, Dikranian K, Zorumski CF, Olney JW, Wozniak DF. Early exposure to common anesthetic agents causes widespread neurodegeneration in the developing rat brain and persistent learning deficits. J Neurosci. 2003 Feb 1;23(3):876-82.</citation>
    <PMID>12574416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slikker et al. FDA science 2005 Forum</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slikker W Jr, Zou X, Hotchkiss CE, Divine RL, Sadovova N, Twaddle NC, Doerge DR, Scallet AC, Patterson TA, Hanig JP, Paule MG, Wang C. Ketamine-induced neuronal cell death in the perinatal rhesus monkey. Toxicol Sci. 2007 Jul;98(1):145-58. Epub 2007 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17426105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olney JW, Wozniak DF, Jevtovic-Todorovic V, Farber NB, Bittigau P, Ikonomidou C. Drug-induced apoptotic neurodegeneration in the developing brain. Brain Pathol. 2002 Oct;12(4):488-98. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12408236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jevtovic-Todorovic V. General anesthetics and the developing brain: friends or foes? J Neurosurg Anesthesiol. 2005 Oct;17(4):204-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16184065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 14, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 14, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lena S. Sun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Emanuel M. Papper Professor of Anesthesiology and Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>New York</keyword>
  <keyword>Columbia</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurodevelopment</keyword>
  <keyword>Child development</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

