<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01538251</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ST261DM11005</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-004765-32</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01538251</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy, Safety and Tolerability of Propionyl-L-Carnitine Hydrochloride in Patients With Mild Ulcerative Colitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Multicenter International Study to Investigate the Safety and Efficacy of Propionyl-L-Carnitine Hydrochloride Modified Release Tablets in Patients Affected by Mild Ulcerative Colitis Under Oral Stable Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>sigma-tau i.f.r. S.p.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>sigma-tau i.f.r. S.p.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the trial is to test safety, tolerability and efficacy of Propionyl-L-carnitine
      modified release tablets 1g/die in reducing the symptoms of the disease with respect to the
      proportion of patients with disease remission at the end of the 8 weeks of treatment. It will
      also aim to investigate capability of the treatment in the maintenance of remission after
      four weeks of treatment interruption; histological changes will be also evaluated and
      finally, improvement in the overall quality of life as measured by the Short Inflammatory
      Bowel Disease Questionnaire (SIBDQ)will be investigated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although it seems clear that an abnormal function of the colonic epithelium is the central
      problem causing inflammation and the unusual immunological response to the normal gut flora
      in inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), the actual causes of these dysfunctions are still
      unknown.

      Short Chain Fatty Acids (SCFA) are the main fuel of the colonic epithelium, and are normally
      produced by the bacterial flora by fermentation of the complex carbohydrates forming non
      soluble fibers usually introduced with everyday diet. Butyrate alone contributes 70% of the
      normal colonocyte energy.

      Studies done using animal models and colonic mucosa biopsies from patients suffering form
      ulcerative colitis (UC) have consistently shown that a metabolic change occurs in diseased
      colonic mucosa, with an impairment of butyrate oxidation (and of beta-oxidation) and an
      energy shortage that is only incompletely compensated by oxidation of glucose and other
      substrates such as glutamine.

      It is also well known that matrix metalloproteases production is highly increased in IBD and
      that serum transglutaminase activity is significantly reduced in patients with IBD.

      Transglutaminases are enzymes contributing to the crosslinking of matrix proteins and the
      reduction seen in patients affected by IBD correlates well with the endoscopic and
      histopathologic grading in UC, meaning that part of the circulating enzyme is sequestered in
      the injured colonic tissue in the effort to re-build the extracellular matrix during the
      healing process.

      Propionyl-L-carnitine Hydrochloride (PLC) is a molecule that has already been shown to reduce
      membrane lipid peroxidation in endothelial cells from bovine aorta and coronary vessels, to
      reduce the effects of hypoxia in coronary endothelial cells, and to play a role in the
      cardiac metabolic abnormalities that contribute to the mechanical dysfunctions leading to
      heart failure.

      Given these properties of Propionyl-L-carnitine Hydrochloride (ST 261) and given the
      peroxidative damage suffered by colonocytes in UC together with their metabolic impairment,
      the use of this molecule for the treatment of UC seemed to be appropriate and sound, in
      particular as a carrier of a propionate moiety that, once transformed into succinate, enters
      the Kreb cycle, acting as an extra burst fuel improving the balance of energy production
      inside tissues.

      Previous clinical experience has shown that PLC promoted complete or nearly complete
      regression of cutaneous trophic ulcers in a large number of vasculopathic patients refractory
      to all other therapies.

      As far as the UC pathology is concerned, the effects of ST 261, given orally or
      intrarectally, were investigated at different dosages, in preclinical experimentation, either
      after a single trinitrobenzene sulphonic acid (TNBS) administration (acute colitis) or after
      repeated TNBS administrations (reactivated colitis). The results showed a reduction in the
      damaged colon area both in acute model and reactivated colitis, even if the beneficial effect
      of restoration of TNBS-induced alterations of tissue morphology is more evident in the
      reactivated colitis model, particularly after oral administration.

      Based on the above-described results a development plan in humans started to investigate the
      activity of PLC in the treatment of ulcerative colitis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Evidence of very low probability to success. No safety issues.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of clinical/endoscopic remissions</measure>
    <time_frame>End of treatment (week 8)</time_frame>
    <description>Remission will be defined according with the overall modified Mayo score (Disease Activity Index). A score ≤ 2 with rectal bleeding sub-score = 0 and no other individual sub-score &gt;1 will be considered necessary to classify the patient in remission state.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Rectal bleeding evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 2, 6 and 8 of treatment and after 4 week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation will be performed by means of Disease Activity Index (DAI) sub-score (from 0 to 3).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in stool frequency evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 2, 6 and 8 of treatment and after 4 week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluations will be performed by means of Disease Activity Index (DAI) sub-score (from 0 to 3).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Histological response to the treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>End of treatment (week 8)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated as an improvement of the histological index of at least 1 point</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in C-reactive protein (CRP) and Fibrinogen</measure>
    <time_frame>End of the treatment (week 8) and after 4 week follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of patients quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>End of treatment period (week8) and after 4 week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A validated specific questionnaire, the SIBDQ by McMaster university will be administered to evaluate changes in patients' quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Haematology</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and end of treatment (week8)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrocardiogram</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at the end of treatment period (week8)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events collection</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Chemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at the end of treatment period (week8)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">147</enrollment>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Propionyl-L-carnitine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>modified release tablets 500 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Modified release tablet 500 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propionyl-L-Carnitine</intervention_name>
    <description>Modified release tablets containing 500 mg of propionyl-L-carnitine. one tablet twice a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Propionyl-L-carnitine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Tablets containing 500 mg of propionyl-L-carnitine. one tablet twice a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have read the Information for the Patient and signed the Informed Consent Form.

          -  Diagnosis of active ulcerative colitis since at least 4 weeks as confirmed
             endoscopically and histologically.

          -  Disease Activity Index comprised between 3 and 6, inclusive (mild ulcerative colitis),
             with rectal bleeding sub-score of at least 1.

          -  Stable background oral aminosalicylates (mesalazine, balsalazide, olsalazine) or
             sulfasalazine standard therapy for greater than or equal to 4 weeks prior to screening
             assessments.

          -  If female, not pregnant or nursing. For women of childbearing potential, willingness
             to avoid a pregnancy during the treatment period and for at least 4 weeks from the
             last dose of drug and utilization of an efficient method of birth control for the
             entire duration of the trial and until the first menses after a 30-day period after
             the last dose of trial medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Crohn's disease and indeterminate colitis.

          -  Current or previous (in the last 10 days preceding the screening) use of systemic
             corticosteroids.

          -  Use of systemic antibiotics in the last 10 days preceding the screening.

          -  Use of systemic Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs on a repeat basis in the last 10
             days preceding the screening.

          -  Use of probiotics started within 10 days preceding the screening. A stable regimen
             from at least 10 days prior to screening is allowed but the patient must be willing to
             continue up to the end of the study.

          -  Use of immunosuppressants or biological agents within the last 6 weeks preceding the
             screening.

          -  Treatment with L-carnitine or its esters derivatives within the last 3 months.

          -  Stool culture positive for enteric pathogens (eg, Shigella, Salmonella, Yersinia,
             Campylobacter) or toxins (C.difficile).

          -  Significantly impaired liver, renal, pulmonary or cardiovascular function as assessed
             by the investigator.

          -  History of colon resection.

          -  Diverticulitis, symptomatic diverticulosis.

          -  Active peptic ulcer disease.

          -  Proctitis (extent of inflammation &lt;15 cm from the anus).

          -  Bleeding disorders

          -  Rectal therapy with any therapeutic enemas or suppositories with the exception of
             those required for endoscopy during the 10 days preceding the screening.

          -  Active or chronic infection(s) or malignancies.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to the active ingredient and excipients of the study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandro Ardizzone, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Head of Inflammatory Bowel Diseases Unit Hospital &quot;Luigi Sacco&quot; Milan - ITALY</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Imelda Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bonheiden</city>
        <state>Antwerpen</state>
        <zip>2820</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitaire Ziekenhuis Gasthuisberg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <state>Flemish Brabant</state>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitair Ziekenhuis Gent</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ghent</city>
        <state>Oost-vlaanderen</state>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Hartziekenhuis Roeselare-Menen vzw</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roeselare</city>
        <state>West-vlaanderen</state>
        <zip>8800</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Derma Plus s.r.o.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ceské Budejovice</city>
        <zip>370 01</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hepato-Gastroenterology HK s.r.o.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hradec Kralove</city>
        <zip>500 12</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fakultní nemocnice Olomouc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Olomouc</city>
        <zip>775 20</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>G.E.P. Clinic s.r.o.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha 10</city>
        <zip>100 00</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MONSE s.r.o</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha 1</city>
        <zip>118 33</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fakultní Thomayerova nemocnice s poliklinikou</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha 4 - Krc</city>
        <zip>140 59</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fakultní Nemocnice v Motole</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha 5</city>
        <zip>15006</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nemocnice Tábor, a.s.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tábor</city>
        <zip>390 03</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orlickoústecká Nemocnice a.s</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ústí nad Orlicí</city>
        <zip>562 18</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Soroka University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beer Sheva</city>
        <zip>84100</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shaare Zedek Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91031</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah Medical Organization, Ein Kerem</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Meir Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kfar-Saba</city>
        <zip>44281</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rabin Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Petah Tikva</city>
        <zip>49100</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaplan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rehovot</city>
        <zip>76100</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tel Aviv Souraski Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <zip>64239</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assaf Harofeh Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zerifin</city>
        <zip>70300</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale &quot;G.B.Morgagni - L. Pierantoni&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Forlì</city>
        <state>Forli-cesena</state>
        <zip>47100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rozzano</city>
        <state>Milano</state>
        <zip>20089</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Luigi Sacco - Az. Osp. Dept. of Gastroenterology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <zip>20157</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinico Universitario Federico II</name>
      <address>
        <city>Napoli</city>
        <zip>80131</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRCSS Policlinico San Matteo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pavia</city>
        <zip>27100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera S. Camillo Forlanini, Roma</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00152</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinico Universitario Agostino Gemelli</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00168</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Onze Lieve Vrouwe Gasthuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>Noord-holland</state>
        <zip>1091 AC</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leids Universitair Medisch Centrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <state>Zuid-holland</state>
        <zip>2333 ZA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMC Utrecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <zip>3584 CX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CMI de Gastroenterologie Dobru Daniela</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tirgu Mures</city>
        <state>Mures</state>
        <zip>540461</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neomed Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brasov</city>
        <zip>500283</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centrul Medical Sana</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucuresti</city>
        <zip>011025</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endocenter Medicina Integrativa SRL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucuresti</city>
        <zip>021978</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gastromedica SRL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iasi</city>
        <zip>700506</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Spitalul Clinic Judetean De Urgenta Sibiu</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sibiu</city>
        <zip>550245</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinic Algomed SRL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Timisoara</city>
        <zip>300002</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Scientific Centre of Coloproctology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>123423</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Educational Institution of Higher Professional Education Novosibirsk State Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Novosibirsk</city>
        <zip>630091</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Research Institute of Physiology of Siberian Branch of Russian Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Novosibirsk</city>
        <zip>630117</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GOU VPO Rostov State Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostov-on-Don</city>
        <zip>344022</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Petersburg GUZ City Policlinic 38</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>193015</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regional Military Clinical Hospital ¿ 442 named after Z.P. Solovyov of Ministry of Defence of Russia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>193124</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint-Petersburg State Institution of Health Protection City Hospital # 26</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>196247</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Krestovsky Medical Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Petersburg</city>
        <zip>197110</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saratov City Hospital #2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov</city>
        <zip>410053</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint-Petersburg Medical Academy</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Petersburg</city>
        <zip>195067</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Educational Institution of Higher Professional Education &quot;Stavropol State Medical Academy&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stavropol</city>
        <zip>355017</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Hospital #2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yaroslavl</city>
        <zip>150010</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NovaMed spol. s.r.o.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Banská Bystrica</city>
        <zip>974 01</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNB Nemocnica Staré Mesto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bratislava</city>
        <zip>813 69</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ABAWI spol.s.r.o.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bratislava</city>
        <zip>82101</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lama Medical Care s.r.o., Gastroentero-hepatologicke centrum Thalion</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bratislava</city>
        <zip>831 04</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neštátna Gastroenterologická Ambulancia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bratislava</city>
        <zip>851 01</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>KM Management sro</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nitra</city>
        <zip>950 01</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gastro I.s.r.o.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prešov</city>
        <zip>08001</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GEA s.r.o Gastroenterologicka ambulancia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trnava</city>
        <zip>91701</zip>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Slovakia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 24, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ulcerative colitis</keyword>
  <keyword>propionyl-l-carnitine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

