<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01532024</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NAP</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-006169-17</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01532024</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exploratory Clinical Study of Neutrophil Activation Probe (NAP) for Optical Molecular Imaging in Human Lungs</brief_title>
  <acronym>NAP</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Exploratory Clinical Study of Microdosing NAP for Optical Molecular Imaging in Human Lungs in Healthy Volunteers and in Patients With Acute Lung Injury in Intensive Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Edinburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Edinburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Seriously ill patients may develop a complication called acute lung injury (ALI), a form of
      inflammation in which lung tissue is filled by fluid containing white blood cells called
      neutrophils. ALI is common and is often fatal (for example in the USA it is estimated that
      190,000 patients develop ALI per annum, of whom 75,000 die). No pharmacological treatment has
      been shown to improve ALI.

      Data from animal models and patients strongly suggest that neutrophils are central to disease
      progression. However no bedside methods exist to rapidly and accurately determine in
      seriously ill patients, if neutrophils are present and if they are releasing damaging enzymes
      such as elastase. As such, the investigating team have developed and synthesised to clinical
      grade, an imaging agent called NAP (Neutrophil Activation Probe) that detects activated
      neutrophils and also the damaging enzyme, human neutrophil elastase (HNE). The investigators
      have extensively tested NAP in animal models for efficacy and safety. It reliably detects
      activated neutrophils and is not toxic.

      NAP is a small molecule that is delivered in tiny doses (called microdoses) to areas of
      inflammation in human lungs through a bronchoscope. The activity of NAP is visualised by
      imaging though a tiny camera that is also introduced through the bronchoscope. This camera
      system is now widely used throughout the world in over 150 sites.

      The investigators therefore aim to test the utility and safety of NAP in an exploratory
      clinical study. The study involves the delivery of NAP to 6 healthy volunteers followed by
      delivering NAP to 3 patients in ICU with pulmonary infiltrates and 6 patients known to have
      bronchiectasis.

      In the healthy volunteers study, healthy male volunteers recruited from the University of
      Edinburgh will be invited to participate.

      In the ICU study, patients will be recruited from the ICU in the Royal Infirmary of
      Edinburgh.

      In the bronchiectasis study, patients will be recruited from the respiratory service in NHS
      Lothian.

      If the study (which is supported by the Medical Research Council) demonstrates safety and
      also the ability to image activated neutrophils, the investigators intention is to design
      future studies in patients with ALI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute lung injury (ALI)/adult respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is clinically important
      (16% of mechanically ventilated patients acquire ALI, of whom one third die), yet no
      pharmacological therapy has been shown to impact significantly on outcome. This is in part
      due to inadequate stratification of patients with neutrophil predominant ALI/ARDS and the
      inability to determine disease activity and hence target therapy.

      Molecular Imaging (MI) offers a potential strategy to visualize neutrophil activity in vivo
      in situ. Indeed FDG PET has been used to image neutrophil activity but it is not a bedside
      modality, and moving critically ill patients to remote scanners is dangerous and expensive
      and there there are currently no bedside 'smart' MI solutions that can guide, at the
      cellular/functional level, the diagnostic or therapeutic pathway in patients with
      inflammatory lung disease. Indeed, in ICU, there is a specific need to rapidly diagnose
      patients with deteriorating gas exchange, particularly those with chest X-ray (CXR)
      shadowing. Such CXR infiltrates result from numerous causes including cardiac failure, fluid
      overload, secondary pneumonia and ALI/ARDS. All require different treatments but, at present,
      options to distinguish these conditions are severely limited, resulting in empirical
      'blunderbuss' antimicrobial therapy and non-correction of the primary condition. There is now
      a pressing need to rapidly stratify such patients to inform focused implementation of
      specific targeted therapies.

      Activated neutrophils and their histotoxic products, particularly human neutrophil elastase
      (HNE), have been specifically implicated in the pathogenesis of ALI/ARDS, and there is
      considerable clinical interest in new drugs in this area. However, there is currently no way
      of rapidly determining whether new therapeutic candidates are exerting their predicted
      effects in situ in the human lung prior to embarking upon major clinical trials. Such a
      solution would inevitably accelerate the pathway of new drugs to clinical application.

      The Proposed Solution: probe-based confocal laser endomicroscopy (pCLE) combined with direct
      intra-pulmonary instillation of microdoses (pharmacologically-inactive and non-toxic) of a
      highly specific and sensitive 'smartprobe' (NAP) will detect neutrophil activity and the
      presence of active HNE in the lungs of ventilated ICU patients.

      pCLE itself safely provides high-resolution, real-time images of the human lung at cellular
      resolution in situ. Alone, however, it provides no functional or molecular information. The
      investigators have therefore embarked on a discovery programme to synthesise highly sensitive
      smartprobes, detectable by pCLE and specifically directed against key inflammatory events.
      This provides a new dimension of clinical application for this cutting-edge technology. NAP,
      the prototype has now been validated in vitro and in vivo where it is effective at a dose of
      &lt; 10µg and generates a powerful fluorescent signal in &lt; 30 sec. Our pilot study aims are to
      apply the combined utility of pCLE and NAP in healthy volunteers and patients with
      inflammatory lung disease. The study will also provide a prototypic foundation that can be
      applied to future smartprobes, not only in the lung but in any organ accessible to endoscopy.

      The primary end-point will be a proof of concept demonstration that this technique can be
      used to visualise activated neutrophils over background autofluorescence. Other end points
      include safety. The investigators shall also assess alveolar (by bronchoscopy) neutrophil
      activation and elastase activity in patients. Demonstration of activated neutrophils by pCLE
      in ICU would be expected to lead directly to clinical trials in patients with ALI/ARDS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Image Neutrophil activity</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Fluorescent amplification of NAP upon exposure to activated neutrophils in lungs of patients with Acute Lung Injury</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of delivery of NAP</time_frame>
    <description>Absence of any adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Lung Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Delivery of intrapulmonary NAP Dose escalation from 5 mcgs to 80mcgs</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pulmonary Infiltrate in ICU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Delivery of NAP (80mcgs) to ventilated patients with pulmonary infiltrates</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with Bronchiectasis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Delivery of NAP (80mcgs) to patients with bronchiectasis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microdose of NAP</intervention_name>
    <description>Delivery of NAP at microdose (&lt;100mcg) by direct pulmonary administration followed by fibreoptic confocal microendoscopy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pulmonary Infiltrate in ICU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with Bronchiectasis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PART A: healthy male volunteers aged between 18 and 40.

          -  PART B: Ventilated patients over the age of 18 in on ITU with pulmonary infiltrate

          -  PART C: Male patients diagnosed with bronchiectasis over the age of 18

        Exclusion criteria for part A:

          1. Age &lt; 18 or &gt;40 years

          2. History of any chronic or ongoing acute illness (with particular reference to asthma,
             upper respiratory tract infection, lower respiratory tract infection, bronchiectasis,
             congenital heart disease, ischaemic heart disease, valvular heart disease, diabetes
             mellitus, chronic renal impairment, urinary tract infection)

          3. Any current medication

          4. Any history of previous reactions to flourescein or any other anaphylaxis

          5. Abnormal physical signs detected at cardiorespiratory examination

          6. Temperature &gt;37.3 degrees Celsius

          7. Oxygen saturation &lt;95% breathing room air

          8. Haemoglobin, white cell count or platelet count outside the normal laboratory
             reference range

          9. Blood sodium, potassium, urea, creatinine, bilirubin, alanine aminotransferase, random
             glucose or C-reactive protein outside the normal laboratory reference range

         10. Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) or forced vital capacity (FVC) &lt;80%
             predicted

         11. FEV1:VC ratio &lt;70%

         12. Any significant cardiorespiratory abnormality detected on chest x-ray

         13. Peripheral venous access insufficient to support 14 gauge cannulae.

         14. General practitioner confirmation of eligibility as a healthy volunteer not received

         15. Failure to provide suitable identification (passport/driving licence)

         16. Refusal to consent to enter details in 'The Over Volunteering Prevention System'
             (TOPS) database

         17. Positive urine drug screen

         18. Participation in any other interventional study or less than three months since their
             last participation in an interventional study

         19. Female

        Exclusion Criteria for part B

          1. Age &lt;18years

          2. Any contraindication for bronchoscopy 22,23

          3. Refusal for participation by attending consultant

          4. Fi02 &gt;70%

          5. PEEP&gt;10cm

          6. Recent pneumothorax (whilst on ventilator)

          7. Any history of previous reactions to flourescein or any other anaphylaxis

          8. Participation in any other interventional study or less than three months since their
             last participation in an interventional study

          9. Female

        Exclusion criteria for Part C

          1. Age &lt;18years

          2. Any contraindication with bronchoscopy

          3. Refusal for aprticipation by attending consultant

          4. Recent pneumothorax (last 4 weeks)

          5. Myocardial infarction within preceding 4 weeks

          6. Any history of previous reactions to fluorescein or any other anaphylaxis

          7. Participation in any other interventional study or less than three months since their
             last participation in an interventional study.

          8. Female
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kev Dhaliwal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Newby, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chris Haslett, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tim Walsh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kevin Dhaliwal, MD</last_name>
    <email>kdhaliwa@staffmail.ed.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ward 118, Intensive Care, Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <state>Scotland</state>
        <zip>EH16 4TJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Walsh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wellcome Trust Clinical Research Facility</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <zip>EH16 4SA</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Infirmary of Edinbrugh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kev Dhaliwal, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 13, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Optical Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Neutrophil</keyword>
  <keyword>Elastase</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Lung Injury</keyword>
  <keyword>ARDS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

