<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01538446</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P110101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01538446</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tailored Antiplatelet Therapy Versus Recommended Dose of Prasugrel</brief_title>
  <acronym>ANTARCTIC</acronym>
  <official_title>The ANTARCTIC Study - Assessment of a Normal Versus Tailored Dose of Prasugrel After Stenting in Patients Aged &gt; 75 Years to Reduce the Composite of Bleeding, Stent Thrombosis and Ischemic Complications</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Allies in Cardiovascular Trials Initiatives and Organized</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Accumetrics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stentys</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to demonstrate the superiority of a strategy of platelet
      monitoring (Monitoring Arm) with down-adjustment of the dose of prasugrel in high responders
      and up-adjustment of the dose of prasugrel in low responders as compared to a more
      conventional strategy of a fixed dose of 5 mg to every patient without monitoring
      (Conventional Arm) as measured by a reduction in the composite endpoint of, cardiovascular
      (CV) death, myocardial infarction (MI) , stroke, stent thrombosis (ARC definition type
      &quot;definite&quot;), urgent revascularisation or bleeding (BARC definition type 2, 3 or 5).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: To demonstrate the superiority of a strategy of platelet monitoring (Monitoring
      Arm) with down-adjustment of the dose of prasugrel in high responders and up-adjustment of
      the dose of prasugrel in low responders as compared to a more conventional strategy of a
      fixed dose of 5 mg to every patient without monitoring (Conventional Arm).Rationale:
      Prasugrel 10 mg is superior to clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndrome treated
      by percutaneous coronary intervention, reducing significantly the rates of ischemic events.
      Elderly patients appear to be at higher risk of bleeding events and pharmacokinetic data
      suggests that elderly patients are exposed to a higher concentration of the active metabolite
      of prasugrel. A reduced dose of 5 mg of prasugrel is therefore proposed to these patients to
      limit the risk of bleeding. On the other hand, the elderly have also a higher ischemic risk
      and higher levels of platelet aggregation under treatment than younger patients and may
      deserve stronger protection from antiplatelet therapy. Platelet function testing appears to
      be of particular interest in patients at high risk of both ischemic and bleeding events like
      the elderly. Too intense platelet inhibition may expose the elderly patients to an excessive
      bleeding risk. Too low platelet inhibition may expose them to recurrent cardiovascular
      ischemic events. The possibility of bedside monitoring of oral antiplatelet therapy offers
      the opportunity of tailoring prasugrel therapy in elderly patients to optimize their
      risk/benefit ratio. Such strategy has never been evaluated in a randomized and adequately
      powered study. Population: Acute coronary syndrome (STEMI and NSTEMI) treated by PCI-stent
      (bare metal stent or drug eluting stent) in patients aged 75 ≥ year. Methods: Monitoring with
      VerifyNow P2Y12, 2 weeks after initiation of 5 mg of maintenance dose of prasugrel, reduction
      of antiplatelet therapy if there is high on-treatment platelet inhibition (HPI) or increase
      in dosing if there is high on-treatment platelet reactivity (HPR). Patients will be monitored
      again 2 weeks later, only if they do not meet the Verifynow P2Y12 targets at the first
      assessment. Primary endpoint net clinical benefit at 12 months:Composite of Cardiovascular
      death, myocardial infarction, stroke, urgent revascularisation, stent thrombosis and
      bleedings according to the BARC definitions (type 2, 3 or 5) Centers: Approximately 40 French
      high volume PCI centers
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite of Cardiovascular death, myocardial infarction, stroke, urgent revascularisation, stent thrombosis and bleedings according to the BARC definitions (type 2, 3 or 5) through 12 months of randomisation</measure>
    <time_frame>through 12 months of randomisation</time_frame>
    <description>Composite of Cardiovascular death, myocardial infarction, stroke, urgent revascularisation, stent thrombosis and bleedings according to the BARC definitions (type 2, 3 or 5) through 12 months of randomisation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the benefice of prasugrel adjustment on the composite ischemic endpoint of cardiovascular (CV) death, MI, definite stent thrombosis and Urgent revascularisation through 12 months of randomisation</measure>
    <time_frame>through 12 months of randomisation</time_frame>
    <description>The key secondary objective is to evaluate the benefice of prasugrel adjustment on the composite ischemic endpoint of cardiovascular (CV) death, MI, definite stent thrombosis and Urgent revascularisation through 12 months of randomisation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CV death, MI, stroke through 12 months of randomisation</measure>
    <time_frame>through 12 months of randomisation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CV death, MI, stroke or Urgent Revascularization through 12 months of randomisation</measure>
    <time_frame>through 12 months of randomisation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CV death: any death</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Any death or resuscitated cardiac death</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CV death or MI</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Definite stent thrombosis (ARC definition)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All types of bleeding according to the BARC definitions 1, 2, 3, 4, 5</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BARC Bleeding of type 2, 3 or 5</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding TIMI major through 12 months of randomisation</measure>
    <time_frame>through 12 months of randomisation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GUSTO severe or moderate bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>STEEPLE bleeding definitions (major, minor or both)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ISTH bleeding definitions (major and clinically relevant non major)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding TIMI minor</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding TIMI minimal</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding TIMI major, minor and combination</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">880</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Coronary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1: Monitoring Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Monitoring Arm: dose adjustment of prasugrel with down-adjustment of the dose of prasugrel in high responders and up-adjustment of the dose of prasugrel in low responders</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2: Conventional Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional Arm: fixed dose of prasugrel 5 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modification of Prasugrel based on a biological assay</intervention_name>
    <description>Monitoring with VerifyNow P2Y12, 2 weeks after initiation of 5 mg of maintenance dose of prasugrel, reduction of antiplatelet therapy if there is high on-treatment platelet inhibition (HPI) or increase in dosing if there is high on-treatment platelet reactivity (HPR) Device: VerifyNow point of care assay VerifyNow (ACCUMETRICS San Diego USA)</description>
    <arm_group_label>1: Monitoring Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prasugrel / clopidogrel</intervention_name>
    <description>fixed dose of prasugrel 5 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>2: Conventional Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Verify Now</intervention_name>
    <description>Monitoring with VerifyNow P2Y12, 2 weeks after initiation of 5 mg of maintenance dose of prasugrel, reduction of antiplatelet therapy if there is high on-treatment platelet inhibition (HPI) or increase in dosing if there is high on-treatment platelet reactivity (HPR) Device: VerifyNow point of care assay VerifyNow (ACCUMETRICS San Diego USA)</description>
    <arm_group_label>1: Monitoring Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute coronary syndrome (STEMI and NSTEMI) treated by PCI

          -  Stent (bare metal stent or drug eluting stent) regardless of the regime of
             thienopyridines administered before randomisation

          -  Age ≥ 75 years.

          -  Aspirin dose of 75 mg will be recommended but study authorizes doses ranging from
             75-160 mg

          -  Ability to understand and to comply with the study protocol.

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior history of ischemic or hemorrhagic stroke or transient ischemic attack, or
             sub-arachnoids haemorrhage

          -  Have received fibrinolytic therapy within 48 hours of entry or randomisation into the
             study

          -  Are receiving vitamin K antagonist

          -  Concomitant medical illness (terminal malignancy) that is associated with reduced
             survival over the expected study treatment period.

          -  History of intolerance or allergy to ASA or approved thienopyridines (ticlopidine,
             clopidogrel, or prasugrel)

          -  Have active pathological bleeding or history of bleeding diathesis

          -  Thrombocytopenia &lt; 100 000 µL

          -  Severe hepatic impairment (Child Pugh class C).

          -  Have a condition associated with poor treatment compliance, including dementia or
             mental illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>75 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gilles MONTALESCOT, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Caremeau à Nimes - Service de Cardiologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nimes</city>
        <zip>30029</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ACTION study group - Institut de Cardiologie- Hôpital la Pitié Salpêtrière</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cayla G, Cuisset T, Silvain J, Leclercq F, Manzo-Silberman S, Saint-Etienne C, Delarche N, Bellemain-Appaix A, Range G, El Mahmoud R, Carrié D, Belle L, Souteyrand G, Aubry P, Sabouret P, du Fretay XH, Beygui F, Bonnet JL, Lattuca B, Pouillot C, Varenne O, Boueri Z, Van Belle E, Henry P, Motreff P, Elhadad S, Salem JE, Abtan J, Rousseau H, Collet JP, Vicaut E, Montalescot G; ANTARCTIC investigators. Platelet function monitoring to adjust antiplatelet therapy in elderly patients stented for an acute coronary syndrome (ANTARCTIC): an open-label, blinded-endpoint, randomised controlled superiority trial. Lancet. 2016 Oct 22;388(10055):2015-2022. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31323-X. Epub 2016 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>27581531</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 24, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute coronary syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Percutaneous coronary intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Prasugrel</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet function test</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Clopidogrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prasugrel Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

