<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01535807</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CorMatrix ECM Study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01535807</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CorMatrix ECM Study: To Identify Inflammatory Markers Following CABG With/Without ECM</brief_title>
  <acronym>CorMatrix</acronym>
  <official_title>CorMatrix ECM Study: To Identify Inflammatory Markers Following CABG With/Without CorMatrix's Extra Cellular Matrix (ECM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Inova Health Care Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CorMatrix Cardiovascular, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Inova Health Care Services</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to identify proteomic inflammatory biomarkers to determine if
      there are differences in the biomarkers in patients who are treated using the CorMatrix ECM
      implant to close the pericardium and the patients whose pericardium is left open (the current
      standard of care).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The pericardium's main function is to secrete proteins that ensure proper functioning within
      the pericardial space and to maintain pericardial pressure. Once dissected the pericardium is
      usually left open at the end of surgery due to the difficulty in realigning the edges and to
      avoid adverse effects cause by an inflammatory response. The body's inflammatory response is
      one of protection and healing of an injury. However many of the inflammatory biomarkers
      released can cause adverse outcomes after cardiac surgery, including: renal failure,
      myocardial infarction, atrial fibrillation, stroke and death.

      CorMatrix extra cellular matrix (ECM) Technology is a Food and Drug Administration (FDA)
      approved unique extra cellular implant material used for pericardial closure and
      reconstruction. Pericardial reconstruction using porcine intestinal ECM is a novel
      application. ECM combines the innate attributes of nature with the precision of science to
      help the heart heal itself. It is an acellular biomaterial that does not encapsulate when
      surgically implanted, but is gradually remodeled, leaving behind organized and healthy
      tissue. The body's tissue begins remodeling at the surgical site while the ECM maintains the
      needed tissue support. When implanted, the ECM acts as a scaffold into which the patient's
      cells migrate and integrate, stimulating the patient's natural wound-healing mechanisms. As
      the patient's cells become active, they lay down their own collagen, which matures over time
      to form strong and permanent tissue repair without leaving behind permanent foreign material.
      Because the ECM contains primarily collagen, the device is gradually replaced as the
      patient's tissue gradually turns over in a natural state of self-renewal.

      A retrospective study compared the incidence of post operative atrial fibrillation (POAF) in
      patients treated with the CorMatrix ECM for pericardial closure following isolated coronary
      artery bypass graft (CABG) versus patients not treated with the patch. The retrospective
      study comprised of 222 patients. 111 were treated with the CorMatrix ECM and the other 111
      were not. Results showed POAF in 34 of 111 control patients but only 20 in 111 CorMatrix ECM
      treated patients, indicating a 54% decrease in the risk of POAF in the CorMatrix ECM treated
      patients. This study shows a statistically significant reduction in the risk of POAF in
      patients undergoing an isolated CABG with pericardial closure using the CorMatrix ECM.

      This is an unblinded, randomized study to identify proteomic inflammatory biomarkers to
      determine if there are differences in the biomarkers in patients who are treated using the
      CorMatrix ECM implant to close the pericardium and the patients whose pericardium is left
      open (the current standard of care). The study will be located at the Inova Heart and
      Vascular Institute (IHVI). The CorMatrix ECM will be implanted during the CABG surgical
      procedure in the IHVI cardiovascular operating rooms (CVOR).

      Sixty (60) patients who are routinely scheduled for a CABG will be recruited and randomly
      assigned to one of the two groups. There will be thirty (30) patients in each group. The
      control &quot;No Intervention&quot; group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving
      the pericardium open according to current standard of care. The treatment &quot;Cormatrix&quot; group
      will receive the CorMatrix EMC during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to
      the specific recommended surgical technique.

      Pericardial fluid and blood samples will be collected from all patients. Pericardial fluid
      and blood samples will undergo novel nanoparticle based biomarker discovery technology to
      harvest proteomic biomarkers at the George mason University. In addition, patients will have
      their cardiac rhythm continually assessed during their hospital stay and then at their follow
      up appointments with their surgeon and cardiologist to determine whether they developed POAF
      post discharge.

      Both genders, greater than eighteen (18) years of age, will be included in the research.
      There are no enrollment restrictions based upon race or ethnic origin and it is expected
      their inclusion will be representative of the population undergoing CABG at IHVI. Pregnant
      women are excluded from the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood and Pericardial Fluid Baseline draw. Pericardial Fluid Post-Op Draw. Blood Post-Op draw Day 1 and Day 3.</time_frame>
    <description>The identification of global low molecular weight (LMW) serum proteomic changes associated with CorMatrix ECM treated patients.
Identification of porcine specific LMW and phosphoproteomic serum protein changes associated with CorMatrix ECM treated patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post Operative Atrial Fibrillation</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Post operative rhythm during hospital stay. Rhythm on discharge. Rhythm at cardiac surgery visit. Rhythm within 30 days of surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CorMatrix Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment &quot;Cormatrix&quot; group will receive the CorMatrix EMC during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control &quot;No Intervention&quot; group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CorMatrix extra cellular matrix (ECM)</intervention_name>
    <description>Cormatrix ECM group will receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
No Intervention group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CorMatrix Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CorMatrix ECM, CorMatrix, ECM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is ≥18 years of age

          -  Subject must be selected as a candidate for isolated Coronary Artery Bypass Graft
             (CABG) procedure

          -  Subject has a Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) of ≥30%

          -  Subject is able and willing to provide written informed consent and HIPAA
             authorization

          -  Subject has a life expectancy of at least one year

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is scheduled for other concomitant surgical procedures (carotid surgery
             included)

          -  Subject has a known hypersensitivity to porcine material

          -  Subject has a religious or cultural objection to the use of blood or porcine products

          -  Subject is scheduled for Off Pump Coronary Artery Bypass procedures (OPCAB)

          -  Subject has a history of diagnosed treated or un-treated pre-operative atrial
             fibrillation or any other type of cardiac arrhythmia

          -  Subject has a history of anti-arrhythmic drug treatment in the past six (6) months

          -  Subject has an implantable cardiac device (e.g., pacemakers, implantable cardioverter
             defibrillators)

          -  Subject has a history of an accessory pathway disorder (e.g., Wolff-Parkinson-White
             syndrome)

          -  Subject has a documented myocardial infarction (MI) within six (6) weeks prior to
             study enrollment

          -  Subject needs emergent cardiac surgery (i.e., cardiogenic shock)

          -  Subject requires intra-aortic balloon pump or intravenous inotropes

          -  Subject has had an infection within six (6) weeks preceding surgery requiring
             antibiotic therapy

          -  Subject is on pre-surgical immunosuppressive therapy (corticosteroids included)

          -  Subject has chronic inflammatory disease (leukemia, lymphoma, arthritis, rheumatoid,
             lupus, Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis, hepatitis C, HIV)

          -  Subject has had therapeutic radiation to the pericardium, either prior to surgery or
             expected during the three (3) week period following surgery

          -  There is an inability to approximate the graft and pericardium edge along the entire
             extent of the defect

          -  Subject is incarcerated

          -  Subject is participating in concomitant research studies of investigational products
             (e.g., Appendage closure devices, septal defect patches)

          -  Subject is unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Niv Ad, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Inova Health Systems</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inova Heart and Vascular Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Falls Church</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22042</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cormatrix.com/</url>
    <description>ECM Technologies by CorMatrix</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 17, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>November 19, 2015</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>November 19, 2015</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2015</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 19, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 19, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary Artery Bypass Graft</keyword>
  <keyword>CorMatrix extra cellular matrix</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial Infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>identify proteomic inflammatory biomarkers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>CorMatrix Group</title>
          <description>The treatment &quot;Cormatrix&quot; group will receive the CorMatrix EMC during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
CorMatrix extra cellular matrix (ECM): - Cormatrix ECM group will receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
- No Intervention group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>The control &quot;No Intervention&quot; group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="22"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="22"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="20"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="20"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Data collection error</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>CorMatrix Group</title>
          <description>The treatment &quot;Cormatrix&quot; group will receive the CorMatrix EMC during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
CorMatrix extra cellular matrix (ECM): - Cormatrix ECM group will receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
- No Intervention group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>The control &quot;No Intervention&quot; group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="20"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="20"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="40"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="61.18" spread="9.88"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="60.17" spread="9.84"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="60.30" spread="9.93"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="35"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="40"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Inflammatory Biomarkers</title>
        <description>The identification of global low molecular weight (LMW) serum proteomic changes associated with CorMatrix ECM treated patients.
Identification of porcine specific LMW and phosphoproteomic serum protein changes associated with CorMatrix ECM treated patients.</description>
        <time_frame>Blood and Pericardial Fluid Baseline draw. Pericardial Fluid Post-Op Draw. Blood Post-Op draw Day 1 and Day 3.</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>CorMatrix Group</title>
            <description>The treatment &quot;Cormatrix&quot; group will receive the CorMatrix EMC during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
CorMatrix extra cellular matrix (ECM): - Cormatrix ECM group will receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
- No Intervention group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Control</title>
            <description>The control &quot;No Intervention&quot; group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Inflammatory Biomarkers</title>
          <description>The identification of global low molecular weight (LMW) serum proteomic changes associated with CorMatrix ECM treated patients.
Identification of porcine specific LMW and phosphoproteomic serum protein changes associated with CorMatrix ECM treated patients.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="20"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="20"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Porcine proteins in pericardial fluid</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Elevated pro-inflammatory proteins in blood</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="20"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Post Operative Atrial Fibrillation</title>
        <description>Post operative rhythm during hospital stay. Rhythm on discharge. Rhythm at cardiac surgery visit. Rhythm within 30 days of surgery.</description>
        <time_frame>Within 30 days</time_frame>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>CorMatrix Group</title>
          <description>The treatment &quot;Cormatrix&quot; group will receive the CorMatrix EMC during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
CorMatrix extra cellular matrix (ECM): - Cormatrix ECM group will receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery for the closure of the pericardium according to the specific recommended surgical technique.
- No Intervention group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Control</title>
          <description>The control &quot;No Intervention&quot; group will not receive the CorMatrix ECM during surgery, leaving the pericardium open according to current standard of care.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="20"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="20"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="20"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="20"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Lisa Fornaresio, PhD</name_or_title>
      <organization>Inova Heart and Vascular Institute</organization>
      <phone>703-776-7071</phone>
      <email>lisa.fornaresio@inova.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

