<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01538797</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>96-016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01538797</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Single Doses of YF476 on Stomach Acidity Compared With Ranitidine and Placebo in Fasted and Fed States</brief_title>
  <official_title>YF476: Effects of a Single Dose at 3 Dose Levels on 24-hour Ambulatory Gastric pH Compared With Placebo and Ranitidine in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Trio Medicines Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ferring Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Trio Medicines Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of the study were:

        -  To compare a single dose of YF476 at 3 dose levels, placebo and ranitidine with respect
           to their effects on basal- and food- stimulated gastric pH in healthy volunteers.

        -  To assess whether there is a relationship between the pharmacokinetics of YF476 and
           gastric pH in healthy volunteers.

        -  To assess the safety and tolerability of single doses of YF476 in healthy volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      YF476 is clearly a potent and selective gastrin/CCK-B antagonist and should inhibit basal and
      meal-stimulated gastric acid secretion and enhance gastric emptying of a liquid meal in man.
      Therefore YF476 might benefit patients with reflux oesophagitis. The compound has been well
      tolerated in animal toxicity studies at doses in excess of the projected therapeutic dose in
      patients, and merits studies in healthy volunteers. Extrapolation from data obtained in
      animals suggests that a single oral dose of about 10mg of YF476 should compare favourably
      with an oral dose of 150mg of ranitidine in man with respect to effect on basal and
      food-stimulated gastric acid secretion. Therefore in the proposed study a range of doses of
      YF476 encompassing that dose will be studied; the exact dose of YF476 will be chosen on the
      basis of the previous study but the top dose will not exceed 100mg. 24-hour ambulatory
      gastric pH will be monitored via an intragastric pH electrode (7-10). Although there is
      variability between subjects with respect to the effects of food and drug treatment on
      gastric pH, the methodology for measurement of ambulatory gastric pH is robust.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1996</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 1996</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically relevant changes from baseline in safety assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Physical examination, ECG and safety tests of blood/urine at screening, 24h after dosing on each Treatment Day and at follow up. Blood pressure and heart rate before and at 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12 and 24h after dosing on each Treatment Day.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Numbers of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events throughout the study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters: Cmax, Tmax, AUC 0-24 h, T1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples (8mL) before and at 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12 and 24h after each dose for assay of YF476.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic parameters: continuous 24 h ambulatory gastric pH</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Recording starts 0.5h before dosing on each Treatment Day; meals taken at 4, 9, 13 &amp; 22h after dosing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Reflux Oesophagitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>YF476</intervention_name>
    <description>There were 5 treatments: 3 dose levels of YF476 (5, 25 and 100 mg), placebo and ranitidine 150 mg. There were at least 7 days between consecutive Treatment Days.</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ranitidine</intervention_name>
    <description>There were 5 treatments: 3 dose levels of YF476 (5, 25 and 100mg), placebo and ranitidine 150mg. There were at least 7 days between consecutive Treatment Days.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female and aged 18-45 years.

          -  No clinically relevant abnormal findings in the clinical history or physical
             examination at the screening assessment which could interfere with the objectives of
             the study or make the subject's participation hazardous.

          -  No clinically relevant abnormal laboratory values at the screening evaluation
             (Attachment 2).

          -  A normal ECG at the screening examination.

          -  A body mass index (Quetelet index) in the range 19-30:

          -  Body Mass Index = weight [kg]_ height [m]2

          -  Normal blood pressure and heart rate at the screening examination, i.e. BP 90-150mmHg
             systolic, 40-95mmHg diastolic; heart rate 40-100 beats/min in seated position.

          -  Subjects must be of sufficient intelligence to understand the nature of the study and
             any hazards of their participation in it. They must be able to communicate
             satisfactorily with the Investigator and to participate in, and comply with the
             requirements of, the entire study.

          -  Subjects must give their written consent to participate after reading the
             Information-for-Volunteers Leaflet and Consent Form, and after having the opportunity
             to discuss the study with the Investigator or his deputy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Females who are pregnant or lactating, or who are sexually active and are not using a
             reliable method of contraception.

          -  Clinically relevant abnormal history or physical findings at the screening assessment,
             which could interfere with the objectives of the study or the safety of the subject's
             participation.

          -  Clinically relevant abnormalities of laboratory values or ECG at screening evaluation.

          -  Presence of acute or chronic illness or history of chronic illness sufficient to
             invalidate subject's participation in the study or make it unnecessarily hazardous.

          -  Impaired endocrine, thyroid, hepatic, respiratory or renal function, diabetes
             mellitus, coronary heart disease or history of any psychotic mental illness.

          -  Participation in other clinical studies of a new chemical entity or a prescription
             medicine within the previous 3 months.

          -  Presence or history of drug or alcohol abuse, or intake of more than 40 units of
             alcohol weekly.

          -  Loss of more than 400mL blood during the 3 months before the study, e.g. as a blood
             donor.

          -  Use of prescription medication during 30 days before the study.

          -  Use of an over-the-counter medicine during 7 days before the study

          -  Blood pressure or heart rate outside those values specified under inclusion criterion
             (f).

          -  Possibility that the subject will not cooperate with the requirements of the protocol.

          -  Evidence of drug abuse on urine testing at study entry.

          -  Positive test for hepatitis B or C or HIV 1 &amp; 2.

          -  High risk of hepatitis or HIV infection.

          -  History of severe allergic disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Malcolm J Boyce, FRCP FFPM</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Trio Medicines Limited</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hammersmith Medicines Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW10 7EW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 24, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 24, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>YF476</keyword>
  <keyword>gastrin receptor antagonist</keyword>
  <keyword>gastric pH</keyword>
  <keyword>healthy subjects</keyword>
  <keyword>ranitidine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophagitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophagitis, Peptic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ranitidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ranitidine bismuth citrate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

