<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01537926</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HALT-HCM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01537926</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypertrophic Regression With N-Acetylcysteine in HCM</brief_title>
  <acronym>HALT</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Feasibility Study With N-acetylcystein (NAC) in Patients With HCM Caused by Sarcomere Proteins Mutations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the sudy is to conduct a small study to gather the preliminary data for future
      lage scale clinical studies that will be designed test the potential beneficial effect of
      over-the counter study anti-oxidant drug called N-acetylcysteine (NAC) in patients with a
      heart muscle condition called Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy (HCM). The present study is a pilot
      feasibility study, the investigators want to find out whether the investigators can recruit
      and retain patients with HCM in the study and whether these patients can tolerate this drug
      and can stay on one year. Likewise, the investigators want to find out any potential side
      effects that this drug might have and estimate whether ii has any beneficial effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective is to perform a pilot study in patients with hypertrophic
      cardiomyopathy (HCM) and mutations in genes encoding sarcomere proteins to assess safety and
      gather the pre-requisite data for subsequent robust randomized placebo-controlled efficacy
      studies with N-acetylcysteine (NAC). We will gather data on the recruitment, accrual,
      retention, and compliance rates of HCM patients randomized to treatment with a placebo or two
      escalating doses of NAC. Likewise, we will determine any potential side effects and estimate
      the effect size of NAC on indices of cardiac hypertrophy.

      HCM, the main focus of our research during the past two decades, is the most common cause of
      sudden cardiac death (SCD) in the young and an important cause of morbidity in the elderly.
      Despite its clinical impact, there is no effective pharmacological therapy for HCM. None of
      the current pharmacological therapies reverses or attenuates cardiac hypertrophy or reduces
      the risk of SCD in adults. Cardiac hypertrophy, the quintessential clinical feature of human
      HCM, is a major determinant of morbidity and the risk of SCD. Regression of cardiac
      hypertrophy is expected to improve morbidity and decrease the risk of SCD in HCM, as observed
      upon regression of load-dependent cardiac hypertrophy.

      We have generated transgenic rabbit and mouse models of HCM and shown that cardiac
      hypertrophy and fibrosis could be reversed through genetic or pharmacological interventions.
      Results with NAC, a precursor to glutathione; the largest intracellular thiol pool against
      oxidative stress, were most promising. In three independent studies in two different
      transgenic models of HCM (rabbits and mouse), treatment with NAC completely reversed cardiac
      hypertrophy and fibrosis and improved indices of diastolic function. The ultimate goal of
      every physician-scientist is to apply the bench discoveries at the bedside. We propose to
      test our findings in the animal models in humans with HCM caused by sarcomere protein
      mutations. The use of NAC is also supported by data showing increased oxidative stress in
      human HCM. Moreover, NAC has been used extensively in humans and has a well-established
      safety profile. Resources including patients with sarcomere protein mutations are available
      to successfully complete a randomized placebo-controlled (N=25) pilot study to test two
      escalating doses of NAC (N=50), administered for one year. We will determine recruitment,
      accrual, retention and compliance rates; tolerability, safety and side effects; and estimate
      the effect size of NAC on the indices of cardiac hypertrophy, as determined by serial cardiac
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at the baseline and after one year of treatment. Only HCM
      patients with sarcomere proteins mutations will be included to exclude phenocopy. The Core
      centers will interpret the phenotypic data to assure homogeneity. Data Coordinating Center
      will assist in the research design, planning and conduct of the study and analysis of the
      data. The findings will set the stage for large-scale robust randomized placebo-control
      efficacy studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment rate</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will determine the estimates and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) of
The recruitment and accrual rates
Patient compliance rate with the two escalating doses of NAC and placebo
Patients developing side effects
Patients who complete the intended 12 months treatment with NAC and placebo.
Baseline estimates and effect size of NAC on indices of cardiac hypertrophy mainly LVM indexed to body surface area (LVMI).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>indices of cardiac mass and function</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in LV maximum and mean wall thicknesses; LVED volume (EDDV), LV end systolic volume (ESV), circumferential LV strain, LVEF, peak filling rate (PFR), peak ejection rate (PER) and time to PER; and macroscopic interstitial myocardial fibrosis, as defined by delayed MRI following gadolinium contrast administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>N-acetylcysteine (NAC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>N-acetylcysteine 600mg by mouth every 12 hours for 90 days. N-acetylcysteine 1200mg by mouth every 12 hours for 270 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo 1 cap by mouth every 12 hours for 90 days. Placebo 2 caps by mouth every 12 hours for 270 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>N-acetylcysteine</intervention_name>
    <description>NAC 600mg capsule or matching Placebo , 1 twice daily for 90 days, then increase to NAC 1,200mg or matching placebo, 2 capsules twice daily for 270 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>N-acetylcysteine (NAC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>sugar pill manufactured to minic NAC 600mg capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>N-acetylcysteine (NAC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with primary cardiac hypertrophy, non-dilated LV cavity and preserved LV
             systolic function, hence, the diagnosis of HCM, who have at least an LV end diastolic
             (LVSD) wall thickness of at least 15 mm on a 2D echocardiogram and

          -  Known to have mutations in genes encoding sarcomeric proteins

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hypersensitivity to NAC

          -  Individuals younger than 18 years old (in the pilot study)

          -  Phenocopy conditions, diagnosed clinically or genetically

          -  Patients who have undergone transcatheter (alcohol) septal ablation within 6 months.

          -  Individuals (typically family members) with causal mutations but an LVSD wall
             thickness of &lt;15 mm

          -  Patients with concomitant diseases such as:

               -  Significant coronary artery disease &gt;70% luminal diameter stenosis in ny of the
                  major coronary arteries (if known);

               -  Valvular heart diseases (more than mild aortic stenosis and mitral regurgitation,
                  the latter judged to be due to primary mitral valve abnormalities);

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension, defined as systolic blood pressure of

                    -  140 mmHg and diastolic blood pressure of ≥90 mmHg on medication, mean of
                       three measurements at rest);

               -  Other significant medical problems, such as moderate to severe chronic renal
                  failure (GFR&lt;45 ml/min/1.73m2), advanced liver disease, cancer, or other
                  disabling conditions

          -  Pregnant women, nursing mothers and those who plan pregnancy during the study period

          -  Those with active asthma (albeit the concern is relevant to nebulizer form but not
             oral formulations)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ali J. Marian, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UTHSC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 17, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ali. J. Marian</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor , Cardiovascular Genetics, IMM</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HALT</keyword>
  <keyword>HCM</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Hypertrophic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetylcysteine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>N-monoacetylcystine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 30, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

