<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01964261</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HS-13-00492</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01964261</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Providing Closed Loop Cortical Control of Extracorporeal Devices to Patients With Quadriplegia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Feasibility Study of the Ability of the Neural Prosthetic System 2 to Provide Direct Closed Loop Cortical Control of Extracorporeal Devices Through the Use of Intracortical Microstimulation in Patients With Quadriplegia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Richard A. Andersen, PhD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rancho Los Amigos National Rehabilitation Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>California Institute of Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is being conducted to develop a brain controlled medical device, called a
      brain-machine interface. The device will provide people with a spinal cord injury some
      ability to control an external device such as a computer cursor or robotic limb by using
      their thoughts along with sensory feedback.

      Development of a brain-machine interface is very difficult and currently only limited
      technology exists in this area of neuroscience. Other studies have shown that people with
      high spinal cord injury still have intact brain areas capable of planning movements and
      grasps, but are not able to execute the movement plans. The device in this study involves
      implanting very fine recording electrodes into areas of the brain that are known to create
      arm movement plans and provide hand grasping information and sense feeling in the hand and
      fingers. These movement and grasp plans would then normally be sent to other regions of the
      brain to execute the actual movements. By tying into those pathways and sending the movement
      plan signals to a computer instead, the investigators can translate the movement plans into
      actual movements by a computer cursor or robotic limb.

      A key part of this study is to electrically stimulate the brain by introducing a small amount
      of electrical current into the electrodes in the sensory area of the brain. This will result
      in the sensation of touch in the hand and/or fingers. This stimulation to the brain will
      occur when the robotic limb touches the object, thereby allowing the brain to &quot;feel&quot; what the
      robotic arm is touching.

      The device being used in this study is called the Neuroport Array and is surgically implanted
      in the brain. This device and the implantation procedure are experimental which means that it
      has not been approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA). One Neuroport Array consists
      of a small grid of electrodes that will be implanted in brain tissue and a small cable that
      runs from the electrode grid to a small hourglass-shaped pedestal. This pedestal is designed
      to be attached to the skull and protrude through the scalp to allow for connection with the
      computer equipment. The top portion of the pedestal has a protective cover that will be in
      place when the pedestal is not in use. The top of this pedestal and its protective cover will
      be visible on the outside of the head. Three Neuroport Arrays and pedestals will be implanted
      in this study so three of these protective covers will be visible outside of the head. It
      will be possible to cover these exposed portions of the device with a hat or scarf.

      The investigators hope to learn how safe and effective the Neuroport array plus stimulation
      is in controlling computer generated images and real world objects, such as a robotic arm,
      using imagined movements of the arms and hands.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient control over the end effector (virtual or physical)</measure>
    <time_frame>One year after array implantation</time_frame>
    <description>The primary effectiveness objective of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of the NPS2 in controlling virtual or physical end effectors. Signals from posterior parietal cortex will allow the subject to control the end effector with accuracy significantly greater than chance; the subject will be able to perceive and discriminate ICMS above the level of chance; and,incorporating stimulation will improve the subject's control over the end effector.
We will evaluate the effectiveness of the NPS2 primarily by calculating the accuracy of the subjects' control over the end effector with and without ICMS, and comparing these different accuracies to the chance level, and to each other. Each subject will serve as his or her own control.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absence of infection or irritation</measure>
    <time_frame>One year after array implantation</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the safety of the NPS2. Implantation will not be associated with infection or irritation, and that the serious adverse event rate will not rise above 1%. We will evaluate the safety of the NPS2 by inspecting the subjects' scalps for evidence of reddening or discharge, by performing regularly scheduled neurologic history and physical exam, and by obtaining feedback from the subjects. The condition of the area will be compared with its condition on previous visits, history will be obtained regarding new symptoms and neurological and physical exam will be compared to baseline exams.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Quadriplegia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neural Prosthetic System 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Neural Prosthetic System 2 consists of three Neuroport Arrays, which are described in detail in the intervention description. Two of the three Neuroport Arrays are inserted into the posterior parietal cortex, an area of the brain used in reach and grasp planning. The third Neuroport Array is inserted into somatosensory cortex, specifically S1 which represents sensory feedback for the hand and fingers. The arrays are inserted and the percutaneous pedestal is attached to the skull during a surgical procedure. Following surgical recovery the subject will participate in study sessions 3-5 times per week in which they will learn to control an end effector by thought augmented with sensory feedback via intracortical microstimulation. They will then use the end effector to perform various reach and grasp tasks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neural Prosthetic System 2 (NPS2)</intervention_name>
    <description>The NPS2 comprises 2 NeuroPort Arrays (Pt) and 1 NeuroPort Array (SIROF). Each Pt array is comprised of 100 1.5 mm microelectrodes organized on a 4mm x 4mm silicon base that is 0.25 mm thick. Each microelectrode is insulated with Parylene-C polymer and is electrically isolated from neighboring electrodes by non-conducting glass. Of the 100 electrodes, 96 are wire bonded using 25m gold alloy insulated wires sealed with a silicone elastomer. The wire bundle is potted to a printed circuit board with epoxy, the circuit board is inserted into the Patient Pedestal (percutaneous connector), and then the Patient Pedestal is filled with silicone elastomer. Two fine platinum reference wires are also attached to the Patient Pedestal. The Patient Pedestal is 19 mm wide at the skin interface. The SIROF Array is similar to the Pt Array, the only difference is a change in the tip of the electrodes from platinum to sputtered iridium oxide film (SIROF).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neural Prosthetic System 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NeuroPort Array</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  High cervical spinal lesion

          -  Age 22-65

          -  Able to provide informed consent

          -  Able to understand and comply with instructions in English

          -  Communicate via speech

          -  Surgical clearance

          -  Life expectancy greater than 12 months

          -  Travel up to 60 miles to study locations up to five days per week

          -  Caregiver monitor for surgical site complications and behavioral changes on a daily
             basis

          -  Psychosocial support system

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of memory problems

          -  Intellectual impairment

          -  Psychotic illness or chronic psychiatric disorder, including major depression if
             untreated

          -  Poor visual acuity

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Active infection or unexplained fever

          -  Scalp lesions or skin breakdown

          -  HIV or AIDS infection

          -  Active cancer or chemotherapy

          -  Diabetes

          -  Autonomic dysreflexia

          -  History of seizure

          -  Implanted hydrocephalus shunt

          -  Previous neurosurgical history affecting parietal lobe function

          -  Medical conditions contraindicating surgery and chronic implantation of a medical
             device

          -  Prior cranioplasty

          -  Unable to undergo MRI or anticipated need for MRI during study

          -  Nursing an infant or unwilling to bottle-feed infant

          -  Chronic oral or intravenous use of steroids or immunosuppressive therapy

          -  Suicidal ideation

          -  Drug or alcohol dependence

          -  Planning to become pregnant, or unwilling to use adequate birth control

          -  Implanted Cardiac Defibrillator, Pacemaker, vagal nerve stimulator, or spinal cord
             stimulator.

          -  Implanted deep brain stimulator (DBS), DBS leads, or cochlear implant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard A Andersen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>California Institute of Technology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Liu, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christi Heck, MD, PhD, MMM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mindy Aisen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rancho Los Amigos National Rehabilitation Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Charles Liu, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>800-872-2273</phone>
    <email>chasliu@cheme.caltech.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mindy Aisen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>562-401-8111</phone>
    <email>maisen@dhs.lacounty.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rancho Los Amigos National Rehabilitation Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Downey</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mindy Aisen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>562-401-8111</phone>
      <email>maisen@dhs.lacounty.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Southern California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>California Institute of Technology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pasadena</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91125</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 15, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 17, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>California Institute of Technology</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard A. Andersen, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>James G. Boswell Professor of Neuroscience</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neural</keyword>
  <keyword>Prosthetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain machine interface</keyword>
  <keyword>brain computer interface</keyword>
  <keyword>brain control</keyword>
  <keyword>paralysis</keyword>
  <keyword>tetraplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>quadriplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>spinal cord injury</keyword>
  <keyword>stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>sensory feedback</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Quadriplegia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

