<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01961986</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-02125</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01961986</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rotator Cuff Sparing Total Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>Rotator Cuff Sparing Total Arthroplasty - A Prospective, Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Design: Prospective, randomized clinical trial, of 120 patients requiring a total shoulder
      replacement (TSR).

      Purpose: To collect and evaluate long-term clinical data on patients whose total shoulder
      replacement (TSR) is performed using the traditional surgical approach (called the
      subscapularis release approach) as compared to patients who have a TSR procedure done using a
      newer surgical approach (called the rotator cuff sparing approach).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design: Prospective, randomized clinical trial, of 120 patients requiring a total shoulder
      replacement (TSR).

      Purpose: To collect and evaluate long-term clinical data on patients whose total shoulder
      replacement (TSR) is performed using the traditional surgical approach (called the
      subscapularis release approach) as compared to patients who have a TSR procedure done using a
      newer surgical approach (called the rotator cuff sparing approach).

      For patients with arthritis, TSR can successfully improve pain and restore function. As a
      result, TSR has become the treatment of choice for patients with shoulder arthritis. Despite
      these generally good outcomes, however, there are concerns that rotator cuff function is
      suboptimal after surgery. One of the rotator cuff tendons is usually cut during the TSR
      procedure to insert the prosthesis and then repaired at the end of the surgery. If the tendon
      does not heal adequately, patients may experience persistent weakness, pain, and even failure
      of the replacement. Recently, a surgical technique called rotator cuff sparing TSR has been
      described where the procedure can be performed without ever cutting any of the rotator cuff
      tendons. As such, there should be minimized risk to the rotator cuff function after the
      surgery. Our study proposes to enroll two groups of patients with shoulder arthritis. The
      first group will be treated with the traditional TSR procedure. The second group will be
      treated with this new rotator cuff sparing surgical technique for TSR where the rotator cuff
      is never violated. After surgery, we will examine motion, strength, and functional use of the
      shoulder. In addition, we will specifically test the rotator cuff strength after the surgery.
      In this fashion, we plan to test the hypothesis that rotator cuff sparing TSR can improve the
      rotator cuff function while maintaining the excellent pain relief and motion that is normally
      observed after the traditional TSR procedure.

      Enrollment: A total of approximately 120 subjects will be enrolled and treated at NYU
      Hospital for Joint Diseases. Subjects participating in the study will be randomly assigned to
      have their total shoulder replacement done using the traditional surgical approach (called
      the subscapularis release approach) or by the newer surgical approach (called the rotator
      cuff sparing approach). For each patient, a number will be created by a random number
      generator. Patients randomized to the even number (2) will receive a traditional TSA
      procedure that includes incision and repair of the subscapularis tendon during the procedure.
      Patients randomized to the odd number (1) will receive the rotator cuff sparing TSA.
      Regardless of the procedure, patients will remain &quot;blind&quot; to the type of procedure they
      received until completion of their 2 year follow up.

      Follow-Up Requirements: Office Visits: Patients' participation will involve five (5) office
      visits (after surgery) over a period of two (2) years. At each visit, as part of the
      patients' regular care, they will have standard x-rays of their shoulder. All patients will
      complete self-administered questionnaires to assess the clinical outcome of the surgery and
      patients satisfaction. The patient administered outcome questionnaires will include the
      SF-12, and Patient Assessment Case Report Form.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 4, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 4, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>Preoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Patient subjective and objective data will be collected for all patients using the Short Form 12 (SF-12)and Patient Assessment forms. From these forms, both American Shoulder and Elbow Society (ASES) outcome score and the Constant score can be derived to assess functional outcome. Additional data will also be collected specific to the integrity and the function of the subscapularis tendon that include the results of the &quot;belly press&quot; and the &quot;lift off&quot; test. They will be graded as &quot;unable&quot;, &quot;maintain against gravity&quot;, &quot;maintain against resistance&quot;, and &quot;full strength.&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <condition>Inflammatory Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TSR: traditional subscap release</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>TSR - traditional subscapularis release approach
Subscapularis tendon release technique TSR</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TSR: rotator cuff sparing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rotator cuff sparing technique TSR</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TSR - traditional subscapularis release</intervention_name>
    <description>Total Shoulder Replacement surgery performed using the traditional subscapularis release approach.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TSR: traditional subscap release</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TSR - rotator cuff sparing</intervention_name>
    <description>Total Shoulder Replacement surgery performed using the rotator cuff sparing approach.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TSR: rotator cuff sparing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is indicated for shoulder joint replacement

          -  Patient is at least 21 years of age

          -  Patient is expected to survive at least 2 years beyond surgery

          -  Patient is willing to participate by complying with pre-and post-operative visit
             requirements

          -  Patient is willing and able to review and sign a study informed consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior arthroplasty in the affected shoulder.

          -  Significant deformity of the proximal humerus that requires a custom made implant or
             where osteotomy of the shaft and / or the tuberosity has to be considered.

          -  Significant medial erosion of the glenoid such that lateral edge of the humeral head
             lies medial to the lateral rim of the acromion.

          -  Significant injury to the brachial plexus

          -  Inability or unwillingness to participate in the post operative evaluation for the
             entire 24 months period.

          -  Pregnant and lactating women will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Young W Kwon, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Hospital for Joint Diseases</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Hospital for Joint Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deshmukh AV, Koris M, Zurakowski D, Thornhill TS. Total shoulder arthroplasty: long-term survivorship, functional outcome, and quality of life. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2005 Sep-Oct;14(5):471-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16194737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khan A, Bunker TD, Kitson JB. Clinical and radiological follow-up of the Aequalis third-generation cemented total shoulder replacement: a minimum ten-year study. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2009 Dec;91(12):1594-600. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.91B12.22139.</citation>
    <PMID>19949123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lo IK, Litchfield RB, Griffin S, Faber K, Patterson SD, Kirkley A. Quality-of-life outcome following hemiarthroplasty or total shoulder arthroplasty in patients with osteoarthritis. A prospective, randomized trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2005 Oct;87(10):2178-85.</citation>
    <PMID>16203880</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norris TR, Iannotti JP. Functional outcome after shoulder arthroplasty for primary osteoarthritis: a multicenter study. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2002 Mar-Apr;11(2):130-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11988723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armstrong A, Lashgari C, Teefey S, Menendez J, Yamaguchi K, Galatz LM. Ultrasound evaluation and clinical correlation of subscapularis repair after total shoulder arthroplasty. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2006 Sep-Oct;15(5):541-8. Epub 2006 Jul 27.</citation>
    <PMID>16979047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller BS, Joseph TA, Noonan TJ, Horan MP, Hawkins RJ. Rupture of the subscapularis tendon after shoulder arthroplasty: diagnosis, treatment, and outcome. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2005 Sep-Oct;14(5):492-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16194740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller SL, Hazrati Y, Klepps S, Chiang A, Flatow EL. Loss of subscapularis function after total shoulder replacement: A seldom recognized problem. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2003 Jan-Feb;12(1):29-34.</citation>
    <PMID>12610483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerber C, Yian EH, Pfirrmann CA, Zumstein MA, Werner CM. Subscapularis muscle function and structure after total shoulder replacement with lesser tuberosity osteotomy and repair. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2005 Aug;87(8):1739-45.</citation>
    <PMID>16085613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qureshi S, Hsiao A, Klug RA, Lee E, Braman J, Flatow EL. Subscapularis function after total shoulder replacement: results with lesser tuberosity osteotomy. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2008 Jan-Feb;17(1):68-72. Epub 2007 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18024179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lafosse L, Schnaser E, Haag M, Gobezie R. Primary total shoulder arthroplasty performed entirely thru the rotator interval: technique and minimum two-year outcomes. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2009 Nov-Dec;18(6):864-73. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2009.03.017. Epub 2009 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>19540778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerber C, Hersche O, Farron A. Isolated rupture of the subscapularis tendon. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 1996 Jul;78(7):1015-23.</citation>
    <PMID>8698718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerber C, Krushell RJ. Isolated rupture of the tendon of the subscapularis muscle. Clinical features in 16 cases. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1991 May;73(3):389-94.</citation>
    <PMID>1670434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tokish JM, Decker MJ, Ellis HB, Torry MR, Hawkins RJ. The belly-press test for the physical examination of the subscapularis muscle: electromyographic validation and comparison to the lift-off test. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2003 Sep-Oct;12(5):427-30.</citation>
    <PMID>14564261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 8, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 9, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rotator Cuff</keyword>
  <keyword>Rotator Cuff Sparing</keyword>
  <keyword>Shoulder Replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Shoulder Replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Shoulder Arthroplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

