<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01967251</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MX030</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1146-1278</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01967251</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy, Safety and Dose-response of Udenafil in Patients With Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia and Erectile Dysfunction</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Triple Blind, Placebo-controlled, Parallel-group Trial to Assess the Efficacy, Safety and Dose Response of Udenafil for 12 Weeks in Mexican Patients With Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia and Erectile Dysfunction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy, dose-response and safety of udenafil
      25 mg, 50 mg and 75 mg every day (q.d.) for 12 weeks in the treatment of lower urinary tract
      symptoms (LUTS) associated with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH and for the treatment of
      erectile dysfunction (ED).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called Udenafil. Udenafil is being tested to treat
      lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) associated with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) and
      for the treatment of erectile dysfunction (ED). This study will look at the change in lower
      urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) associated with benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) and in
      erectile dysfunction (ED) in people who take Udenafil.

      The study will enroll approximately 950 patients. Participants taking BPH or ED medication
      will enter a 4-week wash out period. Patients not previously treated and those who
      accomplished the wash out period will enter a placebo (dummy inactive pill) lead-in period of
      another 4 weeks. Participants will then be randomly assigned (by chance, like flipping a
      coin) to one of the four treatment groups—which will remain undisclosed to the patient and
      study doctor during the study (unless there is an urgent medical need):

        -  Udenafil 25 mg

        -  Udenafil 50 mg

        -  Udenafil 75 mg

        -  Placebo (dummy inactive pill) - this is a tablet that looks like the study drug but has
           no active ingredient

      All participants will be asked to take one tablet at the same time each day throughout the
      study, and will be asked to keep a Sexual Encounter Profile (SEP) diary.

      This multi-centre trial will be conducted in Mexico. The overall time to participate in this
      study is up to 20 weeks. Participants will make 6 visits to the clinic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Total International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The IPSS is an 8 question (7 symptom questions + 1 quality of life question) tool used to screen for, rapidly diagnose, track the symptoms of, and suggest management of the symptoms of the disease benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH). The 7 symptoms questions include feeling of incomplete bladder emptying, frequency, intermittency, urgency, weak stream, straining and nocturia, each referring to during the last month, and each involving assignment of a score from 1 to 5 for a total of maximum 35 points. The 8th question of quality of life is assigned a score of 1 to 6. The total score correlates as follows: 0-7 mildly symptomatic; 8-19 moderately symptomatic; 20-35 severely symptomatic.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Erectile Function Domain of the International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The IIEF is a standardised and validated 15-item self-evaluation scale that provides pre-post treatment clinic evaluations of erectile function, orgasmic function, sexual desire, satisfaction in sexual intercourse and general satisfaction. The Erectile Function domain (6-item) provides pre-post treatment evaluations of erectile function.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>AEs will be evaluated by monitoring participants vital signs, laboratory tests (blood chemistry, hematology, coagulation and serology tests, urianalysis), electrocardiography (ECG).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Erectile Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Udenafil 25 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Udenafil 25 mg, tablets, orally, once daily for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Udenafil 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Udenafil 50 mg, tablets, orally, once daily for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Udenafil 75 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Udenafil 75 mg, tablets, orally, once daily for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Udenafil placebo-matching tablets, orally, once daily for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Udenafil</intervention_name>
    <description>Udenafil tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Udenafil 25 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Udenafil 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Udenafil 75 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Udenafil placebo-matching tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men ≥ 45 years of age.

          2. Sexually active, with a stable female partner with whom the participant expects to
             have a relationship for the entire duration of the study.

          3. The participant has benign prostatic hyperplasia with lower urinary tract symptoms
             (BPH-LUTS) according to clinical diagnostic criteria, with ≥ 6 months of evolution at
             the screening visit.

          4. Clinical history of erectile dysfunction (ED) (defined as the inability to achieve or
             maintain the penile erection to achieve a satisfactory sexual relationship) of at
             least 3 months of evolution.

          5. Freely given informed consent at the screening visit (an essential requirement to
             participate in the study).

          6. Bladder obstruction defined by maximal flow rate (Qmax) of 4-15 mI/sec (with a
             premicturition volume of 150 to 550 mL evaluated by ultrasound, with a minimum
             micturition volume of 125 mL) at Visit I immediately prior to active treatment
             initiation.

          7. Total score of ≥ 13 points in the InternationaI Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS)
             questionnaire at Visit 1, immediately prior to active treatment initiation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participants that are currently taking nitrates, antiandrogens, estrogens,
             luteninizing hormone-releasing hormone agonist/antagonist, or anabolic steroids at
             study entry. Participants that are taking a stable dose level of testosterone are not
             excluded.

          2. Post-void residual (PVR) volume ≥ 300 mL, as assessed by ultrasound at the Visit 1.

          3. Prostate-specific antigen (PSA) ≥ 10.0 ng/mL at the Visit 1.

          4. PSA of 4.0 - 10.0 ng/ml if free PSA is &lt; 0,25 (25%) at Visit 1.

          5. Clinical evidence of prostate cancer.

          6. Glycosylated hemoglobin (Hb1Ac) &gt; 10 % at study entry.

          7. Patients who have undergone bladder catheterization due to acute urine retention.

          8. Medical history or clinical evidence of any pelvic, bladder or urinary tract
             condition, or urinary retention that, as judged by the urologist, might compromise
             protocol compliance.

          9. Any surgical procedure in the lower urinary tract (including prostate biopsy) within
             30 days prior to the Screening Visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico</city>
        <state>Distrito Federal</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico</city>
        <state>Estado de México</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Guadalajara</city>
        <state>Jalisco</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Morelia</city>
        <state>Michoacán</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Cuernavaca</city>
        <state>Morelos</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Monterrey</city>
        <state>Nuevo León</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Cholula</city>
        <state>Puebla</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chihuahua</city>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 17, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 22, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostatic Hyperplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Phosphodiesterase 5 inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Erectile DysfunctionDrug Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erectile Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Udenafil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Phosphodiesterase 5 Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

