<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01963390</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012P000184</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01963390</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metabolomics During Testosterone Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Testosterone Therapy and Its Effects on Metabolic Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Men's Health Boston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Men's Health Boston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      One promising but understudied area in the field of testosterone (T) therapy is its effect on
      metabolism and the development of type II diabetes. Metabolomics is a powerful research tool
      that can detect very early signs of metabolic derangement that may lead to metabolic disease.
      In this observational study, investigators aim to apply metabolomics in order to better
      understand how T therapy influences metabolism. In a clinical population of outpatient men
      with T deficiency investigators will perform comprehensive clinical evaluations and also
      obtain blood for metabolomics. This will be done once prior to T therapy and again after 4-6
      months of T therapy. Investigators hypothesize that they can detect metabolic derangements in
      men with T deficiency and that these derangements will improve with T therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      One promising but understudied area in the field of T therapy is its effect on insulin
      resistance (IR) and the development of type II diabetes and cardiometabolic disease. Although
      several clinical studies suggest T therapy improves metabolic parameters and may prevent
      disease progression, a mechanism for understanding this process is lacking. Investigators
      propose to use metabolomics to shed light on how metabolic function changes with T therapy.

      Metabolomics is an established investigative tool that measures hundreds of unique chemical
      markers (metabolites) involved in normal and diseased cellular processes from a blood sample.
      Previous studies using the Metabolite Profiling Platform at the Broad Institute of
      Harvard/Massachusetts Institute of Technology applied tandem liquid chromatography-mass
      spectrometry (LC-MS)-based metabolomics to large, population-based cohorts. These studies
      identified and validated highly sensitive signatures of IR that successfully predicted occult
      risk for type II diabetes in clinically normal men. Investigators now plan to apply
      metabolomics to a clinical population in order to obtain a new perspective on the biochemical
      metabolic changes that occur based on a man's testosterone status. Investigators plan to
      study men with symptomatic testosterone deficiency identified at Men's Health Boston (MHB),
      an outpatient men's health clinic.

      In a pilot study involving 32 blood samples, investigators have already identified a specific
      metabolomic signature in men undergoing androgen deprivation therapy for prostate cancer.
      Based on these preliminary results and other recent studies, investigators hypothesize that
      they can detect metabolic derangements in men with T deficiency and that these derangements
      will respond to changes in T levels. Investigators will address this hypothesis though the
      following specific aims:

      Aim 1: To characterize metabolite profiles and evaluate metabolic dysfunction in T deficient
      men

      To accomplish this aim investigators will study T deficient men presenting to MHB. In
      addition to metabolite profiling, these men will undergo a comprehensive clinical evaluation
      at MHB including:

        -  Complete History and Physical exam

        -  Assessment of symptoms of T deficiency and sexual function using validated and other
           questionnaires

        -  Comprehensive hormonal and metabolic laboratory evaluation

        -  Body composition (including visceral and subcutaneous adiposity) by dual x-ray
           absorptiometry (DXA) Investigators will build a reference dataset relating metabolite
           profiles with metabolic risk factors in a clinical population of T deficient men. This
           will include data on the relationship between metabolite profiles and sexual and other
           symptoms of T deficiency. Investigators will also compare concentrations of select
           metabolites between T deficient men and matched eugonadal controls previously studied in
           the Framingham cohort.

      Aim 2: To determine how T therapy influences metabolite profiles and IR

        1. To identify metabolites that change in response to raising serum T

        2. To determine how changes in metabolite profiles relate to changes in IR

        3. To determine how response in terms of sexual function symptoms of low T relate to
           response in metabolite profiles and IR.

      Metabolite profiles will be obtained and clinical evaluation performed (described above under
      Aim1) at baseline and again after 6 months of therapy. Investigators will study interactions
      between changes in sexual function and serum T, IR, body composition and metabolite profiles
      (with particular attention to established metabolite markers of IR).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolomics</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4-6 mo of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be sent to the Metabolite Profiling Platform at the Broad Institute of Harvard/Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Metabolomics measures hundreds of unique chemical markers (metabolites) involved in normal and diseased cellular processes from a blood sample. These metabolites include branched chain and aromatic amino acids, ketoacids, and triacylglycerides.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolomics</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be sent to the Metabolite Profiling Platform at the Broad Institute of Harvard/Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Metabolomics measures hundreds of unique chemical markers (metabolites) involved in normal and diseased cellular processes from a blood sample. These metabolites include branched chain and aromatic amino acids, ketoacids, and triacylglycerides.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms of Testosterone Deficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4-6mo of T therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms of T deficiency will be assessed using the clinical history and using validated and other questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Composition</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4-6mo of T therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition, including visceral and subcutaneous adiposity, will be determined using dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting insulin and glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4-6mo of T therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Insulin and glucose will be determined from a fasting blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4-6mo of T therapy</time_frame>
    <description>A clinical lipid profile including LDL, HDL, and total triglycerides will be obtained from a fasting blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms of Testosterone Deficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms of T deficiency will be assessed using the clinical history and using validated and other questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Body composition, including visceral and subcutaneous adiposity, will be determined using dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting insulin and glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Insulin and glucose will be determined from a fasting blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid Profile</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>A clinical lipid profile including LDL, HDL, and total triglycerides will be obtained from a fasting blood sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Testosterone Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone therapy</arm_group_label>
    <description>The study population is a cohort of testosterone deficient men who are planning on undergoing testosterone therapy at an outpatient men's health clinic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Testosterone Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>In this observational study we will be enrolling testosterone deficient men who intend to undergo testosterone therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Serum samples obtained for metabolomics
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Testosterone deficient men who intend to undergo testosterone therapy at an outpatient
        men's health clinic.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Symptomatic testosterone deficiency

          -  Intend to undergo testosterone therapy at Men's Health Boston

          -  Total testosterone &lt;350ng/dL or free testosterone &lt;1.5ng/dL

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 diabetes

          -  Use of exogenous testosterone or clomiphene citrate

          -  Known karyotype abnormalities

          -  Seizure disorders

          -  Malignancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Abraham Morgentaler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Men's Health Boston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ravi Kacker, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Men's Health Boston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Men's Health Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chestnut Hill</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheng S, Rhee EP, Larson MG, Lewis GD, McCabe EL, Shen D, Palma MJ, Roberts LD, Dejam A, Souza AL, Deik AA, Magnusson M, Fox CS, O'Donnell CJ, Vasan RS, Melander O, Clish CB, Gerszten RE, Wang TJ. Metabolite profiling identifies pathways associated with metabolic risk in humans. Circulation. 2012 May 8;125(18):2222-31. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.067827. Epub 2012 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22496159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang TJ, Larson MG, Vasan RS, Cheng S, Rhee EP, McCabe E, Lewis GD, Fox CS, Jacques PF, Fernandez C, O'Donnell CJ, Carr SA, Mootha VK, Florez JC, Souza A, Melander O, Clish CB, Gerszten RE. Metabolite profiles and the risk of developing diabetes. Nat Med. 2011 Apr;17(4):448-53. doi: 10.1038/nm.2307. Epub 2011 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>21423183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rhee EP, Cheng S, Larson MG, Walford GA, Lewis GD, McCabe E, Yang E, Farrell L, Fox CS, O'Donnell CJ, Carr SA, Vasan RS, Florez JC, Clish CB, Wang TJ, Gerszten RE. Lipid profiling identifies a triacylglycerol signature of insulin resistance and improves diabetes prediction in humans. J Clin Invest. 2011 Apr;121(4):1402-11. doi: 10.1172/JCI44442. Epub 2011 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21403394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kapoor D, Goodwin E, Channer KS, Jones TH. Testosterone replacement therapy improves insulin resistance, glycaemic control, visceral adiposity and hypercholesterolaemia in hypogonadal men with type 2 diabetes. Eur J Endocrinol. 2006 Jun;154(6):899-906.</citation>
    <PMID>16728551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heufelder AE, Saad F, Bunck MC, Gooren L. Fifty-two-week treatment with diet and exercise plus transdermal testosterone reverses the metabolic syndrome and improves glycemic control in men with newly diagnosed type 2 diabetes and subnormal plasma testosterone. J Androl. 2009 Nov-Dec;30(6):726-33. doi: 10.2164/jandrol.108.007005. Epub 2009 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19578132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 13, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 13, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 16, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypogonadism</keyword>
  <keyword>Testosterone Deficiency</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

