<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01962506</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COPACS13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01962506</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnostic Utility of Copeptin in Addition to High-sensitivity Cardiac Troponin for the Early Diagnosis of NSTE-ACS</brief_title>
  <acronym>COPACS</acronym>
  <official_title>Diagnostic Utility of Copeptin in Addition to High-sensitivity Cardiac Troponin for the Early Diagnosis of Non-ST-Elevation Acute Coronary Syndromes - The COPACS Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>G. d'Annunzio University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>G. d'Annunzio University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rapid and reliable exclusion of acute myocardial infarction (AMI) during an emergency
      department (ED) triage is a major unmet clinical need. We aimed at verifying the
      non-inferiority of a single-sampling strategy of hs-cTn and copeptin compared with the dual
      hs-cTn sampling for the early diagnosis of Non-ST-Elevation Acute Coronary Syndromes
      (NSTE-ACS) versus Non Coronary Chest Pain (NCCP) in a selected cohort of consecutive patients
      admitted at the Emergency Department.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The evaluation of chest pain patients in the emergency department remains a costly and
      difficult challenge, because a large proportion of them do not suffer from an acute coronary
      syndrome (ACS). The adequate ruling out of ACS in patients with chest pain is crucial, as the
      erroneous discharge of a patient with ACS is associated with a high risk of cardiac events.
      Rapid assessment of these patients is critical to direct further diagnostic and therapeutic
      strategies. Electrocardiography (ECG) and cardiac troponin (cTn) are the current diagnostic
      cornerstones and complement clinical assessment in current AMI guidelines1. They allow to
      rule in an acute myocardial infarction (AMI) within the first 3 hours after presentation in
      the majority of patients and offer the opportunity to initiate appropriate, evidence-based
      treatment. The vast majority of patients presenting to the Emergency Department (ED) with
      suspected AMI, however, finally prove not to have AMI. The current process of ruling out AMI
      is time-consuming and expensive. One fourth to one-third of patients with AMI present without
      significant ECG changes indicative of acute ischemia; therefore, the ECG is of little help to
      rule out AMI, especially in the setting of non-ST elevation ACS (NSTE-ACS). High-sensitivity
      (hs)-cTn assays have been developed recently, enabling measurements of concentrations that
      are ∼10-fold lower than those previously measurable. Recent studies have confirmed the
      increased accuracy of these high-sensitivity assays compared with conventional assays in the
      early detection of AMI and in the safely ruling in or out of coronary causes of chest pain.
      However, concerns have been raised about a possible specificity deficit with these new
      assays. In addition, a second measurement of hs-cTn may be warranted in order to increase the
      accuracy of the assay.

      Copeptin, the C-terminal part of the vasopressin pro-hormone, and a marker of acute
      endogenous stress, has been demonstrated to be useful for a more rapid ruling out of acute
      myocardial infarction. Current evidence for the diagnostic validity and performance of a
      combination of high sensitivity-cardiac troponin and copeptin is limited and controversial. A
      Bayesian probabilistic approach is likely to be the correct way to evaluate the possible
      incremental value of copeptin in the detection of ACS. Thus, we aim at prospectively
      evaluating the diagnostic accuracy of copeptin, hs-cTn, CK-MB and myoglobin, alone or in
      combination with hs-cTn, for the early diagnosis and ruling out of Non-ST-Elevation (NSTE)
      ACS versus non-cardiac causes of chest pain in a selected cohort of Emergency Department (ED)
      chest pain patients according to their pre-test probability, as assessed through a
      combination of two validated clinical risk score systems (i.e. Chest Pain Score and TIMI Risk
      Score).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-inferiority of a single-sampling strategy of hs-cTn and copeptin compared with the dual hs-cTn sampling for the early diagnosis of NSTE-ACS in a selected cohort of consecutive patients admitted at the Emergency Department.</measure>
    <time_frame>On admission to the Emergency Department</time_frame>
    <description>We aimed at verifying the hypothesis that diagnostic efficiency of the combination of copeptin and hs-cTn on admission would be non-inferior with respect to the 3 hours interval hs-cTn serial sampling for the early diagnosis or ruling out of NSTE-ACS versus non cardiac chest pain in a selected cohort of consecutive ED chest pain patients. According to current international guidelines we selected a 20% difference between serial hscTn levels to establish the diagnosis of myocardial infarction, since the change represented twice the recommended maximum imprecision (a coefficient of variation of 10%).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Chest Pain</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients admitted to the Emergency Department.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chest pain duration &gt; 5 minutes at rest or upon minimal exertion

          -  Chest pain onset &lt; 6 hours

          -  Non-traumatic chest pain

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cardiac arrest

          -  STEMI

          -  New left bundle branch block
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fabrizio Ricci</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Cardiology and Center of Excellence on Aging, &quot;G. D'Annunzio&quot; University, Chieti, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fabrizio Ricci</last_name>
    <phone>+393661088684</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Clinicizzato SS. Annunziata</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chieti</city>
        <zip>66100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>G. d'Annunzio University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fabrizio Ricci, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Fabrizio Ricci, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chest pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Copeptin</keyword>
  <keyword>High-sensitivity cardiac troponin</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-ST-Elevation (NSTE) - ACS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chest Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Insipidus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arginine Vasopressin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

