<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01967680</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S-20130025</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01967680</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-sedation Versus Sedation With a Daily Wake-up Trial in Critically Ill Patients Receiving Mechanical Ventilation</brief_title>
  <acronym>NONSEDA</acronym>
  <official_title>Non-sedation Versus Sedation With a Daily Wake-up Trial in Critically Ill Patients Receiving Mechanical Ventilation. The NONSEDA-trial. An Investigator-initiated, Randomised, Clinical, Parallel-group, Multinational, Superiority Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Palle Toft</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Danish Medical Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aase and Ejnar Danielsens Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Odense University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Every year 30,000 Danish patients are admitted to Intensive Care Units (ICU),
      accounting for 2-3% of all patients in hospital and 30% of the yearly hospital expenditure.
      The mortality in the ICU is 12.7 % and the 30-day mortality is 21.2 % according to the
      national Danish Intensive Care Database. Through many years, the standard care has been to
      use continuous sedation of critically ill patients during me-chanical ventilation. However,
      recent research indicates that it is beneficial to reduce the sedation level in these
      patients. A randomised trial found that continuous sedation with a daily wake-up trial
      compared to continuous sedation reduced the time on me-chanical ventilation and the length of
      stay in the intensive care unit. Further, a ran-domised trial comparing continuous sedation
      with a daily wake-up trial to no sedation found that patients in the non-sedated group needed
      mechanical ventilation for a shorter time and had a shorter length of stay in the ICU and in
      the hospital. The trial also indicated a beneficial effect on mortality, however the trial
      was not a priori de-signed or powered with respect to mortality. No randomised trial has been
      published comparing sedation with no sedation, a priori powered to have all-cause mortality
      as primary outcome.

      Objective: To assess the benefits and harms of non-sedation versus sedation with a daily
      wake-up trial in critically ill patients in ICU.

      Design: The NONSEDA trial is an investigator-initiated, randomised, clinical, parallel-group,
      multinational, superiority trial designed to include 700 patients from at least six ICUs in
      Denmark, Norway and Sweden.

      Inclusion criteria: Mechanically ventilated patients with expected duration of me-chanical
      ventilation &gt; 24 hours.

      Exclusion criteria: non-intubated patients, patients with severe head trauma, coma at
      admission or status epilepticus, patients treated with therapeutic hypothermia, patients with
      PaO2/FiO2&lt;9 where sedation might be necessary to ensure sufficient oxygenation or place the
      patient in prone position.

      Experimental intervention: Non-sedation supplemented with pain management during mechanical
      ventilation.

      Control intervention: Sedation with a daily wake-up trial.

      The primary hypothesis is that non-sedation compared to sedation and a daily wake-up trial
      will reduce mortality.

      The secondary hypotheses are that non-sedation compared to sedation and a daily wake-up trial
      will:

        -  Reduce the incidence of a composite outcome of death, acute myocardial in-farction
           (AMI), stroke, pulmonary embolism and other thromboembolic events.

        -  Reduce the number of organ failures.

        -  Increase the days alive without mechanical ventilation.

        -  Increase the days alive outside the ICU.

        -  Increase the days alive outside the hospital.

      Outcomes: The primary outcome is all-cause mortality at 90 days. Secondary out-comes are time
      to death in the trial period, the frequency of the trombo-embolic com-plications, acute renal
      failure, days alive without mechanical ventilation, days alive outside the ICU and hospital.
      Explorative outcomes are mortality at 28 days, organ failure and coma-free, delirium-free
      days.

      Trial size: The investigators will include 700 participants (2 x 350) in order to detect or
      reject 25% relative risk reduction in mortality with a type I error risk of 5% and a type II
      error risk of 20% (power at 80%).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>All cause mortality at 90 days after randomization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days until death</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Days until death throughout the total observation period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular event</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants with a major cardiovascular outcome (acute myocardial infarction, cerebral infarction, cerebral hemorrhage, pulmonary embolus, deep vein thrombosis, other thrombo-embolic event) at 90 days after randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coma and deliriumfree days</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of coma- and delirium-free days (defined as RASS ≥ 3 and no positive CAM-ICU scorings the particular day) within 28 days from randomization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RIFLE-score</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Highest Rifle-score within 28 days from randomization (Rifle-categories: Rifle-R: Increase in serum creatinine x 1.5 from baseline OR urine output &lt; 0.5 mL/kg/hr x 6 h.
Rifle-I: Increase in serum creatinine x 2 from baseline OR urine output &lt; 0.5 mL/kg/hr x 12 h.
Rifle-F: Increase in serum creatinine x 3 from baseline OR urine output &lt; 0.3 mL/kg/hr x 24h OR creatinine ≥ 350μmol/L with acute rise ≥ 44 μmol/L in &lt; 24h)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days until discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Days until discharge from ICU (within 28 days from randomization).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days until the participant is without mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Days until the participant is without mechanical ventilation (within 28 days from randomization).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>All cause mortality at 28 days after randomisation.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Discharge fro ICU</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Days until discharge from the intensive care unit (within 90 days from randomization)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>End of mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Days until the participant is without without mechanical ventilation (within 90 days from randomization)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Discharge from hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Days until discharge from the hospital (within 90 days from randomization).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of organ failures</measure>
    <time_frame>ICU-admission</time_frame>
    <description>Organ failure when the patient is discharged from the ICU.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Accidental extubation</measure>
    <time_frame>ICU-admission</time_frame>
    <description>Number of accidental extubations requiring re-intubation within 1 hour</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Accidental removal of cental venous line</measure>
    <time_frame>ICU-admission</time_frame>
    <description>Number of accidental removals of central venous lines, requiring re-insertion within 4 hours</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygenation</measure>
    <time_frame>During ventilator treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Worst oxygenation status measured by
highest fraction of oxygen in inspired air (FiO2)
worst paO2/FiO2-ratio registered daily</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>1-year survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year from randomisation</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients alive 1 year after randomisation in each group</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">700</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Illness</condition>
  <condition>Respiration, Artificial</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sedation with daily wake-up trial</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group is sedated with continuous infusion to Ramsay score 3-4. During daytime, the patient is awakened as the intravenous infusion of sedatives is discontinued. After a successful wake-up, the infusion of sedative is resumed, starting on half of the pre-wake-up dose. If the patient becomes uncomfortable or agitated during the awakening, sedation is resumed, again starting with half the dosage. The infusion of sedatives is then adjusted to Ramsey score 3-4.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-sedation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will not receive sedatives. Patients are thoroughly and repeatedly informed by the staff of where they are, what have happened, and what type of treatment they are going to receive.
Participants in the non-sedated group are awake and have a natural sleep rhythm. In case these patients develop and outward delirium, it is necessary to have a nurse or other caregiver at the bedside in order to calm the patient. Patients with delirium are treated with haloperidol according to the U.S. guidelines, 2002 and the Danish national guidelines.
If, despite these measures, it is necessary to sedate an agitated patient more than twice, or where sedation might be necessary to ensure sufficient oxygenation or prone position, the patient is sedated and treated like the control-group. Every day during the wake-up trial it is evaluated whether the patient is able to continue the intervention of non-sedation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Non-sedation for intubated, mechanically ventilated patients</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Non-sedation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Controlgroup, sedation with daily wake-up trial</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Sedation with daily wake-up trial</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Endotracheally intubated Expected time on ventilator &gt; 24 h. Age ≥ 18 years Informed
        consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Severe head trauma where therapeutic coma is indicated Therapeutic hypothermia where
        therapeutic coma is indicated Status epilepticus where therapeutic coma is indicated
        Patient has participated in the study before Patient is transferred from another ICU with
        length of stay &gt; 48 hours Patient is comatose at admission PaO2/FiO2 ≤ 9, if sedation is
        necessary for oxygenation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Palle Toft, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Odense University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hanne Tanghus Olsen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Svendborg Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helene K Nedergaard, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kolding Sygehus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Stroem, Postdoc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Odense University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sydvestjysk Sygehus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Esbjerg</city>
        <state>Region Of Southern Denmark</state>
        <zip>6700</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AArhus university Hospital, Noerrebrogade</name>
      <address>
        <city>AArhus</city>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kolding Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kolding</city>
        <zip>6000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Odense University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense</city>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Svendborg Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Svendborg</city>
        <zip>5600</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vestfold Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tonsberg</city>
        <zip>3103</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of North Norway</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tromsoe</city>
        <zip>9038</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Linkjøbing University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Linkoping</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strøm T, Martinussen T, Toft P. A protocol of no sedation for critically ill patients receiving mechanical ventilation: a randomised trial. Lancet. 2010 Feb 6;375(9713):475-80. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)62072-9. Epub 2010 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>20116842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 23, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Odense University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Palle Toft</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

