<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02834572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>473699-41</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02834572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Technology to Match Young Black Men and Transwomen Who Have Sex With Men or Transwomen to HIV Testing Options</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Technology to Match Young Black Men and Transwomen Who Have Sex With Men or Transwomen to HIV Testing Options</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York Blood Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York Blood Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Young Black men who have sex with men (MSM) and transwomen in the US are affected by HIV at
      severely disproportionate rates. A key component of HIV prevention for communities at risk is
      diagnosing HIV infections through regular HIV testing. A significant proportion of young
      Black MSM and transwomen have not tested in the prior year. This research study seeks to
      address low HIV testing rates among young Black MSM and transwomen by testing a brief
      Internet-based HIV testing intervention optimized for mobile devices. The intervention takes
      advantage of the variety of HIV testing options now available, including the HIV self
      testing, couples-based HIV counseling and testing and traditional clinic-based testing and
      will provide men and transwomen with a tailored recommendation of their optimal HIV testing
      approach. The investigators are conducting a pilot randomized study among young Black MSM and
      transwomen followed for 6 months to estimate the intervention's potential efficacy in
      increasing HIV testing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We are conducting a pilot study among 240 young Black MSM and transgender women randomized to
      the Intervention Arm (assessment and algorithm to deliver a tailored recommendation) or
      Control (assessment and standard HIV testing information) and followed for 6 months to
      estimate the intervention's potential efficacy in increasing HIV testing. After informed
      consent, participants are asked to provide contact information on the locator form. Then,
      participants complete a brief quantitative assessment including basic demographics, HIV
      testing history and other factors related to HIV testing. All participants, regardless of
      study arm, then receive information about each HIV testing method including how the tests are
      conducted (blood, oral sample), and availability of counseling and support. Participants then
      are randomized into 1 of the 2 study arms. A computer program will randomly assign each
      participant using randomly ordered block sizes of 4 and 6 and stratified by age (16-23, 24-29
      years) to balance groups.

      Participants assigned to the Intervention Arm will complete a brief quantitative assessment
      lasting approximately 2-3 minutes to assess those factors associated with HIV testing and
      thus are needed to complete the algorithm. They then receive the results of the HIV testing
      algorithm, presented as their personalized HIV testing approach. All participants will
      receive information on resources in New York City to test by all of these methods. The
      control participants are provided with the above information about each testing approach but
      without a recommended approach.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants reporting having an HIV test as assessed by questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported HIV test in the prior 3 months assessed by questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who are aware of HIV self-testing and couples based voluntary counseling and testing as assessed by questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported awareness of HIV self-testing and couples based voluntary counseling and testing assessed by questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of intervention participants recommended a self-test who use a self-test as assessed by questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported use of self test among those recommended a self test - Intervention participants only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of intervention participants recommended testing at a clinic who test at a clinic as assessed by questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported use of testing at a clinic among those recommended to test at a clinic - Intervention participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of intervention participants recommended couples testing who test using couples testing as assessed by questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported use of couples testing among those recommended to test using couples testing - Intervention only</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">236</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Testing</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All About Me</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>assessment and algorithm to provide participants with a tailored recommendation of their optimal HIV testing approach</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIV testing information</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>All About Me</intervention_name>
    <description>Assessment and algorithm to determine recommended HIV testing approach</description>
    <arm_group_label>All About Me</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>HIV testing information</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  male at birth;

          -  self-identify as Black, African American, Caribbean Black, African Black or
             multiethnic Black;

          -  able to read and respond in English;

          -  between 16-29 years of age;

          -  known to be HIV-infected;

          -  insertive or receptive anal intercourse with a man or transwoman in the last 12
             months;

          -  reside in the New York City metropolitan area

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  enrolled in any other HIV research study involving HIV testing

          -  participant in an HIV vaccine trial

          -  currently taking pre-exposure prophylaxis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>29 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beryl Koblin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NY Blood Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Blood Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 14, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York Blood Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Beryl Koblin, Ph, D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

