<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02833727</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-1359</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02833727</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Airway Inflammation and Disease Burden in Asthmatic Smokers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Airway Inflammation and Disease Burden in Moderate to Severe Asthmatic Smokers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Université de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Teva Pharmaceuticals USA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Université de Montréal</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim : To compare, among patients with an uncontrolled moderate to severe asthma, the blood
      eosinophil levels of smokers and non-smokers.

      Secondary aims: In uncontrolled moderate to severe asthmatic subjects, to compare between
      asthmatic smokers and non-smokers: sputum eosinophils counts, fractional exhaled nitric oxide
      (FeNO), pre and post bronchodilator Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) / Forced
      vital capacity (FVC), Asthma-related quality of life, asthma exacerbations during the year
      preceding enrolment in the study, Medical direct and indirect costs related to asthma during
      the year preceding enrolment in the study, and adherence to asthma treatment during the year
      preceding enrolment in the study.

      Methods: Cross sectional observational study. Never-smoker and smoker asthmatics treated with
      at least 2 controller medications with a smoking history ≥10 pack/year with a ACQ score ≥ 1.5
      points will be identified in the database RESP. Their clinical data will be matched to the
      Régie de l'assurance médicale du Quebec (RAMQ) and Maintenance et exploitation des données
      pour l'étude de la clientèle hospitalière (MED-ECHO) administrative databases and reMed (data
      on medications for patients with private health insurance) in order to access to data on
      medical services, hospitalisations and medications delivered by pharmacies. T
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim : To compare, among patients with an uncontrolled moderate to severe asthma, the blood
      eosinophil levels of smokers and non-smokers.

      Hypothesis: Uncontrolled never-smoker asthmatics (NSA) will have a greater level of blood
      eosinophils than uncontrolled asthmatic smokers (AS) (difference in blood eosinophil count at
      least superior to 100 eosinophils per μL).

      Secondary aims: In uncontrolled moderate to severe asthmatic subjects, to compare between
      asthmatic smokers and non-smokers: sputum eosinophils counts, fractional exhaled nitric oxide
      (FeNO), pre and post bronchodilator FEV1 / Forced vital capacity (FVC), Asthma-related
      quality of life, asthma exacerbations during the year preceding enrolment in the study,
      Medical direct and indirect costs related to asthma during the year preceding enrolment in
      the study, and adherence to asthma treatment during the year preceding enrolment in the
      study.

      Methods: Cross sectional observational study. Never-smoker and smoker asthmatics treated with
      at least 2 controller medications with a smoking history ≥10 pack/year with a ACQ score ≥ 1.5
      points will be identified in the Quebec registry in respiratory health (RESP). Their clinical
      data will be matched to the &quot;Régie de l'assurance médicale du Quebec&quot; (RAMQ) and &quot;Maintenance
      et exploitation des données pour l'étude de la clientèle hospitalière&quot; (MED-ECHO)
      administrative databases and database on medications dispensed in community pharmacies to
      patients with private drug insurance (reMed) in order to access to data on medical services,
      hospitalisations and medications delivered by pharmacies. The subjects identified in the RESP
      database fulfilling the definition of moderate to severe uncontrolled asthma will be
      contacted. The Asthma Control Questionnaire (ACQ) will be administered to the subjects over
      the phone. Subjects with an ACQ score ≥ 1.5 points will be invited to come to the research
      center of Sacré-Coeur Hospital. During a unique visit at the Hospital du Sacré-Coeur de
      Montréal, after signature of the consent form, 80 asthmatic smokers and 80 non-smoker
      asthmatic subjects will be asked to complete questionnaires regarding asthma control (if the
      delay between telephone interview and visit to the hospital exceed one week), quality of
      life, and asthma impact on daily activities. FeNO will be measured first. They will then
      perform spirometry. Sputum induction will be performed to obtain sputum cell counts. Blood
      will be drawn to obtain blood eosinophil count and serum cotinine. We will be able to compare
      between asthmatic smokers and non-smoker asthmatics: blood eosinophil counts, sputum
      eosinophils counts, FeNO, pre and post bronchodilator FEV1 / FVC, asthma-related quality of
      life, asthma exacerbations during the year preceding enrolment in the study, Medical direct
      and indirect costs related to asthma during the year preceding enrolment in the study, and
      adherence to asthma treatment during the year preceding enrolment in the study.

      Significance: Anti-interleukin 5 have been shown to be very effective in reducing asthma
      exacerbations in asthmatic subjects with eosinophilic inflammation with frequent asthma
      exacerbations. However, smokers have been excluded from these studies. It will be important
      to determine the burden of asthma in this group of subjects in term of healthcare utilization
      and productivity at work, in order to evaluate whether or not they may benefit from this type
      of medication. If we show that the direct and indirect cost related to asthma are higher in
      asthmatic smokers than non-smokers, it will be even more important to characterize the airway
      inflammation of this group of subjects in order to determine whether they are likely
      candidates to receive new biologic agents in order to improve asthma control, decrease their
      healthcare utilization and improve their productivity at work.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>blood eosinophil count</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sputum eosinophil count</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fractional exhaled nitric oxide (FeNO)</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FEV1</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma-related quality of life score</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>We will use the Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire (AQLQ). This is a 32-item, self-administered, disease-specific quality of life questionnaire that evaluates asthma quality of life across 4 domains: activity limitation, symptoms, emotional distress, and environmental stimuli. Each item is rated on a 7-point scale (1=maximal impairment, 7=no impairment) to yield a mean score out of 7.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma exacerbations</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical direct and indirect costs related to asthma</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to asthma treatment measured by the proportion of days covered (PDC)(%)</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence to controller medications will be measured with the proportion of days covered (PDC), a widely used measure of adherence based on prescription claims data. The PDC will be defined as the sum of the duration of all prescriptions of the medication under study filled in the year preceding the visit, divided by 365 days, expressed in percent. The PDC will be estimated using prescription refills data obtained from the RAMQ and reMed databases in the year preceding enrolment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asthmatic smokers (AS)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Asthmatics will fulfill the following definition of asthma: reversible airflow obstruction and/or a provocative concentration of methacholine inducing a 20% fall in FEV1 (PC20) &lt; 8 mg/ml with a diagnosis of asthma made by a respirologist.
Smokers or ex smokers will be defined by a smoking history of ≥ 10 pack/year.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asthmatic non-smokers (ANS)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Asthmatics will fulfill the following definition of asthma: reversible airflow obstruction and/or a PC20 &lt; 8 mg/ml with a diagnosis of asthma made by a respirologist.
Never smokers will have a life-long history without smoking.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smoking</intervention_name>
    <description>Smoking equal or greater than 10 pack/years; never smokers: lifelong history without smoking.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Asthmatic smokers (AS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Asthmatic non-smokers (ANS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Never-smoker and smoker asthmatics treated with at least 2 controller medications with a
        smoking history ≥10 pack/year with a ACQ score ≥ 1.5 points
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation to the RESP Database.

          -  Never-smoker and smoker asthmatics (smoking history ≥10 pack/year)

          -  Treatment with at least 2 controller medications

          -  ACQ score ≥ 1.5 points will be identified in the database RESP.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Catherine Lemiere, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CIUSS du nord de l'île de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Simone Chaboillez, RT</last_name>
    <phone>514 338 2222</phone>
    <phone_ext>3437</phone_ext>
    <email>s-chaboillez@crhsc.rtss.qc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Catherine Lemiere, MD</last_name>
    <phone>514 338 2222</phone>
    <phone_ext>3437</phone_ext>
    <email>catherine.lemiere@umontreal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital du Sacré-Coeur de Montréal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4J 1C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Simone Chaboillez, RT</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catherine Lemiere, MD,MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tan NC, Nguyen HV, Lye WK, Sankari U, Nadkarni NV. Trends and predictors of asthma costs: results from a 10-year longitudinal study. Eur Respir J. 2016 Mar;47(3):801-9. doi: 10.1183/13993003.00188-2015. Epub 2015 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>26647437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chaudhuri R, Livingston E, McMahon AD, Thomson L, Borland W, Thomson NC. Cigarette smoking impairs the therapeutic response to oral corticosteroids in chronic asthma. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2003 Dec 1;168(11):1308-11. Epub 2003 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>12893649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sunyer J, Springer G, Jamieson B, Conover C, Detels R, Rinaldo C, Margolick J, Muñoz A. Effects of asthma on cell components in peripheral blood among smokers and non-smokers. Clin Exp Allergy. 2003 Nov;33(11):1500-5.</citation>
    <PMID>14616860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Université de Montréal</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Catherine Lemiere</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD,MSc</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>asthma; smoking; Eosinophils; health care costs</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

