<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02833324</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00088864</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02833324</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fitbit for Postoperative Ambulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Can a Fitbit (a Mobile Tracking Device) Increase Ambulation of Colorectal Surgical Patients in the Postoperative Period?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial will investigate whether using reminder alarms with a wireless activity tracking
      device (Fitbit) will increase daily ambulation in individuals who have just had colorectal
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Early mobilization after surgery has been shown to reduce recovery time, incidence of venous
      thromboembolism, length of hospital stay and both pulmonary and general post-operative
      complications. Ambulation is also a main tenant of a fast-track recovery protocol known as
      Enhanced Recovery After Surgery (ERAS), which is commonly used among colorectal surgical
      practices and being implanted across other surgical practices. Despite evidence supporting
      its benefit, early ambulation has been identified as the one of the most difficult clinical
      interventions to enforce and to measure.

      The primary objective of this trial is to investigate whether the use of wireless activity
      tracking device (Fitbit) with 5 daily reminder alarms will increase daily ambulation on
      postoperative day 0 until post operative day 9 or hospital discharge (whichever occurs
      first). Secondary objectives include evaluating the effect of Fitbit as a motivating factor
      on the frequency of postoperative ileus, time to return of bowel function, number of venous
      thromboembolism (VTE), pneumonia (PNA) and other pulmonary complications, number of code
      Medical Emergency Team (MET) alerts, and overall cost saving.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of number of steps taken between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 days (postoperative day 0 through postoperative day 9)</time_frame>
    <description>The number of steps taken by each participant will be measured by a Fitbit, which is a wireless activity tracking device. The number of steps taken will be compared between the study arm receiving the ambulation reminder alarms and the study arm without reminder alarms. The Fitbit is commercially available and is worn on the wrist. Data will be collected from the Fitbit wirelessly using a dedicated study data collection phone and linked with an anonymized patient identifier. Data collection phones attached to chargers will be placed in patient rooms within range of the hospital bed to enable automatic wireless data collection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of time to first ambulation between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 days (postoperative day 0 through postoperative day 9)</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of time from administration of the Fitbit device until first postoperative ambulation will be compared between the study arm receiving the ambulation reminder alarms and the study arm without reminder alarms. Participants cleared to ambulate will be given a package containing the Fitbit device, paired study phone, and chargers while in the Post Anesthesia Care Unit (PACU). Participants will be instructed to equip the device prior to discharge from the PACU.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of incidence of prolonged postoperative ileus between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 days (postoperative day 0 through postoperative day 9)</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of prolonged postoperative ileus during hospitalization will be compared between the study arm receiving the ambulation reminder alarms and the study arm without reminder alarms.
For this study, postoperative ileus is defined as the interval from surgery until there is passage of flatus or stool and an oral diet is tolerated. Prolonged postoperative ileus is determined to be present if two or more of the following criteria are met on or after postoperative day 4, without prior resolution of postoperative ileus:
Nausea or vomiting
The inability to tolerate an oral diet over 24 hours
Absence of flatus over 24 hours
Abdominal distension
Radiologic confirmation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of incidence of pulmonary complications between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 days (postoperative day 0 through postoperative day 9)</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of pulmonary complications during hospitalization will be compared between the study arm receiving the ambulation reminder alarms and the study arm without reminder alarms. For this study, pulmonary complications are defined as respiratory failure requiring mechanical ventilation, pneumonia, atelectasis requiring bronchoscopic intervention, or pneumothorax or pleural effusion requiring percutaneous intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of incidence of venous thromboembolism between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 days (postoperative day 0 through postoperative day 9)</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of venous thromboembolism occurring during hospitalization will be compared between the study arm receiving the ambulation reminder alarms and the study arm without reminder alarms. Venous thromboembolism is when a blood clot (thrombus) forms within a vein and includes deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of length of postoperative hospital stay between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 days (postoperative day 0 through postoperative day 9)</time_frame>
    <description>The length of hospitalization following surgery will be compared between the study arm receiving the ambulation reminder alarms and the study arm without reminder alarms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Care</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit with ambulation reminder alarms</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants who are postoperative for colorectal surgery will wear a Fitbit (a wireless activity tracking device) to count steps taken during their postoperative hospitalization. In addition to being educated on the importance of postoperative ambulation, this arm will have 5 alarms every day reminding them to ambulate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit without ambulation reminder alarms</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants who are postoperative for colorectal surgery will wear a Fitbit (a wireless activity tracking device) to count steps taken during their postoperative hospitalization. Participants will be educated on the importance of postoperative ambulation but will not have ambulation reminder alarms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education regarding ambulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The participants will be educated on the importance of postoperative ambulation during the recovery period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit with ambulation reminder alarms</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit without ambulation reminder alarms</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ambulation reminder alarms</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the intervention arm will receive 5 daily alarms to prompt them to ambulate. Alarms will be set to ring at 9am, 11am, 2pm, 5pm and 9pm. The Fitbit will be worn from the day of surgery (postoperative day 0) through postoperative day 9 or hospital discharge, whichever occurs first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit with ambulation reminder alarms</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fitbit</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants who are postoperative for colorectal surgery, who have been cleared to ambulate during recover, will be equipped with an off-the-shelf Fitbit device (a wireless activity tracking device) which will record steps taken while the participant is hospitalized. The Fitbit will be worn from the day of surgery (postoperative day 0) through postoperative day 9 or hospital discharge, whichever occurs first.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit with ambulation reminder alarms</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit without ambulation reminder alarms</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Undergoing an elective surgical procedure in colorectal services at Emory University
             Hospital

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Post-surgical admission into the intensive care unit (ICU)

          -  Have an open abdomen due to surgical complications

          -  Wound Vacuum Assisted Closure (VAC) dependent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick S Sullivan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Patrick Sean Sullivan MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Postoperative Period</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgery</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

