<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02831621</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14/17/205</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02831621</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise and Ectopic Fat Deposition</brief_title>
  <acronym>ectofat</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Diet Plus Exercise Versus Diet Alone on the Reduction of Ectopic Fat Deposition in Adults With Overweight</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universiteit Antwerpen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universiteit Antwerpen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Excess ectopic fat deposition is associated with development of cardiovascular and metabolic
      diseases. This study investigates how lifestyle interventions can have an effect on different
      sites of ectopic fat deposition and cardiovascular or metabolic factors. Moreover, the
      clinical and economic value of exercise to supplement a hypocaloric diet is investigated.

      Endocrinologists of the University Hospital of Antwerp, Belgium, will be recruiting women
      during consultations. Also, recruitment posters will be used in the University Hospital of
      Antwerp and the University of Antwerp. Potential participants meeting all a priori set
      inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomized by minimization method to a hypocaloric
      diet group (usual care) or a group of hypocaloric diet combined with physical fitness
      training. Both groups will undergo an intake procedure in which personal goals are set and
      barriers to changes in behavior will be discussed. Ectopic fat deposition will be measured by
      imaging techniques after three and six months of intervention. A post-intervention follow-up
      period of six months is planned. Based on the known relationship between ectopic fat and
      cardiovascular outcomes, the short term study results will then be extrapolated to an
      estimation of the reduction of cardiovascular events.

      The following clinical outcomes will be presented: change in ectopic fat in the abdomen
      (visceral fat), the liver (intra hepatic lipids), skeletal muscle (intra myocellular lipids),
      heart (epicardial fat) after a dietary or combined (diet+physical activity) intervention. The
      impact of supervised exercise in addition to diet will be expressed in projected healthcare
      costs and quality adjusted life years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>hepatic lipid content</measure>
    <time_frame>start - 3 months - 6 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The hepatic lipid content will also be measured by a 3T MRI scanner (SIEMENS MAGNETOM Prisma, Siemens Healthcare AG, Zürich, Germany). The body coil will be positioned around the chest, as the subjects lay supine. MRI data will be acquired using STEAM, with the parameter setting as follows: 3.0 cm³ voxel in the right liver, TR/TE 3000/20 ms, and no water suppression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>intra myocellular lipids</measure>
    <time_frame>start - 3 months - 6 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>1H-magnetic resonance spectroscopy (1H-MRs) will be used to quantify lipid levels in the tibialis anterior (slow-twitch) muscle of each subject.The right calf of each subject will be positioned near isocenter surrounded by a body coil within a 3T MRI scanner (SIEMENS MAGNETOM Prisma, Siemens Healthcare AG, Zürich, Germany) following manual shimming on the volume of interest to ensure maximum ﬁeld homogeneity. The 1H-MRs data will be acquired by a single-voxel Point-Resolved Spectroscopy (PRESS) acquisition. Imaging parameters will be set as follows; repetition time (TR)/echotime (TE) 2000/33 ms, voxel size 15 mm³, and weak water suppression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pericardial and epicardial fat</measure>
    <time_frame>start - 3 months - 6 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Multislice ECG-triggered CT will be used to measure pericardial and epicardial fat areas. All scans will be performed at end-diastole and slice thickness of 2.5 mm. No contrast liquid will be used. Data will be analyzed using the corresponding workstation (GE, AW Volumeshare 2).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>visceral fat</measure>
    <time_frame>start - 3 months - 6 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>A single slice CT of the abdomen will be used to evaluate cross-sectional abdominal visceral adipose tissue areas at the L4-L5 region. The abdominal fat mass and its distribution in visceral adipose tissue (VAT) and subcutaneous adipose tissue (SAT) will be calculated by area measurement on the corresponding CT slice.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>antropometric and metabolic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>start - (some at) 3 months - 6 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Every participant will undergo a standard metabolic screening at the beginning of the study. This will include a detailed interview and a clinical examination with anthropometry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>health economic evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>start - 3 months - 6 months - 9 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaires will be used</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>general lifestyle habits and well being: physical activity, quality of life, ...</measure>
    <time_frame>start - 3 months - 6 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess lifestyle habits (about physical activity and diet), motivational factors and quality of life, different questionnaires will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>diet (usual care)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will receive a hypocaloric diet based on the individual resting metabolic rate. Resting metabolic rate (RMR) will be estimated using the WHO formula or measured using indirect calorimetry. Total energy expenditure will be calculated by multiplying RMR with a physical activity level (PAL). The used physical activity level will be 1.3. A hypocaloric diet with an energy deficit of 500 kcal/day will be prescribed. Participants will see a skilled dietician two-weekly the first month and on a monthly basis the next five months to discuss problems and solutions or coping strategies. The first consultation will have a duration of 60 minutes, the next consultations will have a duration of approximately 30 minutes. Each visit, nutritional compliance will be recorded on a 0 to 10 numeric rating scale. The usual care group will be asked to continue with their normal physical activity during the six-month intervention period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>diet+exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For participants of this group, usual care will be supplemented with a prescribed exercise program. For this exercise program the participants will be referred to a local fitness club near home, free of charge. Aerobic training will be done at an intensity of 90-95% of the heart rate achieved at the RCP. Aerobic training will have a duration of 30 to 45 minutes, according to the training stage. Cardio training will be performed on different cardio devices and strength training will be done on isotonic strength training devices. Each training day, core stability training will be completed with four strength exercises for large muscle groups. Each exercise will be done in two sets of 15 repetitions with the goal to achieve better muscular strength endurance.
This combined training will be done individually during six months, three times/week.
In this study, an effort is made to reach a uniform manner of guidance to the physical activity program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lifestyle intervention (diet OR diet+exercise)</intervention_name>
    <description>diet or diet+fitness training</description>
    <arm_group_label>diet (usual care)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>diet+exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants should be willing to undergo a weight loss intervention and body weight
             must be stable during the past six months.

          -  There will be no upper eligibility criterion for body mass index (BMI) but BMI should
             be at least 27 kg/m².

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who have a clinical history of type 2 diabetes, prediabetes (with use of
             medication), or hypothyroidism will be excluded.

          -  when postmenopausal; Premenopausal state will be verified by hormonal data
             (follicle-stimulation hormone (FSH) &lt; 25 mU/ml and estradiol &gt; 20 pg/ml).

          -  Subjects will not be allowed when pregnancy is planned within 12 months

          -  when physical activity is not possible due to problems of the musculoskeletal system

          -  when changes in medication (e.g. beta blockers) are advised by an endocrinologist.

          -  when smoking

          -  when drinking more than two alcoholic consumptions/day or binge drinking
             (self-reported)

          -  when taking medication that influences body weight or metabolism (e.g. tricyclic
             antidepressants)

          -  Since all participants will undergo medical imaging, exclusion criteria related to MRI
             and CT scans are also applicable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>wendy hens</last_name>
    <email>wendy.hens@uantwerpen.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Antwerp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antwerp</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universiteit Antwerpen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wendy Hens</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>candidate PHD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>overweight</keyword>
  <keyword>ectopic fat</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiac Complexes, Premature</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

