<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02835495</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00033688</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R34DK108100</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02835495</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Living Partnerships to Prevent Diabetes in Veterans Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>HELP Vets</acronym>
  <official_title>The Healthy Living Partnerships to Prevent Diabetes in Veterans Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diabetes and obesity are both major public health concerns and the prevalence of diabetes is
      even higher in the patient population of the Veterans Administration. This planning project
      is designed to adapt a successful weight-loss program for delivery through an existing
      outpatient clinic to reach local Veterans at risk for developing diabetes. The information
      gathered as a part of this project will be used to plan a larger trial designed to improve
      the health of Veterans by offering them a diabetes prevention program through their usual
      source of healthcare.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Type II diabetes and its complications disproportionately affect the patient population
      served by the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA). Recent lifestyle interventions have
      demonstrated that weight-loss achieved through reductions in calorie intake and increases in
      physical activity can prevent or delay the onset of diabetes. The Healthy Living Partnerships
      to Prevent Diabetes (HELP PD), a community-based adaptation of the lifestyle intervention
      used in the Diabetes Prevention Program, achieved more than a 7% weight loss at 6 months.

      In HELP Vets, researchers will test the feasibility of further translating the HELP PD
      lifestyle intervention, tailored for use in the Veteran population, in the Kernersville
      Community-Based Outpatient Clinic operated by the VA. The investigators plan to recruit 50
      overweight or obese Veterans at high risk for developing diabetes from the existing patient
      population to participate in a 6-month weight loss intervention led by community health
      workers who are also Veterans. As VA outpatient clinics have the requisite infrastructure to
      identify, screen, and enroll participants and access to Veteran community health workers from
      within their patient populations, they are ideal potential homes for diabetes prevention
      programming. Data gathered during this planning grant will be used to develop a large-scale
      study to test implementing the HELP Vets intervention in a larger segment of the Veteran
      population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment of study participants</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the ability to recruit Veterans to participate in this pilot study, the proportion of Veterans screened who are eligible to participate and the proportion of eligible participants who agree to participate will be estimated. The rate of referrals to the program by providers in the local community-based outpatient clinic will also be monitored.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention of study participants</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the ability to retain Veterans in this pilot study, the percentage of participants who complete the study (attendance at the 6-month assessment visit) as a measure of overall study retention will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the Lifestyle Weight Loss Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of intervention sessions attended will be estimated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The means and standard deviations at baseline and 6 months and the correlation over time will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist Circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The means and standard deviations at baseline and 6 months and the correlation over time will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The means and standard deviations at baseline and 6 months and the correlation over time will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The means and standard deviations at baseline and 6 months and the correlation over time will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The means and standard deviations at baseline and 6 months and the correlation over time will be estimated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Pre-diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lifestyle Weight Loss</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Behavioral: HELP Vets Intervention
Lifestyle intervention consisting of 24 weekly group meetings led by a Veteran community health worker and 3 individual sessions with a nutritionist/diabetes educator</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Behavioral: Individual Education Program
Standard care consisting of 2 individual sessions with a nutritionist/diabetes educator and a monthly newsletter</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HELP Vets Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention involves a dietary weight loss program and an increase in caloric expenditure through moderate physical activity. The primary treatment objectives for the weight loss component of the intervention will be to decrease caloric intake in a nutritionally sound manner so as to produce a weight loss of approximately 0.3 kg per week for a total weight loss of 5-7%. The primary objective for the physical activity component of the intervention will be to promote an increase in home-based energy expenditure to an eventual goal of 180 min/week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lifestyle Weight Loss</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Individual Education Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive two individual sessions with a nutritionist during the first 3 months. In these sessions, the nutritionist will cover basic aspects of healthy eating and activity to support weight loss, discuss existing community resources and increased physical activity and weight loss. These participants will also receive a monthly newsletter on topics related to healthy lifestyle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI 25-40 kg/m2

          -  Evidence of Pre-Diabetes: all participants will be required to qualify based on
             evidence of prediabetes from fasting plasma glucose, oral glucose tolerance test, or
             hemoglobin (HbA1c) taken in the three months.

          -  The appropriate ranges for each test are

          -  HbAlc: 5.7 to 6.4%

          -  Fasting Plasma Glucose: 95-125 mg/dL

          -  Oral Glucose Tolerance Test: 140-200 mg/dL.

          -  Blood measures will be collected from the medical record

          -  Prospective participants must be willing to accept randomization to either the
             lifestyle intervention or the enhanced usual care condition.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently involved in a supervised program for weight loss

          -  Clinical history of diabetes

          -  Clinical history of cardiovascular disease (CVD) occurring within the past 6 months,
             including myocardial infarction, angina, coronary revascularization, stroke, TIA,
             carotid revascularization, peripheral arterial disease, and congestive heart failure

          -  Uncontrolled high blood pressure (BP &gt; 160/100) Potential participants can be
             re-screened after controlled

          -  Pregnancy, planning pregnancy and breast feeding (self-report) during screening; Other
             chronic disease likely to limit lifespan to less than 2-3 years, including any cancer
             requiring treatment in past 5 years except non-melanoma skin cancer

          -  Chronic use of medicine known to significantly affect glucose metabolism (e.g.,
             corticosteroids, protease inhibitors)

          -  Other conditions/criteria likely to interfere with participation and acceptance of
             randomized assignment, including the following: inability/unwillingness to give
             informed consent, another household member already randomized to HELP Vets, major
             psychiatric or cognitive problems (schizophrenia, dementia, self-reported active
             illegal substance or alcohol abuse), participation in another research study that
             would interfere with HELP Vets.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mara Z Vitolins, DrPH MPH RDN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Caroline S Blackwell, BS, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>(336) 713-4061</phone>
    <email>cblackwe@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mariela N Arias, BS</last_name>
    <phone>(336) 716-9470</phone>
    <email>mnarias@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mariela Arias</last_name>
      <phone>336-716-9470</phone>
      <email>mnarias@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mara Z Vitolins, DrPH MPH RDN</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mara Z. Vitolins</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prediabetic State</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Intolerance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

