<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02830594</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16099</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2016-00686</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>16099</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02830594</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pembrolizumab and Palliative Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Metastatic Esophagus, Stomach, or Gastroesophageal Junction Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combining Pembrolizumab and Palliative Radiotherapy in Gastroesophageal Cancer to Enhance Anti-Tumor T Cell Response and Augment the Abscopal Effect</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>City of Hope Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>City of Hope Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well pembrolizumab and palliative radiation therapy works in
      treating patients with esophagus, stomach, or gastroesophageal junction cancer that has
      spread to other parts of the body. Monoclonal antibodies, such as pembrolizumab, may
      interfere with the ability of tumor cells to grow and spread. Palliative radiation therapy,
      such as external beam radiation therapy, uses high energy beams to treat symptoms that are
      caused by tumors. Giving pembrolizumab together with palliative radiation therapy may work
      better in treating patients with esophagus, stomach, or gastroesophageal junction cancer that
      has spread to other parts of the body.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES I. To establish that the combination of pembrolizumab and traditional
      external beam multifractionated radiation therapy (RT) to the primary tumor or a single
      target metastatic site of patients with metastatic gastric, esophageal, and/or
      gastroesophageal junction (GEJ) cancers will lead to an increase in tumor infiltrating
      cytotoxic T-cells and circulating cytotoxic T cells and a reduction in immunosuppressive
      regulatory T cells (Tregs) and myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSCs) in metastatic sites.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To establish that the combination of pembrolizumab and RT is feasible in the patient
      population and evaluate toxicities per National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity
      Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version (ver.) 4.03.

      II. To evaluate overall response rate (ORR) per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors
      (RECIST) 1.1 and immune related (ir)RECIST in this treatment population and correlate with
      tumor T-cell response.

      III. To evaluate progression-free (PFS) and overall survival (OS) in this treatment
      population.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To measure changes in whole genome serum micro ribonucleic acid (miRNA) signature before
      and after protocol therapy and correlate with tumor/immune/stromal cell miRNA expression
      profiling determined by deep sequencing.

      II. To measures changes in fecal and oral microbiomic diversity and correlative with ORR,
      PFS, and OS.

      III. To assess germline mutations in a panel of miRNA regulatory genes using the MiraDx assay
      as predictors of response and toxicity to pembrolizumab and RT.

      OUTLINE:

      INITIAL TREATMENT: Patients undergo palliative external beam RT daily. On day 1, patients
      undergo the first RT fraction and then receive pembrolizumab intravenously (IV) over 30
      minutes. Courses repeat every 3 weeks for up to 35 courses in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      SECOND PHASE: Patients who achieve a complete response, stop study treatment, and then
      experience radiographic disease progression may be eligible for the second phase at the
      discretion of the investigator if no cancer treatment was administered since the last dose of
      pembrolizumab and trial eligibility safety parameters are met. Patients receive pembrolizumab
      IV over 30 minutes on day 1. Courses repeat every 3 weeks for up to 17 courses in the absence
      of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days, every 6 weeks for 1 year,
      and then every 9 and 12 weeks for up to 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 5, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarkers: Comparison of Molecular Biomarkers and Disease Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 18 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Incidence of Adverse Events, Serious Adverse Events, and Treatment Delays</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 36 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR assessed by RECIST 1.1 and irRECIST</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 36 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be determined using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be determined using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of the Gastroesophageal Junction</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Malignant Neoplasm in the Stomach</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Esophageal Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, RT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INITIAL TREATMENT: Patients undergo palliative external beam RT daily. On day 1, patients undergo the first RT fraction and then receive pembrolizumab intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes. Courses repeat every 3 weeks for up to 35 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
SECOND PHASE: Patients who achieve a complete response, stop study treatment, and then experience radiographic disease progression may be eligible for the second phase at the discretion of the investigator if no cancer treatment was administered since the last dose of pembrolizumab and trial eligibility safety parameters are met. Patients receive pembrolizumab IV over 30 minutes on day 1. Courses repeat every 3 weeks for up to 17 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>External Beam Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo palliative external beam radiation therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, RT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Definitive Radiation Therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>EBRT</other_name>
    <other_name>External Beam Radiotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>External Beam RT</other_name>
    <other_name>external radiation</other_name>
    <other_name>External Radiation Therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>external-beam radiation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, RT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, RT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Keytruda</other_name>
    <other_name>Lambrolizumab</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-3475</other_name>
    <other_name>SCH 900475</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented informed consent of the participant

          -  Willing to provide tumor tissue amenable to ultrasound or computed tomography
             (CT)-guided biopsy for biomarker analyses

               -  Patients with malignant ascites are permitted to participate and provide ascites
                  samples for biomarker analyses

               -  Patients receiving radiation to a single metastatic site in which only the
                  primary tumor is accessible for biopsy by endoscopy will also be eligible

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 1

          -  Life expectancy of &gt;= 3 months

          -  Diagnosis of metastatic squamous cell carcinoma and/or adenocarcinoma of the
             esophagus, gastroesophageal junction, or stomach in need of palliative radiotherapy to
             the primary tumor or a single metastatic site for symptoms such as pain, dysphagia,
             and/or gastrointestinal bleeding

             * Patients with adenocarcinoma histology and known human epidermal growth factor
             receptor 2 (HER2) overexpressing disease are permitted to participate if they
             progressed or are intolerant of prior trastuzumab-containing therapy

          -  Measurable metastatic sites of disease outside of the target lesion undergoing
             palliative radiation based on RECIST 1.1 as assessed by the investigator

          -  Have no limits on prior lines of therapy or may be treatment-naive if in need of
             palliative RT provided the patient has not received prior anti-programmed cell death
             protein 1(PD-1), anti-programmed cell death 1 ligand 1 (PD-L1), or anti-programmed
             cell death 1 ligand 2 (PD-L2) therapy

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL

             * May receive transfusion to meet this goal

          -  Total serum bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) OR direct bilirubin =&lt; ULN
             if total bilirubin levels &gt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Albumin &gt;= 2.5 mg/dL

          -  Aspartate aminotransaminase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN OR
             =&lt; 5.0 x ULN if liver metastases present

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x ULN OR creatinine clearance (if measured or calculated per
             institutional standard) &gt;= 60 mL/min if creatinine levels &gt; 1.5 x ULN

               -  Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) can also be used in place of creatinine or
                  creatinine clearance (CrCl)

          -  If not receiving anticoagulants: international normalized ratio (INR) OR prothrombin
             (PT) =&lt; 1.5 x ULN; if on anticoagulant therapy: PT must be within therapeutic range of
             intended use of anticoagulants

          -  If not receiving anticoagulants: activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) =&lt; 1.5 x
             ULN; if on anticoagulant therapy: aPTT must be within therapeutic range of intended
             use of anticoagulants

          -  Negative urine or serum pregnancy test (female of childbearing potential only)

             * If the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy
             test will be required

          -  Female of childbearing potential: willing to use 2 methods of birth control or be
             surgically sterile, or abstain from heterosexual activity for the course of the study
             through 120 days after the last dose of study medication

             * Childbearing potential defined as not being surgically sterilized or have not been
             free from menses for &gt; 1 year

          -  Male: use an adequate method of contraception starting with the first dose of study
             therapy through 120 days after the last dose of study therapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-PD-L2 agents

          -  Prior radiation therapy within the field of the target lesion that in the opinion of
             the treating radiation oncologist would preclude further palliative radiation to a
             dose of 30 gray (Gy)

          -  Anti-cancer monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to study day 1 or who has
             not recovered (i.e., =&lt; grade 1 or at baseline) from adverse events due to agents
             administered more than 4 weeks earlier

          -  Chemotherapy, targeted small molecule therapy, or radiation therapy within 2 weeks
             prior to study day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., =&lt; grade 1 or at baseline) from
             adverse events due to a previously administered agent

               -  Note: Subjects with =&lt; grade 2 neuropathy are an exception to this criterion and
                  may qualify for the study

               -  If subject received major surgery, they must have recovered adequately from the
                  toxicity and/or complications from the intervention prior to starting therapy

          -  Live vaccine within 30 days of planned start of study therapy

             * Note: Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection are generally inactivated flu
             vaccines and are allowed; however intranasal influenza vaccines (e.g., Flu-Mist®) are
             live attenuated vaccines, and are not allowed

          -  Immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of trial treatment

          -  Investigational device within 4 weeks of the first dose of treatment

          -  Currently receiving an investigational agent

          -  About to undergo palliative radiation for a symptomatic central nervous system (CNS)
             metastasis

          -  Systemic steroid therapy

          -  Hypersensitivity to pembrolizumab or any of its excipients

          -  Diagnosis of immunodeficiency

          -  Active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2 years
             (i.e., with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs)

             * Replacement therapy (e.g., thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment

          -  Known history of, or any evidence of active, non-infectious pneumonitis

          -  Current active infection requiring systemic therapy

          -  Known history of active tuberculosis (TB), human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) 1/2,
             hepatitis B or hepatitis C

          -  Known additional malignancy that is progressing or requires active treatment

             * Exceptions include basal cell carcinoma of the skin or squamous cell carcinoma of
             the skin that has undergone potentially curative therapy or in situ cervical cancer

          -  Known active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis

             * Subjects with previously treated brain metastases may participate provided they are
             stable, have no evidence of new or enlarging brain metastases, and are not using
             steroids for at least 7 days prior to trial treatment; this exception does not include
             carcinomatous meningitis which is excluded regardless of clinical stability

          -  History or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality that
             might confound the results of the trial, interfere with the subject's participation
             for the full duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of the subject to
             participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator

          -  Known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with cooperation
             with the requirements of the trial

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding (female only)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Chao</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>City of Hope Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Chao</last_name>
      <phone>800-826-4673</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Chao</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

