<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02830295</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>University of Lleida</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02830295</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Basic Body Awareness Therapy (BBAT) in Patients Suffering From Fibromyalgia</brief_title>
  <acronym>BBAT</acronym>
  <official_title>Physiotherapy in Mental Health: A Clinical Trial of Basic Body Awareness Therapy in Patients Suffering From Fibromyalgia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cristina Bravo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitat de Lleida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomized trial of Basic Body Awareness Therapy (BBAT) is applied in fibromyalgia patients
      as compared with a control intervention consisting of treatment as an usual. Sessions of BBAT
      lasted 90 minutes each and took place twice a week for 5 weeks. The primary end point is a
      change in the Visual Analog Scale score and Body Awareness Rating Scale and the secondary end
      points include Hospital Anxiety Depression, State Trait Anxiety Inventory, Beck Depression
      Inventory and Short Form 36. All assessments will be repeated at post treatment, 12 weeks and
      24 weeks
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This work is a clinical trial of randomised and controlled groups. The hypothesis of study is
      that Basic Body Awareness Therapy applied in patients with fibromyalgia improves, more than
      usual treatment, the pain, normalization of postural pattern and movement, improve in
      psychologic state and improve of quality life.

      The study population will be selected followed the inclusion criteria of fibromyalgia, and
      will be selected in area of primary health center, the patients will be divided in 2 groups,
      control group and treatment group. The groups will be examined at the begin, at 1 month of
      the begin of treatment, in 3 months, 6 months and one year to evaluated the outcomes in long
      time.

      The dependence measurements will be Visual Analog Scale, Basic Body Awareness Rating Scale
      (BARS), SF-36, STAI A/R, BDI-II. The independence measurements will be demographic items:
      sex, age, country, level of studies, social status,..
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analog Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This scale evaluates the pain refered by patient with a scale from 0 to 10 being 10 the maximum pain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Anxiety Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>this scale evaluates the level of depression and anxiety with a questionary that score goes from 0 to 21, being 21 the maximum level of disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>this scale evaluates the level of depression with a questionary that scores from 0 to 63, being 63 the maximum level of depression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>State Trait Anxiety Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>this questionary evaluates the level of anxiety that scores from 0 to 60, being 60 the maximum level of anxiety</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form 36</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>this questionary evaluates the quality of life in different components. The score goes from 0 to 100 being 100 the best score for quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Basic Body Awareness Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Basic Body Awareness Therapy is usual therapy of physiotherapy in health mental in nord of europe. BBAT is based in twelve movements and massage that improve the movement quality of patient, also BBAT improves others movement qualities like biomechanical, physiologic, socio-cultural and existential.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>the patients which below receive the treatment as usual, according the clinic guidelines of Health government</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Basic Body Awareness Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Basic body awareness therapy is a health oriented and person-centred approach with focus on the patient's resources. This is a method in physiotherapy, where we search to promote movement quality in daily life through self-exploration and self-experience.BBAT conceives the person from the biomechanical, physiological, bio-psycho-social and existential aspects, using the movement quality as a witness of the link in between all these perspectives.It can be done individually or in groups, through different daily life movements: lying, sitting, standing, walking, pair movements, use of voice and massages. BBAT has validated and reliable assesment tools, as BARS and BAS-I</description>
    <arm_group_label>Basic Body Awareness Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BBAT (acronym)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients diagnosed of fibromyalgia according the American college of Rheumatology with
             6 months at least

          -  the patients have to stay in different position as lying, sitting and standing

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnancy

          -  suffering from another diseases that increase the pain or another specific diagnosis
             as rheumatic, heart disease and infectious disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bravo Cristina, PT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitat de Lleida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Consorci Sanitari de l'Anoia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Igualada</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08700</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gard G. Body awareness therapy for patients with fibromyalgia and chronic pain. Disabil Rehabil. 2005 Jun 17;27(12):725-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16012065</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Courtois I, Cools F, Calsius J. Effectiveness of body awareness interventions in fibromyalgia and chronic fatigue syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2015 Jan;19(1):35-56. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2014.04.003. Epub 2014 Apr 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25603742</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jones KD, King LA, Mist SD, Bennett RM, Horak FB. Postural control deficits in people with fibromyalgia: a pilot study. Arthritis Res Ther. 2011 Aug 2;13(4):R127. doi: 10.1186/ar3432.</citation>
    <PMID>21810264</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universitat de Lleida</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cristina Bravo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>body awareness therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>physical therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>movement therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

