<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02830919</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EF140</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02830919</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Study of Non-inferiority With Participants Diagnosed With Primary Knee OA (GLACIAL)</brief_title>
  <acronym>GLACIAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase III Clinical Study, Multicenter, Randomized, Single-blind, Parallel Groups for Safety Evaluation and Non-inferiority of Efficacy of Glucosamine Sulfate Plus Chondroitin Sulfate From Bovine Origin (Eurofarma Laboratorios S.A.) Versus Condroflex ® in the Treatment of Symptomatic Knee Primary Osteoarthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eurofarma Laboratorios S.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eurofarma Laboratorios S.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase III clinical study will be conducted in Brazilian research sites. It will be
      included in the study 314 participants diagnosed with primary knee OA according to the
      classification criteria of the ACR. After a washout period, the participants will be
      randomized to receive the combination of glucosamine sulfate + chondroitin sulfate of bovine
      origin of Eurofarma Laboratorios S.A. (N= 157) or the combination of glucosamine sulfate +
      chondroitin sulfate of Zodiac Pharmaceuticals S.A. Condroflex ® (N = 157). The treatment
      period of the study will be of 24 weeks. Each participant will perform seven visits to the
      research site. The main evaluations will be the improve of pain in the target knee by
      questionnaire Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) and
      quality of life by SF-12 questionnaire.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute change of pain WOMAC subscale score 24 weeks after initiation of treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute change the overall assessment of the disease by the investigator along treatment as measured by Visual Analog Scale from 0 to 100mm.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute change score of physical and mental components of the questionnaire SF-12 24 weeks after initiation of treatment compared to baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and profile of adverse events coded as MedDRA by treatment group.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of treatment discontinuation for adverse events and laboratory abnormalities.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">586</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis of Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glucosamine and chondroitin sulfate combination (Eurofarma)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Glucosamine sulfate 1500mg plus chondroitin sulfate 1200mg combination, manufactured by Eurofarma Laboratórios S.A., administered once a day for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glucosamine and chondroitin sulfate combination (Zodiac)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Glucosamine sulfate 1500mg plus chondroitin sulfate 1200mg combination, manufactured by Zodiac Produtos Farmacêuticos S.A. (Condroflex®), administered once a day for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucosamine and chondroitin sulfate combination (Eurofarma)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Glucosamine and chondroitin sulfate combination (Eurofarma)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucosamine and chondroitin sulfate combination (Zodic)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Glucosamine and chondroitin sulfate combination (Zodiac)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Male and female patients meeting all the following criteria will be enrolled in the study:

          1. Aged ≥ 40 years.

          2. Clinical and radiological diagnosis of primary (idiopathic) arthrosis of knee
             according to the criteria of the American College of Rheumatology (ACR).

          3. Kellgren and Lawrence radiological classification of degree 2 or 3 in x-ray of
             knee-target obtained in 3 months prior to the screening visit of the study.

          4. Presence of painful symptoms in the target knee in the last 3 months due to
             osteoarthritis.

          5. Visual analogue scale for evaluation of the pain of osteoarthritis of knee by the
             research participant in the screening visit ≥ 40 mm

          6. Average score ≥ 40 mm in the subscale of &quot;pain&quot; (from 0 to 100 mm) in the target knee
             of the questionnaire Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index
             (WOMAC), in the randomization visit.

          7. Functional class ACR from I to III.

          8. Signing the Informed Consent Form (ICF) before the performance of any study procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients meeting at least one of the following criteria will be excluded from the study:

          1. Diagnosis of septic arthritis, inflammatory arthritis (as rheumatoid arthritis), gout,
             pseudogout, Paget's disease, dysplasias or congenital joint abnormalities.

          2. Presence of inflammatory signals (edema, erythema or joint effusion) in the target
             knee, considered to be clinically significant by investigator.

          3. Serious target knee joint misalignment, defined by investigator.

          4. Predominantly patellofemoral Osteoarthritis in the target knee.

          5. Historical of severe trauma or surgery (including arthroscopy) in the target knee in
             the 6 months before the screening visit.

          6. Planned Surgery to the target knee

          7. Symptomatic Osteoarthritis of the ipsilateral hip.

          8. Use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory, dipyrone and opioid analgesics or narcotics
             from the screening visit, or a washout period for these medicines less than those
             defined by the Protocol, before the randomization visit .

          9. Oral Glucocorticoids, intravenously or intramuscularly in the 30 days prior to the
             screening visit.

         10. Intraarticular corticosteroid Injection and/or hyaluronic acid in the target knee in 6
             months prior to the screening visit.

         11. Use of the following drugs in the periods described below, before the screening visit:

               1. Diacerein, chloroquine or soybean and avocado unsaponifiables extracts in the
                  last 3 months.

               2. Duloxetine hydrochloride in the last 30 days.

               3. Glucosamine Sulphate and/or chondroitin sulfate in the last 6 months.

               4. Strontium ranelate for the past 6 months.

         12. Historical of allergy or intolerance to treatment of the study or to paracetamol.

         13. Physiotherapy or irregular practice of physical activity beginning in the 3 months
             prior to the screening visit.

         14. Diagnosis of fibromyalgia, collagenosis or significative vascular/neurologica diseases
             in lower limbs that may confuse the analysis of the study.

         15. Body mass index ≥ 40 kg/m2.

         16. Need to use cane, crutches or a walker.

         17. Presence of infectious hepatitis active or history of hepatitis medicinal products.

         18. Results of ALT, AST and total bilirubin and fractions above the upper limit of normal.

         19. Serum creatinine level above the upper limit of normal.

         20. Fasting blood glucose &gt; 110 mg/dL or glycated hemoglobin &gt; 6.5%.

         21. Use of anticoagulants.

         22. Consumption of alcohol more than one dose a day (women) or two doses a day (men).

         23. Presence of serious diseases or not controlled.

         24. Planned surgery to occur during the period of participation in the study.

         25. Presence of pregnancy or breastfeeding.

         26. Women of childbearing potential must agree to use highly effective contraception.

         27. Participation in a clinical trial protocol within the previous 12 months unless, at
             the investigator's discretion, his or her participation may imply a direct benefit for
             the participant.

         28. Presence of any condition which, at the investigator's discretion, may consider the
             participation of the patient inadequate for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Suely K Inoue, Pharm D</last_name>
    <phone>+551150908410</phone>
    <email>suely.inoue@eurofarma.com.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Cassiano O Berto, Pharm D</last_name>
    <phone>+551150908412</phone>
    <email>cassiano.berto@eurofarma.com.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Goiânia</city>
        <state>Goiás</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Maringá</city>
        <state>Paraná</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Curitiba</city>
        <state>PR</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis of knee</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucosamine sulfate</keyword>
  <keyword>Chondroitin sulfate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

