<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02830724</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>160131</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>16-C-0131</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02830724</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Administering Peripheral Blood Lymphocytes Transduced With a CD70-Binding Chimeric Antigen Receptor to People With CD70 Expressing Cancers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Study Administering Peripheral Blood Lymphocytes Transduced With a CD70-Binding Chimeric Antigen Receptor to Patients With CD70 Expressing Cancers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      In a new cancer therapy, researchers take a person s blood, select a certain white blood cell
      to grow in the lab, and then change the genes of these cells using a virus. The cells are
      then given back to the person. This is called gene transfer. For this study, researchers will
      modify the person s white blood cells with anti-CD70.

      Objectives:

      To see if a gene transfer with anti-CD70 cells can safely shrink tumors and to be certain the
      treatment is safe.

      Eligibility:

      Adults age 18 and older diagnosed with cancer that has the CD70-expressing cancer.

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with medical history, physical exam, scans, and other tests.
      They may by admitted to the hospital. Leukapheresis will be performed. For this, blood is
      removed through a needle in the arm. A machine separates the white blood cells. The rest of
      the blood is returned through a needle in the other arm.

      Eligible participants will have an intravenous catheter placed in their upper chest. Over
      several days, they will get chemotherapy drugs and the anti-CD70 cells. They will recover in
      the hospital.

      Participants will take an antibiotic for 6 months after treatment. They will repeat
      leukapheresis.

      Participants will visit the clinic every 1-3 months for the first year after treatment, every
      6 months for the second year, and then as determined by their physician. Follow-up visits
      will take 1-2 days. At each visit, participants will have lab tests, imaging studies, and a
      physical exam.

      Throughout the study, blood will be taken and participants will have many tests to determine
      the size and extent of their tumor and the treatment s impact.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  We generated a chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) that engages CD70 using its natural
           ligand CD27, as the binding moiety. Transducing PBL with this CAR conveys
           MHC-independent recognition of CD70 expressing target cells, which include renal cell
           carcinoma and other cancers.

        -  In co-cultures with CD70+ target cells, anti-hCD70 CAR transduced T cells secrete
           significant amounts of IFN-gamma with high specificity.

      Objectives:

      Primary objectives:

        -  Determine the safety of administering PBL transduced with anti-hCD70 CAR in concert with
           preparative lymphodepletion and high dose interleukin-2 (IL-2; aldesleukin).

        -  Determine if anti-hCD70 CAR-transduced PBL can mediate the regression of CD70 expressing
           tumors.

      Eligibility:

      Patients who have CD70 expressing tumors and 18 years of age or older must have:

      -Measurable metastatic disease that has progressed after standard therapy

      Patients may not have:

      -Contraindications for high dose aldesleukin administration.

      Design:

        -  PBMC obtained by leukapheresis will be cultured in the presence of anti-CD3 (OKT3) and
           aldesleukin in order to stimulate T-cell growth.

        -  Transduction is initiated by exposure of these cells to retroviral vector supernatant
           containing replication-incompetent virus encoding the anti-hCD70 CAR.

        -  All patients will receive a non-myeloablative lymphocyte depleting preparative regimen
           of cyclophosphamide and fludarabine.

        -  On day 0 patients will receive their PBL transduced with the anti-hCD70 CAR and then
           begin high dose aldesleukin.

        -  A complete evaluation of evaluable lesions will be conducted approximately 4-6 weeks
           after treatment.

        -  The study will be conducted using a Phase I/II optimal design, with two separate cohorts
           for the Phase II component: 1) renal cell carcinoma and 2) non-renal cell cancers (solid
           tumors only)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 12, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2028</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated cell dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before progression to next-higer dose level</time_frame>
    <description>Highest dose at which less than or equal to 1 of 6 patients experienced a DLT or the highest dose level studied if DLTs are not observed at any of the dose levels</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 weeks after cell infsusion, then every 3 months x3, then every 6 months x2 years, then per PI discretion</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients who have a clinical response to treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Engineered cell survival</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 5 years after cell infusion</time_frame>
    <description>CAR and vector presence will be quantitated in PBMC samples usingestablished PCR techniques</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of treatment related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Aggregate of all adverse events and their frequency</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">113</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Renal Cell Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-myeloablative lymphodepleting preparative regimen of cyclophosphamide and fludarabine + anti-hCD70 CAR transduced PBL + high-dose aldesleukin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>On days -7 and -6: Cyclophosphamide 60 mg/kg/day X 2 days IV in 250 mL D5W with Mesna 15 mg/kg/day X 2 days over 1 hr.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>On days -7 to -3: Fludarabine 25 mg/m2/day IVPB daily over 30 minutes for 5 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aldesleukin</intervention_name>
    <description>Aldeskeukin 720,000 IU/kg IV (based on total body weight) over 15 minutes every eight hours (+/- 1 hour) beginning within 24 hours of cell infusion and continuing for up to 3 days (maximum 9 doses).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-hCD70 CAR PBL</intervention_name>
    <description>On day 0, anti-hCD70 CAR transduced PBL will be infused intravenously on the Patient Care Unit over 20-30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Measurable unresectable cancer expressing CD70 as assessed by immunohistochemistry of
             resected tissue (&gt; 2+ CD70 positive on &gt; 50% of cancer cells, or &gt;1+ CD70 positive on
             &gt;75% of cancer cells).

          2. Patients must have previously received at least one standard therapy for their cancer
             (if available) and have been either non-responders (progressive disease) or have
             recurred.

          3. Patients with 3 or fewer brain metastases that are less than 1 cm in diameter and
             asymptomatic are eligible. Lesions &gt;1cm that have been treated with stereotactic
             radiosurgery must be clinically stable for 1 month after treatment for the patient to
             be eligible. Patients with surgically resected brain metastases are eligible.

          4. Age greater than or equal to 18 years and less than or equal to 70 years.

          5. Willing to sign a durable power of attorney

          6. Ability of subject to understand and the willingness to sign the written informed
             consent document

          7. Clinical performance status of ECOG 0 or 1

          8. Patients of both genders must be willing to practice birth control from the time of
             enrollment on this study and for up to four months after treatment.

          9. Serology:

             -Seronegative for HIV antibody. (The experimental treatment being evaluated in this
             protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who are HIV seropositive can
             have decreased immune-competence and thus be less responsive to the experimental

             treatment and more susceptible to its toxicities.)

             -Seronegative for hepatitis B antigen, and seronegative for hepatitis C antibody. If
             hepatitis C antibody test is positive, then patient must be tested for the presence of
             antigen by RT-PCR and be HCV RNA negative.

         10. Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the treatment on the fetus.

         11. Hematology

               -  Absolute neutrophil count greater than 1000/mm(3) without the support of
                  filgrastim

               -  WBC greater than or equal to 3000/mm(3)

               -  Platelet count greater than or equal to 100,000/mm(3)

               -  Hemoglobin &gt; 8.0 g/dL

         12. Chemistry:

               -  Serum ALT/AST less than or equal to 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

               -  Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.6 mg/dL

               -  Total bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 mg/dL, except in patients with Gilbert
                  s Syndrome who must have a total bilirubin less than 3.0 mg/dL.

         13. More than four weeks must have elapsed since any prior systemic therapy at the time
             the patient receives the preparative regimen, and patients toxicities must have
             recovered to a grade 1 or less (except for toxicities such as alopecia or vitiligo).
             Note: Patients may have undergone minor surgical procedures within the past 3 weeks,
             as long as all toxicities have recovered to grade 1 or less

         14. Subjects must be co-enrolled in protocol 03-C-0277

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Women of child-bearing potential who are pregnant or breastfeeding because of the
             potentially dangerous effects of the treatment on the fetus or infant.

          2. Any form of primary immunodeficiency (such as Severe Combined Immunodeficiency
             Disease).

          3. History of major organ autoimmune disease.

          4. Active systemic infections (e.g.: requiring anti-infective treatment), coagulation
             disorders or any other major medical illnesses.

          5. Concurrent opportunistic infections (The experimental treatment being evaluated in
             this protocol depends on an intact immune system. Patients who have decreased immune
             competence may be less responsive to the experimental treatment and more susceptible
             to its toxicities).

          6. Concurrent systemic steroid therapy.

          7. History of severe immediate hypersensitivity reaction to cyclophosphamide or
             fludarabine.

          8. History of coronary revascularization or ischemic symptoms

          9. Documented LVEF of less than or equal to 45%. Testing is required in patients with:

               -  Clinically significant atrial and/or ventricular arrhythmias including but not
                  limited to: atrial fibrillation, ventricular tachycardia, second or third degree
                  heart block or have a history of ischemic heart disease, or chest pain.

               -  Age greater than or equal to 65 years old

               -  Prior treatment with significant exposure to anthracyclines or cyclophosphamide

         10. Documented FEV1 less than or equal to 60% predicted tested in patients with:

               -  A prolonged history of cigarette smoking (approximately 20 packs/year within the
                  past 2 years).

               -  Symptoms of respiratory dysfunction

         11. Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James C Yang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary E. Link, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(866) 820-4505</phone>
    <email>IRC@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact NCI/Surgery Branch Recruitment Center</last_name>
      <phone>866-820-4505</phone>
      <email>irc@nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2016-C-0131.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goff SL, Smith FO, Klapper JA, Sherry R, Wunderlich JR, Steinberg SM, White D, Rosenberg SA, Dudley ME, Yang JC. Tumor infiltrating lymphocyte therapy for metastatic melanoma: analysis of tumors resected for TIL. J Immunother. 2010 Oct;33(8):840-7. doi: 10.1097/CJI.0b013e3181f05b91.</citation>
    <PMID>20842052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dudley ME, Wunderlich JR, Yang JC, Sherry RM, Topalian SL, Restifo NP, Royal RE, Kammula U, White DE, Mavroukakis SA, Rogers LJ, Gracia GJ, Jones SA, Mangiameli DP, Pelletier MM, Gea-Banacloche J, Robinson MR, Berman DM, Filie AC, Abati A, Rosenberg SA. Adoptive cell transfer therapy following non-myeloablative but lymphodepleting chemotherapy for the treatment of patients with refractory metastatic melanoma. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Apr 1;23(10):2346-57.</citation>
    <PMID>15800326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kochenderfer JN, Dudley ME, Kassim SH, Somerville RP, Carpenter RO, Stetler-Stevenson M, Yang JC, Phan GQ, Hughes MS, Sherry RM, Raffeld M, Feldman S, Lu L, Li YF, Ngo LT, Goy A, Feldman T, Spaner DE, Wang ML, Chen CC, Kranick SM, Nath A, Nathan DA, Morton KE, Toomey MA, Rosenberg SA. Chemotherapy-refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphoma and indolent B-cell malignancies can be effectively treated with autologous T cells expressing an anti-CD19 chimeric antigen receptor. J Clin Oncol. 2015 Feb 20;33(6):540-9. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2014.56.2025. Epub 2014 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>25154820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 3, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic Solid Cancers</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal Cell Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>CAR T Cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

