<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02831426</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RCTBU022016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02831426</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pre-pectoral Breast Reconstruction PART 2</brief_title>
  <acronym>PreBRec</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Multicentric Randomized Comparison of an Acellular Dermal Matrix Versus a Synthetic Mesh in Pre-pectoral Implant Based Breast Reconstruction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The rationale for present trial conception and design moves forward from the assumption that
      a subcutaneous, pre-pectoral reconstruction by means of soft tissue replacement devices is
      feasible, safe and giving rewarding results when compared to the standard retro-pectoral
      technique. Ahead of that, the trial aims to test if there is a difference in the outcomes
      between a biological and a synthetic material when placed as a support under the mastectomy
      skin flaps, both in terms of immediate complications and of long-term results.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This phase III randomized clinical trial will be investigating the Two-stage, using Tissue
      Expander (TE) pre-pectoral reconstructions.

      The trial will comprise two arms:

      PRE-PECTORAL technique with a biological Acellular Dermal Matrix (ADM) prosthesis coverage
      and support + FAT GRAFTING VS PRE-PECTORAL technique with a synthetic Titanium Coated
      Polypropylene Mesh (TCPM) prosthesis coverage and support + FAT GRAFTING
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate in percentage of surgical complications</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Surgical outcomes will be evaluated considering the rate in percentage of cases affected by the following complications among total number:
surgical site infection (any infection requiring an antibiotic therapy, either oral or intravenous), wound dehiscence, seroma (any fluid collection requiring aspiration for more than a month from mastectomy), nipple/skin necrosis (either partial or complete), hematoma, red breast syndrome, with their reintervention rate. Rates will be compared between the two groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate in percentage of technique failure</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The failure rate, as percentage, will be compared between the two arms:
failure will be the prosthesis (implant or TE) loss rate (reintervention with prosthesis removal) among overall number of prostheses implanted.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective quality of life assessment with Baker scale for capsular contracture</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2 years from mastectomy</time_frame>
    <description>Long-term outcomes, after two years from mastectomy and at least 3 months from TE/implant exchange, in quality of life will entail first of all an objective assessment: such evaluation will include the capsular contracture rate, with the assessment of the reintervention rate for amelioration or for a reconstructive strategy change. Among these objective evaluations, any possible short-term complications after second-stage procedure will be investigated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective quality of life assessment with cosmetic evaluation on pictures with a Likert scale for scoring</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2 years from mastectomy</time_frame>
    <description>A third party objective evaluation will be carried out by a group of a surgeon, a nurse and a lay person from a different center from that one where every single case was performed. This third party evaluation will assess the cosmetic outcome based on medical photographic files, giving a score for each patient. Scores from the two arms will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective quality of life assessment with BREAST-Q questionnaire (Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center and The University of British Columbia © 2006, all rights reserved)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2 years from mastectomy</time_frame>
    <description>After 2 years from mastectomy and at least 3 months from TE/implant exchange a subjective evaluation will be carried out with BREAST-Q score (scores from the two arms will be transformed in 100 scale, summed and compared as median)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-efficiency analysis with comparison of cost in money of the two arms</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 years from mastectomy</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of costs with comparison of the two arms will be carried out considering all costs from procedures and materials to possible late reinterventions to resolve complications and problems</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rate in percentage of complications in the sub-group of irradiated patients</measure>
    <time_frame>at 3 years from mastectomy</time_frame>
    <description>An analysis of a specific subgroup of patients will be carried out, namely those previously submitted to a breast irradiation and those submitted to a post-mastectomy radiation therapy. Analysis of short-terms failures and long-term problems with change in reconstruction strategy will be considered.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADM two-stage reconstruction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two-stage with Acellular Dermal Matrix (CELLIS® Breast). Tissue Expander A, Pre-pectoral, subcutaneous, two-stage reconstruction by means of TE supported by ADM</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TCPM two-stage reconstruction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two-stage with Titanium Coated Polypropylene Mesh (TiLOOOP® Bra). Tissue Expander B, Pre-pectoral, subcutaneous, two-stage reconstruction by means of TE supported by TCPM</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Two-stage with Acellular Dermal Matrix (CELLIS® Breast)</intervention_name>
    <description>After mastectomy, an immediate reconstruction will be performed by means of a tissue expander, of any shape and type available, positioned in a subcutaneous, pre-pectoral, position. The tissue expander will be held in place by an ADM (CELLIS® Breast, MECCELLIS BIOTECH, 40 rue Chef de Baie, 17000, La Rochelle FRANCE) either completely wrapped around it or just covering its anterior surface. After at least 6 months a TE/implant exchange procedure will be performed with a synchronous fat grafting procedure to ameliorate the skin flap thickness and softness over the medial border and upper pole. Fat grafting will be performed with the wash and filter principle technique of handling the harvested fat tissue.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADM two-stage reconstruction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tissue Expander two-stage reconstruction with ADM</other_name>
    <other_name>Tissue Expander / Implant exchange</other_name>
    <other_name>Fat grafting</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Two-stage with Titanium Coated Polypropylene Mesh (TiLOOOP® Bra)</intervention_name>
    <description>After mastectomy, an immediate reconstruction will be performed by means of a tissue expander, of any shape and type available, positioned in a subcutaneous, pre-pectoral, position. The tissue expander will be held in place by a Titanium Coated Polypropylene Mesh (TiLOOOP® Bra, pfm medical, ag Wankelstraße 60 ,50996 Köln GERMANY) either completely wrapped around it or just covering its anterior surface. After at least 6 months a TE/implant exchange procedure will be performed with a synchronous fat grafting procedure to ameliorate the skin flap thickness and softness over the medial border and upper pole. Fat grafting will be performed with the wash and filter principle technique of handling the harvested fat tissue.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TCPM two-stage reconstruction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tissue Expander two-stage reconstruction with TCPM</other_name>
    <other_name>Tissue Expander / Implant exchange</other_name>
    <other_name>Fat grafting</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria will entail cases of conservative mastectomies (skin-sparing
             mastectomy SSM, nipple-sparing mastectomy NSM and skin-reducing mastectomy SRM), both
             prophylactic and therapeutic.

        Included patients baseline characteristics will be:

          -  age 18-80 years old

          -  BMI between 18.5 and 35.

          -  Former smokers (up until 3 weeks before surgery)

          -  hypertension at oral medications

          -  diabetes

          -  previous breast surgery

          -  previous breast and chest wall radiation therapy will be allowed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  T4 and metastatic breast cancers

          -  obese patients (BMI over 35)

          -  currently smoking patients (within 3 weeks before surgery)

          -  refusal to sign the consent

          -  severe comorbidities requiring a chronic therapy (renal failure, heart failure,
             cardiovascular diseases, pulmonary diseases, hepatic diseases, and metabolic
             diseases).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tibor Kovacs, PhD, FRCS</last_name>
    <phone>07879408272</phone>
    <email>tiborkovacsdr@yahoo.co.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Matthew Young, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>02071880743</phone>
    <email>matthew.young@gstt.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Breast Surgery Unit, Guy's and St Thomas' Hospital NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 9RT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tibor Kovacs, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00447879408272</phone>
      <email>tibor.kovacs@gstt.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ashutosh Kothari, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claudio Calabrese, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 3, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kovacs</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD, FRCS</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

