<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02838368</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCI-Ipanema</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02838368</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigating Pompe Prevalence in Neuromuscular Medicine Academic Practices</brief_title>
  <acronym>IPANEMA</acronym>
  <official_title>Investigating Pompe Prevalence in Neuromuscular Medicine Academic Practices</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Irvine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Irvine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of type II glycogen-storage disease (Pompe disease) varies depending on
      ethnicity and geographic region. As of 2010, nine studies have been published documenting the
      incidence of Pompe disease. It is most common within the African American population, with an
      incidence of 1 in 14,000. In the U.S. more broadly speaking, the combined incidence of all
      three variants of the disease is 1 in 40,000. These estimates relied on the frequencies of
      three mutations in the gene acid alpha-glucosidase (GAA), leading to variants of the disease.
      Criteria for inclusion in the studies were often non-selective; in many cases, molecular
      genetic screening was done at birth. With such a high prevalence of Pompe disease reported,
      it is expected that large university medical centers specializing in neuromuscular diseases
      would see a higher incidence of Pompe disease among their patients. From a comparable Italian
      multicenter study, it appears that Pompe disease accounts for 3% of all patients presenting
      with proximal weakness with or without CK elevation.

      This study will measure the incidence of Pompe disease based on manifest laboratory
      abnormality, namely low GAA enzyme activity. Analysis of GAA enzyme activity will be
      determined through a blood sample of 4 mL. The study seeks to measure the epidemiology of
      Pompe disease by symptomatically screening all patients who present with symptoms of hitherto
      undiagnosed proximal weakness with or without elevation of the muscle enzyme, creatinine
      kinase (CK), or elevation of CK alone, at thirteen academic tertiary neuromuscular practices
      throughout the United States and Canada. Total recruitment is expected to be ~1,500
      participants. It is anticipated that the number of incident Pompe cases in this cohort would
      be between 3-5%, i.e. 45-75 newly diagnosed cases of Pompe disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The true incidence of Pompe disease among patients seen at neuromuscular clinics.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Pompe Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients age of 8 years and older suspected of late-onset Pompe disease.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 8 years or older.

          -  Geographically accessible to one of the sites.

          -  One of these following three clinical situations: Complaint of proximal muscle
             weakness with or without elevation in creatinine kinase (CK); neck muscle weakness
             (either flexor or extensor) with or without elevation in CK; or elevation of CK in
             isolation.

          -  Capable and willing to provide informed consent or assent and follow study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 8 years of age.

          -  Subjects with an alternative neuromuscular diagnosis that is responsible for subject's
             symptoms

          -  Incapable or unwilling to provide informed consent and to follow research procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tahseen Mozaffar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Irvine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marie Wencel</last_name>
    <phone>(714) 456-2525</phone>
    <email>mwencel@uci.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Irvine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Irvine</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marie Wencel</last_name>
      <phone>714-456-2525</phone>
      <email>mwencel@uci.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tahseen Mozaffar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cupler EJ, Berger KI, Leshner RT, Wolfe GI, Han JJ, Barohn RJ, Kissel JT; AANEM Consensus Committee on Late-onset Pompe Disease. Consensus treatment recommendations for late-onset Pompe disease. Muscle Nerve. 2012 Mar;45(3):319-33. doi: 10.1002/mus.22329. Epub 2011 Dec 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22173792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leslie N, Bailey L. Pompe Disease. 2007 Aug 31 [updated 2017 May 11]. In: Adam MP, Ardinger HH, Pagon RA, Wallace SE, Bean LJH, Stephens K, Amemiya A, editors. GeneReviews® [Internet]. Seattle (WA): University of Washington, Seattle; 1993-2018. Available from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK1261/</citation>
    <PMID>20301438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirschhorn R, Reuser AJ. Glycogen storage disease type II: acid alpha-glucosidase (acid maltase) deficiency. In: Scriver CR, Beaudet A, Sly WS, Valle D, eds. The Metabolic and Molecular Bases of Inherited Disease. New York, NY: McGraw-Hill; 2001:3389-420.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martiniuk F, Chen A, Mack A, Arvanitopoulos E, Chen Y, Rom WN, Codd WJ, Hanna B, Alcabes P, Raben N, Plotz P. Carrier frequency for glycogen storage disease type II in New York and estimates of affected individuals born with the disease. Am J Med Genet. 1998 Aug 27;79(1):69-72.</citation>
    <PMID>9738873</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Musumeci O, la Marca G, Spada M, Mondello S, Danesino C, Comi GP, Pegoraro E, Antonini G, Marrosu G, Liguori R, Morandi L, Moggio M, Massa R, Ravaglia S, Di Muzio A, Filosto M, Tonin P, Di Iorio G, Servidei S, Siciliano G, Angelini C, Mongini T, Toscano A; Italian GSD II group. LOPED study: looking for an early diagnosis in a late-onset Pompe disease high-risk population. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2016 Jan;87(1):5-11. doi: 10.1136/jnnp-2014-310164. Epub 2015 Mar 17.</citation>
    <PMID>25783438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 20, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Irvine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tahseen Mozaffar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glycogen Storage Disease Type II</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

