<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00582452</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>04-127</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI CA101511</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CA109236</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00582452</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Attitudes Towards Prophylactic Colectomy in Hereditary Non-polyposis Colorectal Cancer (HNPCC) Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Attitudes Towards Prophylactic Colectomy in HNPCC Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn more about individual's with a family history of colon
      cancer and the process by which they may decide to undergo or not undergo prophylactic
      colectomy. This is a surgery to remove the colon in order to reduce risk of cancer (or of
      getting cancer again).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hereditary non-polyposis colorectal cancer (HNPCC) is associated with up to an 80% lifetime
      risk of developing colorectal cancer and a 40-50% chance of a metachronous tumor after
      partial colectomy for the disease. For these patients, prophylactic colectomy has been
      proposed as a potential risk management alternative to a lifetime of intensive surveillance
      by colonoscopy. The highly personal nature of such risk management decisions has been
      recognized in the development of individualized genetic counseling services. However, prior
      psychosocial research in this area has tended to use linear statistical techniques in which
      clinically important details are lost in an overly broad, one size-fits-all model that is
      difficult to apply in a one-to-one counseling session. We propose an innovative approach
      based on the Cognitive-Social Health Information Processing (C-SHIP) model in which we will
      explore how attitudes towards prophylactic colectomy are organized into meaningful patterns
      or types that can translate readily into tailored counseling recommendations. Specific aims
      of this study are: 1)to assess levels of intention in prophylactic colectomy among HNPCC
      patients; 2)To identify distinctive decision types based on profiles of perceived pros and
      cons of prophylactic colectomy; and 3) To explore the pattern of relations between decision
      types and counseling-related outcomes (level of intention in colectomy, cancer-specific
      anxiety, and colonoscopy adherence). We will conduct a one-time cross-sectional telephone
      survey of 320 HNPCC patients (defined as either carriers of a mutated mismatch repair gene
      associated with HNPCC or those with a personal/family history meeting published criteria for
      HNPCC). Using cluster analysis we will create a taxonomy of decision types. Prior research
      leads us to expect at least three types: Disengaged, Risk-Focused, and Ambivalent. We
      hypothesize that each type will have a different pattern of relations with the outcome
      variables (e.g., Risk-focused types will show higher level of intention regarding surgery,
      high anxiety, low avoidance, and high colonoscopy adherence, whereas Ambivalent types will
      show higher level of intention regarding surgery, high anxiety, high avoidance, and low
      colonoscopy adherence). Understanding these patterns will enhance the ability of physicians,
      genetic counselors, and other providers to help their patients make well informed, thoughtful
      decisions about the preventive strategy that will best protect their health, emotional
      well-being, and quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Family-Based</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess levels of intention in prophylactic colectomy among individuals at increased familial risk of colorectal cancer and to identify distinctive decision types based on profiles of perceived pros and cons of prophylactic colectomy;</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Affected patients who are at high risk for metachronous colorectal tumors due to mutation status.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Unaffected patients who are at high risk for developing colon cancer based on family history and/or mutation status.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telephone survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Telephone survey</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Unaffected patients who are at high risk for developing colon cancer based on family
        history and/or mutation status, and affected patients who are at high risk for metachronous
        colorectal tumors due to mutation status.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  are from a family that has a known mismatch repair mutation; or

          -  meet Amsterdam I or Amsterdam II criteria that spell out the family and personal
             cancer history characteristics associated with HNPCC

          -  are considered at sufficiently high risk by their CRC specialty physician that
             prophylactic colectomy may be presented as an option (excluding FAP).

        Amsterdam I Criteria

          1. At least three relatives with a colorectal cancer and the following criteria:

               -  One should be a first degree relative of the other two

               -  At least two successive generations should be affected

               -  At least one colorectal cancer should be diagnosed before the age of 50

               -  Familial Adenomatous Polyposis (FAP) should be excluded in the colorectal cancer
                  case(s), if any

             Amsterdam II Criteria (also known as Revised Amsterdam Criteria

          2. At least three relatives with an HNPCC-associated cancer (colorectal cancer, cancer of
             the endometrium, small bowel, ureter, or renal pelvis) *:

               -  One should be a first degree relative of the other two

               -  At least two successive generations should be affected

               -  At least one relative should be diagnosed before age 50

               -  FAP should be excluded in the colorectal cancer case(s), if any *NOTE: ovarian
                  cancer will also be considered an HNPCCassociated cancer as per Lynch et al (NEJM
                  2003)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  non-English speaking

          -  under the age of 18

          -  are unable to give meaningful informed consent due to physical, psychiatric or
             cognitive disability

          -  are from a family affected by FAP

          -  have already undergone subtotal colectomy or total proctocolectomy

          -  are in active treatment and/or less than six months post-surgery for cancer.

          -  Have undergone genetic counseling and testing for HNPCC at MSKCC
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Hurley, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 21, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 28, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 9, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 9, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Karen Hurley, PhD</name_title>
    <organization>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HNPCC</keyword>
  <keyword>prophylactic colectomy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms, Hereditary Nonpolyposis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

