<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00580242</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>07-006</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>RV-MDS-PI-0161</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00580242</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1 Dose Escalating Trial of Bortezomib in Combination With Lenalidomide in Patients With Myelodysplasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Dose Escalating Study of Bortezomib and Lenalidomide in Patients With Untreated or Previously Treated, Primary and Secondary Non 5q- Del Myelodysplasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study proposes using bortezomib in cohorts of 3-6 patients at the doses of 0.7, 1, and
      1.3 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 to determine the MTD in combination with lenalidomide 10 mg
      a day, for 21 days of a 28 day treatment cycle for patients with myelodysplastic syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Currently, there are no curative therapies for myelodysplasia except for allogeneic stem cell
      transplantation. Both lenalidomide and bortezomib have activity as single agents in patients
      with myelodysplasia. This study proposes using bortezomib in cohorts of 3-6 patients at the
      doses of 0.7, 1, and 1.3 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 to determine the MTD in combination
      withlenalidomide 10 mg a day, for 21 days of a 28 day treatment cycle. The planned bortezomib
      doses have been evaluated in previous Phase I clinical studies in similar patient populations
      and have been safe and well tolerated in a twice-weekly schedule of administration.
      Lenalidomide has been shown to have efficacy in myelodysplasia. The combination of
      lenalidomide and bortezomib has been used in patients with multiple myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Establish the maximally tolerated dose of bortezomib, up to 1.3 mg/m2/day, that can be administered in combination with lenalidomide in patients with primary and secondary non 5q del myelodysplasia who are untreated or previously treated.</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess efficacy in terms of the number of patients experiencing a decrease in blast percentage</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess efficacy in terms of the number of patients experiencing a decrease in transfusion requirements</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the toxicity profile of bortezomib when used in combination with lenalidomide for patients with myelodysplasia</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the time (days) to transfusion independence</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine if molecular markers can predict responsiveness to treatment (for consenting patients)</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6 and 9 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Myelodysplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a Phase I dose escalation trial with three cohorts of 3-6 patients each plus 10 additional patients (up to a maximum total of 28 patients) treated at the candidate maximum tolerated dose.Cohorts will receive increasing doses of bortezomib at 0.7, 1, and 1.3 mg/m2 on days 1, 4, 8, and 11 in combination with lenalidomide at 10 mg a day for Days 1-21. Each cycle will be 28 days. Patients will receive up to 9 cycles of treatment, with efficacy assessed after 3, 6, and 9 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>First cohort: Bortezomib 0.7mg/m2 IV on Days on Days 1, 4, 8, and 11. Patients may receive up to 9 cycles with each cycle lasting a total of 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Second cohort: Bortezomib 1mg/m2 IV on Days 1, 4, 8, and 11 Patients may receive up to 9 cycles with each cycle lasting a total of 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Third Cohort: Bortezomib 1.3mg/m2 IV on Days 1, 4, 8, and 11 of each cycle Patients may receive up to 9 cycles with each cycle lasting a total of 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Lenalidomide 10 mg PO QD on Days 1 -21 followed by a 7 day rest period</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Revlimid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients may be untreated or previously treated.

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Able to adhere to study schedule and other protocol requirements

          -  Unequivocal clinicopathologic diagnosis of myelodysplastic syndrome, non 5q- deletion.

          -  Patients may have had prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy for another malignancy or
             myelodysplasia as long as it was completed at least 4 weeks (6 weeks for nitrosureas)
             prior to initiation of therapy.

          -  ECOG performance status of 0-2 (Appendix 10.3)

          -  Life expectancy greater than 3 months

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dl, ALT and AST ≤ 3 X the upper limit of normal (ULN),
             creatinine &lt; 2.0 mg/dl all within 28 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Patients must give voluntary written informed consent and HIPAA authorization before
             performance of any study-related procedure not part of normal medical care, with the
             understanding that consent may be withdrawn by the subject at any time without
             prejudice to future medical care.

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 0.5 x 10 (9)/l

          -  Platelet count &gt; 30 x 10 (9)/l

          -  Prior treatment with 5-azacytidine is encouraged, but not required.

          -  Patients may have had prior treatment for MDS, including single agent lenalidomide or
             bortezomib.

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy
             test with a sensitivity of at least 50mIU/ml within 10-14 days prior to and within 24
             hours of prescribing lenalidomide and must commit to abstinence from heterosexual
             intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of birth control,at least 4 weeks before
             starting taking lenalidomide. FCBP must agree to ongoing pregnancy testing. Men must
             agree not to father a child and agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with
             a female of child bearing potential even if they have had a successful vasectomy.

          -  All study participants must be registered into the mandatory RevAssist Program®, and
             be willing and able to comply with the requirements of RevAssist®.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Ejection fraction &lt; 40%

          -  Patients who have had a myocardial infarction within 6 months of enrollment or has New
             York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure, uncontrolled angina,
             uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, or electrocardiographic evidence of acute
             ischemia or active conduction system abnormalities. Prior to study entry, any ECG
             abnormality at screening has to be documented by the investigator as not medically
             relevant.

          -  Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subject from signing the consent form.

          -  Any condition, including laboratory abnormalities, that in the opinion of the
             investigator places the subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in
             the study or confounds the ability to interpret data from the study.

          -  Patients with major surgery within the 28 days prior to trial enrollment.

          -  Patients with ≥ Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy or active herpes infection

          -  Patients with an uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to,
             ongoing or active infection, cirrhosis, chronic obstructive or restrictive pulmonary
             disease, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, or cardiac
             arrythmia.

          -  Patients with secondary MDS that require concurrent therapy for the primary cancer
             diagnosis.

          -  The development of erythema nodosum as characterized by a desquamating rash while
             taking thalidomide or similar drugs.

          -  Patient with hypersensitivity to bortezomib, boron or mannitol.

          -  Female subject is pregnant or breast-feeding. . Lactating females must agree not to
             breast feed while taking lenalidomide.

          -  Patient has received an investigational drug within 28 days of enrollment.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to thalidomide or lenalidomide

          -  Concurrent use of other anti-cancer agents or treatments.

          -  Known positive for HIV
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Ballen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 21, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 8, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karen Ballen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Leukemia Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myelodysplasia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

