<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00582842</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>02-042</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00582842</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Longitudinal Assessment of Health-Related Quality of Life in Men With Localized Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Longitudinal Assessment of Health-Related Quality of Life in Men With Localized Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess quality-of-life of men with prostate cancer.
      &quot;Quality-of-life&quot; means how you feel about your life as a result of your disease and its
      treatment. The investigators hope that this questionnaire will help show how prostate cancer
      treatments affect quality-of-life. It will help doctors and future patients to make better
      treatment choices. Some men may wish to have a more demanding treatment with a higher risk of
      harmful effects. Others may prefer a treatment that will have the smallest effect on their
      quality-of-life.

      This questionnaire will help us measure these effects and decide which is the best treatment
      for a given patient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The intent of the protocol is to assess health-related quality-of-life (HRQOL) in men treated
      for localized prostate cancer with 1 of 6 established management alternatives: external
      (XRT)or interstitial radiotherapy (IRT), open radical prostatectomy (RP), laparoscopic
      radical prostatectomy (LRP), combined radiotherapy and brachytherapy (Combined RT) or
      watchful waiting (WW). HRQOL is an important aspect of any treatment for prostate cancer due
      to the beliefs by many that cancer control rates are similar across common modalities and
      HRQOL reduction from treatment is substantial (1-5). Therefore, HRQOL appears to occupy a
      central role in the decision making process related to treatment selection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of temporal trends in HRQOL according to intervention group</measure>
    <time_frame>study time points 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 24, 36, and 48 following treatment)and between 60 and 96 months.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of scale score differences between treatment groups</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 24, 36, 48 months and between 60 and 96 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe the quality of life of long-term survivors</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>of prostate cancer following treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1800</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Men with prostate cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Men with prostate cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interview</intervention_name>
    <description>The phone interview will consist of the following items from the follow up questionnaire; 14, 16, 20, 32, 33, 46, 47, 60, and 65. An additional component of this study would be dispensing the HRQOL tool to long-term survivors 10 years or greater after the completion of therapy. The long term QoL study will be a cross-sectional assessment measuring HRQOL in prostate cancer survivors, free of disease at least ten years post-treatment. Patients will complete a questionnaire by selfreport focusing on assessment of HRQOL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>survey instruments using Web-Based Data Collection System (WBDC) survey content</intervention_name>
    <description>The content of the WBDC questionnaire will be similar to the paper form, no alteration in the wording, the order, or the formate of the items will be done. In addition, at the time of each outpatient clinic visit to MSKCC, these subjects will be able to login to WBDC using a computer located in the patient waiting-area, and enter their responses to the different items of the questionnaire if their clinic visit corresponds to any of the study time points 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 24, 36, and 48 following treatment). An additional component of this study would be dispensing the HRQOL tool to long-term survivors 10 years or greater after the completion of therapy. The long term QoL study will be a cross-sectional assessment measuring HRQOL in prostate cancer survivors, free of disease at least ten years post-treatment. Patients will complete a questionnaire by selfreport focusing on assessment of HRQOL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All eligible MSKCC patients (including patients from the regional network sites: Commack,
        Basking Ridge, Rockville Centre and Sleepy Hollow) will be approached by consenting
        professionals and invited to participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of localized, untreated prostate cancer (clinical stages T1-3, Nx, M0)

          -  ability to read the English language

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  other cancer diagnosis for the past three years, except for non-melanoma skin cancer

          -  prior chemotherapy within the last three years; radiation therapy to the pelvis or
             prior pelvic surgery within the past three years

          -  prior neoadjuvant therapy, such as hormones (Bicalutamide use for less than or equal
             to 1 month would not constitute exclusion from study entry)

        For the cross-sectional component of the study, all patients identified to be free of
        disease at least ten years post -treatment will be considered eligible. Patients must have
        no clinical evidence of local, regional or distant recurrences. Patients must have the
        ability to read and understand English. Patients who received hormonal therapy will be
        eligible for the cross-sectional component of the study, but the duration of the hormonal
        therapy must be six months or less. the investigators have identified a cohort of patients
        who fit these criteria from our databases.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Scardino, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memoral Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basking Ridge</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center @ Suffolk</name>
      <address>
        <city>Commack</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11725</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering at Mercy Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockville Centre</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memoral Sloan Kettering Cancer Center@Phelps</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sleepy Hollow</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 21, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 28, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Early Stage</keyword>
  <keyword>Localized</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

