<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00580281</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>06-142</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00580281</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Imatinib on Bone Metabolism in Patients With Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia or Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Imatinib on Bone Metabolism in Patients With Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia or Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The drug that you are taking for your cancer, imatinib (GleevecTM), has recently been shown
      to have some new types of side effects. In some people, imatinib can affect how bones are
      made.

      The purpose of this study is to find out if imatinib is causing these side effects in you. We
      can check how your bones form by testing your blood and urine. We can also check your bone
      strength by doing a special X-ray of your bone called bone density (or DEXA scan).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Preliminary data from this institution suggest that imatinib, likely by inhibiting platelet
      derived growth factor receptor (PDGFR), inhibits bone formation and resorption in a high
      percentage of patients with either chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML) or gastrointestinal
      stromal tumors(GIST).1 Some, but not all, patients taking imatinib developed hypophosphatemia
      but the effect on bone, as measured by markers of bone synthesis and metabolism, was seen in
      some patients with normal phosphate levels as well. Marked urinary phosphate wasting with
      elevated levels of parathyroid hormone was seen in nearly all patients. The effect of
      imatinib on bone may be dose-related. Patients with hypophosphatemia were routinely started
      on oral phosphate replacement, but follow up determinations of urinary phosphate wasting were
      not performed.

      The clinical consequences of these abnormalities on bone are not yet known. This trial will
      study 60 patients with CML in chronic phase, early accelerated phase (as detected by
      cytogenetics only) or GIST who are already taking imatinib. Parameters relating to bone
      metabolism will be checked every 3 months for 2 years. We will determine the incidence of
      bone abnormalities in this treated population, determine whether fasting serum phosphate can
      predict for changes in bone metabolism, determine whether there is change in bone density by
      measuring serial bone densitometry, determine whether oral phosphate replacement can restore
      phosphate balance, and determine whether there is a dose effect of imatinib on parameters of
      bone metabolism.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>This pilot study will collect longitudinal data on bone metabolism for patients treated with imatinib. Sixty patients will be followed over a two-year period on this protocol, with bone marker assessments ascertained every 3 months (+2 weeks).</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 months (+2 weeks)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>blood, urine, and dexa scan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study will involve venipuncture for obtaining blood samples; a spot second void (whenever possible) urine sample will be obtained at the same time. A Dexa scan to evaluate bone density will be obtained at the beginning, middle and end of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blood test, urine test, and bone density x-ray.</intervention_name>
    <description>start of the study (month 0), and at months 3, 6, 9, 12 (1 year), 15, 18, 21, and 24 (2 years)</description>
    <arm_group_label>blood, urine, and dexa scan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with CML in chronic phase, accelerated phase based on cytogenetic
             abnormalities in addition to Philadelphia chromosome but with less than 5 % blasts, or
             GIST taking imatinib

          -  Patients with life expectancy of at least 12 months; patients must be on imatinib at
             time of study entry.

          -  Ability to sign informed consent and/or assent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a known parathyroid disorder; active thyroid disorder except stable,
             replaced hypothyroidism; Cushing's syndrome; uncontrolled diabetes mellitus (could
             have unexpected fluid, electrolyte and mineral shifts); sarcoidosis (elevated
             calcitriol levels from granulomata); hypercalcemia of malignancy (i.e., PTHrP-mediated
             or extensive bone mets);known tumor-induced osteomalacia; Paget's disease of bone;
             known X-linged or autosomal dominant hypophosphatemic rickets/osteomalacia; known
             renal tubular disease (e.g., Fanconi's syndrome); chronic GI malabsorption sydrome.

          -  Patients taking oral calcium in excess of calcium 750 mg and Vitamin D 400 mg daily
             (ie, that contained in a single multivitamin). Patients taking more than these amounts
             may be eligible for this study if vitamin and mineral supplementation in excess of
             this is stopped for a minimum of 2 weeks prior to study entry.

          -  Patients taking oral or intravenous steroids, calcitonin, any selective estrogen
             modulating agent such as tamoxifen or raloxifene, gallium nitrate, and other bone
             seeking radionuceotides, any calcimimetic agent such as cinacalet.

          -  Patients who have had prior treatment with cisplatin, carboplatin, oxaliplatin,
             ifosfamide, or cyclophosphamide.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ellin Berman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 24, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gastric cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Imatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Gleevec</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Imatinib Mesylate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

