<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02609594</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMNIOVLU01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02609594</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Amnioband and Standard of Care vs. Standard of Care Alone in the Treatment of Venous Leg Ulcers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-center Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial Evaluating Two Application Regimens of Amnioband Dehydrated Human Amniotic Membrane and Standard of Care vs. Standard of Care Alone in the Treatment of Venous Leg Ulcers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SerenaGroup, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Musculoskeletal Transplant Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SerenaGroup, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lower extremity ulcers pose significant clinical, humanistic and economic burdens on society.
      Millions of Americans are afflicted with painful, open, draining sores on their lower
      extremities. These sores are referred to as venous leg ulcerations (VLUs).1-5 Under the best
      of circumstances these ulcers require weeks or months to heal. Not uncommonly wound care
      specialists see patients who have suffered for years or faced amputation of the limb as their
      only option to alleviate the pain.

      Standard of care will result in healing in 50% of venous leg ulcers in 12 weeks. However,
      roughly half of patients suffering from venous ulcers will require advanced therapy. Human
      amniotic membrane replaces the damaged extracellular matrix characteristic of chronic ulcers.
      In addition, it contains cytokines that may accelerate healing. In clinical practice and
      recent studies, Dehydrated Human Amniotic Membrane has appeared to be as effective as
      bioengineered skin products. This RCT is designed to evaluate Amnioband Dehydrated Human
      Amniotic Membrane in venous leg ulcers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a multi-center, randomized, trial designed to evaluate the safety and
      effectiveness of Amnioband Dehydrated Human Amniotic Membrane plus multi-layer compression
      therapy versus multi-layer compression alone in the healing of venous leg ulcers.

      The Standard of Care therapy in this study is multi-layer compression therapy. A number of
      compression bandaging systems are commercially available. The choice of compression will be
      at the discretion of the principle investigator.

      The Screening Phase (1-14 days) consists of a series of screening assessments designed to
      determine eligibility followed by, for those who meet the eligibility criteria (described in
      more detail below), At or up to 14 days before the first Screening Period Visit (S1), written
      informed consent from the subject will be obtained by the Investigator or suitably qualified
      designee before the performance of any other protocol-specific procedure.

      Subjects who have not been treated with compression therapy for the target ulcer must receive
      a minimum of 14 days of compression prior to enrollment.

      At the first Screening Period Visit (S1), the Investigator will select the study (target)
      ulcer. Each subject will have only one VLU selected as the study (target) ulcer. In the
      situation where a subject has more than one VLU at the S1 visit, the Investigator will select
      the largest VLU that meets the eligibility criteria of the protocol as the study (target)
      ulcer.

      The Screening Period is designed to determine whether subjects are eligible to proceed to the
      Treatment Period of the study.

      The Treatment Phase (12 Weeks) begins with a series of assessments designed to confirm the
      subjects' continued eligibility. Subjects who continue to meet eligibility criteria will be
      randomized to one of three groups: (1) standard of care: multi-layer compression (2) weekly
      application of Amnioband Dehydrated Human Amniotic Membrane (3) biweekly applications of
      Amnioband Dehydrated Human Amniotic Membrane.

      During the Treatment Phase, subjects will be evaluated on a weekly basis. Efficacy
      evaluations each week will include Investigator assessment of ulcer healing and measurements
      of ulcer size using a digital camera device. Safety evaluations during the Treatment Phase
      will consist of adverse event assessments at each visit.

      Subjects in any of the three groups whose ulcers do not achieve closure at 12 weeks will be
      deemed treatment failures. Subjects in the control arm may cross over to the Amnioband arm if
      they fail to achieve closure although these subjects will not be included in the analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to complete ulcer closure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Ulcer closure is based on wound area measurement and absence of wound exudate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of ulcers achieving 40% ulcer closure</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This is measured by wound area.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of ulcers achieving complete closure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This is measured by wound area and absence of wound exudate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The per unit cost of providing wound care is known. The use of amniotic membrane to standard of care will be compared in terms of the cost of achieving healing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in pain between treatment groups</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pain is measured by subject report on a scale of 0 to 10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Leg Ulcers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to this group will receive standard of care (multi-layer compression therapy).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Weekly application of Amnioband</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Weekly application of Amnioband plus standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Biweekly application of Amnioband</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Biweekly application of Amnioband plus standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Weekly application of Amnioband</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly application of Amnioband.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Weekly application of Amnioband</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biweekly application of Amnioband</intervention_name>
    <description>Biweekly application (every two weeks) of Amnioband.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Biweekly application of Amnioband</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care for this study is weekly multi-layer compression bandaging.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Weekly application of Amnioband</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Biweekly application of Amnioband</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At least 18 years old.

          2. Ankle Brachial Pressure Index (ABI) &gt; 0.75 OR SPP &gt; 30 mmHg OR TCOM &gt; 30 mmHg.*

          3. Presence of a venous leg ulcer extending through the full thickness of the skin but
             not down to muscle, tendon or bone.

          4. The largest ulcer will be designated the index ulcer and the only one included in the
             study. If other ulcerations are present on the same leg they have to be more than 2 cm
             apart from the index ulcer.

          5. Study ulcer (i.e. current episode of ulceration) has been present for greater than one
             month prior to the initial screening visit, and has failed to respond to documented
             conservative measures for greater than (1) one month duration and is excluded if it
             has undergone 12 months of continuous high strength compression therapy over its
             duration.

          6. Study ulcer is a minimum of 2 cm2 and a maximum of 20 cm2 at the randomization visit.

          7. The target ulcer has been treated with compression therapy for at least 14 days prior
             to randomization.

          8. Ulcer has a clean, granulating base with minimal adherent slough at the randomization
             visit.

          9. Females of childbearing potential must be willing to use acceptable methods of
             contraception (birth control pills, barriers, or abstinence).

         10. Subject understands and is willing to participate in the clinical study and can comply
             with weekly visits and the follow-up regimen.

         11. Subject has read and signed the IRB/IEC approved Informed Consent Form before
             screening procedures are undertaken.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Study ulcer(s) deemed by the investigator to be caused by a medical condition other
             than venous insufficiency.

          2. Study ulcer exhibits clinical signs and symptoms of infection.

          3. Known allergy to the components of the multi-layer compression bandaging, or who
             cannot tolerate multi-layer compression therapy.

          4. Study ulcer, in the opinion of the investigator, is suspicious for cancer should
             undergo an ulcer biopsy to rule out a carcinoma of the ulcer.

          5. Subjects with a history of more than two weeks treatment with immunosuppressants
             (including systemic corticosteroids), cytotoxic chemotherapy, or application of
             topical steroids to the ulcer surface within one month prior to initial screening, or
             who receive such medications during the screening period, or who are anticipated to
             require such medications during the course of the study.

          6. Subjects on any investigational drug(s) or therapeutic device(s) within 30 days
             preceding Screening.

          7. Study ulcer improving greater than 30% during the screening phase if the subject was
             not in adequate compression 14 days prior to screening.

          8. History of drug or alcohol abuse.

          9. History of radiation at the ulcer site.

         10. Presence of one or more medical conditions, as determined by medical history,
             hematologic, active auto-immune or immune diseases that, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, would make the subject an inappropriate candidate for this ulcer healing
             study.

         11. History of having Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome (AIDS) or HIV.

         12. Study ulcer has been previously treated with tissue engineered materials (e.g.
             Apligraf® or Dermagraft®) or other scaffold materials (e.g. Oasis, Matristem) within
             the last 30 days

         13. Study ulcer requiring negative pressure wound therapy or hyperbaric oxygen during the
             course of the trial.

         14. Presence of any condition(s) which seriously compromises the subject's ability to
             complete this study, or has a known history of poor adherence with medical treatment.

         15. Ulcers on the dorsum of the foot or with more than 50% of the ulcer below the
             malleolus are excluded.

         16. Pregnant or breast feeding.

         17. Presence of diabetes with poor metabolic control as documented with a HgA1c &gt; 12.0
             within last 90 days

         18. Patients with renal dysfunction whose serum creatinine levels are 3.0mg/dl or greater
             within the last 90 days

         19. History of usage of tobacco products within the last 30 days

         20. History of Liver disease with active Cirrhosis of the liver
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linda Squillante</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Musculoskeletal Transplant Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Heather Connell, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>617-383-3979</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital Wound Care Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurie Bayer, PA-C</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-8743</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Indranil Sinha, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Premier Surgical</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bricktown</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08723</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jarrod Kaufman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>732-262-1600</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inspira Medical Center - Elmer Wound Care Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Elmer</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08318</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St John Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tulsa</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>74135</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Foot and Ankle Wellness Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ford City</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>16226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthew Sabo, DPM</last_name>
      <phone>724-763-4080</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Armstrong County Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kittanning</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>16201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Keyur Patel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>724-543-8893</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SerenaGroup Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15222</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Serena, MD</last_name>
      <phone>814-688-4000</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Martinsville Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Martinsville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>24112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kim Young</last_name>
      <phone>540-676-5886</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nathan Young, DPM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>SerenaGroup, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thomas Serena</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>human amniotic membrane</keyword>
  <keyword>compression therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>venous leg ulcer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

