<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02602054</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HGNAE-07</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02602054</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Best Treatment Strategy: Surgical vs Pharmacological to Close the Ductus Arteriosus Persistent in Preterm Infants</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Best Treatment Strategy: Surgical Versus Pharmacological, to Close the Ductus Arteriosus Persistent in Preterm Infants. A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital General Naval de Alta Especialidad - Escuela Medico Naval</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital General Naval de Alta Especialidad - Escuela Medico Naval</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The decision to treat patent ductus arteriosus in preterm infants, varies from a
      conservative, medical or immediate surgical treatment; although, at present, there is some
      controversy about this decision. This study aims to determine the efficacy and safety of
      surgical versus pharmacological treatment of patent ductus arteriosus in preterm infants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The ductus arteriosus varies in length, diameter and morphology. The duct closure occurs in
      two stages: the first one or functional closure; the second or anatomical closure. This
      condition is associated with other heart diseases, which modify the natural history and
      require individualized treatment. Treatment varies from conservative, pharmacological or
      surgical treatment, and there are many controversies regarding the treatment decision. And
      aims of the closure, is to decrease the likelihood of irreversible pulmonary vascular
      disease, reduce associated morbidity and mortality. The role of prostaglandin E2 is the
      permeability of the conduit, by which is indicated the use of cyclooxygenase inhibitors for
      closure (indomethacin and ibuprofen). In various research studies many factors associated
      with failure of pharmacological treatment (gestational age, antenatal indomethacin less than
      48 hours before delivery, use of high frequency ventilation) are reported, therefore, there
      is an alternative treatment which is surgical closure. In the pharmacological treatment of
      ductus arteriosus persistent it should be individualized according to gestational age,
      respiratory condition and size of the newborn. With early drug treatment can achieve closure
      of patent ductus arteriosus in up to 90% of cases, while the late treatment between 50-65%.
      However, it is reported that after treatment with indomethacin, reopening occurs, two doses
      are recommended more after the first, in addition to its side effects, contraindications and
      complications. As well, ibuprofen contraindications. So the closure of the ductus arteriosus
      persistent may be performed by hemodynamics and surgical closure (standard left thoracotomy
      or thoracoscopic technique). There are specific indications for surgical treatment (no
      response to two cycles of medical treatment in newborns with less than 1000 gr weight in
      which I fail one indomethacin, absolute contraindications to it, with significant hemodynamic
      repercussions. With surgical treatment before the third week of life minimizing morbidity. it
      is reported by many authors that complications are rare and mortality is associated with
      other complications of prematurity. So Surgical treatment is considered as an alternative
      because of its low incidence of complications, mortality and lower cost, plus a total
      occlusion between 94-100% Because of this, the treatment of patent ductus arteriosus in
      preterm infants, ranging from conservative treatment, medical or surgical, and currently
      there is much controversy in the treatment decision.

      This study aims to determine the efficacy and safety of surgical versus pharmacological
      treatment for the permanent closure of the patent ductus arteriosus in preterm infants.

      Methods: Is open label randomized controlled the clinical trial with: 1) experimental group
      assigned to surgical treatment; 2) control group assigned to pharmacological treatment, for
      closure of patent ductus arteriosus.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Success rate of closure patent ductus arteriosus</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Tracking each patient for 10 days after treatment (surgical / pharmacological) to verify success rate of closure of patent ductus arteriosus (Failure of ductal closure ) (%)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from diagnosis to resolution of patent ductus arteriosus</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the time from diagnosis to resolution of patent ductus arteriosus (days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from start of treatment until resolution</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the time from start of treatment until resolution of patent ductus arteriosus (days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time limitation of family contact</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the time limitation of family contact from diagnosis to hospital discharge of newborns of patent ductus arteriosus (days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse effects and complications of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Describe the type of adverse effects and / or complications (Chronic lung disease , Intraventricular haemorrhage, Creatinine level &gt; 1.8 mg/dl, Pneumothorax , Sepsis, Necrotising enterocolitis, Retinopathy of prematurity, Other bleeding) and the frequency of the two study groups (yes / no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death before discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>To compare related mortality among surgical and pharmacological treatment (%)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of mechanical ventilatory support, parenteral nutrition, fasting, supplementary O2</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the duration of mechanical ventilatory support, parenteral nutrition, fasting, supplementary O2 (days).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anatomy of the ductus arteriosus persistent</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Describe the size of the ductus arteriosus (mm)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gestational age at birth</measure>
    <time_frame>At birth</time_frame>
    <description>Describe the gestational age of neonates (weeks)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apgar</measure>
    <time_frame>At birth</time_frame>
    <description>Describe the Apgar score of newborns (3-9)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood flow</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Describe the direction of blood flow of the ductus arteriosus (left-right, left-right, two-way)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gradient of the ductus arteriosus</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Describe the gradient of the ductus arteriosus (mmHg).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Persistent Ductus Arteriosus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Implement surgical treatment for closure of patent ductus arteriosus</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>- Indomethacin: Administer 1 full cycle (3 doses) of indomethacin (1 dose every 12 hours) for 2 days Dose 0.1 - 0.25 mg / kg
- Ibuprofen: Administer 1 full cycle (3 doses) of ibuprofen (1 dose every 24 hours) for 2 days Dose 05 - 10 mg / kg
- Acetaminophen: Administer 1 full cycle (12 doses) of acetaminophen (1 dose every 6 hours) for 3 days Dose 15 mg / kg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard left thoracotomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control group</intervention_name>
    <description>- Indomethacin:
Administer 1 full cycle (3 doses) / (1 dose every 12 hours) in the first fourteen days of life:
Preterm infants less than 48 hours of life: first dose 0.2 mg/kg, second dose 0.1 mg/kg and third dose 0.1 mg/kg Preterm infants more than 48 hours of life: first dose 0.2 mg/kg, second dose 0.2 mg/kg and third dose 0.2 mg/kg And preterm infants more than 7 days of life: first dose 0.2 mg/kg, second dose 0.25 mg/kg and third dose 0.25 mg/kg - Ibuprofen:
Administer 1 full cycle (3 doses) / (1 dose every 24 hours) in the first fourteen days of life of preterm infants:
First dose 10 mg/kg Second dose 05 mg/kg Third dose 05 mg/kg
- Acetaminophen
Administer 1 full cycle, in the first fourteen days of life in preterm infants:
Acetaminophen 15 mg/kg every 6 hours for 3 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pharmacological</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Preterm infants

          -  Preterm infants hospitalized in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit with a diagnosis of
             patent ductus arteriosus

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Preterm infants with supportive treatment and / or drug prior to patent ductus
             arteriosus in another medical unit

          -  Preterm infants diagnosed with heart disease associated complex.

          -  Preterm infants with associated disease (not hemodynamic or cardiovascular) and its
             impact on his state of health prior to drug treatment and / or surgery

          -  Preterm infants with contraindications to pharmacological and / or surgery treatment

          -  Newborns diagnosed with patent ductus arteriosus but with incomplete medical records
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Esaú Luis Nieto, Pediatrician</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital General Naval de Alta Especialidad - Escuela Medico Naval</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Esaú Luis Nieto, Pediatrician</last_name>
    <phone>5564787736</phone>
    <email>dresauln@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Naval de Alta Especialidad</name>
      <address>
        <city>Distrito Federal</city>
        <zip>04477</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Esaú Luis Nieto, Pediatrician</last_name>
      <phone>5564787736</phone>
      <email>dresauln@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gallardo MAF, González SJM, et al. Experiencia en el cierre quirúrgico de ducto arterioso permeable en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Neonatales de un hospital de segundo nivel en Guadalajara, Jalisco, México. Bol Med Hosp Infant Mex 2010; 67: 128-32</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Staines OH, Fuentes TMA, Staines AR. Tratamiento quirúrgico del conducto arterioso persistente. Rev Mex Cir Ped 2005; 12: 39-45.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Golombek SG, Sola A, Baquero H, Borbonet D, Cabañas F, Fajardo C, Goldsmit G, Lemus L, Miura E, Pellicer A, Pérez JM, Rogido M, Zambosco G, van Overmeire B; Primer Grupo de Consenso Clínico SIBEN. [First SIBEN clinical consensus: diagnostic and therapeutic approach to patent ductus arteriosus in premature newborns]. An Pediatr (Barc). 2008 Nov;69(5):454-81. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>19128748</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Elorza MD, Pérez RJ, Quero JJ. Tratamiento del Ductus Arterioso Persistente sintomático del recién nacido pretérmino. Hospital Universitario La Paz. Servicio Madrileño de Salud. 2005 (3): 1-8.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hernando BG, et al. Atención médica a niños &lt; 30 semanas de gestación con conducto arterioso persistente. Rev Mex Pediatr. 2013; 80 (4): 131-135.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>San Luis-Miranda R, Arias-Monroy LG, Peralta-Pedrero ML, Lázaro-Castillo JL, León-Ávila JL, Benítez-Aréchiga ZM, Jáuregui-Ruiz O, Yáñez-Gutiérrez L, Manrique-Valle M. [Clinical guide practice. Patent ductus arteriosus]. Rev Med Inst Mex Seguro Soc. 2012 Jul-Aug;50(4):453-63. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>23234752</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee JH, Ro SK, Lee HJ, Park HK, Chung WS, Kim YH, Kang JH, Kim H. Surgical Ligation on Significant Patent Ductus Arteriosus in Very Low Birth Weight Infants: Comparison between Early and Late Ligations. Korean J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2014 Oct;47(5):444-50. doi: 10.5090/kjtcs.2014.47.5.444. Epub 2014 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25346899</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moore GP, Lawrence SL, Maharajh G, Sumner A, Gaboury I, Barrowman N, Lemyre B. Therapeutic strategies, including a high surgical ligation rate, for patent ductus arteriosus closure in extremely premature infants in a North American centre. Paediatr Child Health. 2012 Apr;17(4):e26-31.</citation>
    <PMID>23543702</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sung SI, Choi SY, Park JH, Lee MS, Yoo HS, Ahn SY, Chang YS, Park WS. The timing of surgical ligation for patent ductus arteriosus is associated with neonatal morbidity in extremely preterm infants born at 23-25 weeks of gestation. J Korean Med Sci. 2014 Apr;29(4):581-6. doi: 10.3346/jkms.2014.29.4.581. Epub 2014 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24753708</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lam JY, Lopushinsky SR, Ma IWY, Dicke F, Brindle ME. Treatment Options for Pediatric Patent Ductus Arteriosus: Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. Chest. 2015 Sep;148(3):784-793. doi: 10.1378/chest.14-2997. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25835756</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kim HK, et al. Effect of indomethacin treatment in full-term infants with symptomatic patent ductus arteriosus. Korean J Perinatol 2013; 24 (4): 237-43.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kwon NH, Lee JH, et al. Risk Factors of Failure of Ibuprofen Treatment in Preterm Infants with HS PDA. Korean J Perinatol 2014; 25 (4): 257-65.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sadeck LS, Leone CR, Procianoy RS, Guinsburg R, Marba ST, Martinez FE, Rugolo LM, Moreira ME, Fiori RM, Ferrari LL, Menezes JA, Venzon PS, Abdallah VQ, Duarte JL, Nunes MV, Anchieta LM, Alves Filho N. Effects of therapeutic approach on the neonatal evolution of very low birth weight infants with patent ductus arteriosus. J Pediatr (Rio J). 2014 Nov-Dec;90(6):616-23. doi: 10.1016/j.jped.2014.04.010. Epub 2014 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>25046256</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>López Sousa M, Pérez Feal A, Soto A, Fraga JM, Couce ML. [Left vocal cord paralysis after patent ductus arteriosus surgery]. An Pediatr (Barc). 2015 Jan;82(1):e7-e11. doi: 10.1016/j.anpedi.2014.04.001. Epub 2014 May 10. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>24815768</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gimeno Navarro A, Cano Sánchez A, Fernández Gilino C, Carrasco Moreno JI, Izquierdo Macián I, Gutiérrez Laso A, Morcillo Sopena F. [Ibuprofen versus indomethacin in the treatment of patent ductus arteriosus in preterm infants]. An Pediatr (Barc). 2005 Sep;63(3):212-8. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>16219273</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Clyman RI, Chorne N. Patent ductus arteriosus: evidence for and against treatment. J Pediatr. 2007 Mar;150(3):216-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17307530</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Van Overmeire B, Chemtob S. The pharmacologic closure of the patent ductus arteriosus. Semin Fetal Neonatal Med. 2005 Apr;10(2):177-84. Epub 2004 Dec 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15701582</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mosalli R, Alfaleh K. Prophylactic surgical ligation of patent ductus arteriosus for prevention of mortality and morbidity in extremely low birth weight infants. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2008 Jan 23;(1):CD006181. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD006181.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18254095</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 16, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 16, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 17, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>persistent ductus arteriosus</keyword>
  <keyword>preterm infants</keyword>
  <keyword>surgical treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacological treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ductus Arteriosus, Patent</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetaminophen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Indomethacin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

