<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02603198</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>34147114500000068</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02603198</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>2%-Mepivacaine With Two Different Vasoconstrictors Solutions in Third Molar Surgery a Comparative Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>2%-Mepivacaine With Two Different Vasoconstrictors; 1:20.000 Levonordefrin or 1:100.000 Epinephrin for Local Anesthesia in Third Molar Surgery: A Comparative Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dental treatments, particularly third molars extraction, can become extremely uncomfortable
      and painful. They are associated to anxiety, fear and many other unpleasant sensations.
      During surgery, patients can present cardiorespiratory repercussions of these sensations.
      This fact generally justifies the employment of methods of monitoring and appliance of safer
      therapeutic alternatives. Local anesthetics are the most frequently drugs used in dentistry.
      Vasoconstrictors, particularly epinephrine, are important components of anesthetic solutions
      to increased time for anesthetic absorption and consequently increasing the duration of
      anesthesia. The use of smaller amounts of anesthetic solution can reduce the risk of systemic
      toxicity, however decrease the total surgical time. It is well known that the amount of
      epinephrine injected into patients during anesthetic procedures can produce adverse
      hemodynamic effects. Levonordefrin was adding to dental cartridges promising to reduce
      cardiac stimulation due it less β activity, and maintain the same clinical and systemic
      effects. But some studies for maxillary or intraosseous infiltrations showed no difference in
      heart rate and any anesthetic success over epinephrine. Thus, this study aims to compare the
      clinical efficacy and safety of anesthetic mepivacaine 2% with epinephrine 1:100,000 or
      1:20,000 levonordefrin employing a clinical trial model of third molars extractions in
      healthy adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      30 healthy patients, both gender between 18 and 40 years-of-age with the necessity of
      bilateral third molar removal with similar surgical difficulty will be recruited from a
      Dental Public University Clinic. Inclusion criteria includes: non-smoking participants,
      minimum of 50 Kg of weight. After clinical and radiographic examination, they will be
      randomized accordingly to the side to be operated in two groups: MEPI-LEVO and MEPI-EPI.
      There will be a memory-washout of 15days between surgeries. In the MEPI-LEVO group, the
      patient will receive local anesthesia employing 2% chloridrato mepivacaine with 1:20.000
      levonordefrin at a maximum of four cartridges of anesthesia. The other side will receive
      2%chloridrato mepivacaine with 1:100.000 epinephrine in the same maximum amount. The surgery
      in both groups will follow strictly patterns of minimum surgical trauma and high cautious
      antiseptic conditions. The same surgeon will do the tooth extractions but the anesthesia will
      be done by another oral surgeon in order to blind the type of anesthetic solution from the
      operator (type of vasoconstrictor used). The amount of bleeding will be quantified just
      immediately after suture by a blinded observer that will record in a visual analogical scale
      between 0 and 10 points, where 0 correspond to absence of bleeding and 10 to excessive
      bleeding.

      Blood pressure and heart rate will be accessed in five different moments:

        1. 20minutes before surgical procedure with patients in awaiting room;

        2. 5 minutes before procedure with patient seated in dental chair;

        3. 5 minutes after anesthesia procedure;

        4. during osteotomy/tooth sectioning and

        5. after 10 minutes of suturing.

      Patients after surgery will receive a diary to record the time when anesthesia sensation had
      ended, the amount of analgesics they had consumed and the level of pain in a visual analogic
      scale. The data will be submitted to statistical analysis with p&lt;0.05 of significance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Blood pressure values</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes pre-operatory, 5 minutes before surgery, 5 minutes after anesthesia, 10 minutes after suture</time_frame>
    <description>assessment of blood pressure values (systolic and diastolic)) in mmHg by a pulse electronic device</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Heart Rate values</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes pre-operatory, 5 minutes before surgery, 5 minutes after anesthesia, 10 minutes after suture</time_frame>
    <description>assessment of Heart Rate in bpm (beats per minute) by a pulse electronic device</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>after 1 hour postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment by a visual analogical scale - blinded observer record</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 8,24 and 48 hours after suture</time_frame>
    <description>assessment by visual Analogical Scale - Patient diary</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Trismus</condition>
  <condition>Edema</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mepivacaine chloridrato epinephrine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Side of operation that is going to receive anesthesia with 2% mepivacaine chloridrato with 1:100.000 epinephrine, maximum of 4 cartridges</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mepivacaine chloridrato levonordefrin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Side of operation that is going to receive anesthesia with 2% mepivacaine chloridrato with 1:20.000 levonordefrin, maximum of 4 cartridges</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mepivacaine chloridrato epinephrine</intervention_name>
    <description>local anesthesia for tooth removal</description>
    <arm_group_label>mepivacaine chloridrato epinephrine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>local anesthesia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mepivacaine chloridrato levonordefrin</intervention_name>
    <description>local anesthesia for tooth removal</description>
    <arm_group_label>mepivacaine chloridrato levonordefrin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>local anesthesia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  minimum body weight of 50Kg, necessity of bilateral impacted third molar removal

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcelo Minharro Cechetti, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Post - Doctorate</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maria Cristina Zindel Deboni</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <zip>05508-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ezmek B, Arslan A, Delilbasi C, Sencift K. Comparison of hemodynamic effects of lidocaine, prilocaine and mepivacaine solutions without vasoconstrictor in hypertensive patients. J Appl Oral Sci. 2010 Jul-Aug;18(4):354-9.</citation>
    <PMID>20835569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hersh EV, Giannakopoulos H. Beta-adrenergic blocking agents and dental vasoconstrictors. Dent Clin North Am. 2010 Oct;54(4):687-96. doi: 10.1016/j.cden.2010.06.009. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20831932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serrera Figallo MA, Velázquez Cayón RT, Torres Lagares D, Corcuera Flores JR, Machuca Portillo G. Use of anesthetics associated to vasoconstrictors for dentistry in patients with cardiopathies. Review of the literature published in the last decade. J Clin Exp Dent. 2012 Apr 1;4(2):e107-11. doi: 10.4317/jced.50590. eCollection 2012 Apr. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24558534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pellicer-Chover H, Cervera-Ballester J, Sanchis-Bielsa JM, Peñarrocha-Diago MA, Peñarrocha-Diago M, García-Mira B. Comparative split-mouth study of the anesthetic efficacy of 4% articaine versus 0.5% bupivacaine in impacted mandibular third molar extraction. J Clin Exp Dent. 2013 Apr 1;5(2):e66-71. doi: 10.4317/jced.50869. eCollection 2013 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24455059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Torres-Lagares D, Serrera-Figallo MÁ, Machuca-Portillo G, Corcuera-Flores JR, Machuca-Portillo C, Castillo-Oyagüe R, Gutiérrez-Pérez JL. Cardiovascular effect of dental anesthesia with articaine (40 mg with epinefrine 0,5 mg % and 40 mg with epinefrine 1 mg%) versus mepivacaine (30 mg and 20 mg with epinefrine 1 mg%) in medically compromised cardiac patients: a cross-over, randomized, single blinded study. Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal. 2012 Jul 1;17(4):e655-60.</citation>
    <PMID>22322521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawaty I, Drum M, Reader A, Nusstein J. A prospective, randomized, double-blind comparison of 2% mepivacaine with 1 : 20,000 levonordefrin versus 2% lidocaine with 1 : 100,000 epinephrine for maxillary infiltrations. Anesth Prog. 2010 Winter;57(4):139-44. doi: 10.2344/0003-3006-57.4.139.</citation>
    <PMID>21174567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 10, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maria Cristina Zindel Deboni</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>third molar</keyword>
  <keyword>tooth extraction</keyword>
  <keyword>impacted tooth</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Trismus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mepivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Racepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vasoconstrictor Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nordefrin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

