<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02602379</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HMR14090</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02602379</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of NoL Index and ANI After Nociceptive Stimulation at Different Infusion Rates of Remifentanil Infusion</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of NoL Index and ANI Variations After Nociceptive Stimulation Under Different Rates of Infusion of Intravenous Remifentanil in Patients Undergoing Laparotomies With Intraoperative Epidural Analgesia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maisonneuve-Rosemont Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medasense Biometrics Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maisonneuve-Rosemont Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Contrary to &quot;immobility&quot; and, to a lesser extent, to the &quot;hypnosis/unconsciousness&quot; component
      of general anaesthesia, the monitoring of &quot;analgesia&quot; remains largely elusive, evaluated
      mainly through poorly sensitive and potentially undesirable changes in patients' vital signs.
      This has led the industry to pursue the development of various devices and indices based on
      other physiological parameters such as heart rate variability (HRV), electroencephalogram
      (EEG), skin conductance, to name only a few. To the best of the knowledge, none of these
      parameters on its own has shown sufficient capacity in detecting different degrees of
      pain/analgesia balance to gain wide clinical use.

      The purpose of this prospective observational study is to evaluate the response of a
      single-parameter index (the Analgesia Nociception Index [ANI]) and a multi-parameter index
      (the Nociception Level [NoL] Index) when patients under combined general anaesthesia/epidural
      anaesthesia for laparotomies are subjected to a standardized painful stimulus (a tetanic
      stimulation over the ulnar nerve at 70 mA, 100 Hz for 30 seconds) at different doses of
      remifentanil infusion at steady state (0,005 mcg/kg/min; 0,05 mcg/kg/min; 0,1 mcg/kg/min;
      0,15 mcg/kg/min). With the painful stimulus held constant but the analgesia provided
      gradually increased, it is expected to characterize the response of these two indices to
      different levels of nociception/anti-nociception balance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients scheduled for elective abdominal surgery by laparotomy (general surgery or
      gynaecological surgery) will receive a thoracic epidural (around T9-T10/T10-T11) and general
      anesthesia. Apart from standard monitoring, the ANI (derived from the EKG) and the NoL index
      (obtained via a finger probe) will be recorded. The epidural catheter will be injected with
      6-10 ml of lidocaine 2% with epinephrine 5 mcg/ml to produce anesthetic level of neuraxial
      blocade and then be perfused with the same solution at 4-8 ml/hour. After incision and
      confirmation of adequate blocade with the epidural local anesthetic, the patient will receive
      a series of painful electric stimulation with a standard nerve stimulator applied over the
      ulnar nerve in tetanic mode for 30 seconds at 100 Hz and 70mA. Each stimulation will occur at
      a different rate of infusion of IV remifentanil at steady state (0,005 mcg/kg/min; 0,05
      mcg/kg/min; 0,1 mcg/kg/min; 0,15 mcg/kg/min). A stimulation at 0,005 mcg/kg/min will be done
      before and after epidural loading with local anesthetics to look for altered variations in
      analysed parameters. The variation and the kinetic of the variations after stimulations will
      be observed for heart rate, mean blood pressure, BIS, ANI and NoL index.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between NoL index responses to electrical stimulus and the i.v. doses of remifentanil infusion given during anesthesia. The n of patients (40 in this study) is calculated on this primary outcome.</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The electrical stimulus will be applied on the forearm of the asleep patient at different doses of iv remifentanil (0.005mcg/kg/min to a maximum of 0.15 mcg/kg.min during anesthesia for abdominal surgery with active intraoperative epidural pain management). It will be evaluated whether or not exists a correlation between the doses of iv remifentanil and the responses of the Nol index after electrical stimulus.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NoL index changes after a standardized electrical stimulus at 4 different concentrations of iv remifentanil infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the NoL changes after a nociceptive stimulus at various intravenous remifentanil infusion doses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ANI index changes after a standardized electrical stimulus at 4 different concentrations of iv remifentanil infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the ANI changes after a nociceptive stimulus at various intravenous remifentanil infusion doses. ANI being another uniparametric pain index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate changes after a standardized electrical stimulus at 4 different concentrations of iv remifentanil infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the changes of Heart Rate after a nociceptive stimulus at various intravenous remifentanil infusion doses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Blood Pressure changes after a standardized electrical stimulus at 4 different concentrations of iv remifentanil infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the changes of Heart Rate after a nociceptive stimulus at various intravenous remifentanil infusion doses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity and specificity of NoL index, ANI index, Heart Rate and Mean blood Pressure in detecting a painful stimulus such as intubation as well as standardized electrical stimulus at remifentanil infusion of 0.005 msg/kg/min</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the sensitivity and specificity of these 4 criteria in detecting a painful stimulus such as intubation and standardized electrical stimulus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tetanic stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Single arm study. See Study description for a through description of the intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tetanic stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard Tetanic stimulation will be used as the stimulus to evaluate responses of the intraoperative pain indexes (ANI and NoL) at different concentration of i.v. remifentanil during anesthesia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tetanic stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients scheduled for elective abdominal surgery by laparotomy (general surgery or
        gynaecological surgery) who will receive a thoracic epidural (around T9-T10/T10-T11) and
        general anesthesia.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ASA status I, II or III

          -  Elective abdominal surgery with median laparotomy under general anaesthesia and
             epidural analgesia.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Coronary artery disease

          -  Serious cardiac arrhythmias (including atrial fibrillation)

          -  Patient refusal

          -  History of substance abuse

          -  Chronic use of psychotropic and/or opioid drugs

          -  Use of drugs that act on the autonomic nervous system (including β-blockers)

          -  History of psychiatric diseases or psychological problems

          -  Contraindications to epidural analgesia

          -  Allergy to remifentanil

          -  Unexpected difficult airway requesting excessive, possibly painful airway
             manipulations.

          -  Dural puncture during epidural catheter installation

          -  Failure of epidural analgesia

          -  Surgical unexpected complications requiring strong haemodynamic support (transfusions,
             vasopressors, inotropes)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Richebé, M.D. PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maisonneuve-Rosemont Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Maisonneuve-Rosemont</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 16, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 16, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Maisonneuve-Rosemont Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Philippe Richebé</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD, Professor of anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Analgesia Nociception Index</keyword>
  <keyword>NoL</keyword>
  <keyword>Nociception Level</keyword>
  <keyword>Remifentanil</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Remifentanil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

