<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02600039</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>37906314.3.0000.5208</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02600039</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Short-term Effect of ELTGOL on Pulmonary Ventilation Valued Through Electrical Impedance Tomography in Cystic Fibrosis Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Short-term Effect of ELTGOL on Pulmonary Ventilation Valued Through Electrical Impedance Tomography in Cystic Fibrosis Patients: Randomized Crossover Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cystic Fibrosis (CF) is the most common lethal autosomal recessive disease. Respiratory
      therapy is always recommended to the CF patient with pulmonary involvement and has differents
      techniques and devices, however, there is no consensus on the effectiveness of the techniques
      used, there is a need to determine the applicability of the therapeutic resources used.
      Therefore, the aim of the study is to determine the short-term effectiveness of ELTGOL on
      Average Electrical Impedance on the End of Expiration (MIEFE) pulmonary, assessed by
      Electrical Impedance Tomography (EIT) in individuals with CF through a clinical trial
      randomized crossover. Volunteers will be included with FC with moderate to severe lung
      disease with chest ≥ 74 cm that do not show: episode of pulmonary infectious exacerbations in
      the last four weeks or during the study period; cor pulmonale; facial deformity that causes
      air leakage; facial trauma and recent face or esophagus surgery; chest pain; hemoptysis in
      the last week; continued use of supplemental oxygen (&gt; 8 hours / day); hemoptysis;
      hemodynamic instability and do not understand the use and command of the techniques used. The
      sample is selected by convenience from the database of individuals assisted data in
      Integrative Medicine Institute Professor Fernando Figueira (IMIP). The research will be
      developed in three phases, divided into three days with an interval of at least 48 hours
      between phases. The first day will undergo initial assessment and in the days following the
      intervention by day, ELTGOL or Acapella, in a randomized order.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average Electrical Impedance on the End-Expiration</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dyspnea assessed by the Borg scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, one minute and thirtieth minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen saturation assessed by oximeter</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, one minute and thirtieth minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preferred technique assessed by an open question</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Effects associeted with ELTGOL and Acapella assessed by an open question</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, one minute and thirtieth minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ELTGOL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acapella</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ELTGOL</intervention_name>
    <description>Individuals will be placed in the lateral decubitus position and instructed to perform slow expirations with an open glottis through a nozzle attached to the mouth from the residual functional capacity to residual volume. Concurrently, a trained and subsequently positioned relative to the voluntary physical therapist will perform a manual compression of the abdominal region dependent and the rib cage to enhance contralateral lung deflation. This intervention is performed so that the time is homogeneous between each repetition interval of one minute between each set. To this end, three sets of ten repetitions will be performed on each lateral decubitus (left and right)</description>
    <arm_group_label>ELTGOL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acapella</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acapella</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant should be comfortably seated and with his elbows on a table. The mouthpiece is attached properly to not allow leaks. The resistance load will be one in which the individual is able to maintain uninterrupted expiration of 3 seconds. Then the patient will be instructed to inhale slowly and deeply, with lung volumes between the residual volume and total lung capacity. The air exhaled by Acapella is directed toward an orifice which opens and closes periodically, promoting oscillations in the air stream throughout the expiratory phase. The expiration is always performed to the VR, and without performing the active contraction of the abdominal muscles. Still prompted an inspiratory pause of 2 seconds for the end of the inspiratory phase. This procedure will be performed in 4 sets of 5 minutes with interval of 1 minute between the series.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ELTGOL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Acapella</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: Volunteers with Cystic Fibrosis and lung disease with chest
        hemiperímetro ≥ 37 cm. Exclusion Criteria: Episode of pulmonary infectious exacerbations in
        the last four weeks or during the study period; cor pulmonale; facial deformity that causes
        air leakage; facial trauma and recent face or esophagus surgery; chest pain; hemoptysis in
        the last week; continued use of supplemental oxygen (&gt; 8 hours / day); hemoptysis;
        hemodynamic instability and do not understand the use and command of the techniques used.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto de Medicina Integral Professor Fernando Figueira</name>
      <address>
        <city>Recife</city>
        <state>Pernambuco</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amanda S Couto, Msc</last_name>
      <phone>+5586999217512</phone>
      <email>sc_amanda@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 6, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 6, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Amanda Silva Couto</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

