<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02608866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201509057RIND</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02608866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single Versus Multiple Fractionated SSRS for Spinal Metastases</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Clinical Trial of Single Versus Multiple Fractionated Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery for Patients With Spinal Metastases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators proposed this randomized study to determine the feasibility of delivering
      single-fraction 16-Gy versus 3-fraction 24-Gy toward spine metastatic lesion and to evaluate
      their toxicity profiles. The investigators' analysis will provide robust data as well as
      predictive factors regarding the outcome after SSRS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although conventionally fractionated radiation therapy has been utilized for decades, the
      rates of complete pain relief and local control for complex tumors are sub-optimal. The
      management of patients with spine metastasis has undergone a great deal of change in the past
      5 years. Improvements in neuroimaging, computer-assisted treatment planning, and radiation
      therapy techniques have led to the development of extracranial radiosurgery.

      SSRS is rapidly being adopted in the clinic as preliminary applications of SSRS appears
      promising. However, the role of SSRS remains in its infancy and lacked high-quality evidence
      about the treatment schedule and lacked a solid understanding of the adverse events. The
      Radiation Therapy Oncology Group (RTOG) 0631 phase 2/3 study was initiated to determine
      whether a more intensive radiation dose delivered by image guided 16-Gy dose single fraction
      SRS could improve pain control and quality of life as compared with conventional
      external-beam radiotherapy in patients with localized spine metastases . While other group
      used treatment schedule in a total dose of 27-30 Gy in three fractions.

      Serious adverse events such as vertebral compression fracture (VCF) is a fairly low-risk
      adverse event after conventional radiotherapy, nevertheless, the crude risk estimates for VCF
      after spinal stereotactic body radiation therapy is relative more frequent. Previous reports
      has raised the caution about the given dose and predictive factors, however; whether these
      two most widely used SSRS schedule (ie. single fraction versus three fractions) provide
      equivalent pain control and minimal side effects remained to be answered.

      There was no randomized trials to assess the SSRS treatment response and SSRS induced grade 3
      or higher adverse events between the two most widely adopted scheme. Thus, the investigators
      proposed the randomized study to determine the feasibility of delivering a single 16-Gy SRS
      dose versus 3 fractions 24-Gy SRS dose and tried to evaluate the toxicity profile and gain
      robust data as well as predictive factors regarding the risk of complications after SSRS,
      including VCF. The investigators will incorporate the recently developed and reported
      reliable Spinal Instability Neoplastic Scoring (SINS) system and well-designed patient
      reported outcome measures (PROMs) into the protocol to predict the adverse event and quality
      of life of each participant. The researchers also tried to investigate the possible
      associations of the potential bone biomarkers for the risk assessment of SSRS-related adverse
      bone events.

      Since the patients were randomized for treatment arms, the effectiveness of SSRS treatment
      scheme and adverse profile can be investigated more properly in the present study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events version 4 Grade 3 or higher adverse events related to spine radiosurgery</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks after SSRS</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of 4-month Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events version 4 grade 3 or higher adverse events definitely, probably or possibly related to treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The pain response rate at the treated index site(s) at 4 months by the numerical rating pain scale</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks after Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life for palliative cancer care patients</measure>
    <time_frame>1-, 2-, 4-, 6-, 9-, and 12-month after Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery</time_frame>
    <description>European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life-Core 30 questionnaire module and Quality of Life questionnaire for palliation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local control rate at the treated index site(s)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrolment until the date of first documented local progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute toxicity (Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events version 4)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 90 days after Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Late toxicity (Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events version 4)</measure>
    <time_frame>From 90 days after Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery until the date of death from any cause, up to 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of spinal cord function by Frankel's classification grading system for spine injury at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks after Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor-related spinal instability by the Spinal Instability Neoplastic Score (SINS) at 4 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks after Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Osseous changes of the treated index site(s) on CT scan within 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>2-, 4-, 6-, 9-, and 12-month after Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Genomic risk of radiation induced vertebral compression fracture</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by grading based on vertebral height loss</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Secondary Malignant Neoplasm of Spine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SF-SSRS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single-Fraction (SF) Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MF-SSRS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multiple-Fraction (MF) Stereotactic Spine Radiosurgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SF-SSRS</intervention_name>
    <description>Spine stereotactic radiosurgery/ablative radiotherapy (SSRS) with 16 Gy in single fraction to the defined target volume using intensity modulated radiotherapy or volumetric modulated arc therapy (VMAT or RapidArc).</description>
    <arm_group_label>SF-SSRS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MF-SSRS</intervention_name>
    <description>SSRS with 24 Gy in three fractions to the defined target volume using intensity modulated radiotherapy or volumetric modulated arc therapy (VMAT or RapidArc). Treatment should be given on every other day. Treatment on the consecutive days to the same target volume is not allowed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MF-SSRS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

        To be eligible for inclusion, patients must fulfill the following criteria:

          1. Patients with a histologic diagnosis of non-hematopoietic malignancy

          2. Radiographic evidence of localized spine metastases without leptomeningeal involvement
             or intramedullary lesion

          3. Maximum three separate sites with a maximal involvement of two continuous vertebral
             levels

          4. Patients do not have prior radiotherapy to the index spine(s)

          5. Patients with metastatic epidural spinal cord compression (≥ grade 2) at the index
             spine(s) who will not be treated with spine surgery after evaluation by neurosurgeon
             or orthopedic doctor

          6. Age ≥ 20 years

          7. Karnofsky performance status (KPS) ≥ 60%.

          8. Life expectancy of ≥ 4 month.

          9. Women of childbearing potential and male participants must practice adequate
             contraception

         10. Patients must be able to comply with the study protocol and follow-up schedules and
             provide study-specific informed consent

        Exclusion criteria Patients fulfill any of the following criteria will be excluded from
        this trial

          1. Prior radiotherapy to the index spine(s)

          2. Serum creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL within 90 days prior registration

          3. Contraindication to MRI such as implanted metal devices or foreign bodies, severe
             claustrophobia

          4. Patients with leptomeningeal involvement or intramedullary metastasis

          5. Inability to tolerate treatment procedure

          6. Bony retropulsion causing neurologic abnormality

          7. Severe, active comorbidities which, in the judgment of the investigator, would make
             the patient inappropriate for entry into this study or interfere significantly with
             the proper assessment of safety and adverse events of the protocol, or limit
             compliance with study requirements, defined as follows:

               -  Uncontrolled active infection requiring intravenous antibiotics at the time of
                  registration

               -  Transmural myocardial infarction ≤ 6 months prior to registration

               -  Unstable angina or congestive heart failure requiring hospitalization ≤ 6 months
                  prior to registration

               -  Life-threatening uncontrolled clinically significant cardiac arrhythmias

               -  Hepatic insufficiency resulting in clinical jaundice and/or coagulation defects

               -  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease exacerbation or other respiratory illness
                  requiring hospitalization or precluding study therapy at the time of registration

               -  Uncontrolled psychiatric disorder

          8. Will receive any other investigational agent or chemotherapy and/or target therapies
             during treatment

          9. Women of childbearing potential and male participants who are sexually active and not
             willing/able to use medically acceptable forms of contraception; this exclusion is
             necessary because the radiation treatment involved in this study may be significantly
             teratogenic
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Feng-Ming Hsu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Taiwan University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shih-Fan Lai, MD</last_name>
    <phone>886-972654376</phone>
    <email>laishihfan@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>100</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Feng-Ming Hsu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>886-2-23123456</phone>
      <phone_ext>67061</phone_ext>
      <email>hsufengming@ntuh.gov.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 25, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stereotactic ablative radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>spine metastasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

