<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02609100</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201507101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02609100</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Video Capsule Endoscopy Versus Colonoscopy in Patients With Melena and Negative Upper Endoscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Video Capsule Endoscopy Versus Colonoscopy in Patients With Melena and Negative Upper Endoscopy: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute gastrointestinal bleeding is a common medical problem. When patients with
      gastrointestinal bleeding present with melena (dark, tarry stool) the blood loss is usually
      originating in the upper gastrointestinal tract (esophagus, stomach or duodenum) and first
      step in evaluating the patient is an upper endoscopy; which allows direct visualization of
      the esophagus, stomach and duodenum. However, the cause of bleeding is located in the small
      bowel or colon in 20-30% of patients who present with melena. Traditionally colonoscopy has
      been the next test preformed if upper endoscopy does not identify the cause of melena/
      gastrointestinal bleeding, however less than 25% of patients who present with melena have
      bleeding originating in the colon, and the remainder of patients have bleeding originating in
      the small intestine, which can only be fully evaluated with video capsule endoscopy (a pill
      camera which is swallowed and takes pictures while it travels thought the small bowel and
      colon). Currently patients only undergo video capsule endoscopy if colonoscopy does not
      identify the cause of bleeding. The investigators are preforming a randomized study which
      seeks to determine if colonoscopy or video capsule endoscopy is a better way to identify the
      cause of gastrointestinal bleeding in patients who present with melena and have normal
      findings on upper endoscopy. To do this the investigators will enroll patients who present
      with melena prior to their upper endoscopy and if the cause of bleeding is not identified at
      that time patients will be randomized to video capsule endoscopy (with the capsule being
      placed into the small bowel during the upper endoscopy) or next day colonoscopy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Poor enrollment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 6, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 6, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with clinically significant findings defined as lesions considered to have a high potential for bleeding to participants with no significant findings from Video Capsule Endoscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to twenty four hours</time_frame>
    <description>Video Capsule Endoscopy identifies clinically significant lesions defined as lesions considered to have high potential for bleeding, such as a large ulceration, tumor or typical angiomata</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of participants with clinically significant findings defined as lesions considered to have a high potential for bleeding to participants with no significant findings from Colonoscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one hour</time_frame>
    <description>Colonoscopy identifies clinically significant lesions defined as lesions considered to have high potential for bleeding, such as a large ulceration, tumor or typical angiomata</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Therapeutic yield of video capsule endoscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Therapeutic yield of video capsule endoscopy is defined as the proportion of endoscopies leading to a therapeutic intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Therapeutic yield of colonoscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Therapeutic yield of colonoscopy is defined as the proportion of endoscopies leading to a therapeutic intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of blood transfused</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days</time_frame>
    <description>Units of blood transfused measured in units of packed red blood cells</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of diagnostic studies performed for evaluation of gastrointestinal bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days</time_frame>
    <description>Includes repeat endoscopies or imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of hospital stay will be recorded in number of days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events related to the video capsule endoscopy and colonoscopy will be recorded</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Video Capsule Endoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Randomization arm one is to video capsule endoscopy (VCE) a non-invasive gastrointestinal endoscopy procedure in which a patient swallows a disposable 1.0 X 2.5 cm 'pill' containing a camera electronically linked to equipment housed in a holster outside of the patient which records images as it passes from the esophagus through the entire tract and is excreted in the feces.
Indications Imaging the small intestine between the distant duodeno-jejunal 'junction,' which is beyond the reach of upper GI endoscopy and the terminal ileum and is similarly beyond the reach of colonoscopy. It is of greatest use in identifying points of bleeding and ulcers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Next Day Colonoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Randomization arm two is to colonoscopy, a test that allows the doctor to look at the inner lining of the large intestine (rectum and colon). He or she uses a thin, flexible tube called a colonoscope to look at the colon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Video Capsule Endoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Video Capsule Endoscopy allows for imaging of the small intestine between the distant duodeno-jejunal junction, which is beyond the reach of upper GI endoscopy and the terminal ileum and is similarly beyond the reach of colonoscopy. It is of greatest use in identifying points of bleeding and ulcers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Video Capsule Endoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colonoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>The colonoscopy helps find ulcers, tumors, and areas of inflammation or bleeding in the large intestine.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Next Day Colonoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>1.0 X 2.5 cm 'pill' containing a camera</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Video Capsule Endoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • Inpatients &gt;18 years of age presenting with lower gastrointestinal bleeding and have
        melenic stool

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide written informed consent

          -  A probable bleeding source is identified on upper endoscopy

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Swallowing Disorder

          -  Unable to tolerate sedation or anesthesia due to medical co-morbidities

          -  Uncorrected coagulopathy (platelet count &lt;50,000, INR&gt; 2, PTT&gt; 2x upper limit of
             normal)

          -  Known or suspected gastrointestinal obstruction or stricture

          -  Cardiac pacemaker or other implanted electromedical device

          -  Contraindication to bowel preparation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vladimir M Kushnir, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Advanced Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>February 2, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>February 26, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>March 20, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>April 19, 2018</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

