<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02601716</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NMRC.2015.0009</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CVD Malaria 26000</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02601716</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PfSPZ Vaccine: Dose Optimization With Heterologous Challenge in Healthy Malaria-Naïve Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Trial of PfSPZ Vaccine Administered by Direct Venous Inoculation: Dose Optimization With Heterologous Challenge in Healthy Malaria-Naïve Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanaria Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Naval Medical Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Walter Reed Army Institute of Research (WRAIR)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Joint Warfighter Medical Research Program</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanaria Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label evaluation of the safety, tolerability, immunogenicity and efficacy of
      PfSPZ Vaccine administered by direct venous inoculation (DVI) in healthy, malaria-naïve adult
      subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be conducted as a collaborative effort between the NMRC, UMB CVD, WRAIR and
      Sanaria, Inc. The study screening, immunizations, and follow-ups for Groups 1 &amp; 2 will take
      place at the UMB CVD. The study screening, immunizations, and follow-ups for Groups 3 &amp; 4
      will take place at the NMRC CTC in Bethesda, MD. The controlled human malaria infections
      (CHMI) will be conducted at WRAIR Entomology, Silver Spring, MD for NMRC subjects, and at UMB
      CVD for UMB CVD subjects.

      There will be 4 groups and a total of 92 subjects (60 immunized subjects and 32 infectivity
      controls). Group 1 (n = 15) subjects will receive PfSPZ Vaccine administered by direct venous
      inoculation (DVI), with 4 doses of 4.5 x 10^5 PfSPZ given every two days, followed by a
      single, boosting dose of 4.5 x 10^5 PfSPZ given 16 weeks later. For participants who were not
      protected after the first CHMI, an additional boosting dose of 4.5x10^5 PfSPZ will be given
      21 weeks later. Group 2 (n = 15) subjects will receive PfSPZ Vaccine administered by DVI,
      with 3 doses of 9.0 x 10^5 PfSPZ administered every 8 weeks. For participants who were not
      protected after the first CHMI, a boosting dose of 9.0 x 10^5 PfSPZ will be given 21 weeks
      later. Group 3 (n = 15) subjects will receive PfSPZ Vaccine administered by DVI, with 3 doses
      of 18 x 10^5 PfSPZ administered every 8 weeks. Following CHMI at 40 weeks, protected subjects
      and one-half of unprotected subjects will receive a final, boosting dose of 18 x 10^5 PfSPZ.
      The remaining half of unprotected subjects will receive a final, boosting dose of 4.5 x 10^5
      PfSPZ. Group 4 (n = 15) subjects will receive PfSPZ Vaccine administered by DVI, with 27 x
      10^5 PfSPZ administered once as a priming dose, followed by 2 doses of 9.0 x 10^5 PfSPZ
      administered every 8 weeks. Following CHMI at 40 weeks, protected subjects and one-half of
      unprotected subjects will receive a final, boosting dose of 9 x 10^5 PfSPZ. The remaining
      half of unprotected subjects will receive a final, boosting dose of 2.25 x 10^5 PfSPZ.

      Protective efficacy will be assessed by CHMI, conducted by exposure to the bites of three to
      five mosquitoes infected with heterologous (7G8 or NF135.C10) Pf parasites, with the number
      of mosquitoes depending on the infection intensity in the mosquitoes). At UMB CVD, protective
      efficacy will be assessed at both 28 and 40 weeks after the first immunization, in Groups 1
      and 2. At NMRC, protective efficacy will be assessed at 40 and 66 weeks after the first
      immunization, in Groups 3 and 4. Unprotected subjects in Groups 1 and 2, and all subjects in
      Groups 3 and 4, will be invited to receive a booster vaccination 21 days prior to the second
      CHMI at the respective sites, in order to assess the efficacy of a booster dose in previously
      vaccinated persons. These vaccine subjects may participate in the second CHMI whether or not
      they were protected in the first CHMI, and independent of their decision to receive the
      booster immunization, to serve as controls for the effect of the first CHMI on immunity.
      Subjects may proceed to CHMI provided they have received at least two of the three
      immunizations scheduled for Groups 2-4, or at least two of the four priming immunizations as
      well as the boost scheduled for Group 1. 7G8-infected mosquitoes may be substituted for
      NF135.C10 mosquitoes in case of difficulties with mosquito production.

      Two subjects in Group 4 will be immunized the day before the rest of the subjects in the
      respective group (referred to as &quot;pilot subjects&quot;) for the first immunization in humans (27 x
      10^5 PfSPZ per dose). The procedure and sequence of events for immunization of the pilot
      subjects, and the rest of the subjects in the respective group will be specific to the study
      site. If there are no safety concerns identified in the pilot subjects that trigger the
      stopping rules, then the remainder of subjects will be immunized the day after the pilot
      subjects are immunized. Subjects will be followed for 56 days beyond both the week 40 and
      week 66 CHMIs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and type of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and type of adverse events (including breakthrough infections), vital signs, clinical laboratory assessments, physical examination findings post first immunization onwards.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days post-CHMI</time_frame>
    <description>Evidence of vaccine-mediated protection against CHMI 24 weeks after last immunization in Groups 1, 2, 3, and 4 by preventing blood stage infection for 28 days (as detected by blood smear analysis) following CHMI.
Evidence of vaccine-mediated protection against CHMI 12 weeks after last immunization in Groups 1 and 2 by preventing blood stage infection for 28 days (as detected by blood smear analysis) following CHMI.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks post-immunization and 28 days post-CHMI</time_frame>
    <description>Antibody responses by PfCSP ELISA two weeks after the second and third immunizations (Groups 2-4) or after the fourth and fifth immunizations (Group 1) (serum dilution at which the optical density is 1.0 referred to as the OD 1.0)
Positive predictive values for anti-PfCSP antibody responses at or above a threshold for predicting sterile protection following CHMI (threshold = OD 1.0 of 2,000)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of immunization till 28 days post-CHMI</time_frame>
    <description>Antibody titers to other Pf proteins by ELISA
Antibody titers to Pf parasite stages by IFA
Capacity of sera from immunized volunteers to inhibit sporozoite invasion (ISI) of hepatocytes in vitro by ISI assay
Analysis of antibodies to any of the thousands of proteins in the Pf proteome using proteome array chips
Analysis of cellular immune responses against PfSPZ, Pf-infected erythrocytes and/or synthetic peptides and/or recombinant proteins from defined Pf proteins by multi-parameter intracellular staining (ICS) by flow cytometry
Analysis of cellular immune responses against PfSPZ, Pf-infected erythrocytes and/or synthetic peptides and/or recombinant proteins from defined Pf proteins by fluorospot assays
Human gene expression profiling focusing on immune response genes
Analysis of host cellular, cytokine and other host responses by Luminex or Luminex-type assays</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">92</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1 subjects (n=15) will receive 4 doses of PfSPZ Vaccine (4.5 x 10^5 PfSPZ/dose) every 2 days, followed by a single, boosting dose (same dose as before) given 16 weeks later, for a total PfSPZ dose = 22.5 x 10^5. PfSPZ Vaccine administered by DVI.
Protective efficacy assessed by heterologous CHMI (7G8) Pf parasites at 28 and 40 weeks after the first immunization, along with 8 infectivity controls. Subjects may proceed to CHMI if they have received at least 2 of 4 priming immunizations and the boost scheduled for Group 1. Participants not protected after the first CHMI will be invited to receive a booster vaccination (4.5 x 10^5 PfSPZ) 21 days prior to the second CHMI. Subjects may participate in the second CHMI whether or not they were protected in the 1st CHMI, to serve as controls for the effect of the 1st CHMI on immunity.
Subjects will be followed for 56 days beyond the final CHMI (post-immunization week 40).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects (n=15) will receive 3 doses of PfSPZ Vaccine (9.0 x 10^5 PfSPZ/dose) every 8 weeks, total PfSPZ dose = 27 x 10^5. PfSPZ Vaccine administered by DVI.
Protective efficacy assessed by heterologous CHMI (7G8) Pf parasites at 28 and 40 weeks after first immunization, along with 8 infectivity controls. Subjects may proceed to CHMI if they have received at least 2 of 3 immunizations scheduled for Group 2. Participants not protected after the first CHMI will be invited to receive a booster vaccination (9.0 x 10^5 PfSPZ) 21 days prior to the second CHMI. Subjects may participate in the second CHMI whether or not they were protected in the 1st CHMI, to serve as controls for the effect of the 1st CHMI on immunity.
Subjects will be followed for 56 days beyond the final CHMI (post-immunization week 40).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 3 subjects (n=15) will receive 3 doses of PfSPZ Vaccine (18 x 10^5 PfSPZ/dose) every 8 weeks for a total PfSPZ dose of 54 x 10^5. PfSPZ Vaccine administered by DVI.
Protective efficacy assessed by CHMI with heterologous (7G8, NF135.C10) Pf parasites at 40 and 66 weeks after the first immunization, along with 8 infectivity controls. Subjects may proceed to CHMI if they have received at least 2 of 3 immunizations scheduled for Group 3. All participants will be invited to receive a booster vaccination (18 x 10^5 PfSPZ) 21 days prior to the second CHMI. Subjects may participate in the second CHMI whether or not they were protected in the 1st CHMI, to serve as controls for the effect of the 1st CHMI on immunity.
Subjects will be followed for 56 days beyond the final CHMI (post-immunization week66).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects (n=15) will receive a single, priming dose of PfSPZ Vaccine (27 x 10^5 PfSPZ/dose), followed by 2 additional immunizations (9.0 x 10^5 PfSPZ per dose) every 8 weeks, total PfSPZ dose = 45 x 10^5. PfSPZ Vaccine administered by DVI.
Protective efficacy assessed by CHMI with heterologous 7G8 and NF135.C10 Pf parasites at 40 and 66 weeks, respectively, along with 8 infectivity controls at each CHMI. Subjects may proceed to CHMI if they have received at least 2 of 3 immunizations scheduled for Group 4. All participants will be invited to receive a booster vaccination (9.0x10^5 PfSPZ) 21 days prior to the second CHMI.
Subjects will be followed for 56 days beyond the final CHMI at (post-immunization week 66).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Infectivity Controls, CHMI (7G8)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infectivity controls (n=24) will not receive any PfSPZ Vaccine. They will serve as infectivity controls for CHMI for all groups. 8 infectivity controls will undergo CHMI with each of two CHMIs (at 28 and 40) for Groups 1 and 2, and 8 infectivity controls will undergo CHMI with the 40 week CHMI for Groups 3 and 4. All CHMI will be conducted by exposure to the bites of 5 mosquitoes infected with heterologous (7G8) Pf parasites. Subjects will be followed for 56 days beyond the last CHMI at week 40 at the UMB site.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Infectivity Controls, CHMI (NF135.C10)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infectivity controls (n=8) will not receive any PfSPZ Vaccine. They will serve as infectivity controls for the second CHMI at week 66 for Groups 3 and 4. CHMI will be conducted by exposure to the bites of 3-5 mosquitoes infected with heterologous (NF135.C10) Pf parasites. Subjects will be followed for 56 days beyond the last CHMI at week 66 at the NMRC site.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PfSPZ Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Aseptic, purified, cryopreserved, radiation-attenuated, Plasmodium falciparum (Pf) sporozoites</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CHMI (7G8)</intervention_name>
    <description>CHMI is conducted by exposure to the bites of five mosquitoes infected with heterologous (7G8) Pf parasites.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Infectivity Controls, CHMI (7G8)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CHMI (NF135.C10)</intervention_name>
    <description>CHMI is conducted by exposure to the bites of three to five mosquitoes infected with heterologous (NF135.C10) Pf parasites.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Infectivity Controls, CHMI (NF135.C10)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adults (male or non-pregnant female) 18 - 50 years of age, inclusive.

          -  Able and willing to participate for the duration of the study.

          -  Able and willing to provide written (not proxy) informed consent.

          -  Physical examination and laboratory results without clinically significant findings
             and a body mass index (BMI) ≤35 for vaccine groups or BMI ≤40 for control groups.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must agree to use effective means of birth control
             (e.g. oral or implanted contraceptives, IUD, female condom, diaphragm with spermicide,
             cervical cap, abstinence, use of a condom by the sexual partner or sterile sexual
             partner) during the entire study. Women with a history of surgical or chemical
             sterilization (e.g. tubal ligation, hysterectomy, other) must provide written
             documentation of infertility from a health care provider.

          -  Willing to refrain from blood donation for 3 years following CHMI.

          -  Agree not to travel to a malaria endemic region during the entire course of the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any history of malaria infection, or travel to a malaria endemic region within 6
             months prior to first immunization.

          -  History of long-term residence (&gt;5 years) in area known to have significant
             transmission of P. falciparum.

          -  Body weight equal to, or less than, 110 pounds.

          -  Has evidence of increased cardiovascular disease risk (defined as &gt; 10%, 5 year risk)
             as determined by the method of Gaziano [Gaziano, 2008]. Risk factors include sex, age,
             systolic blood pressure (mm Hg), smoking status, body mass index (BMI, kg/mm2), and
             reported diabetes status.

          -  Positive HIV, HBsAg or HCV serology.

          -  Positive sickle cell screening test.

          -  An abnormal electrocardiogram, defined as one showing pathologic Q waves and
             significant ST-T wave changes; left ventricular hypertrophy; any non-sinus rhythm
             including isolated premature ventricular contractions, but excluding isolated
             premature atrial contractions; right or left bundle branch block; or advanced
             (secondary or tertiary) A-V heart block.

          -  Current use of systemic immunosuppressant pharmacotherapy.

          -  Current significant medical condition (cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, or
             hematological) or evidence of any other serious underlying medical condition
             identified by medical history, physical examination, or laboratory examination.

          -  History of a splenectomy.

          -  History of neurologic disorder (including seizures) or diagnosis of migraine headache.

          -  History of psychiatric disorders (such as personality disorders, anxiety disorders, or
             schizophrenia) or behavioral tendencies (including active alcohol or drug abuse)
             discovered during the screening process that in the opinion of the investigator would
             make compliance with the protocol difficult.

          -  Plan for surgery between enrollment and CHMI.

          -  Females who are pregnant or nursing, females who plan on becoming pregnant or plan to
             nurse during the study period.

          -  Known allergy to any component of the vaccine formulation, history of anaphylactic
             response to mosquito-bites, or any history of anaphylactic reaction, retinal or visual
             field changes, or known allergy to anti-malarials including chloroquine phosphate,
             atovaquone/proguanil (Malarone®), or artemether/lumefantrine (Coartem®).

          -  Receipt of another investigational vaccine or drug within 30 days prior to the first
             immunization, or plan to participate in another investigational vaccine/drug research
             during or within 1 month following participation in this study (vaccine recipients).

          -  Receipt of another investigational vaccine or drug within 30 days prior to CHMI, or
             plan to participate in another investigational vaccine/drug research during or within
             1 month following participation in this study (infectivity controls).

          -  Receipt of more than three other vaccines during the period 60 days prior to the
             screening visit to 1 month following participation in this study.

          -  Personal beliefs that prohibit the receiving of vaccine product containing human serum
             albumin within the diluent (vaccine recipients only).

          -  Use or planned use of any drug with anti-malarial activity that would coincide with
             the periods of immunization or CHMI.

          -  Anticipated use of medications known to cause drug reactions with atovaquone-proguanil
             (Malarone®), or artemether/lumefantrine (Coartem®) such as cimetidine, metoclopramide,
             antacids, and kaolin.

          -  History of any other illness or condition which, in the investigator's judgment, may
             substantially increase the risk associated with the subject's participation in the
             protocol or compromise the scientific objectives.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexandra Singer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Naval Medical Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland-Baltimore, Center for Vaccine Development</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Naval Medical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Silver Spring</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20910</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seder RA, Chang LJ, Enama ME, Zephir KL, Sarwar UN, Gordon IJ, Holman LA, James ER, Billingsley PF, Gunasekera A, Richman A, Chakravarty S, Manoj A, Velmurugan S, Li M, Ruben AJ, Li T, Eappen AG, Stafford RE, Plummer SH, Hendel CS, Novik L, Costner PJ, Mendoza FH, Saunders JG, Nason MC, Richardson JH, Murphy J, Davidson SA, Richie TL, Sedegah M, Sutamihardja A, Fahle GA, Lyke KE, Laurens MB, Roederer M, Tewari K, Epstein JE, Sim BK, Ledgerwood JE, Graham BS, Hoffman SL; VRC 312 Study Team. Protection against malaria by intravenous immunization with a nonreplicating sporozoite vaccine. Science. 2013 Sep 20;341(6152):1359-65. doi: 10.1126/science.1241800. Epub 2013 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23929949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein JE, Tewari K, Lyke KE, Sim BK, Billingsley PF, Laurens MB, Gunasekera A, Chakravarty S, James ER, Sedegah M, Richman A, Velmurugan S, Reyes S, Li M, Tucker K, Ahumada A, Ruben AJ, Li T, Stafford R, Eappen AG, Tamminga C, Bennett JW, Ockenhouse CF, Murphy JR, Komisar J, Thomas N, Loyevsky M, Birkett A, Plowe CV, Loucq C, Edelman R, Richie TL, Seder RA, Hoffman SL. Live attenuated malaria vaccine designed to protect through hepatic CD8⁺ T cell immunity. Science. 2011 Oct 28;334(6055):475-80. doi: 10.1126/science.1211548. Epub 2011 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21903775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ishizuka AS, Lyke KE, DeZure A, Berry AA, Richie TL, Mendoza FH, Enama ME, Gordon IJ, Chang LJ, Sarwar UN, Zephir KL, Holman LA, James ER, Billingsley PF, Gunasekera A, Chakravarty S, Manoj A, Li M, Ruben AJ, Li T, Eappen AG, Stafford RE, K C N, Murshedkar T, DeCederfelt H, Plummer SH, Hendel CS, Novik L, Costner PJ, Saunders JG, Laurens MB, Plowe CV, Flynn B, Whalen WR, Todd JP, Noor J, Rao S, Sierra-Davidson K, Lynn GM, Epstein JE, Kemp MA, Fahle GA, Mikolajczak SA, Fishbaugher M, Sack BK, Kappe SH, Davidson SA, Garver LS, Björkström NK, Nason MC, Graham BS, Roederer M, Sim BK, Hoffman SL, Ledgerwood JE, Seder RA. Protection against malaria at 1 year and immune correlates following PfSPZ vaccination. Nat Med. 2016 Jun;22(6):614-23. doi: 10.1038/nm.4110. Epub 2016 May 9. Erratum in: Nat Med. 2016 Jun 7;22(6):692.</citation>
    <PMID>27158907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lyke KE, Ishizuka AS, Berry AA, Chakravarty S, DeZure A, Enama ME, James ER, Billingsley PF, Gunasekera A, Manoj A, Li M, Ruben AJ, Li T, Eappen AG, Stafford RE, Kc N, Murshedkar T, Mendoza FH, Gordon IJ, Zephir KL, Holman LA, Plummer SH, Hendel CS, Novik L, Costner PJ, Saunders JG, Berkowitz NM, Flynn BJ, Nason MC, Garver LS, Laurens MB, Plowe CV, Richie TL, Graham BS, Roederer M, Sim BK, Ledgerwood JE, Hoffman SL, Seder RA. Attenuated PfSPZ Vaccine induces strain-transcending T cells and durable protection against heterologous controlled human malaria infection. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2017 Mar 7;114(10):2711-2716. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1615324114. Epub 2017 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>28223498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein JE, Paolino KM, Richie TL, Sedegah M, Singer A, Ruben AJ, Chakravarty S, Stafford A, Ruck RC, Eappen AG, Li T, Billingsley PF, Manoj A, Silva JC, Moser K, Nielsen R, Tosh D, Cicatelli S, Ganeshan H, Case J, Padilla D, Davidson S, Garver L, Saverino E, Murshedkar T, Gunasekera A, Twomey PS, Reyes S, Moon JE, James ER, Kc N, Li M, Abot E, Belmonte A, Hauns K, Belmonte M, Huang J, Vasquez C, Remich S, Carrington M, Abebe Y, Tillman A, Hickey B, Regules J, Villasante E, Sim BK, Hoffman SL. Protection against Plasmodium falciparum malaria by PfSPZ Vaccine. JCI Insight. 2017 Jan 12;2(1):e89154. doi: 10.1172/jci.insight.89154.</citation>
    <PMID>28097230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Plasmodium falciparum</keyword>
  <keyword>PfSPZ Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Sporozoites</keyword>
  <keyword>Controlled Human Malaria Infection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

