<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02608307</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AYACA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02608307</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Medical Treatment Decision Making Using Adaptive Conjoint Analysis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Adolescent and Young Adult, Parental, and Health Care Provider Decision Making Using Conjoint Analysis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the setting of progressive or recurrent cancer, adolescent and young adult (AYA) patients,
      parents, and healthcare providers (HCP) are faced with multiple therapeutic options. Each
      treatment option has a unique risk/benefit ratio, resulting in a need to trade one desirable
      outcome for another or accept acute toxicities and treatment-related morbidity to increase
      the chance of survival. Adding to the complexity of this decision, stake holders characterize
      and value the risk/benefit ratios differently.

      This study seeks to learn what things are important to an adolescent or young adult with
      cancer, parents, and health care providers when making decisions about their treatment
      choices.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE: To quantify the relative importance of various factors believed to be
      important to adolescent and young adult patients with cancer, parents, and health care
      providers when choosing between treatment options in the hypothetical situation of
      progressive or refractory disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Data for this observational study will be collected first at the time the participants enroll
      in the study. If the participant agrees to be re-contacted in the event of disease relapse or
      recurrent cancer, follow-up data will be collected at a second time point up to five years
      after enrollment. This second follow-up time point is optional.

      Participants will complete two short surveys, a guided survey on a laptop computer, and
      interviewer-led interview session. The surveys are the Herth Hope Index (HHI) to assess hope
      in adults in clinical settings, and the Decision Making Preference Questionnaire (DMPQ) to
      identify factors that parents believe influence their role in treatment decision making. The
      guided survey presents a hypothetical situation outlining different treatment options at the
      time of recurrent or progressive disease. Participants will be asked to answer questions
      related to type of treatment, location of treatment, symptoms or side effects from treatment,
      quality of life, chance of unplanned hospitalization, chance of cure, and survival length of
      time.

      Data will be analyzed by group: (1) adolescent and young adult patients, (2) parents, or (3)
      health-care providers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 9, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Once at participant enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Conjoint analysis picks a small subset of possible answer combinations and combination sets and asks respondents which option (profile) they prefer in each set. This data is compiled and a hierarchical Bayesian approach, as implanted in Sawtooth Software package, is used to evaluate the relationship between various attributes and the decision choice. The relative importance of various factors on the decision making process will be evaluated for three groups (patients, parents and HCPs) independently, i.e. by generating three separate models, using Sawtooth software package. At the completion of the survey, the part worth and importance for each different treatment attribute (type, location, symptoms of side effects, change of unplanned hospitalization, quality of life, change of cure, and survival length of time) and levels of treatment (standard chemotherapy, experimental therapy, palliative oral chemotherapy, or no further cancer-directed therapy) of each attributes is calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Brain Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients, parents and health care providers who meet eligibility criteria and consent to participate in the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants will be patients at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital, their parents and
        health-care providers who consent to enroll in the study. All participants must meet
        inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be English speaking.

          -  There are three main participant subsets for the first time point of the study:

               -  AYA patients (aged 13-30) with an oncological diagnosis who are currently
                  receiving active treatment at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital that includes
                  at least chemotherapy, and have been doing so for at least three months.

               -  Parents of a patient (&lt;18) who meets the above criteria. If available, parents of
                  a young adult patient (≥18) who meets the above criteria will be invited to
                  participate.

               -  HCPs of patients at St. Jude with at least 1 year of experience taking care of
                  AYA oncology patients. HCPs must have an MD or DO degree and be an attending
                  physician or clinical fellow at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital.

          -  Patient participants must have an oncological diagnosis that confers less than a 75%
             overall survival based on consultation with an oncologist.

          -  Participants who agree to be re-contacted up to five years later, to consider taking
             part in the T2 time point, must have participated in the T1 time point and the patient
             participant must have relapsed or recurrent disease at the time of re- contact, as
             documented in the medical record.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with relapsed or recurrent disease at the time of initial enrollment.

          -  Patients who only receive local radiation for treatment without adjunctive
             chemotherapy.

          -  Patients or parents who are unable to complete the study due to ill health, cognitive
             compromise, or concern about potential distress based on consultation with a
             psychosocial provider.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lindsay Blazin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lindsay Blazin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
    <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>lindsay Blazin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
      <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lindsay Blazin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
    <description>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org/protocols</url>
    <description>Clinical Trials Open at St. Jude</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Treatment Decision-Making</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents and Young Adult Oncology</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

