<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02608905</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-35985</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02608905</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Dapagliflozin on Inflammation and Endothelial Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Dapagliflozin on Inflammation and Endothelial Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Sodium-glucose cotransporter 2 (SGLT-2) inhibitors reduce hyperglycemia and improve
      peripheral insulin sensitivity by ameliorating glucotoxicity. Insulin resistance in type 2
      diabetes (T2DM) is associated with endothelial dysfunction and vascular inflammation. Thus
      strategies to improve insulin sensitivity and lower glucotoxicity may improve endothelial
      inflammation and vascular inflammation. However, the effects of these agents on vascular
      inflammation and endothelial function is not known in patients with type 2 diabetes although
      anti-inflammatory properties have been demonstrated in various animal models. In the present
      study the investigators will assess if dapagliflozin treatment for 12 weeks decreases
      monocyte inflammation and improves endothelial function in patients with type 2 diabetes on
      metformin monotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The insulin-resistant state of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is largely mediated by
      inflammatory pathways affecting skeletal muscle which is the primary site of whole body
      insulin resistance. Nuclear factor kappa B (NFkappaB) regulates pro-inflammatory cytokines
      which ultimately impair skeletal muscle insulin signaling and fatty acid oxidation; its
      activity reflects overall inflammatory tone in skeletal muscle. Recent human studies confirm
      that NFkappaB is elevated in the skeletal muscle of T2DM human subjects. Furthermore, the
      same inflammatory processes and signaling impairments contribute to worsening endothelial
      dysfunction, which is an independent predictor for future cardiovascular events in T2DM. In
      addition, these SGLT-2 Inhibitors reduce body weight, visceral adiposity, systolic and
      diastolic blood pressure, microalbuminuria, and oxidative stress. However, there are no
      studies examining the effects of SGLT-2 inhibitor therapy on NFkappaB and other inflammatory
      mediators in humans with T2DM. Moreover, no studies have examined the effect of SGLT-2
      inhibitor therapy on endothelial function in this population. In the present study the
      investigators will assess whether dapagliflozin treatment for 12 weeks reduces monocyte
      inflammation and improves endothelial dysfunction in patients with type 2 diabetes on
      metformin monotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Monocyte inflammatory protein Nuclear Factor kappa-B (NFkappaB) (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage change in monocyte inflammatory proteins NFkappaB (%) from baseline in patients with type 2 diabetes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial Flow Mediated Dilatation (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage change in arterial flow mediated dilation (%) from baseline as measured by ultrasound in patients with type 2 diabetes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dapagliflozin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dapagliflozin 5 mg daily by mouth for 2 weeks followed by 10 mg by mouth daily for 10 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablets by mouth daily for 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dapagliflozin</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with Type 2 diabetes will be randomized to receive dapagliflozin 5 mg daily for 2 weeks followed by10 mg daily for 10 weeks by mouth or matching placebo for 12 weeks. All subjects will receive measurements of fasting plasma glucose, Free Fatty Acids, inflammatory markers and adipocytokines, monocyte inflammation, as well as ultrasound assessment of flow-mediated dilatation (FMD) of the brachial artery at baseline and after 12 weeks of drug treatment with either dapagliflozin or placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dapagliflozin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Farxiga</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with Type 2 diabetes will be randomized to receive dapagliflozin 5 mg daily for 2 weeks followed by10 mg daily for 10 weeks by mouth or matching placebo for 12 weeks. All subjects will receive measurements of fasting plasma glucose, Free Fatty Acids, inflammatory markers and adipocytokines, monocyte inflammation, as well as ultrasound assessment of flow-mediated dilatation (FMD) of the brachial artery at baseline and after 12 weeks of drug treatment with either dapagliflozin or placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Provision of informed consent prior to any study specific procedures

          2. Men and women, ages 21 to 70 years. i) Women of childbearing potential must be using
             an acceptable method of contraception to avoid pregnancy throughout the study in such
             a manner that the risk of pregnancy is minimized.

             ii) Women must not be pregnant or breastfeeding.

          3. Patients with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus with the following parameters at study entry:
             hemoglobin A1c ranging from 7.0% to 9.0% and a fasting blood glucose less than or
             equal to 200 mg/dL.

          4. Patients must be on a stable dose of Metformin therapy for 3 months; the dose of
             metformin will not change for the duration of the study.

          5. Patients are allowed, but not required, to be on statins, Angiotensin Converting
             Enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, and angiotensin-receptor blockers at doses that have been
             stable for at least the last 3 months prior to enrollment in the study. Doses will not
             be changed for the duration of the study.

          6. Patients must have a Body Mass Index between 27-35 kg/m2

          7. Patients must have a stable body weight for three months prior to enrollment in the
             study.

          8. Patients must have a Creatinine Clearance greater than 60 mL/min (calculated by
             Cockcroft-Gault formula).

          9. Patients must have Hematocrit greater than or equal to 34%; Serum creatinine less
             than1.5 mg/dl in men and 1.4 mg/dl in women and Creatinine Clearance greater than 60
             ml/min; and serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) less than 2.5 times upper limit of
             normal, serum alanine transaminase (ALT) less than 2.5 times upper limit of normal,
             serum alkaline phosphatase less than 2.5 times upper limit of normal.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of Type 1 diabetes mellitus

          2. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding

          3. Patients receiving lipid-lowering medications other than statins within the last 3
             months.

          4. Patient receiving SGLT-2 inhibitors, incretin therapy, dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP-4)
             inhibitors, thiazolidinediones, insulin, sulfonylureas, alpha-glucosidase inhibitors,
             corticosteroids, immunosuppressive therapy, thiazide or loop diuretics, or hormone
             replacement therapy within the last 3 months .

          5. Patient must stop treatment with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID) and
             antioxidant vitamin supplements at least one week prior to the start of the study

          6. Patients with diabetic gastroparesis.

          7. Patients with current tobacco use.

          8. Patients with active malignancy.

          9. Patients with history of urinary bladder cancer

         10. Patients with a history of clinically significant heart disease, peripheral vascular
             disease, or pulmonary disease will not be studied

         11. Subjects with a history of any serious hypersensitivity reaction to dapagliflozin.

         12. Prisoners, or subjects who are involuntarily incarcerated.

         13. Subjects who are compulsorily detained for treatment of either a psychiatric or
             physical (eg, infectious disease) illness.

         14. Patients with significant cardiac,hepatic or renal disease (Creatinine Clearance less
             than 60 mL/min calculated by Cockcroft-Gault formula) will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mandeep Bajaj, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mandeep Bajaj, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-798-1712</phone>
    <email>bajaj@bcm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mandeep Bajaj, MD</last_name>
      <phone>713-798-1712</phone>
      <email>bajaj@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 17, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mandeep Bajaj</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

