<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02601183</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ThirdMMU-tl</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02601183</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cranial Temperature Early Diagnose Hemorrhagic and Ischemic Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>CTedHI</acronym>
  <official_title>Cranial Temperature, as an Early Diagnosis Marker for Hemorrhagic and Ischemic Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Third Military Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Third Military Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The cerebrovascular diseases can be approximately divided as two types, namely ischemic and
      hemorrhagic stroke. Intravenous thrombolysis within 3-4.5 hours is highly recommended for
      acute ischemic stroke patients. But it's difficult to diagnose the ischemic stroke with the
      hemorrhagic stroke from the early symptoms and signs. It's with high risk of enlarging the
      hematoma if the patients with hemorrhagic stroke received the thrombolytic drugs. And time
      cost by CT or MRI examination is likely to responsible for missing the narrow time window and
      poor prognosis of stroke patients. Consequently, seeking for a noninvasive, rapid, portable
      and inexpensive diagnosis method which can sensitively distinguish the stroke type before CT
      or MRI examination would be very helpful in treating the ischemic stroke patients.

      Because of the blockage in the cerebral supply artery, the heat from circulatory system will
      sharply decrease in infracted hemisphere among the ischemic stroke patients. The reduced
      brain temperature influenced the temperature on the ipsilateral forehead according to the
      data of our animal and preliminary clinical trial. In contrast, the temperature of the
      ipsilateral hemisphere showed a mild increase among the ischemic stroke patients in our
      preliminary experiment. The difference of the temperature tendency on the ipsilateral
      forehead has a great chance to be an early physical mark.

      In our study, 30 ischemic stroke patients and 30 hemorrhagic stroke patients will be
      recruited. In the process of recruitment, the patients with acute stroke attack in no more
      than 4.5 hours will be collected the temperature at the five point without head coverage,
      including ipsilateral tempora, ipsilateral forehead, galbella, contralateral forehead, and
      contralateral tempora. Then the stroke would be recruited into the ischemic and hemorrhagic
      group according to the later CT or MRI results in the hospital. The accuracy and sensibility
      of early brain temperature in distinguishing stroke type would be tested in comparison with
      the diagnosis of imaging examination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stroke is the leading cause of morbidity and disability among the aged population around the
      world, and its incidence is still rising recently. The cerebrovascular diseases can be
      approximately divided as two types, namely ischemic and hemorrhagic stroke. Their
      pathophysiological processes and therapeutical strategies are totally different. For
      hemorrhagic stroke, which takes up about 20% patients with cerebrovascular diseases, there is
      a lack of valid medical management in the very early stage except surgical hematoma removal.
      Whereas it's the key management for ischemic stroke to recanalize the occluded artery and
      restore blood flow before the irreversible brain damage. According the Guidelines for the
      Prevention of Stroke in Patients with Stroke and Transient Ischemic Attack, intravenous
      thrombolysis within 3-4.5 hours is highly recommended for acute ischemic stroke patients. The
      time window of thrombolysis after ischemic stroke is extremely narrow and greatly affected
      the patients' outcomes.

      Despite the efficacious therapy exists, the rate of successful early thrombolysis is still
      awfully low, especially in the developing countries. Only 3-5% stroke patients can take
      advantage of the early thrombolysis. There are two major reasons response for such a low
      successful thrombolysis rate, including the civilian and some first-aid personnel hasn't
      mastered the timing of thrombolysis therapy for ischemic stroke. That would be improved by
      propaganda and education of the stroke knowledge. But what's more critical is the difficulty
      to diagnose the ischemic stroke with the hemorrhagic stroke from the early symptoms and
      signs. It's with high risk of enlarging the hematoma if the patients with hemorrhagic stroke
      received the thrombolytic drugs. For this reason, it's hard for the doctors to provide the
      correct treatment at the first time before imaging examination finished. And the time cost by
      CT or MRI examination is likely to responsible for missing the narrow time window and poor
      prognosis of stroke patients. Consequently, seeking for a noninvasive, rapid, portable and
      inexpensive diagnosis method which can sensitively distinguish the stroke type before CT or
      MRI examination would be very helpful in treating the ischemic stroke patients. The new
      method would enable the first-aid personnel to judge the stroke type in the ambulance and
      decide to apply intravenous thrombolysis or not.

      Because of the blockage in the cerebral supply artery, especially the cerebral middle artery
      which can't be compensated, the blood flow in the corresponding hemisphere would drop sharply
      among the ischemic stroke patients. Along with decreasing heat from circulatory system, the
      infracted hemisphere's temperature should drop. The reduced brain temperature influenced the
      temperature on the ipsilateral forehead according to the data of our animal and preliminary
      clinical trial. In contrast, the temperature of the ipsilateral hemisphere showed a mild
      increase among the ischemic stroke patients in our preliminary experiment. That's possibly
      because the early mitochondrial dysfunction and inflammatory reaction induced by the
      hematoma. The difference of the temperature tendency on the ipsilateral forehead has a great
      chance to be an early physical mark. Temperature test could be rapid and noninvasive, making
      this mark a promising method to help the doctors to distinguish the stroke type in very early
      stage. Earlier diagnosis of ischemic stroke means earlier thrombolysis and much better
      prognosis.

      In our study, 30 ischemic stroke patients and 30 hemorrhagic stroke patients will be
      recruited. In the process of recruitment, the patients with acute stroke attack in no more
      than 4.5 hours will be collected the temperature at the five point without head coverage,
      including ipsilateral tempora, ipsilateral forehead, galbella, contralateral forehead, and
      contralateral tempora. Then the stroke would be recruited into the ischemic and hemorrhagic
      group according to the later CT or MRI results in the hospital. The accuracy and sensibility
      of early brain temperature in distinguishing stroke type would be tested in comparison with
      the diagnosis of imaging examination. It should be emphasized that the diagnosis and
      following treatment should depend on the imaging examination and our brain temperature test
      is rapid and noninvasive. The therapy of the recruited stroke patients wouldn't be influenced
      by the trial and should be as usual as the standard therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnose accordance rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>This evaluation will be based on how accordant ischemic stroke diagnosis by cranial temperature compared with imaging examination.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnose accordance rate</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>This evaluation will be based on how accordant ischemic stroke diagnosis by cranial temperature compared with later clinical diagnosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Hemorrhagic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ischemic stroke</arm_group_label>
    <description>The patients in the group are diagnosed as ischemic stroke by CT or MRA examination within 8h following stroke attack.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hemorrhagic stroke</arm_group_label>
    <description>The patients in the group are diagnosed as hemorrhagic stroke by CT or MRA examination within 8h following stroke attack.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The patients with a symptom and sign of acute stroke admitted to a specialized stroke
        service within 4.5 hours.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1.Patients aged 18 to 80 years. 2.Supratentorial hypertensive intracerebral hemorrhage
             diagnosed by head CT or MRI.

             3.The intracerebral hematoma is more than 10ml. 4.Ischemic stroke diagnosed by head CT
             or MRI. 5.Unilateral middle cerebral artery occlusion or infarcted volume more than
             1/2 of a hemicerebrum.

             6.The head temperature collection within 4.5 hours following stroke attack. 7.Glasgow
             Coma Scale between 5-10.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1.the time after stroke attack exceed 4.5 hours. 2.The intracerebral hematoma is less
             than 10ml. 3.The infarcted volume less than 1/3 of a hemicerebrum. 4.With terminal
             cerebral hernia. 5.Pregnant women. 6.Serious impaired liver function, coagulation
             disorders, AIDS, combine other tumor or special condition.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Feng Hua, Ph.D,MD</last_name>
    <phone>86-137-0832-1681</phone>
    <email>fenghua8888@aliyun.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tan Liang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>86-158-2354-0630</phone>
    <email>tracy200712@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>the Southwest hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chongqing</city>
        <state>Chongqing</state>
        <zip>400038</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yang Jing, Ph,D</last_name>
      <phone>86-023-68754814</phone>
      <email>cqhl13@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>He Laoshi, Ph,D</last_name>
      <phone>86-136-3549-1484</phone>
      <email>45195304@qq.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Feng Hua, Ph,D MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tan Liang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chen Weixiang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ma Kang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Liu Xin, Ph,D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zhang Yangqi, Ph,D</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hu Rong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zhou Zhenghua, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ren Xiaobao, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rong Yuan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zhang Yi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chen Lin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Huang Yi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kernan WN, Ovbiagele B, Black HR, Bravata DM, Chimowitz MI, Ezekowitz MD, Fang MC, Fisher M, Furie KL, Heck DV, Johnston SC, Kasner SE, Kittner SJ, Mitchell PH, Rich MW, Richardson D, Schwamm LH, Wilson JA; American Heart Association Stroke Council, Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing, Council on Clinical Cardiology, and Council on Peripheral Vascular Disease. Guidelines for the prevention of stroke in patients with stroke and transient ischemic attack: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2014 Jul;45(7):2160-236. doi: 10.1161/STR.0000000000000024. Epub 2014 May 1. Erratum in: Stroke. 2015 Feb;46(2):e54.</citation>
    <PMID>24788967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hemphill JC 3rd, Greenberg SM, Anderson CS, Becker K, Bendok BR, Cushman M, Fung GL, Goldstein JN, Macdonald RL, Mitchell PH, Scott PA, Selim MH, Woo D; American Heart Association Stroke Council; Council on Cardiovascular and Stroke Nursing; Council on Clinical Cardiology. Guidelines for the Management of Spontaneous Intracerebral Hemorrhage: A Guideline for Healthcare Professionals From the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2015 Jul;46(7):2032-60. doi: 10.1161/STR.0000000000000069. Epub 2015 May 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26022637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 19, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 19, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 21, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Third Military Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tan Liang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Southwest hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>brain temperture，thrombolysis，early diagnosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

