<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02603900</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15D.490</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02603900</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adductor Canal Catheter vs Local Infiltration of Analgesia for Total Knee Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blinded Randomized Controlled Trial Comparing the Adductor Canal Catheter (ACC) and Local Infiltration of Analgesia (LIA) Following Primary Total Knee Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective randomized controlled trial comparing local infiltration of
      analgesia in the knee joint and adductor canal catheters for postoperative analgesia
      following a primary Total Knee Arthroplasty (TKA).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective, randomized controlled clinical trial comparing two methods of
      postoperative analgesia following primary TKA. Eligible primary TKA patients must be ASA I -
      III and require less than 20 mg oxycodone daily (or its equivalent). Exclusion criteria are:
      allergy to anesthetics, contraindication to regional anesthesia, sensory/ motor disorder
      involving operative limb, non-english speaking, ASA IV or greater, psychiatric or cognitive
      disorders, incarceration, renal insufficiency with Cr &gt; 2.0 and hepatic failure. When
      patients agree to participate in the study the following data will be collected by the
      research staff: ASA physical status, age, height, weight, gender, quantitative opiate use,
      numeric pain score with visual descriptors, painDETECT score, WOMAC score and baseline Pain
      Management Questionnaire. When designated through randomization, local infiltration of
      analgesia will be placed intraoperatively by the surgeons, per usual protocol and patients in
      the LIA group will receive sham adductor canal catheter. All ACC's for both study groups will
      be placed postoperatively in the PACU. Those collecting data will be blinded from identifying
      patients in the control group, as both groups will have ACC placed with same technique.
      Potential risks for each procedure, which will be explained to the patient, include:
      bleeding, local infection, local anesthetic toxicity in the form of seizure and cardiac
      arrest and neuropathy. The preceding are commonly listed though infrequent complications of
      both procedures. Continuous ultrasound will guide the placement of the ACC. All adductor
      canal catheters will remain in for 72 hours. Pt from LIA group will be discharged home with
      sham catheter with a saline infusion at 10 ml/hr via an ambulatory pump. Patients in ACC
      group will be discharged with continuous adductor canal catheter delivering ropivacaine 0.2%
      at 10 ml/hr via an ambulatory pump. Patients will be called daily for pain diary results. As
      well as at 6-8 weeks postoperatively to collect painDetect and WOMAC survey.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative pain via numeric rating scale at rest and with activity during each physical therapy session</measure>
    <time_frame>post-operative day #0 to post-operative day #3</time_frame>
    <description>postoperative pain as measured by numeric rating scale at rest and with movement during each physical therapy session.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative opioid consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>post-operative day #0 to postoperative day # 3</time_frame>
    <description>Opioid consumption during hospitalization in oxycodone equivalents at 24, 48 and 72 hours</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic post-surgical pain measured via validated painDetect and WOMAC questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>6-8 weeks after surgical date</time_frame>
    <description>Assess post-surgical pain and function as measured by PainDetect and WOMAC questionnaires at 6-8 weeks post-operative compared to preoperative pain and function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Passive and Active Range of Motion during Physical Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>POD #0 to postoperative day #2</time_frame>
    <description>Assess quantitative passive and active range of motion during physical therapy as well as Timed up to Go (TUG) which is routine assessment during physical therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Pain</condition>
  <condition>Regional Anesthesia Morbidity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adductor Canal Catheter</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive ropivacaine 0.5% 15 ml for the adductor canal block under ultrasound guided nerve block. A multi-orifice catheter will be placed in the adductor canal and an infusion of ropivacaine 0.2% at 10 ml/hr will be continued for 72 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Local Infiltration of Analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Local infiltration using 20 ml of free bupivacaine solution (Marcaine 0.25% with epinephrine 1:200000, ) diluted with 40 ml of normal saline following implantation of the knee prosthesis, the solution will be injected into the vastus medialis (5 ml), medial retinaculum (5 ml), origin of MCL (5 ml) and LCL (5 ml), lateral portion of quadriceps tendon (5 ml), vastus lateralis (5 ml), and subcutaneous tissues especially along saphenous nerve distribution (30 ml). Postoperatively, a sham adductor canal catheter will be placed as in the ACC arm following stabilization in the PACU to infuse only normal saline with an initial bolus of 15 ml saline and infusion of saline at 10ml/hr for 72 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ropivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>15 ml 0.5% Ropivicaine for primary adductor canal block under ultrasound guidance and 0.2% Ropivicaine infusion 10 ml/hr.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adductor Canal Catheter</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Naropin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bupivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>20 ml bupivacaine ( Marcaine 0.25% with epinephrine 1:200000, Hospira Inc. Lake Forest, IL) diluted with 40 ml of normal saline injected intraoperatively into the knee joint before closure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Local Infiltration of Analgesia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Marcaine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Adductor Canal Catheter</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham catheter placement via ultrasound-guided adductor canal block and 10ml/hr saline via OnQ Pump via continuous catheter in adductor canal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Local Infiltration of Analgesia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adductor Canal Catheter</intervention_name>
    <description>Catheter placed in adductor canal via ultrasound guidance and continuous infusion via OnQ pump.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adductor Canal Catheter</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 40-85

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Physical Status (PS) 1-3. • Undergoing
             Unilateral, Primary, Total Knee Arthroplasty

          -  English as native language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient refusal

          -  History of opioid dependence

          -  Contraindication to peripheral nerve block • Pre-existing significant neuropathy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jaime L Baratta, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jaime L Baratta, MD</last_name>
    <email>jaime.baratta@jefferosn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fischer HB, Simanski CJ, Sharp C, Bonnet F, Camu F, Neugebauer EA, Rawal N, Joshi GP, Schug SA, Kehlet H; PROSPECT Working Group. A procedure-specific systematic review and consensus recommendations for postoperative analgesia following total knee arthroplasty. Anaesthesia. 2008 Oct;63(10):1105-23. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2044.2008.05565.x. Epub 2008 Jul 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18627367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Essving P, Axelsson K, Åberg E, Spännar H, Gupta A, Lundin A. Local infiltration analgesia versus intrathecal morphine for postoperative pain management after total knee arthroplasty: a randomized controlled trial. Anesth Analg. 2011 Oct;113(4):926-33. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3182288deb. Epub 2011 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21821506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Charous MT, Madison SJ, Suresh PJ, Sandhu NS, Loland VJ, Mariano ER, Donohue MC, Dutton PH, Ferguson EJ, Ilfeld BM. Continuous femoral nerve blocks: varying local anesthetic delivery method (bolus versus basal) to minimize quadriceps motor block while maintaining sensory block. Anesthesiology. 2011 Oct;115(4):774-81. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3182124dc6.</citation>
    <PMID>21394001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jenstrup MT, Jæger P, Lund J, Fomsgaard JS, Bache S, Mathiesen O, Larsen TK, Dahl JB. Effects of adductor-canal-blockade on pain and ambulation after total knee arthroplasty: a randomized study. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2012 Mar;56(3):357-64. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-6576.2011.02621.x. Epub 2012 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22221014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kazak Bengisun Z, Aysu Salviz E, Darcin K, Suer H, Ates Y. Intraarticular levobupivacaine or bupivacaine administration decreases pain scores and provides a better recovery after total knee arthroplasty. J Anesth. 2010 Oct;24(5):694-9. doi: 10.1007/s00540-010-0970-x. Epub 2010 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20571832</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 10, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 13, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 25, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 25, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 26, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jaime Baratta</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adductor Canal Catheter</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthroplasty, Replacement, Knee</keyword>
  <keyword>Local infiltration of analgesia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ropivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

