<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02608684</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIT2015-13-Walsh-PemCiGem</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02608684</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Pembrolizumab With Standard Treatment in Patients With Recurrent Platinum-resistant Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>PemCiGem</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Pembrolizumab With Cisplatin and Gemcitabine Treatment in Patients With Recurrent Platinum-resistant Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the efficacy and safety of anti-PD-1 antibody MK-3475 (pembrolizumab) in
      combination with gemcitabine and cisplatin chemotherapy in women with recurrent
      platinum-resistant ovarian cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm, open-label, phase II trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of
      anti-PD-1 antibody MK-3475 (pembrolizumab) in combination with standard of care gemcitabine
      and cisplatin chemotherapy in women with recurrent platinum-resistant ovarian cancer
      (encompasses ovarian, peritoneal and fallopian tube cancer). Subjects will receive 2 cycles
      of gemcitabine and cisplatin chemotherapy followed by 4 cycles of gemcitabine and cisplatin
      combined with pembrolizumab in 21-day treatment cycles. Subjects will continue to receive
      single-agent pembrolizumab every 21 days as maintenance therapy for up to 2 year until
      progression or the subject meets withdrawal criteria. Tumor imaging with CT scan will occur
      at baseline and every 6 weeks (after each second cycle) during chemotherapy treatment and
      every 9 weeks thereafter. The primary endpoint is efficacy as defined overall response rate
      by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST v.1.1). Secondary endpoints for
      efficacy include progression free survival at 6 and 12 months, time to progression, duration
      of response and overall survival. Safety and tolerability of the regimen will be determined
      by assessing the frequency and intensity of adverse events as defined by the Common
      Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE v.4). Quality of life will be measured using
      the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer quality of life questionnaire
      (QLQ-C30).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as complete or partial response per RECIST 1.1 criteria with assessment every 6 weeks during first 6 cycles of therapy and every 9 weeks thereafter.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate by immune-related Response Criteria (irRC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS) at 6 months and at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who have not progressed at 6 and 12 months with progression-free survival calculated from the start of treatment to the date of progression or death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated in months from the start of treatment to disease progression as defined by RECIST 1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated in months as time from documentation of tumor response to disease progression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated in months from the start of treatment to the date of death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and intensity of adverse events (CTCAE v.4)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>As measured at each visit, during safety follow up (30 days after discontinuation of treatment) and during follow up (every nine weeks after discontinuation)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin+Gemcitabine+Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 cycles of 750mg gemcitabine and 30mg cisplatin chemotherapy (standard of care) followed by 4 cycles of gemcitabine and cisplatin combined with pembrolizumab in 21-day treatment cycles.
Gemcitabine 750 mg/m2 every 3 weeks (Q3W) x 6 cycles IV infusion Day 1 and Day 8 of each 3 week cycle Standard of care
Cisplatin 30 mg/m2 Q3W x 6 cycles IV infusion Day 1 and Day 8 of each 3 week cycle after gemcitabine Standard of care
Pembrolizumab 200 mg Q3W starting with cycle 3 IV infusion Day 1 of each 3 week cycle after gemcitabine and cisplatin Experimental</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Pembrolizumab IV solution</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin+Gemcitabine+Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Keytruda</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-3475</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Gemcitabine IV solution</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin+Gemcitabine+Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Cisplatin IV solution</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cisplatin+Gemcitabine+Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Platinol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be willing and able to provide written informed consent/ for the trial.

          -  Be at least 18 years of age on day of signing informed consent.

          -  Have histologically confirmed diagnosis of recurrent epithelial ovarian, peritoneal or
             fallopian tube carcinoma that has progressed within 6 months of prior cytotoxic
             chemotherapy. Histologic confirmation of the primary tumor by review of the pathology
             report is required. Patients must have had at least one prior platinum-based
             chemotherapeutic regimen. Initial treatment may have been administered as an
             intraperitoneal, intravenous or dose-dense regimen. Progression within 6 months of a
             non-platinum containing regimen is eligible if the patient is considered
             platinum-resistant to the last platinum-containing regimen. Patients who have received
             prior cisplatin and gemcitabine treatment are eligible to participate.

          -  Have measurable disease based on RECIST 1.1

          -  Have a performance status of 0 or 1 on the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)
             Performance Scale.

          -  Demonstrate adequate organ function, all screening labs should be performed within 28
             days of treatment initiation.

          -  Female subject of childbearing potential should have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy test within 72 hours prior to receiving the first dose of study medication.
             If the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy
             test will be required. Patients who have had prior hysterectomy and/or bilateral
             oophorectomy are not required to have a pregnancy test.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential should be willing to use 2 methods of birth
             control or be surgically sterile, or abstain from heterosexual activity for the course
             of the study through 120 days after the last dose of study medication. Subjects of
             childbearing potential are those who have not been surgically sterilized or have not
             been free from menses for &gt; 1 year.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Is currently participating and receiving study therapy or has participated in a study
             of an investigational agent and received study therapy or used an investigational
             device within 4 weeks of the first dose of treatment.

          -  Has diagnosis of immunodeficiency or is receiving systemic steroid therapy or any
             other form of immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of trial
             treatment.

          -  Has a known history of active TB (Bacillus Tuberculosis)

          -  Hypersensitivity to pembrolizumab or any of its excipients. Has had a prior
             anti-cancer monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to study Day 1 or who has
             not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at baseline) from adverse events due to agents
             administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          -  Has had prior chemotherapy, targeted small molecule therapy, or radiation therapy
             within 2 weeks prior to study Day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at
             baseline) from adverse events due to a previously administered agent.

        Note: Subjects with ≤ Grade 2 neuropathy are an exception to this criterion and may qualify
        for the study.

        Note: If subject received major surgery including (curative or palliative surgery), they
        must have recovered adequately from the toxicity and/or complications from the intervention
        prior to starting therapy.

        Note: Patients who have hypertension as an adverse event related to prior angiogenesis
        targeted therapy may be allowed if ≤ Grade 2 and considered by investigator to be
        well-controlled on anti-hypertensive agents.

          -  Has a known additional malignancy that is progressing or requires active treatment.
             Exceptions include basal cell carcinoma of the skin or squamous cell carcinoma of the
             skin that has undergone potentially curative therapy or in situ cervical cancer.

          -  Has known active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous
             meningitis. Subjects with previously treated brain metastases may participate provided
             they are stable (without evidence of progression by imaging for at least four weeks
             prior to the first dose of trial treatment and any neurologic symptoms have returned
             to baseline), have no evidence of new or enlarging brain metastases, and are not using
             steroids for at least 7 days prior to trial treatment. This exception does not include
             carcinomatous meningitis which is excluded regardless of clinical stability.

          -  Has active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2 years
             (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs). Replacement therapy (e.g., thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment.

          -  Has a history of (non-infectious) pneumonitis that required steroids or current
             pneumonitis.

          -  Has an active infection requiring systemic therapy.

          -  Has a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality
             that might confound the results of the trial, interfere with the subject's
             participation for the full duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of
             the subject to participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator.

          -  Has known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with
             cooperation with the requirements of the trial.

          -  Is pregnant or breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive children within the projected
             duration of the trial, starting with screening visit through 120 days after the last
             dose of trial treatment.

          -  Has received prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-PD-L2 agent.

          -  Has a known history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) (HIV 1/2 antibodies) or
             positive serum test for HIV as per testing at screening

          -  Has known active Hepatitis B (e.g., HBsAg reactive) or Hepatitis C (e.g., HCV RNA
             [qualitative] is detected) as per test at screening

          -  Has received a live vaccine within 30 days of planned start of study therapy. Note:
             Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection are generally inactivated flu vaccines and
             are allowed; however intranasal influenza vaccines (e.g., Flu-Mist®) are live
             attenuated vaccines, and are not allowed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christine Walsh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinal Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christine Walsh, MD</last_name>
    <phone>310-423-3599</phone>
    <email>Christine.Walsh@cshs.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jenny Lester</last_name>
    <phone>310-423-6241</phone>
    <email>Jenny.Lester@cshs.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christine Walsh, MD</last_name>
      <phone>310-423-3599</phone>
      <email>Christine.Walsh@cshs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jaime Richardson</last_name>
      <phone>310-423-2133</phone>
      <email>cancer.trial.info@cshs.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christine Walsh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christine Walsh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor in Residence, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>platinum-resistant ovarian cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>immune checkpoint inhibitors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

