<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03442998</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Walking Green</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03442998</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Walking Green: Developing an Evidence-base for Nature Prescriptions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Walking Green: Developing an Evidence-base for Nature Prescriptions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesize that walking on a nature trail will lead to greater reductions
      in stress and greater improvements in the capacity to direct attention as compared to walking
      on a suburban sidewalk.

      The effects of walking in these different locations will be measured using physiological and
      psychological outcomes. The study design is a randomized with-in person cross-over trial.
      Subjects will take six 50-minute walks, one walk per week for six weeks. Three walks will
      occur in the urban setting and three in the nature setting. The order of the conditions will
      be randomly assigned to each subject, so that half of the subjects will complete the urban
      walks first and half the subjects will complete the nature walks first. There will be a
      two-week washout period between the two sets of walks. Day of the week will be fixed within
      person, and walks will occur during the mild weather months. In the case of inclement
      weather, the weekly walk will be skipped and an additional week will be added to the
      schedule. Limiting the frequency to one walk per week maximizes feasibility of the protocol
      and minimizes training effects, with any training effects over time being handled primarily
      by randomization (condition order is balanced), but also in the statistical analysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Suburban walks will be mapped out in clean, safe streets with sidewalks within 3 miles of the
      Arboretum, in Chaska, Minnesota. A loop covering approximately 1.25 miles will be mapped. At
      a usual walking speed of 20 minutes per mile, a subject will complete ~ 2 loops. Each walk
      will be timed so that walking speed can be included in the statistical analysis as an
      important covariate.

      Nature Walks will take place at the University of Minnesota Landscape Arboretum, which is
      part of the College of Food, Agricultural and Natural Resource Sciences at the University of
      Minnesota. The Arboretum features more than 1,215 acres of natural landscapes with over 12
      miles of trails. Subjects in this study will take their nature walks on the Green Heron Pond
      Trail and adjacent trails that can be connected to create a walking loop of ~1.25 miles, or
      an out-and-back course, matching the distance of the suburban walk. Heron Pond and its
      adjacent marsh and bog represent three naturally occurring ecosystems in Minnesota that are
      part of the state's geologic and landscape heritage. The bog trail passes through the most
      diverse ecotypes of any Arboretum hike. Oak woods, maple woods and the mosaic of intermingled
      wetlands along the boardwalk offer rich rewards for birders, school groups and families.

      The primary approach to the statistical analysis will be a repeated measures multivariable
      linear regression model. The outcomes will be the psychological and physiological measures of
      stress. The primary independent variable of interest is condition (suburban v. nature). The
      interaction of condition and time (week of the study) provides a formal test of intervention
      effects (differences between the urban and nature walks). That is, over the time course of
      the interventions, are there significant differences in the outcomes between the urban and
      nature walks? Covariates to be evaluated in the models as possible confounders include the
      order of the conditions (urban first v. nature first), age, gender, body mass index, and
      overall habitual physical activity. On an exploratory basis, the investigators will test
      whether these covariates also serve as modifiers of the intervention effect.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 14, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Heart Rate Variability</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made at baseline one-week before the first walk, immediately before and after each walk, and within three days following the third walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>High frequency heart rate variation using ambulatory heart rate monitors (milliseconds).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made at baseline, immediately before and after each walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure (mmHg) using a standard blood pressure cuff.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cortisol Dynamics</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made before each walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>Diurnal cortisol dynamics measured by salivary cortisol (ug/dl), as the normal drop in cortisol during the day is attenuated by exposure to chronic stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cytokine Blood Concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made before each walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>Pro- and anti-inflammatory cytokine concentrations in blood (pg/mL), as stress typically induces an inflammatory response. Blood samples are collected by pricking the subject's finger-tip, collecting drops of blood on Protein SaverTMpaper (Whatman) and then drying the blood spots. The dried blood spots (DBS) are frozen and stored until assayed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Attention restoration</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made at baseline one-week before the first walk, immediately before and after each walk, and within three days following the third walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>The Backward Digit Span test is one of the oldest tests used to evaluate working memory and is used to assess capacity to direct attention (i.e., attention restoration).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CESD</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made at baseline, immediately before and after each walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>CESD: Stress is strongly associated with depression. To measure depressive symptoms we will use the Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale (CESD). Scores are determined by summing the participants' answers to all 20 items from 1 (&quot;less than 1 day&quot;) to 4 (&quot;5-7 days&quot;) pre- and post-walk in each intervention location (nature vs suburban).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PANAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made at baseline, immediately before and after each walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>PANAS: Stress is associated with decreased positive and increased negative affect (mood). We will measure affect using the Positive and Negative Affect Scale (PANAS).
Scores are determined by summing the participants' answers to all 20 items from 1 (&quot;very slightly or not at all&quot;) to 5 (&quot;extremely&quot;) pre- and post-walk in each intervention location (nature vs suburban).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in STAI</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made at baseline, immediately before and after each walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety: Stress is associated with increased levels of anxiety. Anxiety will be measured using the State and Trait Anxiety Inventories (STAI). Scores are determined by summing the participants' answers to all 20 items from 1 (&quot;not at all&quot;) to 4 (&quot;frequently so&quot;) pre- and post-walk in each intervention location (nature vs suburban).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Perceived stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements will be made at baseline, immediately before and after each walk of each condition (nature vs suburban).</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived stress: Cohen's perceived stress scale (PSS) will be used to measure the extent to which subjects assess the events and situations in their lives to be stressful. Scores are determined by summing the participants' answers to all 10 items from 1 (&quot;never&quot;) to 4 (&quot;very often&quot;) pre- and post-walk in each intervention location (nature vs suburban).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <condition>Attention</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Suburban</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants will wall on a suburban sidewalk setting for 50 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nature</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study participants will wall on a nature path setting for 50 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Suburban walk</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject is tested under the 'suburban' condition. We will compare the stress response and working memory response to walking in the two experimental conditions ((1)response to walking on a nature path and (2) response to walking on an urban sidewalk).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Suburban</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nature walk</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject is tested under the 'nature' condition. We will compare the stress response and working memory response to walking in the two experimental conditions ((1)response to walking on a nature path and (2) response to walking on an urban sidewalk).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nature</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 35 to 59

          -  No contraindications to physical activity

          -  No major chronic diseases or specific medications that would contraindicate exercise
             or potentially blunt heart rate variation during exercise

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cardiovascular disease medication

          -  Arthritis

          -  Steroids

          -  Certain blood pressure medications

          -  Diabetes

          -  Cancer

          -  Self-reported depression or anxiety / taking medication for depression or anxiety,

          -  Outside age range

          -  Inability to follow schedule including travel to arboretum

          -  Exceeding physical activity recommendations (250 minutes per week)

          -  Contraindications to walking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark A Pereira, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minnesota Landscape Arboretum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chaska</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55318</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

