<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03447119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H18234</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03447119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Living Well With a Disability Curriculum Adaptation Evaluation Plan</brief_title>
  <official_title>Living Well With a Disability Curriculum Adaptation Evaluation Plan</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Georgia Southern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Georgia Southern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this proposal is to implement a joint project with Georgia Southern University
      and the Effingham County Navigator Team to improve the quality of life of families with a
      child with a disability in southeast Georgia. The final outcome of this project will be a new
      curriculum, Living Well Together, which builds on a previous implementation of the Living
      Well with a Disability curriculum in Bulloch County.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      First, parent facilitators will be recruited and matched with their peers. Parent
      facilitators will be members of the Effingham County Navigator Team with a child with a
      disability. The peer matching resembles the community lay health worker model. The community
      lay health worker model will reduce the amount of time needed to meet face to face with
      families. To begin adapting the facilitator training and curriculum, the program directors
      will work with representatives from the University of Montana Rural Institute on Disabilities
      to review and update training materials. A representative from the Rural Institute on
      Disabilities will deliver an online intensive facilitator training. The facilitator training
      is approximately 15 hours long. The training includes three major components: peer training,
      facilitator training, and Master &quot;Train the Trainer&quot; training. The project directors will
      work with the Effingham County Navigator Team to recruit parents. The Navigator Team will
      recruit five parents as parent facilitators. The parents will work together with the project
      directors to deliver the adapted curriculum to participating families. With bi-weekly
      meetings for 10 weeks between parent facilitators and family participants in the home or
      another desired location. The project directors have already participated in the facilitator
      training and will serve as mentors to newly trained facilitators. At the end of the online
      training session, the parent facilitators will be equipped to successfully implement the
      Living Well curriculum. The project directors will schedule a working meeting before and
      after the facilitator training to discuss curriculum changes with the Rural Institute on
      Disabilities representative. Changes in readability are anticipated since the target audience
      includes adolescents. Curriculum delivery methods will need tailoring to match a family-based
      approach including activities to be completed at the home at the family and individual levels
      for parents, siblings, and children. Both GSU faculty and the Navigator team will lead
      monthly summary meetings to review the adapted content. These meetings will take place at a
      convenient location in the community as determined by the Navigator team. Pre and post focus
      groups will take place before and after these monthly meetings at a convenient locale in the
      community.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Health</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System Parent Proxy scale v 1.0
Global Health
Patient Reported Outcome Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Pediatric Global Health (PROMIS PGH-7) measures general health, quality of life, physical health, mental health, feeling sad, social health (fun with friends), and parents listening to ideas.
Each item is measured on a likert scale from 1 (never) to 5 (always). There is one item for each subscale listed above. A range for each subscale would be 1-5. Typically, results are reported as a whole so the range would be 7 to 35.
For each subscale and the scale as a whole the higher the score, the better the global health.
Subscales are summed to compute the total score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family Relationships</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System Parent Proxy scale v. 1.0
Family Relationships
The Family Relationships subscale measures the importance and strength of the family unit perceived by the child in the past four weeks.
Each item is measured on a Likert scale from 1 (never) to 4 (always). There are four items in this subscale. The reports are reported as a whole so the range is 4 to 16.
The higher the score, the stronger the family relationships.
Items are summed for the total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Life Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System Parent Proxy scale v 1.0 Life Satisfaction
The Life Satisfaction subscale measures quality of life in the past four weeks.
Each item is measured on a Likert scale from 1 (not at all) to 5 (very much). There are eight items in this scale. The range for the whole subscale is 8-40.
The higher the score, the better quality of life.
Each item is summed for the total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System Parent Proxy scale v 1.0 Physical Activity
The Physical Activity subscale reports frequency and intensity of exercise of the child in the past week.
Each item is measured on a Likert scale from 1 (no days) to 5 (6-7 days). There are eight items in this subscale. The total range is 8 (no exercise) to 40 (exercising regularly).
The higher the score, the more physically active the individual is.
The items are summed together for the score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological Stress Experiences</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System Parent Proxy scale v 1.0 Psychological Stress Experiences</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peer Relationships</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System Parent Proxy scale v 1.0 Peer Relationships
The Peer Relationships subscale measures the child's social activity in the last 7 days.
Each item is measured on a Likert scale from 1 (never) to 5 (almost always). There are 7 items in the scale. The range is 7 (doesn't interact with friends) to 35 (very socially active).
The higher the score the better the relationships.
The items are summed together for a total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Education</condition>
  <condition>Community Health Services</condition>
  <condition>Health Services for Persons With Disabilities</condition>
  <condition>Developmental Disabilities</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Living Well with a Disability</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The parents will work together with the project directors to deliver the adapted curriculum to participating families. With bi-weekly meetings for 10 weeks between parent facilitators and family participants in the home or another desired location. The project directors have already participated in the facilitator training and will serve as mentors to newly trained facilitators. At the end of the online training session, the parent facilitators will be equipped to successfully implement the Living Well curriculum.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Living Well with a Disability</intervention_name>
    <description>Implementation of an adapted health promotion program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Living Well with a Disability</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        Families of an adolescent (10-21) with any developmental disability

        Exclusion Criteria

        Family and child are unable to follow directions and participate in curriculum activities.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gavin Colquitt, EdD</last_name>
    <phone>912-478-0889</phone>
    <email>gcolquitt@georgiasouthern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ashley Walker, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>912-478-1710</phone>
    <email>awaker@georgiasouthern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>B and B Care Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>31329</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pauline Shaw, BS</last_name>
      <phone>912-659-9855</phone>
      <email>pshaw@bandbcare.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 31, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Georgia Southern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gavin Colquitt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Developmental Disabilities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

