<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03447678</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INT 178-17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03447678</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pembrolizumab in First Line Treatment of Advanced NSCLC Patients With PD-L1 Low Tumors.</brief_title>
  <acronym>PEOPLE</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Study to Test Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) in First Line Treatment of Advanced NSCLC Patients With PD-L1 Low Tumors (&lt;50%)_ PEOPLE TRIAL (Pembrolizumab in Pd-L1 Low Expressors).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milano</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori, Milano</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, monocentric, open label, phase II trial of intravenous (IV)
      Pembrolizumab monotherapy in subjects previously untreated for their stage IIIB-IV, PD-L1 low
      non small cell lung cancer (NSCLC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 65 subjects with PD-L1 low (PD-L1Lo), EGFR wt, EML4/ALK fusion negative NSCLC
      will be enrolled in this trial for examination of the biological characteristics associated
      to efficacy and safety of Pembrolizumab. Subjects will receive Pembrolizumab iv at dose of
      200 mg every three weeks. Subjects will be evaluated every 9 weeks (63 +/- 3 days) with
      radiographic imaging to assess response to treatment. Subjects will continue with the
      assigned study treatment until RECIST-defined progression of disease, unacceptable toxicity
      or consent withdrawal.

      Treatment with Pembrolizumab will continue until two years of therapy have been administered,
      documented disease progression, unacceptable adverse event(s), intercurrent illness that
      prevents further administration of treatment, investigator's decision to withdraw the
      subject, subject withdraws consent, pregnancy of the subject, noncompliance with trial
      treatment or procedure requirements, or administrative reasons. Pembrolizumab treated
      subjects who obtain a confirmed Complete Response (CR) per RECIST 1.1 may consider stopping
      trial treatment. These subjects may be eligible for re-treatment with Pembrolizumab after
      they have experienced radiographic disease progression at the discretion of the investigator,
      this re-treatment will be the Second Course Phase.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>tumor infiltrating lymphocytes in patients whose tumors have a low PD_L1 expression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>infiltrating T cells that upregulate PD-1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>inhibitory receptors such as TIM-3, LAG-3 and TIGIT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>type of cells being positive for PD-L1(neoplastic cells vs infiltrating immune cells)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>presence and phenotype of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes in the pre-therapy lesions of patients with low expression of PD-L1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>levels of CD3+, CD4+, CD8+ lymphocytes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>expression, in TIL, of markers of functional differentiation to cytolytic stage such as granzyme B and TIA-1, or maturation to memory stage (CD45RO)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>expression of PD1+ by TIL</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>expression of PD-L1 on neoplastic cells vs immune cells</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>expression of inhibitory receptors as LAG-3, TIM-3 and TIGIT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>frequency of FOXP3+ lymphocytes, as well as of CD11b+ CD33+ MDSCs, in pre-therapy lesions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>tumor infiltrating lymphocytes in patients whose tumors have a low PD_L1 expression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>infiltrating T cells that upregulate PD-1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>inhibitory receptors such as TIM-3, LAG-3 and TIGIT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>type of cells being positive for PD-L1(neoplastic cells vs infiltrating immune cells)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>presence and phenotype of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes in the pre-therapy lesions of patients with low expression of PD-L1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>levels of CD3+, CD4+, CD8+ lymphocytes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>expression, in TIL, of markers of functional differentiation to cytolytic stage such as granzyme B and TIA-1, or maturation to memory stage (CD45RO)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>expression of PD1+ by TIL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>expression of PD-L1 on neoplastic cells vs immune cells</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>expression of inhibitory receptors as LAG-3, TIM-3 and TIGIT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune biomarkers distribution between pre and post Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>frequency of FOXP3+ lymphocytes, as well as of CD11b+ CD33+ MDSCs, in pre-therapy lesions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>from the time measurement criteria are met for CR or PR (whichever is first recorded) until the first date that recurrent or progressive disease are objectively documented, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Response Duration (DoR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Disease Control Rate (DCR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness of Pembrolizumab treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>from the time of enrollment to death due to any reasons, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Survival (OS) will be used as effectiveness endpoint</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of Pembrolizumab treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be monitored throughout the trial and graded in severity according to the guidelines outlined in the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4. A particular attention will be placed in the evaluation of potential Immune related adverse events (IrAE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Reported health status for physical, mental and social well-being</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) provides measures of health status that assess physical, mental and social well-being from the patient prospective.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Non Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects with PD-L1 low (PD-L1Lo), EGFR wt, EML4/ALK fusion negative NSCLC</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>humanized antibody used in cancer immunotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Have a confirmed diagnosis of NSCLC in stage IIIB/ IV. Do not have an EGFR sensitizing
             (activating) mutation or ALK translocation and have a PD-L1 &quot;low&quot; (&lt;50%) tumor as
             determined by immunohistochemistry with anti-PD-L1 antibody (DAKO 22C3). Have not
             received prior systemic chemotherapy treatment for advanced NSCLC. Subjects with
             non-squamous histologies will not be enrolled until the EGFR mutation status and/or
             ALK translocation status is available. For patients enrolled who are known to have a
             tumor of predominantly squamous histology, molecular testing for EGFR and ALK
             translocation will not be required .

          2. Be willing and able to provide written informed consent/assent for the trial.

          3. Be &gt;=18 years of age on day of signing informed consent.

          4. Have measurable disease based on RECIST 1.1.

          5. Be willing to provide tissue from archived histological specimen or newly obtained
             core or excisional biopsy of a tumor lesion. Newly-obtained is defined as a specimen
             obtained up to 45 days prior to initiation of treatment on Day 1.

          6. Have a performance status of 0 or 1 on the ECOG Performance Scale.

          7. Demonstrate adequate organ function

          8. All screening labs should be performed within 10 days of treatment initiation

          9. Female subject of childbearing potential should have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy within 72 hours prior to receiving the first dose of study medication. If
             the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy test
             will be required

         10. Female subjects of childbearing potential should be willing to use 2 methods of birth
             control or be surgically sterile, or abstain from heterosexual activity for the course
             of the study through 120 days after the last dose of study medication (Reference
             Section 5.7.2). Subjects of childbearing potential are those who have not been
             surgically sterilized or have not been free from menses for &gt; 1 year

         11. Male subjects should agree to use an adequate method of contraception starting with
             the first dose of study therapy through 120 days after the last dose of study therapy

         12. No history of active malignancy requiring treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The subject must be excluded from participating in the trial if the subject:

          1. Has an EGFR sensitizing mutation and/or an ALK translocation.

          2. Has a PD-L1 expression assessed as &quot;high&quot; by the central laboratory

          3. Has a diagnosis of immunodeficiency or is receiving systemic steroid therapy or any
             other form of immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of trial
             treatment.

          4. Has a known history of active TB (Bacillus Tuberculosis).

          5. Hypersensitivity to Pembrolizumab or any of its excipients.

          6. Has had a prior anti-cancer monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to study
             Day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at baseline) from adverse events
             due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          7. Has had prior chemotherapy, targeted small molecule therapy, or radiation therapy
             within 2 weeks prior to study Day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at
             baseline) from adverse events due to a previously administered agent.

               -  Note: Subjects with ≤ Grade 2 neuropathy are an exception to this criterion and
                  may qualify for the study.

               -  Note: If subjects received major surgery, they must have recovered adequately
                  from the toxicity and/or complications from the intervention prior to starting
                  therapy.

          8. Has a known additional malignancy that is progressing or requires active treatment.
             Exceptions include basal cell carcinoma of the skin or squamous cell carcinoma of the
             skin that has undergone potentially curative therapy or in situ cervical cancer.

          9. Has active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2 years
             (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs). Replacement therapy (eg., thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment.

         10. Has a history of non-infectious pneumonitis that required steroids or has current
             pneumonitis.

         11. Has an active infection requiring systemic therapy.

         12. Has a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality
             that might confound the results of the trial, interfere with the subject's
             participation for the full duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of
             the subject to participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator.

         13. Has known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with
             cooperation with the requirements of the trial.

         14. Is pregnant or breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive or father children within the
             projected duration of the trial, starting with the pre-screening or screening visit
             through 120 days after the last dose of trial treatment.

         15. Has received prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-PD-L2 agent.

         16. Has a known history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) (HIV 1/2 antibodies).

         17. Has known active Hepatitis B (e.g., HBsAg reactive) or Hepatitis C (e.g., HCV RNA
             [qualitative] is detected).

         18. Has received a live vaccine within 30 days of planned start of study therapy. Note:
             Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection are generally inactivated flu vaccines and
             are allowed; however intranasal influenza vaccines (e.g., Flu-Mist®) are live
             attenuated vaccines, and are not allowed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marina Chiara Garassino, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marina Chiara Garassino, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0223903813</phone>
    <email>marina.garassino@istitutotumori.mi.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rosaria Gallucci, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>0223903836</phone>
    <email>rosaria.gallucci@istitutotumori.mi.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <zip>20133</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marina Chiara Garassino, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0223903813</phone>
      <email>marina.garassino@istitutotumori.mi.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rosaria Gallucci, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>0223903836</phone>
      <email>rosaria.gallucci@istitutotumori.mi.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korman A, Chen B, Wang C, Wu L, Cardarelli P, Selby M. Activity of anti-PD-1 in murine tumor models: role of</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rizvi NA,et al. Safety and clinical activity of Pembrolizumab as initial therapy in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). Presented at the ASCO Meeting 2014. abstract 8007.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garon EB, et al. Safety and clinical activity of Pembrolizumab in previously treated patients (pts) with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). Presented at the ASCO Meeting 2014. abstract 8020.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harriet M. Kluger, Sarah B. Goldberg, Mario Sznol, John Tsiouris, Alexander Vortmeyer, Lucia Jilaveanu, Amanda L. Ralabate, Angel L. Rivera, Matthew M. Burke, Upendra P. Hegbe, Justine Vanessa Cohen, Xiaopan Yao, Stephanie Speaker, Matthew Madura, Elizabeth Knapp-Perry, Amit Mahajan, Veronica Chiang. Safety and activity of Pembrolizumab in melanoma patients with untreated brain metastases. 2015 ASCO annual meeting</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>A.S. Berghoff, C. Inan, G. Ricken, G. Widhalm, K. Dieckmann, P. Birner, F. Oberndorfer, B. Dome, R. Bartsch, C. Zielinski and M. Preusser. Tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes (tils) and pd-l1 expression in non- small cell lung cancer brain metastases (bm) and matched primary tumors (pt). Ann oncol (2014) 25 (suppl 4): iv465-iv466.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Disis ML. Immune regulation of cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2010 Oct 10;28(29):4531-8. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2009.27.2146. Epub 2010 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20516428</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dong H, Strome SE, Salomao DR, Tamura H, Hirano F, Flies DB, Roche PC, Lu J, Zhu G, Tamada K, Lennon VA, Celis E, Chen L. Tumor-associated B7-H1 promotes T-cell apoptosis: a potential mechanism of immune evasion. Nat Med. 2002 Aug;8(8):793-800. Epub 2002 Jun 24. Erratum in: Nat Med 2002 Sep;8(9):1039.</citation>
    <PMID>12091876</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sharpe AH, Freeman GJ. The B7-CD28 superfamily. Nat Rev Immunol. 2002 Feb;2(2):116-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11910893</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brown JA, Dorfman DM, Ma FR, Sullivan EL, Munoz O, Wood CR, Greenfield EA, Freeman GJ. Blockade of programmed death-1 ligands on dendritic cells enhances T cell activation and cytokine production. J Immunol. 2003 Feb 1;170(3):1257-66.</citation>
    <PMID>12538684</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Francisco LM, Sage PT, Sharpe AH. The PD-1 pathway in tolerance and autoimmunity. Immunol Rev. 2010 Jul;236:219-42. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-065X.2010.00923.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20636820</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Thompson RH, Dong H, Lohse CM, Leibovich BC, Blute ML, Cheville JC, Kwon ED. PD-1 is expressed by tumor-infiltrating immune cells and is associated with poor outcome for patients with renal cell carcinoma. Clin Cancer Res. 2007 Mar 15;13(6):1757-61.</citation>
    <PMID>17363529</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hino R, Kabashima K, Kato Y, Yagi H, Nakamura M, Honjo T, Okazaki T, Tokura Y. Tumor cell expression of programmed cell death-1 ligand 1 is a prognostic factor for malignant melanoma. Cancer. 2010 Apr 1;116(7):1757-66. doi: 10.1002/cncr.24899.</citation>
    <PMID>20143437</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nomi T, Sho M, Akahori T, Hamada K, Kubo A, Kanehiro H, Nakamura S, Enomoto K, Yagita H, Azuma M, Nakajima Y. Clinical significance and therapeutic potential of the programmed death-1 ligand/programmed death-1 pathway in human pancreatic cancer. Clin Cancer Res. 2007 Apr 1;13(7):2151-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17404099</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gao Q, Wang XY, Qiu SJ, Yamato I, Sho M, Nakajima Y, Zhou J, Li BZ, Shi YH, Xiao YS, Xu Y, Fan J. Overexpression of PD-L1 significantly associates with tumor aggressiveness and postoperative recurrence in human hepatocellular carcinoma. Clin Cancer Res. 2009 Feb 1;15(3):971-9. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-08-1608.</citation>
    <PMID>19188168</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hamanishi J, Mandai M, Iwasaki M, Okazaki T, Tanaka Y, Yamaguchi K, Higuchi T, Yagi H, Takakura K, Minato N, Honjo T, Fujii S. Programmed cell death 1 ligand 1 and tumor-infiltrating CD8+ T lymphocytes are prognostic factors of human ovarian cancer. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Feb 27;104(9):3360-5. Epub 2007 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>17360651</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fourcade J, Kudela P, Sun Z, Shen H, Land SR, Lenzner D, Guillaume P, Luescher IF, Sander C, Ferrone S, Kirkwood JM, Zarour HM. PD-1 is a regulator of NY-ESO-1-specific CD8+ T cell expansion in melanoma patients. J Immunol. 2009 May 1;182(9):5240-9. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.0803245.</citation>
    <PMID>19380770</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cai G, Karni A, Oliveira EM, Weiner HL, Hafler DA, Freeman GJ. PD-1 ligands, negative regulators for activation of naive, memory, and recently activated human CD4+ T cells. Cell Immunol. 2004 Aug;230(2):89-98.</citation>
    <PMID>15598424</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Blank C, Mackensen A. Contribution of the PD-L1/PD-1 pathway to T-cell exhaustion: an update on implications for chronic infections and tumor evasion. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2007 May;56(5):739-45. Epub 2006 Dec 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17195077</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Iwai Y, Ishida M, Tanaka Y, Okazaki T, Honjo T, Minato N. Involvement of PD-L1 on tumor cells in the escape from host immune system and tumor immunotherapy by PD-L1 blockade. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2002 Sep 17;99(19):12293-7. Epub 2002 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>12218188</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tsushima F, Tanaka K, Otsuki N, Youngnak P, Iwai H, Omura K, Azuma M. Predominant expression of B7-H1 and its immunoregulatory roles in oral squamous cell carcinoma. Oral Oncol. 2006 Mar;42(3):268-74. Epub 2005 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>16271509</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Oble DA, Loewe R, Yu P, Mihm MC Jr. Focus on TILs: prognostic significance of tumor infiltrating lymphocytes in human melanoma. Cancer Immun. 2009 Apr 2;9:3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19338264</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Topalian SL, Hodi FS, Brahmer JR, Gettinger SN, Smith DC, McDermott DF, Powderly JD, Carvajal RD, Sosman JA, Atkins MB, Leming PD, Spigel DR, Antonia SJ, Horn L, Drake CG, Pardoll DM, Chen L, Sharfman WH, Anders RA, Taube JM, McMiller TL, Xu H, Korman AJ, Jure-Kunkel M, Agrawal S, McDonald D, Kollia GD, Gupta A, Wigginton JM, Sznol M. Safety, activity, and immune correlates of anti-PD-1 antibody in cancer. N Engl J Med. 2012 Jun 28;366(26):2443-54. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1200690. Epub 2012 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22658127</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Patnaik A, Kang SP, Rasco D, Papadopoulos KP, Elassaiss-Schaap J, Beeram M, Drengler R, Chen C, Smith L, Espino G, Gergich K, Delgado L, Daud A, Lindia JA, Li XN, Pierce RH, Yearley JH, Wu D, Laterza O, Lehnert M, Iannone R, Tolcher AW. Phase I Study of Pembrolizumab (MK-3475; Anti-PD-1 Monoclonal Antibody) in Patients with Advanced Solid Tumors. Clin Cancer Res. 2015 Oct 1;21(19):4286-93. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-14-2607. Epub 2015 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>25977344</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hodi FS, O'Day SJ, McDermott DF, Weber RW, Sosman JA, Haanen JB, Gonzalez R, Robert C, Schadendorf D, Hassel JC, Akerley W, van den Eertwegh AJ, Lutzky J, Lorigan P, Vaubel JM, Linette GP, Hogg D, Ottensmeier CH, Lebbé C, Peschel C, Quirt I, Clark JI, Wolchok JD, Weber JS, Tian J, Yellin MJ, Nichol GM, Hoos A, Urba WJ. Improved survival with ipilimumab in patients with metastatic melanoma. N Engl J Med. 2010 Aug 19;363(8):711-23. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1003466. Epub 2010 Jun 5. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2010 Sep 23;363(13):1290.</citation>
    <PMID>20525992</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chapman PB, Hauschild A, Robert C, Haanen JB, Ascierto P, Larkin J, Dummer R, Garbe C, Testori A, Maio M, Hogg D, Lorigan P, Lebbe C, Jouary T, Schadendorf D, Ribas A, O'Day SJ, Sosman JA, Kirkwood JM, Eggermont AM, Dreno B, Nolop K, Li J, Nelson B, Hou J, Lee RJ, Flaherty KT, McArthur GA; BRIM-3 Study Group. Improved survival with vemurafenib in melanoma with BRAF V600E mutation. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jun 30;364(26):2507-16. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1103782. Epub 2011 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21639808</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Robert C, Thomas L, Bondarenko I, O'Day S, Weber J, Garbe C, Lebbe C, Baurain JF, Testori A, Grob JJ, Davidson N, Richards J, Maio M, Hauschild A, Miller WH Jr, Gascon P, Lotem M, Harmankaya K, Ibrahim R, Francis S, Chen TT, Humphrey R, Hoos A, Wolchok JD. Ipilimumab plus dacarbazine for previously untreated metastatic melanoma. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jun 30;364(26):2517-26. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1104621. Epub 2011 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21639810</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bellati F, Visconti V, Napoletano C, Antonilli M, Frati L, Panici PB, Nuti M. Immunology of gynecologic neoplasms: analysis of the prognostic significance of the immune status. Curr Cancer Drug Targets. 2009 Jun;9(4):541-65. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19519321</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ruffell B, DeNardo DG, Affara NI, Coussens LM. Lymphocytes in cancer development: polarization towards pro-tumor immunity. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 2010 Feb;21(1):3-10. doi: 10.1016/j.cytogfr.2009.11.002. Epub 2009 Dec 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20005150</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Shirabe K, Motomura T, Muto J, Toshima T, Matono R, Mano Y, Takeishi K, Ijichi H, Harada N, Uchiyama H, Yoshizumi T, Taketomi A, Maehara Y. Tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes and hepatocellular carcinoma: pathology and clinical management. Int J Clin Oncol. 2010 Dec;15(6):552-8. doi: 10.1007/s10147-010-0131-0. Epub 2010 Oct 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20963618</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Al-Shibli K, Al-Saad S, Andersen S, Donnem T, Bremnes RM, Busund LT. The prognostic value of intraepithelial and stromal CD3-, CD117- and CD138-positive cells in non-small cell lung carcinoma. APMIS. 2010 May;118(5):371-82. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0463.2010.02609.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20477813</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Clark CE, Beatty GL, Vonderheide RH. Immunosurveillance of pancreatic adenocarcinoma: insights from genetically engineered mouse models of cancer. Cancer Lett. 2009 Jun 28;279(1):1-7. doi: 10.1016/j.canlet.2008.09.037. Epub 2008 Nov 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19013709</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Diederichsen AC, Hjelmborg Jv, Christensen PB, Zeuthen J, Fenger C. Prognostic value of the CD4+/CD8+ ratio of tumour infiltrating lymphocytes in colorectal cancer and HLA-DR expression on tumour cells. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2003 Jul;52(7):423-8. Epub 2003 Apr 15.</citation>
    <PMID>12695859</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gao Q, Qiu SJ, Fan J, Zhou J, Wang XY, Xiao YS, Xu Y, Li YW, Tang ZY. Intratumoral balance of regulatory and cytotoxic T cells is associated with prognosis of hepatocellular carcinoma after resection. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Jun 20;25(18):2586-93.</citation>
    <PMID>17577038</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hillen F, Baeten CI, van de Winkel A, Creytens D, van der Schaft DW, Winnepenninckx V, Griffioen AW. Leukocyte infiltration and tumor cell plasticity are parameters of aggressiveness in primary cutaneous melanoma. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2008 Jan;57(1):97-106. Epub 2007 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>17602225</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Laghi L, Bianchi P, Miranda E, Balladore E, Pacetti V, Grizzi F, Allavena P, Torri V, Repici A, Santoro A, Mantovani A, Roncalli M, Malesci A. CD3+ cells at the invasive margin of deeply invading (pT3-T4) colorectal cancer and risk of post-surgical metastasis: a longitudinal study. Lancet Oncol. 2009 Sep;10(9):877-84. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(09)70186-X. Epub 2009 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19656725</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Li JF, Chu YW, Wang GM, Zhu TY, Rong RM, Hou J, Xu M. The prognostic value of peritumoral regulatory T cells and its correlation with intratumoral cyclooxygenase-2 expression in clear cell renal cell carcinoma. BJU Int. 2009 Feb;103(3):399-405. doi: 10.1111/j.1464-410X.2008.08151.x. Epub 2008 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19021626</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nemolato S, Fanni D, Naccarato AG, Ravarino A, Bevilacqua G, Faa G. Lymphoepitelioma-like hepatocellular carcinoma: a case report and a review of the literature. World J Gastroenterol. 2008 Aug 7;14(29):4694-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18698686</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nobili C, Degrate L, Caprotti R, Franciosi C, Leone BE, Trezzi R, Romano F, Uggeri F, Uggeri F. Prolonged survival of a patient affected by pancreatic adenocarcinoma with massive lymphocyte and dendritic cell infiltration after interleukin-2 immunotherapy. Report of a case. Tumori. 2008 May-Jun;94(3):426-30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18705415</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Oshikiri T, Miyamoto M, Shichinohe T, Suzuoki M, Hiraoka K, Nakakubo Y, Shinohara T, Itoh T, Kondo S, Katoh H. Prognostic value of intratumoral CD8+ T lymphocyte in extrahepatic bile duct carcinoma as essential immune response. J Surg Oncol. 2003 Dec;84(4):224-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14756433</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Piersma SJ, Welters MJ, van der Burg SH. Tumor-specific regulatory T cells in cancer patients. Hum Immunol. 2008 Apr-May;69(4-5):241-9. doi: 10.1016/j.humimm.2008.02.005. Epub 2008 Mar 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18486758</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rao UN, Lee SJ, Luo W, Mihm MC Jr, Kirkwood JM. Presence of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes and a dominant nodule within primary melanoma are prognostic factors for relapse-free survival of patients with thick (t4) primary melanoma: pathologic analysis of the e1690 and e1694 intergroup trials. Am J Clin Pathol. 2010 Apr;133(4):646-53. doi: 10.1309/AJCPTXMEFOVYWDA6.</citation>
    <PMID>20231618</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sasaki A, Tanaka F, Mimori K, Inoue H, Kai S, Shibata K, Ohta M, Kitano S, Mori M. Prognostic value of tumor-infiltrating FOXP3+ regulatory T cells in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma. Eur J Surg Oncol. 2008 Feb;34(2):173-9. Epub 2007 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17928188</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Shen Z, Zhou S, Wang Y, Li RL, Zhong C, Liang C, Sun Y. Higher intratumoral infiltrated Foxp3+ Treg numbers and Foxp3+/CD8+ ratio are associated with adverse prognosis in resectable gastric cancer. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol. 2010 Oct;136(10):1585-95. doi: 10.1007/s00432-010-0816-9. Epub 2010 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>20221835</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Talmadge JE, Donkor M, Scholar E. Inflammatory cell infiltration of tumors: Jekyll or Hyde. Cancer Metastasis Rev. 2007 Dec;26(3-4):373-400. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17717638</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Usubütün A, Ayhan A, Uygur MC, Ozen H, Toklu C, Ruacan S. Prognostic factors in renal cell carcinoma. J Exp Clin Cancer Res. 1998 Mar;17(1):77-81.</citation>
    <PMID>9646237</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hiraoka N. Tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes and hepatocellular carcinoma: molecular biology. Int J Clin Oncol. 2010 Dec;15(6):544-51. doi: 10.1007/s10147-010-0130-1. Epub 2010 Oct 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20924634</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hodi FS, Dranoff G. The biologic importance of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes. J Cutan Pathol. 2010 Apr;37 Suppl 1:48-53. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0560.2010.01506.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20482675</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kloor M. Lymphocyte infiltration and prognosis in colorectal cancer. Lancet Oncol. 2009 Sep;10(9):840-1. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(09)70245-1.</citation>
    <PMID>19717085</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee HE, Chae SW, Lee YJ, Kim MA, Lee HS, Lee BL, Kim WH. Prognostic implications of type and density of tumour-infiltrating lymphocytes in gastric cancer. Br J Cancer. 2008 Nov 18;99(10):1704-11. doi: 10.1038/sj.bjc.6604738. Epub 2008 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>18941457</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Leffers N, Gooden MJ, de Jong RA, Hoogeboom BN, ten Hoor KA, Hollema H, Boezen HM, van der Zee AG, Daemen T, Nijman HW. Prognostic significance of tumor-infiltrating T-lymphocytes in primary and metastatic lesions of advanced stage ovarian cancer. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2009 Mar;58(3):449-59. doi: 10.1007/s00262-008-0583-5. Epub 2008 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>18791714</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nishimura H, Honjo T, Minato N. Facilitation of beta selection and modification of positive selection in the thymus of PD-1-deficient mice. J Exp Med. 2000 Mar 6;191(5):891-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10704469</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pölcher M, Braun M, Friedrichs N, Rudlowski C, Bercht E, Fimmers R, Sauerwald A, Keyver-Paik MD, Kübler K, Büttner R, Kuhn WC, Hernando JJ. Foxp3(+) cell infiltration and granzyme B(+)/Foxp3(+) cell ratio are associated with outcome in neoadjuvant chemotherapy-treated ovarian carcinoma. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2010 Jun;59(6):909-19. doi: 10.1007/s00262-010-0817-1. Epub 2010 Jan 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20087581</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Suzuki H, Chikazawa N, Tasaka T, Wada J, Yamasaki A, Kitaura Y, Sozaki M, Tanaka M, Onishi H, Morisaki T, Katano M. Intratumoral CD8(+) T/FOXP3 (+) cell ratio is a predictive marker for survival in patients with colorectal cancer. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2010 May;59(5):653-61. doi: 10.1007/s00262-009-0781-9. Epub 2009 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19908042</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chew V, Tow C, Teo M, Wong HL, Chan J, Gehring A, Loh M, Bolze A, Quek R, Lee VK, Lee KH, Abastado JP, Toh HC, Nardin A. Inflammatory tumour microenvironment is associated with superior survival in hepatocellular carcinoma patients. J Hepatol. 2010 Mar;52(3):370-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2009.07.013. Epub 2009 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19720422</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Liotta F, Gacci M, Frosali F, Querci V, Vittori G, Lapini A, Santarlasci V, Serni S, Cosmi L, Maggi L, Angeli R, Mazzinghi B, Romagnani P, Maggi E, Carini M, Romagnani S, Annunziato F. Frequency of regulatory T cells in peripheral blood and in tumour-infiltrating lymphocytes correlates with poor prognosis in renal cell carcinoma. BJU Int. 2011 May;107(9):1500-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1464-410X.2010.09555.x. Epub 2010 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20735382</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ropponen KM, Eskelinen MJ, Lipponen PK, Alhava E, Kosma VM. Prognostic value of tumour-infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs) in colorectal cancer. J Pathol. 1997 Jul;182(3):318-24.</citation>
    <PMID>9349235</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dudley ME, Wunderlich JR, Yang JC, Sherry RM, Topalian SL, Restifo NP, Royal RE, Kammula U, White DE, Mavroukakis SA, Rogers LJ, Gracia GJ, Jones SA, Mangiameli DP, Pelletier MM, Gea-Banacloche J, Robinson MR, Berman DM, Filie AC, Abati A, Rosenberg SA. Adoptive cell transfer therapy following non-myeloablative but lymphodepleting chemotherapy for the treatment of patients with refractory metastatic melanoma. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Apr 1;23(10):2346-57.</citation>
    <PMID>15800326</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hunder NN, Wallen H, Cao J, Hendricks DW, Reilly JZ, Rodmyre R, Jungbluth A, Gnjatic S, Thompson JA, Yee C. Treatment of metastatic melanoma with autologous CD4+ T cells against NY-ESO-1. N Engl J Med. 2008 Jun 19;358(25):2698-703. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0800251.</citation>
    <PMID>18565862</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Okazaki T, Maeda A, Nishimura H, Kurosaki T, Honjo T. PD-1 immunoreceptor inhibits B cell receptor-mediated signaling by recruiting src homology 2-domain-containing tyrosine phosphatase 2 to phosphotyrosine. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2001 Nov 20;98(24):13866-71. Epub 2001 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>11698646</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Greenwald RJ, Freeman GJ, Sharpe AH. The B7 family revisited. Annu Rev Immunol. 2005;23:515-48. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15771580</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hamid O, Robert C, Daud A, Hodi FS, Hwu WJ, Kefford R, Wolchok JD, Hersey P, Joseph RW, Weber JS, Dronca R, Gangadhar TC, Patnaik A, Zarour H, Joshua AM, Gergich K, Elassaiss-Schaap J, Algazi A, Mateus C, Boasberg P, Tumeh PC, Chmielowski B, Ebbinghaus SW, Li XN, Kang SP, Ribas A. Safety and tumor responses with lambrolizumab (anti-PD-1) in melanoma. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jul 11;369(2):134-44. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1305133. Epub 2013 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23724846</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Peters S, Adjei AA, Gridelli C, Reck M, Kerr K, Felip E; ESMO Guidelines Working Group. Metastatic non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC): ESMO Clinical Practice Guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol. 2012 Oct;23 Suppl 7:vii56-64.</citation>
    <PMID>22997455</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Scagliotti GV, Parikh P, von Pawel J, Biesma B, Vansteenkiste J, Manegold C, Serwatowski P, Gatzemeier U, Digumarti R, Zukin M, Lee JS, Mellemgaard A, Park K, Patil S, Rolski J, Goksel T, de Marinis F, Simms L, Sugarman KP, Gandara D. Phase III study comparing cisplatin plus gemcitabine with cisplatin plus pemetrexed in chemotherapy-naive patients with advanced-stage non-small-cell lung cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2008 Jul 20;26(21):3543-51. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2007.15.0375. Epub 2008 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>18506025</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schiller JH, Harrington D, Belani CP, Langer C, Sandler A, Krook J, Zhu J, Johnson DH; Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group. Comparison of four chemotherapy regimens for advanced non-small-cell lung cancer. N Engl J Med. 2002 Jan 10;346(2):92-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11784875</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Bray F, Center MM, Ferlay J, Ward E, Forman D. Global cancer statistics. CA Cancer J Clin. 2011 Mar-Apr;61(2):69-90. doi: 10.3322/caac.20107. Epub 2011 Feb 4. Erratum in: CA Cancer J Clin. 2011 Mar-Apr;61(2):134.</citation>
    <PMID>21296855</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Reck M, von Pawel J, Zatloukal P, Ramlau R, Gorbounova V, Hirsh V, Leighl N, Mezger J, Archer V, Moore N, Manegold C. Phase III trial of cisplatin plus gemcitabine with either placebo or bevacizumab as first-line therapy for nonsquamous non-small-cell lung cancer: AVAil. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Mar 10;27(8):1227-34. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2007.14.5466. Epub 2009 Feb 2. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2009 May 10;27(14):2415.</citation>
    <PMID>19188680</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sandler A, Gray R, Perry MC, Brahmer J, Schiller JH, Dowlati A, Lilenbaum R, Johnson DH. Paclitaxel-carboplatin alone or with bevacizumab for non-small-cell lung cancer. N Engl J Med. 2006 Dec 14;355(24):2542-50. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2007 Jan 18;356(3):318.</citation>
    <PMID>17167137</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nishie K, Kawaguchi T, Tamiya A, Mimori T, Takeuchi N, Matsuda Y, Omachi N, Asami K, Okishio K, Atagi S, Okuma T, Kubo A, Maruyama Y, Kudoh S, Takada M. Epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors beyond progressive disease: a retrospective analysis for Japanese patients with activating EGFR mutations. J Thorac Oncol. 2012 Nov;7(11):1722-7. doi: 10.1097/JTO.0b013e31826913f7.</citation>
    <PMID>23059777</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Camidge DR, Bang YJ, Kwak EL, Iafrate AJ, Varella-Garcia M, Fox SB, Riely GJ, Solomon B, Ou SH, Kim DW, Salgia R, Fidias P, Engelman JA, Gandhi L, Jänne PA, Costa DB, Shapiro GI, Lorusso P, Ruffner K, Stephenson P, Tang Y, Wilner K, Clark JW, Shaw AT. Activity and safety of crizotinib in patients with ALK-positive non-small-cell lung cancer: updated results from a phase 1 study. Lancet Oncol. 2012 Oct;13(10):1011-9. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(12)70344-3. Epub 2012 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22954507</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fukuoka M, Wu YL, Thongprasert S, Sunpaweravong P, Leong SS, Sriuranpong V, Chao TY, Nakagawa K, Chu DT, Saijo N, Duffield EL, Rukazenkov Y, Speake G, Jiang H, Armour AA, To KF, Yang JC, Mok TS. Biomarker analyses and final overall survival results from a phase III, randomized, open-label, first-line study of gefitinib versus carboplatin/paclitaxel in clinically selected patients with advanced non-small-cell lung cancer in Asia (IPASS). J Clin Oncol. 2011 Jul 20;29(21):2866-74. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.33.4235. Epub 2011 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>21670455</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Akbay EA, Koyama S, Carretero J, Altabef A, Tchaicha JH, Christensen CL, Mikse OR, Cherniack AD, Beauchamp EM, Pugh TJ, Wilkerson MD, Fecci PE, Butaney M, Reibel JB, Soucheray M, Cohoon TJ, Janne PA, Meyerson M, Hayes DN, Shapiro GI, Shimamura T, Sholl LM, Rodig SJ, Freeman GJ, Hammerman PS, Dranoff G, Wong KK. Activation of the PD-1 pathway contributes to immune escape in EGFR-driven lung tumors. Cancer Discov. 2013 Dec;3(12):1355-63. doi: 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-13-0310. Epub 2013 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24078774</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gettinger S, Herbst RS. B7-H1/PD-1 blockade therapy in non-small cell lung cancer: current status and future direction. Cancer J. 2014 Jul-Aug;20(4):281-9. doi: 10.1097/PPO.0000000000000063. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25098289</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Velcheti V, Schalper KA, Carvajal DE, Anagnostou VK, Syrigos KN, Sznol M, Herbst RS, Gettinger SN, Chen L, Rimm DL. Programmed death ligand-1 expression in non-small cell lung cancer. Lab Invest. 2014 Jan;94(1):107-16. doi: 10.1038/labinvest.2013.130. Epub 2013 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24217091</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Taube JM, Klein A, Brahmer JR, Xu H, Pan X, Kim JH, Chen L, Pardoll DM, Topalian SL, Anders RA. Association of PD-1, PD-1 ligands, and other features of the tumor immune microenvironment with response to anti-PD-1 therapy. Clin Cancer Res. 2014 Oct 1;20(19):5064-74. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-13-3271. Epub 2014 Apr 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24714771</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bauer CA, Kim EY, Marangoni F, Carrizosa E, Claudio NM, Mempel TR. Dynamic Treg interactions with intratumoral APCs promote local CTL dysfunction. J Clin Invest. 2014 Jun;124(6):2425-40. doi: 10.1172/JCI66375. Epub 2014 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24812664</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Highfill SL, Cui Y, Giles AJ, Smith JP, Zhang H, Morse E, Kaplan RN, Mackall CL. Disruption of CXCR2-mediated MDSC tumor trafficking enhances anti-PD1 efficacy. Sci Transl Med. 2014 May 21;6(237):237ra67. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3007974.</citation>
    <PMID>24848257</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ascierto PA, Kalos M, Schaer DA, Callahan MK, Wolchok JD. Biomarkers for immunostimulatory monoclonal antibodies in combination strategies for melanoma and other tumor types. Clin Cancer Res. 2013 Mar 1;19(5):1009-20. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-12-2982.</citation>
    <PMID>23460532</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ng Tang D, Shen Y, Sun J, Wen S, Wolchok JD, Yuan J, Allison JP, Sharma P. Increased frequency of ICOS+ CD4 T cells as a pharmacodynamic biomarker for anti-CTLA-4 therapy. Cancer Immunol Res. 2013 Oct;1(4):229-34. doi: 10.1158/2326-6066.CIR-13-0020. Epub 2013 Jul 31. Erratum in: Cancer Immunol Res. 2014 May;2(5):501.</citation>
    <PMID>24777852</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pico de Coaña Y, Poschke I, Gentilcore G, Mao Y, Nyström M, Hansson J, Masucci GV, Kiessling R. Ipilimumab treatment results in an early decrease in the frequency of circulating granulocytic myeloid-derived suppressor cells as well as their Arginase1 production. Cancer Immunol Res. 2013 Sep;1(3):158-62. doi: 10.1158/2326-6066.CIR-13-0016. Epub 2013 Aug 2. Erratum in: Cancer Immunol Res. 2013 Dec;1(6):438.</citation>
    <PMID>24777678</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tarhini AA, Edington H, Butterfield LH, Lin Y, Shuai Y, Tawbi H, Sander C, Yin Y, Holtzman M, Johnson J, Rao UN, Kirkwood JM. Immune monitoring of the circulation and the tumor microenvironment in patients with regionally advanced melanoma receiving neoadjuvant ipilimumab. PLoS One. 2014 Feb 3;9(2):e87705. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0087705. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24498358</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Improta G, Pelosi G, Tamborini E, Donia M, Santinami M, de Braud F, Fraggetta F. Biological insights into BRAF(V600) mutations in melanoma patient: Not mere therapeutic targets. Oncoimmunology. 2013 Aug 1;2(8):e25594. Epub 2013 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24179707</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brahmer J, Reckamp KL, Baas P, Crinò L, Eberhardt WE, Poddubskaya E, Antonia S, Pluzanski A, Vokes EE, Holgado E, Waterhouse D, Ready N, Gainor J, Arén Frontera O, Havel L, Steins M, Garassino MC, Aerts JG, Domine M, Paz-Ares L, Reck M, Baudelet C, Harbison CT, Lestini B, Spigel DR. Nivolumab versus Docetaxel in Advanced Squamous-Cell Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer. N Engl J Med. 2015 Jul 9;373(2):123-35. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1504627. Epub 2015 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26028407</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bellmunt J, de Wit R, Vaughn DJ, Fradet Y, Lee JL, Fong L, Vogelzang NJ, Climent MA, Petrylak DP, Choueiri TK, Necchi A, Gerritsen W, Gurney H, Quinn DI, Culine S, Sternberg CN, Mai Y, Poehlein CH, Perini RF, Bajorin DF; KEYNOTE-045 Investigators. Pembrolizumab as Second-Line Therapy for Advanced Urothelial Carcinoma. N Engl J Med. 2017 Mar 16;376(11):1015-1026. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1613683. Epub 2017 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28212060</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Reck M, Rodríguez-Abreu D, Robinson AG, Hui R, Csőszi T, Fülöp A, Gottfried M, Peled N, Tafreshi A, Cuffe S, O'Brien M, Rao S, Hotta K, Leiby MA, Lubiniecki GM, Shentu Y, Rangwala R, Brahmer JR; KEYNOTE-024 Investigators. Pembrolizumab versus Chemotherapy for PD-L1-Positive Non-Small-Cell Lung Cancer. N Engl J Med. 2016 Nov 10;375(19):1823-1833. Epub 2016 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27718847</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nghiem PT, Bhatia S, Lipson EJ, Kudchadkar RR, Miller NJ, Annamalai L, Berry S, Chartash EK, Daud A, Fling SP, Friedlander PA, Kluger HM, Kohrt HE, Lundgren L, Margolin K, Mitchell A, Olencki T, Pardoll DM, Reddy SA, Shantha EM, Sharfman WH, Sharon E, Shemanski LR, Shinohara MM, Sunshine JC, Taube JM, Thompson JA, Townson SM, Yearley JH, Topalian SL, Cheever MA. PD-1 Blockade with Pembrolizumab in Advanced Merkel-Cell Carcinoma. N Engl J Med. 2016 Jun 30;374(26):2542-52. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1603702. Epub 2016 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27093365</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Garon EB, Rizvi NA, Hui R, Leighl N, Balmanoukian AS, Eder JP, Patnaik A, Aggarwal C, Gubens M, Horn L, Carcereny E, Ahn MJ, Felip E, Lee JS, Hellmann MD, Hamid O, Goldman JW, Soria JC, Dolled-Filhart M, Rutledge RZ, Zhang J, Lunceford JK, Rangwala R, Lubiniecki GM, Roach C, Emancipator K, Gandhi L; KEYNOTE-001 Investigators. Pembrolizumab for the treatment of non-small-cell lung cancer. N Engl J Med. 2015 May 21;372(21):2018-28. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1501824. Epub 2015 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>25891174</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Robert C, Schachter J, Long GV, Arance A, Grob JJ, Mortier L, Daud A, Carlino MS, McNeil C, Lotem M, Larkin J, Lorigan P, Neyns B, Blank CU, Hamid O, Mateus C, Shapira-Frommer R, Kosh M, Zhou H, Ibrahim N, Ebbinghaus S, Ribas A; KEYNOTE-006 investigators. Pembrolizumab versus Ipilimumab in Advanced Melanoma. N Engl J Med. 2015 Jun 25;372(26):2521-32. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1503093. Epub 2015 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>25891173</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alley EW, Lopez J, Santoro A, Morosky A, Saraf S, Piperdi B, van Brummelen E. Clinical safety and activity of pembrolizumab in patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma (KEYNOTE-028): preliminary results from a non-randomised, open-label, phase 1b trial. Lancet Oncol. 2017 May;18(5):623-630. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(17)30169-9. Epub 2017 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>28291584</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Seiwert TY, Burtness B, Mehra R, Weiss J, Berger R, Eder JP, Heath K, McClanahan T, Lunceford J, Gause C, Cheng JD, Chow LQ. Safety and clinical activity of pembrolizumab for treatment of recurrent or metastatic squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck (KEYNOTE-012): an open-label, multicentre, phase 1b trial. Lancet Oncol. 2016 Jul;17(7):956-965. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(16)30066-3. Epub 2016 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>27247226</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Herbst RS, Baas P, Kim DW, Felip E, Pérez-Gracia JL, Han JY, Molina J, Kim JH, Arvis CD, Ahn MJ, Majem M, Fidler MJ, de Castro G Jr, Garrido M, Lubiniecki GM, Shentu Y, Im E, Dolled-Filhart M, Garon EB. Pembrolizumab versus docetaxel for previously treated, PD-L1-positive, advanced non-small-cell lung cancer (KEYNOTE-010): a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2016 Apr 9;387(10027):1540-50. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)01281-7. Epub 2015 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>26712084</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ribas A, Puzanov I, Dummer R, Schadendorf D, Hamid O, Robert C, Hodi FS, Schachter J, Pavlick AC, Lewis KD, Cranmer LD, Blank CU, O'Day SJ, Ascierto PA, Salama AK, Margolin KA, Loquai C, Eigentler TK, Gangadhar TC, Carlino MS, Agarwala SS, Moschos SJ, Sosman JA, Goldinger SM, Shapira-Frommer R, Gonzalez R, Kirkwood JM, Wolchok JD, Eggermont A, Li XN, Zhou W, Zernhelt AM, Lis J, Ebbinghaus S, Kang SP, Daud A. Pembrolizumab versus investigator-choice chemotherapy for ipilimumab-refractory melanoma (KEYNOTE-002): a randomised, controlled, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol. 2015 Aug;16(8):908-18. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(15)00083-2. Epub 2015 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26115796</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chow LQM, Haddad R, Gupta S, Mahipal A, Mehra R, Tahara M, Berger R, Eder JP, Burtness B, Lee SH, Keam B, Kang H, Muro K, Weiss J, Geva R, Lin CC, Chung HC, Meister A, Dolled-Filhart M, Pathiraja K, Cheng JD, Seiwert TY. Antitumor Activity of Pembrolizumab in Biomarker-Unselected Patients With Recurrent and/or Metastatic Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma: Results From the Phase Ib KEYNOTE-012 Expansion Cohort. J Clin Oncol. 2016 Nov 10;34(32):3838-3845. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2016.68.1478. Epub 2016 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>27646946</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Daud AI, Wolchok JD, Robert C, Hwu WJ, Weber JS, Ribas A, Hodi FS, Joshua AM, Kefford R, Hersey P, Joseph R, Gangadhar TC, Dronca R, Patnaik A, Zarour H, Roach C, Toland G, Lunceford JK, Li XN, Emancipator K, Dolled-Filhart M, Kang SP, Ebbinghaus S, Hamid O. Programmed Death-Ligand 1 Expression and Response to the Anti-Programmed Death 1 Antibody Pembrolizumab in Melanoma. J Clin Oncol. 2016 Dec;34(34):4102-4109. Epub 2016 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>27863197</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

