<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03449823</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAQ9660</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03449823</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Renal Artery Dopplers in Twin Twin Transfusion Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Are Renal Artery Doppler Indices Different Between Monochorionic Diamniotic Twins With Twin-twin Transfusion Syndrome and Monochorionic Diamniotic Twins Without Twin-twin Transfusion Syndrome?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Twin-twin transfusion syndrome (TTTS) is a complication affecting 10-15% of monochorionic,
      diamniotic (MCDA) twin pregnancies. Unevenly distributed blood flow across a shared placental
      circulation results in a volume-restricted donor twin and a volume-overloaded recipient twin,
      and TTTS has high perinatal morbidity and mortality without treatment.

      Differential donor and recipient findings in TTTS can be observed upon ultrasound evaluation.
      TTTS is classified according to the Quintero staging system, which evaluates amniotic fluid
      volumes, fetal bladders, Doppler study of the umbilical artery and ductus venosus, and for
      the presence of hydrops or death. However, due to seemingly complex and variable disease
      pathophysiology, the Quintero system cannot predict outcomes on a case-by-case basis.

      Prior studies have associated fetal renal artery Doppler ultrasound measurements with
      amniotic fluid volume in singleton pregnancies. In fetuses with placental insufficiency,
      adaptive circulatory changes maintain adequate oxygen delivery to vital organs such as the
      heart, brain, and adrenals, with a consequent deprivation to splanchnic organs. In the fetal
      kidney, as vascular resistance increases during hypoxia, renal perfusion decreases
      proportionately. These changes are reflected in renal artery Doppler findings. As these same
      adaptations are believed to occur in donor twins, renal artery Doppler studies may also be of
      value in the TTTS evaluation.

      This study plans to perform renal artery Doppler assessments in MCDA twins complicated by
      TTTS, and compare them to measurements in gestational-age equivalent MCDA twins without TTTS.
      If findings differ significantly, it would support further investigation into the use of
      renal artery Doppler studies for the evaluation of complicated MCDA twins.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TTTS, which complicates 10-15% of MCDA twin pregnancies, is characterized by a net imbalance
      of volume between twins, mediated through abnormal placental blood vessel anastomoses that
      connect the two placental circulations. Clinically, the &quot;donor&quot; twin develops features of
      anemia and hypovolemia, while the &quot;recipient&quot; twin shows signs of hypervolemia and
      hypertensive fluid overload. If untreated, the syndrome has a perinatal mortality rate as
      high as 80-100%. Although modern intrauterine therapies have improved the rates of fetal
      death, significant risks of morbidity and mortality remain even after treatment.

      Twin-twin transfusion syndrome is most commonly classified according to a staging system
      developed by Quintero et al in 1999, which is based on discrete, categorical ultrasound
      findings (amniotic fluid volume, presence/absence of a fetal bladder, umbilical artery
      Doppler studies, fetal hydrops, and death). The system includes 5 stages ranging from mild
      disease with isolated discordant amniotic fluid volumes, to severe disease with demise of one
      or both twins. Although this system has some prognostic value, it also has significant
      limitations due to the highly complex physiologic conditions that are involved in the
      disease. For example, some criteria in the staging system are not consistently representative
      of fetal physiology. Additionally, the stages do not correlate well with overall perinatal
      survival or with outcomes following intrauterine therapies.

      Recent work has demonstrated that the complex pathophysiology of twin-twin transfusion
      syndrome involves a discordant activation of the renin angiotensin system (RAS). RAS is
      normally important in fluid and salt regulation in both the adult and the fetus, and TTTS in
      marked hypovolemia and hypervolemia in monozygous fetuses within the same maternal
      environment. The renal RAS in the donor is up-regulated, presumably as a consequence of
      hypovolemia. The recipient is also exposed to high levels or RAS components, either due to
      the transfusion of these components from the donor via anastomoses, or via discordant
      placental RAS activation, resulting in a hypertensive, hypervolemic state.

      Multiple studies have identified a correlation between Doppler assessment of the fetal renal
      artery and the development of oligohydramnios, a hypovolemic state, in singleton pregnancies.
      However, the use of renal artery Doppler studies has not yet been fully evaluated in twin
      gestations. In particular, it has not been evaluated in MCDA twin gestations complicated by
      TTTS, the pathophysiology of which involves significant alterations in fetal volume and fluid
      status.

      This project is intended to serve as a single-center study to determine if there is indeed a
      difference in renal artery Doppler parameters in sets of MCDA twins with TTTS compared to
      sets of MCDA twins without TTTS. The identification of a significant difference would
      potentially provide support for further investigation into this measurement as a screening
      tool or prognostic indicator when applied to MCDA twin pregnancies.

      Secondary goals of this study include: comparing donor to recipient renal artery Doppler
      findings among pregnancies with TTTS, evaluating serial renal artery Doppler findings over
      time per pregnancy, and evaluating pre- and post-therapy renal artery Doppler findings in
      those pregnancies undergoing therapy for TTTS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 9, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 21, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fetal renal artery Doppler PSV for twin A</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained at the time of enrollment.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the peak systolic velocity for twin A.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fetal renal artery Doppler RI for twin A</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained at the time of enrollment.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the resistive index for twin A.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fetal renal artery Doppler PI for twin A</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained at the time of enrollment.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the pulsatility index for twin A.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fetal renal artery Doppler PSV for twin B</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained at the time of enrollment.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the peak systolic velocity for twin B.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fetal renal artery Doppler RI for twin B</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained at the time of enrollment.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the resistive index for twin B.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fetal renal artery Doppler PI for twin B</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained at the time of enrollment.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the pulsatility index for twin B.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-laser fetal renal artery Doppler PSV for twin A</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained within one week following fetoscopic laser therapy for cases in which this treatment is provided.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the peak systolic velocity for twin A.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-laser fetal renal artery Doppler RI for twin A</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained within one week following fetoscopic laser therapy for cases in which this treatment is provided.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the resistive index for twin A.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-laser fetal renal artery Doppler PI for twin A</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained within one week following fetoscopic laser therapy for cases in which this treatment is provided.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the pulsatility index for twin A.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-laser fetal renal artery Doppler PSV for twin B</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained within one week following fetoscopic laser therapy for cases in which this treatment is provided.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the peak systolic velocity for twin B.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-laser fetal renal artery Doppler RI for twin B</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained within one week following fetoscopic laser therapy for cases in which this treatment is provided.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the resistive index for twin B.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-laser fetal renal artery Doppler PI for twin B</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained within one week following fetoscopic laser therapy for cases in which this treatment is provided.</time_frame>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery with measurement of the pulsatility index for twin B.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Twin Twin Transfusion Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TTTS Cases</arm_group_label>
    <description>Cases of monochorionic / diamniotic twin pregnancies diagnosed with twin-twin transfusion syndrome.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MCDA Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Controls of monochorionic / diamniotic twin pregnancies without a diagnosis of twin-twin transfusion syndrome.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doppler ultrasound of fetal renal artery</intervention_name>
    <description>Doppler ultrasound assessment of the proximal fetal renal artery to with measurement of the peak systolic velocity, resistive index, pulsatility index, and systolic/diastolic ratio.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TTTS Cases</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MCDA Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The subject population will consist of pregnant women with monochorionic / diamniotic
        (MCDA) twin pregnancies with and without twin-twin transfusion syndrome (TTTS). This
        population is selected in order to investigate twin-twin transfusion syndrome, which is a
        disease process that is unique to pregnancies with monochorionic / diamniotic twins.
        Patients will be included in the study if they have a diagnosis of a MCDA twin gestation
        beyond the first trimester or pregnancy (greater than 14 weeks gestation).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant women with monochorionic / diamniotic (MCDA) twin pregnancies with and
             without twin-twin transfusion syndrome (TTTS)

          -  greater than 14 weeks gestation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  higher-order multiple gestation

          -  sonographic evidence of a major structural fetal anomaly (exceptions to this
             structural fetal anomaly exclusion are acquired recipient twin cardiac changes that
             are known to be associated with TTTS - these cases may be considered for study
             inclusion)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joses Jain, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Russell Miller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine, Simpson LL. Twin-twin transfusion syndrome. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2013 Jan;208(1):3-18. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2012.10.880. Epub 2012 Nov 27. Erratum in: Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2013 May;208(5):392.</citation>
    <PMID>23200164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewi L, Jani J, Blickstein I, Huber A, Gucciardo L, Van Mieghem T, Doné E, Boes AS, Hecher K, Gratacós E, Lewi P, Deprest J. The outcome of monochorionic diamniotic twin gestations in the era of invasive fetal therapy: a prospective cohort study. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2008 Nov;199(5):514.e1-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2008.03.050. Epub 2008 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18533114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acosta-Rojas R, Becker J, Munoz-Abellana B, Ruiz C, Carreras E, Gratacos E; Catalunya and Balears Monochorionic Network. Twin chorionicity and the risk of adverse perinatal outcome. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2007 Feb;96(2):98-102. Epub 2007 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>17250837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fusi L, Gordon H. Twin pregnancy complicated by single intrauterine death. Problems and outcome with conservative management. Br J Obstet Gynaecol. 1990 Jun;97(6):511-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2198920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Heteren CF, Nijhuis JG, Semmekrot BA, Mulders LG, van den Berg PP. Risk for surviving twin after fetal death of co-twin in twin-twin transfusion syndrome. Obstet Gynecol. 1998 Aug;92(2):215-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9699754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ong SS, Zamora J, Khan KS, Kilby MD. Prognosis for the co-twin following single-twin death: a systematic review. BJOG. 2006 Sep;113(9):992-8. Epub 2006 Aug 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16903844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quintero RA, Morales WJ, Allen MH, Bornick PW, Johnson PK, Kruger M. Staging of twin-twin transfusion syndrome. J Perinatol. 1999 Dec;19(8 Pt 1):550-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10645517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor MJ, Govender L, Jolly M, Wee L, Fisk NM. Validation of the Quintero staging system for twin-twin transfusion syndrome. Obstet Gynecol. 2002 Dec;100(6):1257-65.</citation>
    <PMID>12468171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamamoto M, El Murr L, Robyr R, Leleu F, Takahashi Y, Ville Y. Incidence and impact of perioperative complications in 175 fetoscopy-guided laser coagulations of chorionic plate anastomoses in fetofetal transfusion syndrome before 26 weeks of gestation. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2005 Sep;193(3 Pt 2):1110-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16157121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor GM, Peart WS, Porter KA, Zondek LH, Zondek T. Concentration and molecular forms of active and inactive renin in human fetal kidney, amniotic fluid and adrenal gland: evidence for renin-angiotensin system hyperactivity in 2nd trimester of pregnancy. J Hypertens. 1986 Feb;4(1):121-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3007602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galea P, Barigye O, Wee L, Jain V, Sullivan M, Fisk NM. The placenta contributes to activation of the renin angiotensin system in twin-twin transfusion syndrome. Placenta. 2008 Aug;29(8):734-42. doi: 10.1016/j.placenta.2008.04.010. Epub 2008 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>18558429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arduini D, Rizzo G. Fetal renal artery velocity waveforms and amniotic fluid volume in growth-retarded and post-term fetuses. Obstet Gynecol. 1991 Mar;77(3):370-3.</citation>
    <PMID>1992401</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stigter RH, Mulder EJ, Bruinse HW, Visser GH. Doppler studies on the fetal renal artery in the severely growth-restricted fetus. Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol. 2001 Aug;18(2):141-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11529994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oz AU, Holub B, Mendilcioglu I, Mari G, Bahado-Singh RO. Renal artery Doppler investigation of the etiology of oligohydramnios in postterm pregnancy. Obstet Gynecol. 2002 Oct;100(4):715-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12383539</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Azpurua H, Dulay AT, Buhimschi IA, Bahtiyar MO, Funai E, Abdel-Razeq SS, Luo G, Bhandari V, Copel JA, Buhimschi CS. Fetal renal artery impedance as assessed by Doppler ultrasound in pregnancies complicated by intraamniotic inflammation and preterm birth. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2009 Feb;200(2):203.e1-11. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2008.11.001.</citation>
    <PMID>19185102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benzer N, Pekin AT, Yılmaz SA, Kerimoğlu ÖS, Doğan NU, Çelik Ç. Predictive value of second and third trimester fetal renal artery Doppler indices in idiopathic oligohydramnios and polyhydramnios in low-risk pregnancies: a longitudinal study. J Obstet Gynaecol Res. 2015 Apr;41(4):523-8. doi: 10.1111/jog.12601. Epub 2014 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>25363086</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Russell Miller</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Renal Artery Doppler</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fetofetal Transfusion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to share individual participant data with other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

