<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00002884</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FRE-CURIE-HDD</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000065193</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EU-96013</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00002884</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chemotherapy and Radiation Therapy in Treating Patients With Cancer of the Esophagus</brief_title>
  <official_title>A PROSPECTIVE RANDOMISED NON SURGICAL TREATMENT OF OESOPHAGEAL CANCER WITH COMBINED CHEMOTHERAPY AND EXTERNAL BEAM IRRADIATION WITH VS WITHOUT HIGH-DOSE BRACHYTHERAPY</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Lyon Sud</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so
      they stop growing or die. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to damage tumor cells. It
      is not yet known whether external-beam radiation therapy plus chemotherapy is more effective
      with or without internal radiation therapy.

      PURPOSE: Randomized phase III trial to compare chemotherapy and external-beam radiation
      therapy with or without internal radiation therapy in treating patients with stage I, stage
      II, or stage III esophageal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Compare the complete local remission rate in patients with unresectable stage
      I, II, or III esophageal cancer treated with chemoradiotherapy with or without endoluminal
      brachytherapy. II. Compare the complete remission rate (local, locoregional, and distant) in
      these patients. III. Compare the overall and disease-free survival in these patients at 2 and
      5 years after therapy. IV. Compare the toxicity and quality of life experienced by these
      patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a randomized, multicenter study. Patients are stratified according to
      participating center, tumor stage, and chemotherapy. All patients receive fluorouracil IV
      continuously over 4 days (days 1-4) and/or cisplatin on day 2 of weeks 1 and 5. External beam
      radiotherapy begins on day 1 of chemotherapy and is delivered in daily fractions, 5 days per
      week, for 5 weeks, followed by a cone down dose administered during week 6. Patients
      randomized to brachytherapy (Iridium 192, high-dose rate) are treated on weeks 11 and 12 and
      receive 2 additional courses of chemotherapy at weeks 9 and 14. Patients randomized to no
      brachytherapy receive additional chemotherapy courses on weeks 9 and 13. Quality of life is
      assessed. Patients are followed every 6 months for 2 years and then annually for 3 years
      years.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 326 patients will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 1996</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">326</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>chemotherapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorouracil</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>brachytherapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically proven squamous cell carcinoma or adenocarcinoma of
        the esophagus No cancer of the cardia Stage T1, T2, T3, or T4 No tumor greater than 7 cm No
        tumor with diameter greater than 3 cm No involved nodes located more than 3 cm from tumor
        Supraclavicular nodal involvement eligible with cervical esophageal tumor No metastasis
        Patient ineligible for surgery because of one of the following: Condition that
        contraindicates surgery Refusal of surgery

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 to 74 Performance status: 0-2 Hematopoietic: WBC at least
        2,000/mm3 Polymorphonuclear lymphocyte count at least 1,500/mm3 Platelet count at least
        80,000/mm3 Hemoglobin at least 10 g/dL Hepatic: Not specified Renal: Creatinine less than
        2.8 mg/dL Cardiovascular: No angina pectoris No history of myocardial infarction No
        contraindication to therapy on EKG No other cardiac contraindication to chemotherapy Other:
        No peripheral neuropathy No second malignancy except basal cell skin cancer, carcinoma in
        situ of the cervix, or other carcinoma in remission for at least 2 years Not pregnant or
        nursing Fertile patients must use effective contraception

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic: Not specified Chemotherapy: Not specified Endocrine
        therapy: Not specified Radiotherapy: Not specified Surgery: See Disease Characteristics
        Other: No prior laser therapy No prior electrocoagulation No prior cryotherapy No prior
        sclerosing injection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Pierre Gerard, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Centre Hospitalier Lyon Sud</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Jules Courmont - Centre Hospitalier Lyon Sud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pierre Benite</city>
        <zip>69495</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 29, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 6, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 6, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>stage I esophageal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II esophageal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III esophageal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus</keyword>
  <keyword>adenocarcinoma of the esophagus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

