<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005919</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000155</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-EI-0155</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005919</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cause of Pigment Dispersion Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Etiology of Pigment Dispersion Syndrome (PDS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn how pigment is released from the iris (the colored part
      of the eye) in patients with pigment dispersion syndrome. It will do this by examining the
      response of the pupil (the central opening of the iris) to a flash of light to determine what
      is happening in the iris to cause release of the pigment.

      In pigment dispersion syndrome, pigment released from the iris is deposited in other parts of
      the eye, including the trabecular meshwork-a filter-like tissue in the front of the eye.
      Aqueous fluid (fluid continuously produced by the eye) normally flows out of the eye through
      the trabecular meshwork. In some patients, the pigment deposits may block tiny holes in the
      meshwork, preventing the fluid from flowing out. This can cause an increase in eye pressure
      that may lead to glaucoma and some loss of vision. Understanding how pigment is released from
      the iris may help predict the course of pigment dispersion syndrome and identify which
      patients will likely develop increased eye pressure.

      Patients with pigment dispersion syndrome and normal volunteers may be eligible for this
      study. All participants will have the following procedures, which will be completed in two
      clinic visits:

      First visit

        1. Examination of the front of the eyes, including the cornea, iris and lens.

        2. Vision testing and measurements of visual field and eye pressure.

        3. Examination of the trabecular meshwork. For this test, a contact lens is placed on the
           eye after the eye has been numbed with anesthetic drops.

      Second visit

        1. Refraction (dilation of the pupils with drops) and examination of the back of the eyes,
           including the optic nerve.

        2. Reaction of the pupils to low-level infrared light (pupillography). During this
           15-minute test, the patient or volunteer wears a lightweight headband with two small
           cameras mounted on it. The cameras-one which views the eye and the other the subject's
           field of view-record pupil dilation and position.

      The test results in patients with pigment dispersion syndrome will be compared with those in
      normal volunteers. Patients will be followed every 6 months (or more often, if medically
      indicated) during the 3-year study to determine changes in eye pressure or visual field.
      Volunteers will be asked to return about once a year for 3 years for repeat pupillography.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to conduct a comprehensive ophthalmologic evaluation and
      comparison of two types of patients and to compare them to normal controls. The two types of
      patients are those with pigment dispersion (PDS) with normal intraocular pressure (IOP) and
      those with PDS and elevated IOP. The hypothesis to be tested is that a developmental
      abnormality of the iris pigment epithelium (IPE) and the dilator muscle is the fundamental
      defect responsible for the pigment dispersion. This defect may involve other structures of
      the eye such as the ciliary and retinal pigment epithelium. The results of pupillography in
      PDS with or without elevated IOP and asymmetric PDS (one eye versus fellow eye) will be the
      outcome parameters.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 2003</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>90</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Pigment Dispersion Syndrome</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        All patients entering the study must have black pigment deposition on the trabecular
        meshwork at the site of Schlemm's canal equal to or greater than 2-plus on the
        goniophotographic scale of 1 to 5 plus.

        Although this condition is rare amongst African-Americans, every effort will be made to
        recruit such individuals.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients with exfoliation syndrome, uveitis, trauma, pigment dispersion with posterior
        chamber intra-ocular lens, pigmented tumors, primary open-angle glaucoma, other conditions
        with associated pigment dispersion such as acute angle-closure glaucoma, ocular hemorrhage,
        Horner's syndrome.

        In addition, normal volunteers will be recruited as controls. They will be free of any eye
        disease and be matched for age, sex and degree of myopia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Eye Institute (NEI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferris FL 3rd, Sperduto RD. Standardized illumination for visual acuity testing in clinical research. Am J Ophthalmol. 1982 Jul;94(1):97-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7091290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferris FL 3rd, Kassoff A, Bresnick GH, Bailey I. New visual acuity charts for clinical research. Am J Ophthalmol. 1982 Jul;94(1):91-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7091289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 17, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 19, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Pigment Dispersion</keyword>
  <keyword>Ocular Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Glaucoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Pupil Reaction</keyword>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <keyword>Pigment Dispersion Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Mutation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Open-Angle</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

