<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001351</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>930086</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>93-I-0086</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001351</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation and Long-Term Follow-up of Patients With Inflammatory Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation and Long Term Follow Up of Patients With Acute or Chronic Inflammatory Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate inflammatory diseases and disorders. Inflammation is the body s
      immune response to many things, including infections and other acute or chronic irritants. It
      may also be a sign of abnormal immune function. This study will allow evaluation and
      long-term follow-up of such disorders to:

        -  Establish and maintain a group of patients that may be eligible for other NIAID
           protocols.

        -  Provide clinical training and experience for NIAID fellows.

        -  Provide a mechanism for NIAID staff to maintain their clinical skills.

        -  Serve as a starting point for new investigations of syndromes not currently under study.

      Patients between 1 and 80 years of age with acute or chronic inflammation, including but not
      limited to viral, fungal or bacterial infections, or abnormal immune responses may be
      eligible for this study. Immediate family members of patients may also be enrolled for
      preliminary examination to see if they are affected in any way that may warrant further
      investigation.

      All patients and family members will have a history, physical examination and laboratory
      tests. Depending on the results, family members may require additional tests. Patients will
      have additional diagnostic tests indicated for their specific disease, according to accepted
      medical standards. These may include routine blood and urine tests, X-rays or other imaging
      studies, body fluid or tissue cultures, skin tests for allergic or immune responses, and
      others as needed.

      Treatments will include only medications approved by the Food and Drug Administration
      according to accepted dose schedules and delivery methods.

      Patients may be requested to donate extra blood for research studies. No more than 450 cc (30
      tablespoons) will be drawn from adults within a 6-week period, and no more that 7 cc (1/2
      tablespoon) from children under 18 years of age in the same time period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Inflammatory disorders, including but not limited to those caused by viral, bacterial,
      fungal, and parasitic infections, and those associated with aberrant immunologic responses
      are exceedingly common acute and chronic disorders affecting humans. The pathogenesis of
      these various disorders are being investigated under a number of NIAID clinical research
      protocols. This protocol is an evaluation and long-term follow protocol of such disorders for
      the purposes of maintaining a group of patients on which LCID investigators draw for our
      other various protocols. The patients admitted under this protocol also provide training and
      experience for members of the NIAID infectious diseases and allergy and immunology fellowship
      training programs as well as to provide a mechanism for the members of the Laboratory of
      Clinical Infectious Diseases to maintain their clinical skills. It is anticipated that the
      patients will receive a degree of clinical evaluation, care and monitoring more extensive
      than that generally available and that specimens collected from them can sometimes be used
      for laboratory studies related to inflammatory conditions. Also, this protocol may serve as a
      start point to studies of syndromes or diseases not being addressed by specific protocols,
      and therefore, can be used to evaluate family members of patients with inflammatory
      conditions when appropriate in order to try to understand further the disease before
      embarking in a specific protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 5, 1993</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of patients</measure>
    <time_frame>at all visits</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">292</enrollment>
  <condition>Immunologic Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Host Response</condition>
  <condition>Infectious Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITIERIA:

        Males and females ages 1 year to 80 years are eligible.

        Inflammatory conditions associated with, but not limited, to acute and chronic infections
        or presumed infections, and congenital or acquired immunologic disorders.

        If appropriate, immediate family members of patients with inflammatory conditions may be
        evaluated under this protocol, as a preamble to see if further investigation is warranted,
        what would be done under a specific protocol.

        Willingness to participate in clinical protocols when appropriate.

        Subjects must maintain a private physician for non-protocol related medical complaints and
        for emergency medical treatment required for these or other of their disorders.

        Willingness to provide tissue samples for studying immune dyregulation and for genetic
        analysis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adriana R Marques, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_1993-I-0086.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen JI, Jaffe ES, Dale JK, Pittaluga S, Heslop HE, Rooney CM, Gottschalk S, Bollard CM, Rao VK, Marques A, Burbelo PD, Turk SP, Fulton R, Wayne AS, Little RF, Cairo MS, El-Mallawany NK, Fowler D, Sportes C, Bishop MR, Wilson W, Straus SE. Characterization and treatment of chronic active Epstein-Barr virus disease: a 28-year experience in the United States. Blood. 2011 Jun 2;117(22):5835-49. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-11-316745. Epub 2011 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>21454450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price S, Shaw PA, Seitz A, Joshi G, Davis J, Niemela JE, Perkins K, Hornung RL, Folio L, Rosenberg PS, Puck JM, Hsu AP, Lo B, Pittaluga S, Jaffe ES, Fleisher TA, Rao VK, Lenardo MJ. Natural history of autoimmune lymphoproliferative syndrome associated with FAS gene mutations. Blood. 2014 Mar 27;123(13):1989-99. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-10-535393. Epub 2014 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>24398331</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hemmer B, Gran B, Zhao Y, Marques A, Pascal J, Tzou A, Kondo T, Cortese I, Bielekova B, Straus SE, McFarland HF, Houghten R, Simon R, Pinilla C, Martin R. Identification of candidate T-cell epitopes and molecular mimics in chronic Lyme disease. Nat Med. 1999 Dec;5(12):1375-82.</citation>
    <PMID>10581079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 1, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Infectious Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Host Response</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunologic Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Infection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immune System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

