<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00003176</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000065986</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NABTC-9701</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-T96-0082</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00003176</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Temozolomide and Carmustine in Treating Patients With Anaplastic Glioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Temozolomide and BCNU for Anaplastic Gliomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>North American Brain Tumor Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so
      they stop growing or die. Combining more than one drug may kill more tumor cells.

      PURPOSE: Phase II trial to study the effectiveness of temozolomide and carmustine in treating
      patients with anaplastic glioma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Evaluate the activity, measured in terms of progression free survival, of
      carmustine plus temozolomide in recurrent glioblastoma. II. Estimate the response rate of
      recurrent glioblastomas to this combination. III. Estimate the response rate of newly
      diagnosed anaplastic astrocytomas and mixed anaplastic glioma to this combination. IV.
      Evaluate the qualitative and quantitative toxicities of this combination in patients with
      anaplastic gliomas.

      OUTLINE: This is a nonrandomized study. Patients are stratified by disease (recurrent
      glioblastoma vs anaplastic astrocytoma or mixed anaplastic glioma). Patients receive
      carmustine intravenously on day 1 two hours prior to temozolomide. Temozolomide is
      administered orally on day 1. Cycles repeat every 42 days. Treatment for patients with
      recurrent glioblastoma may continue for 8 cycles in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity. If there is no disease progression after 8 cycles, treatment may
      continue further at the investigator's discretion. Patients with anaplastic astrocytoma or
      mixed anaplastic glioma continue for 4 cycles of treatment. Patients are followed
      periodically at the investigator's discretion, at least twice in the first 4 months, and then
      until death.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A minimum of 17 patients and a maximum of 37 patients will be accrued in
      the recurrent glioblastoma stratum and 45 patients will be accrued into the anaplastic
      astrocytoma and mixed anaplastic glioma stratum.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 1998</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">82</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carmustine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>temozolomide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed malignant glioma - Recurrent glioblastoma
        - Anaplastic astrocytoma - Mixed anaplastic glioma For recurrent glioblastoma: Required
        documented progression must include an increase in tumor size of at least 25% or appearance
        of new lesion For anaplastic astrocytoma or mixed anaplastic glioma: Must have measurable,
        contrast enhancing disease on postoperative CT or MRI scan No postoperative radiation or
        chemotherapy If patients have received prior brachytherapy or stereotactic radiosurgery,
        they must have confirmation of true progressive disease rather than radiation necrosis by
        PET scanning or biopsy

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: Karnofsky 60-100% Life
        expectancy: Not specified Hematopoietic: WBC at least 3,500/mm3 Absolute neutrophil count
        at least 1,800/mm3 Platelet count at least 125,000/mm3 Hemoglobin at least 9 g/dL
        (transfusion allowed) Hepatic: Bilirubin less than 1.5 mg/dL SGOT less than 2.0 times upper
        limit of normal Renal: Creatinine less than 1.5 mg/dL OR Creatinine clearance greater than
        70 mL/min Cardiovascular: No uncontrolled arrhythmias or conduction defects No unstable or
        newly diagnosed angina pectoris No New York Heart Association class II-IV heart disease No
        congestive heart failure No major problems with edema (e.g., severe Cushing's syndrome,
        residual leg swelling from deep-vein thrombosis) No recent coronary artery disease No
        poorly controlled hypertension (diastolic greater than 110 mmHg and systolic greater than
        180 mmHg) Pulmonary: DLCO greater than 80% of expected value Other: HIV negative No major
        psychiatric illness No other prior malignancy except adequately treated basal cell or
        squamous cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, adequately treated stage I or II cancer
        from which the patient is currently in complete remission, or any other cancer from which
        the patient has been free of disease for 5 years Not pregnant or nursing Adequate
        contraception required of all fertile patients

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: No concurrent biologic therapy Chemotherapy: No
        prior nitrosourea or temozolomide No more than 1 prior chemotherapy regimen allowed for
        patients with glioblastoma At least 6 weeks since mitomycin or procarbazine and recovered
        At least 4 weeks since other prior chemotherapy and recovered No other concurrent
        chemotherapy Endocrine therapy: If receiving steroids, must be on a stable steroid dose for
        at least 72 hours prior to study No other concurrent endocrine therapy Radiotherapy: At
        least 6 weeks since radiotherapy No greater than 10-20% of marrow irradiated in prior
        radiotherapy No other concurrent radiotherapy Surgery: Surgery allowed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Prados, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>UCSF Medical Center at Parnassus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center, UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095-1781</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Cancer Center and Cancer Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115-0128</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109-0752</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Simmons Cancer Center - Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75235-9154</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas - MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030-4009</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78284-7811</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chang SM, Prados MD, Yung WK, Fine H, Junck L, Greenberg H, Robins HI, Mehta M, Fink KL, Jaeckle KA, Kuhn J, Hess K, Schold C. Phase II study of neoadjuvant 1, 3-bis (2-chloroethyl)-1-nitrosourea and temozolomide for newly diagnosed anaplastic glioma: a North American Brain Tumor Consortium Trial. Cancer. 2004 Apr 15;100(8):1712-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15073861</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Prados MD, Yung WK, Fine HA, Greenberg HS, Junck L, Chang SM, Nicholas MK, Robins HI, Mehta MP, Fink KL, Jaeckle KA, Kuhn J, Hess KR, Schold SC Jr; North American Brain Tumor Consortium study. Phase 2 study of BCNU and temozolomide for recurrent glioblastoma multiforme: North American Brain Tumor Consortium study. Neuro Oncol. 2004 Jan;6(1):33-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14769138</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 6, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 13, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 13, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>recurrent adult brain tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>adult glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult anaplastic astrocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult mixed glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult giant cell glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carmustine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

