<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00002476</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRC-PHASE-III-91001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000076951</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UKHAN-1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00002476</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radiation Therapy With or Without Chemotherapy in Treating Patients With Advanced Head and Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase III Randomized Study of Radiotherapy Alone vs With Concurrent Chemotherapy With MTX or VBMF (VCR/BLEO/MTX/5-FU) vs Subsequent Chemotherapy vs Concurrent and Subsequent Chemotherapy in Patients With Advanced Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cancer Research UK</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to damage tumor cells. Drugs used in
      chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so they stop growing or
      die. It is not yet known if radiation therapy plus chemotherapy is more effective than
      radiation therapy alone in treating patients with advanced head and neck cancer.

      PURPOSE: Randomized phase III trial to compare the effectiveness of radiation therapy with or
      without chemotherapy in treating patients with advanced head and neck cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine whether the addition of methotrexate (MTX) or VBMF
      (vincristine/bleomycin/methotrexate/fluorouracil) to radiotherapy for advanced carcinoma of
      the head and neck (with or without primary surgery) influences locoregional control and
      prolongs survival. II. Determine whether an effect on locoregional control or survival is
      apparent when chemotherapy is given during or following radiotherapy and whether it is
      increased when chemotherapy is given at both times. III. Determine, in a special
      randomization of patients with cancer of the oral cavity or oropharynx, whether neck
      irradiation improves locoregional control and survival.

      OUTLINE: Randomized study. Patients without prior surgery are randomized 1:2 to Arms I:II-IV,
      while those with prior surgery are randomized 1:1 between Arms I and II only. Patients with
      tumors of the oral cavity or oropharynx may elect additional randomization between Arms V and
      VI and will receive irradiation of the primary according to the Manchester regimen. Arm I:
      Radiotherapy. Irradiation of the primary and/or lymph nodes according to 1 of 2 regimens
      (Manchester 3-week schedule or SECOG 6-week schedule) using megavoltage equipment. Arm II:
      Radiotherapy plus Concurrent Single-agent or 4-Drug Combination Chemotherapy with Leucovorin
      Rescue. Involved-field irradiation as in Arm I; plus Methotrexate, MTX, NSC-740; with
      Leucovorin calcium, CF, NSC-3590; or VBMF: Vincristine, VCR, NSC-67574; Bleomycin, BLEO,
      NSC-125066; MTX; Fluorouracil, 5-FU, NSC-19893; with CF. Arm III: Radiotherapy plus
      Subsequent Single-agent or 4-Drug Combination Chemotherapy with Leucovorin Rescue.
      Involved-field irradiation as in Arm I; plus MTX or VBMF; with CF. Arm IV: Radiotherapy plus
      Concurrent and Subsequent Single-agent or 4-Drug Combination Chemotherapy with Leucovorin
      Rescue. Involved-field irradiation as in Arm I; plus MTX or VBMF; with CF. Arm V:
      Radiotherapy. Neck node irradiation using megavoltage equipment. Arm VI: Observation. No
      nodal irradiation.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: At least 1,000 patients will be entered.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1990</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2010</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bleomycin sulfate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorouracil</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leucovorin calcium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>methotrexate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vincristine sulfate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>low-LET cobalt-60 gamma ray therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>low-LET photon therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>radiation therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed squamous cell cancer of the head and neck
        suitable for treatment with radiotherapy T2, T3, or T4 primary lesions Any N No distant
        metastasis May also be anaplastic carcinoma, verrucous carcinoma, or transitional cell
        carcinoma (as of 1/97) No occult primaries (as of 1/97) No adenocarcinomas, lymphomas, or
        melanomas (as of 1/97) Synchronous head and neck tumors are eligible (tumor with the worse
        prognosis is entered into study) (as of 1/97) Patients receiving surgery to neck nodes only
        must be randomized as surgery patients (as of 1/97) Patients with tumors of the oral cavity
        or oropharynx may additionally elect randomization to nodal irradiation vs. no further
        therapy provided there is no second primary

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 75 and under for patients electing participation in the nodal
        vs. no nodal irradiation portion of the study Performance status: Not specified
        Hematopoietic: Not specified Hepatic: Not specified Renal: Not specified Other: Fit for any
        protocol treatment option Willing to receive any protocol treatment option Prior malignancy
        allowed provided the treating clinician considers the patient cured

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: No prior therapy Chemotherapy: No prior therapy
        Endocrine therapy: No prior therapy Radiotherapy: No prior therapy Surgery: Prior biopsy or
        excision allowed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey S. Tobias, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University College London Hospitals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Raj Tilak</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indore</city>
        <zip>452001</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Sussex County Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brighton</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>BN2 5BE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Middlesex Hospital- Meyerstein Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>W1N 8AA</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Derriford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plymouth</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>PL6 8DH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southend General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westcliff-On-Sea</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Victoria Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belfast</city>
        <state>Northern Ireland</state>
        <zip>BT12 6BJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Belfast City Hospital Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belfast</city>
        <state>Northern Ireland</state>
        <zip>BT8 8JR</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tobias JS, Monson K, Gupta N, Macdougall H, Glaholm J, Hutchison I, Kadalayil L, Hackshaw A; UK Head and Neck Cancer Trialists' Group. Chemoradiotherapy for locally advanced head and neck cancer: 10-year follow-up of the UK Head and Neck (UKHAN1) trial. Lancet Oncol. 2010 Jan;11(1):66-74. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(09)70306-7. Epub 2009 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>19875337</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 8, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>stage II squamous cell carcinoma of the lip and oral cavity</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II verrucous carcinoma of the oral cavity</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III squamous cell carcinoma of the lip and oral cavity</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III verrucous carcinoma of the oral cavity</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV squamous cell carcinoma of the lip and oral cavity</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV verrucous carcinoma of the oral cavity</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II squamous cell carcinoma of the oropharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III squamous cell carcinoma of the oropharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV squamous cell carcinoma of the oropharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II squamous cell carcinoma of the nasopharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III squamous cell carcinoma of the nasopharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV squamous cell carcinoma of the nasopharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II squamous cell carcinoma of the hypopharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III squamous cell carcinoma of the hypopharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV squamous cell carcinoma of the hypopharynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II squamous cell carcinoma of the larynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II verrucous carcinoma of the larynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III squamous cell carcinoma of the larynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III verrucous carcinoma of the larynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV squamous cell carcinoma of the larynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV verrucous carcinoma of the larynx</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II squamous cell carcinoma of the paranasal sinus and nasal cavity</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III squamous cell carcinoma of the paranasal sinus and nasal cavity</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV squamous cell carcinoma of the paranasal sinus and nasal cavity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vincristine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bleomycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

