<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>980055</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98-AR-0055</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cyclophosphamide and Fludarabine to Treat Lupus Nephritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combination of Cyclophosphamide and Fludarabine for Lupus Nephritis: Tolerance, Toxicity, Efficacy and Effects on B and T Lymphocyte Regeneration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the safety and effectiveness of combination therapy with
      cyclophosphamide (Cytoxan) and fludarabine in treating lupus nephritis (kidney inflammation).
      This condition, common in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus, is caused by abnormal
      action of immune cells called lymphocytes against the kidneys. Left untreated, severe cases
      can result in loss of kidney function. The current treatment of choice-intermittent high
      doses (pulses) of cyclophosphamide-does not work in all patients and causes infertility in
      many women. The rate of infertility in men is not known. This study will examine whether
      fludarabine can safely be given with significantly lower doses of cyclophosphamide, and if
      this combination controls kidney inflammation.

      Patients 18 years of age and older with severe lupus nephritis (called proliferative lupus
      nephritis) may be eligible for this study. Candidates will have a history and physical
      examination; blood and urine tests; chest X-ray; electrocardiogram; cancer screening that may
      include a Pap smear, mammogram, rectal examination, PSA testing, and sigmoidoscopy.

      Participants will be divided into one of the following treatment groups:

      Group 1-Patients undergo three treatment cycles of cyclophosphamide, taken by mouth, and
      fludarabine, injected subcutaneously (under the skin). Patients receive both drugs on day 1
      of the cycle, and fludarabine alone on days 2 and 3. This regimen is repeated once every 5
      weeks for three cycles.

      Group 2-Same as for Group 1, except fludarabine injections are given intravenously (through a
      vein) for the second treatment cycle. Patients in this group have frequent blood sampling
      during the first and second treatment cycles to monitor blood levels of the drug. Samples are
      collected before the first injection is given and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 24 and 48 hours
      after the third injection. A total 12 tablespoons of blood is drawn over a 2-month period.

      All patients will have blood drawn once or twice a week during the first two cycles and then
      less frequently to monitor blood counts. Some patients will have the following additional
      procedures to test the effects of treatment on lymphocytes:

        1. Blood sample collection

        2. Bone marrow aspiration-The skin over the hip bone is cleaned and a local anesthetic is
           injected into the outer covering of the bone. Bone marrow is suctioned through the
           needle into an attached syringe. The procedure is done before treatment begins, at the
           end of treatment, and 6 months after treatment.

        3. Tonsillar biopsy-The tonsils are numbed with a local anesthetic and 1 to 4 pieces of
           tissue are removed using special forceps. The procedure is done before treatment begins,
           at the end of treatment, and 6 months after treatment.

        4. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the abdomen-The patients lies on a table in a narrow
           cylinder (the MRI scanner) containing a strong magnetic field, which is used to create
           images of parts of the body in small section views.

      Patients will be followed for at least 24 months to monitor late side effects and the
      response to treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Studies at the NIH Clinical Center have shown that intermittent pulse cyclophosphamide
      therapy is effective for treating patients with severe lupus nephritis, but may result in
      substantial rates of sustained amenorrhea. Initial studies in patients with autoimmune
      rheumatic diseases have also suggested a beneficial effect from the lymphocyte-specific
      nucleoside analogs chlorodeoxyadenosine and fludarabine. Cyclophosphamide induces DNA
      cross-links whereas, nucleoside analogs inhibits DNA repair indicating complementary and
      partially synergistic modes of action. Whether combination of lower doses of cyclophosphamide
      with nucleoside analogs will increase efficacy while at the same time minimize toxicity from
      higher-cumulative doses of cyclophosphamide has not been determined. In this phase I/II
      study, 15 patients with proliferative lupus nephritis will be treated as outpatients with a
      combination of oral cyclophosphamide (500 mg/m(2)) on day 1 followed by fludarabine (30
      mg/m(2)) subcutaneously on days 1, 2 and 3 every month for 3 cycles. The cumulative dose of
      cyclophosphamide in this regimen is approximately 2.5g as compared to greater than or equal
      to 30g in the standard NIH cyclophosphamide regimen. In this study the tolerance and toxicity
      of this combination will be studied. Regeneration of T and B cells following depletion
      including analysis of antigen-repertoire and function will also be examined. Preliminary
      efficacy information, including rates and time to renal remission and rates of preservation
      of renal function, will be analyzed to be used for future controlled studies. Pharmacokinetic
      analysis will be performed on a subset of patients to determine the bioavailability and
      pharmacokinetic parameters of subcutaneous fludarabine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date>November 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>15</enrollment>
  <condition>Glomerulonephritis</condition>
  <condition>Lupus Nephritis</condition>
  <condition>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SQ Fludarabine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients must be 18 years of age or older and able to provide informed consent.

        Patients must have at least 4 criteria for SLE as defined by the American Rheumatism
        Association (ARA).

        Active glomerulonephritis with:

        Renal biopsy within 1 year with class III or class IV active lupus nephritis, AND;

        Abnormal urine analysis:

        Greater than 10 RBC/hpf and cellular (RBC, WBC or mixed) casts, OR;

        Greater than 10 RBC/hpf and proteinuria greater than 2 g/day, OR;

        Proteinuria greater than 3.5 g/day.

        No patients with severe proliferative lupus nephritis: a. very active renal histology with
        crescents or necrosis in more than 25% of glomeruli; or b. rapidly progressive
        glomerulonephritis (doubling of serum creatinine in less than or equal to 3 months); or c.
        severe impairment of renal function Cr greater than 2.5 mg/dL or GFR less than 50 mL/min
        measured by inulin clearance.

        Patient has not had previous immunosuppressive therapy:

        Patients must not be receiving azathioprine, cyclosporine, methotrexate. Patients receiving
        these drugs will be eligible only if these drugs are discontinued and after a waiting
        period of greater than or equal to 4 weeks;

        Patients must not be receiving cyclophosphamide:

        Greater than 3 pulses (maximum 1 g/m(2)/pulse) within the last 12 months or since last
        renal biopsy showing active disease; OR

        greater than 6 pulses ever.

        Patients must not have had pulse therapy with glucocorticoids or any experimental therapy
        during the 4 weeks before study entry.

        Patients who need at study entry oral corticosteroids in dosages greater than 0.5 mg/kg/day
        of predisone to control extrarenal disease are not eligible.

        Patients with active or chronic infection are not eligible.

        Patients who are pregnant, breast-feeding or using inadequate birth control are not
        eligible.

        Patients who have poorly controlled diabetes mellitus or with evidence of end-organ damage
        are not eligible.

        No history of cerebrovascular accident, seizures within the last 5 years or chronic
        neurologic disease.

        No history of malignancy other than squamous cell and/or basal carcinoma of the skin.

        No confounding medical illness that in the judgment of investigators would pose added risk
        for study participants such as:

        Unstable coronary artery disease, cardiomyopathy or dysrhythmia requiring therapy;

        Pulmonary disease (PFTs less 70% of predicted value or DLCO less than 60%), or;

        Hematologic disease (Hb less than 8 mg/dL, platelets less than 100,000 micro liters or WBC
        less than 2,500/micro liters.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gourley MF, Austin HA 3rd, Scott D, Yarboro CH, Vaughan EM, Muir J, Boumpas DT, Klippel JH, Balow JE, Steinberg AD. Methylprednisolone and cyclophosphamide, alone or in combination, in patients with lupus nephritis. A randomized, controlled trial. Ann Intern Med. 1996 Oct 1;125(7):549-57.</citation>
    <PMID>8815753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boumpas DT, Austin HA 3rd, Vaughan EM, Yarboro CH, Klippel JH, Balow JE. Risk for sustained amenorrhea in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus receiving intermittent pulse cyclophosphamide therapy. Ann Intern Med. 1993 Sep 1;119(5):366-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8338289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boumpas DT, Austin HA 3rd, Vaughn EM, Klippel JH, Steinberg AD, Yarboro CH, Balow JE. Controlled trial of pulse methylprednisolone versus two regimens of pulse cyclophosphamide in severe lupus nephritis. Lancet. 1992 Sep 26;340(8822):741-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1356175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2002</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Remission</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal Function</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Germinal Center</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunoglobulin</keyword>
  <keyword>Glomerulonephritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</keyword>
  <keyword>Lupus Nephritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lupus Erythematosus, Systemic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lupus Nephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

