<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001960</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000007</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-H-0007</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001960</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Studying the Effectiveness of Pacemaker Therapy in Children Who Have Thickened Heart Muscle</brief_title>
  <official_title>Controlled Cross-Over Study of DDD Pacemaker Therapy in Symptomatic Children With Obstructive Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A heart condition called hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (HCM) causes abnormal thickening of the
      heart muscle, which obstructs the flow of blood out of the heart. The thickened muscle and
      the obstruction of blood flow are believed to cause chest discomfort, breathlessness,
      fainting, and a sensation of heart pounding. Treatment options for children with HCM include
      medicine, heart operation, and cardiac transplantation. However, there is no evidence that
      medicine prevents further thickening of heart muscle; operations carry the risk of death; and
      donor hearts are not always available. Several studies have shown that pacemaker treatment
      reduces the obstruction and improves heart complaints in patients with HCM. This study
      investigates further the efficacy of pacemaker treatment in children.

      Patients will have exercise tests after treatment with beta blocker and verapamil and will be
      eligible for the study if heart complaints or reduced exercise performance continue.

      A pacemaker that treats slow heart rhythms will be inserted. The patient will be sedated and
      local anesthesia will be administered to numb the area. The procedure takes about an hour.

      The study will last two years. Patients will be placed on one of two pacemaker programs for
      the first year and another the second year. At 3- and 6-month follow-up visits, a pacemaker
      check and echocardiogram will be performed. After 1 year, patients will be admitted to NIH
      for 2 to 3 days for exercise tests, echocardiogram, and cardiac catheterization. Also, the
      pacemaker will be changed to the second program. At 15- and 18-month follow-up visits, a
      pacemaker check and echocardiogram will be performed. After 2 years, patients will again be
      admitted for 2 to 3 days for exercise tests, echocardiogram, and cardiac catheterization. A
      pregnancy test will be given to females of child-bearing age before each cardiac
      catheterization and electrophysiology study.

      At the end of the study, the pacemaker will be set to the program that worked better.

      Risks of pacemaker insertion include lung collapse, infection, blood vessel damage, bleeding,
      heart attack, and death. Risks of cardiac catheterization include infection, bleeding, blood
      clots, abnormal heart rhythms, perforation of the heart, need for surgery, and death.
      However, the safety record for both these procedures at NIH has been excellent. The radiation
      exposure exceeds the NIH radiation guidelines for children, but this exposure in adults has
      not been associated with any definite adverse effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Studies suggest that DDD pacemaker therapy is effective in improving symptoms and reducing
      intra-ventricular pressures and pressure gradients in children with obstructive HCM during a
      period of rapid body growth when the severity of the disease is expected to worsen. We
      propose a randomized, cross-over study of DDD pacing versus placebo (AAI pacing mode) in
      children who have limited exercise performance and/or symptoms despite medical therapy
      (beta-blocker or verapamil). Study subjects will receive a pacemaker and will be randomized
      to one of two pacing modes (DDD, AAI). After a 1-year follow-up evaluation the children will
      cross-over to the alternative pacing mode, and will be re-evaluated after a further year. All
      children will continue to receive optimum medical therapy (beta-blocker or verapamil) based
      on improvement in symptoms and exercise performance. The subjects will undergo outpatient
      evaluations (exercise tests and echocardiography) 3, 6, 15, and 18 months after pacemaker
      implantation, and inpatient evaluations (exercise tests, echocardiography, and cardiac
      catheterization) 1 year and 2 years after entry into the study. Primary end-points will be
      exercise duration and severity of LV outflow obstruction. The patient, parents, referring
      physician, and individual supervising the exercise tests will be blinded to the pacing mode.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>50</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertrophic Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pacemaker therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Children of either gender, aged 4 to 18 years.

        Obstructive HCM defined as LV hypertrophy, and an LV intra-cavitary pressure gradient
        measured at cardiac catheterization of greater than or equal to 30 mm Hg at rest or greater
        than or equal to 50 mm Hg following isoproterenol infusion to a heart rate of greater than
        or equal to 100 beats per minute.

        Cardiac symptoms (chest discomfort, dyspnea, lightheadedness or presyncope, syncope,
        cardio-respiratory arrest, palpitations, excessive fatigue); and/or exercise duration which
        is less than 10th percentile predicted for age/gender despite a trial of a beta-blocker
        therapy and a trial of verapamil therapy.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Other systemic diseases that prevent assessment by exercise tests and cardiac
        catheterization.

        Chronic atrial fibrillation.

        Positive pregnancy test: A negative urine pregnancy test will be required before each
        cardiac catheterization, electrophysiologic study and thallium study. Pregnant or lactating
        subjects may not participate in the study due to potential teratogenic effects of
        radiation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fananapazir L, Chang AC, Epstein SE, McAreavey D. Prognostic determinants in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Prospective evaluation of a therapeutic strategy based on clinical, Holter, hemodynamic, and electrophysiological findings. Circulation. 1992 Sep;86(3):730-40.</citation>
    <PMID>1516184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wigle ED, Rakowski H, Kimball BP, Williams WG. Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Clinical spectrum and treatment. Circulation. 1995 Oct 1;92(7):1680-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7671349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fananapazir L. Advances in molecular genetics and management of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. JAMA. 1999 May 12;281(18):1746-52. Erratum in: JAMA 1999 Dec 22-29;282(24):2303.</citation>
    <PMID>10328076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2002</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>HCM</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>Pacemaker</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Symptoms</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Hypertrophic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

