<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005636</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>99-085</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000067791</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CWRU-LILY-1599</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>LILLY-H3E-MC-JMCH(a)</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-G00-1767</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005636</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cisplatin With or Without Pemetrexed Disodium in Treating Patients With Malignant Mesothelioma of the Pleura That Cannot be Removed by Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Blind Randomized Phase III Trial of MTA Plus Cisplatin Versus Cisplatin in Patients With Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so
      they stop growing or die. It is not yet known if cisplatin is more effective with or without
      pemetrexed disodium for malignant mesothelioma of the pleura.

      PURPOSE: Randomized phase III trial to compare the effectiveness of cisplatin with or without
      pemetrexed disodium in treating patients who have malignant mesothelioma of the pleura that
      cannot be removed by surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Compare survival in patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma when treated
      with cisplatin with or without LY231514. II. Compare duration of response, time to
      progression, and time to treatment failure in these patients with these treatment regimens.
      III. Compare tumor response rate and clinical benefit of these treatment regimens in these
      patients. IV. Compare Lung Cancer Symptom Scale scores, pulmonary function test scores, and
      lung density determinations with these treatment regimens in these patients. V. Compare
      toxicity of these treatment regimens in these patients. VI. Assess pharmacokinetics and
      vitamin metabolite status with these treatment regimens in these patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a randomized, single blind, multicenter study. Patients are stratified
      according to performance status (Karnofsky 70-80% vs 90-100%), degree of measurability
      (bidimensional vs unidimensional only), histologic subtype (epithelial vs all others), WBC
      (8,300/mm3 and higher vs less than 8,300/mm3), pain intensity (low vs high), analgesic
      consumption (low vs high), dyspnea (low vs high), homocysteine (low vs high), gender,
      country, and treatment center. Patients are randomized to one of two treatment arms. Arm I:
      Patients receive LY231514 IV over 10 minutes followed by cisplatin IV over 2 hours on day 1.
      Arm II: Patients receive cisplatin as in arm I. Treatment repeats every 21 days for at least
      6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients are
      followed at 4 weeks, and then every 3 months thereafter.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 280 patients (140 per treatment arm) will be accrued for this
      study within 15 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2000</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2000</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Malignant Mesothelioma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pemetrexed disodium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed malignant mesothelioma of the pleura not
        amenable to curative surgery Must be radiologically accessible Unidimensionally or
        bidimensionally measurable disease Pleural effusions or positive bone scan not considered
        measurable No brain metastases

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: Karnofsky 70-100% Life
        expectancy: At least 12 weeks Hematopoietic: Absolute neutrophil count at least 1,500/mm3
        Platelet count at least 100,000/mm3 Hemoglobin at least 9 g/dL Hepatic: Bilirubin no
        greater than 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN) Alkaline phosphatase, AST, and ALT no
        greater than 3.0 times ULN (no greater than 5 times ULN with liver involvement) Albumin at
        least 3.0 g/dL Renal: Creatinine clearance at least 45 mL/min Other: No serious systemic
        disorders that may preclude study No prior primary malignancy within the past 5 years
        except carcinoma in situ of the cervix or adequately treated basal cell carcinoma of the
        skin No obvious malnourishment or greater than 10% weight loss within 6 weeks prior to
        study No active infection Not pregnant or nursing Fertile patients must use effective
        contraception during and for 3 months after study

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: Prior immunomodulators allowed for pleurodesis
        No concurrent immunotherapy Chemotherapy: No prior systemic chemotherapy At least 1 week
        since prior bleomycin for pleurodesis Prior intracavitary cytotoxic drugs allowed for
        pleurodesis No other concurrent chemotherapy Endocrine therapy: No concurrent hormonal
        anticancer therapy Radiotherapy: At least 4 weeks since prior radiotherapy to target lesion
        Lesion must be clearly progressive No concurrent radiotherapy Surgery: See Disease
        Characteristics No concurrent surgery for cancer Other: At least 4 weeks since any other
        prior investigational agent No concurrent aspirin or other nonsteroidal antiinflammatory
        drug from 2 days prior to 2 days after study (5 days prior for long acting agents such as
        piroxicam, naproxen, diflunisal, or nabumetone) No other concurrent experimental
        medications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David H. Ilson, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Institute of New Jersey</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Brunswick</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08901</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ireland Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106-5065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 17, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 17, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>localized malignant mesothelioma</keyword>
  <keyword>advanced malignant mesothelioma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent malignant mesothelioma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mesothelioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

