<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001728</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>980146</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98-D-0146</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001728</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Alendronate to Treat Polyostotic Fibrous Dysplasia and McCune-Albright Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial of Alendronate in the Treatment of Polyostotic Fibrous Dysplasia and the McCune-Albright Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the effectiveness of alendronate in treating the bone abnormality in
      polyostotic fibrous dysplasia and McCune-Albright syndrome. In these diseases, areas of
      normal bone are replaced with a fibrous growth similar to a scar. The weakened bone causes
      pain and increases patients' risk of bone fractures and bone deformities. Alendronate belongs
      to a class of drugs called &quot;bisphosphonates,&quot; which are approved by the Food and Drug
      Administration to treat bone weakening, deformity and pain in other medical conditions. It is
      thought that bisphosphonates might work by slowing the activity of osteoclasts-cells that
      break down bone.

      Patients 12 years of age and older with polyostotic fibrous dysplasia or McCune-Albright
      syndrome may be eligible for this 3-year study. Candidates must also be enrolled in NIDCR's
      protocol 98-D-0145 (Screening and Natural History of Patients with Polyostotic Fibrous
      Dysplasia and McCune-Albright Syndrome).

      Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two treatment groups: they will take one
      capsule a day of either alendronate or placebo (a look-alike capsule that has no active
      ingredient). They will take the capsules for 6 months, stop for 6 months, then take them for
      another 6 months and then go off them for 6 months. They will then remain off the drug or
      placebo for an additional 12 months and complete the study with a final follow-up visit at 36
      months. While taking alendronate or placebo, patients will also take calcium and vitamin D to
      prevent secondary hyperparathyroidism-a side effect of alendronate in which the bone does not
      release enough calcium.

      Patients will come to NIH for a physical examination and blood and urine tests every 6 months
      and for monitoring of their bone disease, vision, hearing, pain levels, functional
      evaluation, and photographs every 12 months. Many of the monitoring procedures, including
      imaging studies and biopsies, are performed for the screening protocol (98-D-0145) and will
      not be duplicated for this study. During the study periods when patients are taking
      alendronate or placebo, they will have blood samples drawn by their local physician once
      every 3 months and sent to NIH to check for secondary hyperparathyroidism.

      If at the end of the study alendronate is found to be effective, patients who were in the
      placebo treatment group will be offered alendronate for a 24-month period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Polyostotic fibrous dysplasia (PFD) is a sporadic disorder which affects multiple sites in
      the skeleton. The bone at these sites is rapidly resorbed and replaced by abnormal fibrous
      tissue and mechanically abnormal bone. PFD may occur alone or as part of the McCune-Albright
      Syndrome (MAS), a syndrome originally defined by the triad of PFD, cafe-au-lait pigmentation
      of the skin, and precocious puberty. The bony lesions are frequently disfiguring and painful,
      and depending on the location of the lesion, they can cause significant morbidity. Lesions in
      weight-bearing bones can lead to disabling fractures, while lesions in the skull can lead to
      compression of vital structures such as cranial nerves.

      Currently there are no clearly-defined systemic therapies for this bone disease. Small,
      uncontrolled trials using the second generation bisphosphonate, pamidronate, suggest that
      bisphosphonates may be effective. This study is a phase 2, controlled, double blinded trial
      of the third generation oral bisphosphonate, alendronate for the treatment of fibrous
      dysplasia. We propose to show that treatment with alendronate will improve bone quality,
      decrease bone pain, decrease fractures, and, if the patient is referred to the companion bone
      grafting protocol, will allow for the regeneration of better quality bone.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 24, 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 19, 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Polyostotic Fibrous Dysplasia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fosamax (Alendronate)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        All patients must be concomitantly enrolled in the companion Screening and Natural History
        protocol.

        Any patient with at least 2 active fibrous dysplastic lesions of either the cranial, axial,
        or appendicular skeleton will be eligible for consideration for inclusion in the study. The
        diagnosis will be based on evidence typical findings on bone biopsy (performed during the
        &quot;Screening&quot; protocol). Final consideration for enrollment will depend on diagnosis at the
        NIH.

        Patients must be at least 6 years old.

        Patients may be of child-bearing age, but will be expected to be on a nonhormonal form of
        birth control that gives a 95% protection rate. If a patient becomes pregnant during the
        course of the study, they must withdraw but will be eligible for re-enrollment upon the
        completion of pregnancy and lactation.

        Patients on previous of concomitant therapy are eligible for enrollment. However, patients
        who have received previous treatment with a bisphosphonate must wait one year from the
        completion of the last course before they can be enrolled.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patient, child or parents unwilling to fully cooperate with the evaluation as outlined in
        the schedule and consent form and do not give informed consent.

        Any sexually active patient that is unwilling to use an appropriate contraceptive
        associated with a pregnancy-prevention rate of 95% or greater.

        Pregnancy is an absolute contraindication to be evaluated or admitted to the study and is
        grounds for removal from the study. However, patients may be re-enrolled once pregnancy and
        lactation are completed.

        Severe esophageal motility problems may put patients at increased risk for complications
        from alendronate and are not eligible for the study.

        Significant comorbidities such as decompensated heart failure or diabetes mellitus, renal
        or hepatic failure, or decompensated psychiatric conditions exclude patients from
        enrollment.

        Patients with either a history of sarcoma of the bone or who have a FD lesion that
        undergoes sarcomatous degeneration while enrolled in either this study or any of the
        companion protocols.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liens D, Delmas PD, Meunier PJ. Long-term effects of intravenous pamidronate in fibrous dysplasia of bone. Lancet. 1994 Apr 16;343(8903):953-4.</citation>
    <PMID>7909013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Czerwiec FS, Collins M, Feuillan P, Shenker A. Further study of the therapy for fibrous dysplasia is necessary. J Bone Miner Res. 1997 Dec;12(12):2128-30.</citation>
    <PMID>9421248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mastorakos G, Mitsiades NS, Doufas AG, Koutras DA. Hyperthyroidism in McCune-Albright syndrome with a review of thyroid abnormalities sixty years after the first report. Thyroid. 1997 Jun;7(3):433-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9226216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2, 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Pamela G. Robey, Ph.D./National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research</name_title>
    <organization>National Institutes of Health</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bone Marrow Stromal Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Turnover</keyword>
  <keyword>Fibrous Dysplastic Lesion</keyword>
  <keyword>Polyostotic Fibrous Dysplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>McCune-Albright Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrous Dysplasia, Polyostotic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrous Dysplasia of Bone</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alendronate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

