<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005665</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCRR-M01RR02558-0135</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>M01RR002558</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005665</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ingested Interferon Alpha: Prolongation or Permanence of the &quot;Honeymoon&quot; Phase in Newly Diagnosed Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Center for Research Resources (NCRR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Center for Research Resources (NCRR)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We hypothesize that ingested human recombinant interferon-alpha (hrIFN-a) will prolong the
      &quot;honeymoon&quot; period and enhance B cell survival in type 1 diabetes in a phase II randomized,
      placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trial. We have demonstrated that ingested IFN-a
      prevents type 1 diabetes in the NOD mouse, prolongs the &quot;honeymoon&quot; period in newly diagnosed
      type 1 diabetics, and delays murine islet allograft rejection. The natural history of type 1
      diabetes is unique for a phase frequently referred as the &quot;honeymoon,&quot; a period in which the
      insulin need becomes minimal and glycemic control improves. The B cell (the insulin producing
      cell) partially recovers. However, as with all honeymoons, they end and the patient becomes
      completely insulin-deficient. The general consensus of the international diabetes community
      is to test potential preventive therapies for type 1 diabetes in newly diagnosed patients.
      Prolongation of the honeymoon as the reversal of the disease is considered a positive result.

      In this phase II randomized, double-blind, parallel-design clinical trial we will determine
      whether ingested (oral) human recombinant IFN-a will prolong the &quot;honeymoon&quot; period and
      increase counterregulatory anti-inflammatory cytokine(s).

      We will determine the safety and efficacy of 30,000 units ingested hrIFN-a vs placebo in
      eighty patients with newly diagnosed type 1 diabetes in a phase II trial for one year.
      Primary outcome measures will be a 30% increase in C-peptide levels released after Sustacal
      stimulation at 3, 6, 9, and 12 months after entry. Secondary outcome will be decreasing
      titers of islet cell antibodies (ICA). If successful, a larger and longer phase III trial of
      prevention of type 1 diabetes in high risk patients will be undertaken. We will also
      determine if ingested hrIFN-a increases IL-4, IL-10 or IFN-a production in peripheral blood
      mononuclear cells (PMNC) from patients with recent onset type 1 diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>interferon alpha</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Newly diagnosed type 1 diabetes (within one month of diagnosis).

          -  IDDM patients: Prepubescent, adolescent, or early adult patients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients below the age of 3 or over 25.

          -  Patients will not be eligible if they are on immunosuppressive or immunostimulatory
             medications such as azathioprine, oral nicotinamide, superoxide
             dismutase-desferroxamine, vitamin E, aminoguanidine, oral insulin or other
             experimental therapies at any time.

          -  Patients with a history of alcoholism, renal, cardiac, or pulmonary disease or in whom
             intellectual functioning is impaired sufficiently to interfere with the understanding
             of the protocol, or participation in the treatment and evaluation program

          -  Patients who are pregnant or nursing, or those who are not willing to practice an
             acceptable birth control method

          -  Patients with abnormal pre-treatment values on WBC or who are receiving potentially
             hepatotoxic medications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dept. of Neurology, Rm MSB 7.044 Univ. of Texas-Houston Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 19, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 19, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interferons</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interferon-alpha</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

