<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005447</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4376</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R29HL054874</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005447</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physical Activity and Cardiovascular Disease Prevention</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To provide new scientific information regarding the role of physical activity in primary and
      secondary disease prevention, particularly coronary heart disease (CHD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      The long-term follow-up and data analysis of two epidemiologic studies, a general population
      study and a clinical trial provided the basis for the study. The first study assessed the
      long-term relationship between total physical activity (both during work and leisure time)
      and mortality in a random sample of 1,656 Black and white men and women residents of the City
      of Buffalo, New York. The study focused on participants (30+ years of age at baseline) of the
      Buffalo Health Study, an epidemiological investigation conducted in Buffalo in 1960. As part
      of the investigation, detailed information was gathered from participants with regard to a
      number of demographic and socioeconomic characteristics (age, body mass index, education,
      marital status, etc.) and the participants' usual daily activities (both during a weekday and
      weekend) at work and outside work. This information was used to compute a total physical
      activity index. The study related the participants' physical activity characteristics to
      their all-cause and CHD mortality experience throughout the follow-up period and tested
      whether or not the relationship between physical activity and mortality was similar across
      gender and race. The detailed baseline demographic and socioeconomic data allowed analysis of
      the independence of any observed association between physical activity and mortality.

      The second study extended to 17 years, the follow-up of the National Exercise and Heart
      Disease Project (NEHDP), a multi-center, randomized clinical trial designed to study the
      effects of a regular, medically prescribed and supervised exercise program on the
      rehabilitation of male survivors (ages 30-64 at baseline) of a myocardial infarction (MI).
      Three year findings from the trial reported non-significant differences between the treatment
      and control groups for all-cause mortality, and recurrent MI in favor of the exercise group.
      Other outcomes favoring the treatment group were reported after one year and included
      increased physical working capacity, and decreased body fat, diastolic blood pressure, and
      triglycerides. The study determined vital status for all original study participants, and
      cause of death in the deceased. The longer follow-up permitted analysis of whether the
      long-term survival of the treatment group differed from that of the controls. In addition,
      the investigators were able to assess if the risk factor changes observed in the first year
      of the trial were present after three years, whether these changes were related to long-term
      survival, whether differences in mortality observed in sub-groups (i.e. smokers) after three
      years remained after 17 years, and whether baseline patient characteristics (i.e., anxiety
      and depression) predicted mortality.

      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2001</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dorn JP, Cerny FJ, Epstein LH, Naughton J, Vena JE, Winkelstein W Jr, Schisterman E, Trevisan M. Work and leisure time physical activity and mortality in men and women from a general population sample. Ann Epidemiol. 1999 Aug;9(6):366-73.</citation>
    <PMID>10475536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2002</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

