<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005823</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000067831</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>LRF-AML14</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EU-20016</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ISRCTN62207270</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005823</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intensive Compared With Nonintensive Chemotherapy in Treating Older Patients With Acute Myeloid Leukemia or Myelodysplastic Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial for Patients With Acute Myeloid Leukemia or High Risk Myelodysplatic Syndrome Aged 60 or Over</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Leukemia Research Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop cancer cells from dividing
      so they stop growing or die. It is not yet known if stronger doses of chemotherapy given over
      a longer period of time are as well tolerated or as effective as less intensive chemotherapy.

      PURPOSE: This randomized phase III trial is studying intensive regimens of chemotherapy to
      see how well they work compared to nonintensive regimens of chemotherapy in treating older
      patients with acute myeloid leukemia or myelodysplastic syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

        -  Compare the response rate, survival, quality of life, and supportive care requirements
           with intensive versus nonintensive chemotherapy in older patients with acute myeloid
           leukemia or high risk myelodysplastic syndrome.

        -  Compare response achievement, response duration, survival, toxicity and supportive care
           requirements with differing doses of daunorubicin and cytarabine in these patients
           receiving intensive chemotherapy.

        -  Determine the efficacy of PSC 833 in enhancing the effects of daunorubicin in these
           patients receiving intensive chemotherapy.

        -  Compare relapse rate, deaths in complete remission, disease free survival, and survival
           with short versus long intensive chemotherapy in these patients.

        -  Compare response achievement, response duration, survival, toxicity, quality of life,
           and resource use with hydroxyurea versus cytarabine in these patients receiving low dose
           chemotherapy.

        -  Determine response achievement, response duration, survival, toxicity, quality of life,
           and supportive care requirements with the addition of tretinoin to the nonintensive
           chemotherapy in these patients.

        -  Assess the correlation between P-gp and BCL-2 in family members and treatment outcomes
           and other prognostic factors in these patients with these treatment regimens.

      OUTLINE: This is a randomized, multicenter study. Patients are randomized or electively
      assigned to either intensive or nonintensive chemotherapy*.

      Intensive chemotherapy

        -  Induction therapy: Patients are randomized to 1 of 6 treatment arms. Patients receive 2
           courses of chemotherapy comprising 1 of 2 daunorubicin doses, 1 of 2 cytarabine doses,
           thioguanine, and with or without PSC 833.

      Patients receive daunorubicin IV once daily on days 1-3 with cytarabine IV twice daily and
      oral thioguanine once daily on days 1-10 during course 1. Treatment repeats in approximately
      31 days as in course 1 except cytarabine and thioguanine are given only on days 1-8.

        -  Arm I: Patients receive higher dose of daunorubicin, lower dose of cytarabine, and
           thioguanine.

        -  Arm II: Patients receive higher dose of daunorubicin, higher dose of cytarabine, and
           thioguanine.

        -  Arm III: Patients receive lower dose of daunorubicin, lower dose of cytarabine, and
           thioguanine.

        -  Arm IV: Patients receive lower dose of daunorubicin, higher dose of cytarabine, and
           thioguanine.

        -  Arm V: Patients receive treatment as in arm III in combination with continuous infusion
           of PSC 833 beginning day 1.

        -  Arm VI: Patients receive treatment as in arm IV in combination with continuous infusion
           of PSC 833 beginning on day 1.

      Patients with refractory disease after the first course of induction chemotherapy may
      continue with the intensive protocol arm or enter the nonintensive arm*. Patients who do not
      achieve complete remission after completion of induction chemotherapy are removed from study.
      Patients in complete remission after induction therapy receive consolidation therapy.

        -  Consolidation therapy: Patients in complete remission after induction are randomized to
           either short or long consolidation.

             -  Short consolidation: Patients receive mitoxantrone IV on days 1-3 and cytarabine IV
                over 2 hours twice daily on days 1-3.

             -  Long consolidation: Patients complete short consolidation and then receive
                idarubicin IV over 5 minutes once daily on days 1 and 3, cytarabine IV over 2 hours
                twice daily and etoposide IV over 1 hour once daily on days 1-3.

      Non-intensive chemotherapy*

        -  Patients are randomized to 1 of 4 treatment arms.

             -  Arm I: Patients receive oral hydroxyurea as necessary to control WBC count until
                treatment failure.

             -  Arm II: Patients receive hydroxyurea as in arm I and oral tretinoin daily for up to
                16 weeks.

             -  Arm III: Patients receive low dose cytarabine subcutaneously twice daily on days
                1-10 every 28 days for a minimum of 4 courses.

             -  Arm IV: Patients receive cytarabine as in arm III plus oral tretinoin daily for up
                to 16 weeks.

      NOTE: *Patients with liver function test &gt; 2 times upper limit of normal are not eligible for
      nonintensive randomization

      Quality of life is assessed at study entry, and then at 1, 3, and 6 months.

      Patients are followed at one year.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Approximately 2,000 patients (1,200 to intensive arm and 800 to
      nonintensive arm) will be accrued for this study over 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response achievement</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response duration</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity by WHO Toxicity Grading after each treatment course</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life EORTC QLQ-C30 at 3 days, 1 month, 3 months, and 6 months from study entry</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resource use (use of blood products, antibiotics and days in hospital) after each treatment course</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic/Myeloproliferative Neoplasms</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cytarabine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>daunorubicin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>etoposide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hydroxyurea</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>idarubicin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mitoxantrone hydrochloride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>thioguanine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tretinoin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>valspodar</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Acute myeloid leukemia (de novo or secondary) OR

          -  Myelodysplastic syndrome

               -  More than 10% myeloblasts in the bone marrow

               -  Refractory anemia with excess blasts

               -  Refractory anemia with excess blasts in transformation

               -  Chronic myelomonocytic leukemia

          -  No acute promyelocytic leukemia (FAB type M3)

          -  No blastic phase chronic myeloid leukemia

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

        Age:

          -  60 and over (younger patients allowed if intensive chemotherapy not indicated)

        Performance status:

          -  Not specified

        Life expectancy:

          -  Not specified

        Hematopoietic:

          -  Not specified

        Hepatic:

          -  No liver function test ≥ 2 times normal (for non-intensive therapy arm)

        Renal:

          -  Not specified

        Cardiovascular:

          -  No myocardial infarction within past 6 months in patients receiving daunorubicin or
             PSC 833

        Other:

          -  No other concurrent active malignancy

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

        Biologic therapy:

          -  Not specified

        Chemotherapy:

          -  No prior cytotoxic chemotherapy for leukemia

        Endocrine therapy:

          -  Not specified

        Radiotherapy:

          -  Not specified

        Surgery:

          -  Not specified
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alan K. Burnett, MD, FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital of Wales</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth Hospital at University of Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>B15 2RR</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>England</state>
        <zip>WC1E 6AU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Wales</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cardiff</city>
        <state>Wales</state>
        <zip>CF14 4XN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seedhouse CH, Grundy M, White P, Li Y, Fisher J, Yakunina D, Moorman AV, Hoy T, Russell N, Burnett A, Pallis M; National Cancer Research Network. Sequential influences of leukemia-specific and genetic factors on p-glycoprotein expression in blasts from 817 patients entered into the National Cancer Research Network acute myeloid leukemia 14 and 15 trials. Clin Cancer Res. 2007 Dec 1;13(23):7059-66.</citation>
    <PMID>18056183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burnett AK, Milligan D, Hills RK, et al.: Does all-transretinoic acid (ATRA) have a role in non-APL acute myeloid leukaemia? Results from 1666 patients in three MRC trials. [Abstract] Blood 104 (11): A-1794, 2004.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burnett AK, Milligan D, Goldstone A, Prentice A, McMullin MF, Dennis M, Sellwood E, Pallis M, Russell N, Hills RK, Wheatley K; United Kingdom National Cancer Research Institute Haematological Oncology Study Group. The impact of dose escalation and resistance modulation in older patients with acute myeloid leukaemia and high risk myelodysplastic syndrome: the results of the LRF AML14 trial. Br J Haematol. 2009 May;145(3):318-32. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2141.2009.07604.x. Epub 2009 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>19291085</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burnett AK, Milligan D, Prentice AG, Goldstone AH, McMullin MF, Hills RK, Wheatley K. A comparison of low-dose cytarabine and hydroxyurea with or without all-trans retinoic acid for acute myeloid leukemia and high-risk myelodysplastic syndrome in patients not considered fit for intensive treatment. Cancer. 2007 Mar 15;109(6):1114-24.</citation>
    <PMID>17315155</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burnett AK, Milligan DW, Prentice AG, et al.: Modification or dose or treatment duration has no impact on outcome of AML in older patients: preliminary results of the UK NCRI AML14 trial. [Abstract] Blood 106 (11): A-543, 2005.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burnett AK, Milligan D, Prentice AG, et al.: Low dose Ara-C versus hydroxyurea with or without retinoid in older patients not considered fit for intensive chemotherapy: the UK NCRI AML14 trial. [Abstract] Blood 104 (11): A-872, 2004.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pallis M, Truran L, Grundy M, et al.: P-Glycoprotein overexpresion and internal tandem duplications of FLT3 are characteristic of discrete populations of elderly AML patients. [Abstract] Blood 104 (11): A-196, 2004.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 27, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 17, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 17, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>untreated adult acute myeloid leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute erythroid leukemia (M6)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloblastic leukemia without maturation (M1)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloblastic leukemia with maturation (M2)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myelomonocytic leukemia (M4)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute monoblastic leukemia (M5a)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute megakaryoblastic leukemia (M7)</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory anemia with excess blasts</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory anemia with excess blasts in transformation</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic myelomonocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>secondary acute myeloid leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>de novo myelodysplastic syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute monocytic leukemia (M5b)</keyword>
  <keyword>secondary myelodysplastic syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute minimally differentiated myeloid leukemia (M0)</keyword>
  <keyword>atypical chronic myeloid leukemia, BCR-ABL1 negative</keyword>
  <keyword>myelodysplastic/myeloproliferative neoplasm, unclassifiable</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with 11q23 (MLL) abnormalities</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with inv(16)(p13;q22)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with t(16;16)(p13;q22)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with t(8;21)(q22;q22)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myeloproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic-Myeloproliferative Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitoxantrone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Idarubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyurea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tretinoin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thioguanine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

