<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005207</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1086</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL040152</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005207</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Renin and Prorenin in Pregnancy</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the role of the prorenin-renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) in normal
      and hypertensive pregnancy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      The renin-angiotensin system is involved in the physiology of pregnancy in two ways.
      Circulating angiotensin II affects blood pressure, renal hemodynamics, and uteroplacental
      blood flow. Abnormalities in angiotensin II production rates in hypertensive pregnancy
      contribute to the hemodynamic changes seen in the disease. Additionally, there is a form of
      the renin-angiotensin system in kidney, ovary, and placenta whose function is regulated by
      prorenin. Prorenin, activated by a specific receptor, is involved in the regulation of
      steroid hormone biosynthesis and renal and uteroplacental blood flow.

      The study was conducted in response to a Request for Applications on Research on Hypertension
      in Pregnancy jointly released in 1986 by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute and
      the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      The study was longitudinal in design. Measurements were made of glomerular filtration rate,
      renal plasma flow or uterine blood flow. To define first trimester changes, studies were
      conducted on in vitro fertilization and ovarian failure patients who had a broad spectrum of
      plasma prorenins. Since interrelated changes in renin and prostaglandins may participate in
      the pathogenesis of hypertensive pregnancy, RAAS, prostaglandins, and uteroplacental flow
      velocity profiles were monitored during a placebo-controlled trial of low-dose aspirin in
      chronic hypertensives.

      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1987</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 1992</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy Toxemias</condition>
  <condition>Pre-Eclampsia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thaler I, Weiner Z, Itskovitz J. Systolic or diastolic notch in uterine artery blood flow velocity waveforms in hypertensive pregnant patients: relationship to outcome. Obstet Gynecol. 1992 Aug;80(2):277-82.</citation>
    <PMID>1635744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pitarresi TM, Rubattu S, Heinrikson R, Sealey JE. Reversible cryoactivation of recombinant human prorenin. J Biol Chem. 1992 Jun 15;267(17):11753-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1601850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubattu S, Quimby FW, Sealey JE. Tissue renin and prorenin increase in female cats during the reproductive cycle without commensurate changes in plasma, amniotic or ovarian follicular fluid. J Hypertens. 1991 Jun;9(6):525-35.</citation>
    <PMID>1653292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sealey JE, von Lutterotti N, Rubattu S, Campbell WG Jr, Gahnem F, Halimi JM, Laragh JH. The greater renin system. Its prorenin-directed vasodilator limb. Relevance to diabetes mellitus, pregnancy, and hypertension. Am J Hypertens. 1991 Dec;4(12 Pt 1):972-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1815656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lenz T, James GD, Laragh JH, Sealey JE. Prorenin secretion from human placenta perfused in vitro. Am J Physiol. 1991 Jun;260(6 Pt 1):E876-82.</citation>
    <PMID>2058664</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Itskovitz J, Rubattu S, Rosenwaks Z, Liu HC, Sealey JE. Relationship of follicular fluid prorenin to oocyte maturation, steroid levels, and outcome of in vitro fertilization. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1991 Jan;72(1):165-71.</citation>
    <PMID>1986016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thaler I, Manor D, Rottem S, Timor-Tritsch IE, Brandes JM, Itskovitz J. Hemodynamic evaluation of the female pelvic vessels using a high-frequency transvaginal image-directed Doppler system. J Clin Ultrasound. 1990 May;18(4):364-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2161006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>August P, Lenz T, Ales KL, Druzin ML, Edersheim TG, Hutson JM, Müller FB, Laragh JH, Sealey JE. Longitudinal study of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system in hypertensive pregnant women: deviations related to the development of superimposed preeclampsia. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1990 Nov;163(5 Pt 1):1612-21.</citation>
    <PMID>2146881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thaler I, Manor D, Brandes J, Rottem S, Itskovitz J. Basic principles and clinical applications of the transvaginal Doppler duplex system in reproductive medicine. J In Vitro Fert Embryo Transf. 1990 Apr;7(2):74-85. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2193073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thaler I, Manor D, Itskovitz J, Rottem S, Levit N, Timor-Tritsch I, Brandes JM. Changes in uterine blood flow during human pregnancy. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1990 Jan;162(1):121-5.</citation>
    <PMID>2301480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lenz T, Sealey JE, Maack T, James GD, Heinrikson RL, Marion D, Laragh JH. Half-life, hemodynamic, renal, and hormonal effects of prorenin in cynomolgus monkeys. Am J Physiol. 1991 Apr;260(4 Pt 2):R804-10.</citation>
    <PMID>2012251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>August P, Mueller FB, Sealey JE, Edersheim TG. Role of renin-angiotensin system in blood pressure regulation in pregnancy. Lancet. 1995 Apr 8;345(8954):896-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7707813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sealey JE, Itskovitz-Eldor J, Rubattu S, James GD, August P, Thaler I, Levron J, Laragh JH. Estradiol- and progesterone-related increases in the renin-aldosterone system: studies during ovarian stimulation and early pregnancy. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1994 Jul;79(1):258-64.</citation>
    <PMID>8027239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weiner Z, Thaler I, Levron J, Lewit N, Itskovitz-Eldor J. Assessment of ovarian and uterine blood flow by transvaginal color Doppler in ovarian-stimulated women: correlation with the number of follicles and steroid hormone levels. Fertil Steril. 1993 Apr;59(4):743-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8458490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lenz T, Sealey JE, August P, James GD, Laragh JH. Tissue levels of active and total renin, angiotensinogen, human chorionic gonadotropin, estradiol, and progesterone in human placentas from different methods of delivery. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1989 Jul;69(1):31-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2659618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Itskovitz J, Bruneval P, Soubrier F, Thaler I, Corvol P, Sealey JE. Localization of renin gene expression to monkey ovarian theca cells by in situ hybridization. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1992 Nov;75(5):1374-80.</citation>
    <PMID>1430100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gahnem F, Sealey JE, Atlas SA, Laragh JH. Inhibition of human renin by rat plasma. Rat angiotensinogen is a competitive inhibitor of the human renin-substrate interaction. Am J Hypertens. 1992 Aug;5(8):495-501.</citation>
    <PMID>1388958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thaler I, Weiner Z, Itskovitz J. Renal artery flow velocity waveforms in normal and hypertensive pregnant women. Am J Hypertens. 1992 Jun;5(6 Pt 1):402-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1524766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Itskovitz J, Rubattu S, Levron J, Sealey JE. Highest concentrations of prorenin and human chorionic gonadotropin in gestational sacs during early human pregnancy. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1992 Sep;75(3):906-10.</citation>
    <PMID>1517384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2000</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 13, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eclampsia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pre-Eclampsia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Toxemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

