<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00004196</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000067439</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UAB-9735</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UAB-F970925009</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-G99-1654</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>RPCI-DS-99-14</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00004196</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interferon Alfa-2b in Treating Patients With Melanoma and Early Lymph Node Metastasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter Trial of Adjuvant Interferon Alfa-2b for Melanoma Patients With Early Lymph Node Metastasis Detected by Lymphatic Mapping and Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Interferon alfa-2b may interfere with the growth of cancer cells.

      PURPOSE: Randomized phase III trial to study the effectiveness of interferon alfa-2b in
      treating patients who have melanoma with early lymph node metastasis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

        -  Compare the efficacy of regional lymphadenectomy with or without adjuvant high-dose
           interferon alfa-2b on disease-free survival and overall survival of patients with
           invasive cutaneous melanoma with early or submicroscopic sentinel lymph node metastasis
           detected by histology or immunohistochemistry or by polymerase chain reaction (PCR).

        -  Compare the effect of lymphadenectomy vs observation on disease-free survival and
           overall survival of patients with submicroscopic sentinel lymph node metastasis detected
           only by PCR.

        -  Determine the recurrence rate and survival of patients with submicroscopic sentinel
           lymph node metastasis detected only by PCR.

        -  Determine the positive and negative predictive value of reverse transcriptase PCR
           analysis of sentinel lymph nodes and peripheral blood to identify patients at risk for
           recurrence and death.

      OUTLINE: This is a randomized, multicenter study. Patients in the randomized portions of
      Protocols A and B are stratified according to tumor thickness (1-2 mm vs 3-4 mm vs greater
      than 4 mm) and tumor ulceration (yes vs no).

      All patients undergo wide local tumor excision with lymphatic mapping and sentinel node
      biopsy. Patients with tumors with ambiguous drainage patterns undergo lymphoscintigraphy
      prior to tumor excision. Patients with evidence of metastatic melanoma in the sentinel
      node(s) by routine histology, serial sectioning, or immunohistochemistry and who have
      undergone a prior regional lymph node dissection proceed to protocol A.

        -  Protocol A: Patients with metastasis in a single sentinel node with no evidence of
           extracapsular extension and no metastatic disease in nonsentinel nodes are randomized to
           1 of 2 treatment arms.

             -  Arm I: Patients receive adjuvant high-dose interferon alfa-2b IV 5 days a week for
                4 weeks, then subcutaneously 3 times a week for 48 weeks.

             -  Arm II: Patients undergo observation. Patients with metastases in more than one
                sentinel node with evidence of extracapsular extension or metastasis in any
                nonsentinel node receive adjuvant high-dose interferon alfa-2b as in arm I.

      Patients with no evidence of sentinel node(s) metastases by routine histology, serial
      sectioning, and immunohistochemistry and are negative by polymerase chain reaction (PCR)
      analysis are observed.

        -  Protocol B: Patients with positive sentinel node(s) by PCR analysis are randomized to
           one of three treatment arms.

             -  Arm I: Patients undergo observation.

             -  Arm II: Patients undergo lymph node dissection.

             -  Arm III: Patients undergo lymph node dissection followed by adjuvant high-dose
                interferon alfa-2b IV 5 days a week for 4 weeks.

      Patients are followed every 3 months for 2 years, every 4 months for 1 year, every 6 months
      for 2 years, and then annually thereafter.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 3,000 patients will be accrued for this study within 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2004</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma (Skin)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with metastasis in a single sentinel node with no evidence of extracapsular extension and no metastatic disease in nonsentinel nodes are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms. Patients receive adjuvant high-dose interferon alfa-2b IV 5 days a week for 4 weeks, then subcutaneously 3 times a week for 48 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm AII</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with metastasis in a single sentinel node with no evidence of extracapsular extension and no metastatic disease in nonsentinel nodes are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms. Observational arm: Patients with metastases in more than one sentinel node with evidence of extracapsular extension or metastasis in any nonsentinel node receive adjuvant high-dose interferon alfa-2b as in arm AI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm BI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with positive sentinel node(s) by PCR analysis are randomized to one of three treatment arms. Patients undergo observation. Patients are followed every 3 months for 2 years, every 4 months for 1 year, every 6 months for 2 years, and then annually thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with positive sentinel node(s) by PCR analysis are randomized to one of three treatment arms. Patients undergo lymph node dissection. Patients are followed every 3 months for 2 years, every 4 months for 1 year, every 6 months for 2 years, and then annually thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm BIII</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with positive sentinel node(s) by PCR analysis are randomized to one of three treatment arms. Patients undergo lymph node dissection followed by adjuvant high-dose interferon alfa-2b IV 5 days a week for 4 weeks.
Patients are followed every 3 months for 2 years, every 4 months for 1 year, every 6 months for 2 years, and then annually thereafter.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>recombinant interferon alfa</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>AI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm AII</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm BIII</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lymphangiography</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm BIII</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Observation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm AII</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm BI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histologically confirmed invasive cutaneous melanoma

               -  Breslow thickness at least 1.0 mm

               -  Primary site must be on head, neck, trunk or extremity

               -  No more than 90 days since biopsy

          -  Protocol A:

               -  One or more sentinel lymph nodes with histologic or immunohistochemical evidence
                  of metastatic melanoma

               -  Prior regional lymph node dissection

          -  Protocol B:

               -  Sentinel lymph nodes with no histologic or immunohistochemical evidence of
                  metastatic melanoma

               -  Sentinel lymph node positive by reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction

          -  No prior wide local excision of the primary tumor with a margin greater than 1.5 cm

          -  No primary melanoma involving the eye or mucous membranes

          -  No clinical evidence of satellite lesions or intransit, regional nodal, or distant
             metastases

          -  No second primary invasive melanoma

          -  No prior surgery in the region of the primary draining nodal basin that would disrupt
             normal lymphatic drainage patterns (e.g., skin grafts, tissue transfers or flaps, or
             lymph node dissections)

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

        Age:

          -  18 to 70

        Performance status:

          -  Karnofsky 70-100%

        Life expectancy:

          -  At least 10 years

        Hematopoietic:

          -  WBC at least 3,000/mm^3

          -  Absolute granulocyte count at least 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count at least 70,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin at least 10.0 g/dL

        Hepatic:

          -  Bilirubin less than 2.0 mg/dL

          -  SGOT/SGPT less than 3 times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Alkaline phosphatase less than 3 times ULN

          -  No severe decompensated liver disease (e.g., cirrhosis or autoimmune hepatitis)

          -  No other significant liver disease that would preclude study participation

        Renal:

          -  Creatinine normal

        Cardiovascular:

          -  No cardiovascular disease (e.g., angina or congestive heart failure)

          -  No myocardial infarction within the past year

          -  No tachyarrhythmias

        Pulmonary:

          -  No severe debilitating pulmonary disease (e.g., chronic obstructive pulmonary disease)

        Other:

          -  No hypersensitivity to interferon alfa-2b or related compounds or any component of the
             injection

          -  No major depression or other major psychiatric illness

          -  No thyroid disorder with thyroid function that is not maintained within the normal
             range with medications

          -  No autoimmune disease

          -  No primary or secondary immunodeficiencies

          -  No severe diabetes mellitus prone to ketoacidosis

          -  No significant retinal abnormalities

          -  No evidence of infection

          -  No other malignancy within the past 5 years except basal cell or squamous cell skin
             cancer, carcinoma in situ of the cervix, or stage I laryngeal cancer

          -  No other medical condition that would preclude study participation

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception during and for 6 months after the
             study

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

        Biologic therapy:

          -  No prior immunotherapy

        Chemotherapy:

          -  No prior chemotherapy

        Endocrine therapy:

          -  At least 6 months since prior oral or parenteral steroids

        Radiotherapy:

          -  No prior radiotherapy

        Surgery:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  No prior organ transplantation

        Other:

          -  At least 6 months since prior immunosuppressants

          -  No concurrent immunosuppressants resulting from prior organ transplantation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marshall M. Urist, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294-3300</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>James Graham Brown Cancer Center at University of Louisville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Institute of New Jersey</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Brunswick</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263-0001</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 27, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stage I melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III melanoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interferons</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interferon-alpha</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

