<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00004863</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000067518</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA013330</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>AECM-1199906196</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HYBRIDON-231-100B</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-G00-1665</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00004863</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Paclitaxel and GEM 231 in Treating Patients With Recurrent or Refractory Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Open-Label Safety Study of Escalating Doses of Taxol in Combination With Escalating Doses of GEM231 in Patients With Refractory Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Montefiore Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Montefiore Medical Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so
      they stop growing or die. Combining more than one drug may kill more tumor cells.

      PURPOSE: Phase I trial to study the effectiveness of paclitaxel and GEM 231 in treating
      patients who have recurrent or refractory solid tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the safety and maximum tolerated dose of GEM 231 and paclitaxel in
      patients with recurrent or refractory solid tumors. II. Determine any preliminary antitumor
      activity of this regimen in these patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose escalation study of GEM 231. Patients receive paclitaxel IV over 3
      hours on day 1, immediately followed by GEM 231 over 2 hours on days 1, 4, 8, 11, 15, and 18.
      Treatment continues every 3 weeks in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity. Cohorts of 3-6 patients are treated with one of two doses of paclitaxel and
      escalating doses of GEM 231 until the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is determined. The MTD is
      defined as the dose at which no more than 2 of 6 patients experience dose limiting toxicity.
      Patients are followed monthly for 3 months.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A maximum of 1 patient will be accrued per week for this study until the
      maximum tolerated dose is reached.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1999</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GEM 231</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>paclitaxel</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed advanced solid tumor that is refractory
        to standard therapy or for which no standard therapy exists Measurable or evaluable disease
        No CNS metastases that are untreated, associated with seizures, or require intravenous
        medication and/or hospitalization

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: WHO 0-2 Life expectancy: Not
        specified Hematopoietic: Absolute neutrophil count at least 1,500/mm3 Platelet count at
        least 100,000/mm3 Hemoglobin at least 8.5 g/dL Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater than upper
        limit of normal (ULN), except with Gilbert's syndrome (no greater than 1.5 times ULN if
        liver metastases present) PT and aPTT normal SGOT or SGPT less than 3 times ULN (no greater
        than 5 times ULN if liver metastases present) Renal: Creatinine less than 1.25 times ULN No
        renal tubular dysfunction (i.e., at least 2+ proteinuria within the past 2 weeks) Other:
        Not pregnant or nursing Negative pregnancy test Fertile patients must use effective
        contraception for 1 month prior to, during, and 3 months after study No other serious
        medical condition that would prevent compliance No serious infection No known
        hypersensitivity to paclitaxel or other drugs formulated in Cremophor or any
        oligodeoxynucleotides Adequate venous access No psychological or geographical condition
        that would prevent compliance

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: At least 1 week since prior transfusion Prior
        biologic therapy allowed and recovered No concurrent biologic therapy Chemotherapy: Prior
        chemotherapy allowed and recovered No other concurrent chemotherapy Endocrine therapy:
        Prior hormonal therapy allowed and recovered Concurrent palliative hormonal therapy allowed
        Radiotherapy: Prior radiotherapy allowed and recovered No concurrent radiotherapy (except
        palliative) Surgery: At least 2 weeks since prior major surgery with wound complications
        Other: At least 2 weeks since prior investigational drugs No other investigational drugs
        during or within 28 days of study No concurrent CYP-3A metabolism dependent drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sridhar Mani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albert Einstein Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10461</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 15, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

