<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>980110</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98-EI-0110</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cyclosporin Implant to Treat Uveitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of a Sustained-Release Cyclosporine A Implant for Uveitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety and effectiveness of a sustained-release cyclosporin
      implant to treat uveitis, a sight-threatening eye inflammation caused by an immune system
      abnormality. Previous studies in humans have shown that, taken by mouth, the drug cyclosporin
      is effective in treating chronic uveitis.

      Uveitis may require long-term treatment with potent immune-suppressing drugs, such as
      cyclosporin, cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, azathioprine or steroids. Taken systemically (by
      mouth or injection), however, these drugs can do serious damage to the kidneys, liver or
      lungs, and can raise blood pressure and lower blood cell counts. Because of this, some
      patients cannot or will not use these medicines.

      This small pilot study will evaluate the safety, and to some extent effectiveness, of
      cyclosporin delivered directly into the eye, to try to prevent harmful side effects. In
      animal studies, sustained-release cyclosporin implants did not cause the severe side effects
      seen with systemic use of the drug. Some animals developed opacity of the lens and slowed
      retinal responses, both of which reversed when the drug was stopped. Earlier animal studies
      of cyclosporin injected directly into the eye reduced inflammation that had been produced
      experimentally.

      Patients with uveitis who have active inflammation and poor vision are eligible to
      participate in this study. Patients will be randomly assigned to one of two treatment groups.
      One group will receive a 1-mg implant that releases 0.8 micrograms of drug each day; the
      second group will receive a 2-mg implant that delivers 1.4 micrograms of drug a day.

      Before surgery, patients will have a medical history, basic physical examination, and
      complete eye examination, including special tests called electroretinogram and fluorescein
      angiography. An electroretinogram measures the electrical responses generated in the retina
      in the back of the eye. Fluorescein angiography uses a special camera to photograph the
      retina, showing the condition of the blood vessels in the eye.

      The surgical procedure to place the implant takes about 1.5 hours and may be done under
      either local or general anesthesia. Patients will stay in the hospital overnight. After
      discharge from the hospital, they will return for follow-up visits 1 and 2 weeks after
      surgery, then once a month for 6 months, and then every 3 months until the implant is
      depleted of drug or removed. During these follow-up visits, eye examinations will be repeated
      to evaluate the effects of the implant on the eye. Repeat blood tests will measure the amount
      of cyclosporin in the blood and the drug's effect on the kidneys. When the implant runs out
      of drug (between 2 and 3 years), it may be removed or left in place.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sight threatening uveitis may require long term use of systemic immunosuppressants. In some
      patients, aggressive systemic immunosuppressive therapy fails to control inflammation and can
      lead to serious side effects. Oral Cyclosporin A (CsA) has been shown in several human trials
      to be effective in treating chronic uveitis. This pilot study will assess the safety, and to
      some extent efficacy, of a novel intraocular CsA release implant in patients with active
      inflammation and poor visual acuity in one eye despite immunosuppressant therapy. Patients
      will be randomly assigned to receive in one eye a 1 or 2 mg CsA implant releasing at either
      0.8 microgram per day or 1.4 microgram per day respectively. The main purpose of the study is
      to assess the safety of the CsA implant. Secondary outcomes will include a change from
      baseline in the ocular inflammation, visual acuity, and the need for concomitant
      anti-inflammatory medications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>10</enrollment>
  <condition>Eye Disease</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <condition>Uveitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclosporin A Implant</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Age range: 15 or older.

        Active non-infectious intermediate, posterior or panuveitis present for at least 6 months
        despite systemic immunosupressive therapy including at least 20 mg of oral prednisone or
        use of another immunosuppressive agent.

        Visual acuity worse than 20/80 (55 letters) and better than 5/200 (4 letters) in the eye to
        receive the CsA implant, and better than 20/80 (54 letters) in the non-study eye.

        Bilateral or unilateral uveitis with active inflammation in one eye only (eye to be
        implanted). Patients may continue systemic immunosuppressants with the exception of
        systemic CsA. Patients may not take greater than 1 drop of topical steroid four times a day
        in the eye to be implanted for maintenance of anterior segment inflammation after 1 month
        postoperatively.

        Recordable electroretinogram (ERG).

        Willingness and the ability, with assistance of a care giver, if necessary, to comply with
        treatment and follow-up procedures.

        The ability to understand and sign an informed consent form which must be obtained prior to
        treatment.

        Negative serum pregnancy test (females of childbearing potential only).

        Normal serum creatinine (males 0.9 - 1.4 mg/dL, females 0.7 - 1.3 mg/dL).

        No current or past history of retinal detachment.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Current or past history of retinal detachment.

        Pregnant or lactating patients or patients with potential for conception unless using
        effective contraception. Fertile males must use effective contraception. Contraception
        would no longer be mandatory for participation in this study at three months
        postoperatively assuming (1) negligible CsA absorption, (2) patient is not taking any other
        medications that may affect a developing fetus or spermatogenesis.

        Patients who received therapy within the previous one week with any nephrotoxic drugs.

        Patients having a known allergy to CsA.

        Patients receiving current therapy with CsA. Patients need to be off of systemic CsA seven
        days prior to implant surgery. Patients may continue other immunosuppressive therapies if
        needed to control inflammation in contralateral (non-study) eye provided the inflammation
        is currently not active.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Eye Institute (NEI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pearson PA, Jaffe GJ, Martin DF, Cordahi GJ, Grossniklaus H, Schmeisser ET, Ashton P. Evaluation of a delivery system providing long-term release of cyclosporine. Arch Ophthalmol. 1996 Mar;114(3):311-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8600892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whitcup SM, Salvo EC Jr, Nussenblatt RB. Combined cyclosporine and corticosteroid therapy for sight-threatening uveitis in Behçet's disease. Am J Ophthalmol. 1994 Jul 15;118(1):39-45.</citation>
    <PMID>8023874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith TJ, Pearson PA, Blandford DL, Brown JD, Goins KA, Hollins JL, Schmeisser ET, Glavinos P, Baldwin LB, Ashton P. Intravitreal sustained-release ganciclovir. Arch Ophthalmol. 1992 Feb;110(2):255-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1310588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2004</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Eye</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunosuppression</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitreous</keyword>
  <keyword>Uveitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eye Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

