<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001448</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>950185</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>95-C-0185</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001448</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Oral Candidiasis on the Speech Production, Feeding Skills, and Self-Concept of Children and Adolescents With Symptomatic HIV Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Oral Candidiasis on the Speech Production, Feeding Skills, and Self-Concept of Children and Adolescents With Symptomatic HIV Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main objectives of this study are: 1) to determine whether various levels of severity of
      oral candidiasis (thrush) in the child are associated with different levels of speech
      production, feeding skills, and self-concept, and 2) to assess the effect of the reduction of
      oral thrush over time on the speech function, feeding skills, and self-concept in
      HIV-infected patients who already are receiving various antifungal medications for treatment
      of their thrush (Note: Decisions regarding antifungal therapy are made completely independent
      from this study).

      Children with HIV disease, ages 6-21 years, who have oral thrush are eligible to paricipate
      in the study. The child and his/her parent will be asked to complete a variety of measures at
      specific time intervals over approximately one month during visits to the National Institutes
      of Health for treatment on other protocols. First, a nurse will rate the location and
      severity of thrush in the child's mouth. Then the parent will complete questionnaires
      assessing the effect of oral thrush on the child's feeding and speech skills and everyday
      functioning. Finally, the child will be administered a brief speech and oral-motor evaluation
      and will complete some questionnaires about how the thrush affects his/her day-to-day
      activities and self-concept.

      The results of this study may help to better understand the cause of expressive language
      deficits observed in some children with HIV infection. More specifically, it will determine
      if any speech and feeding problems of HIV-infected children are associated with oral thrush.
      Learning more about the impact of oral thrush on the speech, feeding, and the self-concept of
      children with HIV disease may be used for parent and patient education and to develop
      rehabilitative recommendations to benefit HIV-infected patients with oral thrush.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Language impairments in children with symptomatic HIV infection are associated with the
      direct effects of HIV on the central nervous system (CNS). Furthermore, expressive language
      is more vulnerable to the effects of HIV compared to receptive language (Wolters, et al.,
      1995). Several factors, however, are likely to be involved in producing the expressive
      language impairments observed in the HIV-infected pediatric population. Oral candidiasis
      (thrush), a fungal infection in the oral cavity that frequently appears in HIV-infected
      children (Walsh, 1994), also may contribute to speech and language deficits depending on the
      severity of the thrush. Feeding skills and self-concept may be negatively affected by oral
      thrush as well.

      The effect of oral candidiasis on the speech production, feeding skills, and self-concept of
      children and adolescents with HIV infection will be examined in this pilot study. Several
      disciplines (Neuropsychology, Speech, Nursing, and Infectious Disease) will be involved to
      investigate the severity of oral candidiasis on various aspects of everyday behavior.

      Interdisciplinary assessment of the ramifications of oral thrush on speech production and
      feeding skills have not been conducted to date in children or adolescents infected with HIV.
      Most studies have assessed only single dimensions or functions such as language or they have
      yielded only descriptive data, for example, regarding the severity of oral thrush. This pilot
      study, however, will investigate the association between oral thrush and speech and feeding
      dysfunction using some newly-developed measures. The study will also examine whether oral
      candidiasis may influence the self-concept of children and adolescents with HIV infection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2000</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>50</enrollment>
  <condition>Candidiasis, Oral</condition>
  <condition>Eating Disorders</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Speech Disorders</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Children and adolescents with HIV infection, ages 6 through 21 years of age, who are
        treated in other protocols at the Pediatric Branch of the National Cancer Institute (NCI)
        and have oral candidiasis as determined by the Pediatric Nurse Practitioners, are eligible
        to participate in this study.

        Children and adolescents with infections or diseases other than candidiasis affecting the
        oral cavity as determined by the PNP's during the physical exam will be excluded from the
        study.

        Furthermore, patients who are identified by the speech pathologist to have oro-facial
        structural and/or functional abnormalities that cause a significant disturbance in speech,
        voice, or swallowing will be excluded.

        Children will also not be able t participate in the study if they cannot understand the
        measures, even if the questions are read to them, which will be determined by the
        Neuropsychology staff.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein LG, Sharer LR, Oleske JM, Connor EM, Goudsmit J, Bagdon L, Robert-Guroff M, Koenigsberger MR. Neurologic manifestations of human immunodeficiency virus infection in children. Pediatrics. 1986 Oct;78(4):678-87.</citation>
    <PMID>2429248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pressman H. Communication disorders and dysphagia in pediatric AIDS. ASHA. 1992 Jan;34(1):45-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1540256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolters PL, Brouwers P, Moss HA, Pizzo PA. Differential receptive and expressive language functioning of children with symptomatic HIV disease and relation to CT scan brain abnormalities. Pediatrics. 1995 Jan;95(1):112-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7770287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 1999</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Antifungal Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Articulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>Expressive Language</keyword>
  <keyword>Thrush</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Feeding and Eating Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Candidiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Candidiasis, Oral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Speech Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

