<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00003998</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000067208</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CRC-BOC-SCOTROC</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EU-99010</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00003998</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carboplatin Plus Paclitaxel or Docetaxel in Treating Patients With Ovarian Epithelial Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Prospective Phase III Comparison of Paclitaxel-Carboplatin Versus Docetaxel-Carboplatin as First Line Chemotherapy in Stage Ic-IV Epithelial Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Glasgow</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop cancer cells from dividing
      so they stop growing or die. Combining more than one drug may kill more cancer cells. It is
      not yet known which combination chemotherapy regimen is more effective for treating ovarian
      epithelial cancer.

      PURPOSE: Randomized phase III trial to compare the effectiveness of carboplatin plus
      paclitaxel with that of carboplatin plus docetaxel in treating patients who have ovarian
      epithelial cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Compare the progression free survival of chemotherapy naive patients with
      stage IC-IV ovarian epithelial cancer following initial surgery treated with paclitaxel and
      carboplatin versus docetaxel and carboplatin. II. Compare the toxic effects of these regimens
      in these patients. III. Determine the overall survival, overall response rate, and CA125
      response in these patients after these regimens. IV. Determine the quality of life of these
      patients on these regimens.

      OUTLINE: This is a randomized, multicenter study. Patients are stratified by residual disease
      (none or microscopic vs macroscopic no greater than 2 cm vs or macroscopic greater than 2
      cm), study center, FIGO stage (IC-IV), performance status (0 vs 1 vs 2), tumor grade
      (well-defined vs moderately defined vs poorly defined/undifferentiated vs unknown), interval
      debulking intention (yes vs no vs randomized into OV06 trial), elevated CA125 prior to
      treatment (yes vs no), and primary peritoneal cancer (yes vs no). Patients may undergo
      interval debulking surgery within 4 weeks of the third course of chemotherapy, or following 6
      courses of treatment. Patients undergoing interval debulking after 3 courses should resume
      chemotherapy within 3 weeks of surgery. Patients are randomized into one of two treatment
      arms. Arm I: Patients receive paclitaxel IV over 3 hours, immediately followed by carboplatin
      IV over 1 hour. Arm II: Patients receive docetaxel IV over 1 hour, immediately followed by
      carboplatin IV over 1 hour. Courses are repeated every 21 days. Treatment continues for 6
      courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients with partial
      or complete response may receive 3 additional courses of carboplatin alone thereafter.
      Quality of life is assessed at baseline, prior to each treatment course, and then every 4
      months for 2 years or until disease progression. Patients are followed every 2 months for 2
      years, every 3 months for 1 year, every 4 months for 1 year, and then every 6 months
      thereafter.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Approximately 1050 patients will be accrued for this study within 2.25
      years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1050</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Primary Peritoneal Cavity Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carboplatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>paclitaxel</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>surgical procedure</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed stage IC-IV ovarian epithelial cancer IC
        must have malignant cells in ascitic fluid or peritoneal washing, have tumor on surface of
        the ovary, or have preoperative capsule rupture OR Peritoneal carcinomatosis (ovarian-type)
        No evidence of primary fallopian tube carcinoma No mixed mesodermal tumors No borderline
        ovarian tumors or tumors termed possibly malignant

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: ECOG 0-2 Life expectancy: Not
        specified Hematopoietic: Absolute neutrophil count at least 1,500/mm3 Platelet count at
        least 100,000/mm3 Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater than upper limit of normal (ULN) OR ALT or
        AST no greater than 1.5 times ULN OR Alkaline phosphatase no greater than 3 times ULN
        Renal: Creatinine no greater than 1.25 times ULN Cardiovascular: No hypertension No
        ischemic heart disease No myocardial infarction within the past 6 months No congestive
        heart failure Other: Not pregnant or nursing Fertile patients must use effective
        contraception No uncontrolled infection No other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled
        comorbid medical condition No prior malignancy within the past 5 years, except: Curatively
        treated carcinoma in situ of the cervix Basal cell skin cancer No other concurrent
        malignancy (e.g., endometrial cancer) No prior serious allergic reaction (e.g.,
        anaphylactic shock) No symptomatic grade 2 or greater peripheral neuropathy

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: Not specified Chemotherapy: No prior
        chemotherapy Endocrine therapy: Not specified Radiotherapy: No prior radiotherapy Surgery:
        Prior surgery allowed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul A. Vasey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Glasgow</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>C.R.C. Beatson Laboratories</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <state>Scotland</state>
        <zip>G61 1BD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Marsh S, Paul J, King CR, Gifford G, McLeod HL, Brown R. Pharmacogenetic assessment of toxicity and outcome after platinum plus taxane chemotherapy in ovarian cancer: the Scottish Randomised Trial in Ovarian Cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Oct 10;25(29):4528-35.</citation>
    <PMID>17925548</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Crawford SC, Vasey PA, Paul J, Hay A, Davis JA, Kaye SB. Does aggressive surgery only benefit patients with less advanced ovarian cancer? Results from an international comparison within the SCOTROC-1 Trial. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Dec 1;23(34):8802-11. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2006 Mar 1;24(7):1224.</citation>
    <PMID>16314640</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vasey PA, Jayson GC, Gordon A, Gabra H, Coleman R, Atkinson R, Parkin D, Paul J, Hay A, Kaye SB; Scottish Gynaecological Cancer Trials Group. Phase III randomized trial of docetaxel-carboplatin versus paclitaxel-carboplatin as first-line chemotherapy for ovarian carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2004 Nov 17;96(22):1682-91.</citation>
    <PMID>15547181</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 3, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>stage I ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>primary peritoneal cavity cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peritoneal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

