<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001657</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>970128</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>97-M-0128</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001657</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) in Chronic Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Controlled Studies of Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) in Chronic Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Posttraumatic stress disorder occurs in patients who have experienced, witnessed or have been
      confronted with an event involving actual death or the threat of death, serious injury, or
      the threat to physical health and felt fear, helplessness, or horror. As a result, patients
      continue to re-experience, recollect, dream, or have flashbacks about the traumatic incident.

      Research on PTSD continues to show metabolic changes in specific areas of the brain in
      patients diagnosed with PTSD. For example, neuroimaging studies (functional MRI and PET
      scans) reveal that blood flow and glucose utilization increases in the right frontal, limbic,
      and paralimbic areas of the brain in patients with PTSD, particularly when they are recalling
      the traumatic event associated with their symptoms.

      One potential method for interfering with the neuronal circuitry associated with traumatic
      memories is through the use of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS). This
      technique involves the placement of a cooled electromagnet with a figure-eight coil on the
      patient's scalp and rapidly turning on and off the magnetic flux. This permits non-invasive,
      relatively localized stimulation of the surface of the brain (cerebral cortex). The effect of
      magnetic stimulation varies, depending upon the location, intensity and frequency of the
      magnetic pulses. Preliminary clinical data shows that low frequency rTMS stimulation leads to
      a decrease in regional cerebral blood flow.

      This study is designed to determine if rTMS stimulation in patients diagnosed with PTSD leads
      to symptomatic improvement, reductions in blood flow to specific areas of the brain, and
      improvements in the regulation of the autonomic nervous system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A growing body of data indicates that patients with posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) have
      regionally selective alterations in brain metabolism and processing of information. For
      example, neuroimaging studies reveal increased blood flow and glucose utilization in right
      frontal, limbic and paralimibic brain structures in patients with PTSD, particularly when
      they are recalling the traumatic event associated with their symptoms. These alterations in
      regional brain activity are thought to be related, in part, to the distressing emotional
      symptoms associated with traumatic memories. Autonomic Nervous System (ANS) dysregulation is
      common in PTSD, with sympathetic hyper-reactivity and relative lack of parasympathetic
      modulation. In addition, abnormalities in hormone levels such as thyroid hormones and the
      hypothalmic-pituitary-adrenal axis have been demonstrated. Repetitive transcranial magnetic
      stimulation may provide a non-invasive technique for normalizing the alterations in regional
      brain metabolism, possibly leading to improvements in PTSD symptoms and concomitant
      improvement in ANS and hormonal balance. In particular, preliminary clinical data indicate
      that low frequency (i.e., approximately 0.9-1 Hz) rTMS stimulation leads to a decrease in
      regional cerebral blood flow. The purpose of the present study is to determine, using a
      placebo-controlled, parallel design, whether right frontal rTMS stimulation in patients with
      posttraumatic stress disorder leads to symptomatic improvement, reductions in hemispheric
      regional blood flow, and improvements in ANS regulation. The study hypothesis is that 1 Hz
      right frontal rTMS stimulation will be superior to sham stimulation in reducing PTSD symptoms
      and physiology including improving abnormalities in regional cerebral blood flow, vagal tone,
      and circulating hormone levels.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 2000</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>30</enrollment>
  <condition>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Subjects (age 18-70) meeting DSM-IV criteria for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD).

        Subjects will be individuals with chronic PTSD (i.e., greater than 1 year).

        No subjects with evidence of uncontrolled significant medical illness on physical exam,
        laboratory screening or EKG, presence of cardiac pacemakers, medication pumps, cochlear
        implants, metal objects in the head or eyes, history of a seizure disorder, left
        handedness, or pregnancy.

        No subjects with unstable dissociative symptoms, current self-injurious behavior, current
        eating disorder, active substance abuse (alcohol or illicit substance use within the past
        three months), or active suicidality.

        Subjects will be allowed to be on stable doses of benzodiazepines and/or antidepressants
        while undergoing rTMS treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>George MS, Wassermann EM, Williams WA, Callahan A, Ketter TA, Basser P, Hallett M, Post RM. Daily repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) improves mood in depression. Neuroreport. 1995 Oct 2;6(14):1853-6.</citation>
    <PMID>8547583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pascual-Leone A, Houser CM, Reese K, Shotland LI, Grafman J, Sato S, Valls-Solé J, Brasil-Neto JP, Wassermann EM, Cohen LG, et al. Safety of rapid-rate transcranial magnetic stimulation in normal volunteers. Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol. 1993 Apr;89(2):120-30.</citation>
    <PMID>7683602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rauch SL, van der Kolk BA, Fisler RE, Alpert NM, Orr SP, Savage CR, Fischman AJ, Jenike MA, Pitman RK. A symptom provocation study of posttraumatic stress disorder using positron emission tomography and script-driven imagery. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1996 May;53(5):380-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8624181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 1999</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>15 O PET Scanning</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Cerebral Blood Flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Domestic Abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuroendocrine</keyword>
  <keyword>PET Scanning</keyword>
  <keyword>Police Officers</keyword>
  <keyword>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

