<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005818</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2012-02330</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ID-99-243</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM17003</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000067823</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005818</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SU5416 and Irinotecan in Treating Patients With Advanced Colorectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of Escalating Doses of SU5416 (NSC 696819) in Combination With CPT-11 in Patients With Advanced Colorectal Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase I/II trial to study the effectiveness of combining SU5416 and irinotecan in treating
      patients who have advanced colorectal cancer. SU5416 may stop the growth of colorectal cancer
      by stopping blood flow to the tumor. Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop
      tumor cells from dividing so they stop growing or die
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and dose-limiting toxicity of SU5416 in
      combination with irinotecan in patients with advanced colorectal cancer.

      II. Determine time to disease progression, objective response rate, and survival time in
      these patients receiving this regimen at the MTD.

      III. Evaluate the safety and tolerance of this regimen in these patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of SU5416.

      Patients receive irinotecan IV over 90 minutes on day 1 of weeks 1-4 and SU5416 IV over 60
      minutes on days 1 and 4 of weeks 1-6. Treatment continues every 6 weeks in the absence of
      unacceptable toxicity or disease progression.

      Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of SU5416 until the maximum tolerated dose
      (MTD) is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6
      patients experience dose-limiting toxicity. Once the MTD is determined, additional patients
      are accrued to receive treatment with SU5416 and irinotecan at the recommended phase II dose.

      Patients are followed every 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2000</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2003</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to disease progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method. Associated 95% confidence intervals will be computed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall tumor response rate (CR + PR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Associated 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of entry on study to the date of death of the patients; assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity graded using the NCI CTC version 2.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of the Colon</condition>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of the Rectum</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (irinotecan hydrochloride, semaxanib)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive irinotecan IV over 90 minutes on day 1 of weeks 1-4 and SU5416 IV over 60 minutes on days 1 and 4 of weeks 1-6. Treatment continues every 6 weeks in the absence of unacceptable toxicity or disease progression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>irinotecan hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (irinotecan hydrochloride, semaxanib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Campto</other_name>
    <other_name>Camptosar</other_name>
    <other_name>CPT-11</other_name>
    <other_name>irinotecan</other_name>
    <other_name>U-101440E</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>semaxanib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (irinotecan hydrochloride, semaxanib)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>semoxind</other_name>
    <other_name>SU5416</other_name>
    <other_name>Sugen 5416</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (irinotecan hydrochloride, semaxanib)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the colon or rectum

          -  Patients must have locally advanced or metastatic disease not amendable to potentially
             curative treatment

          -  Patients must have an ECOG performance status of 0-2

          -  Men and women of any racial and ethnic group

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (neutrophils + bands) of &gt;= 1,500/ul

          -  Platelet count of &gt;= 100,000/ul

          -  Patients must have a serum creatinine of =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL or a calculated creatinine
             clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min

          -  Serum bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL, regardless of whether patients have liver involvement
             secondary to tumor

          -  SGOT must be =&lt; 3 times institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Patients must be fully recovered from any previous surgery (at least 4 weeks from
             major surgery)

          -  Patients must have recovered from prior radiation therapy (at least 4 weeks from
             radiation)

          -  Fertile patients (male and female) must agree to use a medically effective
             contraceptive method throughout the treatment period and for 3 months following
             cessation of treatment

          -  Patients must provide written informed consent

          -  Patients must have either measurable or evaluable disease; measurable disease is
             defined as at least one bidimensionally measurable lesion &gt;= 1 x 1 cm that is outside
             the field of any prior radiation therapy

          -  In Phase I: Patients with a history of a prior malignancy are eligible for treatment

          -  In Phase II: Patients who have undergone potentially curative therapy for a prior
             malignancy and who have had no evidence of that disease for &gt; 5 years are eligible for
             treatment; adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer does not apply

          -  In the Phase I portion of the study the following eligibility criteria must be met:

               -  Patients must have received no more than two prior chemotherapy regimens (one of
                  which must have contained a fluorinated pyrimidine) for locally advanced or
                  metastatic disease; if a patient progressed while on or within 6 months of
                  adjuvant therapy, the adjuvant regimen will be considered as treatment for
                  metastatic disease

          -  In the Phase II portion of the study the following eligibility criteria must be met:

               -  Patients must have received one and only one prior chemotherapy regimen, which
                  must have contained a fluorinated pyrimidine, for treatment of locally advanced
                  or metastatic disease; if a patient progressed while on or within 6 months of
                  adjuvant therapy, the adjuvant regimen will be considered as treatment for
                  metastatic disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have previously received SU5416, CPT-11, or any topoisomerase I inhibitor

          -  Patients with uncompensated coronary artery disease on electrocardiogram or physical
             examination, or with a history of myocardial infarction, or severe/unstable angina in
             the past 6 months are not eligible

          -  Patients with diabetes mellitus with severe peripheral vascular disease and patients
             who have had a deep venous or arterial thrombosis (including pulmonary embolism)
             within 3 months of entry are not eligible

          -  Patients with known allergy to Cremaphor, or Cremophor-based drug products

          -  Patients with any active or uncontrolled infection

          -  Patients with psychiatric disorders that would interfere with consent or follow-up

          -  CPT-11 is known to have teratogenic potential and may be excreted in milk; the current
             SU5416 Investigator's Brocure indicates that teratogenicity studies have not yet been
             performed; however, other antiangiogenesis drugs, such as thalidomide, are known to
             have teratogenic potential; based on the available data, there is potential for
             significant risk to a developing fetus or breast-feeding child; therefore, pregnant
             women, women who are breast-feeding, and fertile men and women, unless utilizing birth
             control are excluded from this study; a negative pregnancy test must be documented
             during the screening period for women of childbearing potential

          -  Patients with either a prior history of or clinically apparent central nervous system
             metastases or leptomeningeal carcinomatosis disease

          -  Patients with a history of seizures or who are receiving phenytoin, phenobarbital, or
             other antipileptic prophylaxis

          -  Patients with uncontrolled diabetes mellitus

          -  Patients with known Gilbert's Disease (may have excessive CPT-11-induced toxicity)

          -  Patients with any other severe concurrent disease which in the judgement of the
             investigator would make the patient inappropriate for the study

          -  Patients who have received any investigational drug =&lt; 30 days prior to enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Abbruzzese</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 23, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Camptothecin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Semaxinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

