<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00003009</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000065584 (0I-95-1)</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>LAC-USC-0I951</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-G97-1264</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00003009</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Inhaled Interleukin-2 in Treating Patients With Metastatic or Unresectable Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Inhalation of Interleukin-2 (IL-2) in Patients With Metastatic or Unresectable Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Interleukin-2 may stimulate a person's white blood cells to kill cancer cells.
      Giving interleukin-2 in different ways may kill more cancer cells.

      PURPOSE: Phase I trial to study the effectiveness of inhaled interleukin-2 in treating
      patients with metastatic or unresectable cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Define the safe and tolerance of an inhaled interleukin-2 (IL-2) administered
      once or twice a day. II. Determine blood levels of IL-2 and whether there is detectable
      stimulation of immune cells in patients receiving inhalation IL-2. III. Determine whether
      there is any shrinkage of pulmonary lesions of patients treated on this study.

      OUTLINE: This is a two arm, escalating dose study of interleukin-2 (IL-2). In Arm I patients
      in cohorts of 3-6 are administered daily inhalations of IL-2 over 15 minutes on Monday
      through Friday for 4 consecutive weeks. At least 3 patients are treated at each dose level,
      and all patients in a cohort are observed for at least 2 weeks before escalating to a higher
      dose in absence of dose limiting toxicity. Escalation stops when maximum tolerated dose (MTD)
      is determined. In Arm II the initial dose is 25 percent of the MTD determined in Arm I
      administered by inhalation twice daily on Monday through Friday for 4 weeks. Subsequent
      patient cohorts receive doses escalated by 33 percent above the previous dose level.
      Responding patients continue treatment cycles of 4 weeks with 2 weeks of rest until they
      develop progressive disease or intolerable toxicity. Stable patients may stay on treatment
      for a maximum of 4 cycles.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A minimum of 12-15 and a maximum of 30 patients will be accrued for this
      study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Insufficient Accrual
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>February 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2000</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2000</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>aldesleukin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed unresectable or metastatic cancer
        Confirmed by biopsy or fine needle aspiration Tumors must predominantly involve the lung
        Measurable or evaluable disease No lymphomas or leukemias No AIDS associate Kaposi's
        Sarcoma No uncontrolled brain metastases

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: SWOG 0-1 Life expectancy: At
        least 3 months Hematopoietic: WBC at least 4,000/mm3 Platelet count within normal limits
        Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater than 2 times normal Renal: Creatinine no greater than 2.0
        mg/dL Cardiovascular: Adequate cardiovascular system with NYHA Class 0 or I No uncontrolled
        cardiac arrhythmias Pulmonary: FEV1 at least 65% of predicted FVC at least 65% of predicted
        No asthma or bronchial obstruction that would prevent the delivery of IL-2 to all lobes of
        the lung Other: HIV negative No medical or psychological criteria that would make patient
        unable to tolerate the treatment Not pregnant or nursing Adequate contraception required of
        all fertile patients

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: No prior interleukin-2 Prior biologic response
        therapy allowed No chronic use of immunosuppressive medicines Chemotherapy: Prior
        chemotherapy allowed Endocrine therapy: No chronic steroid use Prior hormonal therapy
        allowed Radiotherapy: No prior or concurrent radiotherapy except as palliative to areas of
        painful metastases outside the lung Surgery: Not specified
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond A. Kempf, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USC/Norris Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033-0800</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 16, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 20, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 20, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

