<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00003125</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000065885</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA062500</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA051008</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>GUMC-97118</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-T97-0033</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00003125</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vaccine Therapy, Interleukin-2, and Sargramostim in Treating Patients With Advanced Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Sequential Vaccinations With ALVAC-CEA and Vaccinia-CEA With the Addition of IL-2 and GM-CSF in Patients With CEA Expressing Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Georgetown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Georgetown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Vaccines may make the body build an immune response to kill tumor cells.
      Colony-stimulating factors such as sargramostim may increase the number of immune cells.
      Interleukin-2 may stimulate a person's white blood cells to kill cancer cells. Combining
      vaccine therapy, sargramostim, and interleukin-2 may kill more cancer cells.

      PURPOSE: Randomized phase II trial to study the effectiveness of vaccine therapy,
      sargramostim, and interleukin-2 in treating patients who have advanced tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Evaluate the safety of sequentially administered vaccinia-carcinoembryonic
      antigen (CEA) vaccine and ALVAC-CEA vaccine (CEA-Avipox vaccine) in two schedules and with
      the addition of sargramostim (GM-CSF) plus or minus interleukin-2 (IL-2) in patients with CEA
      expressing tumors. II. Compare the CEA-specific cellular immune response in cancer patients
      randomized to receive a single vaccination with vaccinia-CEA vaccine followed by three boosts
      with ALVAC-CEA vaccine (V-A-A-A) or the reverse vaccination sequence (A-A-A-V). III.
      Determine whether the addition of GM-CSF alone or with IL-2 enhances the immune response to
      sequentially administered vaccinia-CEA vaccine and ALVAC-CEA vaccine. IV. Compare the enzyme
      linked immunosorbent assay ELISPOT with lymphoproliferative and cytotoxicity assays for
      measuring CEA-specific T lymphocyte immune response.

      OUTLINE: This is two-stage, partially randomized study. In stage one, patients are randomized
      to arm I or II. Arm I: Patients receive vaccinia-carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) vaccine
      intradermally on day 1 of course 1 and ALVAC-CEA vaccine (CEA-Avipox vaccine) intramuscularly
      (IM) on day 1 of courses 2-4. Each course lasts 28 days. Arm II: Patients receive ALVAC-CEA
      vaccine (CEA-Avipox vaccine) IM on day 1 of courses 1-3 and vaccinia-CEA vaccine
      intradermally on day 1 of course 4. Each course lasts 28 days. Patients in arms I and II
      continue 28-day courses through month 6 and then receive 3-month courses for 2 years in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. In stage two, patients are enrolled
      successively into arms III and IV. Arm III: Patients receive vaccines according to whichever
      schedule (arm I or II) was found to be superior plus sargramostim (GM-CSF) subcutaneously
      (SC) on days 1-4 of each course. Each course lasts 28 days. Arm IV: Patients receive vaccines
      plus GM-CSF as in arm III and interleukin-2 SC once daily on days 7-11 of each course. Each
      course lasts 28 days. Patients on arms III and IV continue 28-day courses through month 6 and
      then receive 3-month courses for 2 years in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity. If 2 or more patients in either arm III or IV experience dose limiting
      toxicity, accrual into study stops. Otherwise, the best response among the 4 arms is
      determined and further HLA-A2 positive patients are enrolled into that arm so that a total of
      6 HLA-A2 positive patients with advanced disease and 6 HLA-A2 positive patients with NED
      (without radiographic or clinical evidence of tumor) are treated. If more than one regimen is
      equally superior, the least toxic regimen is chosen for further accrual. Patients are
      followed at 28 days following the last vaccination.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A minimum of 24 patients (6 HLA-A2 positive and up to 3 HLA-A2 negative
      patients per arm) will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2004</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2004</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Unspecified Adult Solid Tumor, Protocol Specific</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ALVAC-CEA vaccine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>aldesleukin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sargramostim</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vaccinia-CEA vaccine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed malignancy that is stage IV and/or at
        high risk of recurrence despite standard treatment Stage IV malignancy that is surgically
        rendered free of macroscopic tumor allowed if current available treatment is not likely to
        offer a survival advantage or result in significant palliation If at high risk for
        recurrence, must have an estimated recurrence rate of at least 75% following definitive
        therapy, such as: Postresection of pancreatic cancer Gastric cancer with regional lymph
        node involvement Node positive stage II or stage III esophageal cancer Stage IIIA or IIIB
        non-small cell lung cancer Breast cancer with at least 10 positive axillary nodes Must have
        low tumor burden or no evidence of disease Must have evidence of prior vaccinia (for
        smallpox immunization) Must have CEA expressing type tumor or a serum CEA elevation of 10
        or greater during course of disease No CNS metastases Hormone receptor status: Not
        specified

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Menopausal status: Not specified Performance
        status: ECOG 0-1 Life expectancy: At least 6 months Hematopoietic: Absolute granulocyte
        count at least 1,500/mm3 WBC at least 3,000/mm3 Platelet count at least 100,000/mm3
        Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater than 2 times upper limit of normal (ULN) SGOT and SGPT no
        greater than 4 times ULN Renal: Creatinine no greater than 2.0 mg/dL OR Creatinine
        clearance at least 50 mL/min Other: HIV negative No uncontrolled seizure disorders,
        encephalitis, or multiple sclerosis No history of allergy or untoward reaction to prior
        vaccination with vaccinia virus No other prior or concurrent diagnosis of altered immune
        function, including eczema, atopic dermatitis, or any autoimmune disease such as systemic
        lupus erythematosus, Sjogren's syndrome, scleroderma, myasthenia gravis, Goodpasture's
        syndrome, Addison's disease, Hashimoto's thyroiditis, or active Graves' disease Must be
        maintaining a reasonable state of nutrition, consistent with weight maintenance No frequent
        vomiting or severe anorexia Must be able to avoid close contact with children 3 years or
        younger, pregnant women, individuals with eczema or history of eczema or other open skin
        conditions, or immunosuppressed individuals for at least 2 weeks after each vaccination No
        serious concurrent medical illnesses including inflammatory bowel disease, Crohn's disease,
        ulcerative colitis, or active diverticulitis Not pregnant or nursing Negative pregnancy
        test Fertile patients must use effective contraception during and for at least 6 months
        after study

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Must have recovered from toxic effects of all prior therapy
        Biologic therapy: Prior vaccinia immunization required No concurrent biologic therapy No
        concurrent immunotherapy Chemotherapy: At least 4 weeks since prior chemotherapy (6 weeks
        since prior nitrosoureas or mitomycin) No concurrent chemotherapy Endocrine therapy:
        Physiologic replacement of steroids allowed No concurrent hormonal therapy Radiotherapy: No
        prior radiotherapy to more than 50% of all nodal groups Surgery: At least 3 weeks since any
        prior major surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John L. Marshall, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lombardi Cancer Center, Georgetown University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Naval Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20889-5000</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 24, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>John Marshall, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Georgetown University</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stage IV breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIA breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III gastric cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV gastric cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIB breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II esophageal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III esophageal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIA non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIB non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>unspecified adult solid tumor, protocol specific</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

