<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00000726</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG 015</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>FDA 20D</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>10991</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00000726</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Foscarnet Treatment of Serious CMV Retinitis Infection in Patients With Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Foscarnet Treatment of Serious CMV Retinitis Infection in Patients With Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To explore the safety and usefulness of foscarnet, an antiviral agent, in the treatment of
      cytomegalovirus (CMV) retinitis. Untreated CMV retinitis is a rapidly progressive, blinding
      disease in AIDS patients. The manner in which foscarnet breaks down in the body and the
      effect of increasing periodic intravenous doses are also studied. Foscarnet is active in
      vitro (test tube) against herpes viruses, including CMV, by inhibiting the virus DNA
      polymerases, enzymes necessary for virus replication, without affecting cellular DNA
      polymerases. Opportunistic CMV disease in AIDS is usually seen as retinitis, colitis,
      esophagitis, hepatitis, pancreatitis, encephalitis, or pneumonia. Ganciclovir has been used
      to treat AIDS patients with CMV disease but can cause severe neutropenia (very low neutrophil
      cell counts). Foscarnet does not suppress the production of neutrophils or other leukocytes
      (myelosuppression) and has shown in vitro activity against HIV.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Foscarnet is active in vitro (test tube) against herpes viruses, including CMV, by inhibiting
      the virus DNA polymerases, enzymes necessary for virus replication, without affecting
      cellular DNA polymerases. Opportunistic CMV disease in AIDS is usually seen as retinitis,
      colitis, esophagitis, hepatitis, pancreatitis, encephalitis, or pneumonia. Ganciclovir has
      been used to treat AIDS patients with CMV disease but can cause severe neutropenia (very low
      neutrophil cell counts). Foscarnet does not suppress the production of neutrophils or other
      leukocytes (myelosuppression) and has shown in vitro activity against HIV.

      Treatment is given for a total of 10 weeks with a 2-week induction regimen followed by
      randomization to daily maintenance foscarnet for 8 weeks. If induction therapy is tolerated
      without unexpected toxicity, patients are allowed to self-administer foscarnet at home via
      central venous catheter and may receive up to 11 days of induction therapy by
      self-administration on an outpatient basis. Foscarnet will be administered in open-label
      fashion so that both investigator and patient will know the dose. Within the study, there are
      8 patients who upon entering the 2nd week of maintenance foscarnet therapy are treated with
      zidovudine (AZT).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 1992</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>53</enrollment>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Foscarnet sodium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Exclusion Criteria

        Concurrent Medication:

        Excluded:

          -  Acyclovir.

          -  Zidovudine (AZT).

          -  Any potentially nephrotoxic agent, especially aminoglycosides, pentamidine, or
             amphotericin B.

        Prior Medication:

        Excluded:

          -  Ganciclovir.

          -  Foscarnet.

          -  Excluded within 7 days of study entry:

          -  Any potentially nephrotoxic agent.

          -  Excluded within 14 days of study entry:

          -  Cytomegalovirus hyperimmune globulin in therapeutic doses.

          -  Immunomodulators.

          -  Biologic response modifiers.

          -  Investigational agents.

          -  Amphotericin B maintenance for a systemic mycosis.

        Known allergy to foscarnet.

        Active AIDS-defining opportunistic infection other than cytomegalovirus (CMV) including
        systemic mycosis, pulmonary or neurologic impairment (comatose).

        Patient must be diagnosed as having:

          -  AIDS CDC Group IV.C.

          -  Cytomegalovirus (CMV) retinitis as identified by its characteristic ophthalmoscopic
             appearance and verified by fundus photography.

          -  One pending culture for CMV from blood and urine prior to study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jacobson M</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County - USC Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USC School of Medicine / Norris Cancer Hosp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA CARE Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Francisco AIDS Clinic / San Francisco Gen Hosp</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>941102859</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mem Sloan - Kettering Cancer Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobson MA, Polsky B, Causey D, Davis R, Tong W, O'Donnell JJ, Kuppermann BD, Heinemann MH, Feinberg J, Lizak P, et al. Pharmacodynamic relationship of pharmacokinetic parameters of maintenance doses of foscarnet and clinical outcome of cytomegalovirus retinitis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1994 May;38(5):1190-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8067763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aweeka F, Gambertoglio J, Mills J, Jacobson MA. Pharmacokinetics of intermittently administered intravenous foscarnet in the treatment of acquired immunodeficiency syndrome patients with serious cytomegalovirus retinitis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1989 May;33(5):742-5.</citation>
    <PMID>2546491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobson MA, O'Donnell JJ, Mills J. Foscarnet treatment of cytomegalovirus retinitis in patients with the acquired immunodeficiency syndrome. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 1989 May;33(5):736-41.</citation>
    <PMID>2546490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobson MA, Crowe S, Levy J, Aweeka F, Gambertoglio J, McManus N, Mills J. Effect of Foscarnet therapy on infection with human immunodeficiency virus in patients with AIDS. J Infect Dis. 1988 Oct;158(4):862-5.</citation>
    <PMID>2844921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobson MA, Causey D, Polsky B, Hardy D, Chown M, Davis R, O'Donnell JJ, Kuppermann BD, Heinemann MH, Holland GN, et al. A dose-ranging study of daily maintenance intravenous foscarnet therapy for cytomegalovirus retinitis in AIDS. J Infect Dis. 1993 Aug;168(2):444-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8393058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobson MA, Causey D, Polsky B, Hardy D, Feinberg JE, O'Donnell JJ, Kuppermann BD, Heinemann MH, Holland G, Mills J. Dose-ranging study of daily intravenous (IV) maintenance foscarnet (PFA) therapy (Rx) for cytomegalovirus (CMV) retinitis in AIDS patients (ACTG protocol 015/915). Int Conf AIDS. 1990 Jun 20-23;6(2):113 (abstract no FB96)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobson MA, Causey D, Hardy D, Polsky B, Mills J, Feinberg JE. Tolerance and efficacy of daily intravenous (IV) maintenance foscarnet (PFA) therapy for cytomegalovirus (CMV) retinitis in AIDS patients (ACTG protocol 015). Int Conf AIDS. 1989 Jun 4-9;5:242 (abstract no MBP123)</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 29, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Retinitis</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS-Related Opportunistic Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Foscarnet</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytomegalovirus Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiviral Agents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Retinitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Foscarnet</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Phosphonoacetic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

