<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001774</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>980013</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>98-N-0013</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001774</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vasodilation in Patients With Fabry's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Investigation of Endothelium-Derived Vasodilation in Patients With Fabry's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fabry's disease a genetic disorder (X-linked recessive) due to the absence of the enzyme
      alpha-galactosidase A. The disease is characterized by abnormal collections of glycolipids in
      cells (histiocytes) within blood vessel walls, tumors on the thighs, buttocks, and genitalia,
      decreased sweating, tingling sensations in the extremities, and cataracts. Patients with
      Fabry 's disease die from complications of the kidney, heart, or brain.

      The objective of this study is to test the belief that patients with Fabry's disease have a
      problem with blood vessels becoming larger. The walls of blood vessels contain muscles that
      when they relax the vessel becomes larger. This process is referred to as vasodilation. It is
      controlled by a substance released by cells in blood vessels called EDRF (endothelium-derived
      relaxing factor).

      Several drugs can affect vasodilation. Researchers believe some drugs may work by blocking
      the affect of EDRF. Researchers would like to test the effects of these drugs on the blood
      vessels of normal volunteers and patients with Fabry's disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fabry disease is a systematic genetic disease in which patients have abnormal blood vessels,
      and leads to numerous complications including cerebrovascular strokes. The objective of this
      study is to test the hypothesis that patients with Fabry disease have abnormal
      endothelial-derived vasodilation. If found to be abnormal, endothelial-derived vasodilation
      will serve as a useful clinical outcome measure in the evaluation of the efficacy of specific
      treatment of Fabry disease, and possibly of other causes of cerebrovascular stroke. The
      endothelium modulates vascular tone by the release of contracting and relaxing substances
      that act on the underlying smooth muscle. It has been previously demonstrated that patients
      with essential hypertension have a blunted vascular response to acetylcholine (an
      endothelium-dependent vasodilator). In the present study, we shall analyze the regional
      vascular responses to acetylcholine and sodium nitroprusside alone, and in the presence of
      L-NMMA (an inhibitor of the synthesis of EDRF by endothelial cells) in 12 patients with Fabry
      disease and 12 normal age matched control subjects. We will infuse drugs into the brachial
      artery and will measure the responses of the forearm vasculature by means of strain gauge
      plethysmography. Forearm blood flow and vascular resistance at baseline and after infusion of
      vasoactive drugs, in Fabry patients, will be compared to the responses obtained in the
      healthy control population. This study will be performed with collaboration of Dr. Julio A.
      Panza, Senior Clinical Investigator from the Cardiology Branch, NHLBI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2000</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>48</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Accident</condition>
  <condition>Fabry Disease</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Male patients with the classic form of Fabry disease, aged 18-50.

        Normal male volunteers of the same approximate age will be included as a control.

        No patients or volunteers with hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, diabetes, peripheral
        vascular disease, coagulopathy, or any other disease predisposing to vasculitis or
        Raynaud's phenomenon.

        No volunteers who are taking any kind of medication.

        Must be able to give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panza JA, Quyyumi AA, Brush JE Jr, Epstein SE. Abnormal endothelium-dependent vascular relaxation in patients with essential hypertension. N Engl J Med. 1990 Jul 5;323(1):22-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2355955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Casino PR, Kilcoyne CM, Quyyumi AA, Hoeg JM, Panza JA. The role of nitric oxide in endothelium-dependent vasodilation of hypercholesterolemic patients. Circulation. 1993 Dec;88(6):2541-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8252665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 1999</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Acetylcholine</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood vessel</keyword>
  <keyword>Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Sodium Nitroprusside</keyword>
  <keyword>Fabry Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Normal Volunteer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fabry Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

