<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00006150</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000159</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-I-0159</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00006150</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Clinical Features and Genetics of Hyperimmunoglobulin E Recurrent Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>Natural History, Management, and Genetics of the Hyperimmunoglobulin E Recurrent Infection Syndrome (HIES)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Hyper IgE Syndromes (HIES) are primary immunodeficiencies resulting in eczema and
      recurrent skin and lung infections. Autosomal dominant Hyper IgE syndrome (AD-HIES; Job's
      syndrome) is caused by STAT3 mutations, and is a multisystem disorder with skeletal,
      vascular, and connective tissue manifestations. Understanding how STAT3 mutations cause these
      diverse clinical manifestations is critical to our complete understanding of bone metabolism,
      bronchiectasis, dental maturation, and atherosclerosis. Mutations in DOCK8 cause many cases
      of autosomalrecessive Hyper IgE syndrome. These individuals suffer from extensive viral
      infections as well as have a high incidence of malignancy and mortality. The pathogenesis of
      this disease is being investigated. Therefore, we seek to enroll patients and families with a
      confirmed or suspected diagnosis of HIES syndrome for extensive phenotypic and genotypic
      study as well as disease management. Patients will be carefully examined by a
      multidisciplinary team and followed longitudinally. Through these studies we hope to better
      characterize the clinical presentation of HIES and to be able to identify further genetic
      etiologies, as well as understand the pathogenesis of HIES. We seek to enroll 200 patients
      and 300 relatives.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Hyper IgE Syndromes (HIES) are primary immunodeficiencies resulting in eczema and
      recurrent skin and lung infections. Autosomal dominant Hyper IgE syndrome (AD-HIES; Job's
      syndrome) is caused by STAT3 mutations, and is a multisystem disorder with skeletal,
      vascular, and connective tissue manifestations. Understanding how STAT3 mutations cause these
      diverse clinical manifestations is critical to our complete understanding of bone metabolism,
      bronchiectasis, dental maturation, and atherosclerosis. Mutations in DOCK8 cause many cases
      of autosomalrecessive Hyper IgE syndrome. These individuals suffer from extensive viral
      infections as well as have a high incidence of malignancy and mortality. The pathogenesis of
      this disease is being investigated. Therefore, we seek to enroll patients and families with a
      confirmed or suspected diagnosis of HIES syndrome for extensive phenotypic and genotypic
      study as well as disease management. Patients will be carefully examined by a
      multidisciplinary team and followed longitudinally. Through these studies we hope to better
      characterize the clinical presentation of HIES and to be able to identify further genetic
      etiologies, as well as understand the pathogenesis of HIES. We seek to enroll 300 patients
      and 300 relatives.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 7, 2000</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Job's Syndrome</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients must be referred to the NIH with a diagnosis or a suspicion of Hyper IgE syndrome.
        Family members of probands and patients referred for other immune syndromes that
        demonstrate some of the characteristics of HIES may also be evaluated under this protocol.
        Male and female patients will be accepted. An inclusion age range will be constructed to
        accommodate at-risk infants born into affected families as well as to be able to examine
        the members of extended families. The extent of evaluation will be tailored to the patient
        s needs, age, and conditions. The cutaneous manifestations of HIE are often present at
        birth and need management from that time on.

        Because this is often an AD disorder, it is important to evaluate family members. Family
        members will have labs drawn for genetic testing and additional labs as clinically
        indicated. Selected family members will have EBV cell lines made and all family members
        will receive a genetic-oriented physical examination with close examination of their
        palates, hyper-extensibility, etc. If on this evaluation any information is uncovered which
        suggests abnormalities related to Hyper IgE syndrome, then further workup would include
        chest X-ray or CT, possible spine films, dental evaluation, dermatology consult, and other
        consults or procedures deemed necessary for that particular relative. For the recessive
        forms of HIES, such as DOCK8 deficiency and PGM3 deficiency, family members may be
        evaluated as possible donors if a hematopoietic stem cell transplant is necessary.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Pregnant women are excluded only from any procedure or test that may endanger the pregnancy
        or the fetus due to the risk from radiographic studies, anesthesia, or certain biopsies. We
        have seen flares of skin disease during pregnancy and therefore believe that

        enrolling and following these patients during pregnancy is appropriate.

        Coronary CT angiography will not be performed on any patient with contraindication to IV
        contrast media. This includes patients with: 1) creatinine value of greater than 1.3 mg/dl,
        2) history of multiple myeloma, 3) use of metformin-containing products less than 24 hours
        prior to contrast media, and 4) history of significant allergic reaction to CT contrast
        agents despite the use of premedication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>105 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexandra Freeman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pamela A Welch, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-0449</phone>
    <email>welchp@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alexandra Freeman, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-9045</phone>
    <email>freemaal@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2000-I-0159.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bale JF Jr, Wilson JF, Hill HR. Fatal histiocytic lymphoma of the brain associated with hyperimmunoglobulinemia-E and recurrent infections. Cancer. 1977 Jun;39(6):2386-90.</citation>
    <PMID>326374</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blum R, Geller G, Fish LA. Recurrent severe staphylococcal infections, eczematoid rash, extreme elevations of IgE, eosinophilia, and divergent chemotactic responses in two generations. J Pediatr. 1977 Apr;90(4):607-9.</citation>
    <PMID>839376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buckley RH, Wray BB, Belmaker EZ. Extreme hyperimmunoglobulinemia E and undue susceptibility to infection. Pediatrics. 1972 Jan;49(1):59-70.</citation>
    <PMID>5059313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 1, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 8, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 9, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>IgE</keyword>
  <keyword>Fractures</keyword>
  <keyword>Pneumonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Scoliosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Eczema</keyword>
  <keyword>Job's Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperimmunologobulin E Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>HIE Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Job Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

