<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001185</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>820083</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>82-N-0083</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001185</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of &quot;Post-Polio Syndrome&quot;</brief_title>
  <official_title>Post-Polio Motor Neuron Disease: Clinical, Virological, and Immunological Studies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Polio or poliomyelitis is the disease caused by the poliovirus. The virus attacks cells in
      the spinal cord and causes symptoms of fever, sore throat, headache, vomiting, and stiffness
      of the neck. Patients with polio can have long-term weakness of muscles as a result of the
      damaged cells in the spinal cord. Occasionally, patients that recover from the disease can
      experience a relapse of muscle weakness. This can occur as long as 25-35 years after first
      having polio. The condition is called &quot;post-polio syndrome&quot;.

      Not all nerve cells in the spinal cord are damaged by the poliovirus. Some nerve cells remain
      healthy and take over the work of the damaged cells. Researchers believe that the &quot;post-polio
      syndrome&quot; may be caused by failure of these overworked nerve cells. However, what causes
      these overworked nerve cells to disintegrate is unknown.

      The purpose of this study is to apply specific scientific tests to answer important questions
      about the causes and development of the post-polio syndrome. Researchers will investigate
      possible genetic, immunologic, and physiologic causes of the &quot;post-polio syndrome&quot;. The study
      itself will not provide therapy for patients with the condition, but may lead to the
      development of therapies in the future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      &quot;Post-polio syndrome&quot; defines the new muscle weaknesses and the variety of new difficulties
      with daily living that some patients experience 25-35 years after maximum recovery from acute
      paralytic poliomyelitis. The new weakness appears to be due to disintegration of the distal
      nerve terminals of the surviving motor neurons whose soma has been stressed for years to
      maintain large motor units via excessive distal sprouting. The factors responsible for the
      disintegration of axonal sprouts and manifestation of the new weakness and fatigue are
      unknown. Whether an immune response to the poliovirus, immunogenetic, dysimmune or aging
      factors play a role in the pathogenesis of this process is also unknown.

      The purpose of this protocol is to apply specific neuromuscular, electrophysiological,
      histological, virological, and immunological tests to answer pertinent questions regarding
      the pathogenesis of the post-polio syndrome. Studied patients will undergo a series of
      clinical neuromuscular evaluations, quantitative muscle testing, electromyography including
      single fiber EMG, immunogenetic, viral and immunochemical studies in the serum and spinal
      fluid, muscle biopsy and swallowing evaluation. Although this is not a therapeutic study, the
      information obtained would help us understand the pathogenetic mechanisms of the new weakness
      and could help us design possible therapies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 1982</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 2003</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>360</enrollment>
  <condition>Poliomyelitis</condition>
  <condition>Postpoliomyelitis Syndrome</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA

        Patients with prior history of a well documented acute paralytic poliomyelitis with or
        without development of new neuromuscular symptoms after a minimum of 15 years from the
        acute illness will be studied.

        Patients will be screened in the outpatient clinic and will be studied as inpatients (or,
        if stable, as outpatients) for three day stay.

        Severly disabled patients with unstable respiratory function or those who require intensive
        care nursing or respiratory assistance will be excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dalakas MC, Elder G, Hallett M, Ravits J, Baker M, Papadopoulos N, Albrecht P, Sever J. A long-term follow-up study of patients with post-poliomyelitis neuromuscular symptoms. N Engl J Med. 1986 Apr 10;314(15):959-63.</citation>
    <PMID>3007983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dalakas M. Postpolio syndrome. Curr Opin Rheumatol. 1990 Dec;2(6):901-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2083155</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sonies BC, Dalakas MC. Dysphagia in patients with the post-polio syndrome. N Engl J Med. 1991 Apr 25;324(17):1162-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2011159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Poliomyelitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Motor Neurons</keyword>
  <keyword>Late Viral Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Motor Neuron Firing</keyword>
  <keyword>Immune Defects</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-polio Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-polio Motor Neuron Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Poliomyelitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postpoliomyelitis Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

