<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00003037</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>97-040</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000065659</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-G97-1285</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00003037</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination Chemotherapy as Induction Therapy in Treating Patients With Stage III Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Trial of the Combination of Docetaxel, Gemcitabine and Cisplatin (DGP) as Induction Chemotherapy in Patients With Stage III Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so
      they stop growing or die. Combining more than one drug may kill more tumor cells.

      PURPOSE: Phase I/II trial to study the effectiveness of combination chemotherapy with
      docetaxel, gemcitabine, and cisplatin as induction therapy in treating patients with stage
      III non-small cell lung cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and schedule of docetaxel,
      gemcitabine, and cisplatin as induction chemotherapy in patients with Stage III non-small
      cell lung cancer (NSCLC) scheduled to undergo subsequent surgical resection or irradiation.
      II. Determine the major objective response rate of this combination therapy in these
      patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose escalation study. Docetaxel in administered as a 1 hour IV infusion
      at week 1, 5, and 9. Gemcitabine is administered as a 30 minute IV infusion at weeks 1, 2, 3,
      5, 6, 7, 9, 10, and 11. Cisplatin is administered as a 20 minute IV infusion at weeks 3, 7,
      and 11. In addition, G-CSF is administered subcutaneously on days 2 through 6 of each 28 day
      cycle following each dose of docetaxel. Three patients are entered at each dose level and
      must complete one cycle of therapy. If no patient experiences dose limiting toxicity (DLT),
      then 3 patients are treated at the next higher dose level. If 1 patient experiences DLT, then
      3 more patients are treated at that same dose level. If 2 of 6 patients experience DLT, then
      that dose is declared the maximum tolerated dose (MTD). Once the MTD is determined, the Phase
      II portion of the study begins and additional patients are treated at the dose level just
      below the MTD. Patients who show complete or partial response, or no change, after
      chemotherapy, undergo surgical resection or radiotherapy to remove or reduce their tumor.
      Patients are assessed for disease progression and unacceptable toxicities every 4 weeks till
      end of treatment.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: An estimated 40 patients will be accrued in this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2002</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2002</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>gemcitabine hydrochloride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed Stage III (T1-2 N2-3 M0, T3 N2 M0, or T4
        N0-3 M0) non-small cell lung cancer Must be candidates for either a resection with curative
        intent or definitive thoracic irradiation following induction chemotherapy No malignant
        pericardial or pleural effusions or superior vena cava syndrome Must have measurable or
        evaluable indicator lesions

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: Karnofsky 70-100%
        Hematopoietic: WBC at least 4,000/mm3 Platelet count at least 160,000/mm3 Hepatic:
        Bilirubin no greater than 1.0 mg/dL SGOT and/or SGPT no greater than 1.5 times the upper
        limit of normal Alkaline phosphatase no greater than 5 times the upper limit of normal
        Renal: Creatinine clearance at least 65 mL/min Cardiovascular: Must have stable heart
        rhythm No unstable angina No myocardial infarction within 6 months No clinical evidence of
        congestive heart failure Neurologic: Must have normal auditory function No symptoms of
        peripheral neuropathy Other: No prior malignancy except non-melanoma skin cancer or in situ
        carcinoma of the cervix Not pregnant Adequate contraception required of all fertile
        patients

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: Not specified Chemotherapy: No prior
        chemotherapy Endocrine therapy: Not specified Radiotherapy: No prior radiation therapy
        Surgery: Not specified
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jorge Gomez, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 27, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>stage IIIA non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIB non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

