<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>950140</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>95-AR-0140</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Controlled Trial of Intermittent Fludarabine for Psoriatic Arthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Controlled Trial of Intermittent Fludarabine for Psoriatic Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a placebo controlled study evaluating the role of fludarabine (a nucleoside analog
      targeting both resting and proliferating lymphocytes) in the treatment of moderate to severe
      psoriotic arthritis. Patients should have failed at least one disease modifying antirheumatic
      drug.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The efficacy and toxicity of immunosuppressive therapy using the adenine analogue fludarabine
      will be evaluated in 20 patients with psoriatic arthritis, who have failed or have developed
      intolerable side-effects to at least one disease modifying antirheumatic drug including
      sulfasalazine, gold, methoxypsoralen and long wave ultraviolet A light (PUVA), retinoids,
      methotrexate or cyclosporin. In this double-blind, placebo-controlled trial patients will
      receive a four month course of intravenous fludarabine (30 mg/m(2)/day for 2-3 days every 4
      weeks for a total of four cycles) or placebo by a block randomization procedure to ensure
      groups balanced for disease activity. After a washout period of two months, the patients
      receiving placebo will have the option of crossing over to the fludarabine arm for an
      additional four months of treatment. Disease activity (both skin and joints) will be
      monitored throughout the study. At the end of the study, physician and patient assessment of
      disease activity as well as drug-related toxicities will be analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 2000</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>20</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthritis, Psoriatic</condition>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fludarabine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Ability to provide informed consent to all aspects of the study after full information is
        provided.

        Age equal to or older than 18 years.

        Psoriatic arthritis of more than 6 months duration defined by the following criteria:

        A psoriatic skin lesion (or history of psoriatic skin lesion documented by a physician)
        with or without nail involvement.

        Peripheral arthritis alone or in combination with sacroiliitis. Patients with chest
        expansion less than 2.5 cm or decreased flexion of the cervical and lumbosacral spine
        flexion by 50% or more will be excluded.

        A negative serum test for rheumatoid factor and absence of subcutaneous nodules.

        Radiographic findings (if present) compatible with psoriatic arthritis (&quot;pencil in cup
        lesion,&quot; osteolysis of the terminal phalanx, asymmetrical sacroiliitis, erosive
        oligoarticular arthritis or spinal syndesmophytes).

        Criteria a-c are required for diagnosis whereas criterion d is optional.

        Active arthritis with 3 or more painful or swollen joints considered capable of responding
        to drug therapy and at least 2 of the following:

        Tenderness or pain on movement of at least 3 joints (or periarticular areas).

        30 minutes of morning stiffness (in peripheral joints or in the spine).

        Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) greater than or equal to 28mm/hour or C-reactive
        protein (CRP) greater than 0.8 mg/dl.

        Failure to respond or development of intolerable side effects to at least one of the
        following treatments: sulfasalazine, gold retinoids, PUVA, methotrexate, azathioprine or
        cyclosporin. A waiting period of equal to or greater than 4 weeks after the end of previous
        systemic treatment will be required before initiation of fludarabine treatment. Topical
        treatment for psoriasis (glucocorticoids, tar, anthralin, etc.) should be discontinued 2
        weeks prior to study entry.

        not have seropositive, symmetric polyarthritis.

        Must not have the spondylitic form of psoriatic arthritis (spondylitis alone or in
        combination with shoulder and hip arthritis).

        Must not have arthritis mutilans.

        Must not be receiving glucocorticoids in doses greater than 10mg/day of prednisone.

        Patients must not have acute or chronic infections requiring antimicrobial therapy or
        serious viral (e.g., hepatitis, herpes zoster or HIV infections) or fungal infections.
        Patients with a positive PPD who have not received INH or other antituberculous therapy may
        be excluded if in the opinion of an infectious disease consultant immunosuppressive therapy
        is contraindicated.

        Females must not be pregnant or lactating. Females of childbearing age must be practicing
        birth control.

        No pre-existing malignancy other than basal cell carcinoma. All females must have a
        negative Papanicolaou smear within a 3 month period prior to study entry.

        No history of cerebrovascular accidents, seizure disorder or chronic neurologic disease.

        No history of documented coronary artery disease, cardiomyopathy or dysrhythmia requiring
        therapy.

        No confounding medical illness that in the judgment of the investigators would pose added
        risk for study participants (e.g., chronic hepatic, renal or pulmonary disease (PFTs less
        than 70% of predicted value or DLCO less than 60%) or bone marrow hypoplasia (Hb less than
        10 mg/dl, platelets less than 100.000/dl or WBC less than 3.400/dl).

        No patients who have received alkylating agents for greater than or equal to 1 year.

        No patients with creatinine clearance (CrCl) less than 50 ml/min.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 1999</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Adenine Analogue</keyword>
  <keyword>Apoptosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytokines</keyword>
  <keyword>Psoriasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Synovium</keyword>
  <keyword>Psoriatic Arthritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Psoriatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

