<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00003412</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000066424</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>BIH-L97-0252</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-T98-0002</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00003412</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interleukin-12 in Treating Women With Metastatic Breast Cancer Who Have Received High-Dose Chemotherapy and Peripheral Stem Cell Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study of Post Transplant rhIL-12 High Dose Cyclophosphamide, Thiotepa, and Carboplatin in the Treatment of Metastatic Breast Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Interleukin-12 may kill tumor cells by stopping blood flow to the tumor and by
      stimulating a person's white blood cells to kill breast cancer cells.

      PURPOSE: Phase I trial to study the effectiveness of interleukin-12 in treating women with
      metastatic breast cancer who have received high-dose chemotherapy and peripheral stem cell
      transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the toxic effect profile and maximum tolerated dose of
      interleukin-12 (rhIL-12) in women with advanced breast cancer who have undergone high dose
      chemotherapy with stem cell rescue. II. Determine the effect of rhIL-12 on cellular and
      humoral immune systems following high dose chemotherapy. III. Explore the effect on treatment
      failure of rhIL-12 after high dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose escalation study of interleukin-12 (rhIL-12). RhIL-12 therapy begins
      3-5 weeks after discharge from the chemotherapy/stem cell transplant hospitalization or 2-3
      weeks after completion of posttransplant radiation. Patients receive rhIL-12 subcutaneously
      twice a week for 12 consecutive weeks. Treatment continues in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity. Cohorts of 3-6 patients are treated at each dose level
      of rhIL-12. The maximum tolerated dose is defined as the dose at which no more than 1 of 6
      patients experiences dose limiting toxicity. Patients are followed every 2 months after
      treatment.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Approximately 6-35 patients will be accrued for this study within 1-2
      years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>June 1998</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>recombinant interleukin-12</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically proven stage IV breast cancer presenting as primary
        metastatic disease or with recurrence after an initial diagnosis of localized disease
        Enrollment in protocol for high dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue using the &quot;STAMP V&quot;
        regimen (cyclophosphamide, thiotepa, and carboplatin) No enrollment in research transplant
        protocol whose primary endpoint is response duration or recovery time from toxic effects No
        brain or CNS metastases Hormone receptor status: Not specified

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 to 60 Sex: Female Menopausal status: Not specified
        Performance status: Karnofsky 80-100% Life expectancy: At least 6 months Hematopoietic: WBC
        at least 3,000/mm3 Platelet count at least 100,000/mm3 Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater than
        1.5 times normal SGOT no greater than 2.5 times normal Renal: Creatinine no greater than
        1.8 mg/dL Creatinine clearance at least 60 mL/min Cardiovascular: Systolic ejection
        fraction at least 50% No significant cardiovascular disease or cardiac arrhythmia requiring
        drug or device intervention Pulmonary: DLCO and FEV1 greater than 50% Neurologic: No
        significant peripheral neuropathy or CNS disease Other: Fertile patients must use effective
        contraception Not pregnant or lactating Not HIV positive No concurrent active infections
        requiring IV antibiotic therapy No significant gastrointestinal bleeding or uncontrolled
        peptic ulcer disease No history of inflammatory bowel disease No clinically significant
        autoimmune disease No other serious illness or medical condition

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: See Disease Characteristics Chemotherapy: See
        Disease Characteristics No concurrent chemotherapy Endocrine therapy: No concurrent
        corticosteroids Radiotherapy: No concurrent radiotherapy Surgery: Not specified Other: At
        least 4 weeks since any investigational drugs No concurrent investigational drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Avigan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2001</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 31, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>stage IV breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-12</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

