<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005556</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R29HL056901</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005556</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Retention of Bone Marrow Donors in a National Registry</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To identify factors that affected the National Marrow Donor Program's (NMDP) success in
      retention of bone marrow volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      As bone marrow transplantation becomes one of the preferred treatments for life-threatening
      diseases of the blood, increasing numbers of patients must seek compatible marrow from
      unrelated donors. The low probability of finding a good patient-donor marrow match means that
      between one- to two-thirds of ill patients never locate a donor with perfectly compatible
      marrow. Furthermore, once volunteers are identified as a preliminary match for a patient, 30
      to 40 percent are either unwilling or medically unable to actually donate marrow. Thus,
      volunteer attrition contributes significantly to the problems already inherent in finding a
      suitable donor candidate.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      The study examined the relationship of volunteer characteristics and donor center factors to
      volunteer psychological outcomes during two critical stages in the blood testing process and
      to donor center rates of volunteer cooperation at these stages.

      Longitudinal and cross-sectional survey data were gathered from a total of over 2,900
      potential marrow donors who were at one of two critical decision points in the process
      leading to donation (DR-blood-typing, CT-blood-typing), and from personnel at the 100 NMDP
      donor centers. These data allowed the investigators to (a) describe the distribution and
      interrelationships between donor center structural characteristics and the strategies centers
      utilize for volunteer recruitment and retention, (b) determine which donor center factors
      (both structural and tactical) and volunteer background characteristics best predict positive
      volunteer-specific psychological outcomes at later typing stages, and examine and revise
      models of individual volunteer-specific outcomes and aggregate across-center retention rates.

      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1997</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2003</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Bone Marrow Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Blood Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Galen Switzer</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dew MA, Switzer GE, DiMartini AF, Matukaitis J, Fitzgerald MG, Kormos RL. Psychosocial assessments and outcomes in organ transplantation. Prog Transplant. 2000 Dec;10(4):239-59; quiz 260-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11232552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Switzer GE, Dew MA, Goycoolea JM, Myaskovsky L, Abress L, Confer DL. Attrition of potential bone marrow donors at two key decision points leading to donation. Transplantation. 2004 May 27;77(10):1529-34.</citation>
    <PMID>15239616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myaskovsky L, Switzer GE, Dew MA, Goycoolea JM, Confer DL, Abress L. The association of donor center characteristics with attrition from the national marrow donor registry. Transplantation. 2004 Mar 27;77(6):874-80.</citation>
    <PMID>15077030</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2004</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 13, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

