<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4288</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL052080</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anger and Cardiovascular Risk in Urban Youth</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To examine anger and cardiovascular disease risk in urban youth. The project studied patterns
      of hemodynamic responses to social and nonsocial stressors, ambulatory blood pressure (BP),
      fasting insulin, fasting glucose, lipid profiles, and central obesity in adolescents from a
      wide range of socioeconomic status (SES) backgrounds.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Urban adolescents at high risk for cardiovascular disease (CVD) exhibit a pattern of
      hemodynamic responses that: (a) is evoked by social encounters that arouse anger,
      defensiveness, and distrust; (b) appears related to increased insulin resistance; (c) is more
      pronounced in males and African Americans; and (d) may constitute a pathway via which chronic
      exposure to stressful social environments increases CVD risk.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      There were four studies. Study 1 in the first two years measured hemodynamics in 200 subjects
      to test the hypothesis that hostile distrust was associated with increased total peripheral
      resistance (TPR) response to social challenge, and that adolescents exhibiting this response
      pattern had elevated levels of ambulatory BP, fasting insulin, glucose, blood lipids, and
      central obesity. Study 2 followed 200 subjects for four years to determine if defensive
      hostility and distrust were related to tracking at higher levels of BP (measured every 6
      months), and insulin/ glucose/ cholesterol (measured once per year). Study 3 in years 3 and 4
      evaluated the influence of race on the cross-situational consistency of hostile distrust/BP
      by measuring the latter responses in 200 adolescents during structured encounters with a
      friend of the same race and sex, an unfamiliar same-race peer, and an unfamiliar other-race
      peer (black or white). Study 4 evaluated video and audiotape recordings from Studies 1 and 3
      to test the hypothesis that distrustful individuals expressed more hostile affect in
      encounters with others, elicited more negative treatment, were perceived as hostile
      regardless of observer race or gender, and thus experienced chronic, health-damaging
      interpersonal stress. Study 4 data were used to examine the possibility that hostile distrust
      is related to exposure to crime, poverty, and racial discrimination.

      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1995</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 1999</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ewart CK, Jorgensen RS, Kolodner KB. Sociotropic cognition moderates blood pressure response to interpersonal stress in high-risk adolescent girls. Int J Psychophysiol. 1998 Mar;28(2):131-42.</citation>
    <PMID>9545651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ewart CK, Suchday S. Discovering how urban poverty and violence affect health: development and validation of a Neighborhood Stress Index. Health Psychol. 2002 May;21(3):254-62. Erratum in: Health Psychol. 2002 Sep;21(5):458..</citation>
    <PMID>12027031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2002</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

