<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005903</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000145</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-N-0145</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005903</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Continuously Infused Recombinant-Methionyl Human Glial Cell Line-Derived Neurotrophic Factor (GDNF) to Treat Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dose-Escalation Trial of Continuously Infused Recombinant-Methionyl Human Glial Cell Line-Derived Neurotrophic Factor for the Treatment of PSP</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the safety and effectiveness of an experimental drug called GDNF
      delivered through an investigational device to treat progressive supranuclear palsy (PSP).
      The drug will be administered directly into the brain through catheters attached to an
      infusion pump implanted in the abdomen. The study will evaluate 1) if the drug is safe and
      well tolerated when given by this method; 2) the performance of the catheters and pump
      system, and 3) the effects of GDNF on PSP symptoms.

      PSP is a rare neurological disease that causes eye movement dysfunction, muscle rigidity,
      slowness of movement, swallowing, speech, emotional, cognitive and personality problems.
      Patients 35 to 75 years old with PSP may be eligible for this study. Candidates will be
      screened at the National Institutes of Health outpatient clinic in Bethesda, MD, with a
      medical history, physical examination, neurological and neuropsychiatric evaluations, blood
      tests, electrocardiogram, CT scan of the brain, and baseline studies including a special eye
      examination, evaluation of symptoms, lumbar puncture (spinal tap) and psychiatric interview.

      Patients enrolled in the study will undergo surgery to place two catheters into the brain and
      two infusion pumps under the skin in the upper abdomen. The surgery will be performed at
      Vanderbilt University Medical Center in Nashville, TN. It will be done under general
      anesthesia and will require a 3 day hospitalization. Within 24 hours after the surgery, a CT
      scan of the brain will be done to ensure the catheters are properly placed. Patients return
      to NIH two weeks after surgery for post-surgery examination and treatment initiation.

      All patients will receive continuous infusions of GNDF through one catheter and placebo (an
      inactive salt solution) through the other for 6 months. Half of the patients will receive
      placebo in the right side of the brain and GNDF in the left, and half will receive GNDF in
      the right side of the brain and placebo in the left. All patients will also undergo the
      following procedures:

      Brief physical examination, and evaluation of symptoms and adverse side effects - every 2
      weeks

      Blood and urine tests - every 2 weeks for the first 2 months and then every 8 weeks until the
      end of the study

      CT scan to check catheter placement - weeks 9 and 27

      Thorough evaluation of symptoms - before beginning treatment and weeks 1, 5, 9, 17 and 27

      Neuropsychiatric evaluation - week 27

      Special eye examination - weeks 1 and 27

      Lumbar puncture - week 27

      Additional blood tests to measure drug concentration and antibodies - 6 times during the
      study

      In addition, some patients may be asked to have positron emission tomography (PET) scans or a
      single photon emission tomography (SPECT) scan, or both.

      The potential benefit of GDNF is unknown. In studies with rats and monkeys, GNDF increased
      the number and size of brain cells containing the chemical messenger dopamine and some
      movement and balance problems were lessened. Earlier studies of GDNF infused into the
      ventricles of patients with Parkinson's disease showed no benefit and no serious harm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The safety and initial efficacy of the unilateral intralenticular infusion of
      recombinant-methionyl human glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor (r-metHuGDNF) will be
      compared with the contralateral intralenticular infusion of a placebo solution, both
      continuously administered using chronically implanted catheters and pumps in up to 10
      patients with progressive supranuclear palsy. Safety will be evaluated by analyzing implant-,
      post-implant-, and treatment-emergent adverse events, clinical laboratory test results, and
      disease status. Efficacy will be studied by comparing left and right sided neurologic
      function using validated clinical scales as well as by putative surrogate biochemical and
      radiographic measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>15</enrollment>
  <condition>Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GDNF &amp; Synchro Med Infusion System</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Diagnosis of PSP with bilateral symptoms based on medical history and neurologic
             examination in accordance with NINDS criteria. Those evidencing ratable limb
             dysfunction bilaterally as well as a past history levodopa responsivity will be
             especially sought.

          2. PSP will be considered clinically to be at a moderate to moderately advanced stage
             (PSP Staging System grade BB - DD), associated with ratable parkinsonian signs in the
             limbs bilaterally and a Hoehn and Yahr grade of 3 - 5.

          3. Men or nonpregnant women age 35 to 75 years. Women of childbearing potential must have
             a negative human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG) test result immediately before (within
             48 hours) catheter and pump implantation and repeated again immediately before (within
             48 hours) the start of drug infusion; men and women of childbearing potential must
             practice adequate contraception during the course of the study.

          4. Before any study-specific procedures are performed, the subject and their designated
             representative must give signed informed consent for their participation. All patients
             must sign a Durable Power of Attorney (DPA). Device implantation must occur within 60
             days after a subject consents to participate in the study.

          5. The subject is medically able to undergo the surgical procedures required to implant
             bilateral pumps and intracranial catheters using stereotactic procedures.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Treatment with levodopa, dopamine agonists or any other antiparkinsonian medications.

          2. Presence of clinically significant psychosis or hallucinations.

          3. Any disorder that precludes a surgical procedure (e.g., bleeding diathesis, signs of
             sepsis or inadequately treated infection) alters wound healing or renders bilateral
             catheter and infusion pump implants unsuitable.

          4. Any history of clinically significant head trauma or cerebrovascular disease or recent
             history (within previous 2 years) of drug or alcohol abuse.

          5. A computed tomography (CT) scan or magnetic resonance image (MRI) of the brain within
             3 months before the implantation procedure that indicates the presence of a central
             nervous system abnormality that may interfere with the assessments of safety or
             biologic effect in this protocol, or represent a surgical risk to the subject.

          6. The presence of an intracranial shunt or catheter system other than the one used in
             this protocol.

          7. Any medical disability, condition or laboratory abnormality (e.g., severe degenerative
             arthritis, compromised nutritional state, body weight less than 15% of ideal, Na less
             than 130 (grade 3 or above), cardiovascular disease) that would be deemed likely to
             increase risk of participation in the protocol or interfere with assessment of the
             safety and biologic effect of study materials, the chronic implantation of catheters
             and infusion pumps, or would compromise the ability of the subject to give informed
             consent.

          8. Known allergy to E coli-derived products or history of anaphylaxis.

          9. Treatment with an investigational agent or used an investigational device within 60
             days before the first dose of study material, other than those described in this
             protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Litvan I. The clinical and pathologic hallmarks of progressive supranuclear palsy. Curr Opin Neurol. 1997 Aug;10(4):346-50. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9266160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Santacruz P, Uttl B, Litvan I, Grafman J. Progressive supranuclear palsy: a survey of the disease course. Neurology. 1998 Jun;50(6):1637-47.</citation>
    <PMID>9633705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pahwa R. Progressive supranuclear palsy. Med Clin North Am. 1999 Mar;83(2):369-79, v-vi. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10093583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 7, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Parkinsonism</keyword>
  <keyword>Trophic Factor</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurodegenerative Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Supranuclear Palsy, Progressive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

