<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001937</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000014</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-C-0014</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001937</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing the Effectiveness of Fluconazole and a New Medicine (FK463) in Preventing Fungal Infections in Bone Marrow Transplant Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III, Randomized, Double-Blind, Comparative Trial of FK463 Versus Fluconazole for Prophylaxis of Fungal Infections in Patients Undergoing a Hematopoetic Stem Cell Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fever and infection are serious complications of cancer treatment such as bone marrow
      transplant, especially when white blood cell counts are low. When the number of white blood
      cells is below 500, the person has a condition called neutropenia and has a high risk of
      developing an infection. At the first sign of fever, antibiotics are started. However,
      antibiotics do not kill fungus germs, and fungal infections may be difficult to treat. Thus,
      the prevention of fungal infections in this population is important. The only medicine
      approved for prevention of fungal infections is fluconazole, which prevents some but not all
      types of such infections. A new antifungal medication called FK463 works against more types
      of fungal infections than fluconazole does. This study will compare the effectiveness,
      safety, and tolerance of FK463 as compared with fluconazole.

      Eight hundred patients will be enrolled in this study. They will be randomly assigned to
      receive either fluconazole or FK463. Before the medicine is begun, a physical exam as well as
      a blood sample, mouth swab, urine sample, and chest x-ray will be done. The fluconazole or
      FK463 will be administered once a day for one hour into the bloodstream through a catheter in
      the vein. Blood tests will be taken twice a week. Cultures from the blood, mouth, and urine
      will be taken throughout the study. X-rays and CT scans will only be taken if a fungal
      infection is suspected. If fever develops, blood will be drawn to check for fungi. If fever
      and neutropenia continue for more than 4 days, FK463 or fluconazole will be stopped and a
      standard medication called amphotericin B will be started.

      Both FK463 and fluconazole will be administered until white blood cell count returns to
      greater than 500 (signifying recovery from neutropenia), or up to 42 days after
      transplantation. Patients will be evaluated 4 weeks after the medicine is stopped.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to determine the efficacy and safety of FK463 versus
      fluconazole in preventing fungal infections in patients undergoing an autologous (for
      hematologic malignancies) or allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant. This is a Phase
      III, multicenter, randomized, double-blind study in patients six months of age and older.
      Study drug, either FK463 at 50 mg/day (1.0 mg/kg/day in patients weighing less than 50 kg) or
      fluconazole at 400 mg/day (8 mg/kg/day in patients weighing less than 50 kg), will be
      administered intravenously once daily in a blinded manner. Study drug will continue until
      neutrophil recovery (defined as a post nadir absolute neutrophil count (ANC) of greater than
      or equal to 500/mm3). Patients who develop a proven, probable, or suspected (requires
      empirical antifungal therapy) fungal infection will be discontinued from the prophylactic
      regimen. The maximum time the patient may receive study drug is 42 days post transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2000</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>800</enrollment>
  <condition>Aspergillosis</condition>
  <condition>Candidiasis</condition>
  <condition>Fungemia</condition>
  <condition>Mycoses</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FK463</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluconazole</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Informed consent of the patient or legally authorized representative must be obtained prior
        to entry.

        Verbal assent will be obtained from minors capable of understanding.

        Patients may be of either gender. Females of childbearing potential must have a negative
        pregnancy test obtained within 14 days prior to the first dose of study drug.

        Patients greater than or equal to 6 months of age.

        Patients at risk of systemic fungal infections due to their immunocompromised state due to
        one of the following:

        Patient with a hematologic malignancy undergoing an autologous hematopoietic stem cell
        transplant;

        Any patient undergoing an allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant.

        Patients must have sufficient venous access to permit administration of study drug and
        monitoring of safety variables.

        No patients who are pregnant or nursing. Females of childbearing potential must avoid
        becoming pregnant by abstinence or barrier methods of birth control while receiving
        antifungal agents.

        No patients with moderate or severe liver disease, as defined by:

        AST or ALT greater than 5 times upper limit of normal (ULN), OR;

        Total bilirubin greater than 2.5 times ULN.

        No patients with evidence of a deeply invasive or disseminated fungal infection at time of
        enrollment.

        No patients who have received systemic antifungal agents within 72 hours prior to the first
        dose of study drug.

        No patients receiving an autologous transplant for nonhematologic malignancies.

        No patients known to be infected with HIV due to the lack of data on drug interaction
        between highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) and FK463.

        No patients previously randomized in this study.

        No patients with a history of anaphylaxis attributed to azole compounds or the echinocandin
        class or antifungals.

        No patients with a concomitant medical condition, in the opinion of the investigator and/or
        medical monitor, whose participation may create an unacceptable additional risk for the
        patient.

        No patients receiving another investigational drug other than for the treatment of cancer
        or supportive care.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goodman JL, Winston DJ, Greenfield RA, Chandrasekar PH, Fox B, Kaizer H, Shadduck RK, Shea TC, Stiff P, Friedman DJ, et al. A controlled trial of fluconazole to prevent fungal infections in patients undergoing bone marrow transplantation. N Engl J Med. 1992 Mar 26;326(13):845-51.</citation>
    <PMID>1542320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slavin MA, Osborne B, Adams R, Levenstein MJ, Schoch HG, Feldman AR, Meyers JD, Bowden RA. Efficacy and safety of fluconazole prophylaxis for fungal infections after marrow transplantation--a prospective, randomized, double-blind study. J Infect Dis. 1995 Jun;171(6):1545-52.</citation>
    <PMID>7769290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pannuti C, Gingrich R, Pfaller MA, Kao C, Wenzel RP. Nosocomial pneumonia in patients having bone marrow transplant. Attributable mortality and risk factors. Cancer. 1992 Jun 1;69(11):2653-62.</citation>
    <PMID>1315207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 1999</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Aspergillosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Candidiasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Fungal Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Fungemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Prophylactic Antifungal Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Candidiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aspergillosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fungemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Micafungin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

