<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00002866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MA15</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CAN-NCIC-MA15</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-V96-1063</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000065138</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00002866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Docetaxel and Epirubicin With and Without G-CSF in Treating Women With Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A PHASE I/II STUDY OF DOCETAXEL AND EPIRUBICIN AS FIRST LINE THERAPY FOR METASTATIC BREAST CANCER</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NCIC Clinical Trials Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Canadian Cancer Trials Group</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so
      they stop growing or die. Colony-stimulating factors such as G-CSF may increase the number of
      immune cells found in bone marrow or peripheral blood and may help a person 's immune system
      recover from the side effects of chemotherapy.

      PURPOSE: Phase I/II trial to study the effectiveness of docetaxel and epirubicin with and
      without G-CSF in treating women with metastatic breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the maximum tolerated dose and recommended phase II dose of
      docetaxel in combination with epirubicin and filgrastim (G-CSF) as first-line therapy in
      women with metastatic breast cancer (phase II closed as of 03/27/2000). II. Determine the
      pharmacokinetic profile of docetaxel and epirubicin in these patients. III. Evaluate the
      toxicity of this regimen given at the recommended phase II dose. IV. Determine the response
      rate and duration of response in patients treated with this regimen.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter, dose-escalation study of epirubicin and docetaxel. Patients
      receive epirubicin IV over 15 minutes followed by docetaxel IV over 60 minutes on day 1.
      Patients also receive filgrastim (G-CSF) subcutaneously on days 4-13. Treatment continues
      every 3 weeks for at least 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity. Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of epirubicin and docetaxel until
      the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is determined. The MTD is defined as the dose in which at
      least 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity. Additional patients will be accrued
      to receive treatment at the recommended phase II dose (phase II closed as of 03/27/2000).
      Patients are followed at 1 month and then every 3 months for survival.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Approximately 15-20 patients will be accrued within 4-5 months for the
      phase I portion of the study. A total of 15-30 patients will be accrued within 7-8 months for
      the phase II portion of the study (closed as of 03/27/2000).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Neutropenia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>filgrastim</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>epirubicin hydrochloride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically or cytologically confirmed breast cancer Newly
        diagnosed or progressive metastatic disease with at least 1 metastatic target lesion No
        known clinical brain or leptomeningeal metastasis Phase I entry: Measurable and/or
        evaluable disease with an indicator lesion outside prior radiotherapy field Phase II entry:
        (closed as of 03/27/2000) Bidimensionally measurable disease with an indicator lesion
        outside prior radiotherapy field At least 1 x 1 cm on chest x-ray At least 2 x 2 cm on CT
        scan or ultrasound Skin lesion or node at least 1 x 1 cm No bone-only lesion Hormone
        receptor status: Not specified

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 16 and over Sex: Female Menopausal status: Not specified
        Performance status: ECOG 0-2 Hematopoietic: Absolute granulocyte count at least 2,000/mm3
        Platelet count at least 100,000/mm3 Hemoglobin at least 10 g/dL Hepatic: Bilirubin no
        greater than the upper limit of normal (ULN) AST/ALT no greater than 1.5 times ULN Alkaline
        phosphatase no greater than 2.5 times ULN (no greater than 5.0 times ULN if AST/ALT normal)
        Renal: Creatinine no greater than 1.5 times ULN Cardiovascular: Left ventricular ejection
        fraction at least 50% at rest by MUGA or echocardiogram No congestive heart failure No
        angina pectoris (even if controlled) No myocardial infarction within the past year No
        uncontrolled arrhythmia No uncontrolled hypertension Other: No active infection No grade 2
        or greater symptomatic peripheral neuropathy No significant neurologic or psychiatric
        disorder, including dementia or seizures No peptic ulcer, unstable diabetes mellitus, or
        other contraindication to dexamethasone No prior malignancy except nonmelanomatous skin
        cancer or excised carcinoma in situ of the cervix Not pregnant or nursing Fertile patients
        must use effective contraception Geographically accessible

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: No concurrent supportive colony-stimulating
        factors (e.g., filgrastim (G -CSF)) (Prophylactic treatment during the second step of phase
        I allowed) Chemotherapy: Phase I patients: At least 12 months since prior adjuvant
        chemotherapy Prior neoadjuvant chemotherapy allowed Prior cumulative dose of doxorubicin no
        greater than 300 mg/m2 Prior cumulative dose of epirubicin no greater than 500 mg/m2 If
        epirubicin dose level at least 90 mg/m2: Prior cumulative dose of doxorubicin no greater
        than 200 mg/m2 Prior cumulative dose of epirubicin no greater than 300 mg/m2 Phase II
        patients: (closed as of 03/27/2000) No prior neoadjuvant or adjuvant chemotherapy regimen
        other than cyclophosphamide, methotrexate, and fluorouracil, or doxorubicin and
        cyclophosphamide given for a maximum of 4 courses All patients: No prior chemotherapy for
        metastatic disease No prior taxanes Endocrine therapy: Prior hormonal therapy in the
        adjuvant and/or metastatic setting allowed if subsequent disease progression No more than 2
        prior hormonal therapy regimens for metastatic disease No concurrent corticosteroids
        (except for premedication or hypersensitivity reaction) Radiotherapy: See Disease
        Characteristics At least 4 weeks since prior radiotherapy (unless single fractions for
        palliation) Concurrent local palliative radiotherapy for control of bone pain or for other
        reasons with no curative intent allowed Concurrent whole-brain radiotherapy for brain
        metastasis allowed No concurrent radiotherapy to sole measurable lesion Surgery: Not
        specified Other: No other concurrent investigational drugs or anticancer therapy No
        concurrent preventive IV antibiotics
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maureen E. Trudeau, BSc, MA, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Toronto Sunnybrook Regional Cancer Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint John Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint John</city>
        <state>New Brunswick</state>
        <zip>E2L 4L2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Sunnybrook Regional Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital - Toronto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's College Campus, Sunnybrook and Women's College Health Science Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 1B6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hotel Dieu de Montreal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2W 1T8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 27, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>stage IV breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>neutropenia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neutropenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epirubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

