<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00001925</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990030</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-N-0030</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00001925</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Alcohol on Tremors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Alcohol on Physiologic and Pathologic Tremors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Tremors are involuntary movements of a part or parts of the body that occur because of
      alternating contraction and relaxation of muscles. The causes behind most tremors are poorly
      understood.

      Some studies suggest tremors could be caused by abnormalities in a particular area of the
      brain called the olivary nucleus. Researchers believe that the cells making up the olivary
      nucleus may be responsible for generating a central rhythm of the body and may therefore also
      be responsible for the generation of tremors.

      Consumption of alcohol has been known to reduce tremors in some patients. Researchers believe
      that the alcohol may work directly on the cells of the olivary nucleus. As a result,
      researchers would like to determine the effects of alcohol on three different kinds of
      tremors (physiological, symptomatic palatal, and essential palatal).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The pathophysiology and anatomical basis of most tremors remains poorly understood. One
      particular theory of essential tremor, the olivary hypothesis, has gained support from
      various studies. These studies point to the olivary nucleus as possible central rhythm
      generator. Cells in the olivary nucleus show spontaneous rhythmic discharges that can be
      suppressed by alcohol. Since alcohol is known to suppress tremor in some patients with
      essential tremor, one can theorize that it is through its effect on the olivary nucleus; that
      is, the inferior olive is the generator of the tremor. Given this assumption, we intend to
      study the effect of alcohol on three different kinds of tremor: the 8-12 Hz component of
      physiological tremor, symptomatic palatal tremor and essential palatal tremor. Our hypothesis
      is that the central generator of each of these types of tremor lies in the inferior olive and
      that the ingestion of alcohol should reduce the amplitude of the tremor, similar to the
      effect of alcohol seen in essential tremor.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>23</enrollment>
  <condition>Tremor</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alcohol</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A total of 20 subjects will be enrolled in the study. 10 normal subjects will be enrolled
        in the study. All will have an 8-12 Hz component of physiologic tremor as determined by
        neurophysiologic studies. Patients will have a prominent 8-12 Hz spike on accelerometry
        recordings that is associated with an EMG spike at the same frequency.

        5 patients with essential palatal tremor and 5 patients with symptomatic palatal tremor
        will be included.

        All participants must be a minimum of 21 years of age.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        The presence of any medical condition, such as liver disease, history or family history of
        alcoholism, that can reasonably be expected to subject the patient to unwarranted risk or
        compromise the value of the data.

        Any patient with pathologic tremor, such as parkinsonian rest tremor, essential tremor, or
        tremor secondary to medications or structural brain lesions.

        Any clinically significant laboratory abnormalities.

        Lack of effective contraception.

        Patients who are pregnant.

        Inability to understand the nature of the study or its procedures.

        Persons under the age of 21, who are not of legal age to consume alcohol in Maryland.

        Patients taking any psychoactive medications including certain cough or cold medicine
        preparations.

        No one will be excluded or discriminated against based on the grounds of race, creed,
        gender, color, or national origin. Every attempt will be made to include women and
        minorities in the study population.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hömberg V, Hefter H, Reiners K, Freund HJ. Differential effects of changes in mechanical limb properties on physiological and pathological tremor. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1987 May;50(5):568-79.</citation>
    <PMID>3585382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deuschl G, Krack P, Lauk M, Timmer J. Clinical neurophysiology of tremor. J Clin Neurophysiol. 1996 Mar;13(2):110-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8849966</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lutes J, Lorden JF, Beales M, Oltmans GA. Tolerance to the tremorogenic effects of harmaline: evidence for altered olivo-cerebellar function. Neuropharmacology. 1988 Aug;27(8):849-55.</citation>
    <PMID>2851115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2002</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 1999</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 1999</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Inferior Olives</keyword>
  <keyword>Calcium Channels</keyword>
  <keyword>Accelerometry</keyword>
  <keyword>Electromyography</keyword>
  <keyword>Palatal Tremor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tremor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

