<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00004990</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>000100</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00-DK-0100</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00004990</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Once-A-Month Steroid Treatment for Patients With Focal Segmental Glomerulosclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pulse Dexamethasone in Focal Segmental Glomerulosclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the safety and effectiveness of a monthly dosing regimen of
      dexamethasone-a strong steroid medication-to treat patients with focal segmental
      glomerulosclerosis (FSGS). Patients with this disease have kidney fibrosis (scarring) and
      proteinuria (excessive excretion of protein in the urine) that, in about half of the patients
      eventually requires kidney dialysis or transplant. Currently, the most effective treatment
      for FSGS is high-dose steroids (prednisone) taken daily for 4 to 6 months. However, only
      about 30 percent of patients respond to this treatment, and it causes serious side effects in
      many patients. Other drugs, such as cyclosporin and cyclophosphamide, improve proteinuria in
      even fewer patients (about 10 percent) and also have serious side effects. This study will
      explore whether a monthly pulse dose of steroids will achieve disease remission with less
      toxicity.

      Adults and children with FSGS who: 1) have not received steroid treatment, or 2) could not
      tolerate daily steroid treatment, or 3) relapsed after conventional steroid treatment may be
      eligible for this study. Those enrolled will take dexamethasone by mouth for 4 days every 4
      weeks for a total of 8 months. Patients will undergo various tests before treatment starts
      (baseline), during the course of treatment, and in follow-up visits to evaluate the effects
      of treatment as follows:

        1. Review of kidney biopsy, medical evaluation, measurement of total daily urine protein
           excretion and kidney function, psychiatric testing for depression or other mood disorder

        2. Measurements of blood pressure, blood chemistries and urine protein excretion - monthly
           during treatment

        3. Questionnaire about the effects of treatment, if any, on mood and feelings - monthly
           during treatment

        4. Photographs of the face and body (in underwear or shorts and tank top) to evaluate body
           fat distribution- baseline and 8 months

        5. Eye examinations for cataracts and glaucoma - baseline and 8 months

        6. Bone density scan (DEXA scan) of the lower spine and hip - baseline, 4 and 12 months

        7. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the hips

        8. Psychological evaluation and quality of life evaluation - baseline, 1, 2 and 8 months

        9. Blood tests for adrenal gland function - baseline, 4 and 8 months

       10. Blood and urine tests - 10, 12, 15, and 18 months

      Patients who achieve remission (whose urine protein levels decrease to normal) before
      completing the 8 months of dexamethasone will take one more dose and then stop therapy, but
      continue with follow-up. Patients who achieve remission but relapse may be offered a second
      course of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness and toxicity of an alternative
      steroid dosing regimen for patients with focal segmental glomerulosclerosis (FSGS), using a
      pilot study design that will enroll 20 patients. Although the literature reports variable
      steroid responsiveness, remission rates of up to 30-40 percent have recently been reported in
      nephrotic adult patients treated with daily prednisone at 1 mg/kg/day for at least 4 months,
      followed by a taper over 3-4 months. Such a prolonged and aggressive steroid course is
      fraught with significant morbidity, but this approach has been advocated by some authors
      because of the poor prognosis for renal survival in nephrotic patients with FSGS who do not
      achieve remission with steroid treatment. We plan to test an eight month course of high dose
      steroid therapy administered in monthly pulses instead of daily doses, for comparable
      efficacy in achieving remission, and for the occurrence of adverse steroid side effects. We
      plan to enroll patients with nephrotic syndrome due to biopsy-proven FSGS, who have either
      not been treated, or have responded to conventional steroid dosing regimens and relapsed. We
      plan to treat them with monthly oral pulses of dexamethasone (40-60 mg/d x 4 days), for 8
      months. The primary endpoint will be induction of complete remission, defined as urine
      protein less than 300 mg/d. Patients will also be evaluated for manifestations of steroid
      toxicity. Patients will be seen in follow up at intervals up to 24 months following study
      entry. If this study suggests that remission of nephrotic syndrome can be attained with this
      regimen, and with an acceptable toxicity profile, we will plan a randomized controlled trial
      of this regimen compared with daily or alternate day oral steroids.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>20</enrollment>
  <condition>Glomerulonephritis</condition>
  <condition>Nephrotic Syndrome</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Adults and children.

        Biopsy proven FSGS, including idiopathic FSGS and collapsing FSGS, but excluding
        HIV-associated FSGS and secondary FSGS associated with morbid obesity, sickle cell anemia,
        reflux nephropathy, chronic tubular injury, congenital renal anomalies, and reduced nephron
        mass.

        Glomerular filtration rate will be estimated using 4 variable MDRD GFR equation, which
        incorporates age, race, gender, and serum creatinine.

        If disease has been present less than or equal to 1 year, estimated GFR must be greater
        than or equal to 40 ml/min.

        If disease has been present greater than or equal to 1 year, estimated GFR must be greater
        than or equal to 60 ml/min.

        Nephrotic range proteinuria, defined as urine protein greater than or equal to 3.5 g/1.73
        m(2)/d.

        Patients who received steroids for FSGS and who entered complete remission but have
        relapsed with nephrotic range proteinuria will be eligible.

        If hypertensive, adequate blood pressure control (target BP less than or equal to 130/80 mm
        Hg at greater than 75% of measurement in adults).

        Patients must have been taking an angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor or angiotensin
        receptor antagonist for at least 6 weeks, unless intolerant of these medications.

        Women with child-bearing potential must maintain an effective birth control regimen (oral
        contraceptive, intrauterine device, barrier plus spermicide).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Inability to give informed consent or cooperate with study.

        Poorly controlled diabetes (as defined by hemoglobin A1C of greater than or equal to 8.5 on
        entry screening, or daily insulin requirement of greater than or equal to 100 units) or
        hypertension (defined as systolic BP consistently greater than 160 and/or diastolic BP
        consistently greater than 100 on three or more drugs).

        Evidence of chronic or occult infection. Specifically, must not have evidence of active
        hepatitis B, hepatitis C, HIV or untreated mycobacterial infection.

        Current or prior use of cytotoxic agents or cyclosporin for FSGS. If previously treated
        with these agents for a non-renal indication, therapy must have concluded at least 12
        months prior to study.

        Existence of any other condition which would complicate the implementation or
        interpretation of the study.

        History of steroid-induced psychiatric disorder, known avascular necrosis of hip or
        symptomatic osteoporosis (e.g., known compression fractures), brittle diabetes mellitus, or
        glaucoma. Patients with other psychiatric disorders will be evaluated on a case by case
        basis.

        Patients who have been treated with steroids equivalent to 1 mg/kg/day for greater than or
        equal to 8 weeks without remission will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adams DM, Kinney TR, O'Branski-Rupp E, Ware RE. High-dose oral dexamethasone therapy for chronic childhood idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura. J Pediatr. 1996 Feb;128(2):281-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8636831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alexanian R, Dimopoulos MA, Delasalle K, Barlogie B. Primary dexamethasone treatment of multiple myeloma. Blood. 1992 Aug 15;80(4):887-90.</citation>
    <PMID>1498331</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andersen JC. Response of resistant idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura to pulsed high-dose dexamethasone therapy. N Engl J Med. 1994 Jun 2;330(22):1560-4. Erratum in: N Engl J Med 1994 Jul 28;331(4):283.</citation>
    <PMID>8177245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2004</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 20, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Nephrotic Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Steroids</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteoporosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Adrenal Suppression</keyword>
  <keyword>Proteinuria</keyword>
  <keyword>Focal Segmental Glomerulosclerosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nephrotic Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nephrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulosclerosis, Focal Segmental</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

