<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00005448</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4377</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL056814</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00005448</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adverse Events With Magnesium Sulfate</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate in pregnant women the adverse pulmonary effects of magnesium sulfate (MgSO4),
      a commonly used drug for tocolysis or arrest of labor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      Preterm labor is a major public health concern in the United States. The delay of labor,
      particularly for idiopathic preterm labor, is important because it allows further fetal
      development and the opportunity to administer steroids which improve fetal lung maturity. It
      is now common for MgSO4 to be administered to delay labor. The most dangerous adverse event
      with MgSO4 treatment is the development of pulmonary edema which may lead to maternal adult
      respiratory distress syndrome and death with associated fetal morbidity and mortality. The
      estimates of the frequency of this complication vary from 0 to 8 percent. Therefore, improved
      understanding of the pulmonary toxicity of this therapeutic agent is clinically important.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      There were three phases in the study. The first, a retrospective cohort study, examined the
      incidence rate of pulmonary edema when MgSO4 was administered as a tocolytic agent. The
      second, a case-control study nested within the cohort, examined the relationship between the
      patient and other clinical factors and the incidence of pulmonary edema in patients treated
      with MgSO4. The third phase used the results of the case-control study to develop and
      validate a predictive index to define a group of patients at increased risk of developing
      pulmonary edema associated with MgSO4.

      Patients were identified using ICD-9-CM codes for preterm labor and delivery. The medical
      record was reviewed to determine exposure to MgSO4 as a tocolytic agent, excluding patients
      who received MgSO4 for other indications. Cases were defined as probable when patients met
      the clinical definition for pulmonary edema, including chest X-ray findings. The medical
      charts of both cases and a random sample of non cases were then reviewed in detail and the
      data from these groups were compared. The primary analysis of these case-control data
      included unadjusted analysis and multivariable explanatory models to provide insight into the
      risk factors for pulmonary edema associated with MgSO4. The data from the case-control study
      were used to develop a clinical predictive index. The predictive rule was then validated in a
      separate patient population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2002</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2002</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George Macones</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Macones GA, Segel SY, Stamilio DM, Morgan MA. Prediction of delivery among women with early preterm labor by means of clinical characteristics alone. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1999 Dec;181(6):1414-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10601922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Macones GA, Segel SY, Stamilio DM, Morgan MA. Predicting delivery within 48 hours in women treated with parenteral tocolysis. Obstet Gynecol. 1999 Mar;93(3):432-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10074994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2000</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2000</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

