<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03085173</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-1570</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03085173</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of &quot;Armored&quot; CAR T Cells Targeting CD19 For Patients With Relapsed CD19+ Hematologic Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of CD19-Targeted EGFRt/19-28z/4-1BBL &quot;Armored&quot; Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) Modified T Cells in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory CD19+ Hematologic Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Juno Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this phase I study is to test the safety of different dose levels of specially
      prepared cells collected from the patient called &quot;modified T cells&quot;. The investigators want
      to find a safe dose of modified T cells for patients with this type of cancer that has
      progressed after standard therapy. The investigators also want to find out what effects these
      modified T cells have on the patient and the cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A Phase I Trial of CD19-Targeted EGFRt/19-28z/4-1BBL &quot;Armored&quot; Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) Modified T Cells in Patients with Relapsed or Refractory Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>occurring within 30 days from the last infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Cohorts of 3-6 patients each will be treated with escalating doses of modified T cell. At least 3 patients will be treated at each dose level with an accrual of no more than 2 patients per month within each dose level. At least two weeks will elapse from the first patient's T cell infusions before the second patient is treated (on dose level 1) to allow for toxicity and safely assessment. All patients treated at the preceding dose level will be observed a minimum of 4 weeks before dose escalation occurs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</condition>
  <condition>Relapsed</condition>
  <condition>Refractory</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EGFRt/19-28z/4-1BBL CAR T cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following enrollment, patients will undergo leukapheresis of peripheral blood for further T cell enrichment, activation and genetic modification using a retroviral vector encoding a CD19targeted CAR, the co-stimulatory ligand 4-1BBL and the EGFRt safety system (EGFRt/19-28z/4-1BBL). These T cells will be expanded and after the appropriate number of cells is generated, the modified T cells may be infused fresh or frozen for later use according to standard operation procedures. Modified T cell infusions will be administered 2-7 days following completion of the treating investigator's choice of conditioning chemotherapy. Serial sampling of blood and bone marrow will be performed following treatment to assess toxicity, therapeutic effects, and survival of the genetically modified T cells.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EGFRt/19-28z/4-1BBL CAR T cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Cohorts of 3-6 patients will be infused with escalating doses of EGFRt/19-28z/4-1BBL CAR T cells to establish the maximum tolerated dose (MTD). There are 4 planned dose levels: 1 x 10^5, 3 x 10^5, 1 x 10^6, and 3 x 10^6 CAR T cells/kg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EGFRt/19-28z/4-1BBL CAR T cells</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have CD19+ B cell malignancy with relapsed or refractory disease,
             defined as below:

        Patients with CLL:

          -  Refractory to or relapsed after at least 2 prior chemo or chemoimmunotherapy (e.g.
             FCR, BR) requiring further treatment

          -  Refactory to or relapsed after at least 1 prior biologic agent (e.g. Ibrutinib,
             idelalisib, venetoclax, except a single agent anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody) requiring
             further treatment

        Patients with iNHL (FZ, MZL, WM):

          -  Refractory or relapsed after at least 2 lines of chemoimmunotherapy (including at
             least one course of anti-CD20 antibody)

          -  Refractory or relapsed after at least 1 prior biologic agent (e.g. lenalidomide,
             ibrutinib, idelalisib)

          -  Patients must have measurable disease (for WM patients, measureable disease is
             demonstrable monoclonal paraprotein and bone marrow involvement)

        Patients with DLBCL, Transformed B cell lymphoma, or High grade B cell lymphoma:

          -  Refractory to or relapsed after 1 or more prior chemoimmunotherapies with at least one
             containing an anthracycline and CD20 directed therapy

          -  Transplant ineligible

          -  Biopsy proven relapsed disease

        Patients with ALL, CML in lymphoid blast crisis or Burkitt's lymphoma:

          -  Refractory to at least 1 prior induction chemotherapy

          -  Relapsed after at least 1 prior multiagent systemic chemotherapy that included
             induction and consolidation

          -  Patients with Philadelphia chromosome-positive ALL must have failed a second
             generation tyrosine kinase inhibitor

               -  Age ≥ 18 years of age

               -  Creatinine ≤2.0 mg/100 ml, direct bilirubin ≤2.0 mg/100 ml, AST and ALT ≤3.0x
                  upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Adequate pulmonary function as assessed by ≥92% oxygen saturation on room air by
                  pulse oximetry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Karnofsky performance status &lt;70

          -  Pregnant or lactating women. Women and men of childbearing age should use effective
             contraception while on this study and continue for 1 year after all treatment is
             finished

          -  Impaired cardiac function (LVEF &lt;40%) as assessed by ECHO or MUGA scan

          -  Patients with active known autoimmune disease are ineligible

          -  Patients with following cardiac conditions will be excluded:

               -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) stage III or IV congestive heart failure

               -  Myocardial infarction &lt;/= 6 months prior to enrollment

               -  History of clinically significant ventricular arrhythmia or unexplained syncope,
                  not believed to be vasovagal in nature or due to dehydration &lt;6 months prior to
                  enrollment

               -  History of severe non-ischemic cardiomyopathy with EF &lt;/=20%

          -  Patients with HIV or active hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection are ineligible

          -  Patients with uncontrolled systemic fungal, bacterial, viral or other infection are
             ineligible

          -  Patients with any concurrent active malignancies as defined by malignancies requiring
             any therapy other than expectant observation or hormonal therapy, with the exception
             of squamous and basal cell carcinoma of skin

          -  Patients with history or presence of clinically significant neurological disorders
             such as epilepsy, generalized seizure disorder, severe brain injuries are ineligible

          -  Any other issue which, in the opinion of the treating physician, would make the
             patient ineligible for the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jae Park, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jae Park, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-4048</phone>
    <email>parkj6@mskcc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Craig Sauter, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-3460</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jae Park, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-4048</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Craig Sauter, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3460</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jae Park, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/mskcc/html/44.cfm</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CAR T Cells Targeting CD19</keyword>
  <keyword>EGFRt/19-28z/4-1BBL</keyword>
  <keyword>16-1570</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

