<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03086642</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAQ9966</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03086642</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Talimogene Laherparepvec (T-VEC) in Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Talimogene Laherparepvec Administered Endoscopically for the Treatment of Locally Advanced or Metastatic Pancreas Cancer Refractory to at Least One Chemotherapy Regimen</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yvonne Saenger</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out which doses of talimogene laherparepvec (T-Vec) can
      be given safely to participants with pancreatic cancer that is either too big to be taken out
      by surgery or has spread to other parts of the body. The study will also see if T-Vec can
      cause tumor shrinkage or prevent its growth.

      The primary objective is to determine the rate of dose limiting toxicity at tested doses of
      talimogene laherparepvec administered endoscopically to pancreatic tumors, and to identify a
      maximum tolerated dose (MTD).

      Secondary exploratory efficacy endpoints include change in longest diameter in the injected
      lesion(s), overall response rate (ORR) per RECIST v1.1 and modified immune-related response
      criteria (mirRC as defined in section 11), progression free survival (PFS) and overall
      survival (OS) at 6, 12, and 24 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDA) is an area of great unmet need. PDA accounts for 90%
      of pancreatic tumors in 2016. The standard of care for pancreas cancer is cytotoxic
      chemotherapy, but this is not particularly effective with best response rates reported of
      20-30% and no significant long-term 5-year survival for patients who are not surgical
      candidates. Talimogene laherparepvec (previously known as OncoVEXGM-CSF) is an intratumorally
      delivered oncolytic immunotherapy comprised of an immune-enhanced herpes simplex virus type-1
      (HSV-1) that selectively replicates in solid tumors. Talimogene laherparepvec was the first
      oncolytic viral therapy to be approved by the Federal Drug Administration (FDA) for the
      treatment of cancer, specifically melanoma. There is the potential that talimogene
      laherparepvec could exert a systemic effect mitigating the potential of PDA to metastasize.

      This is a phase 1 dose escalation study to evaluate the safety of talimogene laherparepvec in
      PDA. To find out which doses are safe, all participants enrolled in this study will receive
      up to 4 injections of T-Vec. At least two doses will be evaluated in this study, depending on
      how many side effects are seen at each dose. Participants will not be able to pick the dose,
      as this will be determined based on the study experience with participants enrolled
      previously.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 16, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>36-48 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the highest dose of study treatment that does not cause unacceptable side effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in size of injected lesion(s)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 11 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To make an exploratory assessment of activity of talimogene laherparepvec in pancreatic cancer, as measured by change in size of the injected lesion(s)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients whose cancer shrinks or disappears after treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The length of time during and after the study treatment of cancer, that a patient lives with the disease but it does not get worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The length of time from either the date of diagnosis or the start of study treatment for cancer, that patients diagnosed with the disease are still alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>T-Vec</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All enrolled patients will receive a test dose of talimogene laherparepvec (10^6 PFU/ml) on day 1, followed by treatment doses at escalating concentrations weeks 4, 7, and 10. A biopsy will be obtained during each scheduled endoscopy prior to talimogene laherparepvec injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Talimogene laherparepvec</intervention_name>
    <description>T-Vec will be administered by intratumoral injection into pancreatic tumors accessible endoscopically with ultrasound guidance (at least one pancreatic lesion must be injected during each treatment).
On day 1 of week 1 the first dose of talimogene laherparepvec will be up to 4.0 mL of 10^6 PFU/mL. The second injection up to 4.0 mL of 10^6, 10^7, or 10^8 PFU/mL should be administered no sooner than day 1 of week 4 but should not be delayed more than 7 days after the scheduled time point. The maximum volume of T-Vec administered at any one time is 4.0 mL for any individual lesion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>T-Vec</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>T-Vec</other_name>
    <other_name>T Vec</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient must have pathologically confirmed, locally advanced or metastatic pancreatic
             adenocarcinoma deemed surgically unresectable by a surgeon with expertise in
             pancreatic cancer

          2. Disease must be refractory to or intolerant of at least first-line chemotherapy which
             contains 5-fluorouracil or gemcitabine

          3. The primary lesion must be accessible for endoscopic biopsy and injection as evaluated
             by a gastroenterologist at NewYork Presbyterian -Columbia. Further, the patient must
             be deemed able to tolerate repeated endoscopy procedures by an anesthesiologist and/or
             gastroenterologist at NewYork Presbyterian-Columbia

          4. Age 18 years or older

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0, 1, or 2

          6. Radiologically measurable disease in the pancreas ≥1cm, as defined by RECIST v1.1

          7. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          8. Females of child-bearing potential (defined as a sexually mature woman who (1) has not
             undergone hysterectomy [the surgical removal of the uterus] or bilateral oophorectomy
             [the surgical removal of both ovaries] or (2) has not been naturally postmenopausal
             for at least 24 consecutive months [i.e., has had menses at any time during the
             preceding 24 consecutive months]) must:

             i. Either commit to true abstinence from heterosexual contact (which must be reviewed
             on a monthly basis), or agree to use, and be able to comply with, effective
             contraception (&lt;/=1% failure rate annually) without interruption, 28 days prior to
             starting therapy (including dose interruptions), and while on study medication or for
             a period of 30 days following treatment completion. [Periodic abstinence (eg,
             calendar, ovulation, symptothermal, post-ovulation methods) and withdrawal are not
             acceptable methods of contraception].

             ii. Have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test within 72 hours prior to enrollment.
             If urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy test
             will be required.This applies even if the subject practices true abstinence from
             heterosexual contact.

          9. Male subjects must practice true abstinence or agree to use a condom during sexual
             contact with a pregnant female or a female of childbearing potential while
             participating in the study, during dose interruptions and for 30 days following
             treatment discontinuation, even if he has undergone a successful vasectomy.

         10. Adequate organ and marrow function as defined below without need for hematopoietic
             growth factor or transfusion support:

               -  Hemoglobin ≥8.0g/dl

               -  Platelets ≥75,000/microliter (mcL)

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1500/mm3 (1.5x109/L)

               -  Total bilirubin ≤1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN) or Direct
                  bilirubin ≤ ULN with total bilirubin &gt;1.5 x ULN

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (SGOT)/alanine transaminase (ALT) (SGPT) ≤1.5 x
                  ULN

               -  INR and aPTT ≤ 1.5 x ULN Unless the patient is on therapeutic anticoagulation in
                  which case the international normalized ratio (INR) and activated partial
                  thromboplastin time (aPTT) must be within the therapeutic range of intended use
                  of anti-coagulants

               -  Serum creatinine ≤1.5 x ULN or Creatinine clearance ≥60 mL/min/1.73 m2 by
                  Cockcroft-Gault

               -  Lipase ≤3 x ULN

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cystic pancreatic cancer. Microcystic disease may be eligible

          2. Patients with pancreatic metastases deemed likely to limit the patient's ability to
             participate in the study for the complete duration (ie. &gt;3 months), including but not
             limited to:

               1. Presence of central nervous system (CNS) metastasis including brain metastasis or
                  compromise resulting from extrinsic disease in the bone or dura

               2. Presence of more than 5 liver metastases or one liver metastasis measuring more
                  than 3cm

               3. Cancer antigen (CA)19-9 &gt;3000 U/mL

               4. Oxygen requirement attributable to pleural effusion or other malignant process

               5. Symptomatic ascites or radiographic evidence of more than trace ascites

          3. Pancreatitis that is active or within the preceding 3 months which in the judgment of
             the endoscopist would make tumor injection likely to trigger severe recurrent
             pancreatitis.

          4. Prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 14 days prior to first dose of therapy or
             has not recovered to CTCAE grade 1 or better from adverse event at time of enrollment
             due to cancer therapy administered more than 28 days prior to enrollment. or prior
             biological cancer therapy, targeted therapy, or major surgery within 28 days prior to
             first dose of therapy or unresolved grade 2 or greater toxicity from prior treatment,
             including chemotherapy, hormonal therapy, or radiotherapy, at the time of study
             enrollment. The following ongoing treatments are permitted:

               1. Hormone-replacement therapy or oral contraceptives

               2. Hormone therapy for primary prevention of breast cancer

          5. Patients may not receive Coumadin while on study. Patients may receive low molecular
             weight heparin or novel oral anticoagulants (eg. dabigatran, apixaban, rivaroxaban)
             provided that the dose is held 1-2 days before injections are given and biopsies are
             performed per the protocol. Anti-platelet agents and herbal substances are allowed at
             the discretion of the treating endoscopist.

          6. Active herpetic skin lesions or prior complications of herpetic infection (e.g.,
             herpetic keratitis or encephalitis) or requires intermittent or chronic systemic
             (intravenous or oral) treatment with an antiherpetic drug (e.g., acyclovir), other
             than intermittent topical use.

          7. Previous treatment with talimogene laherparepvec or any other oncolytic virus

          8. Prior therapy with tumor vaccine

          9. Currently receiving treatment with another investigational device or drug study, or &lt;
             28 days since ending treatment with another investigational device or drug study(s).
             Other investigational procedures while participating in this study are excluded.

         10. Known to have acute or chronic active hepatitis B infection, hepatitis C infection, or
             known to have human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection.

         11. Subject has known sensitivity to talimogene laherparepvec or any of its components to
             be administered during dosing.

         12. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection including Tuberculosis (TB) and C. difficile, symptomatic congestive heart
             failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirements. This includes known
             clinically significant liver disease, including active viral, alcoholic, or other
             hepatitis; cirrhosis; fatty liver; and inherited liver disease

         13. Severe infections within 4 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1, including but not limited to
             hospitalization for complications of infection, bacteremia, or severe pneumonia

         14. Major surgical procedure within 28 days prior to Cycle 1, Day 1 or anticipation of
             need for a major surgical procedure during the course of the study

         15. Female subject of childbearing potential who is unwilling to use acceptable method(s)
             of effective contraception during study treatment and through 3 months after the last
             dose of talimogene laherparepvec. (Note: Women not of childbearing potential are
             defined as: Any female who is post-menopausal [age &gt; 55 years with cessation of menses
             for 12 or more months or less than 55 years but not spontaneous menses for at least 2
             years or less than 55 years and spontaneous menses within the past 1 year, but
             currently amenorrheic (eg, spontaneous or secondary to hysterectomy), and with
             postmenopausal gonadotropin levels (luteinizing hormone and follicle-stimulating
             hormone levels &gt; 40 IU/L) or postmenopausal estradiol levels (&lt; 5 ng/dL) or according
             to the definition of &quot;postmenopausal range&quot; for the laboratory involved] or who have
             had a hysterectomy, bilateral salpingectomy, or bilateral oophorectomy).

         16. Sexually active subjects and their partners unwilling to use male or female latex
             condom to avoid potential viral transmission during sexual contact while on treatment
             and within 30 days after treatment with talimogene laherparepvec.

         17. Subject who is unwilling to minimize exposure with his/her blood or other body fluids
             to individuals who are at higher risks for HSV-1 induced complications such as
             immunosuppressed individuals, individuals known to have HIV infection, pregnant women,
             or children under the age of 1 year, during talimogene laherparepvec treatment and
             through 30 days after the last dose of talimogene laherparepvec.

             Immunotherapy-Related Exclusion Criteria:

         18. History or evidence of active autoimmune disease that requires systemic treatment (ie,
             with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive drugs).
             Replacement therapy (eg, thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid replacement
             therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a form of
             systemic treatment for patients with prior allogeneic bone marrow transplantation or
             prior solid organ transplantation.

             • The use of inhaled or oral corticosteroids and mineralocorticoids (e.g.,
             fludrocortisone) for patients with orthostatic hypotension or adrenocortical
             insufficiency is allowed.

         19. Received live vaccine within 28 days prior to enrollment.

         20. Evidence of clinically significant immunosuppression such as the following:

               -  Primary immunodeficiency state such as Severe Combined Immunodeficiency Disease

               -  HIV positive

               -  Receiving systemic immunosuppressive therapy (&gt; 2 weeks) including oral steroid
                  doses &gt; 10 mg/day of prednisone or equivalent within 2 months prior to enrollment

               -  Concurrent opportunistic infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yvonne M Saenger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dan Otap</last_name>
    <phone>212-342-3970</phone>
    <email>do2267@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yvonne M Saenger, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-317-6313</phone>
      <email>yms4@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yvonne M Saenger, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hiccc.columbia.edu/ct/</url>
    <description>Cancer Center's clinical trials online search tool</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 16, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yvonne Saenger</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director. Melanoma Immunotherapy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>locally advanced pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>locally advanced pancreas cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic pancreas cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory pancreas cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>T-Vec</keyword>
  <keyword>T Vec</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancrelipase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

