<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03086863</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03086863</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Electroacupuncture for Poststroke Patients With Shoulder Pain</brief_title>
  <acronym>EAPSSP</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness and Safety of Electroacupuncture for Poststroke Patients With Shoulder Pain: Study Protocol for a Multicenter, Randomized, Patient and Assessor Blinded, Sham Controlled, Parallel, Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kyunghee University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wonkwang University Gwangju Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Rehabilitation Center, Seoul, Korea</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kyunghee University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, randomized, sham-controlled, patient- and assessor-blinded, and
      parallel trial to explore the effectiveness and safety of electroacupuncture (EA) therapy,
      compared with sham EA, for poststroke shoulder pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is aimed at showing the effectiveness and safety of electroacupuncture therapy for
      the stroke survivors with shoulder pain. 60 stroke survivors with shoulder pain will be
      enrolled in two traditional Korean medicine hospitals and randomly divided into either of
      verum or sham electroacupuncture group with 1:1 of allocation ratio. The participants will
      receive 9 sessions of electroacupuncture procedures for 3 weeks. Patients and outcome
      assessors will be blinded from the beginning to the study completion. Visual analogue scale
      will be primarily evaluated, and pain rating scale, Fugl-Meyer assessment upper extremity,
      modified Ashworth scale, manual muscle test, passive range of motion, Korean version of
      modified Barthel index, and Korean version of Beck depression inventory will be measured,
      too. Blinding index will be assessed. For safety, adverse events will be collected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 29, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 29, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean difference of visual analogue scale (VAS) between baseline and endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>VAS is a patient-rated outcome with a 10-cm line representing 'not painful at all' for zero and 'most painful' for ten. Patient marks x on the line by oneself, based on how intense he/she thinks the pain is and assessor measures the length from zero point to x mark, which is the pain score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>before-after change of visual analogue scale (VAS) (intragroup effect)</measure>
    <time_frame>1~3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>VAS is a patient-rated outcome with a 10-cm line representing 'not painful at all' for zero and 'most painful' for ten. Patient marks x on the line by oneself, based on how intense he/she thinks the pain is and assessor measures the length from zero point to x mark, which is the pain score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean difference of pain rating scale (PRS) between baseline and endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>PRS is a patient-rated outcome to assess pain with 4 items for intensity (0-10 points), frequency (0-5 points), duration (0-5 points) and aggravating factors (0-5 points). The pain score is the product of the intensity point and the sum of frequency, duration, aggravating factors points (0-150 points in total).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean difference of Fugl-Meyer assessment - upper extremity (FMA-UE) between baseline and endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>FMA-UE assesses physical performance of upper extremity following stroke. The original FMA scale includes 4 domains of motor function, sensation qualities, passive range of motion, and joint pain with 3-point items ('cannot perform' for 0, 'perform partially' for 1, and 'perform fully' for 2). We are going to measure only 8 items for upper extremity (shoulder retraction, elevation, abduction, abduction to 90°, adduction/internal rotation, external rotation, flexion 0-90°, and flexion 90-180°)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean difference of passive ranges of motion (PROM) between baseline and endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>PROM for shoulder flexion, abduction, and extension will be measured with goniometer. The maximum degrees under passive movement of shoulder unless patients suffer from pain will be tested.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean difference of manual muscle test (MMT) between baseline and endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>MMT assesses muscle strength in poststroke shoulder injury. Assessors will rate on a grade of 0 (no contraction at all) to 5 (complete range of motion against gravity with maximum resistance) for hemiplegic shoulder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean difference of modified Ashworth scale (MAS) between baseline and endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>MAS is a clinical rating scale to measure tonal abnormality after stroke. Assessors should grade from 0, meaning no increase in muscle tone, to 5, meaning that rigid shoulder on flexion or extension.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean difference of Korean version of modified Barthel index (K-MBI) between baseline and endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>K-MBI is an ordinal scale used to measure performance in activities of daily living. Ten items (personal hygiene, bathing, feeding, toilet use, stair climbing, dressing, bowel control, bladder control, walking, and chair/bed transfers) will be graded between 1 (completely dependent on others to perform) and 5 (completely independent on others to perform), respectively, and it scores up to 100 points in total.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean difference of Korean version of Beck depression inventory (K-BDI) between baseline and endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>K-BDI is a patient-rated outcome with 21 items, 0 to 3 points of each item. The higher the total score is, the severe the depressive level is.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mean difference of the occurrence numbers of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>3 times per week, 3 weeks, through study completion,</time_frame>
    <description>At every visit, assessors will ask a post-interventional question about adverse events. The number of adverse events will be recorded for each group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>new Blinding index (BI)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks (only at the end of the study)</time_frame>
    <description>Patients and outcome assesses will be asked which group they think they belong to and select one of the answers (verum electroacupuncture group, sham electroacupuncture group, or unknown). With the answers, the new BI will be calculated with mean and variances following the preceding study. The index score varies from 1 of complete lack of blinding, 0 of consistency with perfect blinding, or −1 of opposite guessing of their groups.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Shoulder Pain</condition>
  <condition>Stroke, Complication</condition>
  <condition>Cerebral Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Cerebral Hemorrhage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>verum electroacupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Electroacupuncture on LI4, LI15, TE14, SI9, SI11, and GB21, unilaterally
Needle insertion by 10-15 mm and de qi sensation
Park sham guide tubes
Low frequency electronic stimulation (30 Hz)
Retention for 20 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sham electroacupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Park sham device on on LI4, LI15, TE14, SI9, SI11, and GB21, unilaterally
Needle installation without penetration
Park sham guide tubes
Low frequency electronic stimulation (30 Hz) for a fake noise without conduction
Retention for 20 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>electroacupuncture</intervention_name>
    <description>All the patients in verum electroacupuncture group will receive acupuncture on the six adjacent acupoints (LI4, LI15, TE14, SI9, SI11, and GB21) in unilateral side. Acupuncture needles (stainless steel, 0.25 mm × 40 mm, Dong Bang Acupuncture Inc., Republic of Korea) will be inserted 10-15 mm in depth and de qi sensation will be elicited. Park sham guide tubes will be used in verum group, too. Low frequency stimulate (STN-111, Stratek, Republic of Korea) will be connected to the tips of needles to provide electrical stimulation at middle frequency (30 Hz). Needles with electrical stimulation will be retained for 20 minutes. Patients should take this procedure 3 times a week for 3 weeks (9 sessions in total).</description>
    <arm_group_label>verum electroacupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>verum EA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sham electroacupuncture</intervention_name>
    <description>We selected a non-penetrating sham needling, i.e., Park sham device, which has been developed and validated in preceding studies as comparison. On the exactly same 6 acupoints as verum electroacupuncture group, needles will be installed with Park sham guide tubes and the same electrical stimulators will be connected the tips of needles. Since the needles do not penetrate the skin, the stimulation is not electrically conducted. To be sure of patient blinding, the low frequency stimulate will be turned on with the same frequency (30 Hz), which makes a fake noise, resulting in letting patients believe that they are taking real electroacupuncture therapy for 20 minutes. Sham group will also 9 session for 3 weeks (3 sessions a week).</description>
    <arm_group_label>sham electroacupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sham EA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosed with cerebral hemorrhage or infarction examined by computed tomography (CT)
             magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at least 2 weeks or more ago;

          -  complaining hemiplegic shoulder pain of VAS ≥4;

          -  agreeing that any treatments, including analgesics, for hemiplegic shoulder pain will
             not be changed from the previous 2 weeks prior to the enrollment until the last
             evaluation, if applicable;

          -  fully explained about the clinical research and sign the informed consents.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  disorders, traumatic injury, or surgery of shoulders even before their stroke;

          -  pacemakers, embedded neural stimulator, cardiac arrhythmia, epilepsy, peripheral
             neural injury on their medical history;

          -  psychiatric disorders;

          -  cancer within the past 5 years, regardless of its prognosis and location;

          -  cognitive impairment that interferes with clinical assessment;

          -  hypersensitivity or fears to acupuncture;

          -  bleeding disorders (e.g. hemophilia or von Willebrand disease, etc.),

          -  pregnancy,

          -  difficulty in communicating with researchers, or

          -  any other conditions who are considered inappropriate for participating in the trial
             by experienced practitioners.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Euiji Lee, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kyunghee University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyung Hee University Korean Medicine Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>156-853</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee SH, Lim SM. Acupuncture for Poststroke Shoulder Pain: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2016;2016:3549878. doi: 10.1155/2016/3549878. Epub 2016 Jul 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27547224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bang H, Ni L, Davis CE. Assessment of blinding in clinical trials. Control Clin Trials. 2004 Apr;25(2):143-56.</citation>
    <PMID>15020033</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park J, White A, Stevinson C, Ernst E, James M. Validating a new non-penetrating sham acupuncture device: two randomised controlled trials. Acupunct Med. 2002 Dec;20(4):168-74.</citation>
    <PMID>12512790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price DD, McGrath PA, Rafii A, Buckingham B. The validation of visual analogue scales as ratio scale measures for chronic and experimental pain. Pain. 1983 Sep;17(1):45-56.</citation>
    <PMID>6226917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim C, Kim C, Chun SI. Clinical value of a new self assessment method of pain. Journal of Korean Acamedy of Rehabilitation Medicine 22(2):305-311, 1998. (Korean)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim HS, Her JG, Ko JY, Park DS, Woo JH, You YY, Choi YE. Reliability, concurrent validity, and responsiveness of the Fugl-Meyer assessment (FMA) for hemiplegic patients. Journal of Physical Therapy Science 24(9):893-899, 2012.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mendell JR, Florence J. Manual muscle testing. Muscle Nerve. 1990;13 Suppl:S16-20.</citation>
    <PMID>2233877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gregson JM, Leathley M, Moore AP, Sharma AK, Smith TL, Watkins CL. Reliability of the Tone Assessment Scale and the modified Ashworth scale as clinical tools for assessing poststroke spasticity. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1999 Sep;80(9):1013-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10489001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jung HY, Park BK, Shin HS, Kang YK, Pyun SB, Paik NJ, Kim SH, Kim TH, Han TR. Development of the Korean version of modified barthel index (K-MBI): multi-center study for subjects with Stroke. Journal of Korean Acamedy of Rehabilitation Medicine 31(3):283-297, 2007. (Korean)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rhee MK, Lee YH, Park SH, Sohn CH, Chung YC, Hong SK, Lee BK, Chang P, Yoon AR. A stadardization study of beck depression inventory Ⅰ - Korean version (K-BDI): reliability and factor analysis. The Korean Journal of Psychopathology 4(1):77-95, 1995. (Korean)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rhee MK, Lee YH, Jung HY, Chio JH, Kim SH, Kim YK, Lee SK. A stadardization study of beck depression inventory Ⅱ - Korean version (K-BDI): validity. The Korean Journal of Psychopathology 4(1):96-104, 1995 . (Korean)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang KF, Zhang LJ, Lu F, Lu YH, Yang CH. Can Ashi points stimulation have specific effects on shoulder pain? A systematic review of randomized controlled trials. Chin J Integr Med. 2016 Jun;22(6):467-72. doi: 10.1007/s11655-015-2107-4. Epub 2015 Jun 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26129899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kyunghee University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lee Eui-ju</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Ph.D. KMD.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>electroacupuncture</keyword>
  <keyword>randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shoulder Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

