<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03088644</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108269</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-004007-31</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>54175446EDI1004</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03088644</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Investigate P2X7 Receptor Occupancy by JNJ-54175446 With the Newly Developed P2X7 Receptor Positron Emission Tomography (PET) Tracer 18F-JNJ-64413739</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Study to Investigate P2X7 Receptor Occupancy by JNJ-54175446 With the Newly Developed P2X7 Receptor PET Tracer 18F-JNJ-64413739</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen-Cilag International NV</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen-Cilag International NV</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to measure the whole body distribution and radiation
      dosimetry of 18F-JNJ-64413739 (Part A), to measure the uptake, distribution, and clearance
      (CL) of 18F-JNJ-64413739 in the brain of healthy male subjects by Positron Emission
      Tomography (PET) and to model tissue specific kinetics of 18F-JNJ-64413739 with the
      appropriate input function (IF) (Part B), to measure subject test retest variability in the
      distribution of 18F-JNJ-64413739 in the brain of healthy male subjects by comparing PET scans
      obtained at least 1 week apart (Part C) and following single oral dose administration of
      JNJ-54175446, to measure the blocking of 18F-JNJ-64413739 uptake in the brain at the time to
      reach maximum plasma concentration (tmax) of JNJ-54175446 and model the exposure/receptor
      interaction of JNJ-54175446 in healthy male subjects (Part D).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 24, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 14, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 14, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A: Effective Radiation Dose Following Injection of 18F-JNJ-64413739</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The tissue radioactivity will be measured per organ for up to 5 hours after injection of up to 185 megaBecquerel (MBq) of 18F-JNJ-64413739 and corrected for attenuation by computed tomography (CT) transmission scans using PET/CT. These measurements will be used to estimate effective radiation dose per organ and total body.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part B: Total and Regional Brain Compartmental Kinetics for Volume of Distribution of 18F-JNJ-64413739</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Distribution of 18F-JNJ-64413739 in brain will be measured by dynamic PET/magnetic resonance (MR) scans obtained from the time of injection for up to 120 minutes along with measurement of the tracer input function with arterial samples for intact tracer and metabolites to establish the total and regional compartmental kinetics and volume of distribution (V[t]) of 18F-JNJ-64413739.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part C: Test Retest Variability in the Distribution of 18F-JNJ-64413739</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Test Retest Variability within subjects will be assessed based on percent difference in V[t] following 18F-JNJ-64413739 PET/MR scans obtained at least 1 Week apart. V[t] will be the parameter for the estimated volume of distribution of the tracer derived from the kinetic model that best fits the data from Part B. It will be calculated by formula [100*abs (V[t]test - V[t]retest)/[( V[t]test+ V[t]retest)/2].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part D: Plasma Concentrations of JNJ-54175446</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics will be calculated for the plasma concentrations of JNJ-54175446.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part D: Percentage of P2X7 Receptor Occupancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percent reduction in V[t] of 18F-JNJ-64413739 in brain regions of interest will be calculated by PET/MR scans obtained at pre and post treatment with single doses of JNJ-54175446.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Number of Subjects With Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability of 18F-JNJ-64413739</measure>
    <time_frame>Part A and B: Up to 4 Weeks; Part C: Up to 5 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical event that occurs in a subject administered an investigational product, and it does not necessarily indicate only events with clear causal relationship with the relevant investigational product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part D: Number of Subjects With Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability of JNJ-54175446</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical event that occurs in a subject administered an investigational product, and it does not necessarily indicate only events with clear causal relationship with the relevant investigational product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part A: 18F-JNJ-64413739</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive an intravenous (IV) bolus injection of 18F-JNJ-64413739 at a dose between 150 and 185 megaBecquerel (MBq) on Day 1 of Part A to investigate the total body biodistribution and measure the radiation dosimetry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part B: 18F-JNJ-64413739</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive an IV bolus injection of 18F-JNJ-64413739 at a dose between 150 and 185 MBq on Day 1 of Part B to measure the uptake, distribution, and clearance in brain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part C: 18F-JNJ-64413739</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive an IV bolus injection of 18F-JNJ-64413739 for a PET/MR scan on Day 1 and a repeat 18F-JNJ-64413739 PET/magnetic resonance (MR) scan at least 1 week later to determine the test-retest variability in V[t]. 18F-JNJ-64413739 doses will be between 150 and 185 MBq.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part D: JNJ-54175446 + 18F-JNJ-64413739</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will have a baseline 18F-JNJ-64413739 PET/MR scan on Day 1. On Day 2 they will receive JNJ-54175446 (maximum 600 milligram [mg]) orally (after light breakfast) and then an IV injection of 18F-JNJ-64413739 four hours after dosing for a PET/MR scan. At least 1 week later, they will receive another dose of JNJ-54175446, and then an IV injection of 18F-JNJ-64413739 four hours later for a second post-treatment PET/MR scan. 18F-JNJ-64413739 doses will be between 150 and 185 MBq.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JNJ-54175446</intervention_name>
    <description>JNJ-54175446 up to 600 mg suspension for oral dose administration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part D: JNJ-54175446 + 18F-JNJ-64413739</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>18F-JNJ-64413739</intervention_name>
    <description>18F-JNJ-64413739 fluid for injection administered intravenously.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part A: 18F-JNJ-64413739</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part B: 18F-JNJ-64413739</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part C: 18F-JNJ-64413739</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 30 kilogram per square meter (kg/m^2) inclusive
             (BMI = weight/height^2)

          -  Nonsmoker (not smoked for 3 months prior to screening)

          -  Is willing to allow the investigators to place an arterial catheter in the radial
             artery, is assessed via physical examination (Allen Test) to be a good subject for
             arterial catheter placement and should not be allergic to local anesthetics for
             catheter placement (Part B-C-D)

          -  During the study and for a minimum of 1 spermatogenesis cycle (defined as
             approximately 90 days) after receiving the last dose of study drug, in addition to the
             highly effective method of contraception, a man: who is sexually active with a woman
             of childbearing potential and has not had vasectomy must agree to use a barrier method
             of contraception (e.g., condom with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/suppository or
             partner with occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal
             foam/gel/film/cream/suppository). In addition, their female partner should also use an
             highly effective method of birth control (e.g. hormonal contraception) for at least
             the same duration; who is sexually active with a woman who is pregnant must use a
             condom; must agree not to donate sperm

          -  Subjects must have signed an informed consent document indicating that they understand
             the purpose of, and procedures required for the study and are willing to participate
             in the study and comply with the study procedures and restrictions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exposed to greater than (&gt;)1 millisievert (mSv) of ionizing radiation participating as
             a subject in research studies in the 12 months before the start of this study

          -  Clinically significant abnormal physical and neurological examination, vital signs or
             12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) at screening or admission

          -  History of or current significant medical illness including (but not limited to)
             cardiac arrhythmias or other cardiac disease, hematological disease, lipid
             abnormalities, bronchospastic respiratory disease, diabetes mellitus, renal or hepatic
             insufficiency, thyroid disease, parkinson's disease, infection, or any other illness
             that the Investigator considers should exclude the subject. History of epilepsy or
             fits or unexplained black-outs

          -  Serology positive for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C virus (HCV)
             antibodies or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibodies

          -  Subject has a history of drug or alcohol abuse according to Diagnostic and Statistical
             Manual of Mental Disorders (5th edition) (DSM-V) criteria within 6 months before
             Screening or positive test result(s) for alcohol and/or drugs of abuse (opiates
             (including methadone), cocaine, amphetamines, methamphetamines, cannabinoids,
             barbiturates, ecstasy and benzodiazepines) at screening or admission of each period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen-Cilag International NV Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen-Cilag International NV</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

