<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03084055</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1516/029</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03084055</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial of an Intervention for Adults With Depression: the eMotion Study.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial of a Web-based Intervention Using Behavioral Activation and Physical Activity for Adults With Depression: the eMotion Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Exeter</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Glasgow</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Exeter</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Physical activity has many potential mood enhancing benefits, and may be as effective as
      anti-depressants and psychological therapies for treating depression and low mood. However,
      getting people with depression to become more active is challenging. Behavioural Activation
      (BA) is an evidenced based psychotherapeutic treatment that focuses on increasing exposure to
      positive environmental stimuli which could provide an effective delivery mechanism for
      increasing physical activity for people who are more sedentary than the general population.
      The purpose of this study is to examine the feasibility of delivering a theory informed
      online intervention combining physical activity and BA (eMotion) to people with depression,
      and to examine its effects on depressive symptoms and physical activity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A randomised controlled trial (RCT) design will be used in this study. 120 participants
      experiencing depressive symptoms (&gt;10 on the PHQ-8) over the age of 18 will be recruited from
      the community. Participants will be eligible to participate if the over 18, score over 10 on
      the PHQ-8 and, are able to walk unaided for at least 5 minutes and have access to the
      internet. Following baseline measures, participants will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to the
      intervention or waiting list control arm and be followed up at 2 and 5 months. Those
      randomised to the intervention arm will receive eMotion which is comprised of a series of
      weekly audio visual modules designed to increase exposure to positive activities and physical
      activity. Main outcomes of interest include recruitment, retention, fidelity and
      acceptability. Baseline and follow up measures will also include the PHQ-8, and objective
      (GENEActvie accelerometers) and subjective (IPAQ) measures of physical activity. A parallel
      process evaluation will run alongside the RCT.

      If effective, this intervention has the potential to improve depressive symptoms in a wide
      range of hard to reach people in the community and increase their physical activity. Further
      evaluation in a full scale RCT is planned pending results of this trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 15, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 15, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>Depression will be measured using tThe Personal Health Questionnaire (PHQ-8). The PHQ-8 is an 8 item measure used to measure the frequency of depressive symptoms. This is a freely available brief self-report questionnaire which assesses depressive symptoms based on the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual for Mental Disorders (DSM-IV). Each item is rated on a scale of 0 to 3 with a maximum score of 24. It has been shown to have good validity, reliability, sensitivity and specificity. It has also been shown to discriminate between levels of major and major severe depression being 10-19, and 20-23 respectively (Kroenke et al., 2009)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>Objective physical activity will be assessed using GeneACTIVE wrist worn accelerometers. The accelerometer is a small wrist worn device that measures and records acceleration. 1 minute epochs will be used to measure movement, with higher counts per minute reflecting higher levels of physical activity as recommended in previous studies (Helgadóttir, Forsell, &amp; Ekblom, 2015; Mailey et al., 2010).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>General Anxiety Disorder (GAD-7) is a 7 item scale which measures symptoms and severity of anxiety based on the DSM-IV criteria and included in the minimum IAPT data set (Spitzer, Kroenke, Williams, &amp; Lowe, 2006).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Affective Mood State</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>Ecological Momentary Assessment of Mood (EMA) will be taken using a one item 10 point scale asking the participant to rate their mood where 1 = sad and 10 = happy. This will be taken twice per day randomly over five days during baseline data collection and at two months follow up using 'Text local', a text messaging service which allows participants to respond with a number response indicating their current mood at that point in time. This approach is adapted from previous research (van Rijsbergen, Bockting, Berking, Koeter, &amp; Schene, 2012).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported physical activity will be measured using the short-form IPAQ which measures Minutes per week of moderate to vigorous physical activity will be assessed by using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ). The IPAQ is a valid cross national measure of self-reported physical activity (Craig et al., 2003).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fidelity of receipt</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>The website will be assessed by asking questions understanding, perceived understanding the key learning goals for participants in all groups.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fidelity of enactment</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>Fidelity of enactment will be measured by asking participants in all groups if they have carried out specific behaviour change techniques relating to physical activity, and behavioural activation along with rating confidence.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Participant satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>The Client Satisfaction Questionnaire - Short Form (CSQ-SF). This is a 4 item measure which will be used to assess participant satisfaction in eMotion 2 months post randomization.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Participant views of intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Two months</time_frame>
    <description>Qualitative interviews after the final intervention session, all participants who receive eMotion will be invited to participate in a semi structured interview over the phone. The purpose of this is to further examine the acceptability of the intervention and any suggestions for improvement which can be absorbed into a next trial.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">62</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Symptoms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>eMotion intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomised to the intervention arm will receive eMotion for two months. eMotion is comprised of a series of weekly audio visual modules designed to increase exposure to positive activities and physical activity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waiting list control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the waiting list control group will be given no intervention for two months; the control group will then be able to access eMotion if they wish but this will not form part of the research project</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>eMotion</intervention_name>
    <description>eMotion is comprised of a series of weekly audio visual modules designed to increase exposure to positive activities and physical activity</description>
    <arm_group_label>eMotion intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults (aged ≥18 years).

          -  Adults with possible mild to moderately severe depression reflected by a score of
             between 10 and 23 (i.e. moderate to moderately severe depressive symptoms) on the
             Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-8) as has been done in previous studies looking at
             low mood and depressive symptoms.

          -  Adults living in the UK.

          -  Having access to the internet.

          -  Able to walk continuously and unaided for a minimum of 5 minutes.

          -  Provision of informed consent to participate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults (aged &lt;18 years).

          -  Adults without possible mild to moderately severe depression reflected by a score of
             between 10 and 23 (i.e. moderate to moderately severe depressive symptoms) on the
             Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-8) as has been done in previous studies looking at
             low mood and depressive symptoms.

          -  Adults not living in the UK.

          -  No access to the internet.

          -  Not able to walk continuously and unaided for a minimum of 5 minutes.

          -  Lacking capacity to give informed consent to participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey D Lambert, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Exeter</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Exeter</name>
      <address>
        <city>Exeter</city>
        <state>Devon</state>
        <zip>EX1 2LU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

