<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03084666</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F130312023</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03084666</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Remote Ischemic Preconditioning Living Donor Renal Transplant Protocol</brief_title>
  <official_title>Remote Ischemic Preconditioning Living Donor Renal Transplant Protocol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, patients undergoing live donor kidney transplantation will be allocated to the
      control group or remote ischemic preconditioning group (RIPC). RIPC is the utilization of
      short periods of ischemia to provide protection of the myocardium or other organ (i.e.
      kidney) from a subsequent ischemic event. Before allograft implantation, RIPC will be
      accomplished in the recipient and donor by inducing intermittent extremity ischemia through
      intermittent inflation of an extremity tourniquet three times for five-minute intervals with
      five minutes of deflation between inflation periods. The monitored clinical end points will
      include total urine output following kidney reperfusion over five days, plasma creatinine
      declination over five days, initiation of dialysis, and development of graft injury.
      Magnitude of graft injury is the primary endpoint and will be measured using biochemical
      markers, such as, plasma and urinary concentration of neutrophil gelatinase associated
      lipocalin (NGAL), IL-18, and KIM-1. The sample size calculation is based on a projected
      difference of NGAL levels between the two study arms. Hall et al reported a mean NGAL level
      of 49 mg/mL (SD = 37 mg/mL) for a group of patients that had immediate graph function and a
      mean NGAL level of 248 mg/mL in a group of patients with slow graft function. (which Hall
      reference is this) Based on these data, a conservative estimate of a mean difference between
      study groups will be considered 35 mg/mL NGAL. Using these assumptions, an alpha level of
      0.05 and 80% power, a sample size of n= 19 per study group will be calculated. By rejecting
      our null hypothesis, RIPC may serve as a safe, cost-effective protective strategy to prevent
      allograft injury in the clinical setting of live donor kidney transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All female patients of childbearing age that qualify for this study will receive a urinary
      pregnancy test prior to enrollment. Application of a tourniquet will occur after induction of
      anesthesia and intubation with minimal possibility of causing discomfort as the patient will
      be anesthetized. The tourniquet will be applied preferably to a leg but an arm will be used
      if a leg is unavailable. The tourniquet will be inflated for three 5 minute intervals over a
      30 minute period of time using the Zimmer A.T.S. 2000 Tourniquet System. Patients will be
      randomly allocated to one of two groups. The experimental group will have the tourniquet
      inflated on the leg or arm to 200 mmHg. The control group will have the tourniquet inflated
      on the leg or arm to only 20 mmHg. An audible timer will be used to help alert investigators
      that the tourniquet is in need of deflation after each 5-minute interval. The tourniquet will
      be removed after the needed 30 minutes of inflation/deflation to prevent inadvertent
      inflation of the tourniquet. Blood and Urine specimens will be labeled with patient name and
      medical record number. Urine samples will be taken in the operating room and at 6,12,24,48
      hours postoperatively to test for urinary biomarkers at the O'Brien Clinical Research Center.
      Blood samples for calculation of serum blood urea nitrogen and creatinine will be
      collected/processed/distributed/stored according to current UAB main laboratory guidelines as
      this test is routinely ordered on renal transplant patients. Urinary biomarker laboratory
      testing samples will be obtained by a bedside nurse placed in a routine urine sample
      container and a co-investigator will then bring samples to the laboratory where the samples
      will be tested for NGAL, KIM-1, and IL-18. Blood samples will be taken daily for the first 5
      days. A blood sample will be taken from the patient at 1 month to determine the serum blood
      urea nitrogen level and the creatinine level. The degree of allograft injury will be assessed
      by the levels of urinary biomarkers NGAL, IL-18, and KIM-1. Incidence of allograft or
      transplanted kidney primary malfunction will be based on urine output during the first three
      days after transplantation, the one month serum creatinine concentration, one month estimated
      glomerular filtration rate calculated according to diet modification. Additional secondary
      endpoints include 90-day mortality, length of ICU stay, and length of hospital stay. There is
      a low probability of tourniquet postoperative pain secondary to time of tourniquet inflation
      being both intermittent and for a short period of time. Inconvenience includes phone
      discussions with researchers/coordinators and preoperative discussions addressing risks and
      benefits of the study. Tourniquets will not be placed on extremities with preexisting
      arteriovenous fistulas or grafts utilized for hemodialysis. In addition, tourniquets will be
      placed after oscillometric blood pressure cuff placement for intraoperative
      anesthesia/surgical monitoring to provide adequate patient blood pressure assessment. The
      tourniquet will not be placed on the same extremity as the oscillometric blood pressure cuff.
      The primary investigator or a co-investigator will be present during times of tourniquet
      inflation. The patient will be assessed for complications immediately after tourniquet
      removal, in the PACU, and in the ICU/or step down unit. Finally, patient complication
      assessment will occur on the transplant floor after effects of anesthesia have completely
      resolved within 24 hours of tourniquet application. The extremity will also be assessed for
      injury at the 1-month follow up visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 13, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In this study, patients undergoing live donor kidney transplantation will be allocated to the control group or remote ischemic preconditioning group (RIPC). RIPC is the utilization of short periods of ischemia to provide protection of the myocardium or other organ (i.e. kidney) from a subsequent ischemic event.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Remote Ischemic Preconditioning (RIPC)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>RIPC may serve as a safe, cost-effective protective strategy to prevent allograft injury in the clinical setting of live donor kidney transplantation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment will receive 200 mmHg of pressure from a Zimmer ATS tourniquet system for three 5 minute intervals.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Our control group will receive 20 mmHg of pressure from a Zimmer ATS tourniquet system for three 5 minute intervals.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zimmer ATS tourniquet system</intervention_name>
    <description>The tourniquet is the same kind that is used in orthopedic surgeries to limit blood loss in arm or leg surgery. It can be inflated to a set pressure for a set amount of time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  &gt; OR = 19 years of age receiving a living donor renal transplant and their donors

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt; 19 years of age

          -  No safe extremity to place tourniquet

          -  Patients with previous muscle, vascular, or nerve injury to an extremity,

          -  Patients with only one available extremity that has an arteriovenous fistula

          -  Patients who are hemodialysis dependent who have not received hemodialysis in the past
             4 days

          -  Paraplegic/quadriplegic patients

          -  Active pathologic cutaneous lesions on extremities

          -  Patients with a history of tourniquet pain or CRPS

          -  Pregnant patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mali Mathru, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UAB Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Betty Herard, MBA, MA</last_name>
    <phone>205-934-0045</phone>
    <email>bherard@uabmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ayesha Bryant, MSPH, MD</last_name>
    <phone>205-996-7383</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UAB Department of Anesthesiology and Perioperative Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Betty Herard, MBA, MA</last_name>
      <phone>205-934-0045</phone>
      <email>bherard@uabmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ayesha Bryant, MSPH, MD</last_name>
      <phone>205-996-7383</phone>
      <email>asbryant@uabmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mali Mathru, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mali Mathru</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

