<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03083626</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-1378</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03083626</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Water Temperature on the Cold Pressor Test</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Water Temperature on the Cold Pressor Test in Patients With Opioid-Induced Hyperalgesia in Comparison to Healthy Controls</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Georgetown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Georgetown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This current study is intended to be completed under the umbrella of the current GHUCCTS IRB-
      approved study &quot;Opioid-Induced Hyperalgesia In Prescription Opioid Abusers: Effects of
      Pregabalin&quot; (Lyrica study) (PRO00000669). In this proposed study, 10 healthy male, 10 healthy
      female participants and 5 male, 5 female OIH participants (from the parent Lyrica study), who
      are prescription opioid abusers with chronic pain currently taking Suboxone, will be asked to
      take the cold pressor test at 1, 5, and 9 degrees Celsius and to report the time at which
      pain has completely gone away following each test. The purpose of this study is to examine
      how the water temperature of the cold pressure test might affect the participants' response
      (i.e., the participants pain threshold and pain tolerance) and to see if there is a
      difference in how each participation group is affected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Since the 1940s, the cold pressor test (CPT) has been used experimentally as a pain induction
      method due to its reliability, cost effectiveness and minimal production of side effects. In
      the CPT, a patient is asked to place his or her hand and forearm in an ice bath until the
      pain is too great to remain in the water. Researchers have employed the CPT to test a wide
      range of pain management techniques, including medications, cognitive- based therapies, or
      acupuncture, as well as to explore pain perception. The CPT has been performed on a variety
      of participants, including adolescents, drug abusers, and those suffering from chronic back
      pain.

      In their classic 1989 paper, Walsh and colleagues developed the normative model of the CPT
      demonstrating that variations in response are dependent upon age, sex and ethnicity. In 2004,
      however, Mitchell et al. discovered that the water temperature of the CPT also plays a
      crucial role in the pain tolerance time of the subjects, noting that a temperature variation
      of 4°C produced significantly different results for the same subject. While the Mitchell
      investigations improved upon the standard for the proper CPT technique, as seen implemented
      in the works of Rash and Campbell, their discoveries were based on healthy individuals.

      Researchers have explored the CPT responses of patients with an altered pain perception, such
      as patients with Opioid-Induced Hyperalgesia (OIH), in comparison to healthy controls,
      demonstrating greater sensitivity in OIH patients. What has not been studied is the effect of
      temperature on CPT response in OIH patients. Further, the CPT has been shown to have a
      relatively lengthy recovery time averaging around 10 minutes; however, the recovery time for
      hypersensitive patients, such as OIH patients, has yet to be studied.

      As an extension of the work of Mitchell and colleagues, the proposed research will assess the
      effects of temperature difference and recovery time of the CPT on patients with OIH in
      comparison to healthy normal control patients. This work is a sub-study of a larger study,
      Opioid-Induced Hyperalgesia In Prescription Opioid Abusers: Effects of Pregabalin
      (PRO00000669), conducted by principal investigator Dr. Peggy Compton. The goal of the parent
      study is to evaluate the ability of pregabalin to diminish chronic low back or arthritic pain
      and OIH in a sample of prescription opioid abusers (POAs) opioid therapy. This current study
      is not assigning specific interventions to study subjects. Healthy control and OIH
      participants will complete all study measures in a single two-hour study session.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved Pain Threshold Response</measure>
    <time_frame>1 two-hour study session</time_frame>
    <description>In a well-described sample of prescription opioid abusers and healthy control subjects, the cold pressor test will be administered to examine how long it takes for a subject to start feeling pain when they immerse their forearm in the cold water (measured in seconds).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved Pain Tolerance Response</measure>
    <time_frame>1 two-hour study session</time_frame>
    <description>In a well-described sample of prescription opioid abusers and healthy control subjects, the cold pressor test will be administered to examine how long subjects' can withstand feeling pain when they immerse their forearm in the cold water (measured in seconds).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved Pain Recovery Response</measure>
    <time_frame>1 two-hour study session</time_frame>
    <description>In a well-described sample of prescription opioid abusers and healthy control subjects, the cold pressor test will be administered to examine how long it takes for subjects' to recover from the pain they experienced when they had their forearm immersed in the cold water (measured in seconds).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prescription opioid abusers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients 21-65 years old taking suboxone or methadone, currently experiencing chronic pain, not taking any opioid analgesic medication for painful condition on a regular basis, not have any current psychiatric or neurological illnesses, not have a history of heart disease in order to be healthy enough to complete the cold pressor test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy control participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients 21-65 years old not taking suboxone or methadone, not experiencing chronic pain, not taking any opioid analgesic medication for painful condition on a regular basis, not have any current psychiatric or neurological illnesses, not have a history of heart disease in order to be healthy enough to complete the cold pressor test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cold pressor test</intervention_name>
    <description>The cold pressor test is a procedure used for examining pain threshold and tolerance by subjects placing their forearm in an ice bath. Each participant will take the CPT at 1 °C, 5°C, and 9°C. The first CPT will always be at 1 °C, to ensure participants tolerate the ice bath at the standard temperature. The order of the subsequent CPT at 5°C and 9°C, will be randomized to control for differential carry over effects. Participants will be instructed to say &quot;Pain&quot; when pain is initially detected (threshold). Then they will be asked to keep the immersed limb in the container until the pain can no longer be tolerated and say &quot;Stop&quot; and remove the arm from the water when tolerance is reached.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prescription opioid abusers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy control participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A total of 10 prescription opioid abusers with chronic low back or arthritis pain and
        stable on opioid therapy (on methadone or buprenorphine) will be enrolled in the study.
        Meeting the same inclusion exclusion criteria of the prescription opioid abusers (except
        treatment methadone or buprenorphine), a total of 20 male and female healthy controls will
        be recruited.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between 21 and 65 years old

          -  On suboxone or methadone for at least ten days

          -  Currently experiencing chronic low back or arthritis pain

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Be on any opioid analgesic

          -  Have a neurological or psychiatric illness (i.e., schizophrenia, Raynaud's disease,
             urticaria, stroke) that would affect pain responses

          -  Have an abnormal screening EKG, history of heart disease, stroke, liver or kidney
             disease or acute hepatitis, or currently have a pacemaker or uncontrolled high blood
             pressure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgetown University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington, D.C.</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20057</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahles, T. A., Blanchard, E. B., &amp;Leventhal, H. (1983). Cognitive control of pain: Attention to the sensory aspects of the cold pressor stimulus. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 7(2), 159-177.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellar D, Kamimori GH, Glickman EL. The effects of low-dose caffeine on perceived pain during a grip to exhaustion task. J Strength Cond Res. 2011 May;25(5):1225-8. doi: 10.1519/JSC.0b013e3181d9901f.</citation>
    <PMID>21522070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brands AM, Schmidt AJ. Learning processes in the persistence behavior of chronic low back pain patients with repeated acute pain stimulation. Pain. 1987 Sep;30(3):329-37.</citation>
    <PMID>2959899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang YP, Compton P. Management of chronic pain with chronic opioid therapy in patients with substance use disorders. Addict Sci Clin Pract. 2013 Dec 16;8:21. doi: 10.1186/1940-0640-8-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24341916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chu LF, Clark DJ, Angst MS. Opioid tolerance and hyperalgesia in chronic pain patients after one month of oral morphine therapy: a preliminary prospective study. J Pain. 2006 Jan;7(1):43-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16414554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Compton MA. Cold-pressor pain tolerance in opiate and cocaine abusers: correlates of drug type and use status. J Pain Symptom Manage. 1994 Oct;9(7):462-73.</citation>
    <PMID>7822886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Compton P. Pain tolerance in opioid addicts on and off naltrexone pharmacotherapy: a pilot study. J Pain Symptom Manage. 1998 Jul;16(1):21-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9707654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edens, J. L., &amp; Gil, K. M. (1995). Experimental induction of pain: Utility in the study of clinical pain. Behavior Therapy, 26(2), 197-216.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hellström B, Lundberg U. Pain perception to the cold pressor test during the menstrual cycle in relation to estrogen levels and a comparison with men. Integr Physiol Behav Sci. 2000 Apr-Jun;35(2):132-41.</citation>
    <PMID>11021338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee M, Silverman SM, Hansen H, Patel VB, Manchikanti L. A comprehensive review of opioid-induced hyperalgesia. Pain Physician. 2011 Mar-Apr;14(2):145-61. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21412369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchell LA, MacDonald RA, Brodie EE. Temperature and the cold pressor test. J Pain. 2004 May;5(4):233-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15162346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pomerleau OF, Turk DC, Fertig JB. The effects of cigarette smoking on pain and anxiety. Addict Behav. 1984;9(3):265-71.</citation>
    <PMID>6496202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Radtke T, Eser P, Kriemler S, Saner H, Wilhelm M. Adolescent blood pressure hyperreactors have a higher reactive hyperemic index at the fingertip. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2013 Dec;113(12):2991-3000.</citation>
    <PMID>24077645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walsh NE, Schoenfeld L, Ramamurthy S, Hoffman J. Normative model for cold pressor test. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 1989 Feb;68(1):6-11.</citation>
    <PMID>2917058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolf S, Hardy JD. STUDIES ON PAIN. OBSERVATIONS ON PAIN DUE TO LOCAL COOLING AND ON FACTORS INVOLVED IN THE &quot;COLD PRESSOR&quot; EFFECT. J Clin Invest. 1941 Sep;20(5):521-33.</citation>
    <PMID>16694857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Narcotic abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid related disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Opiate substitution treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Buprenorphine</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregabalin</keyword>
  <keyword>Methadone</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methadone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vasoconstrictor Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

