<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03085849</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAQ8257</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03085849</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SGI-110 Plus Durvalumab/Tremelimumab in SCLC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of SGI-110 Followed by Combined Durvalumab Plus Tremelimumab in Subjects With Extensive-stage Small Cell Lung Cancer (ES-SCLC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Catherine Shu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives

      Dose escalation phase:

      • To estimate the maximum tolerated dose of SGI-110 when given prior to durvalumab and
      tremelimumab, as determined by the rate of DLT

      Dose expansion phase:

      • To estimate the rate of treatment related adverse events for combination therapy with
      SGI-110 (at the MTD), durvalumab, and tremelimumab in order to guide phase 2 trial design

      Secondary Objectives

      Both phases:

        -  To measure changes in expression levels of predicted neoantigens before and after
           epigenetic therapy with SGI-110 by performing WES and RT-PCR on tumor biopsies

        -  To estimate overall response rate (ORR), median duration of response (mDOR), median
           progression-free survival (mPFS), and median overall survival (mOS) with this treatment
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SCLC accounts for approximately 15% of new cases of lung cancer, and an estimated 33,000
      cases are expected to be diagnosed in the United States in 2016.1 Compared to NSCLC, SCLC
      typically has a more rapid doubling time, a higher growth fraction, and earlier development
      of distant metastases. Patients with limited stage (LS) disease are treated with curative
      intent using definitive, concurrent chemotherapy and thoracic radiotherapy. For patients with
      extensive stage (ES) disease, systemic chemotherapy can prolong survival in most cases,
      however long-term survival is rare 2,3. Despite the activity of several agents in SCLC, an
      etoposide plus platinum (i.e. cisplatin) doublet regimen remains the standard of care in the
      first-line setting because of its higher activity compared to other chemotherapy regimens, as
      well as the ease of combining it with radiation. Initial response rates may be as high as
      70-90% in LS-SCLC and 50-70% in ES-SCLC.4 However, the disease typically recurs rapidly which
      is reflected by median survival rates of 9 to 11 months for ES-SCLC and a 2-year survival
      rate of less than 5%.

      This study has a 3 + 3 design that will be used to assess the safety of SGI-110 given prior
      to flat doses of durvalumab (1500 mg) and tremelimumab (75 mg). The starting dose of SGI-110
      will be 30 mg/m2 (dose level 0) and the target dose that is predicted to be safe and most
      effective will be 45 mg/m2 (dose level 1). These doses have been chosen based on safety and
      efficacy data from phase 1 clinical trials in other solid tumors, as described above.
      Patients enrolled in any given dose level will be evaluated for safety (adverse events
      monitoring) and efficacy. There will be mandatory pre- and on-treatment tumor biopsies
      performed in alternating fashion on cycle 1 day 8 +/- 2 days or cycle 2 day 8 +/- 2 days. The
      DLT observation period will last for 4 weeks (28 days) and ends on C2D1. Delayed serious
      immune-mediated adverse events will also be monitored but will not be considered dose
      limiting toxicities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of SGI-110</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the highest dose cohort for SGI-110 with a rate of dose limiting toxicity (DLT) &lt;33%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of treatment related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days after last study dose</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the percentage of patients receiving study treatment and experiencing grade 3-4 treatment related adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months after last study dose</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the proportion of patients with tumor size reduction of a predefined amount and for a minimum time period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median Progression Free Survival (mPFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months after last study dose</time_frame>
    <description>The length of time during and after the treatment of a disease, such as cancer, that a patient lives with the disease but it does not get worse. Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method in number of weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median Overall Survival (mOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months after last study dose</time_frame>
    <description>The length of time from the start of treatment for a disease, such as cancer, that half of the patients in a group of patients diagnosed with the disease are still alive. Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method in number of weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median Duration of Response (mDOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months after last study dose</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of overall response is measured from the time measurement criteria are met for complete response or partial response (whichever is first recorded) until the first date that recurrent or progressive disease is objectively documented (taking as reference for progressive disease the smallest measurements recorded since the treatment started).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Extensive-stage Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects with ES-SCLC, progressive after platinum-based first-line chemotherapy will receive SGI-110 followed by combined durvalumab plus tremelimumab.
Dose escalation phase: 6-12 patients
MTD expansion cohort: 10 patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Durvalumab</intervention_name>
    <description>1500 mg IV on day 8 (flat dose) until progression</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MEDI4736</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tremelimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>75 mg IV on day 8 (flat dose) x 4 doses</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CP-675,206</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SGI-110</intervention_name>
    <description>SC daily for 5 days (days 1-5) until progression or toxicity
Dose escalation scheme:
Dose level -1 - SGI-110 20 mg/m2 SC daily; Dose level 0 - SGI-110 30 mg/m2 SC daily; Dose level 1 - SGI-110 45 mg/m2 SC daily; and SGI-110 given on days 1-5 of every 28 day cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Guadecitabine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For inclusion in the study, patients should fulfill the following criteria:

          1. Written informed consent and any locally-required authorization (e.g., HIPAA in the
             USA, EU Data Privacy Directive in the EU) obtained from the subject prior to
             performing any protocol-related procedures, including screening evaluations

          2. Age ≥ 18 years at time of study entry

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG performance status of 0 or 1)

          4. Life expectancy of ≥ 12 weeks

          5. Adequate normal organ and marrow function as defined below Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL
             Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L (&gt; 1500 per mm3) Platelet count ≥ 100 x
             109/L (&gt;100,000 per mm3) Serum total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x institutional upper limit of
             normal (ULN) (for patients with a diagnosis of Gilbert's syndrome, direct bilirubin ≤
             1.5 x ULN) AST (SGOT)/ALT (SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x institutional upper limit of normal unless
             liver metastases are present, in which case it must be ≤ 5x ULN

             Serum creatinine CL&gt;40 mL/min by the Cockcroft-Gault formula (Cockcroft and Gault
             1976) or by 24-hour urine collection for determination of creatinine clearance:

             Males:

             Creatinine CL (mL/min) = Weight (kg) x (140 - Age) . 72 x serum creatinine (mg/dL)

             Females:

             Creatinine CL (mL/min) = Weight (kg) x (140 - Age) x 0.85 72 x serum creatinine
             (mg/dL)

          6. Females of childbearing potential who are sexually active with a non-sterilized male
             partner must use a highly effective method of contraception from the time of
             screening, and must agree to continue using such precautions for 180 days after the
             final dose of investigational product. Cessation of contraception after this point
             should be discussed with a responsible physician. Periodic abstinence, the rhythm
             method, and the withdrawal method are not acceptable methods of contraception. Female
             subjects must also refrain from egg cell donation for 180 days after the final dose of
             investigational product.

             A) Females of childbearing potential are defined as those who are not surgically
             sterile (i.e. bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy, or complete
             hysterectomy) or those who are not postmenopausal (defined as 12 months with no menses
             with postmenopausal gonadotropin levels [luteinizing hormone and follicle-stimulating
             hormone], or estradiol levels within the postmenopausal range according to local
             guidelines without an alternative medical cause).

             B) A highly effective method of contraception is defined as one that results in a low
             failure rate (i.e. less than 1% per year) when used consistently and correctly.

          7. Subject is willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the study
             including undergoing treatment and scheduled visits and examinations including follow
             up.

          8. Subjects must have a histologically confirmed diagnosis of small cell lung carcinoma.
             A fresh, pre-treatment tumor biopsy will be required to evaluate tumor infiltrating
             lymphocytes, PD-L1 IHC staining, methylation status, etc. as outlined in the study
             timeline. All subjects are also required to have a C1D8 (or C2D8) biopsy.

          9. Subjects must have extensive-stage disease (by NCCN criteria) that is progressive or
             relapsed after platinum-based chemotherapy.

         10. Tumor burden must be radiographically measurable by RECIST criteria.

         11. At time of Day 1 of the study, subjects with central nervous system metastases must
             have been treated and must be asymptomatic and meet the following:

               1. No concurrent treatment, inclusive of but not limited to surgery, radiation,
                  and/or corticosteroids

               2. Neurologic stability (lack of signs and symptoms greater than baseline prior to
                  XRT) until the time of dosing

               3. For radiation treatment, there should be at least 14 days between the last day of
                  stereotactic radiosurgery or gamma-knife treatment and Day 1 of protocol
                  treatment. For WBRT, there should be at least 28 days between last day of WBRT
                  and Day 1 of protocol treatment.

               4. Note: patients with leptomeningeal disease or cord compression are excluded from
                  the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects should not enter the study if any of the following exclusion criteria are
        fulfilled:

          1. Involvement in the planning and/or conduct of the study (applies to both AstraZeneca
             staff and/or staff at the study site).

          2. Previous enrollment in the present study.

          3. Participation in another clinical study with an investigational product during the
             last 4 weeks.

          4. Any previous treatment with a PD1 or PD-L1 inhibitor, including durvalumab or an
             anti-CTLA4, including tremelimumab

          5. Any previous treatment with a hypomethylating agent, including decitabine,
             azacitidine, or SGI-110.

          6. History of another primary malignancy except for:

               -  Malignancy treated with curative intent and with no known active disease ≥ 5
                  years before the first dose of study drug and of low potential risk for
                  recurrence

               -  Adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer or lentigo maligna without evidence
                  of disease

               -  Adequately treated carcinoma in situ without evidence of disease e.g., cervical
                  cancer in situ

          7. Receipt of the last dose of anti-cancer therapy (chemotherapy, immunotherapy,
             endocrine therapy, targeted therapy, biologic therapy, tumor embolization, monoclonal
             antibodies, gamma-knife, other investigational agent) ≤ 14 days prior to the first
             dose of study drug. For WBRT, the washout period is 28 days. Local treatment of
             isolated lesions for palliative RT (by radiotherapy, for example) is acceptable.

          8. Mean QT interval corrected for heart rate (QTc) ≥ 470 ms calculated from
             electrocardiogram (in triplicate, if applicable) using Fredericia's Correction

          9. Liver cirrhosis or chronic liver disease Childs-Pugh B or C.

         10. Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 28 days before the first
             dose of durvalumab or tremelimumab, with the exceptions of intranasal and inhaled
             corticosteroids or systemic corticosteroids at physiological doses, which are not to
             exceed 10 mg/day of prednisone, or an equivalent corticosteroid.

         11. Receipt of the tyrosine kinase inhibitor sunitinib within 90 days before the first
             dose of study therapy.

         12. Any unresolved toxicity ( &gt; CTCAE grade 2) from previous anti-cancer therapy.

         13. Any prior Grade ≥ 3 immune-related adverse event (irAE) while receiving any previous
             immunotherapy agent, or any unresolved irAE &gt;Grade 1

         14. Active or prior documented autoimmune disease within the past 2 years NOTE: Subjects
             with vitiligo, Grave's disease, or psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment (within
             the past 2 years) are not excluded.

         15. Active or prior documented history of pneumonitis or interstitial lung disease.

         16. Active or prior documented inflammatory bowel disease (e.g., Crohn's disease,
             ulcerative colitis)

         17. History of primary immunodeficiency

         18. History of allogeneic organ transplant

         19. History of hypersensitivity to durvalumab, tremelimumab, SGI-110, or any excipient.

         20. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, active peptic ulcer disease or gastritis, active
             bleeding diatheses including any subject known to have evidence of acute or chronic
             hepatitis B, hepatitis C or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), or psychiatric
             illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements or
             compromise the ability of the subject to give written informed consent

         21. Known history of active tuberculosis

         22. Leptomeningeal carcinomatosis or cord compression

         23. Receipt of live attenuated vaccination within 30 days prior to study entry or within
             30 days of receiving durvalumab or tremelimumab

         24. Female subjects who are pregnant or breast-feeding, or male or female patients of
             reproductive potential who are not willing to employ a highly effective method of
             contraception from screening to 180 days after the last dose of investigational
             therapy.

         25. Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with
             evaluation of study treatment or interpretation of patient safety or study results

         26. Symptomatic or uncontrolled brain metastases requiring concurrent treatment (surgery,
             RT, corticosteroids)

         27. Subjects with uncontrolled seizures.

         28. Concomitant use of drugs with laxative properties and/or herbal/natural remedies for
             constipation. These agents should be avoided for 90 days after the last dose of
             investigational therapy, given the potential for exacerbation of diarrhea.

         29. Known significant mental illness or other conditions such as active alcohol or other
             substance abuse/addiction that, in the opinion of the investigator, predisposes the
             subject to high risk of noncompliance with the protocol.

        Procedures for withdrawal of incorrectly enrolled patients are presented in Section 5.5.1.
        If a patient withdraws from participation in the study, then his or her
        enrollment/randomization code cannot be reused. Withdrawn patients will not be replaced.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Catherine Shu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dan Otap</last_name>
    <phone>212.342.3970</phone>
    <email>do2267@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anu Sadhu, BA</last_name>
      <phone>212-342-3747</phone>
      <email>as5055@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Naiyer Rizvi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siegel RL, Miller KD, Jemal A. Cancer statistics, 2016. CA Cancer J Clin. 2016 Jan-Feb;66(1):7-30. doi: 10.3322/caac.21332. Epub 2016 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26742998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chute JP, Chen T, Feigal E, Simon R, Johnson BE. Twenty years of phase III trials for patients with extensive-stage small-cell lung cancer: perceptible progress. J Clin Oncol. 1999 Jun;17(6):1794-801.</citation>
    <PMID>10561217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jänne PA, Freidlin B, Saxman S, Johnson DH, Livingston RB, Shepherd FA, Johnson BE. Twenty-five years of clinical research for patients with limited-stage small cell lung carcinoma in North America. Cancer. 2002 Oct 1;95(7):1528-38.</citation>
    <PMID>12237922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Catherine Shu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tremelimumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azacitidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

