<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03083483</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00078782</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03083483</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Utilizing Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation to Enhance Laparoscopic Technical Skills Training</brief_title>
  <official_title>Utilizing Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation to Enhance Laparoscopic Technical Skills Training</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test the influences of transcranial direct current
      stimulation (tDCS) on the acquisition of laparoscopic surgical skills. For this purpose, the
      investigator will compare variants of tDCS in the first of 2 experiments. The second arm of
      the trial will investigate gaze training in a similar study design. These questions will be
      evaluated using the validated Fundamentals of Laparoscopic Surgery (FLS) module 1, with the
      overall goal of developing a surgical training curriculum that achieves expert level skill in
      an expedited timeframe. This research provides a novel approach to general surgery training
      that has the potential to reduce the amount of time and repetitions required to achieve
      expert laparoscopic skills.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Developing expert performance requires assessment of the thought processes underlying
      performance and continued refinement of skills in order to obtain automaticity and intuition.
      Therefore, developing expert surgical skill is a process likely to take longer than the
      length of residency, thereby diminishing the quality of care delivered to patients.

      The proposed study will implement novel neuroscience techniques of transcranial direct
      current stimulation to determine if it has the capacity to accelerate technical surgical
      skill learning in order to achieve competency and expertise in an earlier timeframe. tDCS is
      a non-invasive brain stimulation technique that delivers constant, low current stimulation
      via electrodes placed on the scalp to modify cortical excitability in an area of interest.
      When applied to the motor cortex, promising data indicates that tDCS-induced changes lead to
      expedited recovery in stroke patients as well as enhanced learning in healthy individuals.

      This technique has never been applied in the training of surgical residents making this
      project an innovative approach to enhance skill development.

      Experiment 1: Determine if tDCS can accelerate the learning of laparoscopic skills.

      In this experiment the investigators will compare behavioral learning curves from FLS modules
      1 and 5 in three cohorts who undergo either active tDCS to the bilateral motor cortex
      (bilateral configuration), active tDCS to the supplementary motor cortex (SMA configuration),
      or sham tDCS (half in each configuration). This will be tested in groups of 20 participants
      who train for 40-minutes in each of 6 sessions that occur within 3 weeks. The investigators
      hypothesize that both active bilateral and SMA tDCS will lead to faster skill acquisition as
      measured by trials required to gain proficient completion scores (calculated as time plus
      errors), relative to sham.

      The investigators hypothesize that both bilateral and vertex tDCS will lead to faster skill
      acquisition, with bilateral greater than vertex as measured by trials required to gain
      proficient module completion scores, relative to the group of participants who practice
      without active tDCS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 21, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 21, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Subjects are randomized into SMA or bilateral M1 tDCS configurations. They are further randomized into active or sham tDCS.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>For the tDCS portion of the protocol, the subject and investigator will be blinded to active vs sham. The configuration and order of FLS tasks will be known to both.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to completion</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be collected for a pre- and post- test repetition prior to and after the 6 separate training sessions which will take place within a 7-day span. This will be evaluated in retrospective review of recorded videos through study completion.</time_frame>
    <description>Completion time for each repetition of FLS tasks 1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of tasks completed</measure>
    <time_frame>The number of completed tasks will be calculated during retrospective review of recorded video through study completion. The six training sessions for data collection will be completed within a 7-day span.</time_frame>
    <description>The number of times each task is completed during the duration of the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of errors</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be collected for every repetition performed during the 6 separate training sessions within a 7-day period. These errors will be defined and retrospective review of recorded video through study completion.</time_frame>
    <description>The number of errors (as defined by FLS) during completion of tasks will be recorded and transitioned into a time addition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">71</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bilateral M1, active tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is an arm of the first phase of the study utilizing tDCS in two different configurations (bilateral M1 vs SMA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SMA, active tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is an arm of the first phase of the study utilizing tDCS in two different configurations (bilateral M1 vs SMA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is an arm of the first phase of the study utilizing tDCS in two different configurations (bilateral M1 vs SMA). Half of these subjects will be placed in the SMA configuration and the other half in the bilateral M1 electrode configuration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS)</intervention_name>
    <description>tDCS will apply a low, direct current for the duration of the study session while the subject is training the specific laparoscopic tasks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bilateral M1, active tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SMA, active tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Soterix</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &gt;18 years, healthy male and female

          2. Negative urine pregnancy test for female participants

          3. Willing and able to provide informed consent

          4. Able to follow study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Indwelling metallic implants

          2. Neurological or psychiatric medical history

          3. Drug or alcohol abuse

          4. Current or prior brain tumor

          5. Current or prior seizures

          6. Neuroactive medications

          7. Current pregnancy

          8. Damage, rash, or skin lesion in area of electrode placement
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Morgan L Cox, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Greg Appelbaum, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

