<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03472924</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>7967</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03472924</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Kinesio Tape® on Arthrogenic Muscle Inhibition and Rate of Torque Development</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Kinesio Tape® on Arthrogenic Muscle Inhibition and Rate of Torque Development</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates whether the use of Kinesio Tape® in combination with a standard exercise
      program improves muscle function in individuals with chronic ankle instability. Twenty
      participants will receive Kinesio Tape® and perform an ankle exercise program, while twenty
      will perform the ankle exercise program without Kinesio Tape®.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Decreased ability to voluntarily activate the entire motoneuron (MN) pool following joint
      injury is known as arthrogenic muscle inhibition (AMI), which is commonly quantified by
      measuring central activation ratio (CAR). AMI is not only observed immediately after joint
      injury, but has been shown to persist during and after rehabilitation. It is proposed that
      AMI, by negatively impacting neuromuscular factors such as muscle strength, muscle
      activation, and rate of torque development (RTD), contributes to a prolonged rehabilitation
      process and higher risk of re-injury. Unfortunately, AMI cannot be reduced by traditional
      rehabilitation interventions such as strength training alone. Therefore, it is necessary to
      identify an intervention that can effectively decrease AMI in order to facilitate
      improvements in muscle function in individuals with AMI.

      Kinesio Tape® is commonly used to facilitate muscle contraction in athletic populations. This
      elastic therapeutic tape is popular in the athletic setting because it can be applied and
      used continually during exercise and activities of daily living for up to 2-3 days without
      restricting movement. It has been suggested that Kinesio Tape® facilitates muscle contraction
      by inducing increased sensory input via skin stimulation. The tape activates cutaneous
      mechanoreceptors with the greater afferent feedback thought to improve the efferent output
      from the central nervous system to the target muscles. While this technique is widely used in
      the clinical setting to improve muscle function, the facilitative effect of Kinesio Tape® has
      not been demonstrated- perhaps due to three key limitations of previous investigations.
      First, previous studies have predominantly recruited healthy participants without muscle
      function deficits. Therefore, there could have been a ceiling effect whereby there was no
      observable effect of Kinesio Tape® due to a lack of muscle dysfunction in these healthy
      individuals. Second, most investigators have generally taken outcome measurements immediately
      before Kinesio Tape® application and less than 24 hours later. This is much shorter than the
      2-3 days that Kinesio Tape® is used clinically and may not be long enough to induce an
      observable, facilitative effect. Finally, the protocols utilized in previous investigations
      also failed to mimic clinical practice by not combining Kinesio Tape® application with a
      therapeutic exercise protocol targeting the inhibited muscle.

      Therefore, the purpose of this study is to investigate the effects of prolonged application
      (&gt; 48hours) of Kinesio Tape® incorporated with a therapeutic exercise protocol on AMI and
      muscle function. To do so, we will use the peroneus longus muscle in individuals with
      functional ankle instability (FAI) as a model, given that AMI has been shown to exist in this
      muscle in individuals with FAI.

      The following specific aims will be tested:

      Aim#1. To investigate the effect of prolonged application (&gt; 48hours) of Kinesio Tape®
      incorporated with a therapeutic exercise protocol on AMI of the peroneus longus in
      individuals with FAI.

      Aim#2. To investigate the effect of prolonged application(&gt; 48hours) of Kinesio Tape®
      incorporated with a therapeutic exercise protocol on peroneus longus muscle function in
      individuals with FAI.

      Our central hypothesis is that prolonged application of Kinesio Tape® in combination with
      therapeutic exercise will diminish AMI and improve muscle function of the inhibited peroneus
      longus muscle.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Central Activation Ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline and 2 days post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Ratio between maximal voluntary evertor torque and torque produced following the application of an exogenous electrical stimulus</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Torque Development</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline and 2 days post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of explosive strength determined by placing a line of best fit to a recorded torque-time curve</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal Voluntary Isometric Contraction</measure>
    <time_frame>Change between baseline and 2 days post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of maximal voluntary isometric torque that participant can produce</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Neural Inhibition</condition>
  <condition>Injuries, Ankle</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kinesio Tape</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Kinesiotaping of the peroneus longus according to the guidelines provided by the Kinesio Taping Association (Kase, K. 2016) followed by standardized set of therapeutic exercises that are commonly implemented in ankle rehabilitation programs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Baseline measures followed by standardized set of therapeutic exercises that are commonly implemented in ankle rehabilitation programs, but no use of kinesiotape.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Kinesiotaping</intervention_name>
    <description>The application of Kinesio Tape® (kinesiotaping) according to the guidelines provided by the Kinesio Taping Association (Kase, K. 2016). A 5 cm width strip of Kinesio Tape® (Kinesio TEX Products, NKT-050, Japan) will be applied from origin (the head of the fibula) to insertion (the medial cuneiform and first metatarsal) of the peroneus longus in a longitudinal direction. The proximal anchors will be applied without tension, and the Kinesio Tape® placed on approximately 50% stretch before being applied over the peroneus longus and the distal anchor point.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kinesio Tape</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kinesio Tape®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. A history of at least one significant ankle sprain on the involved (injured) limb i.
             The initial sprain must have occurred at least 12 months prior to the study enrollment
             ii. Was associated with inflammatory symptoms (pain, swelling, etc.) iii. Created at
             least one interrupted day of desired physical activity.

          2. The most recent injury on the involved (injured) ankle must have occurred more than 3
             months prior to the study enrollment.

          3. A history of the involved (injured) ankle joint 'giving way', and/or recurrent sprain
             and/or 'feelings of instability' on the involved (injured) limb Participants should
             report at least 2 episodes of 'giving way' in the 6 months prior to the study
             enrolment.

          4. Be 18-35 years of age

          5. Have not had a past allergic reaction to Kinesio Tape®

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have a history of previous surgeries to the musculoskeletal structures (i.e., bones,
             joint structures, nerves, etc.) in either lower extremity.

          2. Have a history of a fracture in either lower extremity requiring realignment.

          3. Had acute injury to the musculoskeletal structures of other joints of either lower
             extremity in the previous 3 months which impacted joint integrity and function (i.e.,
             sprains, fractures, etc.) and resulted in at least 1 interrupted day of desired
             physical activity.

          4. Are not able to be matched according to our group allocation procedure

          5. Have had a past allergic reaction to Kinesio Tape®

          6. Currently display symptoms of an acute sprain including swelling, heat, redness, pain,
             discoloration, and/or loss of range of motion or function

          7. Any diagnosed vestibular disorder, Charcot-Marie-Tooth disorder, Ehlers-Danlos, or
             other hereditary nerve, balance or connective tissue disorder

          8. Report a possibility that they may be pregnant as hormonal changes may affect
             ligamentous laxity

          9. Have suffered more than one ankle sprain on the uninvolved limb

         10. Have had an ankle sprain on the uninvolved limb within the past 12 months

         11. Have episodes of giving way of the ankle on the uninvolved limb besides the single
             time when they may have sprained this ankle.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc F Norcross, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marc F Norcross, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>541-737-6788</phone>
    <email>marc.norcross@oregonstate.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97331</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc F Norcross, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>541-737-6788</phone>
      <email>marc.norcross@oregonstate.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akbaş E, Atay AO, Yüksel I. The effects of additional kinesio taping over exercise in the treatment of patellofemoral pain syndrome. Acta Orthop Traumatol Turc. 2011;45(5):335-41. doi: 10.3944/AOTT.2011.2403. Erratum in: Acta Orthop Traumatol Turc. 2011;45(6):471.</citation>
    <PMID>22032998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoshida A, Kahanov L. The effect of kinesio taping on lower trunk range of motions. Res Sports Med. 2007 Apr-Jun;15(2):103-12.</citation>
    <PMID>17578750</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McVey ED, Palmieri RM, Docherty CL, Zinder SM, Ingersoll CD. Arthrogenic muscle inhibition in the leg muscles of subjects exhibiting functional ankle instability. Foot Ankle Int. 2005 Dec;26(12):1055-61.</citation>
    <PMID>16390639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AMI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ankle Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

