<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03479138</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIBSP-ANN-2017-77</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03479138</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-Eosinophilic Neutrophilic Asthma</brief_title>
  <acronym>ANNE</acronym>
  <official_title>Asma Neutrofílica y No Eosinofílica</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundació Institut de Recerca de l'Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Spanish Clinical Research Network - CAIBER</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundació Institut de Recerca de l'Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Define and characterize the neutrophilic phenotype of severe asthma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Neutrophilic asthma (NA) is the asthma phenotype less known, causes a severe disease and does
      not have a specific treatment. Research on the neutrophilia mechanisms, new neutrophil (NEU)
      types and bronchial microbiome, can provide an opportunity to better understand the NA
      pathogenesis.

      OBJECTIVES: 1. To describe the clinical characteristics of NA and its sub-phenotypes
      (SUBSTUDY 1); 2. To determine the NEU types associated with the NA and its sub-phenotypes
      (SUBSTUDY 2); and 3. To identify the bronchial microbiological flora of the NA, specifically
      related to lung microbiome and the immune response against Chlamydia Pneumoniae (SUBSTUDY 3).

      METHODS: Multicenter prospective study including 100 patients with severe asthma (GINA/GEMA
      criteria): 50 with non-neutrophilic asthma (&lt;65% NEU in induced sputum [IS]); and 50 with NA
      (&gt; 64% NEU in IS). SUBSTUDY 1: clinical variables (years of evolution, exacerbations, ACT,
      miniAQLQ), comorbidities (GERD, nasal polyposis, obesity, ASS), pulmonary function (FEV1,
      FENO, TLC, Aspergillus), prick-test and CT scan chest; SUBSTUDY 2 (in IS and plasma):
      apoptotic index by means NE culture and flux cytometer (Annexin-V-FITC), NEU phenotype by
      surface markers (CD16, CD66b, CD62L, HLA-DR, CD177, CD11b, CD63, CXCR2, CXCR4) with density
      gradient study and determination of cytokines (IL-6, IL-8, IL-17, IL-1, IL-22) by ELISA;
      SUBSTUDY 3 (in IS): bronchial microbiome for 16S rRNA by PICRUSt, and anti-Chlamydia
      Pneumoniae IgA by ELISA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phenotype of neutrophils</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the types of neutrophils (in induced sputum and blood) associated with neutrophilic asthma and its subphenotypes according to flow citometry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiome analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To analyse the bronchial microbiological flora of neutrophilic asthma</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical demographic characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the clinical characteristics and natural history of the neutrophilic asthma and its subphenotypes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To describe demographic characteristics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Neutrophilic Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neutrophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients 18 to 80 years old diagnosed of severe asthma, requiring treatment at least with LABA+ high doses ICS, with eosinophil count in blood&lt;300/mm3. They must be ex-smokers with less than 10 packs-year and no other relevant pulmonary disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non neutrophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients 18 to 80 years old diagnosed of severe asthma, requiring treatment at least with LABA+ high doses ICS, with eosinophil count in blood&lt;300/mm3. They must be ex-smokers with less than 10 packs-year and no other relevant pulmonary disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Induced sputum</intervention_name>
    <description>Characterization with flow cytometry of the phenotype of the neutrophils isolated in the sputum, microbiome</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neutrophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non neutrophilic asthma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Induced Sputum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients bewteen 18-80 years with severe asthma.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 - 80 years old

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of asthma (according to spanish guideline GEMA)

          -  Severe persistent asthma (step 5-6 GEMA)

          -  Eosinophils&lt;300/mm3 in peripheral blood

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Respiratory infection during the previous month

          -  Significant lung pathology not attributable to asthma (bronchiectasis with Reiff
             score&gt;3)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de la Santa Creu i Sant Pau. Carrer Mas Casanovas 90.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Astrid Crespo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+34-935565972</phone>
      <email>acrespo@santpau.cat</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.gemasma.com/</url>
    <description>Website of the spanish guideline of asthma</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://ginasthma.org/</url>
    <description>Website of the european guideline of asthma</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nair P, Aziz-Ur-Rehman A, Radford K. Therapeutic implications of 'neutrophilic asthma'. Curr Opin Pulm Med. 2015 Jan;21(1):33-8. doi: 10.1097/MCP.0000000000000120. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25415406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wenzel SE, Szefler SJ, Leung DY, Sloan SI, Rex MD, Martin RJ. Bronchoscopic evaluation of severe asthma. Persistent inflammation associated with high dose glucocorticoids. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1997 Sep;156(3 Pt 1):737-43.</citation>
    <PMID>9309987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simpson JL, Baines KJ, Ryan N, Gibson PG. Neutrophilic asthma is characterised by increased rhinosinusitis with sleep disturbance and GERD. Asian Pac J Allergy Immunol. 2014 Mar;32(1):66-74. doi: 10.12932/AP0322.32.1.2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24641293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaw DE, Berry MA, Hargadon B, McKenna S, Shelley MJ, Green RH, Brightling CE, Wardlaw AJ, Pavord ID. Association between neutrophilic airway inflammation and airflow limitation in adults with asthma. Chest. 2007 Dec;132(6):1871-5. Epub 2007 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>17925424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wenzel SE. Asthma phenotypes: the evolution from clinical to molecular approaches. Nat Med. 2012 May 4;18(5):716-25. doi: 10.1038/nm.2678. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22561835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simpson JL, Powell H, Boyle MJ, Scott RJ, Gibson PG. Clarithromycin targets neutrophilic airway inflammation in refractory asthma. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2008 Jan 15;177(2):148-55. Epub 2007 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>17947611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Polosa R, Thomson NC. Smoking and asthma: dangerous liaisons. Eur Respir J. 2013 Mar;41(3):716-26. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00073312. Epub 2012 Aug 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22903959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sutherland ER, Martin RJ. Asthma and atypical bacterial infection. Chest. 2007 Dec;132(6):1962-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18079229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uddin M, Nong G, Ward J, Seumois G, Prince LR, Wilson SJ, Cornelius V, Dent G, Djukanovic R. Prosurvival activity for airway neutrophils in severe asthma. Thorax. 2010 Aug;65(8):684-9. doi: 10.1136/thx.2009.120741.</citation>
    <PMID>20685741</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newcomb DC, Peebles RS Jr. Th17-mediated inflammation in asthma. Curr Opin Immunol. 2013 Dec;25(6):755-60. doi: 10.1016/j.coi.2013.08.002. Epub 2013 Sep 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24035139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chesné J, Braza F, Mahay G, Brouard S, Aronica M, Magnan A. IL-17 in severe asthma. Where do we stand? Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2014 Nov 15;190(10):1094-101. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201405-0859PP. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25162311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bruijnzeel PL, Uddin M, Koenderman L. Targeting neutrophilic inflammation in severe neutrophilic asthma: can we target the disease-relevant neutrophil phenotype? J Leukoc Biol. 2015 Oct;98(4):549-56. doi: 10.1189/jlb.3VMR1214-600RR. Epub 2015 May 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25977288</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pillay J, Ramakers BP, Kamp VM, Loi AL, Lam SW, Hietbrink F, Leenen LP, Tool AT, Pickkers P, Koenderman L. Functional heterogeneity and differential priming of circulating neutrophils in human experimental endotoxemia. J Leukoc Biol. 2010 Jul;88(1):211-20. doi: 10.1189/jlb.1209793. Epub 2010 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>20400675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beyrau M, Bodkin JV, Nourshargh S. Neutrophil heterogeneity in health and disease: a revitalized avenue in inflammation and immunity. Open Biol. 2012 Nov;2(11):120134. doi: 10.1098/rsob.120134. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23226600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green BJ, Wiriyachaiporn S, Grainge C, Rogers GB, Kehagia V, Lau L, Carroll MP, Bruce KD, Howarth PH. Potentially pathogenic airway bacteria and neutrophilic inflammation in treatment resistant severe asthma. PLoS One. 2014 Jun 23;9(6):e100645. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0100645. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24955983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiley JP, Caler EV. The lung microbiome. A new frontier in pulmonary medicine. Ann Am Thorac Soc. 2014 Jan;11 Suppl 1:S66-70. doi: 10.1513/AnnalsATS.201308-285MG.</citation>
    <PMID>24437410</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marri PR, Stern DA, Wright AL, Billheimer D, Martinez FD. Asthma-associated differences in microbial composition of induced sputum. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2013 Feb;131(2):346-52.e1-3. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2012.11.013. Epub 2012 Dec 23.</citation>
    <PMID>23265859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang YJ, Nariya S, Harris JM, Lynch SV, Choy DF, Arron JR, Boushey H. The airway microbiome in patients with severe asthma: Associations with disease features and severity. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2015 Oct;136(4):874-84. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2015.05.044. Epub 2015 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>26220531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin RJ, Kraft M, Chu HW, Berns EA, Cassell GH. A link between chronic asthma and chronic infection. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2001 Apr;107(4):595-601.</citation>
    <PMID>11295645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brusselle GG, Vanderstichele C, Jordens P, Deman R, Slabbynck H, Ringoet V, Verleden G, Demedts IK, Verhamme K, Delporte A, Demeyere B, Claeys G, Boelens J, Padalko E, Verschakelen J, Van Maele G, Deschepper E, Joos GF. Azithromycin for prevention of exacerbations in severe asthma (AZISAST): a multicentre randomised double-blind placebo-controlled trial. Thorax. 2013 Apr;68(4):322-9. doi: 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2012-202698. Epub 2013 Jan 3.</citation>
    <PMID>23291349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blasi F. Atypical pathogens and respiratory tract infections. Eur Respir J. 2004 Jul;24(1):171-81. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15293621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frehn L, Jansen A, Bennek E, Mandic AD, Temizel I, Tischendorf S, Verdier J, Tacke F, Streetz K, Trautwein C, Sellge G. Distinct patterns of IgG and IgA against food and microbial antigens in serum and feces of patients with inflammatory bowel diseases. PLoS One. 2014 Sep 12;9(9):e106750. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0106750. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25215528</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tuuminen T, Edelstein I, Punin A, Kislova N, Stratchounski L. Use of quantitative and objective enzyme immunoassays to investigate the possible association between Chlamydia pneumoniae and Mycoplasma pneumoniae antibodies and asthma. Clin Microbiol Infect. 2004 Apr;10(4):345-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15059128</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>severe asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>induced sputum</keyword>
  <keyword>asthma phenotypes</keyword>
  <keyword>neutrophilic inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>microbiome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

