<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03470064</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17200175</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03470064</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Predictive Factors of Right Ventricular Function Early After Repair of Tetralogy of Fallot</brief_title>
  <official_title>Predictive Factors of Right Ventricular Function Early After Repair of Tetralogy of Fallot</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to assessing right ventricular function early after surgical repair of
      tetralogy of Fallot and identifying the risk factors associated with development of RV
      dysfunction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The shape of the RV is dramatically modified by surgical repair of CHD, with infundibular
      bulging and apical dilation and deformation, leading to a large range of RV shapes(1,2).
      Moreover, pericardial section and suture during surgery influence RV geometry, as RV is
      normally more con-strained by the pericardium then the LV because of its thinner wall (3).

      Intra cardiac repair(ICR) is the definitive management of TOF. Refinement in surgical
      techniques, advancements in anaesthetic &amp; critical care has resulted in improving survival
      following ICR. Post operative mortality following ICR is reported between 1% - 5% (3). Post
      operative low cardiac output and mortality has been attributed to many factors such as
      anatomical defects with small main pulmonary artery annulus, severe hypoplasia or absent
      right or left pulmonary artery, ventriculotomy and right ventricular (RV) outflow patch,
      myocardial hypoxia during cardiopulmonary bypass, or ARDS (4). Certain patients despite
      satisfactory ICR exhibit difficult post operative course which is characterized by prolonged
      ventilation &amp; inotropic support. These patients have been identified to exhibit features of
      RV dysfunction (low cardiac output, high central venous filling pressure, increased inotropic
      requirement, and prolonged ventilation). Identification of risk factors to characterise this
      subset of patients allows for better allocation of hospital resources, improved outcome, and
      substantially reduced hospital costs. This study will try to identify the risk factors
      associated with development of RV dysfunction &amp; its course over a period of three months in
      patients of tetralogy following ICR.

      MRI is a gold standard for assessment of right ventricular function (5). However, MRI has
      restricted availability, is costly, and there are many patients in whom MRI—non compatible
      devices prohibit its use.

      Because of its complex shape, there is no geometrical assumption that can allow
      quantification of RV volumes and ejection fraction (RVEF) by standard two-dimensional (2D)
      echocardiography. For this reason, surrogate parameters of RV systolic function are used most
      frequently to assess RV systolic function, because they are easy to measure, feasible and
      reproducible. These parameters include:-

        -  Tricuspid annulus movement:- Measurements of tricuspid annulus movement by M-mode
           (tricuspid annular plane systolic excursion [TAPSE]) or tissue Doppler imaging (peak
           systolic velocity [PSV]) are used most frequently to assess RV function; they are highly
           feasible and reproducible. However, several studies have shown their dependence on
           loading condition; TAPSE and PSV values are increased in volume overload and decreased
           in pressure overload (6), independent of RVEF.

      -2D global longitudinal peak systolic strain of the RV lateral wall:- Speckle-tracking
      echocardiography is a new technology that allows quantification of myocardial regional
      deformation. The main advantage compared with tissue Doppler imaging is its angle
      independency; it was also thought to be less load dependent, but further studies demonstrated
      that 2D longitudinal strain values increase in volume overload and decrease in barometric
      overload (7).

      - Isovolumic acceleration time(IVA):- Is a quantitative assessment of RV contractile function
      that is supposed to be unaffected by RV geometry or loading conditions. In patients with
      tetralogy of Fallot, studies have shown a good correlation between pulmonary regurgitation
      severity and IVA (8,9).

      -Myocardial performance index :- Myocardial performance index (MPI) is another tissue
      Doppler-derived parameter of RV systolic function. MPI is calculated using the following
      formula: MPI =(isovolumic contraction time + isovolumic relaxation time)/ejection time (10).

      - Fractional area change:- FAC has been shown to correlate well with RVEF measured by MRI in
      the general population (10).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 29, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of RV function early after surgical repair of tetralogy of fallot</measure>
    <time_frame>within one week postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>the study aim to assess the function of the Right ventricle early after surgical repair of tetralogy of fallot by echocardiography.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow up the course of RV function over a period of three months in patients of tetralogy of fallot following surgical repair .</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>the study aim to follow up the function of the Right ventricle after surgical repair of tetralogy of fallot by echocardiography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Tetralogy of Fallot</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RV Dysfunction</arm_group_label>
    <description>All pediatric patients who present to pediatric cardiothoracic unit, Assiut University Hospital and who meet the listed inclusion and exclusion criteria will be eligible for the study. Patients' charts will be retrieved based on their surgical procedures. The charts will be reviewed and eligible patients will be filtered. The needed variables will be entered into our data base for later data analysis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        1. Pediatric patients up to 12 years old.

          2. Recent echocardiography before the surgery giving detailed data about the components
             congenital anomalies of tetralogy of Fallot and if there are other associated
             congenital anomalies.

          3. Obtaining written informed consent from parents or guardians of all patients
             confirming their willing and comply with study requirements

          4. Parents or guardians of the Patient are willing to comply with all follow-up visits
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Pediatric patients up to 12 years old.

          2. Recent echocardiography before the surgery giving detailed data about the components
             congenital anomalies of tetralogy of Fallot and if there are other associated
             congenital anomalies.

          3. Obtaining written informed consent from parents or guardians of all patients
             confirming their willing and comply with study requirements

          4. Parents or guardians of the Patient are willing to comply with all follow-up visits.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with tetralogy of Fallot who are indicated to palliative procedures and not
             for definitive surgical repair as in case of:-

               -  Neonates with TOF and pulmonary atresia

               -  Children with hypoplastic pulmonary artery

               -  Age less than 3 months who have medically unmanageable hypoxic spells

               -  Infant weight less than 2.5 kg

               -  Abnormal coronary artery anatomy

          2. Patients with TOF who are contraindicated to primary repair as in case of:-

               -  Multiple VSDs

               -  Multiple coexisting intracardiac malformations

               -  Small pulmonary arteries

               -  Very low birth weight

               -  The presence of an anomalous coronary artery

          3. Patient inaccessible for follow-up visits required by protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ehab Zahran, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assiut University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ehab Zahran, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>00201220589292</phone>
    <email>dr.ehabzahran@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assiut University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Asyut</city>
        <zip>71515</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>ehab zahran, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>002/01220589292</phone>
      <email>dr.ehabzahran@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>faculty of medicine faculty of medicine-assiut university</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assiut University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Asyūţ</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tamborini G, Muratori M, Brusoni D, Celeste F, Maffessanti F, Caiani EG, Alamanni F, Pepi M. Is right ventricular systolic function reduced after cardiac surgery? A two- and three-dimensional echocardiographic study. Eur J Echocardiogr. 2009 Jul;10(5):630-4. doi: 10.1093/ejechocard/jep015. Epub 2009 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19252190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eroglu AG, Sarioglu A, Sarioglu T. Right ventricular diastolic function after repair of tetralogy of Fallot: its relationship to the insertion of a 'transannular' patch. Cardiol Young. 1999 Jul;9(4):384-91.</citation>
    <PMID>10476828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Higgins CB. Which standard has the gold? J Am Coll Cardiol. 1992 Jun;19(7):1608-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1534338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carminati M, Pluchinotta FR, Piazza L, Micheletti A, Negura D, Chessa M, Butera G, Arcidiacono C, Saracino A, Bussadori C. Echocardiographic assessment after surgical repair of tetralogy of fallot. Front Pediatr. 2015 Feb 2;3:3. doi: 10.3389/fped.2015.00003. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25699243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jategaonkar SR, Scholtz W, Butz T, Bogunovic N, Faber L, Horstkotte D. Two-dimensional strain and strain rate imaging of the right ventricle in adult patients before and after percutaneous closure of atrial septal defects. Eur J Echocardiogr. 2009 Jun;10(4):499-502. doi: 10.1093/ejechocard/jen315. Epub 2009 Jan 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19155264</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frigiola A, Redington AN, Cullen S, Vogel M. Pulmonary regurgitation is an important determinant of right ventricular contractile dysfunction in patients with surgically repaired tetralogy of Fallot. Circulation. 2004 Sep 14;110(11 Suppl 1):II153-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15364855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eidem BW, O'Leary PW, Tei C, Seward JB. Usefulness of the myocardial performance index for assessing right ventricular function in congenital heart disease. Am J Cardiol. 2000 Sep 15;86(6):654-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10980218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anavekar NS, Gerson D, Skali H, Kwong RY, Yucel EK, Solomon SD. Two-dimensional assessment of right ventricular function: an echocardiographic-MRI correlative study. Echocardiography. 2007 May;24(5):452-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17456062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wheeler M, Leipsic J, Trinh P, Raju R, Alaamri S, Thompson CR, Moss R, Munt B, Kiess M, Grewal J. Right Ventricular Assessment in Adult Congenital Heart Disease Patients with Right Ventricle-to-Pulmonary Artery Conduits. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2015 May;28(5):522-32. doi: 10.1016/j.echo.2014.11.016. Epub 2015 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25648672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leonardi B, Taylor AM, Mansi T, Voigt I, Sermesant M, Pennec X, Ayache N, Boudjemline Y, Pongiglione G. Computational modelling of the right ventricle in repaired tetralogy of Fallot: can it provide insight into patient treatment? Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2013 Apr;14(4):381-6. doi: 10.1093/ehjci/jes239. Epub 2012 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23169758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>ehab abd-alaal zahran</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant lecturer at cardiothoracic surgery department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tetralogy of Fallot</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>This study aims to assessing right ventricular function early after surgical repair of tetralogy of Fallot and identifying the risk factors associated with development of RV dysfunction.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

