<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03473886</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1K23HL135277-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03473886</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Developing a Positive Psychology Intervention to Promote Health Behaviors in Metabolic Syndrome: Proof-of Concept Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>MAPP-II</acronym>
  <official_title>Developing a Positive Psychology Intervention to Promote Health Behaviors in Metabolic Syndrome: Proof-of Concept Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aim #1 (Feasibility; primary aim): To assess the feasibility of the positive
      psychology (PP)-motivational interviewing (MI) group-based physical activity intervention and
      outcome assessments in patients with metabolic syndrome (MetS).

      Hypothesis: The PP exercises and MI-based goal-setting sessions will be feasible: most (≥50%)
      of participants will complete 6/8 exercises/sessions. Furthermore, we will be able to obtain
      objective physical activity measurement follow-up data from at least 80% of enrolled
      participants at 8 weeks.

      Specific Aim #2 (Acceptability): To assess whether the intervention is acceptable to
      participants, as measured by ratings provided after each PP and MI exercise.

      Hypothesis: The intervention will be acceptable: participants will rate each PP and MI
      exercise with a mean score of at least 7 out of 10 on ratings of ease of completion and
      helpfulness.

      Specific Aim #3 (Outcomes): To assess whether this preliminary intervention appears to result
      in improvement of physical activity, related health behaviors (sedentary time, diet quality),
      and psychological well-being (optimism, positive affect, anxiety, depression).

      Hypothesis: The intervention will lead to improvements in physical activity, related health
      behaviors, optimism and positive affect, and reductions in depression and anxiety at 8 weeks
      compared to baseline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this proof-of-concept study, investigators will run two 8-week PP-MI groups (complete n=8
      each, n=16 total) for primary care patients with MetS. Investigators will use ratings of
      feasibility and acceptability for each of the sessions and obtain objective physical activity
      measures pre- and post- group. Investigators will also obtain questionnaire-based information
      related to health behavior adherence and psychological and physical health to ensure the
      feasibility of these methods prior to further testing. Investigators may gather exit
      interview data to assess participant liking, utility, and additional needs, to allow for
      further refinement of the intervention.

      Baseline information about enrolled participants will be obtained from the patients, care
      providers, and the electronic medical record as required for characterization of the
      population. This information will include medical data related to MetS (e.g., blood sugar,
      blood pressure, body mass index, triglycerides, cholesterol), current medications, and
      sociodemographic data (age, gender, race/ethnicity, education, marital status).

      Participants will attend 90-minute groups sessions that will be held at two primary care
      clinics (MGH Healthcare Centers). The overall structure of each session will be: 30 minutes
      for positive psychology exercise review/discussion, 30 minutes for physical activity goal
      setting, education, and discussion, and 30 minutes for a group walk or indoor exercises in
      inclement weather.

      Participants will be asked to wear an Actigraph GT3x+ accelerometer for 1 week at baseline
      and 1 week at follow-up to assess the feasibility of doing so. Accelerometers such as this
      one are considered to be the standard for measuring habitual physical activity. They are
      pedometer-size devices that attach to a belt and are worn at the waist. Participants will
      also be given a Fitbit Zip to keep, which they will be asked to wear daily for the duration
      of the study in order to track their activity (steps).

      Upon beginning the groups, participants will be provided with a treatment manual with weekly
      PP exercises, information about the importance of physical activity and related health
      behaviors, and how to set goals to improve these behaviors. The PI will lead all groups.

      For the first session, in the PP portion, participants will discuss and be assigned the first
      exercise- gratitude for positive events- and will be instructed to complete the PP exercise
      during the next week. Prior to completing the exercise, participants will be asked to rate
      their current levels of happiness and optimism. Immediately after completing the exercise,
      participants will rate the ease of exercise completion, overall utility of the exercise, and
      their current levels of happiness and optimism, all using 10-point Likert scales. In the
      first goal-setting session, we will discuss the importance of physical activity in MetS.
      Participants will be given a Fitbit Zip to keep, which they will use to track the number of
      steps they take each day, for the duration of the study. Investigators will review
      instructions for use and set a goal for monitoring their baseline physical activity over the
      next week. Fitbits will not be used as an outcome measure but as a tool that participants can
      use to monitor their activity and set goals. Finally, the last 30 minutes will be spent doing
      a group walk around the local clinic neighborhood. All group walks and exercises will be done
      at a pace comfortable for participants.

      Participants will be asked to complete the 8 total weekly PP exercises, set physical activity
      goals, and attend as many group sessions as they can.

      All sessions will include (a) a review and discussion of the past week's PP exercise, (b) a
      discussion of the rationale of the next week's PP exercise using the PP manual, and (c)
      assignment of the next week's PP exercise. For the goal-setting/MI portion, participants will
      (a) review their goals and steps from the prior week, (b) discuss techniques for improving
      physical activity (e.g., monitoring physical activity, taking standing breaks), and (c) set
      goals for the next week. The exercises and content for both PP and MI will be assigned in the
      same order for all participants receiving them.

      Immediately after the week 8 session, investigators will distribute the same self-report
      questionnaires that were administered at baseline (before week 1). The Actigraphs will then
      be collected at this point and the data will be uploaded to assess for valid wear time. If
      participants have not worn them for enough time (&gt;4 days), investigators will send it home
      with them and ask them to re-wear it and mail it back.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 27, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the PP-MI-Based Health Behavior Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks of group sessions</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be measured by examining the number of completed exercises.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked for feedback related to the program and study procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity Adherence (Actigraph)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ActiGraph GT3X+ accelerometers are validated as measures of physical activity and have been used in numerous studies of physical activity in patients with medical illness. In this trial, participants will wear the accelerometer to assess the feasibility of doing so and to ensure adequate capture of physical activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of Actigraph</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be measured by examining the rates of use of the Actigraph.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Life Orientation Test- Revised Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The LOT-R is a well-validated 6-item instrument used to measure dispositional optimism. (Range: 5-30)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Positive and Negative Affect Schedule Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The positive affect items on the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule (PANAS), a well-validated scale used in other intervention trials, will be used to measure positive affect. (Range: 10-50)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The HADS will be used to measure depression and anxiety. This is a well-validated scale with few somatic symptom items that can confound mood/anxiety assessment in medically-ill patients. (Range: HADS-A, HADS-D; 0-21 each)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in The Neighborhood Environment Walkability Scale-Abbreviated Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The NEWS-A will be used to measure residents' perceptions of neighborhood design related to physical activity, including places for walking and cycling, aesthetics, traffic hazards, and crime. (Range: 16-64)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Barriers to Being Active Quiz Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The BBAQ is a 21-item measure, published by the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), that explores seven main categories of barriers, including lack of time, energy, and resources. (Range: 0-63)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in The Medical Outcomes Study Short Form-12 Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-12 will be used to measure quality of life. This instrument has been used in many patient-oriented studies. (Range: SF-12 PCS and SF-12 MCS); range 0-100 each)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in The International Physical Activity Questionnaire-Short Form Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-baseline screening and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The IPAQ-SF is a validated scale that measures self-reported physical activity in the past 7 days in the domains of vigorous activity, moderate activity, and walking.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in The Community Healthy Activities Model Program for Seniors Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The CHAMPS is a checklist of physical and social activities completed in the past week. CHAMPS includes strength and flexibility items and is designed to detect changes in physical activity among older adults.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System Fruit and Vegetable Module</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The CDC's BRFSS Fruit and Vegetable Module is a brief questionnaire about frequency of eating different types of fruits and vegetables.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in National Cancer Institute's Percentage Energy from Fat Screener Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The National Cancer Institute's Percentage Energy from Fat Screen is a brief questionnaire that estimates people's typical percentage of energy derived from eating common fat-containing foods, as fat content is related to metabolic syndrome progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm: PP-MI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will complete an 8-week group physical activity and positive psychology program, in which they will complete exercises related to increasing positive emotions and physical activity during and between the group sessions. They will track their activity (steps) and set personalized physical activity goals each week, as complete a group walk or indoor exercise during the group sessions. We will ask questions about participants' health and health behaviors, and ask them to wear a physical activity monitor at the beginning and end of the program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intervention arm: PP-MI</intervention_name>
    <description>The positive psychology exercises include gratitude-based activities, strengths-based activities, and meaning-based activities. The physical activity goal setting exercises include the following topics: health benefits, social resources, and neighborhood walkability.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm: PP-MI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • Both of the two MetS components most strongly related to MetS outcomes and most sensitive
        to lifestyle change:

          -  elevated abdominal obesity (waist circumference &gt;102 cm in men or &gt;88 cm in women)

          -  If waist circumference is not available, body mass index (BMI) will be used as a
             surrogate measure based on prior research (BMI ≥29.1 kg/m2 for men and 27.2 kg/m2 for
             women).

        AND

        - elevated blood pressure (systolic ≥130 and/or diastolic ≥85 mm Hg or be on blood pressure
        medication).

          -  Plus ≥1 additional MetS component:

               -  Serum triglycerides ≥150 mg/dL

               -  High-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol &lt;40 mg/dL in men or &lt;50 mg/dL in women

               -  Fasting plasma glucose &gt;100mg/dL.

          -  Suboptimal physical activity defined as ≤150 minutes/week moderate intensity activity,
             which represents less than national-level recommendations.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to speak/read English

          -  Cognitive deficits impeding ability to participate or provide informed consent
             (measured by a 6-item screen)

          -  Illness likely to lead to death in the next 6 months per PCP

          -  Current treatment for cancer, liver, or renal disease

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Documented severe mental illness (e.g., psychosis, suicidality)

          -  No telephone access

          -  Inability to be physically active

          -  Diabetes or known or suggested cardiac disease, given that this is a primary
             prevention study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rachel Millstein, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rachel Millstein, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>617-724-2047</phone>
    <email>ramillstein@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jeff Huffman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-724-2910</phone>
    <email>jhuffman@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel Millstein, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-2047</phone>
      <email>ramillstein@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rachel Millstein</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant in Psychology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome X</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

