<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03479775</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>929-13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03479775</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Muscle Function and Traumatic Knee Injury in Sports</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Muscle Function as a Potential Risk and/or Protective Factor for Traumatic Knee Injury in Youth Female Athletes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lund University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lund University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aims of the project are to 1) evaluate different aspects of muscle function and its role
      as a potential risk and/or protective factor for traumatic knee injury in youth female
      athletes; 2) develop and evaluate a battery of muscle function tests, easily used and
      requiring minimal equipment, to be applied as an on-the-field screening tool to detect muscle
      function deficiencies and monitoring youth female athletes at high risk of traumatic knee
      injury.

      A prospective cohort design will be used, including approximately 100 female athletes (age
      15-19) from Swedish senior sports high schools who are involved in high risk sports (soccer,
      handball, floorball and basket). A test battery for muscle function has been developed
      consisting of 11 tests that previously have been used for the assessment of muscle function.
      The tests will be instructed and supervised by educated test leaders. Measurements will take
      place at the athletes' school and carried out during the first semester (autumn 2017 and
      2018). Data on injury surveillance and exposure (hours of match and training participation)
      will be collected prospectively over two years using a web-designed registration form. All
      athletes will on a weekly basis report their hours of training, minutes of match play and all
      time-loss injuries occurring during sport activity. Details on injury mechanism and diagnosis
      will be collected by each school's medical staff. The present study will contribute new
      knowledge on the role of muscle function and develop and evaluate a battery of muscle
      function tests to be used as an on-the-field screening tool for monitoring youth female
      athletes at high risk of traumatic knee injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A prospective cohort design will be used for the present study comprising approximately 100
      (determined by power analysis) female athletes (age 15-19) from Swedish senior high schools
      who are involved in high risk sports (soccer, handball, floorball and basket). The study
      started autumn 2017 with assessment of muscle function at baseline, instructed and supervised
      by two test leaders. Before the test session the athlete will be informed and tutored about
      the injury and exposure registration procedure. Measurements takes place in a secluded room
      at the athletes' school and will be carried out during the first semester (autumn 2017 and
      2018). Data relating to sport affiliation, number of years of specific sport training, the
      number of training hours per week and her/his training routines, level of competition and
      participation in other sports, age, body weight and height will also be conducted using a
      questionnaire. After the baseline assessment, the athletes will participate in a continuous
      web based prospective injury registration protocol and be followed for two years.

      Outcome measures Data on injury surveillance and exposure (hours of match and training
      participation) will be collected prospectively over two years using a web-designed (REDCap
      Software) registration form. All athletes will on a weekly basis report their hours of
      training, minutes of match play and all time-loss injuries occurring during sport activity.
      Details on injury mechanism, nature, and diagnosis will be collected by each school's medical
      staff. The outcome of interest is a traumatic knee injury, i.e., ACL or other ligament
      injury, meniscal, cartilage damage or fracture, diagnosed by physical examination and/or MRI,
      arthroscopy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 12, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>2 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Traumatic knee injury assessed by a web-designed (REDCap Software) registration form</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle strength will be assessed using an isometric handheld dynamometer (Commander Echo, JTECH Medical, Salt Lake City, Utah, USA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Collected during 2 month at 1 session</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscular endurance and neuromuscular tests will be video-recorded using the Coach Eye app for smart phone</measure>
    <time_frame>Collected during 2 month at 1 session</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>ACL Injury</condition>
  <condition>Meniscus Lesion</condition>
  <condition>Cartilage Injury</condition>
  <condition>Ligament Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Youth female athletes with poor muscle function</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Youth female athletes with good muscle function</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Female athletes (age 15-19) from Swedish senior high schools who are involved in high risk
        sports (soccer, handball, floorball and basket).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female high-school athlete

          -  age 15-19 y

          -  must play soccer, handball, floorball or basketplayer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  illness, which might affect the test results

          -  injury to the lower extremity at the time of baseline data collection -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>19 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sofia Ryman Augustsson</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Lunds University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sofia Ryman Augustsson</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lund</city>
        <zip>22100</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Knee Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anterior Cruciate Ligament Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

