<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03478527</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ProBrain01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03478527</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Probiotics, Brain Structure and Psychological Variables</brief_title>
  <acronym>ProBrain01</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Probiotic Bacteria on Brain Structure and Function and on Psychological Variables</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Theory and research on the gut-brain-axis emphasizes complex interactions between the gut
      microbiota, immunological and hormonal responses, brain function, brain structure, as well as
      resulting behavioral manifestations, such as cognitive functions and mental illness.
      Probiotics are living micro-organisms that change the composition of the gut microbiota and
      have a positive effect on the host's general health and well-being. Probiotic bacteria
      naturally occur in foods such as Sauerkraut, olives, and dark chocolate, and are currently
      also added to industrial products.

      Regarding the effect of probiotics on brain structure and function, animal studies have shown
      that the administration of probiotics in mice and rats was linked to neurogenesis in the
      hippocampus and and improvement of associated cognitive functions. The majority of these
      studies applied probiotics for 4 weeks. The substances used in these studies were often
      composed of several bacterial strains, suggesting that the neurogenic effect may not be
      reducible to a specific type of probiotic bacteria. In addition, probiotics seem to be
      effective in improving memory abilities, including spatial and non-spatial memory both in
      rodents and humans. Regarding mental illness, in comparison to animal studies for beneficial
      effect of probiotics on anxiety, depression and stress, the evidence in humans is compelling,
      but methodologically sound (randomized-controlled trial [RCT], double blind) studies are
      still lacking.

      To sum up, the present study is going to be the first RCT with human participants that
      investigates structural and functional changes of the hippocampus through probiotic bacteria,
      using Magnet Resonance Imaging (MRI). In addition, the study aims at advancing research in
      the field by investigating probiotic effects on a broader spectrum of cognitive functions,
      particularly those associated with hippocampal activity (e.g. spatial memory, verbal memory).
      In addition, effects on several types of mental illness (e.g. anxiety, depression, stress)
      will be studied. Furthermore potential mechanisms that may promote the aforementioned effects
      will be examined by investigating changes in immunological parameters, the 'brain derived
      neurotrophic factor' (BDNF), and oxytocin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A double-blind RCT intervention study will be conducted to investigate the effect of a
      probiotic dietary supplement vs. a placebo (powdered milk), taken by healthy human
      participants (N = 60) for 28 days. Both substances are administered in doses of 4.4g per day.
      The probiotics dietary supplement used in the present study is a freely available product
      sold under the name of Vivomixx®. It contains eight bacterial strains: Lactobacilli (L.
      paracasei, L. plantarum, L. acidophilus und L.delbrueckii subsp. bulgaricus), Bifidobacteria
      (B. longum, B. infantis, B. breve), and Streptococcus thermophiles. This product was chosen,
      because another supplement with an identical composition of bacteria as Vivomixx® was found
      to be linked to hippocampal neurogenesis in mice. The placebo milk powder contains no
      probiotic bacteria. It is a commercial baby food product; brand name Bebivita®, product name
      'Anfangsmilch'.

      First, participants will be screened online for eligibility (T0). Before and after the 28-day
      intake period, participants are asked to perform several cognitive tests and fill out
      questionnaires (T1, T2) at our laboratory (ca. 2 hours). Afterwards, blood samples will be
      drawn (ca. 5 minutes) and a magnet resonance tomography (MRT) session (ca. 1.5 hours) will be
      conducted, where participants will perform an object pattern separation task in the scanner
      (T1, T2). Furthermore, a follow-up after 1 month (T3), including the same assessments as at
      T1 and T2, will be conducted.

      During the intake period participants will fill out a brief questionnaire on a weekly basis,
      which includes an assessment of state depressiveness and anxiety, defecation (control item to
      rule out adverse effects), recent (start of) intake of medication, recent (onset of) intake
      of antibiotics, and recent intercurrent illness (e.g. influenza). In addition, participants
      will record their food intake (protocol) for one week (7 consecutive days) during the intake
      period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 8, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>1 Verum group, receiving the probiotic Vivomixx®
1 Placebo group, receiving a milk powder placebo (Bebivita® Anfangsmilch)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>double blind</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in hippocampal volume, assessed via Magnet Resonance Imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increases in hippocampal volume in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) will be analyzed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in functional brain activation during fMRI task</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increases in functional connectivity (using BOLD signal) in hippocampal regions in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) during pattern separation fMRI task will be analyzed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in depression</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>decreases in levels of depression, assessed with Beck's Depression Inventory - II Revised (BDI-II-R) sum score in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) will be analyzed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in spatial navigation</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increases in test performance scores (number of correct responses, degree of accuracy measured as position hits) in the Tunnel task in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) are expected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Interleukin-6 (IL-6)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>decreases in IL-6 blood serum concentration levels in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) are expected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in IL-1ß</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>decreases in IL-1ß blood serum concentration levels in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) are expected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Tumor Necrosis Factor alpha (TNF-alpha)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>decreases in TNF-alpha blood serum concentration levels in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) are expected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor (BDNF)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increases in blood serum level concentration of BDNF in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) are expected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in verbal learning test performance</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increases in verbal learning performance score, assessed with the Verbal Learning Memory Test (VLMT) in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) are expected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in pattern separation fMRI task</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increases in the pattern separation task performance (no. of correct responses to picture stimuli) in in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) are expected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Oxytocin (OXT)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increases in blood serum concentration levels of OXT in verum experimental group (in comparison to placebo control) are expected (as compared to placebo control)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Processing speed or performance IQ</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increases in processing speed assessed by a digit-symbol test (BIS; Berliner Intelligenzskala) in verum experimental group (as compared to placebo control)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in cognitive emotion regulation - functional emotion regulation</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>increase in functional emotion regulation questionnaire sum score (as assessed with the Cognitive Emotion Regulation Questionnaire; CERQ) in verum experimental group (as compared to placebo control)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sleepiness</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>decrease in sleepiness questionnaire sum score (ESS; Epworth Sleepiness Scale) scores in verum experimental group (as compared to placebo control)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in cognitive emotion regulation - dysfunctional emotion regulation</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (day 0) after intake period (day 28) and at follow up (day 84)</time_frame>
    <description>decrease in dysfunctional emotion regulation questionnaire sum score (as assessed with the Cognitive Emotion Regulation Questionnaire; CERQ) in verum experimental group (as compared to placebo control)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Verum condition probiotics</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The verum condition in the present study is a freely available probiotic product sold under the name of Vivomixx®. It contains eight bacterial strains: Lactobacilli (L. paracasei, L. plantarum, L. acidophilus und L.delbrueckii subsp. bulgaricus), Bifidobacteria (B. longum, B. infantis, B. breve), and Streptococcus thermophiles. 30 Participants will be randomly assigned to that condition. The intake period is 28 days, dose = 4.4g.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the placebo condition participants will receive a milk powder that contains no probiotic bacteria. It is a commercial baby food product Bebivita® Anfangsmilch (milk powder). 30 Participants will be randomly assigned to that condition. The intake period is 28 days, dose = 4.4g.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vivomixx®</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will take in a dose of 4.4g for 28 consecutive days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Verum condition probiotics</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>probiotic dietary supplement</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bebivita® Anfangsmilch (milk powder)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will take in a dose of 4.4g for 28 consecutive days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo condition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  healthy participants

          -  age 18-40

          -  informed consent for all parts of the study (including MRT)

          -  none of the exclusion criteria (see below) fulfilled

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age &lt; 18 or &gt; 40 years

          -  pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  left-handedness

          -  degenerative or inflammatory diseases of the central nervous system

          -  severe cognitive/ neuropsychological impairment

          -  severe pain syndrome or other severe organic diseases

          -  epilepsy

          -  (past or present) psychiatric disorders

          -  neurological disorder

          -  severe diabetic polyneuropathy

          -  malignancies/ cancer

          -  cardiac insufficiency

          -  arterial hypertension

          -  heart attack/ stroke

          -  severe hepatic or renal insufficiency

          -  diseases of the hemopoietic system

          -  alcoholism/ drug addiction

          -  medical history of severe allergic or toxic reactions

          -  current participation in drug trial

          -  doubts about legal capacity/ capability of understanding

          -  referral to institutions based on court/ official order

          -  treatment with centrally acting medication (e.g. antipsychotics, antiepileptics,
             antidepressants, etc.)

          -  non-removable metal pieces (aneurysm clips, artificial limbs, etc.) or implanted
             electronic devices (pacemaker, osmotic or other implanted pumps, cochlear implants,
             etc.)

          -  claustrophobia

          -  acute (respiratory) infection, physical uneasiness

          -  tattoos in the head region, permanent make-up

          -  non-removable piercings

          -  chronic/ acute gastrointestinal diseases

          -  vegetarianism, veganism

          -  current intake of antibiotics or intake of antibiotics at any time point during the
             last 2 months

          -  lactose intolerance

          -  general focus on probiotic diet
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simone Kühn, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf, Klinik und Poliklinik für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie, UKE Martinistraße 52, 20246 Hamburg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leonie Ascone Michelis, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 152 51 93 84 24</phone>
    <email>l.ascone-michelis@uke.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf, Klinik und Poliklinik für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jürgen Gallinat, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0) 40 7410 - 52205</phone>
      <email>j.gallinat@uke.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buffington SA, Di Prisco GV, Auchtung TA, Ajami NJ, Petrosino JF, Costa-Mattioli M. Microbial Reconstitution Reverses Maternal Diet-Induced Social and Synaptic Deficits in Offspring. Cell. 2016 Jun 16;165(7):1762-1775. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2016.06.001.</citation>
    <PMID>27315483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>El Aidy S, Dinan TG, Cryan JF. Immune modulation of the brain-gut-microbe axis. Front Microbiol. 2014 Apr 7;5:146. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2014.00146. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24778631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Foster JA, McVey Neufeld KA. Gut-brain axis: how the microbiome influences anxiety and depression. Trends Neurosci. 2013 May;36(5):305-12. doi: 10.1016/j.tins.2013.01.005. Epub 2013 Feb 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23384445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu J, Sun J, Wang F, Yu X, Ling Z, Li H, Zhang H, Jin J, Chen W, Pang M, Yu J, He Y, Xu J. Neuroprotective Effects of Clostridium butyricum against Vascular Dementia in Mice via Metabolic Butyrate. Biomed Res Int. 2015;2015:412946. doi: 10.1155/2015/412946. Epub 2015 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26523278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu WH, Chuang HL, Huang YT, Wu CC, Chou GT, Wang S, Tsai YC. Alteration of behavior and monoamine levels attributable to Lactobacillus plantarum PS128 in germ-free mice. Behav Brain Res. 2016 Feb 1;298(Pt B):202-9. doi: 10.1016/j.bbr.2015.10.046. Epub 2015 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26522841</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Möhle L, Mattei D, Heimesaat MM, Bereswill S, Fischer A, Alutis M, French T, Hambardzumyan D, Matzinger P, Dunay IR, Wolf SA. Ly6C(hi) Monocytes Provide a Link between Antibiotic-Induced Changes in Gut Microbiota and Adult Hippocampal Neurogenesis. Cell Rep. 2016 May 31;15(9):1945-56. doi: 10.1016/j.celrep.2016.04.074. Epub 2016 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27210745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wallace CJK, Milev R. The effects of probiotics on depressive symptoms in humans: a systematic review. Ann Gen Psychiatry. 2017 Feb 20;16:14. doi: 10.1186/s12991-017-0138-2. eCollection 2017. Review. Erratum in: Ann Gen Psychiatry. 2017 Mar 7;16:18.</citation>
    <PMID>28239408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang H, Lee IS, Braun C, Enck P. Effect of Probiotics on Central Nervous System Functions in Animals and Humans: A Systematic Review. J Neurogastroenterol Motil. 2016 Oct 30;22(4):589-605. doi: 10.5056/jnm16018. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27413138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Probiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychiatric Symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Function</keyword>
  <keyword>Hippocampus</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxytocin</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunological Parameters</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

