<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03470818</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16.081</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03470818</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Applying Flipped Classroom Concepts to Simulation: the Effect of Pre-teaching Medical Content on Resident Acquisition and Retention of Non-technical Skills</brief_title>
  <acronym>Flipped Sim</acronym>
  <official_title>Applying Flipped Classroom Concepts to Simulation: the Effect of Pre-teaching Medical Content on Resident Acquisition and Retention of Non-technical Skills</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to assess if letting learners know in advance what
      medical illnesses will be practiced in an upcoming simulation session and providing them with
      instruction regarding that medical content ahead of time (flipped classroom model) will allow
      them to focus on the application of Crisis Resource Management (CRM) principles during a
      simulation session and result in an increase retention of theses skills. Secondary objectives
      of this study are to assess the relationship between the study intervention and learners'
      emotional responses and its impact on the retention of non-technical skills, in occurrence
      CRM
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The term &quot;flipped classroom&quot; refers to courses where basic educational content has been
      removed from the in-class schedule and has instead been provided in advance for learners to
      review prior to face-to-face interaction with the instructor. Consequently, during class
      time, learners use time ordinarily spent in lecture to instead practice applying their
      knowledge.

      Although this methodology has been mainly described in classroom-based instruction, the
      underlying theory can conceptually apply to simulation training in the context of medical
      education. Too often, and especially with junior learners, time during simulation instruction
      is spent giving feedback directed at performance gaps caused by a lack of medical knowledge
      (e.g. medication dose, treatment plan, etc.). Unfortunately, teaching medical knowledge
      during debriefings takes away from the time spent practicing and discussing non-technical
      skills (NTS) such as communication, leadership, etc. If the objectives of a simulation
      session are directed towards increasing competencies in NTS (e.g., Crisis Resource Management
      [CRM]), efforts should be made to maximize the time spent on the application of these skills.
      Ensuring that learners possess the medical knowledge required to accomplish the task work of
      a case (e.g. diagnosis, treatment, etc.) beforehand could help focus their attention on
      teamwork competencies and result in educational gains.

      The benefit of applying a flipped classroom model to simulation-based CRM instruction is
      anchored in two hypotheses:

        1. The Cognitive Load Theory Hypothesis: Applying a flipped classroom model to CRM training
           could decrease the load imposed on learners' cognitive processes. According to this
           theory, working memory has a finite capacity and can only take on a certain load. When
           it is overloaded, new information cannot be processed and learning is impeded.
           Temporally separating the instructional content could help learners concentrate on the
           intended learning objectives of a simulation exercise designed to practice CRM skills.
           This could lead to enhanced proficiency and retention of these skills.

        2. The Control Value Theory of Achievement Emotions Hypothesis: Achievement emotions are
           defined as emotions induced by learning activities or their outcomes. They are generated
           when performances of students are appraised according to a standard of excellence.
           Central to this theory is that &quot;[…] individuals experience specific achievement emotions
           when they feel in control of, or out of control of, achievement activities and outcomes
           that are subjectively important to them […]&quot;. Negative emotions, such as anxiety, have
           been shown to reduce the cognitive resources available for learning. Providing
           preparatory instruction could regulate learners' stress response and reduce its impact
           on learning. In fact, increasing learners' knowledge of what will happen during
           simulation training can enhance their perceived control over the learning experience and
           limit the emergence of anticipatory anxiety. The act of sharing information prior to
           simulation training may also been seen as a gesture of transparency on the instructor's
           behalf. This has the potential to realign the perceived role of the instructor to a
           coaching instead of a judging role. A shared understanding of the upcoming learning
           experience may lessen socioevaluative anxiety by emphasizing the formative nature of the
           activity.

      This study specifically tries to provide an answer to this research question: &quot;Does providing
      preparatory instruction regarding the medical content of a simulation case to junior medical
      residents allow learners to focus more on Crisis Resource Management (CRM) principles thus
      resulting in an increase retention of Crisis Resource Management (CRM) skills three months
      after a technology-enhanced simulation session aimed at the acquisition of CRM competencies?&quot;

      The research question and underlying hypotheses will be tested in a between-subjects
      experimental design using a mixed-method approach. Subjects will be randomly allocated to an
      intervention (i.e. &quot;flipped simulation&quot;) or a control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Crisis Resource Management skills</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
    <description>The between group difference in Crisis Resource Management skills three months post instruction measured by the overall Ottawa Crisis Resource Management Global Rating Scale mean score
Scale ranges: 1 - 7
Higher scores are associated with better performance</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Crisis Resource Management skills</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in mean scores on the Ottawa Crisis Resource Management Global Rating Scale subcategories for the instructional and assessment sessions
Scale ranges: 1 - 7
Higher scores are associated with better performance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress response with salivary cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group difference in stress response (i.e. Peak minus baseline State Trait Anxiety Inventory score) during the instructional session and the learning assessment at 3 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress response with State Trait Inventory Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group difference in stress response (i.e. Peak minus baseline State Trait Anxiety Inventory score) during the instructional session and the learning assessment at 3 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress response difference with State Trait Anxiety Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group difference in the mean change in stress response between the instructional session and the learning assessment at 3 months as measured by the State Trait Anxiety Inventory (i.e. State Trait Anxiety Inventory stress response for the assessment session minus the State Trait Anxiety Inventory stress response for the instructional session)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress response difference with salivary cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group difference in the mean change in stress response between the instructional session and the learning assessment at 3 months as measured by cortisol levels (i.e. Cortisol stress response for the assessment session minus the cortisol stress response for the instructional session)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emotional response assessed with the Achievement Emotion Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group difference in the incidence of specific achievement emotions before, during and after the Crisis Resource Management simulation training and the learning assessment at 3 months as specified in the Achievement Emotion Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in the qualitative themes obtained through semi-structure interviews for each groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Crisis Resource Management</condition>
  <condition>Flipped Classroom</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Preparatory instructional videos (flipped classroom model)
32 participants
Application of a flipped classroom model
Prior to the simulation session, the intervention group will have received the study intervention. This consists in the provision of preparatory instruction about the medical knowledge required to complete the task work of the upcoming simulated acute care clinical situation. The format used to convey this off-loaded educational content will be short (approximately 15 minutes) narrated video PowerPoint presentations; every relevant medical situation incorporated in the simulation case will have a dedicated video presentation.
These videos will be available to the intervention group participants on a web-based platform one week prior to the simulation session</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham videos
Participants in the control group will also be called to watch an online video prior to the simulation activity. However, this video presentation will not have any form of information regarding the upcoming simulation case; it will be an introductory video discussing the capacities of the simulation facility.
This will limit any unwanted &quot;snowball&quot; effect where discussion between research participants could lead the control group participants to inquire about a video presentation that they would not exposed to.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Preparatory instructional videos (flipped classroom model)</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention consists in the provision of preparatory instruction about the medical knowledge required to complete the task work of the upcoming simulated acute care clinical situation. The format used to convey this off-loaded educational content will be short (approximately 15 minutes) narrated video PowerPoint presentations; every relevant medical situation incorporated in the simulation case will have a dedicated video presentation.
These videos will be available to the intervention group participants on a web-based platform one week prior to the simulation session</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham video</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the control group will be called to watch an online video prior to the simulation activity. However, this video presentation will not have any form of information regarding the upcoming simulation case; it will be an introductory video discussing the capacities of the simulation facility. This will limit any unwanted &quot;snowball&quot; effect where discussion between research participants could lead the control group participants to inquire about a video presentation that they would not exposed to.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  First year residents in any surgical or medical specialty (including family medicine)
             that are required to achieve competencies in CRM skills per residency program
             requirements

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  endocrine disorders affecting cortisol metabolism (i.e., hypo/hyperthyroidism,
             Cushing's syndrome/disease, adrenal insufficiency, etc.)

          -  Corticosteroid therapy (except for topical)

          -  Use of drugs interfering with physiologic stress response (i.e., antidepressant
             medication, benzodiazepines, beta-blockers, calcium channel blockers, etc.)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Knowledge of the simulation scenarios before study inclusion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicholas Robillard, MD</last_name>
    <phone>514-890-8000</phone>
    <email>n.robillard@umontreal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2X 3E4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicholas Robillard, MD</last_name>
      <phone>514-890-8000</phone>
      <email>n.robillard@umontreal.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Medical Education</keyword>
  <keyword>Flipped Classroom</keyword>
  <keyword>Anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>Simulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Achievement Emotions</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

