<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03473236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4004002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03473236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1A Safety Trial of Inhaled PK10571</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1A Single Ascending Dose and Multiple Ascending Dose Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Randomized Trial of Oral Inhalation PK10571 in Healthy Adult Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gossamer Bio Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pulmokine Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Worldwide Clinical Trials</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gossamer Bio Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 1A randomized double blind placebo controlled single ascending dose and
      multiple ascending dose trial of inhaled PK10571 in healthy adult subjects
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary endpoint for this trial is safety. This is a first-in-human, single-center,
      randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, two-part study in healthy adult males and
      females of non-childbearing potential. &quot;Double-Blind&quot; means neither the study subject nor the
      investigator knows if PK10571 or placebo is being given. &quot;Placebo&quot; means a capsule filled
      with a powder that does not contain the active drug, PK10571. Because the safety profile of
      PK10571 in humans is unknown and this is the first clinical study to assess PK10571 in
      humans, a single-ascending dose design will be used in Part A of the study going from a low
      dose to higher doses based on safety. Part B will be a multiple-ascending dose design to be
      run only after review of safety and measurement of drug levels in the blood from Part A.

      In the single ascending dose study (Part A) up to five doses may be given to different groups
      of study subjects based on safety and measurement of drug levels in the blood. Subjects will
      be randomized into one dose cohort to receive either PK10571 or placebo. Within each cohort,
      6 subjects will receive active drug and 2 subjects will receive placebo.

      In the multiple ascending dose study (Part B), up to three doses of PK10571 will be tested.
      The daily dose will be administered daily for 7 days with close clinical monitoring. The dose
      for the first cohort of Part B will be determined by review of the safety and drug levels
      from Part A by the Safety Review Committee. The dose interval for the first cohort of Part B
      (i.e., once daily, twice daily, or up to three times daily) will be determined by review of
      the safety and drug levels in the blood from Part A by the Safety Review committee.
      Subsequent doses and dosing intervals will be determined by review of the safety and drug
      levels from the prior cohort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 4, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 3, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety As Determined by Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Safety As Determined by Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (mild, moderate, severe)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by Changes in Pulmonary Function</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary function measured by spirometry (FEV1, FVC)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by analysis of Electrocardiograms</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of 12-lead electorcardiograms (measurement of QT interval)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by evaluation of heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of heart rate (beats per minute)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by measurement of blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of blood pressure (systolic and diastolic in mm Hg)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by changes in oxygen saturation</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of oxygen saturation (%)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by changes in liver function</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of liver function (AST and ALT)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by changes in kidney function</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of BUN and creatinine</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by changes in Hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of hemoglobin</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as determined by changes in White Blood Cell Count</measure>
    <time_frame>11-35 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of white blood cell count</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic analysis of inhaled PK10571: Peak Plasma Concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>11 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of peak plasma concentration after dosing (Cmax)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic analysis of inhaled PK10571: Area Under the Plasma Concentration versus time</measure>
    <time_frame>11 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic analysis of inhaled PK10571: Half-life in Plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>11 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of half-life of study drug in plasma after dosing (T1/2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Safety Issues</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 1 Single Ascending Dose Protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 2 Single Ascending Dose Protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 3 Single Ascending Dose Protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 4 Single Ascending Dose Protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 5 Single Ascending Dose Protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 1 Multiple Ascending dose protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 2 Multiple Ascending Dose Protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose 3 Multiple Ascending dose protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PK10571 or Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Inhaled PK10571 or Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Generic Dry Powder Inhaler</intervention_name>
    <description>Dry Powder Inhaler used for inhalation of active drug or placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:Males and Females (if unable to become pregnant); Age 18-55; Non-smoker;
        Ability to give informed consent; Ability to use DPI effectively. (See full protocol for
        additional details) - Exclusion Criteria Subjects will be excluded for any of the
        following.

          1. Hospitalization within the 6 months prior to the first dose of study treatment.

          2. History or presence of clinically significant cardiovascular, pulmonary, hepatic,
             renal, hematologic, GI, endocrine, immunologic, dermatologic, neurologic, oncologic,
             or psychiatric disease or any other condition that, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, would jeopardize the safety of the subject or the validity of the study
             results.

          3. History or presence of active lung disease (i.e., asthma, chronic obstructive
             pulmonary disease [COPD], pulmonary fibrosis, hemoptysis, bronchiectasis) or prior
             intubation.

          4. Currently uses an inhaler.

          5. History or presence of heart disease (i.e., prior myocardial infarction [MI], coronary
             artery disease, heart failure, hypertension, pulmonary hypertension, valve disease,
             atrial fibrillation, other arrhythmia, or prolonged QT syndrome).

          6. History or presence of cancer (with the exception of basal cell skin cancer that has
             been effectively treated).

          7. History of diabetes mellitus.

          8. History of thyroid disease other than hypothyroidism control with levothyroxine and
             documented normal thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH).

          9. History of tuberculosis, Lyme disease, or other chronic or opportunistic infection.

         10. History of positive purified protein derivative (PPD) skin test, or positive PPD test
             at screening.

         11. Has a positive test for hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C antibody, or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) at screening or has been previously treated for hepatitis
             B, hepatitis C, or HIV infection.

         12. History of smoking within the past 15 years.

         13. Is a female with a positive pregnancy test result, or who has the ability to become
             pregnant, or who is lactating.

         14. Has forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) less than 80% predicted, forced vital
             capacity (FVC) ˂80% predicted, or resting oxygen saturation less than 97% on room air
             at screening or baseline.

         15. Upper respiratory infection within the 3 months prior to the first dose of medication.

         16. History of major bleeding or major surgical procedure of any type within 6 months
             prior to the first dose of medication.

         17. History of minor bleeding disorders such as epistaxis, rectal bleeding (spots of blood
             on toilet paper), and gingival bleeding within 3 months before the study treatment.

         18. History of bleeding disorder or coagulopathy.

         19. Females with history of dysfunctional uterine bleeding, including history of
             menorrhagia or metrorrhagia, unless subject has had a hysterectomy.

         20. History of GI bleed.

         21. Has used any over-the-counter (OTC) medication, nutritional or dietary supplements,
             herbal preparations, or vitamins within 7 days prior to the first dose of medication.

         22. Has used any antiplatelet agents such as acetylsalicylic acid (ASA), nonsteroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), clopidogrel (or similar agent) or anti-coagulants
             within 7 days prior to the first dose of medication.

         23. Has used any prescription medication, except female hormonal replacement therapy,
             within 14 days prior to the first dose of study medication.

         24. Has been treated with any known drugs that are moderate or strong inhibitors/inducers
             of CYP enzymes such as barbiturates, phenothiazines, cimetidine, carbamazepine, etc.,
             within 30 days prior to the first dose of study medication and that in the
             Investigator's judgment may impact subject safety or the validity of the study
             results.

         25. History of peripheral vascular disease.

         26. History of autoimmune or collagen vascular disease.

         27. History of sleep apnea.

         28. History of clinically significant allergy to medications.

         29. History of anaphylaxis.

         30. History of liver disease

         31. History of alcohol or drug abuse.

         32. Prolonged QTc on 12-lead ECG (i.e., QTc corrected using Fridericia's formula [QTcF]
             ˃450 msec), PR &gt;210 msec, or QRS &gt;110 msec at screening.

         33. Evidence of prior MI on ECG; presence of atrial fibrillation on ECG; presence of
             pre-excitation, 2nd or 3rd degree heart block, or abnormal waveform morphology that
             would preclude accurate measurement of the QT interval duration or other clinically
             significant abnormalities.

         34. Chest x-ray reveals presence of infiltrate or other abnormality (mass, granuloma,
             fibrosis, pulmonary thickening, pleural effusion, pulmonary edema, wide mediastinum,
             cardiomegaly, or clinically significant increased interstitial markings).

         35. History of neurologic disorder (i.e., multiple sclerosis, amyotrophic lateral
             sclerosis [ALS], cerebrovascular accident [CVA], transient ischemic attach [TIA])

         36. History of deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolus.

         37. History of clotting disorder.

         38. History of mental illness requiring drug treatment or hospitalization.

         39. History of renal failure or proteinuria (defined as 1+ proteinuria: ≥75 mg/dL on
             isolated urinalysis).

         40. Test results greater than the upper limit of normal (ULN) for AST, ALT, or total
             bilirubin

         41. Out of range results on the following coagulation tests: INR, prothrombin time (PT),
             or partial thromboplastin time (PTT).

         42. Total cholesterol &gt;250 mg/dL or triglycerides &gt;300 mg/dL at screening (based on
             fasting lipid profile).

         43. Estimated creatinine clearance less than 60 mL/min.

         44. Hemoglobin at screening of &lt;11.5 g/dl (if female subject) or &lt;12.5 g/dl (if male
             subject).

         45. Has a clinically significant abnormal finding on the physical exam, medical history,
             electrocardiogram (ECG), or clinical laboratory results at screening. Note: Subjects
             with abnormal laboratory results not specifically excluded by this protocol may be
             enrolled if the Investigator deems the out-of-range values as not clinically
             significant.

         46. History of treatment with a kinase inhibitor.

         47. Has been on a significantly abnormal diet during the 4 weeks preceding the first dose
             of study medication.

         48. Has donated blood or plasma within 30 days prior to the first dose of study
             medication.

         49. Has participated in another clinical trial (randomized subjects only) within 30 days
             prior to the first dose of study medication.

         50. Has a positive urine screen for drugs of abuse (amphetamines, barbiturates,
             benzodiazepines, cocaine, cannabinoids, opiates) or cotinine.

         51. Vital signs (measured sitting after 3 minutes rest) at screening that are not within
             the following ranges (inclusive): heart rate: 40-100 beats per minute [bpm]; systolic
             blood pressure (BP): 90-145 mmHg; diastolic BP: 50-95 mmHg. Out-of-range vital signs
             may be repeated once. Blood pressure will be measured in both arms at screening, with
             a 3-minute rest between each measurement. Predose vital signs will be assessed by the
             Principal Investigator or designee (e.g., a medically qualified sub-investigator)
             prior to study drug administration. The Principal Investigator or designee will verify
             the eligibility of each subject with out-of-range vital signs and document approval
             prior to dosing.

         52. Significant difference (i.e., greater than 15 mmHg) between the systolic blood
             pressure in each arm at screening.

         53. History of lactose intolerance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Administrator</last_name>
    <phone>858-987-4363</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrials@gossamerbio.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Phase 1 Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>00000</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Manager</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

