<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03478111</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C008RAIII</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03478111</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CMAB008 With MTX Therapy in Adult Patients With Moderately to Severely Active Rheumatoid Arthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Methotrexate (MTX) Based, Parallel-group, Multicenter Phase III Study to Evaluate Efficacy and Safety of CMAB008 in Adult Patients With Moderately to Severely Active Rheumatoid Arthritis, Compared to Remicade</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai Biomabs Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Biomabs Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      CMAB008 is an infliximab biosimilar candidate. The host cell of Remicade is mouse myeloma
      SP2/0 cell, however, the host cell of CMAB008 is CHO (Chinese hamster ovary cell). It seems
      that CMAB008 has lower immunogenicity and higher safety, because Remicade comprises more
      complex-type and hybrid-type glycans than CMAB008. However, it is not yet known whether
      CMAB008 is not inferior to Remicade. This randomized, double-blind trial investigates the
      efficacy and safety of CMAB008 for moderately to severely active rheumatoid arthritis,
      compared to Remicade.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-inferiority trial. The primary outcome is the percentage of subjects achieving
      ACR20. According to the global instruction of Remicade, the effective rate of Remicade is
      50%, and the placebo is 20%. Calculate the critical value δ=（50%-20%）×50%=15%, one-side
      α=0.025, β=0.20, experimental group : control group = 1:1, the results are: CMAB008 group 175
      participants, control group 175 participants, 350 participants in total. Take 10% drop-out
      into consideration, the finial sample sizes are: CMAB008 group 196 participants, control
      group 196 participants, 392 participants in total.

      During the entire duration of the study, all adverse events (AE) and all serious adverse
      events (SAEs) are collected, fully investigated and documented in source documents and case
      report forms (CRF). Study duration encompassed the time from when the participant sign the
      informed consent until the last protocol-specific procedure has been completed, including a
      safety follow up period.

      This study will be conducted in compliance with the protocol, the current version of the
      Declaration of Helsinki, the guidelines of Good Clinical Practice (GCP) as well as all
      national legal and regulatory requirements.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double-blind</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects achieving ACR20</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the percentage of subjects achieving ACR20 of all subjects</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects achieving ACR20</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 2,6,14,22 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the percentage of subjects achieving ACR20 of all subjects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects achieving ACR50,70</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 2,6,14,22,30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the percentage of subjects achieving ACR50,70 of all subjects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement rate of the duration of morning stiffness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 2,6,14,22,30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement rate=(before the treatment - after the treatment)/before the treatment *100%</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement rate of the number of joint swelling or tenderness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 2,6,14,22,30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement rate=(before the treatment - after the treatment)/before the treatment *100%</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement rate of Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 2,6,14,22,30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement rate=(before the treatment - after the treatment)/before the treatment *100%.
Visual Analogue Scale(VAS) is designed to present to the respondent a rating scale. Respondents mark the location on the 10-centimeter line corresponding to the amount of pain they experienced. VAS data of this type is recorded as the number of centimeters from the left of the line with the range 0-10.
No pain &lt;-- 10 cm. --&gt; Pain as bad as possible</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement rate of Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 2,6,14,22,30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement rate=(before the treatment - after the treatment)/before the treatment *100%.
The Health Assessment Questionnaire (HAQ) Disability Index assesses a patient's level of functional ability. There are 20 questions in eight categories of functioning which represent a comprehensive set of functional activities - dressing, rising, eating, walking, hygiene, reach, grip, and usual activities. The patient's responses are made on a scale from zero (no disability) to three (completely disabled).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement rate of physicochemical indexes of curative effect (ESR, CRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to 2,6,14,22,30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement rate=(before the treatment - after the treatment)/before the treatment *100%</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">392</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CMAB008+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: CMAB008 (recombinant chimeric anti-TNF-α monoclonal antibody injection) infusion of 3mg/kg in Week 0, 2, 6, 14, 22, 30.
Drug: MIX (methotrexate) will be oral administered at a dose of 7.5mg~15mg weekly from Week 0 to 38.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Remicade+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: Remicade (recombinant chimeric anti-TNF-α monoclonal antibody injection) infusion of 3mg/kg in Week 0, 2, 6, 14, 22, 30.
Drug: MIX (methotrexate) will be oral administered at a dose of 7.5mg~15mg weekly from Week 0 to 38.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CMAB008</intervention_name>
    <description>the study drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>CMAB008+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>infliximab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MTX</intervention_name>
    <description>basic therapy drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>CMAB008+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Remicade+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>methotrexate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Remicade</intervention_name>
    <description>active comparator</description>
    <arm_group_label>Remicade+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>infliximab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age≥18 years, males or females;

          2. Diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis according to American College of Rheumatology (ACR)
             1987 Revised Criteria for the Classification of Rheumatoid Arthritis, and in
             moderately to severely active stage during screening;

          3. Have had one or more DMARDs failure (defined as &quot;failure of traditional/conventional
             DMARD(s) due to lack of efficacy/desired response or side effects&quot; according to 2015
             American College of Rheumatology Guideline for the Treatment of Rheumatoid Arthritis);

          4. Non-use of DMARDs (including: Chloroquine, Hydroxychloroquine, Gold Compound,
             Penicillamine, Salicylazosulfapyridine, Azathioprine, Cyclophosphamide, Cyclosporine
             A, Leflunomide, Thalidomide etc.) except for MTX in the last 4 weeks before screening;

          5. Have completed at least 3 months of treatment with MTX, and steadily at the dosage of
             7.5mg~15mg/w at least 4 weeks prior to screening;

          6. Non-use of Non-steroidal Anti-inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs) in the last 2 weeks before
             enrollment, or if using NSAIDs, should stabilize dose at least 2 weeks;

          7. Non-use of glucocorticoid (including intramuscular corticotropin) systematically
             (e.g., oral administration, intramuscular or intravenous injection) or intra-articular
             injection; or if concurrent taking glucocorticoid orally, dose (equivalent to the dose
             of Prednisone) should stabilize≤10mg/d at least 4 weeks;

          8. Non-use of Chinese medicine (e.g., Tripterygium, Total Glucosides of Paeony Capsules)
             for rheumatoid arthritis in the last 4 weeks before screening;

          9. Pregnancy test should be negative for procreative female, or not lactating. Both male
             and female subjects should consent to take effective contraception throughout the
             study and at least 6 months after the study;

         10. Signed the informed consent form;

         11. Can participate in visits on schedule;

         12. Can understand and complete assessment forms correctly.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Weight＞75Kg;

          2. Inoculated live (attenuated) viral/bacterial vaccine in the last 4 weeks before
             screening;

          3. Use of biologicals (including but nor limited to Infliximab, Etanercept, Adalimumab,
             Tocilizumab, Rituximab etc.) for rheumatoid arthritis in the last 3 months before
             screening;

          4. Severe infection (e.g., acute hepatitis, pneumonia, acute pyelonephritis) in the last
             2 months before enrollment, or previous hospitalization due to infection, or previous
             use of antibiotics, antifungal or antiviral drugs due to infection. However, low-grade
             infection (e.g., acute upper respiratory infections, simplex urinary tract infection)
             is not considered as exclusion criteria, whether the subject can be chosen depends on
             investigator;

          5. Suffering from acute infection or recurrent infections disease during screening, e.g.,
             respiratory system infection (influenza, upper respiratory infection, bronchiectasia
             etc.), acute episode of chronic pyelonephritis, infectious skin wound etc,;

          6. Previous opportunistic infection (e.g., herpes zoster, active cytomegalovirus,
             mycoplasma, pneumocystis pneumonia, histoplasma, aspergillus, mycobacteria except for
             mycobacterium tuberculosis) in the last 6 months before screening;

          7. History of prosthetic joint infections, or suspicious prosthetic joint infections with
             antibiotic therapy and unremoved prosthetic joint;

          8. History of severe hepatic diseases; or HbsAg positive; or only HbcAb positive in
             Second Liver 5 Indexes, and HBV-DNA positive; or HCV-infected patient;

          9. AIDS-infected patient or HIVpositive;

         10. One of the following situations relating to tuberculosis:

               1. Concurrent or previous active tuberculosis. Chest X-ray examination (suggest
                  chest anteroposterior and lateral position films) should be performed in the last
                  3 months before screening, to provide evidence for concurrent or previous
                  tuberculosis;

               2. Intimate contact with active tuberculosis patient recently; or high-risk and/or
                  immunocompromised group (e.g., long-term use of glucocorticoids,
                  immunosuppressor), and with any signs of latent tuberculosis infection;

               3. PPD test (inject 5IU TB-PPD intradermally, measure the diameter of skin
                  induration 72 hours later) performed in the last 3 weeks before screening:
                  diameter of induration≤15mm, and with vesicle or necrosis; or diameter of
                  induration＞15mm;

               4. If cannot perform PPD test, perform T-SPOT test: T-SPOT test positive, chest file
                  and clinical evidence indicate that the patient is unsuitable for participation;

         11. History of organ allograft operation (except for keratoplasty more than 3 months
             before the first use of investigational drug);

         12. Concurrent or previous malignant tumor (except for total excision and no recurrence of
             cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma, basal-cell carcinoma or carcinoma in situ of
             cervix) in the last 5 years before screening;

         13. History of lymphoid malignancies (lymphoma) or lymphoproliferative disease; or
             symptoms and signs indicate that may be lymphoproliferative disease (e.g., lymph node
             enlargement at neck, clavicle or axilla) during screening; or splenomegaly (≥subcostal
             2cm);

         14. Concurrent or previous demyelinating diseases of the central nervous system (e.g.,
             multiple sclerosis);

         15. Concurrent or previous congestive heart failure;

         16. Concurrent or previous other autoimmune disease, and may be expected to affect the
             assessment of investigational drug;

         17. Severe, progressive, uncontrolled cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, pulmonic,
             gastrointestinal, hematopoietic, endocrine, neural diseases, or other situations that
             the patient is considered as unsuitable for participation by investigator;

         18. History of severe drug or alcohol abuse with clinical symptoms; history of poor drug
             compliance; or other situations that may interfere protocol compliance (e.g., mental
             disease, frequent travel, lack of willingness);

         19. Laboratory tests results meet one of the following indexes: HGB&lt;8.5g/dL,
             WBC&lt;3.5*10^9/L, PLT&lt;80*10^9/L, ALT/AST&gt;2*upper limit of normal value, CREA&gt;upper limit
             of normal value;

         20. Allergic reaction against human immunoglobulin, infliximab or other ingredient;

         21. Participation in another drug clinical trial in the last 30 days before screening or
             within 5 half-lives of drug (longer time shall prevail).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yin Su, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University People's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yin Su, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+8613321120132</phone>
    <email>suyin0921@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking University People's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100044</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yin Su, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>+8613321120132</phone>
      <email>suyin0921@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infliximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

