<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03474991</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SNF#173532</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03474991</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>KIDS-STEP_Betamethasone Therapy in Hospitalised Children With CAP</brief_title>
  <acronym>KIDS-STEP</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomised Placebo-controlled Multi-centre Effectiveness Trial of Adjunct Betamethasone Therapy in Hospitalised Children With Community Acquired Pneumonia (CAP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss National Fund for Scientific Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to concurrently evaluate whether adjunct treatment with
      corticosteroids in children hospitalized with CAP is more effective in terms of the
      proportion of children reaching clinical stability and whether such adjunct treatment is no
      worse in terms of CAP relapse.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) in young children remains high (20-
      30/1000 child-years) even in high-income settings with routine pneumococcal vaccination, and
      is associated with a high rate of hospitalisation (around 10/1000 child-years). In low-and
      middle-income settings, pneumonia is the leading infectious cause of death in children less
      than 5 years of age. In high-income settings, working mothers of children hospitalised with
      CAP have been reported to loose on average 4.2 workdays compared with 1.7 workdays for
      children with CAP managed in primary care. In addition to this economic burden, there is a
      substantial impact on quality of life for the affected child and the family. Children who are
      admitted with CAP experience on average 13 nonroutine days with slightly shorter periods of
      decreased appetite (8.5 days), disordered sleep (4.5 days) and absence from routine
      out-of-home childcare (7.5 days). Any intervention that ensures rapid clinical stabilization
      allowing for early hospital discharge without negative impacts on the overall recovery in
      children hospitalised with CAP would therefore carry substantial socioeconomic benefits.

      Only few small trials have addressed the potential impact of oral steroid treatment in CAP
      during childhood. Nagy et al reported a significant reduction in fever duration and length of
      stay in children with severe CAP receiving methylprednisolone for 5 days compared with
      children receiving placebo in a randomised trial with 59 participants. A randomised trial
      comparing adjunct dexamethasone or methylprednisolone against standard of care (no placebo)
      planning to enroll 40 participants was being set up but has been withdrawn prior to
      recruitment (NCT01631916). A placebo-controlled randomised trial of adjunct corticosteroids
      in CAP complicated by pleural effusion and/or empyema with 56 participants has been completed
      (NCT01261546), but has not yet reported on its findings. An observational analysis using
      propensity scores found that adjunct corticosteroids were associated with a shorter hospital
      stay only in children also receiving beta-agonist therapy, concluding that any benefit might
      only be seen in children with acute wheezing. All in all, there is a lack of pragmatic
      randomized controlled trials ( RCT) with sufficient power and high external validity to
      provide a definitive answer to the question of the effect of adjunct steroids in children
      hospitalised with CAP.

      Infection-related unwanted effects of adjunct steroids are potentially relevant in the
      context of childhood CAP. A higher proportion of children hospitalised with CAP reaching
      early clinical stability would only be desirable if this were shown not to be offset by a
      higher rate of clinically relevant CAP recurrence. A rebound phenomenon after corticosteroid
      discontinuation has been postulated to explain a higher rate of infection recurrence (19%
      compared with 9% in placebo group) among adults. Data from a recent individual patient data
      metaanalysis, however, indicate that an increased risk of CAP recurrence may be rather
      associated with longer duration of adjunct steroids in adults with CAP. To our knowledge, the
      question about the effect of adjunct steroid treatment in childhood CAP in relation to a
      postulated rebound phenomenon measured clinically as CAP recurrence has not been formally
      addressed in a trial. CAP-specific readmission rates for children are low at around 5%. In
      bronchiolitis, another acute lower respiratory tract infection for which oral corticosteroid
      treatment has been investigated, an increased risk of hospital revisits associated with
      steroid treatment could not be identified in a Cochrane metaanalysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>KIDS-STEP is a phase III strategic investigator-initiated, randomised, placebo-controlled, fully blinded multicentre superiority trial with two parallel groups</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>time to clinical stability</measure>
    <time_frame>from randomization until hour 48</time_frame>
    <description>(i) The proportion of children clinically stable at 48 hours after randomization in the active treated group (oral betamethasone for 2 days) as compared to the control group (placebo) will be one primary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CAP-related re-admission measured by number of childs re-admitted to hospital due to CAP</measure>
    <time_frame>from randomization until day 28</time_frame>
    <description>(ii) The proportion of children with CAP-related readmission within 28 days after randomization comparing oral betamethasone and placebo will be the co-primary outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">700</enrollment>
  <condition>Community-acquired Pneumonia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Celestamine® N 0.5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>oral betamethasone solution, once daily for two consecutive days at 0.1-0.2 mg/kg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>oral placebo matched to the product described above</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Celestamine®</intervention_name>
    <description>Children in KIDS-STEP will be receiving either oral betamethasone (Celestamine®) or oral placebo dosed once daily for two consecutive days. Celestamine® N 0.5 liquidum is a betamethasone solution and will be used in the active comparator arm. Study medication will be administered orally once a day on two consecutive days. A standard dose of 0.1-0.2 mg/kg will be used. All doses used in KIDS-STEP fall into the range of recommended doses according to the Summary of Medical Product Characteristics.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Celestamine® N 0.5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Body weight between 7 kg and 35 kg

          -  Admission to hospital (i.e. assignment of an inpatient case number)

          -  Clinical diagnosis of CAP (according to predefined criteria)

          -  Parent and/or child (as age-appropriate) willing to accept all possible randomised
             allocations and to be contacted by telephone weekly up to and including at 4 weeks
             after randomisation

          -  Informed consent form for trial participation signed by parent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of local chest complications

          -  Chronic underlying disease associated with an increased risk of very severe CAP or CAP
             of unusual aetiology

          -  Bilateral wheezing without focal chest signs (most likely to represent respiratory
             tract infection affecting the medium airways, i.e. not pneumonia)

          -  Inability to tolerate oral medication

          -  Documented allergy or any other known contraindication to any trial medication

          -  Subacute or chronic conditions requiring higher betamethasone equivalent or known
             primary or secondary adrenal insufficiency

          -  Transfer for any reason to a non-participating hospital directly from the paediatric
             emergency department

          -  Parent are unlikely to be able to reliably participate in telephone follow-up because
             of significant language barriers

          -  Participation in another study with investigational drug within the 30 days preceding
             and during the present study,

          -  Previous enrolment into the current study,

          -  Enrolment of the investigator, his/her family members, and other dependent persons.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johannes van der Anker, Prof MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Basel Children's Hospital (UKBB)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Julia A Bielicki, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+41 61 704</phone>
    <phone_ext>1212</phone_ext>
    <email>julia.bielicki@ukbb.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Regina Santoro</last_name>
    <phone>+41 61 704</phone>
    <phone_ext>2854</phone_ext>
    <email>regina.santoro@ukbb.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kantonsspital Aarau, Klinik für Kinder u. Jugendliche</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarau</city>
        <zip>5001</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Henrik Koehler, Prof MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Basel Children's Hospital (UKBB)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <zip>4056</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ulrich Heininger, Prof MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 61 704</phone>
      <phone_ext>12 12</phone_ext>
      <email>ulrich.heiniger@ukbb.ch</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inselspital Bern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Daniel Garcia</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geneva University Hospital, Department of Pediatrics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Geneva</city>
        <zip>1211</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Constance Barrazone, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre hospitalier universitaire vaudois</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lausanne</city>
        <zip>1011</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandra Asner, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Luzerner Kantonsspital, Kinderspital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Luzern</city>
        <zip>6000</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marco Lurà, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kantonsspital Luzern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Gallen</city>
        <zip>9007</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christia Kahlert, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University-Childrens Hospital Zürich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zürich</city>
        <zip>8032</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christoph Berger, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Betamethasone benzoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Betamethasone-17,21-dipropionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Betamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Betamethasone Valerate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Betamethasone sodium phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

