<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03477500</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-001362-25</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03477500</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RCT Comparing Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation Versus Alemtuzumab in MS</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAM-MS</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation Versus Alemtuzumab for Patients With Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Haukeland University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Haukeland University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomized multicentre, multinational, treatment interventional study of RRMS
      patients with breakthrough inflammatory disease activity in spite of ongoing standard
      immunomodulatory medication. The study has two treatment arms; arm A: HSCT (hematopoietic
      stem cell transplantation) and arm B: alemtuzumab, a registered immunomodulatory treatment of
      RRMS. A pre-planned 3-year follow-up extension period will be performed depending on future
      funding.

      The aim of the study is to assess the effectiveness and side effects of a new treatment
      intervention in RRMS; HSCT, and, thereby, the value of HSCT in clinical practice. Data from
      recently published patient series indicate that HSCT may have a significantly higher
      treatment effect than currently registered RRMS immunomodulatory treatments. This study will
      determine the relative role of HSCT versus alemtuzumab.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized study of autologous HSCT using a low intensity, non-ablative
      conditioning regimen with cyclophosphamide and ATG versus treatment with the currently
      presumed best available immunomodulatory medication (alemtuzumab) in RRMS patients with
      significant inflammatory disease activity in spite of ongoing immunomodulatory MS treatment.

      Significant disease activity is defined as having one or more clinically reported multiple
      sclerosis (MS) relapse(s), AND 1 or more T1 Gd-enhanced lesion(s), OR three or more new or
      enlarging T2 lesions on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) over the last year while being
      treated on immunomodulatory medication by standard national guidelines. The relapse(s) must
      have occurred 3 or more months after the onset of an immunomodulatory treatment, as
      immunomodulatory treatment in MS may reach full effect after 3 months or more.

      Both the knowledge of the treatment effect of registered immunomodulatory therapies for RRMS,
      and the number of treatments approved for RRMS by the European Medicines Agency (EMA) are
      rapidly increasing. During the study period, there may thus appear new supplementing
      information on other MS immunomodulatory treatments that favour the use of a new comparator
      (replacing or supplementing alemtuzumab as a comparator). This will be evaluated by the PMC
      if applicable during the study period and the planned extension period.

      If the treatment efficacy obtained by HSCT is better than the currently most efficacious
      standard, immunomodulatory treatment in randomized treatment trials, HSCT will likely be
      approved as a part of the standard treatment recommendations for a significant proportion of
      RRMS patients. A randomized study regarding with statistical power to evaluate the clinical
      outcome of autologous HSCT compared to a standard immunomodulatory treatment in MS has not
      yet been published. Except for Sweden, HSCT is currently not registered as a part of standard
      MS treatment in the public health services of Europe. The HSCT regimen for the study will be
      identical to the regimen used in similar patient populations in Sweden, Norway and Denmark.

      Alemtuzumab has been chosen as the primary comparator, because it is the immunomodulatory
      medication currently authorised by the EMA for treatment of RRMS with the most favourable
      therapeutic effects. In a meta-analysis of immunomodulatory treatment effects in RRMS,
      alemtuzumab was the immunomodulatory drug with the most eminent reduction of annualized
      relapse rate and 3 month confirmed disability progression.

      In this study, a health economic evaluation will be included. Accordingly, the proposed study
      should provide a robust basis for future official decisions regarding the role of HSCT in
      RRMS treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 21, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 21, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 21, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with no evidence of disease activity (NEDA, as defined per protocol).</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period with a 5 year (240 week) planned extension</time_frame>
    <description>A protocol-defined disease activity event is the occurrence of at least one of the following:
A new T1 Gd-enhanced lesion on MRI of the brain and spinal cord
A new T2 hyperintense lesion on MRI of brain and spinal cord
A protocol-defined MS relapse (see below)
24 week confirmed disability progression based on increases in Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NEDA-4</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with no evidence of disease activity, including atrophy (NEDA 4), as per protocol defined disease activity events (as defined in section 2.2) plus atrophy (measured yearly atrophy above threshold of 0, 4 %)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre-planned study extension:</measure>
    <time_frame>5 year (240 week) period.</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who have NEDA 4</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first protocol-defined disease activity event</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Time to first sign of new disease activity, as measured as new relapses, EDSS-progression, MRI-activity or brain atrophy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Expanded Disability Status scale (EDSS) from baseline (Visit 4.1) to Weeks 96 and 240</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>EDSS is an ordinal scale in half-point increments that quantifies disability in participants with MS. It assesses the 7 functional systems (visual, brainstem, pyramidal, cerebellar, sensory, bowel/bladder and cerebral) as well as ambulation. EDSS total score ranges from 0 (normal neurological examination) to 10 (death due to MS), where higher scores indicate worse neurological function. Change was calculated by subtracting retreatment baseline (annual visit prior to the retreatment start date) value from EDSS scores at specified time points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients who, at Week 96, have protocol-defined Confirmed Disability Improvement (CDI) , confirmed stable EDSS or Confirmed Disability Progression (CDP) compared to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Disability progression, as measured with EDSS. EDSS is an ordinal scale in half-point increments that quantifies disability in participants with MS. It assesses the 7 functional systems (visual, brainstem, pyramidal, cerebellar, sensory, bowel/bladder and cerebral) as well as ambulation. EDSS total score ranges from 0 (normal neurological examination) to 10 (death due to MS), where higher scores indicate worse neurological function. Change was calculated by subtracting retreatment baseline (annual visit prior to the retreatment start date) value from EDSS scores at specified time points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Annualized rate of protocol-defined relapses during 96 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>ARR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to onset of first protocol-defined relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Time to first relapse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in MRI T2-weighted hyperintense lesion volume from baseline to weeks 96 (and 240)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Change in T2-weighted hyperintense lesion volume</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in MRI T1-weighted hypointense lesion volume from baseline to weeks 96 (and 240)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Change in MRI T1-weighted hypointense lesion volume</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in brain volume from baseline to week 96 (and week 240)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Change in brain volume</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to detection of a new MRI T2 lesion</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Time to New MRI T2-lesion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total number of MRI T1-weighted Gd-enhanced lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Gd-lesions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients free from T1 Gd-enhancing lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients free from T1 Gd-enhancing lesions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Nine-hole-peg test (9-HPT) score from baseline to week 96 (and 240)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>The 9HPT is a brief, standardized, quantitative test of upper extremity function. The participant picks up 9 pegs puts them in a block containing nine empty holes, and, once they are in the holes, removes them again as quickly as possible one at a time. The total time to complete the task is recorded. Two consecutive trials with the dominant hand are immediately followed by two consecutive trials with the non-dominant hand. The two trials for each hand are averaged</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Timed 25 Foot Walk (T25FW) score from baseline to week 48, 96 (and 240)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>The T25FW is a quantitative mobility and leg function performance test based on a timed walk over 25 feet. The participant is directed to one end of a clearly marked 25-foot course and is instructed to walk 25 feet as quickly as possible, but safely. The time is calculated from the initiation of the instruction to start and ends when the participant has reached the 25-foot mark. The task is immediately administered again by having the patient walk back the same distance. The score for the T25FW is the average of the 2 completed trials. The 95% CI of the percentage is based on normal approximation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in The Brief International Cognitive Assessment for Multiple Sclerosis (BICAMS) score from baseline to week 96 (and 240)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>BICAMS is a composite cognitive assessment tool comprising of the three components : Symbol Digit Modalities Test (SDMT) , California Verbal Learning Test-II (CVLT-II) and Brief visuospatial memory test- Revised (BVMT-R)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient reported quality of life based on the EuroQoL Health Related Quality of Life - 5 Dimensions - 5 Levels (EQ-5D 5L) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D 5L is a 5 item questionnaire (assessing - mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, anxiety/depression) and visual analogue scale (VAS) enables calculation of quality adjusted life years (QALY) to enable health economic analyses to be performed. Each dimension assessed has 5 response scales to select from: no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems, and extreme problems</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Survival</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rate and nature of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Rate and nature of adverse events</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>The FSS questionnaire contains nine statements that rate the severity of fatigue symptoms. A low value (e.g., 1); indicates strong disagreement with the statement, whereas a high value (e.g., 7); indicates strong agreement. A total score of 36 or more suggests presence of fatigue.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Multiple Sclerosis Impact Scale (MSIS) - 29</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Multiple Sclerosis Impact Scale-29 (MSIS-29) is a validated MS specific questionnaire consisting of 29 questions of which 20 addressed the physical impact component and 9 assessed the psychological impact. A combined score can be generated, or both components can be reported separately. The psychological wellbeing assessment portion of the MSIS-29 was comprised of 9 questions in which subjects rate the impact of MS on their day-to-day life from 1=no impact to 5=extreme impact. The total Psychological Score was calculated using following formula: sum of score for 9 questions - 9/0.36. The total score range ranges from 0-100 where, lower total score indicates less psychologically-related impact while a higher total score indicates greater psychologically-related impact on a subject's functioning.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of relapses (residual disability (EDSS) after relapses)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>EDSS is an ordinal scale in half-point increments that quantifies disability in participants with MS. It assesses the 7 functional systems (visual, brainstem, pyramidal, cerebellar, sensory, bowel/bladder and cerebral) as well as ambulation. EDSS total score ranges from 0 (normal neurological examination) to 10 (death due to MS), where higher scores indicate worse neurological function. Change was calculated by subtracting retreatment baseline (annual visit prior to the retreatment start date) value from EDSS scores at specified time points.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year (96 week) period, with planned extension for 5 year (240 week) period</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of serious adverse events</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HSCT (Cyclophosphamide and ATG)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Day 1: Cyclophosphamide 2.0 g/m2 body surface area Days 5-10: Granulocyte colony stimulating factor (filgrastim) 5 mcg/kg body weight/day sc.
Day 11 and until apheresis is discontinued: Granulocyte colony stimulating factor (filgrastim) 5 mcg/kg body weight x 2 sc/day.
HSCT days -5 to -2: Cyclophosphamide 50 mg/kg/day. HSCT days -5 to -1: Anti-thymocyte globulin (ATG-rabbit, Thymoglobuline®) 0.5 mg/kg body weight iv on day -5, 1.0 mg ATG-rabbit/kg will be given iv on day -4, and 1.5 mg ATG-rabbit /kg will be given iv on days -3,-2 and -1 over 10 hours.
HSCT day 0: Reinfusion of a minimum of 3,0 x 106 CD 34+ cells/kg body weight.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alemtuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Alemtuzumab 12 mg iv daily on 5 consecutive days at first alemtuzumab treatment cycle, followed by 3 consecutive days at the second alemtuzumab treatment cycle 12 months later.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide and ATG</intervention_name>
    <description>Hematopoetic stem cell transplantation</description>
    <arm_group_label>HSCT (Cyclophosphamide and ATG)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sendoxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alemtuzumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Alemtuzumab (Lemtrada)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alemtuzumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lemtrada</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age between ≥18 to ≤50, both genders

          2. Women of childbearing potential* (WOCBP) and men in a sexual relation with WOCBP must
             be ready and able to use highly effective methods of birth control per ICH M3 (R2)
             that result in a low failure rate of less than 1% per year when used consistently and
             correctly.

          3. Diagnosis of RRMS using revised McDonald criteria of clinically definite MS1

          4. An EDSS score of 0 to 5.5

          5. Significant inflammatory disease activity in the last year despite treatment with
             standard disease modifying therapy (interferon beta, glatiramer acetate, dimethyl
             fumarate, teriflunomide, fingolimod, natalizumab)

             a. Significant inflammatory disease activity is defined by: i. One or more clinically
             reported multiple sclerosis (MS) relapse(s), ii. AND 1 or more T1 Gd-enhanced
             lesion(s), iii. OR three or more new or enlarging T2 lesions on magnetic resonance
             imaging (MRI) The relapse(s) must have been treated with iv or oral high dose
             corticosteroids prescribed by a neurologist, and must have occurred 3 or more months
             after the onset of an immunomodulatory treatment, as MS immunomodulatory treatment may
             reach full effect after 3 months or more2.

          6. The patient is a RRMS-patient referred from neurological departments in Norway,
             Denmark, Sweden or possibly other European countries to an assigned study site.

          7. Signed informed consent and expected patient cooperation regarding the treatment
             schemes and procedures planned in the treatment and follow-up periods must be obtained
             and documented according to ICH GCP and national/local regulations.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known hypersensitivity or other known serious side effects for any of the study
             medications, including co-medications such as high-dose glucocorticosteroids

          2. Any illness or prior treatment that in the opinion of the investigators would
             jeopardize the ability of the patient to tolerate aggressive chemotherapy or high-dose
             glucocorticosteroids

          3. Any ongoing infection, including CMV, EBV, HSV, VZV, hepatitis virus, toxoplasmosis,
             HTV, HIV or syphilis infections, as well as hepatitis B surface antigen positivity
             and/or hepatitis C PCR positivity verified at Visit 1

          4. Patients without a history of chickenpox or without vaccination against varicella
             zoster virus (VZV), unless tested for antibodies to VZV. VZV negative patients can
             only be included if they receive vaccination against VZV at least 6 weeks prior to
             inclusion.

          5. Current or previous treatments with long-term effects that may influence the treatment
             effects or potential toxicities/side effects of the treatment arms. This includes, but
             is not restricted to previous treatment with rituximab, mitoxantrone, cladribine and
             alemtuzumab

          6. Treatment with glucocorticoids or ACTH within one month prior to study inclusion

          7. Having experienced an MS relapse within one month prior to study inclusion

          8. Prior or current major depression

          9. Prior or current psychiatric illness, mental deficiency or cognitive dysfunction
             influencing the patient ability to make an informed consent or comply with the
             treatment and follow- follow-upup phases of this protocol.

         10. Prior or current alcohol or drug dependencies

         11. Cardiac insufficiency, cardiomyopathy, significant cardiac dysrhythmia, unstable or
             advanced ischemic heart disease (NYHA III or IV)

         12. Significant hypertension: BP &gt; 180/110

         13. Prior history of malignancy except localized basal cell, squamous skin cancer or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

         14. Known thyroid disease, and/or abnormal serum thyroid hormone status

         15. Failure to willingly accept or comprehend risk of irreversible sterility as a side
             effect of therapy

         16. WBC &lt; 1,5 x 109/L

         17. Platelet (thrombocyte) count &lt; 100 x 109/L

         18. ALAT and/or ASAT more than 2 times the upper normal reference limit (UNL)

         19. Serum creatinine &gt; 200 µmol/L

         20. Serum bilirubin &gt; 20 µmol/L

         21. Presence of metallic objects implanted in the body that would preclude the ability of
             the patient to safely have MRI exams

         22. Diagnosis of primary progressive MS

         23. Diagnosis of secondary progressive MS

         24. Treatment with natalizumab, fingolimod and dimethylfumarate within the last 2 months
             (washout must be performed as specified in section 5.1 prior to inclusion in the
             study)

         25. Use of teriflunomide (Aubagio®) within the previous 2 years unless cleared from the
             body (plasma concentration &lt; 0.02mcg/ml following elimination from the body with
             cholestyramine or activated powdered charcoal) as specified in section 5.1

         26. Any hereditary neurological disease such as Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease or
             Spinocerebellar ataxia

         27. Any disease that can influence the patient safety and compliance, or the evaluation of
             disability

         28. History of hypersensitivity reaction to rabbit

         29. Women who are pregnant, breast-feeding, or who plan to become pregnant within the
             timeframe of this study

         30. Currently enrolled in another investigational device or drug study, or less than 30
             days since ending another investigational device or drug study(s), or receiving other
             investigational treatment(s). Patients participating in a purely observational trial
             will not be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lars Bø, MD, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne Kristine Lehmann, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aymen B Ahmed, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Einar Kristoffersen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Øivind Torkildsen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Trygve Holmøy, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Akershus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margitta Kampman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tromsø University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathrine K Liane, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Olavs Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joachim Burman, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Akademiska sjukhuset, Uppsala</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Morten Blinkenberg, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jan Lycke, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Øivind Torkildsen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+4755976032</phone>
    <email>ofto@helse-bergen.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lars Bø, MD, Phd</last_name>
    <phone>55977039</phone>
    <email>labo@helse-bergen.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Morten Blinkenberg, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>Morten.Blinkenberg@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Finn T Sellebjerg, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>finn.thorup.sellebjerg@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VUmc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joep Killestein, PhD</last_name>
      <email>joep.killestein@vumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haukeland University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergen</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Øivind Torkildsen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>4755976032</phone>
      <email>ofto@helse-bergen.no</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lars Bø, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>55977039</phone>
      <email>labo@helse-bergen.no</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Akershus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Trygve Holmøy, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>trygve.holmoy@medisin.uio.no</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of North Norway</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tromsø</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Margitta Kampman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>Margitta.T.Kampman@unn.no</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Olav's University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trondheim</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathrine Lian, MD</last_name>
      <email>Kathrine.Krokenes.Lian@stolav.no</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sahlgrenska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gothenburg</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jan Lycke, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>jan.lycke@gu.se</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Akademiska sjukhuset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Uppsala</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joachim Burman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>joachim.burman@neuro.uu.se</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ram-ms.no</url>
    <description>Study site (in Norwegian)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>multiple sclerosis,</keyword>
  <keyword>HSCT</keyword>
  <keyword>alemtuzumab</keyword>
  <keyword>RCT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis, Relapsing-Remitting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alemtuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified individual participant data for all primary and secondary outcome measures will be made available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

