<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02453373</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LRS-01-13-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02453373</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Helping Stroke Patients With ThermoSuit Cooling</brief_title>
  <acronym>SISCO</acronym>
  <official_title>Helping Stroke Patients With ThermoSuit Cooling</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Life Recovery Systems</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tulane University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Life Recovery Systems</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to assess the feasibility of using the Life Recovery Systems
      ThermoSuit Device to induce therapeutic hypothermia (32-34°C) in victims of ischemic stroke.
      This feasibility clinical study will enroll a total of 30 patients with acute ischemic stroke
      at two clinical centers. Subjects will receive hypothermia plus conventional therapy (such as
      IV-tPA and/or neurothrombectomy therapies if indicated). Endpoints will include feasibility
      of cooling, adverse events, and neurological recovery in comparison with matched historical
      controls.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients presenting to the emergency department with clinical signs and symptoms of acute
      ischemic stroke will undergo initial evaluation. The patient will be screened for study
      eligibility. A medical history and list of active medications will be documented. A physical
      will be conducted including the patient's temperature, hemodynamic and neurological status
      (NIHSS score), 12-lead ECG, and routine baseline laboratory values including magnesium, CBC,
      BMP, coagulation parameters, CK, CK-MB, and Troponin I. If all inclusion criteria and no
      exclusion criteria are present, a member of the research team will consult the patient's
      attending physician for permission to approach the patient. If he/she agrees, a member of the
      team will inform the patient or guardian about the study's purpose and obtain written
      informed consent. A screening log will be kept of all patients screened for this study and
      the reasons they were not enrolled.

      Prior to initiating hypothermia, Magnesium Sulfate will be administered intravenously to
      control shivering and tPA administered intravenously (if indicated). Induction doses of
      propofol or etomidate will be used to aid in the suppression of patient discomfort.
      Hypothermia will generally be initiated in the ED or ICU, as soon as possible after the
      informed consent has been obtained. However, in cases in which neurothrombectomy is indicated
      and judged by the investigators to be feasible to start within 90 minutes of enrollment,
      cooling will be delayed until its completion, and shall afterward be initiated as soon as
      possible. In all cases the patient will be placed in the LRS ThermoSuit in the supine
      position.

      Cooling will be started as specified in the Operator's Manual for the ThermoSuit device. Core
      temperature will be measured and monitored through a nasopharyngeal or esophageal temperature
      probe.

      Cooling will be initiated by circulating ice-cold water (0-8°C ± 2.0°C) through the
      ThermoSuit, and the start time will be recorded. Patient core and TSS water temperatures will
      be electronically recorded. The patient will be cooled until the core temperature reaches
      between 32°C to 34°C. This will require approximately 5 to 20 minutes of cooling by the
      ThermoSuit device (not expected to be more than 30 minutes). Arterial blood pressure and
      heart rate will be recorded every 5 minutes from the baseline just before the start of
      cooling until 30 minutes after the cooling has started.

      The clinician will be prompted by the automated monitor to purge the fluid from the suit when
      the patient's core temperature reaches approximately 34°C. The purging will take
      approximately 2 minutes. Start and stop times of purging will be recorded. The patient's body
      temperature should continue to decrease and then stabilize within the target range. The time
      at which the core temperature reaches 34°C will be recorded.

      The patient will be removed from the ThermoSuit immediately after water finishes draining
      from the suit. The time of removal will be recorded.

      Sedatives and analgesics will be administered for patient comfort as needed. Whether or not
      shivering occurs during cooling will be recorded, as well as start and stop times.

      Body temperature will be maintained in the range of 32°C to 34°C for a period of 24 hours
      following the cooling induction using a cooling blanket system.

      After 24 hours of therapeutic hypothermia, the patient will be re-warmed with the
      cooling/warming blanket until core body temperature reaches 36.5°C. This is anticipated to
      take approximately 8 hours.

      All patients will be admitted to the intensive care unit for close monitoring of
      physiological parameters: blood pressure, heart rate and rhythm, arterial oxygen saturation,
      potassium level, acid-base balance, and indicators of infection. A head CT will be performed
      upon admission and 24-48 hours later. Neurological status over the first 24 hours will be
      closely monitored and accompanied by additional brain imaging if changes in the neurological
      status occur. In ICU level patients, neurological status will be evaluated q1hr with the
      mini-NIHSS (items 1a, 1b, 1c, and motor scores for each limb), Glasgow Coma Scale, and
      pupillary light response. In the case of deterioration, repeat imaging which will include CT
      or MRI will be performed within 48 hours to compare to admission studies. Blood pressure,
      heart rate and rhythm, cell count, electrolytes, magnesium, coagulation profile, cardiac
      enzymes, liver enzymes and serum amylase will be monitored. All neurological, cardiovascular,
      respiratory, digestive, hematological, and metabolic complications will be recorded and
      treated accordingly. Intubated patients (if any) will be extubated upon rewarming if their
      neurological status allows for safe extubation. NIHSS will be recorded daily, and prior to
      discharge.

      Follow-Up on Day 5-7 post-treatment or at discharge (whichever comes first)

      Records to be collected at this time will include those related to physical exam, patient
      temperature, hematology, clinical chemistry, ECG, blood pressure, heart rate, concomitant
      medications, results of any follow-up CT or MRI scans, NIHSS, Glasgow Coma Scale, pupillary
      light response, MRS, Quality of Life (Neuro-QOL), and any adverse events.

      3 Month Follow Up

      NIHSS, MRS, and Quality of Life (Neuro-QOL) will be calculated at 90 days (+/-10 days)
      post-stroke. Any additional adverse events will also be recorded at this time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 25, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 25, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of cooling as indicated by percentage of patients cooled to target within 1 hour of start of cooling</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour after start of cooling</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility of rapidly cooling victims of ischemic stroke with the ThermoSuit System to 32-34°C.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurological outcome as indicated by NIHSS</measure>
    <time_frame>Hospital discharge or day 5-7 post-treatment (whichever comes first)</time_frame>
    <description>NIH Stroke Scale at hospital discharge or day 5-7 post-treatment (whichever comes first)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of the cooling treatment as indicated by rates of significant adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>A comparison of significant adverse event rates between the treatment and historical control group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurological outcome as indicated by MRS score</measure>
    <time_frame>Hospital discharge or day 5-7 post-treatment (whichever comes first)</time_frame>
    <description>Dichotomized modified Rankin score (mRS); an mRS score of less than or equal to 2 is to be considered a good outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in neurological outcome as indicated by NIHSS</measure>
    <time_frame>Hospital discharge or 5-7 days post-treatment (whichever comes first) and 90 +/- 10 days post-stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Change in NIHSS from that measured at hospital discharge or 5-7 days post-treatment (whichever comes first) to that measured at 90 +/- 10 days post-stroke</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in neurological status as indicated by MRS</measure>
    <time_frame>Hospital discharge or 5-7 days post-treatment (whichever comes first) and 90 +/- 10 days post-stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Change in dichotomized modified Rankin scale from that measured at hospital discharge or 5-7 days post-treatment (whichever comes first) to that measured at 90 +/- 10 days post-stroke</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patient death within 90 days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life as indicated by Neuro-QOL score</measure>
    <time_frame>Hospital discharge or 5-7 days post-treatment (whichever comes first) and 90 +/- 10 days post stroke</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Life of treated patients as assessed using Neuro-QOL forms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of procedure and device related SAEs</measure>
    <time_frame>0 to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of all procedure and device related significant adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Brain Ischemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ThermoSuit Cooling Induction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction of therapeutic hypothermia (32-34 degrees C) using the LRS ThermoSuit System. Prior to initiating hypothermia, Magnesium Sulfate will be administered intravenously to control shivering and tPA administered intravenously (if indicated). Induction doses of propofol or etomidate will be used to aid in the suppression of patient discomfort. Neurothrombectomy will be performed if indicated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Historical Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Historical patients treated for ischemic stroke using conventional medical treatments, but without induced hypothermia.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ThermoSuit Cooling Induction</intervention_name>
    <description>Rapid induction of therapeutic hypothermia (32-34 degrees C) using the Life Recovery Systems ThermoSuit System</description>
    <arm_group_label>ThermoSuit Cooling Induction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LRS ThermoSuit</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnesium Sulfate</intervention_name>
    <description>Magnesium sulfate will be administered intravenously as needed to control shivering</description>
    <arm_group_label>ThermoSuit Cooling Induction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Epsom salt</other_name>
    <other_name>Magnesium sulphate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tPA</intervention_name>
    <description>tPA will be administered intravenously if indicated</description>
    <arm_group_label>ThermoSuit Cooling Induction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tissue plasminogen activator</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propofol</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction doses of propofol or etomidate will be used to aid in the suppression of patient discomfort</description>
    <arm_group_label>ThermoSuit Cooling Induction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Diprivan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etomidate</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction doses of propofol or etomidate will be used to aid in the suppression of patient discomfort</description>
    <arm_group_label>ThermoSuit Cooling Induction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Amidate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurothrombectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>If indicated, neurothrombectomy will be performed using an FDA-cleared device within the FDA-cleared treatment window.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ThermoSuit Cooling Induction</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Endovascular Thrombectomy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ischemic cortical stroke with NIHSS &gt; _5_;

          -  Treatment initiated within 8 hours from known time of onset;

          -  Patient dimension criteria: Height: 147-190 cm (58 - 75 in) Width: ≤66 cm (26 in)
             (elbow to elbow).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Sepsis (bacteremia and clinical syndrome within 72 h);

          -  Known preexisting coagulopathy, (INR &gt; 1.3, PTT &gt;1.5 x control), active bleeding of
             unknown cause, immune compromised state, thrombocytopenia (platelet count &lt;
             160,000/mm), and history of cold agglutinin disease;

          -  Hemodynamically significant cardiac dysrhythmias (eg. QTc interval &gt;450 msec,
             bradycardia (heart rate less than 50), Mobitz Type II second degree AV block (or
             higher AV block), and severe ventricular dysrhythmias (sustained VT or VF) ) which
             cause significant hypotension (SBP ≤ 120 mmHg requiring more than two pressor
             medications);

          -  Preexistent illness with life expectancy &lt;6 months;

          -  Pregnancy;

          -  Rapidly improving symptoms;

          -  Melena, or gross hematuria;

          -  Sickle cell disease;

          -  Temperature &lt; 35°C on admission to Emergency Department;

          -  Recent (&lt; 1 week) incisions;

          -  Any intracerebral hemorrhage;

          -  A history of a brain vascular lesion (e.G. aneurism or arteriovenous malformation);

          -  A history of brain disease or damage (e.g. neoplasm or dementia);

          -  Patients receiving IV tPA &gt; 3 hours from stroke onset;

          -  Bradycardia (heart rate ≤ 50);

          -  High degree AV block;

          -  Ventricular tachycardia;

          -  Ventricular fibrillation.

          -  Significant hypotension &lt; 120 mm Hg, regardless of the underlying cause

        Exclusions for Patients to receive IV tPA :

          -  Suspicion of subarachnoid hemorrhage on pretreatment evaluation, even with normal
             neuroimaging;

          -  Systolic blood pressure greater than 185 mm of Hg or diastolic blood pressure &gt;110
             mmHg at the time of t-PA infusion and/or patient requires aggressive treatment to
             reduce blood pressure to within these limits;

          -  Seizure at onset of stroke;

          -  Active internal bleeding;

          -  Known bleeding diathesis, including but not limited to:

               -  Platelet count less than 100,000/mm3

               -  Heparin during the preceding 48 hours and elevated aPTT (greater than upper limit
                  of normal for laboratory)

               -  Current use of oral anticoagulants (ex: warfarin) and INR &gt;1.7;

               -  Current use of direct thrombin inhibitors or direct factor Xa inhibitors

               -  Elevated prothrombin time (PT) greater than 15 seconds.

          -  Major surgery or other serious trauma during preceding 14 days;

          -  Intercranial or intraspinal surgery, stroke, serious head trauma during preceding 3
             months;

          -  Recent arterial puncture at a non-compressible site;

          -  Recent lumbar puncture during preceding 7 days;

          -  History of intracranial hemorrhage, neoplasm, arteriovenous malformation, or aneurysm;

          -  Recent Acute Myocardial Infarction

          -  Abnormal blood glucose (&lt;50 or &gt;400 mg/dL)

          -  Suspected/confirmed endocarditis

        Exclusions for Patients Receiving Neurothrombectomy &gt;

          -  Patients with known hypersensitivity to nickel-titanium

          -  Patients with stenosis and/or pre-existing stent proximal to the thrombus site that
             may preclude safe recovery of the revascularization device

          -  Patients with angiographic evidence of carotid dissection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aimee Aysenne, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tulane University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert B Schock, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>973-283-2800</phone>
    <phone_ext>201</phone_ext>
    <email>bschock@life-recovery.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Richard Hettenbach, M.A.</last_name>
    <phone>973-283-2800</phone>
    <email>rhettenbach@life-recovery.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rapides Regional Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alexandria</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>71301</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gonzalo I Hidalgo, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>318-443-0490</phone>
      <email>ghidalgo@interspond.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lacey Bean</last_name>
      <phone>318-769-7094</phone>
      <email>Lacey.Bean@hcahealthcare.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tulane University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aimee Aysenne, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>504-407-6928</phone>
      <email>aaysenne@tulane.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Bonnie Katalenich, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>504-988-6200</phone>
      <email>bkatalen@tulane.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Justin Salerian, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 25, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etomidate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Magnesium Sulfate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tissue Plasminogen Activator</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

