<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02454673</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CUN-GCNMEM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02454673</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Therapeutic Individualization for Patients With Locally Advanced Gastric and Gastroesophageal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Approximation to the Therapeutic Individualization in Patients With Locally Advanced Gastric and Gastroesophageal Cancer Through Modelling and Generation of Predictive Gene Signatures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clinica Universidad de Navarra, Universidad de Navarra</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clinica Universidad de Navarra, Universidad de Navarra</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate whether the R0 rate, pathological response degree,
      patterns of recurrence and long-term outcomes may be initially predicted in patients with
      locally advanced gastroesophageal junction and gastric cancer treated with a neoadjuvant
      approach and salvage surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with locally advanced gastroesophageal junction and gastric cancer with T3-4 and/or
      N+ are included. Initially, patients are diagnosed by computerized tomography scan and
      endoscopic ultrasound. The neoadjuvant strategy consisted of 3-4 cycles of preoperative
      chemotherapy (group A) or 3-4 courses of induction chemotherapy followed by concurrent
      chemoradiotherapy (group B). Chemoradiotherapy comprised weekly chemotherapy concurrently
      with daily external beam radiotherapy up to 45 Gy). Surgery is scheduled 4 to 6 weeks after
      the end of CRT. Pathological response is graded according to the Becker criteria. Statistical
      analysis is performed IBM SPSS v20. Nonlinear mixed effects (NLME) modelling is applied to
      evaluate the impact of dynamic changes in tumor size, neutrophil lymphocyte ratio (NLR) and
      platelet lymphocyte ratio (PLR) on the clinical outcome of these patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of diagnosis until death, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival was defined as the period from diagnosis until death (from any cause). Nonlinear mixed effects population modelling to evaluate the impact in clinical outcome of dynamic markers as tumor size, neutrophil lymphocyte ratio (NLR) and platelet lymphocyte ratio (PLR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of diagnosis until treatment failure, assessed up to 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>DFS was defined as the time from diagnosis to the first date of local or distant cancer. Nonlinear mixed effects population modelling to evaluate the impact in clinical outcome of dynamic markers as tumor size, neutrophil lymphocyte ratio (NLR) and platelet lymphocyte ratio (PLR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological Response at the Time of Surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 10 to 28</time_frame>
    <description>Specimen analysis according to TNM classification. Pathological complete response is defined as no invasive cancer cells in the surgical specimen.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>R0 Resection rate at the Time of Surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 10 to 28</time_frame>
    <description>The R0 resection rate after the neoadjuvant protocol. R0 is defined as a microscopically margin-negative resection, in which no gross or microscopic tumor remains in the primary tumor bed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor Regression Grade at the Time of Surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 10 to 28</time_frame>
    <description>Estimate of tumor regression grade at the time of surgery according to Becker Criteria: Grade 1a, No residual tumor; Grade 1b, &lt;10% residual tumor; Grade 2, 10-50% residual tumor; Grade 3, &gt;50% residual tumor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lymph nodes response at the Time of Surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 10 to 28</time_frame>
    <description>Participants were assessed for node-negative lymph nodes at the time of surgery according to TNM classification. Node-negative (pN0) participants had no regional lymph node metastasis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimate of TN Change From Baseline to Surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 10 to 28</time_frame>
    <description>Estimate of TN change due to neoadjuvant treatment is defined as the estimate of the evidence of downstaging between baseline and surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">121</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Effects of Chemotherapy</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <description>3-4 cycles of preoperative chemotherapy
Surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <description>3-4 cycles of induction chemotherapy
Radiotherapy with concurrent chemotherapy for 5 weeks
Surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Surgical specimen with potential for extraction of DNA.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with locally advanced adenocarcinoma gastric cancer for a neoadjuvant protocol
        consisting of preoperative chemotherapy or induction chemotherapy, chemoradiotherapy and
        salvage surgery. Patients must have a medically fit condition to complete the protocol.

        Initial staging comprises a thoracic and abdominal computerised tomography scan, endoscopic
        ultrasound endoscopy (EUS), biopsy and blood test including blood cell count, hepatic and
        renal function.

        Radiological and endoscopic evaluations are performed at baseline and at the completion of
        chemotherapy and chemoradiotherapy.

        Blood tests are acquired at baseline, before each chemotherapy course and concurrently with
        evaluations. Blood tests are also obtained during follow-up and at the time progression.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the stomach or gastroesophageal cancer

          -  Age ≥18 years old

          -  Performance Status- Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 0-1

          -  Body mass index ≥ 18

          -  No prior chemotherapy or chemoradiotherapy

          -  TNM stage of T3-T4 and/or positive regional lymph nodes (N+) by endoscopic ultrasound
             or computed tomography (CT)

          -  No evidence of metastasis (M0)

          -  Adequate hematological, liver and renal functions (ALT and AST≤2.5 UNL, total
             bilirubin ≤1.5 UNL, and serum creatinine ≤1.5 UNL)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with previous (less than 10 years) or current history of malignant neoplasms,
             except for curatively treated

          -  Patients with evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic disease

          -  Medically unfit for chemotherapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Javier Rodriguez Rodriguez, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinica Universidad de Navarra</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Universidad de Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cunningham D, Allum WH, Stenning SP, Thompson JN, Van de Velde CJ, Nicolson M, Scarffe JH, Lofts FJ, Falk SJ, Iveson TJ, Smith DB, Langley RE, Verma M, Weeden S, Chua YJ, MAGIC Trial Participants. Perioperative chemotherapy versus surgery alone for resectable gastroesophageal cancer. N Engl J Med. 2006 Jul 6;355(1):11-20.</citation>
    <PMID>16822992</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xiong BH, Cheng Y, Ma L, Zhang CQ. An updated meta-analysis of randomized controlled trial assessing the effect of neoadjuvant chemotherapy in advanced gastric cancer. Cancer Invest. 2014 Jul;32(6):272-84. doi: 10.3109/07357907.2014.911877. Epub 2014 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24800782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stahl M, Walz MK, Stuschke M, Lehmann N, Meyer HJ, Riera-Knorrenschild J, Langer P, Engenhart-Cabillic R, Bitzer M, Königsrainer A, Budach W, Wilke H. Phase III comparison of preoperative chemotherapy compared with chemoradiotherapy in patients with locally advanced adenocarcinoma of the esophagogastric junction. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Feb 20;27(6):851-6. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.17.0506. Epub 2009 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19139439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carton E, Caldwell MT, McDonald G, Rama D, Tanner WA, Reynolds JV. Specialized intestinal metaplasia in patients with gastro-oesophageal reflux disease. Br J Surg. 2000 Jan;87(1):116-21.</citation>
    <PMID>10606922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moehler M, Baltin CT, Ebert M, Fischbach W, Gockel I, Grenacher L, Hölscher AH, Lordick F, Malfertheiner P, Messmann H, Meyer HJ, Palmqvist A, Röcken C, Schuhmacher C, Stahl M, Stuschke M, Vieth M, Wittekind C, Wagner D, Mönig SP. International comparison of the German evidence-based S3-guidelines on the diagnosis and multimodal treatment of early and locally advanced gastric cancer, including adenocarcinoma of the lower esophagus. Gastric Cancer. 2015 Jul;18(3):550-63. doi: 10.1007/s10120-014-0403-x. Epub 2014 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25192931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee S, Oh SY, Kim SH, Lee JH, Kim MC, Kim KH, Kim HJ. Prognostic significance of neutrophil lymphocyte ratio and platelet lymphocyte ratio in advanced gastric cancer patients treated with FOLFOX chemotherapy. BMC Cancer. 2013 Jul 22;13:350. doi: 10.1186/1471-2407-13-350.</citation>
    <PMID>23876227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 26, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Neoadjuvant therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacodynamics</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Nonlinear Dynamics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

