<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02458690</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1411802537</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL122245</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02458690</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>eIMPACT Trial: Modernized Collaborative Care to Reduce the Excess CVD Risk of Older Depressed Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>eIMPACT Trial: Modernized Collaborative Care to Reduce the Excess CVD Risk of Older Depressed Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this randomized controlled trial is to evaluate whether the investigators
      modernized IMPACT intervention for depression (eIMPACT), delivered before the onset of
      cardiovascular disease (CVD), reduces the risk of future CVD. Participants will be primary
      care patients who are depressed but do not have a history of CVD. Half of the participants
      will receive standard depression treatment in primary care (usual care), and the other half
      will receive one year of eIMPACT, a collaborative stepped care program including
      antidepressants and computerized and telephonic cognitive-behavioral therapy. To evaluate
      change in CVD risk, the investigators will measure artery function using ultrasound before
      and after the 1-year treatment period. It is hypothesized that patients who receive the
      eIMPACT intervention will have greater improvements in artery function than patients who
      receive usual care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the number one killer of American men and women, and its
      economic burden is substantial and on the rise. Adults with depression are at elevated risk
      of CVD events and poor CVD prognosis. Unfortunately, past trials of depression treatments
      have not observed the anticipated cardiovascular benefits. A novel explanation for these null
      results is that the interventions in these trials, which all involved patients with
      preexisting CVD, were delivered too late in the natural history of CVD. To begin to evaluate
      our hypothesis that treating depression before clinical CVD onset could reduce CVD risk, the
      investigators are conducting a phase II randomized controlled trial of 216 primary care
      patients aged ≥ 50 years with a depressive disorder and CVD risk factors but no clinical CVD.
      Patients will be randomized to one year of eIMPACT, our modernized IMPACT intervention, or
      usual primary care for depression. eIMPACT is a collaborative stepped care intervention
      involving a multidisciplinary team delivering evidenced-based depression treatments
      consistent with patient preference. The investigator shave modernized our intervention by
      incorporating computerized cognitive-behavioral therapy and delivering other treatment
      components via telephone. Our central hypothesis is that eIMPACT will improve endothelial
      dysfunction, which is considered a barometer of CVD risk, in depressed adults by decreasing
      depressive symptoms, autonomic dysfunction, systemic inflammation, and platelet activation.
      The investigators will test our central hypothesis by carrying out these specific aims: (1)
      to determine whether eIMPACT reduces the excess CVD risk of depressed patients (primary
      outcome: endothelial dysfunction; exploratory outcome: incident CVD events) and (2) to
      examine candidate mechanisms underlying the effect of eIMPACT on CVD risk (secondary
      outcomes: depressive symptoms, autonomic dysfunction, systemic inflammation, and platelet
      activation). A positive trial would generate the mechanistic rationale, efficacy evidence,
      and effect size estimates needed to justify and design a multisite, event-driven, phase III
      trial to confirm eIMPACT's efficacy in reducing CVD risk. Demonstrating that depression
      treatment reduces CVD risk, the primary expected outcome of this line of research, would have
      a substantial positive impact. It would identify a novel target (depression) for CVD
      prevention efforts, and it would equip providers with a new disseminable and scalable tool
      (eIMPACT) to simultaneously treat depression and manage the CVD risk of a large cohort of
      high-risk patients. Collectively, these changes to clinical practice should translate into
      reduced CVD morbidity, mortality, and costs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Brachial Flow-Mediated Dilation (FMD) at 12-months</measure>
    <time_frame>0 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patients undergo ultrasound assessment of brachial FMD in accordance with established guidelines. After a 10-minute supine rest, high-resolution baseline images of the brachial artery will be obtained from 3 consecutive cardiac cycles. Next, the forearm cuff will be inflated to 250 mmHg for 5 minutes and then will be rapidly deflated. At 60 and 90 seconds post-deflation, images from 3 consecutive cardiac cycles will be acquired. FMD values will be computed as the % increase in brachial diameter at either 60 or 90 seconds after cuff deflation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">216</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Dysthymic Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Depressive Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>eIMPACT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>eIMPACT is a collaborative stepped care intervention involving a multidisciplinary team delivering evidenced-based treatments consistent with patient preference. Intervention approaches include antidepressant medications, a computerized cognitive-behavioral therapy called Beating the Blues (BtB), and telephonic cognitive-behavioral therapy called Problem Solving Treatment in Primary Care (PST-PC).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients and their primary care providers are informed of the positive depression screen, and follow-up is encouraged.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Beating the Blues (BtB)</intervention_name>
    <description>BTB is a widely used, empirically supported, stand-alone CBT program for depression designed for primary care patients and appropriate for adults with little computer experience and a 5th-6th grade reading level. BtB utilizes an interactive, multimedia format to deliver eight 50-minute, weekly therapy sessions. Although sessions are tailored to each patient's problems, general topics include challenging dysfunctional thoughts, activity scheduling, problem solving, graded exposure, task breakdown, sleep management, and relapse prevention. Patients are also assigned tailored homeworks that are customized to their needs and reviewed at the start of each session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>eIMPACT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</other_name>
    <other_name>Computer-Based Psychotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Problem Solving Treatment in Primary Care (PST-PC)</intervention_name>
    <description>PST-PC is a manualized, empirically supported CBT developed for use by healthcare professionals in primary care. The focus of the 6-10 30-minute sessions is teaching patients approaches for solving current problems contributing to depression. We are delivering PST-PC via telephone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>eIMPACT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</other_name>
    <other_name>Telephonic Psychotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antidepressant Medications</intervention_name>
    <description>The IMPACT treatment manual provides guidelines for using antidepressants, such as selecting a medication, titrating, switching to another medication, managing side effects, and avoiding drug interactions. The depression clinical specialist (DCS) will work with the patient's primary care provider to develop a plan that follows the IMPACT algorithm. Primary care providers will manage prescriptions. To optimize eIMPACT for CVD risk reduction, we will restrict the list of antidepressants to SSRIs (except paroxetine) and serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs).</description>
    <arm_group_label>eIMPACT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitors (SSRIs)</other_name>
    <other_name>Serotonin-Norepinephrine Reuptake Inhibitors (SNRIs)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized to usual primary care for depression are informed of their depression diagnosis, encouraged to follow-up with their primary care provider, and provided a list of local mental health services. The patient's primary care provider will receive a letter indicating that their patient has a depressive disorder and was randomized to usual care. This letter also provides a list of local mental health services. Like those in the intervention group, usual care patients continue to have access to services that are part of usual care in the targeted systems. There are no restrictions on the care received.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Treatment As Usual (TAU)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary care patients

          -  Age ≥ 50 years

          -  Current depressive disorder

          -  Elevated CVD risk

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of clinical cardiovascular disease

          -  Presence of the following chronic disorders: HIV/AIDS, chronic kidney disease,
             systemic inflammatory disease, or past-year cancer

          -  History of bipolar disorder or psychosis

          -  Continuous (e.g., daily) treatment for a systemic inflammatory condition (e.g.,
             rheumatoid arthritis, lupus, Crohn's disease, and ulcerative colitis) in the past 3
             months. Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) use is allowed, given its high
             prevalence in the target population.

          -  • Current use of anticoagulants (Aspirin and cholesterol and blood pressure
             medications are allowed)

          -  Acute risk of suicide

          -  Severe cognitive impairment

          -  Current pregnancy

          -  Ongoing depression treatment with a psychiatrist outside of the Eskenazi
             Health/Midtown system (ongoing depression treatment with a Eskenazi Health/Midtown
             psychiatrist is allowed, as we will be able to collaborate and coordinate depression
             care)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jesse C Stewart, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University-Purdue University Indianapolis (IUPUI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IUPUI Department of Psychology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 19, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 19, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jesse Stewart</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Psychology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Primary Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Older Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Antidepressant Medications</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Computer-Based Psychotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dysthymic Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antidepressive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Serotonin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Norepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Serotonin Uptake Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

