<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02450851</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>150130</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>15-HG-0130</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02450851</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Genetic Evaluation of Individuals With Undiagnosed Disorders Through the Undiagnosed Diseases Network</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical and Genetic Evaluation of Patients With Undiagnosed Disorders Through the Undiagnosed Diseases Network</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Without an explanation for severe and sometimes life-threatening symptoms, patients and
      their families are left in a state of unknown. The NIH helped create a network of medical
      research centers, called the Undiagnosed Diseases Network (UDN), to provide care and answers
      for these individuals.

      Objectives:

      - To improve diagnosis and care for people with undiagnosed diseases.

      Eligibility:

      - People with undiagnosed diseases, and their relatives.

      Design:

        -  Participants will travel to one of the UDN medical centers for a 5-day clinical and
           research visit.

             -  As part of the visit, UDN healthcare providers may ask participants to have:

                  -  Clinically indicated tests and procedures performed including:

                       -  A physical exam

                       -  Blood and urine tests

                       -  A review of health and family history

                       -  X-rays and body scans

                       -  Surveys

                       -  Photographs of the face and body

                       -  A special diet to see if the body can handle the food without having a
                          reaction, like vomiting

                       -  Video or voice recordings

                       -  Other tests and procedures to help reach a diagnosis

                  -  Research tests and procedures performed including:

                       -  A skin biopsy. For this, a small piece of skin will be taken.

                       -  Surveys

                       -  Other tests and procedures for research that may not be related to a
                          diagnosis or treatment.

        -  Most participants will be asked to give samples for genetic testing.

        -  Participants may be contacted after their visit to discuss test results. They may also
           be contacted in the future for interviews and surveys.

        -  Relatives of participants may be asked to give samples for genetic testing. They may be
           asked to have parts of their visit recorded and to have additional tests. They may also
           be contacted in the future for interviews and surveys.

        -  Clinical and research information collected will be stored in a database.

        -  Information and samples collected will be shared with others for research purposes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Without an explanation for severe and sometimes life-threatening symptoms, patients and their
      families are left in a state of unknown. Many individuals find themselves being passed from
      physician to physician, undergoing countless and often repetitive tests in the hopes of
      finding answers and insight about what the future may hold. This long and arduous journey to
      find a diagnosis does not end for many patients- the Office of Rare Diseases Research (ORDR)
      notes that 6% of individuals seeking their assistance have an undiagnosed disorder. In 2008,
      the National Institutes of Health (NIH) Undiagnosed Diseases Program (UDP) was established
      with the goal of providing care and answers for these individuals with mysterious conditions
      who have long eluded diagnosis. The NIH UDP is a joint venture of the NIH ORDR, the National
      Human Genome Research Institute Intramural Research Program (NHGRI-IRP), and the NIH Clinical
      Research Center (CRC). The goals of the NIH UDP are to: (1) provide answers for patients with
      undiagnosed diseases; (2) generate new knowledge about disease mechanisms; (3) assess the
      application of new approaches to phenotyping and the use of genomic technologies; and (4)
      identify potential therapeutic targets, if possible. To date, the UDP has evaluated 3300
      medical records and admitted 750 individuals with rare and undiagnosed conditions to the NIH
      Clinical Center. The NIH UDP has identified more than

      70 rare disease diagnoses and several new conditions. The success of the NIH UDP prompted the
      NIH Common Fund to support the establishment of a network of medical research centers, the
      Undiagnosed Diseases Network (UDN), for fiscal years 2013-2020. The clinical sites will
      perform extensive phenotyping, genetic analyses, and functional studies of potential
      disease-causing variants. The testing performed on patients involves medically indicated
      studies intended to help reach a diagnosis, as well as research investigations that include a
      skin biopsy, blood draws, and DNA analysis. In addition, the UDN will further the goals of
      the UDP by permitting the sharing of personally identifiable phenotypic and genotypic
      information within the network. By sharing participant information and encouraging
      collaboration, the UDN hopes to improve the understanding of rare conditions and advance the
      diagnostic process and care for individuals with undiagnosed diseases.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 19, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Making a diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Admission and ad hoc after that</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8000</enrollment>
  <condition>Undiagnosed Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  The applicant has a condition that remains undiagnosed despite thorough evaluation by
             a healthcare provider and has at least one objective finding.

          -  The applicant (or legal guardian) agrees to the storage and sharing of information and
             biomaterials in an identified fashion amongst the UDN centers, and in a de-identified
             fashion to research sites beyond the network.

          -  For the metabolomics analysis site-specific research project, the individual must be a
             patient in the inherited metabolic disease clinic at Boston Children s Hospital or the
             Oregon Health &amp; Science University and have a confirmed diagnosis of an inherited
             metabolic disorder based on DNA, enzyme analysis, or other standard practice.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  The applicant has a diagnosis that explains the objective findings.

          -  Review of the records suggests a diagnosis and further evaluation by the UDN is deemed
             unnecessary.

          -  The UDN is unlikely to improve on the comprehensive workup the applicant already
             received

          -  The applicant is too seriously ill to travel safely to the UDN site and
             telemedicine/distance consult is not possible or appropriate.

          -  For the metabolomics analysis site-specific research project, individuals who are
             pregnant, have intercurrent illness, or are using drugs and/or supplements deemed
             likely to alter the usual metabolic state will be excluded. Individuals unable to
             provide informed consent or assent will also be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William A Gahl, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Mazur</last_name>
    <phone>(844) 746-4836</phone>
    <email>udn@hms.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Mazur</last_name>
      <phone>844-746-4836</phone>
      <email>udn@hms.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children s Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Univ Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2015-HG-0130.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://undiagnosed.hms.harvard.edu</url>
    <description>https://undiagnosed.hms.harvard.edu</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gahl WA, Boerkoel CF, Boehm M. The NIH Undiagnosed Diseases Program: bonding scientists and clinicians. Dis Model Mech. 2012 Jan;5(1):3-5. doi: 10.1242/dmm.009258.</citation>
    <PMID>22228787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gahl WA, Markello TC, Toro C, Fajardo KF, Sincan M, Gill F, Carlson-Donohoe H, Gropman A, Pierson TM, Golas G, Wolfe L, Groden C, Godfrey R, Nehrebecky M, Wahl C, Landis DM, Yang S, Madeo A, Mullikin JC, Boerkoel CF, Tifft CJ, Adams D. The National Institutes of Health Undiagnosed Diseases Program: insights into rare diseases. Genet Med. 2012 Jan;14(1):51-9. doi: 10.1038/gim.0b013e318232a005. Epub 2011 Sep 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22237431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gahl WA, Tifft CJ. The NIH Undiagnosed Diseases Program: lessons learned. JAMA. 2011 May 11;305(18):1904-5. doi: 10.1001/jama.2011.613.</citation>
    <PMID>21558523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 8, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 19, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rare Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Undiagnosed Disease</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

