<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02451865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-001595</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-00618</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Garon MEK162 NSCLC</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>14-001595</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016042</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02451865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Binimetinib With Docetaxel in Treating Patients With Previously Treated, Stage IV Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IB Dose Escalation and Expansion Trial of MEK 162 With Docetaxel in Previously Treated Stage IV, Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase Ib trial studies the safety and best dose of binimetinib when given in combination
      with docetaxel in treating patients with previously treated, stage IV non-small cell lung
      cancer. Binimetinib and docetaxel may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the
      enzymes needed for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Evaluate the safety and tolerability of increasing doses of MEK162 (binimetinib) with
      docetaxel 75 mg/m2 every 21 days in patients with stage IV non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC)
      that have progressed after at least one prior systemic therapy.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine objective tumor response rate (RR) as defined by Response Evaluation Criteria In
      Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 with MEK162 and standard doses of docetaxel in stage IV NSCLC.

      II. Determine progression free survival (PFS) of MEK162 and standard doses of docetaxel.

      III. Evaluate the pharmacokinetic profile of MEK162 when given along with docetaxel.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Evaluate tissue biomarkers in baseline tumors and at the time of progression to correlate
      with clinical outcome II. Assess the activation status of extracellular signal-regulated
      kinase (ERK), protein kinase B (Akt) and ribosomal protein S6 kinase (S6K) in tumor biopsy
      samples at baseline and at the time of progression.

      III. Determine the cytokine profile before and after treatment in patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of binimetinib.

      Patients receive binimetinib orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-21 and docetaxel
      intravenously (IV) on day 21. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 6 courses in the
      absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients who have stable disease or
      better after completing 6 courses of binimetinib and docetaxel may continue receiving
      binimetinib PO BID in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days and then annually
      for up to 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events, graded according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version (v)4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Side effects will be tabulated according to grade and will do sub-analysis based on patient demographic categories such as age and ECOG performance status.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of dose-limiting toxicities, graded according to the CTCAE v4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Side effects will be tabulated according to grade and will do sub-analysis based on patient demographic categories such as age and ECOG performance status.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose of binimetinib in combination with docetaxel</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker analyses</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Will determine if there is a correlation of baseline biomarkers and objective tumor response. For categorical markers will use Fisher's exact test to examine the relationship with response and different categorical variables at specific time points. For quantitative markers will use one-way analysis of variance to compare the marker levels between response categories. Correlations between pairs of quantitative markers will be performed using Pearson correlations if the marker distributions are approximately normal. For non-normality will use the Kendall correlation coefficients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mutations in KRAS and NRAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Will determine if there is a correlation of response in patients treated with docetaxel and binimetinib with mutations in KRAS and NRAS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective tumor response rate (the rate of complete response or partial response), as defined by RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion ever achieving a clinical and objective tumor response will be estimated and will construct an exact one-sided 90% confidence interval to identify the likely range for the underlying tumor response rate. Tumor response will be correlated with biomarkers as well as other patient characteristics such as ECOG performance status, k-ras and neuroblastoma RAS viral oncogene homolog (n-ras) mutational status using a variety of analytic techniques.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) profile will assess binimetinib (MEK162) levels during treatment cycles</measure>
    <time_frame>On days 1 and 8 of course 1 and on day 1 of course 2</time_frame>
    <description>Analyzed by tabulation of PK values with mean and standard deviation at each time point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cox-proportional hazards regression models will be used to correlate time to disease progression to both quantitative and categorical variables. Survival distributions will be estimated with the Kaplan-Meier method and significant differences between survival rates will be calculated with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Non-Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (binimetinib and docetaxel)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive binimetinib PO BID on days 1-21 and docetaxel IV on day 21. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients who have stable disease or better after completing 6 courses of binimetinib and docetaxel may continue receiving binimetinib PO BID in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Binimetinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (binimetinib and docetaxel)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ARRY-162</other_name>
    <other_name>ARRY-438162</other_name>
    <other_name>MEK162</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (binimetinib and docetaxel)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RP56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere Injection Concentrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (binimetinib and docetaxel)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed written informed consent

          -  A histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of stage IV NSCLC

          -  Must have progressed on at least one prior line of platinum-based therapy for stage IV
             NSCLC (excluding docetaxel or mitogen activated protein kinase kinase [MEK]
             inhibitors)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-1

          -  Measurable disease defined by RECIST criteria

          -  Ability to provide adequate tissue from archival tumor specimen; confirmation of
             adequate tissue is required prior to enrollment

          -  In expansion cohort only: patient's kirsten rat sarcoma viral oncogene homolog (KRAS)
             mutational status must be known prior to enrollment

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.5 x 10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &gt;= 9 g/dL without transfusions

          -  Platelets (PLT) &gt;= 100 x 10^9/L without transfusions

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and/or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 1.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 mg/dL

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;= 45% as determined by a multigated
             acquisition (MUGA) scan or echocardiogram, and QTc interval =&lt; 480ms

          -  Able to take and retain oral medications

          -  Patient is deemed by the investigator to have the initiative and means to be compliant
             with the protocol (treatment and follow-up)

          -  Negative serum beta-human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG) test (female patient of
             childbearing potential only) performed locally within 72 hours (hrs) prior to first
             dose

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History or current evidence of retinal vein occlusion (RVO) or current risk factors to
             RVO (e.g. uncontrolled glaucoma or ocular hypertension, history of hyperviscosity or
             hypercoagulability syndromes)

          -  History of Gilbert syndrome

          -  Previous or concurrent malignancy within the last 3 years with the exception of
             adequately treated skin basal or squamous cell with adequate wound healing

          -  Prior therapy with a MEK-inhibitor or docetaxel for metastatic non-small cell lung
             cancer (docetaxel in the adjuvant setting will be allowed)

          -  Epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) mutant and/or anaplastic lymphoma receptor
             tyrosine kinase (ALK) gene rearranged tumor

          -  Impaired cardiovascular function or clinically significant cardiovascular diseases,
             including any of the following within 6 months of enrollment: myocardial infarction,
             unstable angina, coronary artery bypass graft (CABG), coronary angioplasty, or
             stenting, symptomatic chronic heart failure, clinically significant cardiac
             arrhythmias and/or conduction (except atrial fibrillation and paroxysmal
             supraventricular tachycardia)

          -  Uncontrolled arterial hypertension despite appropriate medical therapy

          -  Known positive serology for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), active hepatitis B,
             and/or active hepatitis C infection

          -  Neuromuscular disorders that are associated with elevated creatine kinase (CK) (e.g.,
             inflammatory myopathies, muscular dystrophy)

          -  Subjects planning on embarking on a new strenuous exercise regimen after first dose of
             study treatment that can result in significant increases in plasma CK levels

          -  Impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal disease (e.g., ulcerative
             disease, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption)

          -  Any other condition that would, in the investigator's judgment, contraindicate the
             patient's participation in the clinical study due to concerns regarding safety or
             compliance with clinical study procedures

          -  Patients who have undergone major surgery =&lt; 3 weeks prior to starting study drug or
             who have not recovered from side effects of such procedure

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Women of child-bearing potential defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant who are unwilling to use highly effective methods of contraception
             throughout the study and 15 days after study drug discontinuation

          -  Sexually active males unless they are willing to use a condom during intercourse while
             taking the drug and for 15 days after stopping treatment and are willing to forego
             fathering a child in this period; a condom is required to be used also by vasectomized
             men

          -  Medical, psychiatric, cognitive or other conditions that may compromise the patient's
             ability to understand the patient information, give informed consent, comply with the
             study protocol or complete the study

          -  Grade II or greater neuropathy at baseline

          -  Symptomatic brain metastases (if a patient has brain metastases and is on steroids,
             the steroid dose must have been stable for at least 14 days) or brain metastases that
             have not been previously treated

          -  Treatment with prior chemotherapy, monoclonal antibodies, other protein or peptide
             therapeutics or anticancer immunotherapy within 21 days of the first dose of study
             drug

          -  Treatment with prior radiotherapy within 28 days of initiating study drug; however, if
             the radiation portal covered =&lt; 10% of the bone marrow reserve, the patient may be
             enrolled without respect to the end date of radiotherapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Edward Garon</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCLA / Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA / Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

