<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02457442</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SPRV</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>157/15</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02457442</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interaction of Sevoflurane Propofol and Remifentanil in Anesthesia for Laparoscopic Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPRV</acronym>
  <official_title>Validation of the Interaction Model of the Anesthetic Potency of Sevoflurane, Propofol and Remifentanil</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recently a new model for the interaction of sevoflurane propofol and remifentanil was
      developed. The potency of any combination of the three drugs is defined as probability that a
      subject tolerates laryngoscopy without movement response. The model allows to compare the
      potency of intravenous and inhalation anesthetics. If the model is valid also for other
      stimuli than laryngoscopy and for other responses (e.g. blood pressure or heart rate increase
      upon stimulation). If the model is valid equipotent concentrations of sevoflurane and
      propofol the same remifentanil concentration would be sufficient to suppress hemodynamic
      response to a given stimulus. This will be investigated it the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      In general anesthesia propofol or volatile anesthetic are usually combined with opioids and
      the synergy between hypnotics and opioids is used to reduce the dose of each component in
      order to minimize side effects and to allow a rapid recovery. Current pharmacodynamic
      interaction models allow to estimate the potency of combinations of propofol and opioids,
      volatile anesthetics and opioids or propofol and sevoflurane respectively. In these
      interaction models the potency of the drug combinations is expressed as probability that
      motor response to laryngoscopy is suppressed (= tolerance of laryngoscopy, PTOL). The potency
      of the hypnotic drugs is represented by the concentration preventing motor response to
      laryngoscopy in 50% of the population (Ce50 hypnotic). Conversely potency of the opioids is
      represented as concentration reducing the Ce50 of the hypnotics by 50%.

      The data of the three previous studies on propofol-remifentanil, propofol-sevoflurane and
      sevoflurane-remifentanil interaction were pooled and reanalyzed. The result was a triple
      interaction model of sevoflurane, propofol and remifentanil where sevoflurane and propofol
      were additive and either propofol or sevoflurane were synergistic with remifentanil. In
      contrast to the previous studies the response surface of the propofol-remifentanil and
      sevoflurane-remifentanil derived from the pooled re-analysis had a similar shape, which is
      reflected by a common C50 remifentanil and a common slope parameter. This means that
      remifentanil is equally synergistic to propofol and sevoflurane. The next step is to validate
      this interaction model with other stimuli than laryngoscopy and with other responses to
      stimulation that movement.

      In clinical practice not motor response but hemodynamic response (heart rate and arterial
      blood pressure increase) upon surgical stimulation is used to titrate anesthetics and
      opioids.

      In laparoscopic surgery after a small skin incision, carbon dioxide is inflated into the
      abdominal cavity to maintain an intraabdominal pressure of 14 mmHg. Recently the sevoflurane
      concentration preventing a heart rate or blood pressure increase greater than 20% upon
      installation of pneumoperitoneum (MAC BAR pneumoperitoneum) has been determined: The MAC BAR
      pneumoperitoneum (95% CI) of sevoflurane was 4.6 (4.3-4.9) without opioids and 2.4 (2.2-2.6)
      and 1.7 (1.4-2.1) vol% with an effect site remifentanil concentration of 1 and 2 ng
      ml-1.These values all correspond to 90% probability to tolerate laryngoscopy (PTOL) according
      to our triple interaction model (Hannivoort, BJA 2016), which indirectly supports our model.

      The main purpose of this randomized controlled study is to validate our
      sevoflurane-propofol-remifentanil interaction model using skin incision and carbon dioxide
      insufflation (pneumoperitoneum) as stimulus and blood pressure and heart rate response as
      endpoint.

      Objective

      To determine the C50 remifentanil preventing a 20% increase of heart rate or mean arterial
      pressure upon installation of pneumoperitoneum at equipotent concentrations of sevoflurane or
      propofol To determine the C50 of sevoflurane and propofol preventing a 20% increase of heart
      rate or mean arterial pressure upon installation of pneumoperitoneum at a standardized
      concentration of remifentanil

      To determine the C50 of propofol or sevoflurane preventing a 20% increase of heart rate or
      mean arterial pressure upon installation of pneumoperitoneum at standardized concentrations
      of remifentanil plus sevoflurane or propofol respectively.

      Methods

      Patients will be randomly assigned to six groups with different propofol sevoflurane and
      remifentanil target concentrations for skin incision: Two groups with be given
      propofol-remifentanil, sevoflurane-remifentanil and sevoflurane-propofol-remifentanil
      respectively. The up-and-down method will be applied to determine the C50ies. During surgery
      primarily remifentanil and secondarily sevoflurane or propofol are titrated to maintain mean
      arterial pressure and bispectral index within predefined limits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>20% heart rate or mean arterial pressure increase upon installation of pneumoperitoneum</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes within pneumoperitoneum, expected to be on average ca. 5-15 minutes</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean (SD) Bloodpressure during surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Values recorded on computer HD every 10 sec during anesthesia, expected to be on average ca. 60 - 240 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean (SD) Bispectral Index during surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Values recorded on computer HD every 10 sec. during anesthesia, expected to be on average ca. 60 - 240 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean (SD) Remifentanil concentration during surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery, expected to be on average ca. 60 - 240 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative quality of recovery score</measure>
    <time_frame>During hospital stay, expected to be on average ca. 3-5 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Drug Interactions</condition>
  <condition>Anesthesia, Conduction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PR1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Propofol-Remifentanil: Prop high, Remi low. Changing Remi (up-and-down)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PR2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Propofol-Remifentanil: Prop low, Remi high. Changing Prop (up-and-down)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SR1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sevoflurane-Remifentanil: Sevo high, Remi low. Changing Remi (up-and-down)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SR2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sevoflurane-Remifentanil: Sevo low, Remi high. Changing Sevo (up-and-down)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SPR1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sevoflurane-Propofol-Remifentanil: Sevo plus Remi intermediate, Remi intermediate; changing Propofol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SPR2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sevoflurane-Propofol-Remifentanil: Sevo plus Remi intermediate, Remi intermediate; changing Sevoflurane.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propofol and Remifentanil</intervention_name>
    <description>High propofol and low remifentanil, changing remifentanil (up-and-down method)</description>
    <arm_group_label>PR1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propofol and Remifentanil</intervention_name>
    <description>Low propofol and high remifentanil, changing propofol (up-and-down method)</description>
    <arm_group_label>PR2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sevoflurane and Remifentanil</intervention_name>
    <description>High sevoflurane and low remifentanil, changing remifentanil (up-and-down method)</description>
    <arm_group_label>SR1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sevoflurane and Remifentanil</intervention_name>
    <description>Low sevoflurane and high remifentanil, changing sevoflurane up-and-down method)</description>
    <arm_group_label>SR2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SPR 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Triple combination with intermediate propofol and sevoflurane and intermediate remifentanil.
SPR 1: Changing Propofol for skin incision.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SPR1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SPR2</intervention_name>
    <description>Triple combination with intermediate propofol and sevoflurane and intermediate remifentanil.
Changing Sevoflurane for skin incision.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SPR2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ASA physical status 1 or 2

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Cardiovascular disease

          -  Pulmonary disease

          -  Liver disease

          -  CNS disease

          -  Alcohol or drug abuse

          -  Chronic intake of CNS active drugs

          -  Body mass index &gt; 35

          -  Diabetes mellitus

          -  Hypersensitivity or allergy to one of the study drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martin Luginbühl, PD Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Spitalnetzbern. Institut für Anästhesiologie Tiefenau-Ziegler</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Martin Luginbühl, PD Dr. med</last_name>
    <phone>+41 31 308 84 44</phone>
    <email>martin.luginbuehl@dkf.unibe.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Anesthesiology and Pain Therapy, Bern University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Martin Luginbühl, PD Dr. med</last_name>
      <phone>+41 31 308 84 44</phone>
      <email>martin.luginbuehl@spitalnetzbern.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Luginbühl, PD Dr. med</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schumacher PM, Dossche J, Mortier EP, Luginbuehl M, Bouillon TW, Struys MM. Response surface modeling of the interaction between propofol and sevoflurane. Anesthesiology. 2009 Oct;111(4):790-804. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181b799ef.</citation>
    <PMID>19741484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heyse B, Proost JH, Schumacher PM, Bouillon TW, Vereecke HE, Eleveld DJ, Luginbühl M, Struys MM. Sevoflurane remifentanil interaction: comparison of different response surface models. Anesthesiology. 2012 Feb;116(2):311-23. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318242a2ec.</citation>
    <PMID>22222473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luginbühl M, Schumacher PM, Vuilleumier P, Vereecke H, Heyse B, Bouillon TW, Struys MM. Noxious stimulation response index: a novel anesthetic state index based on hypnotic-opioid interaction. Anesthesiology. 2010 Apr;112(4):872-80. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181d40368.</citation>
    <PMID>20216387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bouillon TW, Bruhn J, Radulescu L, Andresen C, Shafer TJ, Cohane C, Shafer SL. Pharmacodynamic interaction between propofol and remifentanil regarding hypnosis, tolerance of laryngoscopy, bispectral index, and electroencephalographic approximate entropy. Anesthesiology. 2004 Jun;100(6):1353-72.</citation>
    <PMID>15166553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hannivoort LN, Vereecke HE, Proost JH, Heyse BE, Eleveld DJ, Bouillon TW, Struys MM, Luginbühl M. Probability to tolerate laryngoscopy and noxious stimulation response index as general indicators of the anaesthetic potency of sevoflurane, propofol, and remifentanil. Br J Anaesth. 2016 May;116(5):624-31. doi: 10.1093/bja/aew060.</citation>
    <PMID>27106965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 26, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anesthetics, Inhalation</keyword>
  <keyword>Anesthetics, Intravenous</keyword>
  <keyword>Analgesics, Opioid</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Remifentanil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sevoflurane</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

