<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02456402</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1111</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02456402</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Drug Coated Balloon Compared to Bare Metal Stent for de Novo Coronary Artery Lesions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of Drug Coated Balloon Compared to Bare Metal Stent Using FFR-guidance for the Treatment of de Novo Coronary Artery Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ulsan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Seoul National University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ulsan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized trial will assess the efficacy of Drug Coated Balloon (DCB) compared to Bare
      Metal Stent (BMS) using Fractional Flow Reserve (FFR) guidance for de novo coronary artery
      lesions in patients unable to tolerate dual antiplatelet therapy and at high risk of
      bleeding. Patients will be randomized after balloon angioplasty to receive either DCB or BMS.
      Endpoints are late luminal loss at 9 months, and major adverse cardiac events including
      arterial thrombosis at 1, 9 and 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although the use of drug-eluting stents (DES) has reduced in-stent restenosis when compared
      to bare metal stents (BMS) and decreased the incidence of adverse clinical events (1-2), DES
      therapy is limited by delayed arterial healing, late acquired malapposition and
      neo-atherosclerosis leading to an increased risk of late stent thrombosis and late restenosis
      (3-4). Conceptually, a permanent stent inhibits advantageous vascular remodeling and durable
      polymer provokes excessive inflammation (5). Non-stent based local drug delivery using
      paclitaxel-coated balloon has emerged as a new clinical treatment alternative by maintaining
      the anti-proliferative properties of DES (6). There is limited data on the efficacy of Drug
      Coated Balloon (DCB) treatment for de novo coronary lesions when compared to BMS. To avoid
      the risk of abrupt closure of target lesion after balloon angioplasty, a reliable predictor
      of coronary flow is necessary especially in de novo lesions of major coronary arteries.
      Therefore, using fractional flow reserve (FFR) after angioplasty as a good indicator of
      immediate functional improvement and reduced restenosis (7), the aim of this study is to
      assess the efficacy of DCB treatment compared to BMS in patients with de novo coronary artery
      lesions.

      Patients with de novo coronary artery lesions with &gt; 50% stenosis in a single vessel and at
      high risk of bleeding with the inability to tolerate dual antiplatelet therapy (DAPT) will be
      included in this trial. Patients will undergo balloon angioplasty and if the FFR post balloon
      angioplasty is &gt; 0.80, they will be randomized to receive either DCB or BMS. Patients will
      receive Quantitative Coronary Angiography (QCA) analysis at 9 months follow-up. Endpoints are
      late luminal loss at 9 months and major adverse events including arterial thrombosis at 1, 9
      and 12 months and these endpoints will be compared between DCB and BMS groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Late luminal loss</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major adverse cardiovascular events (MACE) (death, myocardial infarction, repeat revascularization, recurrent ischemic symptoms)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post procedure (up to 1 hour), 1 month, 9 months and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial thrombosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Post procedure (up to 1 hour), 1 month, 9 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Any stent thrombosis - acute, subacute/late stent thrombosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fractional Flow Reserve</measure>
    <time_frame>Post procedure (up to 1 hour) and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>FFR is the ratio of the pressure measured at the distal portion of the target lesion and the aortic ostium at maximal hyperemia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Stable Angina</condition>
  <condition>Unstable Angina</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug Coated Balloon</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PCB (SeQuent Please®, paclitaxel-coated balloon catheter, B. Braun, Melsungen, Germany)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bare Metal Stent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>BMS (Vision®)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Drug Coated Balloon</intervention_name>
    <description>If post balloon angioplasty FFR is more than 0.80, either DCB treatment or BMS implantation will be carried out based on randomization of 1:1. DCB (SeQuent Please paclitaxel-coated balloon catheter, B. Braun, Melsungen, Germany) will be applied at the predilated lesions. PCB will be delivered rapidly and inflated for 60 seconds with nominal pressure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug Coated Balloon</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bare Metal Stent</intervention_name>
    <description>BMS (Vision®) will be applied at the predilated lesions after angiographic confirmation of the target lesion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bare Metal Stent</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Stable Angina and Unstable angina

          -  single de novo coronary artery lesions in a single vessel with &gt; 50% diameter stenosis
             with a reference diameter &gt; 2.75mm

          -  Patients at high risk of bleeding and whom cannot tolerate dual antiplatelet therapy
             for &gt; 1 month are inclusion criteria for the study and are listed here:

          -  Unexplained anemia

          -  Atrial fibrillation with CHADSVASC &gt; or equal to 1

          -  Patients awaiting for non cardiac surgery within a year

          -  History of massive hemorrhage requiring transfusion

          -  History of upper GI bleeding

          -  Malignancy

          -  Poor compliance with medication

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  STEMI/NSTEMI within the preceding 72 hours

          -  Multivessel disease, chronic total occlusion, long lesions and left main disease

          -  heart failure with ejection fraction &lt; 35% and/or cardiogenic shock

          -  Previous history of or planned coronary artery bypass grafting

          -  life expectancy of less than 1 year
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eun-Seok Shin, M.D., PhD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ulsan University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ulsan University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dong-gu</city>
        <state>Ulsan</state>
        <zip>682-714</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eun-Seok Shin, MD., PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>+82 52 250 7056</phone>
      <email>sesim1989@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morice MC, Serruys PW, Sousa JE, Fajadet J, Ban Hayashi E, Perin M, Colombo A, Schuler G, Barragan P, Guagliumi G, Molnàr F, Falotico R; RAVEL Study Group. Randomized Study with the Sirolimus-Coated Bx Velocity Balloon-Expandable Stent in the Treatment of Patients with de Novo Native Coronary Artery Lesions. A randomized comparison of a sirolimus-eluting stent with a standard stent for coronary revascularization. N Engl J Med. 2002 Jun 6;346(23):1773-80.</citation>
    <PMID>12050336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moses JW, Leon MB, Popma JJ, Fitzgerald PJ, Holmes DR, O'Shaughnessy C, Caputo RP, Kereiakes DJ, Williams DO, Teirstein PS, Jaeger JL, Kuntz RE; SIRIUS Investigators. Sirolimus-eluting stents versus standard stents in patients with stenosis in a native coronary artery. N Engl J Med. 2003 Oct 2;349(14):1315-23.</citation>
    <PMID>14523139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joner M, Finn AV, Farb A, Mont EK, Kolodgie FD, Ladich E, Kutys R, Skorija K, Gold HK, Virmani R. Pathology of drug-eluting stents in humans: delayed healing and late thrombotic risk. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2006 Jul 4;48(1):193-202. Epub 2006 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>16814667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nakazawa G, Vorpahl M, Finn AV, Narula J, Virmani R. One step forward and two steps back with drug-eluting-stents: from preventing restenosis to causing late thrombosis and nouveau atherosclerosis. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2009 May;2(5):625-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2009.01.011.</citation>
    <PMID>19442951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Unverdorben M, Kleber FX, Heuer H, Figulla HR, Vallbracht C, Leschke M, Cremers B, Hardt S, Buerke M, Ackermann H, Boxberger M, Degenhardt R, Scheller B. Treatment of small coronary arteries with a paclitaxel-coated balloon catheter in the PEPCAD I study: are lesions clinically stable from 12 to 36 months? EuroIntervention. 2013 Sep;9(5):620-8. doi: 10.4244/EIJV9I5A99.</citation>
    <PMID>24058078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheller B, Speck U, Abramjuk C, Bernhardt U, Böhm M, Nickenig G. Paclitaxel balloon coating, a novel method for prevention and therapy of restenosis. Circulation. 2004 Aug 17;110(7):810-4. Epub 2004 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>15302790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bech GJ, Pijls NH, De Bruyne B, Peels KH, Michels HR, Bonnier HJ, Koolen JJ. Usefulness of fractional flow reserve to predict clinical outcome after balloon angioplasty. Circulation. 1999 Feb 23;99(7):883-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10027810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 18, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ulsan University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof Eun-Seok Shin, MD. PhD.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Interventional Cardiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Angina Pectoris</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angina, Stable</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angina, Unstable</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

