<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03348774</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-5083</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03348774</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Scrutinizing the Heterogeneity of SLE: Defining Phenotypes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Scrutinizing the Heterogeneity of Systemic Lupus Erythematosus: Defining Phenotypes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      SLE disease course is characterized by unpredictable relapses and remissions in the majority
      of patients. However, in a small proportion (approximately 5%), SLE presents with a
      monophasic pattern, meaning that these patients have active disease before and immediately
      after diagnosis and after some time they achieve prolonged remission (for 12 years on
      average). Interestingly, about half of these patients do so and require no medications. On
      the other end of the clinical spectrum, approximately 50% of the patients demonstrate
      persistent disease activity and usually have the highest risk for developing co-morbidities
      and irreversible damage. A major goal of clinical research in SLE is to improve disease
      management based on disease course. By better characterizing SLE disease course we hope to
      better identify patients early in the disease course for targeted therapies to prevent and or
      reduce future SLE complications.

      The overall objective of our project is to define distinct phenotypes of SLE based on disease
      course, clinical features, pathogenic mechanisms, genetic factors and relevant biomarkers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific aims of this study are:

        1. To test the clinical impression of the disease courses by modeling the course of the
           disease in each of three sub-populations of patients where it is anticipated that one
           sub-population will experience relapsing and remitting disease activity, one will
           experience persistently active disease and another will exhibit a monophasic pattern.

        2. To develop predictive models for group membership to enhance the accuracy of prognosis.

        3. To test these models in the inception cohort of SLE patients within the Toronto Lupus
           Cohort.

      Study Design: Retrospective longitudinal observational cohort

      Patients will be categorised into three disease courses:

      I. Relapsing-remitting II. Persistently active III. Monophasic Relapsing/remitting is defined
      as periods of disease activity SLEDAI-2K of 4 or more, (but if only 4 cannot be from serology
      alone) less than 50% of the time alternating with periods of inactivity (SLEDAI-2K &lt;4) over
      the course of follow-up.

      Persistently active disease is defined as SLEDAI-2K of 4 or more, (but if only 4 cannot be
      from serology alone), in greater than 80% of the visits, or no 2 consecutive visits with
      SLEDAI-2K &lt; 4.

      Monophasic course is defined as disease activity SLEDAI-2K of 4 or more, (but if only 4
      cannot be from serology alone) for an initial period of less than 3 years followed by
      resolution and inactive disease (SLEDAI-2K of 0 excluding serology) for at least 5 years.

      Clinical and laboratory characteristics, therapies and outcomes for each subgroup will be
      described. Identification of all clinical and laboratory features of lupus contained in the
      CRF will be compared for each group, as well as the medications prescribed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 9, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Course Patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>All 49,000 visits within the Toronto Lupus Cohort will be probed for patterns of disease activity using SLEDAI-2K measurements on each assessment. A finite mixture model will be fitted to the data to accommodate for three sub-populations of patients. Disease course for each sub-populations will be defined in terms of multistate model where the states reflected meaningfully different degrees of disease activity as measured by the SLEDAI-2K scores.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">950</enrollment>
  <condition>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with SLE have been followed prospectively at the University of Toronto Lupus
        Clinic since 1970. All patients ≥4 or more of the 1997 ACR criteria for SLE, or have 3
        criteria and a typical lesion of SLE on renal or skin biopsy. Patients are evaluated at 2-6
        month intervals according to a standard protocol which includes a detailed clinical
        history, physical examination, and laboratory evaluation . It includes all information
        necessary to calculate disease activity and damage indices, as well as comorbidities.
        Disease activity is assessed by the SLE Disease Activity Index 2000 (SLEDAI-2K) , and
        accumulated damage by the SLICC/ACR damage index (SDI) .

        To date there are 1767 patients with 2 or more visits registered in the Lupus Clinic
        Database, with 43079 assessments recorded. Their characteristics are shown in Table 1.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients enrolled in the study for aims 1 and 2 must meet the following inclusion criteria:

          1. ≥4 American College of Rheumatology (ACR) criteria or 3 ACR criteria plus a typical
             histological lesion of SLE on renal or skin biopsy.

          2. Patients must have a minimum of 2 assessment visits.

        Patients enrolled in the study for aim 3 must meet the following criteria:

          1. Must be inception patients seen within one year of diagnosis of SLE

          2. ≥4 American College of Rheumatology (ACR) criteria or 3 ACR criteria plus a typical
             histological lesion of SLE on renal or skin biopsy.

          3. Patients must have a minimum of 6 assessment visits to ensure categorization into one
             of the disease courses derived in aims 1 and 2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have not had 2 assessment visits for aims 1 and 2

          2. Patients who have not had 6 assessments for aim 3.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Murray Urowitz</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network and University of Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Health Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 17, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 17, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Murray B Urowitz, MD FRCP(C)</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Priniple Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Disease Course</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lupus Erythematosus, Systemic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No IPD data will be shared with other researchers</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

