<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03342560</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017P000940</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03342560</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Beyond Confounders: Addressing Source of Measurement Variability and Error in Shear Wave Elastography</brief_title>
  <official_title>Beyond Confounders: Addressing Source of Measurement Variability and Error in Shear Wave Elastography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Toshiba America Medical Systems, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic liver disease is a major problem in the general population and there is an unmet need
      to diagnose(and screen) for liver disease with using noninvasive, cost-effective and
      sensitive techniques.The investigators hypothesize that variation using ultrasound
      elastography for the estimation of stage of liver fibrosis and steatosis in patients with
      diffuse liver disease exists due to different methods of measurements, and/or different
      systems. The proposed investigation is a cross-sectional study using ultrasound elastography
      and fat quantification modalities. The investigators are planning to enroll 30 subjects 18
      years old and older in whom diffuse liver disease is suspected, and who have undergone
      non-focal liver biopsy in the past 6 months or are scheduled to undergo biopsy within 3
      months of enrollment, as part of their routine clinical care. The investigators will use 4
      different ultrasound devices with their shear wave elastography and speed of sound functions.

      Specific aims;

        -  Compare shear wave elastography(SWE) measurements from different ultrasound systems;
           using histopathology as reference standards.

        -  Assess intra-operator and inter-operator reliability by measuring variability in
           elastography values by two operators on a single system.

        -  Determine the steatosis effect on liver disease, with using speed of sound(SoS) mode

        -  Determine the effect of deviations from guidelines(less number of measurements and
           measurements during active breath)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Liver disease and cirrhosis are important causes of morbidity and mortality in the United
      States and are a major public health problem with 40,000 deaths and more than 1.4 billion
      dollars spent on medical services. Hepatic fibrosis is the final common pathway for many
      different liver insults and is known to be a dynamic process, which is reversible if
      diagnosed early and treated. If untreated, fibrosis eventually progresses to cirrhosis, which
      is irreversible. The diagnosis of fibrosis relies on liver biopsy (the gold standard)
      however, is an invasive procedure with risks and sampling errors. Indirect biomarkers of
      fibrogenesis can measure some of these components to determine categories of fibrosis, with a
      sensitivity and specificity of 47% and 90% respectively.It is shown in the literature that,
      fat content of liver is related with fibrosis development. Biopsy is accepted as the most
      accurate technique to assess liver fat and fibrosis amount.

      Fibrotic livers demonstrate increased stiffness, a property that can be measured using
      technology named Ultrasound Elastography or sonoelastography (SWE). SWE is performed by
      insonating the patient with a low energy, amplitude, and frequency shear wave created by a
      vibrating probe. The propagated wave travels faster with increasing fibrosis: the stiffer the
      tissue, the faster the shear wave propagates. A pulse-echo ultrasound acquisition allows
      measurement of the wave velocity and the results are presented as kilopascals (kPa). Prior
      reports have described sensitivity and specificity for liver fibrosis detection of 80% and
      97% respectively for SWE. The benefits of SWE are that it is inexpensive, reproducible,
      painless, rapid (&lt; 10 min), easy to perform, and can be used for diagnosis, prognosis and
      monitoring disease progression. Speed of sound measurement on liver, is demonstrated in
      previous studies as a quantitative parameter to assess the lipid profile. However,
      significant variations exist as a result of variation of systems, and scanning protocols.

      The objective of this study is to compare this variation and study the factors that might
      cause these variations.

      The proposed investigation is a cross-sectional study using ultrasound elastography and fat
      quantification modalities. The investigators are planning to enroll 30 subjects 18 years old
      and older in whom diffuse liver disease is suspected, and who have undergone non-focal liver
      biopsy in the past 6 months or are scheduled to undergo biopsy within 3 months of enrollment,
      as part of their routine clinical care.

      All subjects will be required to come to the MGH main campus for 2 study visits within 60
      days of each other. In addition, subjects will need to fast for at least 4 hours prior to
      study visits

      There will be two visits in this study and maximum 60 days time frame between the visits is
      anticipated. Two operators will perform the ultrasound examination. Reproducibility and
      repeatability of the ultrasound devices will be estimated.

      Ultrasound examination including sonoelastography will be performed using four FDA-approved
      ultrasound units; (1) Toshiba Aplio500, (2) Siemens S3000, (3) GE LOGIQ E9, (4) Fibroscan.
      Both operators will perform;

        1. Toshiba APLIO500

           • Median Elastograpy (10 measurements) on regular and variable map at a depth(in the
           sweet spot- 2cm from capsule and 6.5cm from skin)

        2. Siemens S3000

           • Median SWE value (10 measurements) at a depth(in the sweet spot- 2cm from capsule and
           6.5cm from skin)

        3. GE LOCIQ E9

             -  Median SWE value (10 measurements) at a depth(in the sweet spot- 2cm from capsule
                and 6.5cm from skin) Median SWE value with active breath(10measurements) Median SWE
                value with less number of acquisitions(3measurements)

             -  20 B-mode image acquisitions using variable speed of sound inputs (1400m/sec to
                1600m/sec at increments of 10 m/sec) will be obtained.

        4. Fibroscan • 10 measurements will be made using the Fibroscans device.

      In second visit, all measurements will be repeated with the same operators.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 29, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 10, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 10, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Shear wave elastography values in kPa</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(day0)</time_frame>
    <description>Shear wave elastography provides stiffness values of the tissues in units kPa. The basic physics of this technique, monitors the diverted shear waves in the tissue. In this study median values of 10 shear wave acquisitions will be recorded. Acquired results will be compared with biopsy proven fibrosis stage.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Shear wave elastography values in m/s</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(day0)</time_frame>
    <description>Shear wave elastography provides stiffness values of the tissues in units m/s. The basic physics of this technique, monitors the diverted shear waves in the tissue. In this study median values of 10 shear wave acquisitions will be recorded. Acquired results will be compared with biopsy proven fibrosis stage.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sonographic grey scale images in speed of sound function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline(day0)</time_frame>
    <description>An increasing pattern of speed of sound(from 1400m/s to 1600m/s), changes grey scale distribution of the image in liver with steatosis. Grey scale distribution analysis will be made</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Fibroses</condition>
  <condition>Liver Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Liver Steatoses</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>30 Patients with known liver biopsy results</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with chronic liver disease with known biopsy results</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sonographic SWE measurements with Toshiba APLIO500</intervention_name>
    <description>Sonographic Shear wave elastography will be performed to quantify liver fibrosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>30 Patients with known liver biopsy results</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sonographic SWE measurements with Siemens ACUSON S3000</intervention_name>
    <description>Sonographic Shear wave elastography will be performed to quantify liver fibrosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>30 Patients with known liver biopsy results</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sonographic SWE measurements with GE LOGIQ E9</intervention_name>
    <description>Sonographic Shear wave elastography will be performed to quantify liver fibrosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>30 Patients with known liver biopsy results</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SWE measurements with FibroScan</intervention_name>
    <description>Transient elastography will be performed to quantify liver fibrosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>30 Patients with known liver biopsy results</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sonographic speed of sound measurements with GE LOGIQ E9</intervention_name>
    <description>Sonographic speed of sound function of the machine will be used to quantify liver steatosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>30 Patients with known liver biopsy results</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult Patients

          -  Men or Woman

          -  Suspected diffuse liver disease and have had a liver biopsy within the last 6 months
             or are scheduled for a liver biopsy in the next 3 months.

          -  Consent to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Acute illness/ cognitive impairment resulting in inability to cooperate with
             ultrasound

          -  Patients that do not consent to ultrasound examination
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony E. Samir, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Associate Medical Director, Ultrasound Imaging Services</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anthony E. Samir, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>617 643 2009</phone>
    <email>asamir@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anthony E. Samir, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>617-643-2009</phone>
      <email>asamir@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anthony E. Samir, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manish Dhyani, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raymond T. Chung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Atul K. Bhan, MD, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Younossi ZM, Stepanova M, Afendy M, Fang Y, Younossi Y, Mir H, Srishord M. Changes in the prevalence of the most common causes of chronic liver diseases in the United States from 1988 to 2008. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2011 Jun;9(6):524-530.e1; quiz e60. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2011.03.020. Epub 2011 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21440669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mokdad AA, Lopez AD, Shahraz S, Lozano R, Mokdad AH, Stanaway J, Murray CJ, Naghavi M. Liver cirrhosis mortality in 187 countries between 1980 and 2010: a systematic analysis. BMC Med. 2014 Sep 18;12:145. doi: 10.1186/s12916-014-0145-y.</citation>
    <PMID>25242656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinzani M, Rombouts K. Liver fibrosis: from the bench to clinical targets. Dig Liver Dis. 2004 Apr;36(4):231-42. Review. Erratum in: Dig Liver Dis. 2004 Aug;36(8):562-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15115333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schölmerich J, Holstege A. Aetiology and pathophysiology of chronic liver disorders. Drugs. 1990;40 Suppl 3:3-22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2081479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pellicoro A, Ramachandran P, Iredale JP, Fallowfield JA. Liver fibrosis and repair: immune regulation of wound healing in a solid organ. Nat Rev Immunol. 2014 Mar;14(3):181-94. doi: 10.1038/nri3623. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24566915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Actis GC, Olivero A, Lagget M, Pellicano R, Smedile A, Rizzetto M. The practice of percutaneous liver biopsy in a gastrohepatology day hospital: a retrospective study on 835 biopsies. Dig Dis Sci. 2007 Oct;52(10):2576-9. Epub 2007 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>17436094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cadranel JF, Rufat P, Degos F. Practices of liver biopsy in France: results of a prospective nationwide survey. For the Group of Epidemiology of the French Association for the Study of the Liver (AFEF). Hepatology. 2000 Sep;32(3):477-81.</citation>
    <PMID>10960438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van der Poorten D, Kwok A, Lam T, Ridley L, Jones DB, Ngu MC, Lee AU. Twenty-year audit of percutaneous liver biopsy in a major Australian teaching hospital. Intern Med J. 2006 Nov;36(11):692-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17040353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sparchez Z. Complications after percutaneous liver biopsy in diffuse hepatopathies. Rom J Gastroenterol. 2005 Dec;14(4):379-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16400355</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bravo AA, Sheth SG, Chopra S. Liver biopsy. N Engl J Med. 2001 Feb 15;344(7):495-500. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11172192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rousselet MC, Michalak S, Dupré F, Croué A, Bedossa P, Saint-André JP, Calès P; Hepatitis Network 49. Sources of variability in histological scoring of chronic viral hepatitis. Hepatology. 2005 Feb;41(2):257-64.</citation>
    <PMID>15660389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Regev A, Berho M, Jeffers LJ, Milikowski C, Molina EG, Pyrsopoulos NT, Feng ZZ, Reddy KR, Schiff ER. Sampling error and intraobserver variation in liver biopsy in patients with chronic HCV infection. Am J Gastroenterol. 2002 Oct;97(10):2614-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12385448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bedossa P, Dargère D, Paradis V. Sampling variability of liver fibrosis in chronic hepatitis C. Hepatology. 2003 Dec;38(6):1449-57.</citation>
    <PMID>14647056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedrich-Rust M, Buggisch P, de Knegt RJ, Dries V, Shi Y, Matschenz K, Schneider MD, Herrmann E, Petersen J, Schulze F, Zeuzem S, Sarrazin C. Acoustic radiation force impulse imaging for non-invasive assessment of liver fibrosis in chronic hepatitis B. J Viral Hepat. 2013 Apr;20(4):240-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2893.2012.01646.x. Epub 2012 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>23490368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fierbinteanu-Braticevici C, Andronescu D, Usvat R, Cretoiu D, Baicus C, Marinoschi G. Acoustic radiation force imaging sonoelastography for noninvasive staging of liver fibrosis. World J Gastroenterol. 2009 Nov 28;15(44):5525-32.</citation>
    <PMID>19938190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferraioli G, Tinelli C, Dal Bello B, Zicchetti M, Filice G, Filice C; Liver Fibrosis Study Group. Accuracy of real-time shear wave elastography for assessing liver fibrosis in chronic hepatitis C: a pilot study. Hepatology. 2012 Dec;56(6):2125-33. doi: 10.1002/hep.25936. Epub 2012 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22767302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poynard T, Munteanu M, Luckina E, Perazzo H, Ngo Y, Royer L, Fedchuk L, Sattonnet F, Pais R, Lebray P, Rudler M, Thabut D, Ratziu V. Liver fibrosis evaluation using real-time shear wave elastography: applicability and diagnostic performance using methods without a gold standard. J Hepatol. 2013 May;58(5):928-35. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2012.12.021. Epub 2013 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23321316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen S, Sanchez W, Callstrom MR, Gorman B, Lewis JT, Sanderson SO, Greenleaf JF, Xie H, Shi Y, Pashley M, Shamdasani V, Lachman M, Metz S. Assessment of liver viscoelasticity by using shear waves induced by ultrasound radiation force. Radiology. 2013 Mar;266(3):964-70. doi: 10.1148/radiol.12120837. Epub 2012 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23220900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goertz RS, Zopf Y, Jugl V, Heide R, Janson C, Strobel D, Bernatik T, Haendl T. Measurement of liver elasticity with acoustic radiation force impulse (ARFI) technology: an alternative noninvasive method for staging liver fibrosis in viral hepatitis. Ultraschall Med. 2010 Apr;31(2):151-5. doi: 10.1055/s-0029-1245244. Epub 2010 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>20306380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takahashi H, Ono N, Eguchi Y, Eguchi T, Kitajima Y, Kawaguchi Y, Nakashita S, Ozaki I, Mizuta T, Toda S, Kudo S, Miyoshi A, Miyazaki K, Fujimoto K. Evaluation of acoustic radiation force impulse elastography for fibrosis staging of chronic liver disease: a pilot study. Liver Int. 2010 Apr;30(4):538-45. doi: 10.1111/j.1478-3231.2009.02130.x. Epub 2009 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19874490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedrich-Rust M, Wunder K, Kriener S, Sotoudeh F, Richter S, Bojunga J, Herrmann E, Poynard T, Dietrich CF, Vermehren J, Zeuzem S, Sarrazin C. Liver fibrosis in viral hepatitis: noninvasive assessment with acoustic radiation force impulse imaging versus transient elastography. Radiology. 2009 Aug;252(2):595-604. doi: 10.1148/radiol.2523081928.</citation>
    <PMID>19703889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang QB, Zhu H, Liu HL, Zhang B. Performance of magnetic resonance elastography and diffusion-weighted imaging for the staging of hepatic fibrosis: A meta-analysis. Hepatology. 2012 Jul;56(1):239-47. doi: 10.1002/hep.25610. Epub 2012 Jun 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22278368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sterling RK, Lissen E, Clumeck N, Sola R, Correa MC, Montaner J, S Sulkowski M, Torriani FJ, Dieterich DT, Thomas DL, Messinger D, Nelson M; APRICOT Clinical Investigators. Development of a simple noninvasive index to predict significant fibrosis in patients with HIV/HCV coinfection. Hepatology. 2006 Jun;43(6):1317-25.</citation>
    <PMID>16729309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calès P, Oberti F, Michalak S, Hubert-Fouchard I, Rousselet MC, Konaté A, Gallois Y, Ternisien C, Chevailler A, Lunel F. A novel panel of blood markers to assess the degree of liver fibrosis. Hepatology. 2005 Dec;42(6):1373-81.</citation>
    <PMID>16317693</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adams LA, Bulsara M, Rossi E, DeBoer B, Speers D, George J, Kench J, Farrell G, McCaughan GW, Jeffrey GP. Hepascore: an accurate validated predictor of liver fibrosis in chronic hepatitis C infection. Clin Chem. 2005 Oct;51(10):1867-73. Epub 2005 Jul 28.</citation>
    <PMID>16055434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Forns X, Ampurdanès S, Llovet JM, Aponte J, Quintó L, Martínez-Bauer E, Bruguera M, Sánchez-Tapias JM, Rodés J. Identification of chronic hepatitis C patients without hepatic fibrosis by a simple predictive model. Hepatology. 2002 Oct;36(4 Pt 1):986-92.</citation>
    <PMID>12297848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crespo G, Fernández-Varo G, Mariño Z, Casals G, Miquel R, Martínez SM, Gilabert R, Forns X, Jiménez W, Navasa M. ARFI, FibroScan, ELF, and their combinations in the assessment of liver fibrosis: a prospective study. J Hepatol. 2012 Aug;57(2):281-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2012.03.016. Epub 2012 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22521355</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenberg WM, Voelker M, Thiel R, Becka M, Burt A, Schuppan D, Hubscher S, Roskams T, Pinzani M, Arthur MJ; European Liver Fibrosis Group. Serum markers detect the presence of liver fibrosis: a cohort study. Gastroenterology. 2004 Dec;127(6):1704-13.</citation>
    <PMID>15578508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wai CT, Greenson JK, Fontana RJ, Kalbfleisch JD, Marrero JA, Conjeevaram HS, Lok AS. A simple noninvasive index can predict both significant fibrosis and cirrhosis in patients with chronic hepatitis C. Hepatology. 2003 Aug;38(2):518-26.</citation>
    <PMID>12883497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Imbert-Bismut F, Ratziu V, Pieroni L, Charlotte F, Benhamou Y, Poynard T; MULTIVIRC Group. Biochemical markers of liver fibrosis in patients with hepatitis C virus infection: a prospective study. Lancet. 2001 Apr 7;357(9262):1069-75.</citation>
    <PMID>11297957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anthony Samir</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Service Chief,Body Ultrasound Department of Radiology, Assistant Professor at Harvard Medical School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liver Fibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Ultrasound Elastography</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Steatosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Shear wave speed</keyword>
  <keyword>Stiffness</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Biopsy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Cirrhosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Extracts</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

