<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03348215</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SU_BME_KERR01102017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03348215</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enhanced Treadmill Gait Training With Lower Limb Support After Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENTRES</acronym>
  <official_title>The Design and Testing of a Targeted, Treadmill Based Training Program for Post-Stroke Gait Rehabilitation, Through Co-Production With Users; Incorporating Visual Flow, and Functional Electrical Stimulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Strathclyde</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Strathclyde</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This series of single case studies aims to test the feasibility and acceptability of an
      enhanced treadmill system for the recovery of gait function in stroke survivors. Forty adult
      participants who have had a stroke in the past year that resulted in impaired gait function
      and are attending a local hospital for gait training, will be recruited. Participants will be
      asked to attend a rehabilitation clinic for seven weeks, three times a week where they will
      receive enhanced treadmill training supervised by a physiotherapist. Assessment sessions will
      take place in week 1, weeks 5 and 8, and after 3 months. Outcome measures recorded during
      assessment sessions will include gait variables (e.g. speed, cadence, step length and joint
      kinematics) measured overground and on the treadmill using motion capture technology and
      outside using body worn sensors (inertial motion unit). Participants will complete a
      questionnaire on their community walking habits and asked to wear a physical activity monitor
      for 48 hours to record stepping time.

      The basic intervention will comprise of walking on a treadmill capable of adjusting its speed
      to match that of the user (using feedback from the motion capture system) and a large
      television screen showing a virtual reality scene (woodland walking) with visual
      perturbations (virtual obstacle avoidance). In addition participants will be divided equally
      and randomly (Latin square) to either wear an ankle foot orthosis (AFO group) or functional
      electrical stimulation (FES group) while walking on the treadmill but not provided for home
      use. Training sessions will last up to a max of 20 minutes, will be supervised by a
      physiotherapist and participants will wear a safety harness to remove any risk of trip falls.
      Any adverse event such as muscle/joint pain, illness or a fall at home will be recorded,
      participants and physiotherapists will also be asked for feedback on their experience with
      the treadmill system using questionnaires and semi-structured interviews
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design Series of single case studies investigating feasibility and acceptability of an
      enhanced treadmill training system incorporating self pacing, virtual reality and
      biomechanical support with either an ankle foot orthosis (AFO) or functional electrical
      stimulation (FES) which will be decided using a Latin square.

      Participants Individuals referred to rehabilitation services due to impaired walking function
      resulting from a stroke in the past 12 months and who are medically stable, will be invited
      to participate.

      Target sample size = 40. Eligible participants will be approached about participation by a
      clinical trials nurse who will allow at least 48 hours for consideration before giving
      consent. The percentage of eligible people invited to participate who then agree to
      participate will be noted as the recruitment rate.

      Outcome measures Following informed consent, participants will be asked to attend a
      physiotherapy gym at a local hospital for a total of eight consecutive weeks, three times a
      week with a follow assessment 3 months later.

      Outcome measures will be recorded at weeks 1, 5, 8 and 20. These will include:

        1. Physical activity recorded over 48 hours using an accelerometer based sensor worn on the
           thigh (ActivPal, PalTechnologies, Glasgow, UK).

        2. Spatiotemporal gait variables (walking speed, cadence, step length, stride length,
           stance duration) during treadmill, overground indoor and overground outdoor walking
           using a combination of motion capture technology (Vicon, Oxford Metrics, Oxford, UK) and
           inertial sensors (Trigno, Delsys, Mass, USA).

        3. Lower limb 3D joint angles during treadmill, overground indoor and overground outdoor
           walking using a combination of motion capture technology (Vicon, Oxford Metrics, Oxford,
           UK) and inertial sensors (Trigno, Delsys, Mass, USA).

        4. Acceptability of the intervention using bespoke satisfaction questionnaires and semi
           structured interviews with the therapists and participants.

        5. Adverse and serious adverse events such as falls, illness, joint/muscle soreness will be
           recorded as part of the routine research governance but also to assess acceptability and
           feasibility.

        6. Community walking ability using a standard questionnaire (Perry, J., et al. (1995).
           &quot;Classification of Walking Handicap in the Stroke Population,&quot; Stroke 26(6): 982-989.)
           and a semi structured interview.

      Intervention The core of the intervention will be walking on a self-pacing, single belt,
      treadmill (N-mill, Motekforce link, Amsterdam) in front of a large (65 inch) high definition
      screen (Dell, USA) which will show a virtual reality scene (woodland walk) synchronised with
      the belt speed to provide an immersive walking environment. The treadmill is surrounded by
      six motion capture cameras (VICON, Oxford Metrics, Oxford, UK) which capture the three
      dimensional movement of markers placed on the lower limbs and trunk of the individual. These
      data are used to control the belt speed and provide performance feedback to
      therapists/patients either in real time through visualisation on the screen or afterwards
      when the data are fully processed. Using a Latin square to remove selection bias participants
      will be further allocated to either receive an ankle foot orthosis (AFO group) or functional
      electrical stimulation (FES group), both of which will be used only during the treadmill.
      training. At the initial assessment visit participants will be examined for skin damage or
      impaired circulation in the lower leg and foot which would exclude them from using an AFO or
      FES.

      FES group A dual-channel surface electrical stimulator (NeuroTrac® Rehab, Model number:
      ECS305A) will be used to stimulate four major muscle groups; the ankle dorsiflexors and
      plantarflexors, and the knee flexors and extensors. The FES will be triggered using real time
      data from the motion capture system. The physiotherapist will decide which muscle groups
      should be used to support gait training and the timing and amplitude of the FES administered.
      Participants will be excluded from the FES group if they have any implants in the vicinity of
      the FES sites. These participants will be transferred to the AFO group if they are agreeable.
      Skin integrity will be check at each treatment visit before and after the intervention.
      Should signs of skin trauma present the intervention will discontinued and the participant
      provided with advice and referred to their general practitioner if considered appropriate by
      the physiotherapists.

      AFO group A standard AFO (polypropylene posterior leaf) will be fitted under the guidance of
      the physiotherapist and orthotist. A range of sizes (small, medium, large and extra ) will be
      available (Complete care shop, Lancashire, UK) which will be adjusted using heel raises so
      that the lower leg has an angle of 10-12 degrees to the vertical at the point of mid stance.
      The AFO will be worn during the treadmill walking only. If participants are already using an
      AFO they will continue to use this as before.

      Duration Duration will be determined by the supervising physiotherapist based on the
      participant's tolerance. The aim will be to increase incrementally to a maximum of 20 minutes
      of continuous walking.

      Frequency Frequency will be determined by the supervising physiotherapist based on tolerance
      of the participant and practical issues such as transport. The aim will be to attend three
      times a week.

      The treadmill training (AFO and FES groups) will replace any conventional gait training
      provided by the therapists, however, any unrelated training e.g. Upper limb exercises or
      speech therapy will continue as normal practice.

      Intensity Walking speed will be set at a comfortable pace. Initially this will be 80% of
      their overground indoor walking assessed at week one. Speed will be increased incrementally
      as appropriate and advised by the physiotherapist.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a singles subject design with participants acting as their own control. Control data being recorded during the week before the intervention begins</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>The primary gait measure (number of daily steps in teh community) will be collected by an independent assessor.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant compliance with the intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants attending 60% of training sessions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Community walking ability</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Walking Ability Questionnaire:
This questionnaire measures ability to walk in the community/home. (Perry et al (1995). Stroke, 26(6), pp.982-989.) This is a questionnaire based on self reported ability in 19 ambulatory activities , 8 in the home and 11 in the community. Each activity has an associated ordinal scale of ability ranging from &quot;unable&quot; to &quot;independent&quot;. The overall score ranges between 0 and 76 with higher scores equating to better community walking.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity behaviour</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time spent lying, sitting, standing and walking during a 48 hour period using an established physical activity monitor (ActivPal, PalTechnologies, Glasgow, Scotland)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait performance</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Speed, step length, cadence, lower limb angles. Measured by motion capture system (Vicon, Oxford, UK) indoors (overground and treadmill) and outdoors with body mounted sensors (Trigno, Delsys, Mass. USA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant satisfaction with the enhanced treadmill training.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction questionnaires using 5 point ordinal scales of satisfaction. 7 Items related to the intervention, such as the virtual reality projection, are rated on an ordinal scale. An overall score between 0 and 25 is calculated with a higher score indicating greater satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants satisfaction with the intervention and overall research experience</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Semi structured interviews:
Participant's opinions will be sought regarding the intervention and their overall experience in this research study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Treadmill Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treadmill walking with an immersive environment and bio mechanical support (body weight, ankle-foot -orthosis and functional electrical stimulation)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enhanced Treadmill Training</intervention_name>
    <description>6 week programme of treadmill training with addition of an immersive environment (virtual reality projection), body weight support, orthotics and functional electrical stimulation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Treadmill Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Over 18 years old.

          2. Have had a diagnosed stroke.

          3. Onset of stroke between 1 week and 12 months prior to recruitment.

          4. Attending Coathill Hospital (NHS Lanarkshire) for stroke rehabilitation which includes
             gait training.

          5. Have Hemiplegia.

          6. Medically Stable.

          7. Able to follow simple, verbal instructions in English, or in another language if an
             appropriate translator is available.

          8. Able to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Considered by the GP or NHS clinicians to be unsafe to do mild exercise for the
             duration of time required (about 20 minutes).

          2. Have contracture of the hip, knee or ankle which prevents walking.

          3. Have any skin irritation on the shank.

          4. Have a cardiac pacemaker.

          5. A body mass that exceeds the capacity of the equipment (&gt;100Kg).

          6. Cognitive impairment severe enough to prevent adherence with the protocol (assessed by
             the clinicians responsible for each volunteer).

          7. Walking difficulty before stroke (for example, patients who had history of severe
             spinal stenosis or peripheral vascular diseases)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Kerr, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Strathclyde</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew Kerr, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0141054802855</phone>
    <email>a.kerr@strath.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Philip Rowe, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>01415483032</phone>
    <email>philip.rowe@strath.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Coathill Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Coatbridge</city>
        <state>Lanarkshire</state>
        <zip>ML5 4DN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Barber Mark, MD</last_name>
      <email>mark.barber@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Strathclyde</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Andrew Kerr</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gait rehabilitation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

