<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03341897</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VARICOCELE TREATEMENT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03341897</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Varicocele Treatement by Endovasculer Embolization</brief_title>
  <official_title>Endovasculer Treatement of Male Pelvic Venous Insufficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A varicocele is a collection of varicose veins within the pampiniform (spermatic) plexus
      secondary to reflux in the internal spermatic vein (ISV).The condition affects 10% to 15% of
      the general population but is detected in as many as 40% of men undergoing an infertility
      workup. Depending on the method used for diagnosis, varicoceles are reported as bilateral in
      17% to 77% of men. Traditionally, the diagnosis was made through clinical examination;
      however,as with other venous reflux disorders, ultrasound has become the mainstay of
      diagnosis. The traditional indications for treatment include infertility in patients with
      appropriate semen abnormalities, chronic groin pain, testicular atrophy in adolescent
      varicoceles, and recurrent varicocele after previous repair. Other indications more recently
      described with variable strength of evidence include low serum testosterone (with or without
      erectile dysfunction), benign prostatic hypertrophy,enhancement of assisted fertility
      techniques, and recurrent first trimester pregnancy loss.Infertility affects 10% to 15% of
      men of reproductive age. In approximately 50%, a cause is not found. The proof that
      varicocele repair improves fertility remains elusive; however, there is general acceptance
      that treatment does improve abnormalities of semen production.The traditional measures to
      assess semen production are sperm motility,morphology, and total sperm count. However, sperm
      counts greatly vary from day to day in any individual patient, and these measures correlate
      poorly with infertility outcomes.

      The investigators do this study to evaluate the effectiveness of endovascular therapy using
      coils and other sclerosing agents and compare their results with other traditonal surgical
      methods in treatement of varicocele.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All included patients will undergo the following:

        -  History &amp; examination

        -  Semen analysis preintervention.

        -  Scrotal duplex scan of testicular vessels and testicular size .

      Technique:

        -  All interventions will be performed in the endovascular OR with set on C-ARM.

        -  Patient's position and comfort are issues that are important initially.

      STEPS FOR SPERMATIC VENOGRAPHY AND VARICOCELE EMBOLIZATION

      Step 1: Vascular Access

      Access can be achieved via the internal jugular or femo¬ral veins. Our preferred method is to
      puncture the right internal jugular vein under ultrasound guidance.

      Step 2: Left Renal Vein Injection

      During left renal vein injection, the origin of the left spermatic vein is noted .

      Step 3: Left Spermatic Vein Catheterization

      The catheter is manipulated into the left spermatic vein. A varicocele is present if the
      contrast refluxes into the pampiniform plexus. If the direction of flow is antegrade, this is
      considered to represent a negative spermatic venogram.

      Step 4: Spermatic Vein Occlusion

      If varicocele is confirmed, the spermatic vein is occluded, preferably immediately above the
      internal inguinal ring and along its full length to within 2 to 3 cm of its origin. The use
      of liquid embolics with or without metallic coils has become the most common method.
      Embolization with coils alone without liquid should be avoided, even for &quot;straightforward&quot;
      cases due to a high rate of recurrence. It is important to look for collaterals throughout
      the procedure, which may only become visible after distal occlusion . These collaterals are
      the usual cause of technical failure or recurrence and therefore must be occluded. Options
      for occlusion methods are described as follows.

      Some practitioners place coils in the distal ISV before injecting glue. Coils in the proximal
      ISV are not necessary. Avoiding injection of glue into the scrotum is essential, either by
      previously placed distal coils or external compression. Overinjection of glue will result in
      extension into the renal vein or embolization into the pulmonary artery.

      Step 5: Right Spermatic Venography

      The same steps performed for the left spermatic vein are repeated for the right spermatic
      vein, except that the right spermatic vein usually arises directly from the infe¬rior vena
      cava. If reflux is demonstrated, embolization is performed in the same manner as on the left.
      The right spermatic vein arises from the inferior vena cava at an acute angle, which can make
      catheterization from the femoral route especially difficult.

      POSTPROCEDURE CARE

      The patient is kept in bed for 1 hour postprocedure. The patient is advised to take
      anti-inflammatory agents as needed and to avoid any activity involving the Valsalva maneuver,
      such as lifting, vigorous, or &quot;hitting type&quot; sports for 3 full days beginning the day after
      the proce¬dure. Most patients report a minor dull ache in the back or groin lasting &lt; 2 to 5
      days. Fewer than 5% of patients will develop more severe pain lasting up to 14 days,
      requiring oral analgesics and anti-inflammatory agents and avoidance of vigorous exercise
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>semen analyis criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month</time_frame>
    <description>sperm number in milion/ml</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>semen analysis criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month</time_frame>
    <description>sperm motility</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Varicocele</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical varicocelectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>endovasculer embolization of varicocele</intervention_name>
    <description>Step 1: Vascular Access
Access can be achieved via the internal jugular or femoral veins. Step 2: Left Renal Vein Injection Step 3: Left Spermatic Vein Catheterization Step 4: Spermatic Vein Occlusion Step 5: Right Spermatic Venography POSTPROCEDURE CARE
The patient is kept in bed for 1 hour postprocedure. The patient is advised to take anti-inflammatory agents as needed and to avoid any activity involving the Valsalva maneuver, such as lifting, vigorous, or &quot;hitting type&quot; sports for 3 full days beginning the day after the proce¬dure. Most patients report a minor dull ache in the back or groin lasting &lt; 2 to 5 days. Fewer than 5% of patients will develop more severe pain lasting up to 14 days, requiring oral analgesics and anti-inflammatory agents and avoidance of vigorous exercise.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical varicocelectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age between 18 to 40 years.

          2. Grade three reflux by duplex ultrasound..

          3. Recurrent varicocele after surgical treatement.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any contraindication for endovascular therapy regarding radiation or dye or sclerosing
             agents.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ahmed Qwashty</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>embolization</keyword>
  <keyword>coiling</keyword>
  <keyword>varicocele</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varicocele</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Inflammatory Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

