<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03341754</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S-14-07</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NMRC.2016.0006</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NavOx</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03341754</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial to Evaluate the Safety, Immunogenicity, and Efficacy of Malaria Infection in Malaria Na誰ve Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Trial With Controlled Human Malaria Infection to Evaluate the Safety, Immunogenicity, and Protective Efficacy of Two-Antigen and Three-Antigen Plasmodium Falciparum DNA Prime-Adenovirus Boost Malaria Vaccine Regimens in Healthy Malaria Na誰ve Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>U.S. Army Medical Research and Materiel Command</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Walter Reed Army Institute of Research (WRAIR)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Agency for International Development (USAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Naval Medical Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>U.S. Army Medical Research and Materiel Command</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study designed to assess the safety, tolerability, immunogenicity, and protective
      efficacy of 2 heterologous prime-boost vaccine regimens in healthy, malaria na誰ve adults. The
      study will include 2 vaccine groups and an infectivity control (IC) group consisting of
      non-immunized subjects. Subjects to be immunized will be randomly assigned to one of two
      vaccine groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a study designed to assess the safety, tolerability, immunogenicity, and protective
      efficacy of 2 heterologous prime-boost vaccine regimens in healthy, malaria na誰ve adults. The
      study will include 2 vaccine groups and an infectivity control (IC) group consisting of
      non-immunized subjects. Subjects to be immunized will be randomly assigned to one of two
      vaccine groups. Approximately 4 weeks after administration of the boosting immunization the
      vaccinated groups and the IC group will participate in CHMI wherein subjects will be exposed
      to the bites of 5 Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes carrying infectious Pf sporozoites within a
      controlled clinical environment. Protection will be determined by the examination of thick
      blood smears through 28 days post-CHMI and by retrospective PCR analysis for the presence of
      blood stage parasites. All groups will be enrolled and evaluated in one cohort. Due to a
      limit in the number of subjects who can undergo malaria challenge at the facility in one day,
      CHMI will be conducted over two days.

      Group 1 (2-antigen): 3 doses at 4 week intervals (Week 0, 4, and 8) of DNA prime with D-C +
      D-A at 2 mg total (1 mg per construct) per dose as two 1 mL IM injections of the blended
      D-CA, one in each arm, via Biojector 2000 needle-free injection device or an equivalent
      disposable syringe needle-free injection device. This will be followed after 16 weeks (Week
      24) by 1 dose of ChAd63-C + ChAd63-A boost, at a total dose of 1 x 1011 virus particles (vp)
      (5 x 1010 vp/construct) as a single IM injection of 0.65mL, using a needle and syringe.

      Group 2 (3-antigen): 3 doses at 4 week intervals (Week 0, 4, and 8) of DNA prime with D-C +
      D-A + D-T at 3 mg total (1 mg per construct) per dose as two 1 mL intramuscular (IM)
      injections of the blended D-CAT, one in each arm, via Biojector 2000 needle-free injection
      device or an equivalent disposable syringe needle-freeinjection device. This will be followed
      after 16 weeks (Week 24) by 1 dose of ChAd63-C + ChAd63-A + ChAd63-T boost, at a total dose
      of 1.5 x 1011 vp (5 x 1010 vp/construct) as a single IM injection of 1.0mL, using a needle
      and syringe.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study will include 2 vaccine groups and an infectivity control (IC) group consisting of non-immunized subjects.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Trial subjects will be blinded from their treatment</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of Serious Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Through day 7 after each immunization</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of Serious Adverse Events following immunization through day 7 after each immunization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of Abnormal Physical Symptoms (Clinical Abnormalities)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through day 28 after each immunization</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of Abnormal Physical Findings following immunization through day 28 after each immunization.
Grading Scale:
Grade 1= No interference with activity; Grade 2= Some interference with activity; Grade 3=Prevents daily activity; Grade 4= ER visit or hospitalization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of Abnormal Laboratory Values</measure>
    <time_frame>Through day 28 after each immunization</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of Abnormal Laboratory Values following immunization through day 28 after each immunization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of Any Serious Adverse Events Throughout the Study Period</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment through 3 months after CHMI</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of Any Serious Adverse Events Throughout the Study Period, from enrollment through 3 months after CHMI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaccine Efficacy Determined by Time to Development of Parasitemia</measure>
    <time_frame>after CHMI: Days 7 - 28</time_frame>
    <description>Vaccine Efficacy Determined by Time to Development of Parasitemia as measured by microscopic examination of thick smears and by Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) after CHMI and PCR analysis conducted retrospectively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of Antibody Titers Against Sporozoite and Erythrocyte Stage Parasites</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 231 and 286</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of antibody titers against sporozoite and erythrocyte stage parasites by immunofluorescence assay (IFA) using sera/plasma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of correlation between pre-immunization HuAd5 neutralizing antibody titers and the protective efficacy against CHMI and humoral and cellular immune responses of the 2 prime-boost regimens</measure>
    <time_frame>HuAd5: Days -14 to -1; Cellular Immunity: Days -14 to -1, 84, 168 and 195; Humoral Immunity: Days -14 to -1, 14, 28, 42, 56, 70, 84, 168, 195</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the association between the subjects' pre-immunization neutralizing antibody titers to HuAd5 and the protective efficacy and humoral and cellular immunogenicity, of these prime-boost regimens to CSP, AMA1 and TRAP as measured by ELISA and FluoroSpot assays</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Immunogenicity of the 2 Vaccine Regimens</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 - 286</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of immunogenicity,of the 2 heterologous prime-boost vaccine regimens (D/ChAd63-CA vs. D/ChAd63-CAT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 (D/ChAd63-CA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>(2-antigen): 3 doses at 4 week intervals (Week 0, 4, and 8) of DNA prime with D-C + D-A at 2 mg total (1 mg per construct) per dose as two 1 mL IM injections of the blended D-CA, one in each arm, via Biojector 2000 needle-free injection device or an equivalent disposable syringe needle-free injection device. This will be followed after 16 weeks (Week 24) by 1 dose of ChAd63-C + ChAd63-A boost, at a total dose of 1 x 1011 virus particles (vp) (5 x 1010 vp/construct) as a single IM injection of 0.65mL, using a needle and syringe.
Week 0 = Prime with D-CA Week 4 = Prime with D-CA Week 8 = Prime with D-CA Week 24 = Boost with ChAd63-CA Week 28 = Controlled Human Malaria Infection (CHMI)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 (D/ChAd63-CAT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>(3-antigen): 3 doses at 4 week intervals (Week 0, 4, and 8) of DNA prime with D-C + D-A + D-T at 3 mg total (1 mg per construct) per dose as two 1 mL intramuscular (IM) injections of the blended D-CAT, one in each arm, via Biojector 2000 needle-free injection device or an equivalent disposable syringe needle-free injection device. This will be followed after 16 weeks (Week 24) by 1 dose of ChAd63-C + ChAd63-A + ChAd63-T boost, at a total dose of 1.5 x 1011 vp (5 x 1010 vp/construct) as a single IM injection of 1.0mL, using a needle and syringe.
Week 0 = Prime with D-CAT Week 4 = Prime with D-CAT Week 8 = Prime with D-CAT Week 24 = Boost with ChAd63-CAT Week 28 = Controlled Human Malaria Infection (CHMI)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Infectivity Control (IC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be exposed to the bites of 5 Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes carrying infectious Pf sporozoites within a controlled clinical environment.
Week 28 = Controlled Human Malaria Infection (CHMI)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>D/ChAd63-CA</intervention_name>
    <description>Priming Component (DNA) = NMRC-M3V-D-PfCA (D-CA) Vaccine Boosting Component = ChAd63-PfCA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 (D/ChAd63-CA)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>D/ChAd63-CAT</intervention_name>
    <description>Priming Component (DNA) = NMRC-M3V-D-PfCAT (D-CAT) Boosting Component = ChAd63-PfCAT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 (D/ChAd63-CAT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Infectivity Control (IC) Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be exposed to bites of 5 Anopheles stephensi mosquitoes carrying infectious Pf sporozoites within a controlled clinical environment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Infectivity Control (IC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Controlled Human Malaria Infection (CHMI)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults (male or non-lactating, non-pregnant female) between 18 to 50 years of age at
             the time of enrollment

          -  Available and willing to participate for duration of study

          -  Able and willing to provide a written informed consent

          -  Able to complete an Assessment of Understanding (Appendix C) with a score of at least
             80% correct

          -  In good general health with no clinically significant health problems as established
             by medical history, physical examination, and laboratory screening

          -  Men and women of childbearing potential must agree to consistently use effective means
             of birth control throughout the duration of the study

               -  Sexually active females, unless surgically sterile or at least 1 year
                  postmenopausal, must use an effective method of avoiding pregnancy (including
                  oral or implanted contraceptives, intrauterine device, female condom, diaphragm
                  with spermicide, cervical cap, abstinence, use of a condom by the sexual partner
                  or sterile sexual partner) from 14 days prior to the first immunization and must
                  agree to continue using such precautions during the study and for 6 months after
                  the last study visit (which occurs at 90 days after CHMI).

               -  If female subjects are unable to bear children due to menopause or have had a
                  procedure performed (tubal ligation or hysterectomy), a medical note from a
                  physician is required.

               -  If post-menopausal, subjects must have experienced at least 1 year of amenorrhea
                  and provide a medical note from her physician documenting this medical history.

               -  Sexually active men must agree to use effective means of birth control such as
                  barrier methods (use of a condom) from the day of the first immunization and for
                  the duration of the study (through 3 months after CHMI). Vasectomy is considered
                  an adequate means of birth control. Men who underwent sterilization or vasectomy
                  must provide a medical note from his physician documenting such procedure.

          -  Agree not to travel to a malaria endemic area during the course of the study

          -  Agree to refrain from blood donation during the study and for 3 years following CHMI

          -  Must be willing to take anti-malarial treatment after CHMI, if indicated.

          -  Must agree to stay in a pre-determined hotel near the NMRC CTC during the designated
             post-CHMI followup period from approximately 7 days after malaria challenge until
             antimalarial treatment is completed, if indicated

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Weight &lt; 110 pounds

          -  Body mass index (BMI) &gt; 35 kg/m2

          -  Pregnant (positive urine pregnancy test) or nursing at screening or plans to become
             pregnant or nurse at any period from the time of enrollment through 6 months after the
             last study visit (which will occur at 90 days after CHMI).

          -  Receipt of any investigational malaria vaccine

          -  Any history of malaria infection

          -  Travel to a malaria endemic region within 6 months of enrollment or during the study
             (from enrollment through 3 months after CHMI)

          -  History of long-term residence (&gt;5 years) in an area known to have significant
             transmission of P falciparum (http://www.cdc.gov/malaria/map/)

          -  History of clinically significant contact dermatitis or sensitivity to products that
             contain Kathon, such as shampoos, conditioners, soaps, detergents, moisturizers,
             lotions, baby wipes, or cosmetics

          -  Positive CSP and AMA1 ELISpot assay at screening

          -  Positive CSP and AMA1 ELISA assay at screening

          -  Seropositive for the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), and/
             or hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg)

          -  Positive sickle cell screening test, including evidence of sickle cell trait or sickle
             cell anemia (due to its effect on subject's susceptibility to malaria)

          -  History of thalassemia or thalassemia trait (due to its effect on subject's
             susceptibility to malaria)

          -  Participation in any clinical study involving another investigational vaccine, drug,
             or other products within 60 days prior to the first immunization or plan to
             participate in such a clinical study during or within 1 month following the active
             study phase of the study (from the day of the first immunization through 3 months
             after CHMI)

          -  Allergy to any component of the vaccine formulation or serious adverse reaction to
             other vaccines (such as hives, anaphylaxis, respiratory difficulty, angioedema, or
             abdominal pain)

          -  History of a severe and/or anaphylactic response to mosquito-bites

          -  Known allergy to chloroquine phosphate, atovaquone/proguanil, or
             artemether/lumefantrine, which will be used to treat subjects who may develop malaria
             after Plasmodium falciparum challenge

          -  History of psoriasis (given its interaction with chloroquine)

          -  History of porphyria

          -  History of hemolytic anemia

          -  Use or planned use of any drugs with significant anti-malarial activity, such as
             doxycycline, clindamycin, azithromycin, or trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole among others
             that would coincide with periods of CHMI or post-CHMI followup

          -  Has evidence of increased cardiovascular disease risk (&gt; 5%-10%, 5-year risk)

               -  As determined by the method of Gaziano et al (2008, Appendix D)

               -  Risk factors include sex, age (years), smoking status, body mass index (BMI,
                  kg/m2), presence or absence of diabetes mellitus, and blood pressure.

          -  An abnormal EKG, defined as one showing Q waves and/or significant ST-T wave changes,
             left ventricular hypertrophy, any non-sinus rhythm (excluding isolated premature
             atrial contraction), right or left bundle branch block, or advanced (secondary or
             tertiary) A-V heart block

          -  Current or chronic use of systemic immunosuppressant pharmacotherapy or
             immunomodulators; however, subjects may be allowed to use inhaled steroids or topical
             steroids.

          -  History of splenectomy (given its effects on immunity to malaria)

          -  Receipt of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within 90 days of scheduled
             immunization

          -  History of neurologic disorder (including seizures or migraine headache)

          -  History of cancer (except for basal cell carcinoma of the skin)

          -  Current significant medical condition (cardiovascular, pulmonary, hepatic, renal, or
             hematological) or evidence of any other serious underlying medical condition
             identified by medical history, physical examination, or laboratory screening tests

          -  History of any other illness or condition which, in the investigator's judgment, may
             substantially increase the risk associated with the subject's participation in the
             protocol or compromise the scientific objectives. This may include psychiatric
             disorders (such as personality disorders, anxiety disorders, major depressive disorder
             or schizophrenia) or behavioral tendencies (including active alcohol or drug abuse)
             discovered during the screening process that in the opinion of the investigator would
             make compliance with the protocol difficult

          -  Plan for surgery during the study (from enrollment until 3 months post-CHMI) with the
             exception of minor cutaneous procedures

          -  Females who are pregnant or nursing, or plan to become pregnant or nurse during the
             study period (from enrollment through 3 months post CHMI) or within 6 months after the
             last study visit

          -  Any other significant finding that in the opinion of the investigator would increase
             the risk of having an adverse outcome from participating in this study or compromise
             the scientific objectives
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nimfa Teneza-Mora, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>United States Military Malaria Vaccine Program, NMRC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nimfa Teneza-Mora, MD</last_name>
    <phone>301-295-0021</phone>
    <email>nimfa.c.tenezamora.mil@mail.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sai Majji</last_name>
    <phone>301-619-7079</phone>
    <email>sai.p.majji.ctr@mail.mil</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NMRC Clinical Trials Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20889</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Judith Epstein, MD</last_name>
      <phone>301-252-9026</phone>
      <email>judith.e.epstein.mil@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>WRAIR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Silver Spring</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20910</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Judith Epstein, MD</last_name>
      <phone>301-252-9026</phone>
      <email>judith.e.epstein.mil@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/malaria/publications/world-malaria-report-2015/report/en/</url>
    <description>World Health Organization: World Malaria Report 2015 (cited 03Jan2016)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beadle C, Hoffman SL. History of malaria in the United States Naval Forces at war: World War I through the Vietnam conflict. Clin Infect Dis. 1993 Feb;16(2):320-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8443317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breman JG, Alilio MS, Mills A. Conquering the intolerable burden of malaria: what's new, what's needed: a summary. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2004 Aug;71(2 Suppl):1-15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15331814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buchbinder SP, Mehrotra DV, Duerr A, Fitzgerald DW, Mogg R, Li D, Gilbert PB, Lama JR, Marmor M, Del Rio C, McElrath MJ, Casimiro DR, Gottesdiener KM, Chodakewitz JA, Corey L, Robertson MN; Step Study Protocol Team. Efficacy assessment of a cell-mediated immunity HIV-1 vaccine (the Step Study): a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled, test-of-concept trial. Lancet. 2008 Nov 29;372(9653):1881-1893. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61591-3. Epub 2008 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>19012954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein JE, Rao S, Williams F, Freilich D, Luke T, Sedegah M, de la Vega P, Sacci J, Richie TL, Hoffman SL. Safety and clinical outcome of experimental challenge of human volunteers with Plasmodium falciparum-infected mosquitoes: an update. J Infect Dis. 2007 Jul 1;196(1):145-54. Epub 2007 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>17538895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ogwang C, Afolabi M, Kimani D, Jagne YJ, Sheehy SH, Bliss CM, Duncan CJ, Collins KA, Garcia Knight MA, Kimani E, Anagnostou NA, Berrie E, Moyle S, Gilbert SC, Spencer AJ, Soipei P, Mueller J, Okebe J, Colloca S, Cortese R, Viebig NK, Roberts R, Gantlett K, Lawrie AM, Nicosia A, Imoukhuede EB, Bejon P, Urban BC, Flanagan KL, Ewer KJ, Chilengi R, Hill AV, Bojang K. Safety and immunogenicity of heterologous prime-boost immunisation with Plasmodium falciparum malaria candidate vaccines, ChAd63 ME-TRAP and MVA ME-TRAP, in healthy Gambian and Kenyan adults. PLoS One. 2013;8(3):e57726. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0057726. Epub 2013 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23526949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roestenberg M, O'Hara GA, Duncan CJ, Epstein JE, Edwards NJ, Scholzen A, van der Ven AJ, Hermsen CC, Hill AV, Sauerwein RW. Comparison of clinical and parasitological data from controlled human malaria infection trials. PLoS One. 2012;7(6):e38434. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0038434. Epub 2012 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22701640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Verhage DF, Telgt DS, Bousema JT, Hermsen CC, van Gemert GJ, van der Meer JW, Sauerwein RW. Clinical outcome of experimental human malaria induced by Plasmodium falciparum-infected mosquitoes. Neth J Med. 2005 Feb;63(2):52-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15768480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malaria Infection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

