<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03341117</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2345</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03341117</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Acetylsalicylic Acid and Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <official_title>Acetylsalicylic Acid Administered in Patients With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus and Its Effect on the Antioxidant Enzyme System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centro Universitario de Ciencias de la Salud, Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centro Universitario de Ciencias de la Salud, Mexico</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      OBJETIVE To assess the effect of acetylsalicylic acid on antioxidant enzymatic system in
      patients with type 2 diabetes
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A randomized, double blind placebo controlled clinical trial was carried out in 21 adult
      patients with type 2 diabetes. Acetylsalicylic acid 300mg/d was administered orally for 3
      months to study group (n=11) and placebo to the control group (n=10).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A randomized double blind, placebo controlled clinical trial was carried out in 21 drug naïve adults (35-50 year of age) with DM2 with &lt;5 years since diagnosis. They were overweight or obese (BMI 25.0 - 35.0 kg/m2), had glycosylated hemoglobin A1C (HbA1c) level between 6.5 - 9%. This protocol study was reviewed and approved by the hospital based ethics committee, and written informed consent was obtained from all volunteers. Subject was selected from the same residential area and socioeconomic status. No participants were excessively sedentary or participated in heavy physical activity. All individuals were nonsmokers. Their body weight was stable for al last 3 months before the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>A randomized double blind, placebo controlled clinical trial was carried out in 21 drug naïve adults,regimen was prescribed to the subjects.
The allocation was 1:1 concealed and done by simple randomization using a table of random numbers. After randomization, 11 patients received of ASA 300 mg once daily and 10 patients received placebo (calcined magnesia) in the same pharmacological presentation for 90 days, the dose was based in the non-affectation of renal uric acid resorption.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Modification in the antioxidant enzymatic system activity (total antioxidant capacity, catalase, glutathione peroxidase , superoxide dismutase) in patients with type 2 diabetes after the administration of acetylsalicylic acid</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>In both groups (intervention an d placebo) of 21 patients each, all the patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, the antioxidant enzymatic system activity was measured before and after the administration of the acetylsalicylic acid, one capsule before each food for a period of 90 days. The patient was on a 12-hour fast.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modification in lipid profile in patients with type 2 diabetes after the administration of Acetylsalicylic Acid</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>In both groups (intervention and placebo ) of 21 patients each , all patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, lipid profile was measured in mg/dL, before and after the administration of the acetylsalicylic acid, one capsule before each food for a period of 90 days. The patient was on a 12-hour fast.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatic safety after the administration of acetylsalicylic acid through the determination of hepatic profile</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>The hepatic profile was determined through the serum levels of transaminases in U/L (Glutamic oxalacetic transaminase and Glutamic pyruvic transaminase) after of administration during 90 days of acetylsalicylic acid, The patient was on a 12-hour fast.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal safety of administration of acetylsalicylic acid through the determination of serum creatinine</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>The serum creatinine was measured in mg/dL, before and after of administration during 90 days of acetylsalicylic acid. The patient was on a 12-hour fast.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modification in HbA1c in patients with type 2 diabetes after the administration of Acetylsalicylic Acid</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>In both groups (intervention and placebo ) of 21 patients each , all patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, HbA1c was measured in %, before and after the administration of the acetylsalicylic acid, one capsule before each food for a period of 90 days. The patient was on a 12-hour fast.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modification in fasting glucose in patients with type 2 diabetes after the administration of Acetylsalicylic acid</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>In both groups (intervention and placebo ) of 21 patients each , all patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus, glucose was measured in mg/dL, before and after the administration of the acetylsalicylic acid, one capsule before each food for a period of 90 days. The patient was on a 12-hour fast.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Antioxidant Enzyme System</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acetylsalicylic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients were randomly assigned to received Acetylsalicylic acid 300 mg once daily for 90 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>calcined magnesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients were randomly assigned to received placebo (calcinaned magnesia),
1 capsule 300 mg before each meal for a period of 90 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acetylsalicylic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Acetylsalicylic acid 300 mg per capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acetylsalicylic acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aspirin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Calcined magnesia</intervention_name>
    <description>Calcined magnesia 300 mg per capsule</description>
    <arm_group_label>calcined magnesia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 2 Diabetes

          -  BMI 25.0 - 35.0 kg/m2

          -  HbA1c between 6.5 - 9%.

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Same residential area and socioeconomic status.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Sedentary or heavy physical activity.

          -  Nonsmokers.

          -  Body weight was stable for al last 3 months before the study.

          -  Personal history of hepatic, renal, gastric or coronary artery disease.

          -  Hypersensibility to acetylsalicylic acid.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jandeleit-Dahm K, Cooper ME. The role of AGEs in cardiovascular disease. Curr Pharm Des. 2008;14(10):979-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18473849</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rahimi R, Nikfar S, Larijani B, Abdollahi M. A review on the role of antioxidants in the management of diabetes and its complications. Biomed Pharmacother. 2005 Aug;59(7):365-73. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16081237</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giacco F, Brownlee M. Oxidative stress and diabetic complications. Circ Res. 2010 Oct 29;107(9):1058-70. doi: 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.110.223545. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21030723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henriksen EJ, Diamond-Stanic MK, Marchionne EM. Oxidative stress and the etiology of insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes. Free Radic Biol Med. 2011 Sep 1;51(5):993-9. doi: 10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2010.12.005. Epub 2010 Dec 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21163347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johansen JS, Harris AK, Rychly DJ, Ergul A. Oxidative stress and the use of antioxidants in diabetes: linking basic science to clinical practice. Cardiovasc Diabetol. 2005 Apr 29;4:5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15862133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zatalia SR, Sanusi H. The role of antioxidants in the pathophysiology, complications, and management of diabetes mellitus. Acta Med Indones. 2013 Apr;45(2):141-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23770795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newsholme P, Haber EP, Hirabara SM, Rebelato EL, Procopio J, Morgan D, Oliveira-Emilio HC, Carpinelli AR, Curi R. Diabetes associated cell stress and dysfunction: role of mitochondrial and non-mitochondrial ROS production and activity. J Physiol. 2007 Aug 15;583(Pt 1):9-24. Epub 2007 Jun 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17584843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lapshina EA, Sudnikovich EJ, Maksimchik JZ, Zabrodskaya SV, Zavodnik LB, Kubyshin VL, Nocun M, Kazmierczak P, Dobaczewski M, Watala C, Zavodnik IB. Antioxidative enzyme and glutathione S-transferase activities in diabetic rats exposed to long-term ASA treatment. Life Sci. 2006 Oct 4;79(19):1804-11. Epub 2006 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>16815474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baltazar MT, Dinis-Oliveira RJ, Duarte JA, Bastos ML, Carvalho F. Antioxidant properties and associated mechanisms of salicylates. Curr Med Chem. 2011;18(21):3252-64. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21671857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caballero F, Gerez E, Batlle A, Vazquez E. Preventive aspirin treatment of streptozotocin induced diabetes: blockage of oxidative status and revertion of heme enzymes inhibition. Chem Biol Interact. 2000 Jun 1;126(3):215-25.</citation>
    <PMID>10862819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jeyaseelan L, Rao PS. Methods of determining sample sizes in clinical trials. Indian Pediatr. 1989 Feb;26(2):115-21.</citation>
    <PMID>2753525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldfine AB, Silver R, Aldhahi W, Cai D, Tatro E, Lee J, Shoelson SE. Use of salsalate to target inflammation in the treatment of insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes. Clin Transl Sci. 2008 May;1(1):36-43. doi: 10.1111/j.1752-8062.2008.00026.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19337387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blakytny R, Harding JJ. Prevention of cataract in diabetic rats by aspirin, paracetamol (acetaminophen) and ibuprofen. Exp Eye Res. 1992 Apr;54(4):509-18.</citation>
    <PMID>1623937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coudray C, Favier A. Determination of salicylate hydroxylation products as an in vivo oxidative stress marker. Free Radic Biol Med. 2000 Dec;29(11):1064-70.</citation>
    <PMID>11121712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ames PR, Batuca JR, Muncy IJ, De La Torre IG, Pascoe-Gonzales S, Guyer K, Matsuura E, Lopez LR. Aspirin insensitive thromboxane generation is associated with oxidative stress in type 2 diabetes mellitus. Thromb Res. 2012 Sep;130(3):350-4. doi: 10.1016/j.thromres.2012.03.025. Epub 2012 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22521214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lemkes BA, Bähler L, Kamphuisen PW, Stroobants AK, Van Den Dool EJ, Hoekstra JB, Nieuwland R, Gerdes VE, Holleman F. The influence of aspirin dose and glycemic control on platelet inhibition in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. J Thromb Haemost. 2012 Apr;10(4):639-46. doi: 10.1111/j.1538-7836.2012.04632.x.</citation>
    <PMID>22252020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Müller KA, Chatterjee M, Rath D, Geisler T. Platelets, inflammation and anti-inflammatory effects of antiplatelet drugs in ACS and CAD. Thromb Haemost. 2015 Aug 31;114(3):498-518. doi: 10.1160/TH14-11-0947. Epub 2015 Jul 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26224127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagelschmitz J, Blunck M, Kraetzschmar J, Ludwig M, Wensing G, Hohlfeld T. Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of acetylsalicylic acid after intravenous and oral administration to healthy volunteers. Clin Pharmacol. 2014 Mar 19;6:51-9. doi: 10.2147/CPAA.S47895. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24672263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dzeshka MS, Shantsila A, Lip GY. Effects of Aspirin on Endothelial Function and Hypertension. Curr Hypertens Rep. 2016 Nov;18(11):83. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27787837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grimaldi R, Bisi M, Lonni E, Beggiato E, Valpreda A, Lococo MF, Dosio E, Presutti DG, Tagliabue M, Gaita F. Laboratory aspirin resistance reversibility in diabetic patients: a pilot study using different pharmaceutical formulations. Cardiovasc Drugs Ther. 2014 Aug;28(4):323-9. doi: 10.1007/s10557-014-6536-7.</citation>
    <PMID>24984883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdin AA, Baalash AA, Hamooda HE. Effects of rosiglitazone and aspirin on experimental model of induced type 2 diabetes in rats: focus on insulin resistance and inflammatory markers. J Diabetes Complications. 2010 May-Jun;24(3):168-78. doi: 10.1016/j.jdiacomp.2009.01.005. Epub 2009 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19328014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centro Universitario de Ciencias de la Salud, Mexico</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sara Pascoe Gonzalez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD Clinical Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acetylsalicylic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>antioxidant enzyme system</keyword>
  <keyword>stress oxidative</keyword>
  <keyword>type 2 diabetes mellitus.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antioxidants</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Magnesium Oxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

