<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03343405</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MindBody</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03343405</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Online Mind/Body Program for Fertility</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fertility &amp; Well-Being: Mind/Body Protocol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Vermont</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Vermont</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot-study assesses the feasibility and acceptability of an Online Mind/Body Fertility
      Program, designed to help individuals and/or couples cope with the physical and emotional
      impact of infertility by learning special relaxation strategies and improving lifestyle
      habits. Participants included women experiencing infertility who had not given birth to a
      child. Half of participants received access to the 10-week Online Mind-Body Program and the
      other half were placed on a waiting-list.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Infertility is defined as the inability to conceive a child. A couple may be acknowledged as
      infertile if conception has not occurred after 12 months of having regular, unprotected
      intercourse. Over six million couples in the United States are affected by infertility.
      Research suggests that there is a relationship between psychological distress and
      infertility, but the relationship is complex. The information from this study will be used to
      better understand the relationship between psychological distress and infertility among
      couples. Furthermore, the investigators are interested in testing Dr. Alice Domar's Mind/Body
      Fertility Program that was designed to help individuals regain control of their life and
      learn new lifestyle habits that can increase their chances of conceiving. There is evidence
      that individuals that participated in the group format of this treatment protocol showed
      statistically significant decreases in physical and psychological symptoms of stress and
      increases in conception rates. Our primary goals are to evaluate patients willingness to be
      recruited and randomized as well as their adherence and attrition to the program. Our
      secondary goals are to evaluate reductions in emotional distress (i.e., anxiety, depression,
      and stress) and enhance emotion regulation skills as well as pregnancy rates.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 14, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 14, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 14, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A between groups repeated measure experimental design. Participants that met inclusion criteria and were interested in continuing with the study were randomized to either the treatment or wait-list group. Participants randomized to the treatment group were provided with 10 online program modules provided weekly over 10 weeks. After 10-weeks the wait-list group had the opportunity to participate in the intervention protocol if they desire. All participants will be asked to complete pre-, mid-, post-, f/u- intervention questionnaires.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility 1: Feasibility of recruitment and randomization</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants recruited and randomized. From time study began to when recruitment closed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility 2: Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time between recruitment and completion of the study. Time between recruitment and randomization; time between each of the modules; time between each of the assessments (pre-assessment; mid-assessment; post-assessment, and follow-up).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility 3: Participant retention and acceptability</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of enrolled participants that completed each stage of the study (mid-assessment, post-assessment, follow-up, and each of the ten modules for the intervention group only).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability 1: Ease of modules</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked at the end of each module: &quot;how easy was this module.&quot; Answer choices are on a 3-point Likert scale, ranging from 1 (&quot;easy&quot;) to 3 (&quot;not easy&quot;). Data collected from beginning to end of intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability 2: Helpfulness</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked at the end of each module: &quot;how helpful was the module.&quot; Answer choices are on a four-item Likert scale ranging from 0 (&quot;unhelpful&quot;) to 3 (&quot;very helpful&quot;). Data is collected throughout the Mind/Body program, intervention group only.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction of Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participant satisfaction as measured by the Client Satisfaction Inventory Short-Form (McMurtry &amp; Hudson, 2000). This measurement is a 9-item self-report scale that assesses the satisfaction of the participant with the effects of the treatments. Participants are asked to rate the way they feel about the services they received on a 7-point Likert scale, ranging from 1 (&quot;none of the time&quot;) to 7 (&quot;all of the time&quot;). The total scores range between 0 and 100 (for scoring algorithm, see McMurty &amp; Hudson, 2000), with higher scores indicating more satisfaction. Data is collected for the intervention group at post-assessment only.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy: Between group comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported confirmation of pregnancy. Data collected at baseline, pre-assessment, mid-assessment, post-assessment, and follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety 1: Individual changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Individual changes in anxiety as measured by the Beck Anxiety Inventory. The Beck Anxiety Inventory is a 21-item self-report measure used to assess somatic or panic-related anxiety symptoms. Individuals are asked to rate their symptoms of anxiety over the past week on a 4-point Likert scale from 0 (&quot;not at all&quot;) to 3 (&quot;severely; I could barely stand it&quot;). A total score is calculated by summing all items. Scores range from 0 (no anxiety severity) to 63 (severe anxiety severity). Data collected throughout study (baseline, pre-assessment, mid-assessment, post-assessment, and follow-up) as well as at the beginning of each intervention module.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety 2: Between group changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group changes in anxiety as measured by Beck Anxiety Inventory (Beck, Steer, Beck, &amp; Newman, 1993). The Beck Anxiety Inventory is a 21-item self-report measure used to assess somatic or panic-related anxiety symptoms. Individuals are asked to rate their symptoms of anxiety over the past week on a 4-point Likert scale from 0 (&quot;not at all&quot;) to 3 (&quot;severely; I could barely stand it&quot;). A total score is calculated by summing all items. Scores range from 0 (no anxiety severity) to 63 (severe anxiety severity). Data collected throughout study (baseline, pre-assessment, mid-assessment, post-assessment, and follow-up) as well as at the beginning of each intervention module.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression 1: Individual changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Individual changes in depression as measured by the Beck Depression Inventory - 2nd Edition. The Beck Depression Inventory - 2nd Edition is a 21-item self-report measure used to assess cognitive, affective, and physical depressive symptoms. Questions include content such as sadness, guilt, disappointment, and loss of energy. Participants are asked to rate each item on a 4-point Likert scale from 0 (not endorsed) to 3 (endorsed at maximum severity). A total score is calculated by summing all items. Scores range from 0 (no depressive symptoms) to 63 (severe depressive symptoms). Data collected at baseline, pre-assessment, mid-assessment, post-assessment and follow-up).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression 2: Between group changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group changes in depression as measured by the Beck Depression Inventory - 2nd Edition (Beck, Steer, Ball, &amp; Ranieri, 1996). The Beck Depression Inventory - 2nd Edition is a 21-item self-report measure used to assess cognitive, affective, and physical depressive symptoms. Questions include content such as sadness, guilt, disappointment, and loss of energy. Participants are asked to rate each item on a 4-point Likert scale from 0 (not endorsed) to 3 (endorsed at maximum severity). A total score is calculated by summing all items. Scores range from 0 (no depressive symptoms) to 63 (severe depressive symptoms). Data collected at baseline, pre-assessment, mid-assessment, post-assessment and follow-up).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress: Between group changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group changes in stress as measured by Perceived Stress Scale. The Perceived Stress Scale is a 10-item questionnaire measuring the present level of self-rated stress in the last month. Items were designed to assess how unpredictable, uncontrollable, and overloaded respondents find their lives. Higher scores indicate more distress. Participants are asked to rate each item on a 5-point Likert scale from 0 (&quot;never&quot;) to 4 (&quot;very often&quot;). Scores range from 0 to 40 where higher scores indicate greater perceived stress (for scoring algorithm see Cohen, 1988; Cohen, Kamarck, &amp; Mermelstein, 1983).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mindfulness: Between group comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group changes in mindfulness as measured by the Five-Factor Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ; Baer, Smith, Hopkins, Krietemeyer, &amp; Toney, 2006). The FFMQ is a 39-item self-report measure used to assess a trait-like tendency to be mindful in daily life. It has five subscales (i.e., observe, describe, awareness, non-judgmental, and non-reactive). Each question on the FFMQ is rated on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (&quot;never or very rarely true&quot;) to 5 (&quot;very often or always true&quot;). Total score (adding subscale scores) ranges from 39 to 195 with higher scores indicating greater mindfulness (for scoring algorithm see Baer, Smith, Hopkins, Krietemeyer, &amp; Toney, 2006). Data collected at baseline, mid-assessment, and post-assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fertility Problem Inventory: Between group changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group changes in fertility related distress as measured by The Fertility Problem Inventory. The Fertility Problem Inventory is a 46-item questionnaire that measures domains (Social Concern, Sexual Concern, Relationship Concern, Need for Parenthood, and Rejection of Child-Free Lifestyle) considered important in understanding perceived infertility related stress as well as an overall global index of infertility-related stress (composite score of the all domains). The overall score ranges from 46 to 276. For each of the scales, higher scores indicate more fertility related distress (for a scoring algorithm see Newton, Sherrard, &amp; Glavac, 1999). Data collected at baseline, post-assessment, and follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emotion Regulation: Between group comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group changes in emotion regulation as measured by the Difficulties in Emotional Regulation Scale (DERS; Gratz &amp; Roemer, 2004). The DERS is a 36-item self-report questionnaire measuring problems with emotional regulation based on responses indicating impairment in six dimensions (Goals, Impulse, Awareness, Nonacceptance, Strategy, and Clarity) and a total score (sum of all subscales). Total score ranges from 36 to 180. For each of the scales, higher scores indicate greater difficulties with emotional regulation in each of the domains (for scoring algorithm see Gratz &amp; Roemer, 2004). Data collected at baseline and post-assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship Quality: Between group comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between group changes in emotion regulation as measured by the Dyadic Adjustment Scale (Spanier, 1976). The Dyadic Adjustment Scale is a 32-item questionnaire assessing relationship difficulty in four domains (Consensus, Satisfaction, Affective Expression, and Cohesion) and a total score. The total score ranges form 0 and 151. Greater scores indicate greater marital satisfaction (for scoring algorithm see, Spanier, 1976). Data collected at baseline and post-assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction 2: Qualitative</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Open-ended questions regarding components of the mind/body program throughout the ten modules and post-intervention to provide context around satisfaction of intervention.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">71</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention: Online Mind/Body</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the intervention group (i.e., Online Mind/Body Program for Fertility) were provided the 10 online modules provided weekly (one module per week), intended to be completed over 10 weeks. Additionally, participants received weekly therapeutic feedback.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait-List</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>After 10-weeks being in the wait-list group, participants had the potential to participate in the intervention protocol if they desire.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online Mind/Body Program for Fertility</intervention_name>
    <description>The Mind/Body intervention involves (1) reducing physical symptoms of stress, (2) enhancing lifestyle behaviors related to fertility, (4) self-nurturing and coping skills, and (5) relaxation methods.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention: Online Mind/Body</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women and Men

          -  Infertility diagnosis

          -  Trying to get pregnant

          -  18 years or older

          -  Read and write English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No current diagnosis for an active psychotic disorder, eating disorder, substance
             abuse or dependence

          -  Not reporting current suicidal ideation/intent

          -  No psychotropic medication changes in the last four weeks

          -  Has not completed a formal mind/body program focused on infertility that included
             relaxation, yoga, mindfulness, cognitive restructuring, stress reduction strategies,
             listening and communication skills, goal setting and assertiveness training.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jessica Clifton, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Vermont</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Vermont</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05405</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.uvm.edu/~olmndbdy/</url>
    <description>Online Mind/Body Program for Fertility</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Domar AD, Clapp D, Slawsby EA, Dusek J, Kessel B, Freizinger M. Impact of group psychological interventions on pregnancy rates in infertile women. Fertil Steril. 2000 Apr;73(4):805-11. Erratum in: Fertil Steril 2000 Jul;74(1):190.</citation>
    <PMID>10731544</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Domar AD, Clapp D, Slawsby E, Kessel B, Orav J, Freizinger M. The impact of group psychological interventions on distress in infertile women. Health Psychol. 2000 Nov;19(6):568-75.</citation>
    <PMID>11129360</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Domar AD, Rooney KL, Wiegand B, Orav EJ, Alper MM, Berger BM, Nikolovski J. Impact of a group mind/body intervention on pregnancy rates in IVF patients. Fertil Steril. 2011 Jun;95(7):2269-73. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2011.03.046. Epub 2011 Apr 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21496800</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Vermont</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jessica Clifton</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Post-Doctoral Associate</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mind/Body</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

