<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03341780</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SoutherCCO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03341780</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Standard Amblyopia Therapy in Adult Amblyopes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Standard Amblyopia Therapy in Adult Amblyopes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Southern California College of Optometry</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Allergan</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Southern California College of Optometry</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Amblyopia is characterized by a reduction in visual acuity, contrast sensitivity, and
      binocular visual functions. The two main causes of amblyopia are anisometropia and strabismus
      which alter the synaptic connections between neurons along the visual pathway. Current
      treatment for amblyopia has indicated that the younger the amblyope, the greater the effect
      of treatment. The purpose of this study is to determine if standard amblyopia treatment
      improved visual acuity in adult amblyopes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Functional amblyopia is an optically uncorrectable decrease in visual acuity, i.e., spatial
      resolution, with no apparent pathological or morphological cause. There are several
      etiological origins for amblyopia in the human population; anisometropia and strabismus are
      the two most prevalent etiological factors. Anisometropic amblyopia is a decrease in visual
      acuity (spatial resolution) that is the result of a large difference in refractive error
      between the two eyes. Strabismic amblyopia is characterized by an eye misalignment early in
      life which is associated with a decrease in visual acuity.

      The initial site of the defect in amblyopia is the primary visual cortex. The amblyopic eye
      is placed at a competitive disadvantage to the nonamblyopic eye which results in a reduction
      in the synapses or cells responding to the amblyopic eye. The conditions associated with
      amblyopia must be present prior to the end of the critical period of neural development for
      amblyopia to develop. The neurophysiological systems of anisometropic and strabismic monkeys
      have differences in the distributions of binocular cortical cells. Anisometropic amblyopic
      monkeys only exhibit binocular cells that are tuned to low spatial frequencies. If a neuron
      has a high spatial resolution, it is unlikely that the neuron will be binocular. However,
      strabismic amblyopic monkeys exhibit few binocular cells and, moreover, there does not appear
      to be a spatial frequency dependent distribution of these binocular cells. The strabismic
      subjects typically displayed few binocular cells, regardless of the spatial frequency tuning
      of the cell.

      If the amblyopic eye is compared to the nonamblyopic eye, two important differences are
      noted. First, the amblyopic eye has a lower contrast sensitivity at high spatial frequencies
      (and sometimes at all spatial frequencies) than the nonamblyopic eye. This also results in a
      decrease in visual acuity for the amblyopic eye. Second, the amblyopic eye demonstrates a
      longer latency for neural transmission than the nonamblyopic eye.

      There is very little published on adult amblyopia therapy. This is because clinicians
      initially believed that amblyopia could not be treated after the end of the critical period.
      The prevailing theory was that the synaptic contacts between cells could only be modified
      during the critical period. In children, the majority of the improvement in acuity (80%)
      takes place in the first 6 weeks of therapy. There is a direct relationship between the hours
      of patching and the improvement in acuity. Most of the improvement in acuity occurs after the
      first 100 hours of patching.

      There is a linear dose-response function for amblyopia treatment. The logMAR acuity increases
      0.1 log unit or 1 chart line per 120 hours of patching. The response does not differ between
      the types of amblyopia. It has also been demonstrated that there is only a minimal benefit to
      patching more than 2 hours/day.

      In a Pediatric Eye Disease Investigator Group (PEDIG) study, 189 amblyopic children were
      treated with 2 hours of patching per day. The amblyopic eye acuities ranged from 20/40 -
      20/80 before treatment. The average improvement in acuity after 4 months of treatment was
      0.24 logMAR (2.4 lines improvement on a logMAR chart). Another study used amblyopes with
      poorer acuity (20/100 - 20/400 before therapy). After 4 months of patching, the average
      increase in acuity was 0.48 logMAR (or an increase of 4.8 lines on a logMAR chart). The
      average acuity went from 20/250 (i.e., 1.10 logMAR) before treatment to 20/63 (i.e., 0.50
      logMAR) after treatment. The results were the same for anisometropic amblyopes and strabismic
      amblyopes. In another study with amblyopes with starting acuity worse than 20/100, the
      improvement was 3.7 ± 2.5 logMAR chart lines of acuity.

      Recent studies have suggested that adult amblyopia can be treated with non-standard therapy.
      Patching combined with active, near, threshold-training tasks and continuous feedback is
      employed in these studies. These studies indicate that amblyopia can be treated after the
      critical period ends. It is suggested that these perceptual learning tasks improve
      performance in the amblyopic eye by decreasing neural noise. Standard amblyopia therapy
      typically employed in children has not been investigated in adult amblyopes. The purpose of
      this study is to use standard amblyopic therapy to determine if there is an enhancement in
      visual performance in the amblyopic eye of adults.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 16, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 24, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 24, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>LogMAR acuity will be measured with the eETDRS chart</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Amblyopia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>amblyopia therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Any of the following amblyopia training activities may be employed during patching: board games, card games, coloring in O's, comic books, craft projects, crossword puzzles, dot-to-dot patterns, drawing, hammering nails, jacks, jigsaw puzzles, lego and other blocks, marbles, mazes, peg-board activities, perceptual materials, pickup sticks, reading, sewing, shooting games, stringing beads, throwing or hitting games, tracing, and video or computer games.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be recruited from the College community and University Eye Clinic. An
        announcement will be made to the College community and volunteers accepted.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Amblyopic patients with acuities between 20/40 (0.30 logMAR) and 20/400 (1.30 logMAR).

          -  All subjects will be over the age of 18.

          -  Prior amblyopia therapy is not an exclusion criteria.

          -  Subjects will be recruited from the College community and University Eye Clinic.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A significant cataract that affects vision.

          -  Glaucoma, diabetes, uncontrolled high blood pressure.

          -  Other ocular or systemic diseases that will affect visual acuity.

          -  The inability to give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Ridder, OD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Southern California College of Optometry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>von Noorden GK. Amblyopia: a multidisciplinary approach. Proctor lecture. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1985 Dec;26(12):1704-16.</citation>
    <PMID>3934105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Michaels DD. Visual optics and refraction: a clinical approach. St Louis, MO: C.V. Mosby Co.; 1980.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crawford ML, Blake R, Cool SJ, von Noorden GK. Physiological consequences of unilateral and bilateral eye closure in macaque monkeys: some further observations. Brain Res. 1975 Jan 24;84(1):150-4.</citation>
    <PMID>1111823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hubel DH, Wiesel TN, LeVay S. Plasticity of ocular dominance columns in monkey striate cortex. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 1977 Apr 26;278(961):377-409.</citation>
    <PMID>19791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart CE, Moseley MJ, Stephens DA, Fielder AR. Treatment dose-response in amblyopia therapy: the Monitored Occlusion Treatment of Amblyopia Study (MOTAS). Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2004 Sep;45(9):3048-54.</citation>
    <PMID>15326120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Repka MX, Beck RW, Holmes JM, Birch EE, Chandler DL, Cotter SA, Hertle RW, Kraker RT, Moke PS, Quinn GE, Scheiman MM; Pediatric Eye Disease Investigator Group. A randomized trial of patching regimens for treatment of moderate amblyopia in children. Arch Ophthalmol. 2003 May;121(5):603-11.</citation>
    <PMID>12742836</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holmes JM, Kraker RT, Beck RW, Birch EE, Cotter SA, Everett DF, Hertle RW, Quinn GE, Repka MX, Scheiman MM, Wallace DK; Pediatric Eye Disease Investigator Group. A randomized trial of prescribed patching regimens for treatment of severe amblyopia in children. Ophthalmology. 2003 Nov;110(11):2075-87.</citation>
    <PMID>14597512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holmes JM, Edwards AR, Beck RW, Arnold RW, Johnson DA, Klimek DL, Kraker RT, Lee KA, Lyon DW, Nosel ER, Repka MX, Sala NA, Silbert DI, Tamkins S; Pediatric Eye Disease Investigator Group. A randomized pilot study of near activities versus non-near activities during patching therapy for amblyopia. J AAPOS. 2005 Apr;9(2):129-36.</citation>
    <PMID>15838439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holmes JM, Lazar EL, Melia BM, Astle WF, Dagi LR, Donahue SP, Frazier MG, Hertle RW, Repka MX, Quinn GE, Weise KK; Pediatric Eye Disease Investigator Group. Effect of age on response to amblyopia treatment in children. Arch Ophthalmol. 2011 Nov;129(11):1451-7. doi: 10.1001/archophthalmol.2011.179. Epub 2011 Jul 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21746970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levi DM, Li RW. Perceptual learning as a potential treatment for amblyopia: a mini-review. Vision Res. 2009 Oct;49(21):2535-49. doi: 10.1016/j.visres.2009.02.010. Epub 2009 Feb 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19250947</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levi DM, Li RW. Improving the performance of the amblyopic visual system. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 2009 Feb 12;364(1515):399-407. doi: 10.1098/rstb.2008.0203. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19008199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ridder WH 3rd, Rouse MW. Predicting potential acuities in amblyopes: predicting post-therapy acuity in amblyopes. Doc Ophthalmol. 2007 May;114(3):135-45. Epub 2007 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>17310345</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amblyopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

