<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03344835</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HK-CaP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03344835</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hong Kong Prostate Cancer Study Group Database</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comprehensive Assessment of the Physical and Biological Effects of Patients With Prostate Cancer in Hong Kong</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer (PCa) is ranked 3rd in annual incidence of male cancer and ranked 5th for
      cancer-related death in men in Hong Kong which accounts for about 9.1 deaths per 100,000 men
      in 2011. Its incidence is rising rapidly, almost tripled in the past 10 years. In Hong Kong,
      the two main screening methods for PCa are digital rectal examination (DRE) and serum
      prostate-specific antigen (PSA) level blood test, and the gold standard of diagnosis of PCa
      is transrectal ultrasound (TRUS) with prostate biopsy.

      For those who diagnosed with PCa, there are different kinds of managements depending on
      patient's age group and disease stage. Watchful waiting is for older patients who presents
      with low-risk prostate cancer. And active surveillance is applicable to patients who are
      eligible for potentially curative management. While radiotherapy or radical prostatectomy are
      recommended as curative management for early stage PCa, androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) is
      the main treatment modality for advanced or recurrent prostate cancer. Advanced prostate
      cancer that recurrence is called castration refractory prostate cancer (CRPC). There are many
      new agents, including second line hormonal therapy, chemotherapy, androgen biosynthesis
      inhibitors, immunotherapy, bone targeting agents etc., available for the further management.

      In this study, investigators would like to establish a local prostate cancer registry to
      facilitate the collection of clinical information and outcomes of prostate cancer management.
      Hopefully, this registry can provide information regarding the epidemiology, natural history,
      and treatment outcomes of local prostate cancer. The information would be helpful for
      research, public education, health care planning and also international collaboration.
      Ultimately, patients and public would be benefited from these works.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The prostate gland is a clinically important male accessory sex gland and vital for its
      production of semen. Prostate cancer (PCa) is ranked 3rd in annual incidence of male cancer
      and ranked 5th for cancer-related death in men in Hong Kong which accounts for about 9.1
      deaths per 100,000 men in 2011. Its incidence is rising rapidly, almost tripled in the past
      10 years. Although this cancer is extremely rare before age 40 but the incidence increases
      with age, as the elderly population continues to increase, the impact of PCa on the men's
      health and also the burden on health care system will continue to rise. In addition to age,
      epidemiological data shows that race is also an important risk factor for prostate cancer.
      African-American men have the highest rates of prostate cancer in the world. For Asian
      populations, native Chinese and Japanese showed the lowest prostate cancer rates, though the
      incidence is rapidly increasing in the past decades.

      The two main screening methods for PCa are digital rectal examination (DRE) and serum
      prostate-specific antigen (PSA) level blood test. DRE is an exam to check for growths or
      enlargement of the prostate gland. A tumor in the prostate can often be felt as a hard
      nodule. This may be done as a regular exam or check for the symptoms. If problems are
      suspected, DRE is usually done together with PSA, which was first introduced to evaluate the
      possibility of present of PCa in 1987. A common PSA threshold for biopsy in Hong Kong and
      Asia is PSA level greater than 4.0 ng/mL. Despite the controversial of PSA and some newer
      markers for PSA diagnosis, it is still the most common screening for PCa, due to the low cost
      and simplicity.

      The gold standard of diagnosis of PCa is transrectal ultrasound (TRUS) with prostate biopsy.
      During the procedure, usually ten cores of biopsies will be taken and sent for pathological
      evaluation. If any of the biopsies are found malignant, Gleason score will be given and the
      stage of cancer will be determined.

      Unlike other malignancy, PCa is characterized by its slow progression nature and even for
      metastatic disease the 5-year survival is up to 20%. Therefore, there will be different kinds
      of management for difference age group and disease stage: active surveillance (AS), watchful
      waiting, and treatments. Watchful waiting is for older patients who presents with low-risk
      prostate cancer. In these cases, treatment is probably not suitable for them due to the old
      age and low effectiveness. Contrasting watchful waiting, AS is applicable to patients who are
      eligible for potentially curative management. During AS, PCa is closely monitored for signs
      of progression. PSA blood test and DRE are usually administered at times along with a repeat
      biopsy of the prostate at one year and then at specific intervals thereafter. If symptoms
      develop, or if tests indicate the cancer is growing, treatment will be necessary.

      For early stage of prostate cancer, radiotherapy or radical prostatectomy are recommended as
      curative management. The purpose of these treatments is to cure the disease. Over 80% of
      patients were cured with no recurrence. Currently, robotic prostatectomy is the main surgical
      approach for localized prostate cancer with acceptable perioperative results. Radiotherapy,
      both external beam and brachytherapy, are also standard therapy for prostate cancer. The
      overall complication rate, as reported from the Western literatures, for both surgery and
      radiotherapy are quite low. The final choice of treatment will largely depend on the join
      decision between physicians and patients.

      However, for advanced or recurrent prostate cancer, androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) is the
      main treatment modality. While the effectiveness of ADT is well documented in the literature,
      the adverse effect profile in Asian patients, in particular to the cardiovascular system and
      bone metabolism, was not well documented.

      Due to the continue changes in the behavior of prostate cancer cell under androgen deprivated
      environment, advanced prostate cancer will eventually entered a stage of castration
      refractory prostate cancer (CRPC). Currently, there are many new agents, including second
      line hormonal therapy, chemotherapy, androgen biosynthesis inhibitors, immunotherapy, bone
      targeting agents etc., available for the further management of these CRPC patients.
      Unfortunately, the clinical outcome and side effect profiles for further treatment for
      patients with in local Chinese population, as well as in Asian population was still not that
      certain.

      Due to the continue changes in the behavior of prostate cancer cell under androgen deprived
      environment, advanced prostate cancer will eventually entered a stage of castration
      refractory prostate cancer (CRPC). Currently, there are many new agents, including second
      line hormonal therapy, chemotherapy, androgen biosynthesis inhibitors, immunotherapy, bone
      targeting agents etc., available for the further management of these CRPC patients.
      Unfortunately, the clinical outcome and side effect profiles for further treatment for
      patients with in local Chinese population, as well as in Asian population was still not that
      certain.

      Facing the increase in clinical demand by the drastic increase in patient population,
      together with the rapid development in various therapies for different stages of prostate
      cancer, there is a need to have better understanding about the natural history, clinical
      outcomes of various therapies for prostate cancer. Therefore, investigators would like to
      establish a local prostate cancer registry to facilitate the collection of clinical
      information and outcomes of prostate cancer management. Hopefully, this registry can provide
      information regarding the epidemiology, natural history, and treatment outcomes of local
      prostate cancer. The information would be helpful for research, public education, health care
      planning and also international collaboration. Ultimately, patients and public would be
      benefited from these works

      In this study, both retrospective and prospective cohort study design will be adopted.
      Patients diagnosed with prostate cancer from 2016 will be captured prospectively and those
      who diagnosed in or before 2015 will be captured retrospectively. Patients diagnosed with
      prostate cancer in the hospitals under the New Territories East Cluster (NTEC) &amp; New
      Territories West Cluster (NTWC) will be identified in specialist clinics, wards, and during
      TRUS, and then enrolled to the study. This study will be conducted by observation; no
      intervention article is used. The time of diagnosis of prostate cancer will be set as
      baseline of that subject. All the demographic and medical background will be traced back. All
      patients will be followed up every 6 months and thereafter. During the follow-up, patients'
      medical status including survival, cancer status, treatment, complications will be captured
      from the medical records.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2040</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2035</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>10 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific survival</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>The cancer specific survival of different disease stages in Hong Kong Chinese prostate cancer patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Survival of different disease stages in Hong Kong Chinese prostate cancer patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biological progress</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time to biochemical progression of different disease stages in Hong Kong Chinese prostate cancer patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>PSA response for different treatment modalities at different disease stages</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications rate</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Complications rate of different modalities of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15000</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prostate Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with prostate cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Prostate Cancer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients diagnosed with prostate cancer, in NDH, PWH and TMH, since 1995 would be
        included in the registry. Both retrospective and prospective cohort study design will be
        adopted in this study. Patients diagnosed with prostate cancer in the hospitals under the
        NTEC &amp; NTWC cluster will be identified in specialist clinics, wards, and during TRUS, and
        then enrolled to the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient at the age of 18 or above

          -  Patients with clinical diagnosis of prostate cancer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed to have ductal type of prostate cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Prostate cancer only happens in male patients</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chi Fai NG, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chi Fai NG, MD</last_name>
    <phone>3505 3953</phone>
    <email>ngcf@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Siu Ying YIP, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>3505 1663</phone>
    <email>siuying@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prince of Wales Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shatin</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chi Fai NG, MD</last_name>
      <phone>3505 3953</phone>
      <email>ngcf@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Siu Ying YIP, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>3505 1663</phone>
      <email>siuying@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiu PK, Wong AY, Hou SM, Yip SK, Ng CF. Effect of body mass index on serum prostate-specific antigen levels among patients presenting with lower urinary tract symptoms. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev. 2011;12(8):1937-40.</citation>
    <PMID>22292628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng CF, Chiu PK, Lam NY, Lam HC, Lee KW, Hou SS. The Prostate Health Index in predicting initial prostate biopsy outcomes in Asian men with prostate-specific antigen levels of 4-10 ng/mL. Int Urol Nephrol. 2014 Apr;46(4):711-7. doi: 10.1007/s11255-013-0582-0. Epub 2013 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>24136184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sasagawa I, Nakada T. Epidemiology of prostatic cancer in East Asia. Arch Androl. 2001 Nov-Dec;47(3):195-201.</citation>
    <PMID>11695843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ng CF, Yeung R, Chiu PK, Lam NY, Chow J, Chan B. The role of urine prostate cancer antigen 3 mRNA levels in the diagnosis of prostate cancer among Hong Kong Chinese patients. Hong Kong Med J. 2012 Dec;18(6):459-65.</citation>
    <PMID>23223645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sim HG, Cheng CW. Changing demography of prostate cancer in Asia. Eur J Cancer. 2005 Apr;41(6):834-45. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15808953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang W, Yuasa T, Tsuchiya N, Maita S, Kumazawa T, Inoue T, Saito M, Ma Z, Obara T, Tsuruta H, Satoh S, Habuchi T. Bone mineral density in Japanese prostate cancer patients under androgen-deprivation therapy. Endocr Relat Cancer. 2008 Dec;15(4):943-52. doi: 10.1677/ERC-08-0116. Epub 2008 Jul 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18667685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilt TJ, Thompson IM. Clinically localised prostate cancer. BMJ. 2006 Nov 25;333(7578):1102-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17124221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilt TJ, MacDonald R, Rutks I, Shamliyan TA, Taylor BC, Kane RL. Systematic review: comparative effectiveness and harms of treatments for clinically localized prostate cancer. Ann Intern Med. 2008 Mar 18;148(6):435-48. Epub 2008 Feb 4. Review. Erratum in: Ann Intern Med. 2008 Jun 3;148(11):888.</citation>
    <PMID>18252677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yip KH, Yee CH, Ng CF, Lam NY, Ho KL, Ma WK, Li CM, Hou SM, Tam PC, Yiu MK, Fan CW. Robot-assisted radical prostatectomy in Hong Kong: a review of 235 cases. J Endourol. 2012 Mar;26(3):258-63. doi: 10.1089/end.2011.0303. Epub 2012 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22192108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chi Fai NG</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor NG, Chi Fai</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Disease Outcome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

