<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03341130</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F17-00320</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03341130</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Determinants of Tooth Movement in Oral Appliance Treatment of OSA.</brief_title>
  <acronym>TACO</acronym>
  <official_title>Determinants of Occlusal Changes in Oral Appliance Treatment of OSA - A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Université de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laval University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a sleep related breathing disorder, affecting approximately
      10% of adults. Mandibular advancement oral appliances (OAM) are an effective treatment for
      OSA, however, long term use has shown to lead to changes in teeth positioning and jaw
      alignment (bite changes), which has resulted in some patients stopping treatment.

      It is becoming common clinical practice for doctors to prescribe the use of repositioning
      splints to help reduce the bite changes associated with using OAM. However, this has not been
      studied in a clinical trial.

      This study will compare the bite changes between patients using OAM alone against patients
      using a morning repositioning splint in addition to OAM. Other variables, such as oral
      health, the size of mandibular advancement, and treatment adherence will also be measured to
      determine if they have an effect on the bite changes associated with OAM use.

      By understanding the key the factors that influence the bite changes associated with OAM use
      and potentially validating a technique to reduce these changes, this study will improve the
      clinical practice of Dental Sleep Medicine, leading to improved health outcomes for OSA
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Mandibular advancement oral appliances (OAM) are an effective treatment for obstructive sleep
      apnea (OSA). However, prolonged OAM treatment leads to significant changes in occlusion for
      the majority of patients. As such it is not uncommon to find changes in occlusion and the
      resulting decrease in quality of life in long-term users of oral appliances to be cited as a
      reason for discontinuing OAM treatment. Understanding the determinants of occlusal changes
      and clinical strategies to minimize or prevent them are essential to the practice of Dental
      Sleep Medicine, where treatment success is predicated on high levels of adherence.

      Morning Repositioners or alternative oral appliances/splints that counteract the muscle
      splinting of the mandible in a forward postured position have been advocated by some
      practitioners as a means of minimizing the occlusal changes associated with OAM treatment.
      However, this has not been studied in a prospective clinical trial.

      The proposed study is a single-blinded prospective randomized controlled trial at three
      clinical centers, with the specific aim of assessing the effectiveness of mandibular
      repositioning splint use on minimizing the occlusal changes associated with OAM treatment.
      Secondary aims include also determining the effects of periodontal disease, treatment
      adherence, and magnitude of mandibular advancement on occlusal changes associated with OAM
      treatment.

      90 OSA patients will receive OAM treatment following standard practices. A titration period
      of two months will be used to adjust the position of mandibular advancement for each patient,
      which will involve clinical follow-up visits at a minimum of 1 week, 1 month and 2 months
      after initiation of OAM treatment. Each participant will be randomly assigned to either the
      treatment or control group. The treatment group will receive a mandibular repositioning
      splint to wear for a minimum of 1 hour in the mornings following removal of OAM. A positive
      control group will receive no additional splint, and but will be managed using standard
      practices, including jaw stretching exercises as needed. A second negative control group
      consisting of 15 healthy adults not undergoing any oral appliance treatment will also be
      included.

      Prior to receiving treatment, participants will undergo a baseline assessment where
      demographic, anthropometric, and specific periodontal health data will be collected. All
      measurements will be repeated at a minimum of 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion,
      with routine follow-up appointments and adherence data collected every six months.

      To directly address the primary aim of this study, occlusal variables will be measured by a
      combination of methods including analysis of digitized dental models, cephalometric analysis
      and intra-oral radiography bone level measurements. Secondary outcome variables to assess the
      effectiveness of morning mandibular repositioning splint therapy will include average OAM
      adherence (hours/night), quality of life (Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire, FOSQ),
      and change in mandibular incisor root length and attachment loss. Adherence will be measured
      by compliance monitors embedded in the oral appliance and mandibular repositioning splints.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Analysis of primary outcomes will be performed by an examiner blinded to group allocation.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Overjet</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>The change in the extent of horizontal (anterior-posterior) overlap of the maxillary central incisors over the mandibular central incisors, measured from digital dental model analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected every 6 months after treatment commencement, up to 36 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence will be measured by the DentiTrac smart chip (Braebon Medical Corporation, Kanata, Canada) embedded in the oral appliance and mandibular repositioning splints. The adherence will be measured in hours per night and nights per week.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life using Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ-10)</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 1, 2, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>FOSQ-10 measures functional status and difficulty in performing everyday activities via 10 questions. The range of scores for any question is from 1 to 4. There is also a 0 score option for participants who do not engage in a particular activity for other reasons, in which case the question will be excluded. There are 5 subscales that measure: general productivity, activity level, vigilance, social outcomes, and intimacy and sexual relationships. To obtain the total score, a mean-weighted item score is computed for those subscales with more than one item. To calculate a mean-weighted item score calculate the mean of the answered items with responses &gt; 1 for each subscale. The total score is then derived by calculating the mean of the subscale scores and multiplying that mean by five. Total score ranges between 5 and 20. Higher scores indicate better functional status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daytime Sleepiness</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 1, 2, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of OSA specific fatigue using Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) questionnaire. ESS measures daytime sleepiness via 8 questions that ask about daytime sleepiness during common everyday conditions. The potential range of scores for any questions is from 0 to 3. Higher values represent worse outcomes. Their are no subscales for ESS. The answers to the questions are all summed up. Total score ranges between 0 and 24. A score above 10 indicates daytime sleepiness with higher scores indicating more sleepiness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Overbite</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>Using digital dental model analysis to evaluate the change in the extent of vertical (superior-inferior) overlap of the maxillary central incisors over the mandibular central incisors, measured relative to the incisal edges.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dental Crowding</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in dental crowding, measured by digital dental model analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intermolar Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in distance between molars, measured by digital dental model analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intercanine Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in distance between canines, measured by digital dental model analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Posterior Occlusal Changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the number of posterior teeth with open occlusal contacts, measured from digital dental model analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anterior Occlusal Changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected at 0, 18 and 36 months after appliance insertion.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the number of anterior teeth in crossbite, measured from digital dental model analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment group will will be treated a mandibular advancement oral appliance following standard practices. The treatment group will also receive a mandibular repositioning splint to wear in the mornings for a minimum of 1 hour following removal of their mandibular advancement oral appliance, in an effort to reduce the side effects resulting from use of the mandibular advancement oral appliance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Positive Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The positive control group will will be treated a mandibular advancement oral appliance following standard practices. The positive control group will not receive any additional oral appliances. Side effects resulting from use of the mandibular advancement oral appliance will be managed using standard practices, including jaw stretching exercises as needed for comfort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Negative Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The negative control group is comprised of 15 healthy individuals recruited specifically from faculty members at the UBC Faculty of Dentistry. This group will undergo the same clinical data collection as the treatment group and the negative control group but will not receive any treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mandibular Repositioning Splint</intervention_name>
    <description>The Morning Repositioner is a hands-free bite deprogrammer designed to help return the patient's jaw back to its pre-treatment centric position.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Morning Repositioner</other_name>
    <other_name>Morning Aligner</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mandibular Advancement Oral Appliance</intervention_name>
    <description>Mandibular Advancement Oral Appliances are dental splints used to keep the jaw in an advanced position, opening the upper airway during sleep.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Positive Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>OAM</other_name>
    <other_name>MAS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment naive (have never used an oral appliance as treatment for OSA);

          -  Age 25 - 65 years old, who are able to freely provide informed consent;

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) ≤ 35;

          -  8 or more teeth per arch to support treatment with OAM;

          -  Apnea-Hypopnea Index (AHI) within the range 5≤AHI≤50 documented with polysomnography
             in the last 2 years ***OR***

          -  Respiratory Disturbance Index (RDI) within the range 20 ≤ RDI ≤ 50 documented with
             level III portable sleep test ***OR***

          -  Oxygen Desaturation Index (ODI) ≥ 10

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Extensive periodontal disease with significant tooth mobility;

          -  Inability to protrude jaw;

          -  Insufficient vertical opening to accommodate treatment with OAM;

          -  Pregnancy (if a participant becomes pregnant during the trial, the participant will be
             withdrawn from the study).

          -  Uncontrolled congestive heart failure (defined as a prior clinical diagnosis, an
             ejection cut-off of 40% or clinical sign in the opinion of a primary care physician or
             cardiologist) that makes it unsafe in the opinion of the investigators for the subject
             to participate in the trial;

          -  Coronary artery disease unless stable for at least 6 months and considered by the
             investigators to have a stable disease;

          -  Any history of angina, myocardial infarction or stroke;

          -  Any history of major depressive disorder along with current moderate-severe disease;

          -  Active cancer management (unless in remission for more than 1 year);

          -  Known renal failure (with need for dialysis)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Benjamin T Pliska, DDS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Benjamin T Pliska, DDS</last_name>
    <phone>604-822-7237</phone>
    <email>pliska@dentistry.ubc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of British Columbia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6T 1Z3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Benjamin T Pliska, DDS</last_name>
      <phone>604-822-7237</phone>
      <email>pliska@dentistry.ubc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eleanor F Cawthorne, BSc</last_name>
      <phone>604-827-0690</phone>
      <email>ecawthorne@dentistry.ubc.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Benjamin T Pliska, DDS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Benjamin Pliska</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>OSA</keyword>
  <keyword>Mandibular Advancement Splint</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Appliance</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Repositioning Splint</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

