<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03343275</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DEV-LCD-02-17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03343275</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combined Use of a Medical Device and a Dietary Complement in Patient Urinary pH Control in Patients With an Implanted Double J Catheter.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicenter, Controlled and Randomized Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Combined Use of a Medical Device and a Food Supplement in the Control of Urinary pH in Patients With an Implanted Double Pigtail Catheter</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Devicare S.L.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clever Instruments S.L.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Devicare S.L.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effectivity in urinary pH Control and the prevention of
      calcification in Double J catheter using a device combined with the intake of dietary
      supplements. Every patient will receive hygienic-dietary indications.

      Patients will also take one out of the three dietary supplements regarded within the study
      (pH Up, pH Down and Cysteine) to control the adequate pH level, always following medical
      indications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Several studies have shown the importance of urinary pH Control (pHv) to determine the
      frequency of catheter incrustation, this measure being a variable to be taken into account in
      the management of catheterized patients. However, the level of pHv is influenced by multiple
      factors, so its routine control is difficult to interpret. The nucleation pH (pHn) was
      described on 1999: the pH where the incrustation starts to form. In his study he observed
      that the pH of the patients who developed a catheter blockage and the pH of those who were
      not very similar (7.46 and 7.38 respectively), but observed that the pHv of the patients who
      did not have incrustations was much lower and therefore had a much wider safety margin.

      As already mentioned, pHv is influenced by different factors, but it is especially sensitive
      to diet. For this reason, hygienic and dietetic interventions (exercise, diet, fluid intake,
      etc.) are one of the preventive measures of incrustation of the catheter of great utility,
      although its effectiveness is subject to patient adherence.

      Lit-control®pH Down is a dietary supplement with an acidifying effect on urine, which helps
      in the prevention of complications arising from the alkalinization of urine. It contains
      L-methionine, phytin (calcium-magnesium phytate salt), zinc and vitamin A. The two active
      components in pHv acidification are L-methionine and phytin,while zinc and vitamin A increase
      the action of phytin. Specifically, zinc favors the affinity of its affinity for calcium
      phosphate and vitamin A prevents its degradation by alkaline phosphatase.

      L-methionine is an essential amino acid that plays an important role in metabolic processes.
      It is normally acquired through food and absorbed in the small intestine to be metabolized in
      the liver via cysteine to sulphate and protons. Consequently, its administration produces a
      significant reduction of urinary pH.

      According to the European Association of Urology (UAE), urinary acidification with
      L-methionine up to pH 5.8 - 6.2 is recommended as a therapeutic measure for calculations of
      struvite, calcium phosphate and ammonium urate at doses of 600- 1500 mg / day. This
      recommendation is based on the results observed in 1996, where an acidification of the pH of
      the urine of the patients was observed from 7.5 to 5.5 after the administration of 1500-3000
      mg / day (3-6 capsules) of 500mg / day. Also in the study of Hesse 1999 a significant
      reduction in urinary pH was observed up to pH = 6.0 after the administration of a single dose
      of 1500 mg of L-methionine, maintaining this effect for 24h. In addition, a significant
      reduction was observed versus the control group in terms of the relative supersaturation for
      struvite and brushite in the urine of 24h. In another more recent study, the authors studied
      the circadian course of urinary pH after the administration of 1500 mg of L-methionine. They
      observed a strong decrease in urinary pH up to 2h after the administration of the amino acid
      that remained at significantly low levels for 8h, resulting in a pH level for 24h between
      5.98 and 6.32. Therefore, in order to guarantee therapeutic doses of L-Methionine (1500mg /
      day), the Lit-control®pH Down regimen to follow would be equivalent to 3 capsules per day
      (500 mg / capsule).

      On the other hand, the device Lit-control® pH Meter is a medical device that allows patients
      to self-monitor their pHv daily in their own home, allowing a thorough control of the pH and
      the level of risk of incrustation. The device has been validated for use in lithiasic
      patients, with applicability in the treatment of other urological pathologies related to the
      acid-base balance of urine, calcifications of urinary catheters, cystitis, urinary tract
      infections, painful bladder syndrome and bladder hyperactive

      The objective of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of the food supplement
      Lit-control®pH Down in the prevention of double J catheter incrustation and in the control of
      urinary pH together with the use of the device Lit-control® pH meter
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Adults attending urology/nephrology consultation whom have been recently implanted a double J cathether or have its implantation programmed and are able of taking care in urinary pH self-control.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incrustation Score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>0 (No incrustation); 1(Sporadic incrustation less than 1-2 mm); 2 (Wide area calcifications more than 1-2 mm) ; 3 (Total obstruction)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary pH level</measure>
    <time_frame>2 times/day</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Catheter implant cause</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Medical evaluation and diagnosis leading to catheter implant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-control below values 6.2</measure>
    <time_frame>2 times/day</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anatomic alterations on the urinary system</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Medical evaluation on the different alterations present in the urinary system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Previous uropathic obstructive incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of obstructions in the past two months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Date of past catheter implants</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pH control: Total time</measure>
    <time_frame>2 times/day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2 hours urine analysis :Fasting</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine culture</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications associated with catheter implant</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>The clinical will evaluate the patient treatment adherence by means of Morisky-Green test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Catheter extraction data</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Possibility of complications during the extraction, date of extraction, intervention type, intervention duration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blockage risk factor</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month prior intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation by clinical evaluation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Date of catheter extraction</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of previous catheter</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Description of the previous catheter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of different symptoms associated with the previous catheterization</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Different symptomatology associated with the previous catheterization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Catheter Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dietary supplement : Lit-Control® pH Down
Pharmaceutical form: capsules
Administration : oral
Dose: 3 capsules/day.
• Sanitary product : Lit-Control® pH Meter
In vitro diagnosis sanitary product
Use:Urinary pH evaluation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo:
Pharmaceutical form: capsules
Administration : oral
Dose: 3 capsules/day.
• Sanitary product : Lit-Control® pH Meter
In vitro diagnosis sanitary product
Use:Urinary pH evaluation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lit control pHDown</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients within the experimental arm will receive dietary supplement Lit-control®pH Down to help them keep their urinary pH in the adequate levels, being these considered as the preventive ones to avoid catheter calcification (pH&lt;6.2) being the 3 capsule per day indication. On the other hand, the control arm will receive a placebo product with similar organoleptic qualities and the same posology characteristics. Both arms wil use Lit-Control® pH Meter device to keep self- control of the urinary pH; also, both will receive the same hygienic-dietary indications about the care of the catheter.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥18 years old

          -  Patients which have been recently implanted a Double J catheter (less than a week
             implant) or who have planned their implant and have been recommended with pH control
             to avoid incrustation/calcification.

          -  Patients who accept their participation in the study and give their informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with base pathologies wich , based on clinical criteria, aren´t sensitive
             about the study dietary supplement indications.

          -  Patients which have programmed the catheter extraction 3 weeks before base visit.

          -  Uric and cystinuric patients which requires pH control different from the established
             study protocol .
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Valme</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <state>Andalucía</state>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hospitalet De Llobregat</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Santiago de Compostela</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago de compostela</city>
        <state>Galicia</state>
        <zip>15706</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Álvaro Cunqueiro</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vigo</city>
        <state>Pontevedra</state>
        <zip>36312</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fundació Puigvert</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08025</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico Universitario San Cecilio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Granada</city>
        <zip>18012</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario La Paz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28046</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari i Politècnic La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46026</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Rio Hortega</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valladolid</city>
        <zip>47012</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Catheter, incrustation, pH Control</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

