<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03342378</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UW17078</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA014520</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-1010</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P50DE026787</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03342378</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PET-MRI Assessment of Early Tumor Response to Predict Outcomes of HPV-Positive Oropharynx Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>PET-MRI Assessment of Early Tumor Response to Predict Outcomes of HPV-Positive Oropharynx Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This proposal explores the novel hypothesis that the variability in outcomes within the
      Intermediate Risk(IR) HPV-positive Oropharynx Squamous Cell Carcinoma(OPSCC) cohort can be
      exploited to identify a subpopulation that exhibits outcomes similar to Low Risk (LR)
      HPV-positive Oropharynx Squamous Cell Carcinoma and therefore would be appropriate candidates
      for radiation dose de-escalation approaches. Current literature using PET, CT, and MRI as
      single imaging modalities have identified certain criteria within heterogenous patient
      populations that are associated with clinical outcomes. Here, the investigators will test the
      hypothesis that multiparametric analysis of simultaneously-acquired MRI and PET quantitative
      imaging biomarker data from the primary tumor prior to initiating therapy, after 2 weeks of
      chemoradiation(CRT), and 3 months following completion of chemoradiation in patients with
      Intermediate Risk HPV-positive Oropharynx Squamous Cell Carcinoma will generate parametric
      maps that are predictive of clinical outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine if the primary tumor response in patients with IR HPV-positive</measure>
    <time_frame>Following 2-weeks of CRT</time_frame>
    <description>OPSCC following 2 weeks of CRT is predictive of clinical outcomes.
The primary endpoint of Aim 1 is absolute volumetric change of the primary tumor between pre-treatment and following 2-weeks of CRT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To define the difference of the primary tumor response in patients with LR HPV-positive OPSCC and HPV-negative OPSCC following 2 weeks of CRT.</measure>
    <time_frame>Following 2-weeks of CRT</time_frame>
    <description>The hypothesis suggests that there will be a more pronounced decrease in volume of the primary tumor following 2-weeks of CRT for LR HPV-positive OPSCC (most favorable prognosis) compared to HPV-negative OPSCC (least favorable prognosis).
We will use one-sided two-sample unequal-variance t-tests to determine if there is difference in mean volumetric changes in LR HPV-positive and HPV-negative groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Oropharynx Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oropharynx Cancer Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with OPSCC will be treated with comprehensive head and neck RT to 70 Gy in 33 fractions with concurrent weekly cisplatin at 40 mg/m2 and at the University of Wisconsin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensity modulated radiotherapy (IMRT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Intensity modulated radiotherapy (IMRT) will be delivered over 6.5 weeks in 33 daily fractions. Treatments will be initiated on Monday or Tuesday. Missed treatments will be compensated for by delivering an additional BID treatment during the week given at least 6 hours apart OR treating on the Saturday of that week, OR adding to the end of treatment. Gross disease will receive 70 Gy in 2.12 Gy fractions, areas at high-risk for subclinical disease will receive 60 Gy in 1.82 Gy fractions, and areas at low-risk for harboring subclinical disease will receive 56 Gy in 1.70 Gy fractions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oropharynx Cancer Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chemotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Eligible patients will receive cisplatin 40 mg/m2 intravenous in 1000 mL of normal saline 0.9% over 60-90 minutes weekly in combination with radiation therapy for treatment of their cancer. Dose modifications and supportive measures will be done according to current standards of care at the University of Wisconsin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oropharynx Cancer Patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cisplatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PET-MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>All imaging data will be acquired using a 3.0T PET-MRI scanner with a standard bore size of 60 cm. Patients will be placed in standard non-ferrous head and neck immobilization devices during PET-MRI to simulate their anticipated positioning during subsequent CT simulation and treatment. A head and neck PET-MRI study will be performed with scan sequences tailored for the site of interest. The PET-MRI exam will take approximately 60 minutes to complete.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oropharynx Cancer Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with OPSCC will be enrolled on an institutional review board approved clinical
        trial and treated with comprehensive head and neck RT to 70 Gy in 33 fractions with
        concurrent weekly cisplatin at 40 mg/m2 and at the University of Wisconsin.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically- or cytologically-proven diagnosis of squamous cell carcinoma
             (including papillary squamous cell carcinoma and basaloid squamous cell carcinoma
             variants) of the oropharynx (tonsil or base of tongue)

          -  III-IVB (T3N0, T1-3N1, T4aN0-3, T4bN0-3, T1-4N2, T1-4N3) (AJCC 8th edition) based upon
             the following minimum diagnostic workup:

               -  General history and physical examination (including nasolarygopharyngoscopy or
                  indirect mirror exam) by a radiation oncologist or medical oncologist or ENT head
                  and neck surgeon within 8 weeks prior to registration.

               -  Diagnostic CT of the neck with IV contrast

               -  Chest imaging

               -  CXR or CT chest without contrast

          -  Patient must not have any contraindications to undergoing a 3.0T PET-MRI

          -  Zubrod Performance Status 0-1 within 2 weeks prior to registration.

          -  Required labs:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500 cells/mm3.

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000 cells/mm3.

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 8.0 g/dl; Note: The use of transfusion or other intervention to
                  achieve Hgb ≥ 8.0 g/dl is acceptable, but not within 2 weeks of start of
                  treatment.

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 2 mg/dl within 2 weeks prior to registration.

               -  AST or ALT ≤ 3 x the upper limit of normal within 2 weeks prior to registration.

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dl within 2 weeks prior to registration or creatinine
                  clearance (CCr) ≥ 50 ml/min within 2 weeks prior to registration determined by
                  24-hour collection or estimated by Cockcroft-Gault formula:

               -  CCr male = [(140 - age) x (weight in kg)]/[(Serum Cr mg/dl) x (72)]

               -  CCr female = 0.85 x (CCr male)

               -  Patient must be deemed able to receive weekly cisplatin chemotherapy

               -  Smoking history defined by pack-years (calculated by multiplying the number of
                  packs of cigarettes smoked per day by the number of years the person has smoked).

               -  Negative serum pregnancy test within 2 weeks prior to registration for women of
                  childbearing potential.

               -  Patient must provide study specific informed consent prior to study entry.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cancers considered to be from an oral cavity, nasopharynx, hypopharynx, larynx, and
             oropharynx primaries confined entire to the soft palate and posterior oropharyngeal
             wall even if p16 positive, are excluded. Carcinoma of the neck of unknown primary site
             origin (even if p16 positive) are excluded. Patients with a primary tumor not able to
             be defined by PET-MRI are excluded.

          -  Distant metastasis or adenopathy below the clavicles.

          -  Gross total excision of the primary tumor with or without nodal dissection.

          -  Prior invasive malignancy (except non-melanomatous skin cancer) unless disease free
             for a minimum of 3 years. (For example, carcinoma of the breast, colon or cervix are
             all permissible if patients are disease free for ≥ 3 years.)

          -  Prior radiotherapy to the head and neck region that would result in overlap of
             radiation therapy fields.

          -  Severe, active co-morbidity, defined as follows:

               -  Unstable angina and/or congestive heart failure requiring hospitalization within
                  the last 6 months.

               -  Transmural myocardial infarction within the last 6 months

               -  Acute bacterial or fungal infection requiring intravenous antibiotics at the time
                  of registration.

               -  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease exacerbation or other respiratory illness
                  requiring hospitalization or precluding study therapy within 30 days of
                  registration.

               -  Pregnancy or women of childbearing potential and men who are sexually active and
                  not willing/able to use medically acceptable forms of contraception; this
                  exclusion is necessary because the treatment involved in this study may be
                  significantly teratogenic.

               -  Patients who are unfit for cisplatin chemotherapy due to concomitant conditions,
                  including but not limited to significant peripheral neuropathy, worsening renal
                  function, hearing loss, or other toxicities that prevents treatment with
                  cisplatin chemotherapy.

          -  Presence of passive and/or active devices that are not compatible with the 3.0T PET/MR
             scanner environment. Any person with the following will be excluded: cardiac
             pacemaker, metal fragments in or around the eye, venous umbrella, permanent eyeliner
             or permanent artificial eyebrows. Patents with the following potentially non-MRI
             compatible devices will undergo screening using the standard UWHC MRI screening
             protocol by trained UWHC personnel: cardiac pacemaker, heart valve replacement,
             intracranial aneurysm clips, middle ear, eye, joint, or penile implants, joint
             replacements, implantable hearing aids, neurostimulator devices, insulin pumps,
             shunts/stents, metal mesh/coil implants; metal plate/pin/screws/wires, or any other
             metallic implants. Also, patients with anatomical constraints limiting the feasibility
             of MRI will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew E Witek, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cancer Connect</last_name>
    <phone>800-622-8922</phone>
    <email>cancerconnect@uwcarbone.wisc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Carbone Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cancer Connect</last_name>
      <phone>800-622-8922</phone>
      <email>cancerconnect@uwcarbone.wisc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew E Witek, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.wisc.edu/</url>
    <description>UW Carbone Cancer Center Homepage</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HPV</keyword>
  <keyword>HPV-positive</keyword>
  <keyword>Oropharynx Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oropharyngeal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

