<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03538730</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB17-1794</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03538730</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pain After Tonsillectomy Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>PAT</acronym>
  <official_title>Pain After Tonsillectomy Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Calgary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pain is a common experience in childhood. Healthy children can undergo up to 20 painful
      procedures by the age of 5. Moreover, millions of children undergo surgery (e.g.,
      tonsillectomies) each year, which is commonly linked to pain and distress. Pain from, and
      fear of, medical experiences are not short lasting. Indeed, they can influence children long
      after the painful situation is over. Children's memories of pain after surgery can affect
      painful experiences in the future. Negative memories of pain (when children remember more
      pain than the actual level of pain experienced) are linked to higher pain and distress. As
      well, children who are more anxious and who experience greater pain are more likely to
      develop negatively biased pain memories, which then leads to greater fear and pain at
      subsequent pain experiences. It has been suggested that the ways in which parents and
      children talk about pain following painful events is important for how children remember the
      pain.

      This study will be one of the first to look at whether a parent-led memory reframing
      intervention can reduce children's negative memories of surgery.

      The study will include 100 children scheduled for a tonsillectomy and one of their parents.
      They will be recruited from the Alberta Children's Hospital. Parents will complete a survey
      1-3 weeks before their child's surgery, and then the child's pain and anxiety will be
      monitored on the day of surgery and for 2 weeks after surgery. Two weeks after surgery, the
      parent and child will come to the hospital and be assigned to a control group or a memory
      reframing session. Six weeks after surgery, parents and children will complete a telephone
      interview.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Pain is a common experience in childhood. Healthy children who are compliant with medical
      care undergo up to 20 painful procedures by the age of 5. Moreover, millions of children
      undergo surgery (e.g., tonsillectomies) each year, which is commonly linked to pain and
      distress. Pain from, and fear of, medical experiences are neither short lasting or benign and
      can influence children long after the painful stimulus is removed. Children's memories of
      needle-related, experimental, post-surgical, and procedural pain are a powerful predictor of
      future pain experiences, and can be more influential to future pain than the initial pain
      itself. Memory is susceptible to distortion. Negative biases in pain memories (i.e., recalled
      pain is higher than initial pain report) are associated with higher subsequent pain,
      distress, and worse medical compliance. Empirical and theoretical work has implicated several
      factors in the development of negatively biased pain memories in children. Children who are
      more anxious and who experience greater pain are more likely to develop negatively biased
      pain memories, which then leads to greater fear and pain at subsequent pain experiences.
      Parents and adolescents who think more catastrophically about child pain prior to surgery
      tend to develop more negatively biased pain memories months later. In fact, parents'
      catastrophic thinking about child pain was found to be the most important predictor of
      children's memory biases and subsequent pain trajectories. It has been suggested that
      parental and child anxiety lead to memory biases due to the ways in which parents and
      children discuss pain following painful events (e.g., by emphasizing threatening aspects of
      the experience).

      We recently published a conceptual developmental framework in the journal PAIN outlining
      cognitive and social factors that may influence children's pain memory development. Of
      particular importance is early childhood (ages 4-7 years) when children are most liable to
      memory biases due to suggestibility effects. It is also during this time that parents are
      most influential in shaping children's cognitions, emotions, and behaviors. Our model posits
      that the socio-linguistic context (e.g. parent-child narratives about pain) in which pain
      memories develop is most important in early childhood and sets the stage for future pain
      experiences.

      There have been few studies examining memory reframing interventions in the context of
      children's recall of (needle) pain. In our recent systematic review, existing trials of
      memory reframing interventions were found to be efficacious in reducing negative memory
      biases. Parent-child reminiscing about past negative events plays a powerful role in how
      autobiographical memories of those events are subsequently retrieved and reframed.
      Parent-child narrative style also influences children's coping and psychological functioning.
      Young children whose parents are topic-extending and elaborative (e.g., who ask open-ended
      questions to pull for more detailed accounts of the past) and who use emotional language, are
      more accurate and detailed in recalling their pasts, which is adaptive.

      Recent data from our lab provides evidence that parents who reminisce with their children
      about surgery using a particular style (e.g., more elaborative, less topic-switching) and
      content (e.g., less content about pain, fear, medical procedures; more explanations) have
      children who later remember post-surgical pain in a more accurate or positively biased way.
      Parental reminiscing style and content have been effectively targeted in interventions to
      improve children's memory development. However, negatively biased memories of post-surgical
      pain, which can lead to persistent pain problems, have not been targeted, despite a relative
      dearth of, and need for, interventions for this pediatric population. Moreover, existing
      memory reframing interventions did not employ parents, who play a critical role in children's
      pain memory formation and are underutilized intervention agents. Parents are potentially the
      most powerful and accessible intervention agents, and our recent data provides strong
      evidence that the language parents use when reminiscing with children following
      tonsillectomies influences children's pain memory biases.

      The aim of the proposed research study is to conduct a pilot study to examine the preliminary
      efficacy, feasibility, and acceptability of a brief parent-led memory reframing intervention
      following pediatric surgery to foster more adaptive (i.e., less negatively biased) pain
      memories. The intervention will draw from our recent data and extant memory reframing and
      narrative-based intervention techniques and teach parents more adaptive styles of reminiscing
      with their children about a past surgery. We will accomplish our aims by extending our
      existing program of research on post-surgical pain memory development of children (aged 4-7
      years), randomly assigning parents to receive a memory reframing intervention or attention
      control following surgery, and subsequently assessing children's memories for pain. This
      study will be the first to develop and pilot test a brief, parent-led intervention aimed at
      changing the way children recall their pain after surgery. Given the vital role of pain
      memories in shaping future pain experiences and the need for interventions in the pediatric
      surgery context, this study has great potential to contribute an accessible and feasible
      post-surgical pediatric pain management intervention and foster more adaptive pain
      trajectories and medical experiences in childhood.

      Study aims:

      Primary Aim: To examine the preliminary efficacy, feasibility, and acceptability of a
      parent-led memory reframing intervention on children's post-surgical pain memories.
      Hypothesis 1: Children in the intervention group will go on to recall post-surgical pain in a
      more accurate or positively biased way as compared to the control group who will remember
      pain in a more negatively biased way. The intervention will be judged by parents to be
      feasible and acceptable.

      Secondary Aim: To examine the influence of baseline individual child and parent
      characteristics on children's pain memories. Hypothesis 2: Children who are more anxious,
      less self-efficacious, have worse sleep quality, and whose parents are more anxious and
      catastrophize more about child pain prior to surgery will subsequently remember pain in a
      more negatively biased way.

      Methods:

      Sample:

      One hundred children (50 intervention, 50 control) between the ages of 4-7 years and one of
      their parents will be recruited from the Ear Nose and Throat (ENT) Clinic at Alberta
      Children's Hospital. A child will be eligible to participate if he/she 1.) is between 4 and 7
      years old at the time of recruitment; 2.) is scheduled for an elective outpatient
      tonsillectomy (with or without adenoidectomy); 3.) is able to understand and speak English
      4.) has at least one of his/her parents/caregivers consent to participating in the study and
      this caregiver is able to speak and read English. Exclusion criteria include: 1) receiving
      pre-medication with anxiolytics (Midazolam; administered to &lt; 5% of youth), as it might
      interfere with child's preoperative anxiety and memory formation; 2) serious medical
      co-morbidities (American Society of Anesthesiologists [ASA] ≥ III physical status) that would
      interfere with standardized protocols of analgesic administration and surgical technique; 3)
      developmental disabilities or speech/language delays, as it may make it difficult for the
      participants to complete all necessary study tasks (e.g., assent, narrative task, memory
      interview).

      Procedure:

      Patients will be identified through surgery schedule lists. At entry into the clinic, a
      member of the ENT Clinic will provide potentially eligible patients with information about
      the study. Parents provide permission to be contacted by the research team. A few weeks
      before surgery, a member of the research team will conduct a recruitment phone call with all
      eligible patients' parents to discuss the study. After the recruitment phone call, online
      consent forms will be emailed to interested participants. Parents will provide consent for
      the child's participation; children, who are 7 years old or over or turn 7 during the course
      of participation in the study, will provide assent. One week before surgery, parents will
      complete measures of parent catastrophizing about child pain (PCS-P), child language (CCC2),
      and child sleep (SDSC). For descriptive purposes, parents will report on socio-demographics
      (e.g., child age, household income), preparation that they/their child received about the
      surgery and what this entailed (e.g., coping skills), and family history of tonsillectomies
      and surgeries. On the day of surgery, measures of parental state anxiety (STAI-S) will be
      obtained as well as children's levels of pain intensity (FPS-R) and pain-related fear (CFS).
      A trained observer will objectively assess preoperative child anxiety during anesthesia
      induction (mYPAS).

      As per standard clinical care: In Day Surgery, all patients will receive Tylenol 15 mg/kg
      orally pre-operatively, unless there is a specific contraindication. One parent may be
      present at anesthesia induction with their child. The child will receive an inhalational
      induction with sevoflurane, oxygen, and nitrous oxide. An intravenous will then be inserted,
      and the child will be maintained on either volatile anesthetic or total intravenous
      anesthetic (TIVA) for the procedure. During the procedure, all patients will receive
      dexamethasone 0.2 mg/kg IV, ondansetron 0.1 mg/kg IV, and morphine for analgesia. The child
      will then be extubated deep or awake at the end of the procedure and transferred to the
      Post-Anesthesia Care Unit (PACU). All of the ENT surgeons will use cautery to the tonsillar
      bed as their surgical technique for tonsillectomy with or without adenoidectomy. The patients
      will be recovered in the PACU. Whether or not to bring a parent or caregiver into the PACU
      will be at the discretion of the PACU nurse and the anesthesiologist. Information regarding
      the surgical technique used and analgesic and anesthetic agents administered on the day of
      surgery will be collected via medical chart review.

      A researcher will obtain ratings of child pain intensity and pain-related fear shortly
      following surgery. Parents will be given and instructed on how to administer these scales so
      that child-reports of pain can be captured at home. These scales and instructions will also
      be provided to parents via emailed survey links (REDCap). Consistent with previous studies,
      proxy and self-reports of child average and worst pain intensity and pain-related fear will
      be assessed on days 1, 2, 3, 7 and 14 post-surgery. Proxy-reports of child sleep (SDSC) will
      be assessed on day 14 post-surgery. Parents will also report on the use of analgesics at
      home. At 2-weeks post-surgery, parents and children will come to the PI's research lab at the
      Alberta Children's Hospital during which time they will be randomized into an intervention or
      control group. Randomization will be conducted by an external statistician using a computer
      random number generator. Allocation concealment will be achieved using sequentially numbered,
      opaque, and sealed envelopes. Group allocation will be revealed by a researcher at the outset
      of the lab visit.

      During the lab visit, parents in both groups will talk to a researcher for approximately 20
      minutes while another researcher plays with the child (e.g., coloring, playing toys) in a
      separate room.

      Control Group. Similar to previous narrative and memory interventions, parents in the control
      group will receive instructions from a researcher on how to engage in child-directed play.
      Importantly, they will not talk about pain or the past surgery experience. After this
      20-minute period, parents in the control group will be instructed to reminisce with their
      children about the in-hospital and post-surgery periods as they normally would.

      Intervention Group. Parents in the intervention group will receive instructions from a
      researcher about adaptive ways of reminiscing about the in-hospital and post-surgery periods.
      The intervention will draw from existing narrative-based interventions that have taught
      parents to reminisce with their children about past negative events in more elaborative and
      emotion-rich ways (e.g., using more open-ended questions, to follow up on children's answers
      by providing new details about the event, to talk more about emotions, and to praise
      children's answers). We will also include elements of past pain memory reframing
      interventions and findings from our recent data. Specifically, parents will be taught to
      reminisce with their children about the in-hospital and post-surgery periods by providing
      more explanations for events, using less utterances about pain, fear, and medical procedures,
      emphasizing positive aspects of the child's surgery memory (e.g., when they got a treat), and
      enhancing children's self-efficacy regarding their ability to cope with pain. Researchers
      will also provide suggestions for specific questions and remarks to make while reminiscing.
      Parents and researchers will engage in brief role-plays to solidify the techniques, which
      will be followed by researcher feedback. After this 20-minute period, parents in the
      intervention group will be instructed to reminisce with their children about the in-hospital
      and post-surgery periods using the intervention strategies.

      After parents and children have finished reminiscing, parents in both groups will be asked to
      complete a short survey similar to the one completed at baseline. Three to four weeks after
      surgery, children in both groups will complete a telephone pain memory interview to assess
      children's recall of the in-hospital and post-surgery periods. Then, parents in the
      intervention group will complete a brief semi-structured telephone interview to assess
      feasibility and acceptability of the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>At 2-weeks post-surgery, parent-child dyads will participate in a lab visit during which time they will be randomized into an intervention or control group. Randomization will be conducted by an external statistician using a computer random number generator. Allocation concealment will be achieved using sequentially numbered, opaque, and sealed envelopes.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Group allocation will be revealed to one investigator at the outset of the lab visit. Other investigators and participants will remain masked until the end of the memory interview. Outcome assessors will remain masked for the duration of the study.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Children will complete a pain memory interview via telephone where they will be asked to recall the in-hospital and post-surgery (i.e., while at home) time periods and complete the same pain intensity and pain-related fear scales based on their memories of those time periods. Biases in memory will be defined as the deviation in recalled and initial/experienced pain reports. Similar to our previous research, statistical models predicting pain memories will control for initial pain ratings that correspond to each memory question. Negatively biased pain memories will be defined as children who remember more pain and fear as compared to their initial pain reports. Positively biased pain memories will be defined as recalled pain that is less than initial pain reports. Accurate memories reflect no difference between recalled and experienced levels of pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child preoperative anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The 27-item Modified Yale Preoperative Anxiety Scale (mYPAS) will be used by two trained observers to assess anxiety prior to and during anesthesia induction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery, days 1, 2, 3, 7, and 14 post-surgery, 3-4 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>We will capture sensory and affective aspects of pain and pain-related fear. Pain intensity will be assessed using a well-validated single-item faces pain scale (Faces Pain Scale-Revised; FPS-R), with anchors 'no pain' (0) and 'very much pain' (10).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child pain-related fear</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery, days 1, 2, 3, 7, and 14 post-surgery, 3-4 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>We will capture sensory and affective aspects of pain and pain-related fear. Children's pain-related fear will be assessed using the Children's Fear Scale (CFS), with anchors 'not at all scared' (0) and 'most scared possible' (4).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week pre-surgery, 2 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will rate their pain-related self-efficacy regarding their child's post-surgical pain using a single item 100-mm visual analogue scale (VAS). Parents will be asked to rate how confident they are that they could decrease their child's post-surgical pain, with anchors 'no confidence' (0) to 'complete confidence' (100).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week pre-surgery, 2 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The psychometrically-sound 26-item Sleep Disturbance Scale for Children (SDSC) will be used to assess parental report of children's sleep quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child language and communication skills</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week pre-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The Children's Communications Checklist-2 (CCC-2) is a psychometrically-sound 70-item measure designed to assess communication skills in youth aged 4-16 years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week pre-surgery, day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will use the 40-item State-Trait Anxiety inventory (STAI) to assess their own state and trait anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent catastrophic thinking about child pain</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week pre-surgery, 2 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The Pain Catastrophizing Scale-Parent Version (PCS-P) is a 13-item self-report measure that assesses catastrophic thoughts and feelings that parents may have when their child experiences pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility will be assessed using study recruitment/enrollment statistics, completion of the study elements; and researchers' and parents' ratings of parents' motivation to learn, understanding of the intervention, and parent-child and parent-researcher rapport rated on 11-point Likert scales (0, 'not at all' to 10, 'very much').</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability and satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The parent-report 9-item Treatment Evaluation Inventory-Short Form (TEI-SF) will be used to assess parental acceptability and satisfaction with the intervention; however, items will be slightly modified to pertain to the memory reframing intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Semi-structured telephone interviews will be conducted to assess treatment satisfaction and elicit feedback.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-child narratives</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Narratives will be video-recorded, transcribed, broken down into utterances, and coded by two independent coders using established coding schemes derived from the child development literature on children's narratives and memories. Coders have been trained and will be masked to treatment condition. The following aspects of narratives will be coded: Reminiscing style/level of elaboration (elaboration vs. repetition) and content (e.g., references to pain, anxiety/fear, medical procedures, emotions, explanations). Proportions of narrative utterance type over the entire number of utterances used will be calculated. Based on previous research, the primary narrative codes for the analyses will be parent reminiscing style (elaboration), and content related to pain, anxiety, medical procedures, and explanations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical records review: Surgery technique</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Through the medical records review, we will gather information about the surgery technique (Tonsillectomy, with or without adenoidectomy; additional procedures performed).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical records review: parental presence at induction</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Through the medical records review, we will gather information about parental presence at induction (i.e., was a parent present? Yes/No).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical records review: anesthetic technique</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Through the medical records review, we will gather information about the anesthetic technique (maintenance with volatile or TIVA), intraoperative opioid administration, awake or deep extubation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical records review: duration of PACU stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Through the medical records review, we will gather information about duration of PACU stay (in minutes).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical records review: parental presence in PACU</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Through the medical records review, we will gather information about parental presence in PACU (i.e., was parent present in PACU? Yes/No).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical records review: analgesics in Day Surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Through the medical records review, we will gather information about analgesic administration in Day Surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical records review: overnight stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Through the medical records review, we will gather information about an overnight stay (i.e., did the child stay overnight after their surgery? Yes/No).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Analgesic consumption after discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 2, 3, 7, and 14 post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Analgesic administration (or absence thereof) will be recorded at home. The questions will include medicine type (including any specific remedies to reduce pain due to swallowing), dose, and number of times medicine was administered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Socio-demographics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week pre-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A brief socio-demographic form will be administered to assess: ethnic background, level of education, household income, and family composition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical history</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week pre-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A brief medical history form will be administered to assess: family surgical and medical history, and surgery preparation and knowledge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Attention Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Similar to previous narrative and memory interventions, parents in the control group will receive instructions from a researcher for 20 minutes on how to engage in child-directed play. Importantly, they will not talk about pain or the past surgery experience.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Memory Reframing Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents in the intervention group will spend 20 minutes with a researcher and receive instructions about adaptive ways of reminiscing about the in-hospital and post-surgery periods.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Memory Reframing</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention will draw from existing narrative-based interventions, past pain memory reframing interventions and findings from our recent data. Specifically, parents will be taught to reminisce with their children about the in-hospital and post-surgery periods by encouraging children to provide more explanations, using less utterances about pain, avoiding repetitions, emphasizing positive aspects of the child's surgery memory (e.g., when children used coping methods such as deep breathing, when they got a treat), and enhancing children's self-efficacy regarding their ability to cope with pain.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Memory Reframing Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Scheduled to undergo an elective outpatient tonsillectomy with or without
             adenoidectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children receiving pre-medication with anxiolytics (Midazolam; administered to &lt; 5% of
             youth),

          -  who have serious medical co-morbidities,

          -  and/or who have developmental disabilities or speech/language delays
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>7 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melanie Noel, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alberta Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T3B 6A8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Calgary</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Melanie Noel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

