<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03535649</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Vedolizumab-5045</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1208-5399</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03535649</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Assess Clinical Effectiveness and Safety of Vedolizumab Intravenous in Real World Clinical Practice in Ulcerative Colitis (UC) Korean Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Effectiveness and Safety of Vedolizumab Intravenous in Real World Clinical Practice in Ulcerative Colitis Korean Patients: a Multicenter Post-marketing Retrospective Observational Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the clinical effectiveness by the clinical response at
      6 weeks and the safety of vedolizumab intravenous in UC Korean participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a retrospective, non-interventional study of participants with moderate to severe UC.
      The study will review medical records of participants who have initiated medical treatment
      with vedolizumab intravenous during the defined eligibility period under routine clinical
      practice to provide the real world data on the effectiveness and safety of vedolizumab
      intravenous.

      The study will enroll approximately 100 participants. All participants will be enrolled in
      one observational group: Vedolizumab

      The retrospective data will be collected in the index period, that is the time between 01
      August 2017 and 30 June 2018, from the date of diagnosis of UC until the date when
      participant is enrolled into the study on Baseline or until the end of treatment or death of
      participants or lost-to-follow up.

      The multi-center trial will be conducted in Republic of Korea. The overall duration of study
      will be approximately 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Response at Week 6 Based on Partial Mayo Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical response based on Partial Mayo score is defined as a reduction of at least 3 points and a decrease of at least 30 percent (%) from the baseline score, with a decrease of at least 1 point on the rectal bleeding subscale, or an absolute rectal bleeding score of 0 or 1. Mayo score is an instrument designed to measure disease activity of UC. Partial Mayo score consists of 3 sub-scores: stool pattern, most severe rectal bleeding of the day, and global assessment by physician, each graded from 0 to 3 with higher scores indicating more severe disease. These scores are summed to give a total score range of 0 to 9; where higher score indicating more severe disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Adverse Events of Special Interest (AESIs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to approximately 12 months post-index date or end of treatment, lost to follow up or death, whichever came first</time_frame>
    <description>Index date is defined as the date when vedolizumab treatment was initiated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to approximately 12 months post-index date or end of treatment, lost to follow up or death, whichever came first</time_frame>
    <description>Index date is defined as the date when vedolizumab treatment was initiated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Pregnancy during the Study</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to approximately 12 months post-index date or end of treatment, lost to follow up or death, whichever came first</time_frame>
    <description>Index date is defined as the date when vedolizumab treatment was initiated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Response at Week 14 Based on Partial or Complete Mayo Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 14</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical response is defined as a reduction of at least 3 points and a decrease of at least 30% from the baseline score, with a decrease of at least 1 point on the rectal bleeding subscale, or an absolute rectal bleeding score of 0 or 1. Mayo score is an instrument designed to measure disease activity of UC. Complete Mayo score consists of 4 sub-scores: stool pattern, most severe rectal bleeding of the day, endoscopic findings and global assessment by physician, each graded from 0 to 3 with higher scores indicating more severe disease. These scores are summed to give a total score range of 0 to 12. Partial Mayo score consists of 3 sub-scores: stool pattern, most severe rectal bleeding of the day, and global assessment by physician, each graded from 0 to 3 with higher scores indicating more severe disease. These scores are summed to give a total score range of 0 to 9. Here, higher scores indicates more severe disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Remission at Weeks 6 and 14 Based on Complete Mayo Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 6 and 14</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical remission is defined as a complete Mayo score of less than or equal to (&lt;=) 2 with no sub-score greater than (&gt;) 1. Mayo score is an instrument designed to measure disease activity of UC. Complete Mayo score consists of 4 sub-scores: stool pattern, most severe rectal bleeding of the day, endoscopic findings and global assessment by physician, each graded from 0 to 3 with higher scores indicating more severe disease. These scores are summed to give a total score range of 0 to 12.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Effectiveness on Mucosal Healing at Weeks 6 and 14 Based on Mayo Endoscopic Sub-score</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 6 and 14</time_frame>
    <description>Mucosal healing is defined as Mayo endoscopic sub-score of 0 or 1 compared to baseline. Mayo score is an instrument designed to measure disease activity of UC. Endoscopic findings is a sub-score of complete Mayo score, which ranges from 0 to 3, with higher scores indicating more severe disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Colitis, Ulcerative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vedolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants diagnosed with moderate to severe active UC and having failed tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF alpha) antagonist therapy and who have initiated vedolizumab intravenous treatment between 01 August 2017 and 30 June 2018 from approximately 15 participating sites will be observed from the date of UC diagnosis until the date when participant is enrolled into the study or until the end of treatment or death of participants or lost-to-follow up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants diagnosed with moderate to severe UC, having failed TNF-alpha antagonist
        therapy and who have initiated treatment with vedolizumab intravenous between 01 August
        2017 and 30 June 2018.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1. Moderately to severely active UC and having failed TNF-alpha antagonist therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Was treated with vedolizumab intravenous outside of the locally approved label in
             Korea.

          2. Was enrolled in an Interventional Intestinal Bowel Disease clinical trial at time of
             using vedolizumab intravenous.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Takeda Study Registration Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>+1-877-825-3327</phone>
    <email>medicalinformation@tpna.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vedolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

