<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03531372</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ABO-NB-SEM-17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03531372</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mipolixin® Compared to Poliprotect® in Moderate Functional Dyspepsia and Heartburn.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Safety of Mipolixin® Compared to Poliprotect ® in the Relief of Symptoms of Moderate Functional Dyspepsia and Heartburn: A Randomized, Double-blind, Parallel Group,Non-inferiority Clinical Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Aboca Spa Societa' Agricola</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>La Sociedad Española de Médicos de Atención Primaria</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dynamic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Aboca Spa Societa' Agricola</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluation of the clinical efficacy of two medical devices, Mipolixin® and Poliprotect®, in
      improving the overall symptom severity of functional dyspesia and/or heartburn
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in overall symptom severity from baseline (day 0) to day 14 between the two study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 and Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the change in the score of a visual analog scale (VAS) (from &quot;no symptoms&quot; to &quot;overwhelming symptoms&quot;) used for evaluating overall symptom severity from baseline (day 0) to day 14 after treatment initiation, between the two study arms. A decrease in VAS score of at least 30% is considered as a clinically meaningful improvement, and therefore subjects achieving a decrease ≥30% in this scale will be considered as responders. The non-inferiority is considered demonstrated if the 95% confidence interval of the difference in the percentage of responders between both study arms lies within the non-inferior margin value defined of 20%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Responders from baseline to day 3 and day 7</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, Day 3 and Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of responder patients (VAS score decrease of at least 30%) on the basis of the mean change in the overall symptom severity assessed by the VAS score from baseline to day 3 and day 7 in both study arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-assessment severity of individual specific symtoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, Day 1, Day 3, Day 7 and Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison between Mipolixin® and Poliprotect® in the mean change of the score of the self-assessed severity of individual specific symtoms (bothersome postprandial fullness, bothersome early satiation, bothersome epigastric pain, bothersome epigastric burning, and bothersome heartburn) rated on a 100 mm VAS (from &quot;no symptoms&quot; to &quot;overwhelming symptoms&quot;) from baseline to 1 3, 7 and 14 days after treatment initiation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the score of GOS scale from baseline to day 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 and Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the score of GOS ( Global Overall Symptom) scale from baseline to day 14 in both study arms. A decrease in GOS score ≥2 is considered as a clinically meaningful improvement, and therefore subjects achieving a decrease in overall severity score ≥2 from baseline in this scale will be considered as responders.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of AEs during study treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and type of adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs) reported during study treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of AEs and clinical findings during study period</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will be assessed on the basis of all AEs experienced during study treatment and all observed and volunteered AEs and abnormal findings on physical examination, including vital signs throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction (treatment administration)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3, Day 7 and Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Patient level of satisfaction in terms of treatment administration/posology will be assessed by means of specific questions about patient level of satisfaction after the 2-week treatment period. The response will be scored on a 4-point Likert scale from 0 to 4, as follows: 1 = &quot;very satisfied&quot;, 2 = &quot;quite satisfied&quot;, 3 = &quot;somewhat satisfied&quot;, 4 = &quot;not satisfied&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction (taste)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3, Day 7 and Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Patient level of satisfaction in terms of chewable tablets taste will be assessed by means of specific questions about patient level of satisfaction after the 2-week treatment period. The response will be scored on a 4-point Likert scale from 0 to 4, as follows: 1 = &quot;very satisfied&quot;, 2 = &quot;quite satisfied&quot;, 3 = &quot;somewhat satisfied&quot;, 4 = &quot;not satisfied&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment compliance will be evaluated by performing the IP accountability. This data will be corroborated with the information recorded in the patient diary concerning the daily administered and missed doses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">158</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyspepsia</condition>
  <condition>Heartburn</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mipolixin®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mipolixin® (Advanced Natural Antacid - AdNA)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Poliprotect®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Poliprotect® (Neobianacid)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mipolixin®</intervention_name>
    <description>1.55g chewable tablet 5 times a day for 2 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mipolixin®</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Advanced Natural Antacid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Poliprotect®</intervention_name>
    <description>1.55 g chewable tablet 5 times a day for 2 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Poliprotect®</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Neobianacid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to provide informed consent, preferably in writing or, failing that, orally in
             front of a witness, before any study procedure is performed.

          -  Male and female patients aged 18 to 75 years old (inclusive).

          -  Patients with symptoms of functional dyspepsia (according to the Rome IV criteria) of
             moderate severity (VAS score between 30 mm and 70 mm) and/or bothersome heartburn
             within 2 and 14 days prior to the screening/baseline visit.

             o According to the current Rome IV diagnostic criteria, functional dyspepsia is
             defined as one or more of the following symptoms: postprandial fullness (classified as
             postprandial distress syndrome), early satiation (inability to finish a normal sized
             meal, also classified as postprandial distress syndrome), and epigastric pain or
             burning (classified as epigastric pain syndrome).

          -  Ability of the patients (according to the investigator's opinion) to comprehend the
             full nature and purpose of the study including possible risks and side effects.

          -  Patients who agree not to alter their diet in any way for the duration of the trial
             and to maintain it at steady state.

          -  Patients who agree not to make any major lifestyle changes during the trial.

          -  Willingness to comply with all the study procedures and schedule.

          -  Chronic therapies (if not related to the gastroenterological pathologies object of the
             study, according to the opinion of the investigator) are allowed, if the regimen is
             maintained stable during the whole study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Declines or unable to provide informed consent.

             - Disease or health condition

          -  Patient presenting at least one of the following symptoms or conditions at screening:
             anemia, chronic gastrointestinal bleeding, progressive unintentional weight loss,
             epigastric mass, anorexia, persistent or recurrent vomiting, dysphagia or odynophagia,
             porphyria, hypophosphatemia, and/or cachexia.

          -  Patients presenting with at least of the following gastrointestinal conditions at
             screening: erosive GERD, Barrett's oesophagus or oesophageal stricture, active or
             healing gastroduodenal ulcer (except scars), history of gastric, duodenal or
             esophageal surgery, symptomatic gallstone, and/or other gastrointestinal disease such
             as gastroenteritis, inflammatory bowel disease, celiac disease and/or colorectal
             cancer.

          -  Patients with known malignancy disease, infectious disease or severe heart or
             pulmonary disease.

          -  Patients with known severe liver or kidney disease (AST/SGOT, ALT/SGPT &gt;2 upper limits
             of normal, serum creatinine &gt;1.5 mg/dl).

          -  Patients with mental or metabolic disorders and any other disease that according to
             the physician can compromise the patient´s safety and/or patient´s study compliance.

             - Treatments

          -  Patients receiving any treatment (pharmacological or medical device) for heartburn or
             dyspeptic symptoms within the last 14 days prior to randomization.

          -  Patients receiving any drugs that could affect symptoms or study evaluation such
             antacids, PPIs, H2RAs, prokinetics, and/or gastric mucosal protectants at baseline
             and/or taken within the last 14 days prior to randomization.

          -  Patients receiving any drugs that could affect symptoms or the study as antibiotics,
             NSAIDs, anticholinergics and/or cholinergic agents.

        Note: Patients will be asked to avoid any drugs of the above mentioned since the beginning
        of the study (baseline visit) until the end of the study.

          -  Patients under triple therapy or eradication therapy against Helicobacter pylori.

          -  Patients planned for long-term new therapies with anti-anxiety agents,
             glucocorticosteroids and anti-inflammatory agents during study period.

          -  Known hypersensitive or intolerance to any components of the study medical devices.

          -  Previous intake of any of the study medical devices.

             - Other general conditions

          -  Patients who are unable to understand or are unwilling to sign an informed consent
             form.

          -  Unable or unwilling to complete all required screening and/or follow-up assessments.

          -  Unable to understand and complete self-administered scales/questionnaires planned to
             be used in the study.

          -  Participation in interventional research studies of investigational medicinal or
             device products (ongoing or terminated less than 30 days before screening)

          -  Patients with active alcohol or drug addiction or any other condition that, in the
             investigator's opinion, would interfere with their ability to comply with the study
             requirements.

          -  Patients with any concurrent condition that, in the investigator's opinion, would
             jeopardize the safety of the patient or compliance with the protocol.

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women;

          -  Women of childbearing potential and sexually active: they must be willing to use at
             least one acceptable effective contraceptive measure (- progestogen-only oral hormonal
             contraception, where inhibition of ovulation is not the primary mode of action , -
             male or female condom with or without spermicide, - cap, diaphragm or sponge with
             spermicide). Pregnancy test will be performed at screening and at the final/premature
             withdrawal visit. The use of contraception in male patients is not required.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Niccolò Ravenni, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>39 0575 746</phone>
    <phone_ext>711</phone_ext>
    <email>nravenni@aboca.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Albuñol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuñol</city>
        <zip>18700</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Antonio Miguel Martín Almendros, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Disset de Setembre</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Prat De Llobregat</city>
        <zip>08820</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francisco Marín Jiménez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Disset de Setembre</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Prat De Llobregat</city>
        <zip>08820</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patricia Lorenzo Nieto, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Disset de Setembre</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Prat De Llobregat</city>
        <zip>08820</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marta Poch Mora, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Disset de Setembre</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Prat De Llobregat</city>
        <zip>08820</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Antonia Leiva Pintado, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Disset de Setembre</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Prat De Llobregat</city>
        <zip>08820</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Susana Sostres Francàs, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Disset de Setembre</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Prat De Llobregat</city>
        <zip>08820</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anna Ramón Velasco, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Disset de Setembre</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Prat De Llobregat</city>
        <zip>08820</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rosaura Figueras Camós, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Montesa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Milagros González Béjar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Montesa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Pilar Javierre Miranda, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Goya</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amelia Maria González Gamarra, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Primary Care Centre Eloy Gonzalo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mercedes Martínez Abad, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Comillas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28019</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Manuel Frías Vargas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Baviera</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28028</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Teresa Sarriá Sánchez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Las Americas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parla</city>
        <zip>28981</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Blanca Sanz Pozo, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Las Americas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parla</city>
        <zip>28981</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Luis Enrique Morales Cobos, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Las Americas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parla</city>
        <zip>28981</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria del Prado García García-Alcañiz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS San Blas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parla</city>
        <zip>28981</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ezequiel Arranz Martínez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CS Isabel II</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parla</city>
        <zip>28982</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Palacios Martínez, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Consultorio Local Perales de Tajuña</name>
      <address>
        <city>Perales de Tajuña</city>
        <zip>28540</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miguel Ángel María Tablado, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyspepsia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heartburn</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antacids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

